<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[CombinaTexas 2020]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>8250.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>8250</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Stefaan De Winter</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sgdewint@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922599</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The CombinaTexas 2020 conference will be held at Texas A&amp;M University, College Station TX on April 10-11, 2020. The conference will feature six fifty-minute plenary lectures and a number of contributed talks in various areas of Combinatorics and Graph Theory. The aim of the CombinaTexas conference series is to enhance the educational and research atmosphere of combinatorialists in Texas and the surrounding states, increase communication between mathematicians of the region, and provide a forum for presentation and discussion of the most recent developments in the field of Combinatorics. CombinaTexas was established in 2000 and rotated among different institutions in the South Central United States until 2014. Since then it has been hosted at Texas A&amp;M University. CombinaTexas 2020 is the nineteenth conference in this series.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The topics of the CombinaTexas Series include all branches of Combinatorics, Graph Theory, and their connections to Algebra, Geometry, Probability Theory, and Computer Science. In 2020 the confirmed plenary speakers are Miklos Bona (University of Florida), Tri Lai (University of Nebraska- Lincoln), Chun-Hung Liu (Texas A&amp;M University), Nathan Reading (North Carolina State University), Stephanie van Willigenburg (University of British Columbia), Josephine Yu (Georgia Institute of Technology). They will present research in enumerative combinatorics, combinatorial representation theory, cluster algebras, tiling theory, topological graph theory, and tropical geometry. About 70 participants are anticipated, with an estimated 20 contributed talks in parallel sessions. More information about the conference is available at the webpage https://www.math.tamu.edu/conferences/combinatexas/&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/09/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/09/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2000531</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Huafei C</FirstName>
<LastName>Yan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Huafei C Yan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[cyan@math.tamu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000105672</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/09/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Laura</FirstName>
<LastName>Matusevich</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>F</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Laura F Matusevich</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[laura@math.tamu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000489818</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/09/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Texas A&amp;M University</Name>
<CityName>COLLEGE STATION</CityName>
<ZipCode>778454375</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9798626777</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>400 HARVEY MITCHELL PKY S STE 30</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>JF6XLNB4CDJ5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TEXAS A &amp; M UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>HH6VX5XDL284</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Texas A&M University Main Campus]]></Name>
<CityName>College Station</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>778433368</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3368 TAMU]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7970</Code>
<Text>Combinatorics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~8250</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>CombinaTexas is a combinatorics conference series in the South Central United States. It is dedicated to the enhancement of both the educational and research atmospheres of the community of combinatorialists and graph theorists in Texas and the surrounding states. The aim of the CombinaTexas series is to increase communication between mathematicians in the region, promote the research of the regional combinatorics community, and provide a forum for presentation and discussion of developments in the field of combinatorics.<br /><br />This conference was originally scheduled on April 10--11, 2020. However, due to the COVID-19 outbreak since March 2020 and the school restrictions on public events, it had to be postponed, and the grant was extended to May 31, 2022. With the support of this grant, two conferences were held: a virtual one in the spring of 2021 and an in-person one in the spring of 2022.&nbsp;</p> <p><br />CombinaTexas 2021 took place on February 20-21&nbsp; through ZOOM. The online version allowed it to have more participants: There were 101 registered participants from all over the world, and 67 of them were students or early career mathematicians. This conference had 6 plenary talks and 32 contributed talks. Special social events were arranged in the online platform @GatherTown.&nbsp;</p> <p>CombinaTexas 2022 took place on March 4-5 at Texas A&amp;M University, College Station, Texas. It is one of the earliest in-person conference since the pandemic. Due to the on-going pandemic and the uncertainty of air-travel, the conference had a moderate size. A majority of the participants came from Texas or Louisiana. There were 39 registered participants, among which 28 were students or early career mathematicians. This conference had 4 plenary talks and 13 contributed talks. Coffee, refreshment, and a working lunch were provided.&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Intellectual Merit.</strong><br />The conference series is an efficient way to integrate research and education, while promoting teaching, training, and learning. Participants have the opportunity to learn cutting edge developments from the distinguished invited researchers, disseminated their own work through contributed talk sessions,&nbsp;communicate with peers,&nbsp; and establish their own network. It is especially important for graduate students, many of whom have not had a research conference since they entered graduate school.&nbsp;</p> <p><br /><strong>Broader Impacts.</strong><br />The CombinaTexas conference series has a significant impact on the department and on the combinatorial community in the region. The pandemic has prevented us from having in-person conferences for two years. Research communication outside the classroom reduced substantially all over the country.&nbsp; The conference met the need of the community during the pandemic.&nbsp; The conference especially aimed to support&nbsp; early career mathematicians. In both conferences&nbsp; the majority of the participants were students, postdocs, or junior faculty.&nbsp;The conference also enhanced the diversity of the local mathematics community.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/11/2022<br>      Modified by: Huafei C&nbsp;Yan</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ CombinaTexas is a combinatorics conference series in the South Central United States. It is dedicated to the enhancement of both the educational and research atmospheres of the community of combinatorialists and graph theorists in Texas and the surrounding states. The aim of the CombinaTexas series is to increase communication between mathematicians in the region, promote the research of the regional combinatorics community, and provide a forum for presentation and discussion of developments in the field of combinatorics.  This conference was originally scheduled on April 10--11, 2020. However, due to the COVID-19 outbreak since March 2020 and the school restrictions on public events, it had to be postponed, and the grant was extended to May 31, 2022. With the support of this grant, two conferences were held: a virtual one in the spring of 2021 and an in-person one in the spring of 2022.    CombinaTexas 2021 took place on February 20-21  through ZOOM. The online version allowed it to have more participants: There were 101 registered participants from all over the world, and 67 of them were students or early career mathematicians. This conference had 6 plenary talks and 32 contributed talks. Special social events were arranged in the online platform @GatherTown.   CombinaTexas 2022 took place on March 4-5 at Texas A&amp;M University, College Station, Texas. It is one of the earliest in-person conference since the pandemic. Due to the on-going pandemic and the uncertainty of air-travel, the conference had a moderate size. A majority of the participants came from Texas or Louisiana. There were 39 registered participants, among which 28 were students or early career mathematicians. This conference had 4 plenary talks and 13 contributed talks. Coffee, refreshment, and a working lunch were provided.   Intellectual Merit. The conference series is an efficient way to integrate research and education, while promoting teaching, training, and learning. Participants have the opportunity to learn cutting edge developments from the distinguished invited researchers, disseminated their own work through contributed talk sessions, communicate with peers,  and establish their own network. It is especially important for graduate students, many of whom have not had a research conference since they entered graduate school.    Broader Impacts. The CombinaTexas conference series has a significant impact on the department and on the combinatorial community in the region. The pandemic has prevented us from having in-person conferences for two years. Research communication outside the classroom reduced substantially all over the country.  The conference met the need of the community during the pandemic.  The conference especially aimed to support  early career mathematicians. In both conferences  the majority of the participants were students, postdocs, or junior faculty. The conference also enhanced the diversity of the local mathematics community.           Last Modified: 08/11/2022       Submitted by: Huafei C Yan]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
