<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Trace Formulas, L-Functions, and Automorphic and Arithmetic Periods]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>300000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>100000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Andrew Pollington</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>adpollin@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924878</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The main objective of this project is to study the relation between L-functions and various periods, both automorphic and arithmetic. The L-function is an important object in the modern study of questions in number theory, in particular, solving Diophantine equations like the famous Birch and Swinnerton-Dyer conjecture and its generalizations. L-functions are also crucial in the study of representations of transformation groups, which have an important role in physics. The work is expected to provide important new understanding of these relations in higher dimensional cases. The investigator plans to organize workshops related to the project, which will provide students, postdocs, and other researchers in the area substantial opportunities for instruction, discussion, and collaboration.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The scope of this project consists of four parts. In the first part, the investigator will use some new techniques in the study of trace formulas to solve questions concerning the relation between L-functions and automorphic periods -- those periods obtained by integrating automorphic forms along certain subgroups. The second part aims to extend some explicit formulas of automorphic periods, known as the Ichino-Ikeda formula, to more general cases by removing certain assumptions that are usually hard to check. The third part aims to provide unconditional evidence toward the Beilinson-Bloch conjecture on the relation between L-functions and Chow groups, which will generalize parallel results in the Birch and Swinnerton-Dyer conjecture to higher dimensional cases. In the last part, the investigator plans to adopt a new approach via a relative trace formula to obtain variants of the arithmetic triple product formula concerning the height of certain cycles on a product of three modular elliptic curves.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/28/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/18/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2000533</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yifeng</FirstName>
<LastName>Liu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Yifeng Liu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[yifeng.liu@yale.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000628530</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/28/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate>03/18/2021</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Congling</FirstName>
<LastName>Qiu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Congling Qiu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[congling.qiu@yale.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000837054</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/18/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Yale University</Name>
<CityName>NEW HAVEN</CityName>
<ZipCode>065118917</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2037854689</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>105 WALL ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CT03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>FL6GV84CKN57</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>YALE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>FL6GV84CKN57</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Yale University]]></Name>
<CityName>New Haven</CityName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>065116810</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[10 Hillhouse Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CT03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1264</Code>
<Text>ALGEBRA,NUMBER THEORY,AND COM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~100000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><div class="page" title="Page 1"> <div class="layoutArea"> <div class="column"> <p><strong>Intellectual merit</strong></p> <p><span>One origin of number theory is to solve polynomial equations over the field&nbsp;</span><span>Q&nbsp;</span><span>of rational numbers, i.e., to find&nbsp;</span><span>Q</span><span>-points on algebraic varieties over&nbsp;</span><span>Q</span><span>. In modern number theory, we want to quantify these points or to investigate their configuration and distribution. A natural extension is to study algebraic cycles, i.e., formal linear combinations of closed subvarieties, on algebraic varieties over fields closely related to&nbsp;</span><span>Q</span><span>. &nbsp;</span><span style="font-size: 12px;">&nbsp;Chow groups are abelian groups of algebraic cycles modulo rational equivalence. Here, rational equivalence identifies algebraic cycles via &ldquo;defor- mation&rdquo; along the projective line.</span></p> <div class="page" title="Page 1"> <div class="layoutArea"> <div class="column"> <p><span>Starting with a polynomial equation y^2=f(x)</span><span>&nbsp;that defines a curve C. If&nbsp;</span><span style="font-size: 12px;">f(x) is cubic, &nbsp;</span><span style="font-size: 12px;">there is a natural abelian group law on&nbsp;</span><span style="font-size: 12px;">C and</span><span style="font-size: 12px;">&nbsp;C&nbsp;is an elliptic curve.&nbsp;</span><span style="font-size: 12px;">Moreover, the Birch--Swinnerton-Dyer (BSD) conjecture &mdash; one of the most important problems in number theory &mdash; equates the rank of&nbsp;</span><span style="font-size: 12px;">C</span><span style="font-size: 12px;">(</span><span style="font-size: 12px;">Q</span><span style="font-size: 12px;">) and the central vanishing order of &nbsp;</span><span style="font-size: 12px;">the&nbsp;</span><span style="font-size: 12px;">L</span><span style="font-size: 12px;">-function</span><span style="font-size: 12px;">&nbsp;</span><span style="font-size: 12px;">of&nbsp;</span><span style="font-size: 12px;">C. &nbsp;</span><span style="font-size: 12px;">In the case of vanishing order 1, Gross and Zagier showed that an earlier construction of Heegner using CM points on some modular curves (i.e., moduli spaces of Elliptic curves) actually gives a point in&nbsp;</span><span style="font-size: 12px;">C</span><span style="font-size: 12px;">(</span><span style="font-size: 12px;">Q</span><span style="font-size: 12px;">) of infinite order.&nbsp;</span><span style="font-size: 12px;">The key ingredient is the Gross&ndash; Zagier formula that relates &nbsp;</span><span style="font-size: 12px;">heights&nbsp;</span><span style="font-size: 12px;">of CM points and derivatives of&nbsp;</span><span style="font-size: 12px;">L</span><span style="font-size: 12px;">-functions for modular forms</span><span style="font-size: 12px;">. &nbsp;</span><span style="font-size: 12px;">This is the most important tool we have for the BSD conjecture.&nbsp;</span><span style="font-size: 12px;">One of the Beilinson--Bloch (BB) conjecture vastly generalizes the&nbsp;Birch and Swinnerton-Dyer conjecture using Chow groups. The major&nbsp;</span><span style="font-size: 12px;">outcomes of the project are on the BB conjecture,&nbsp;via establishing generalizations of the Gross--Zagier formula in higher dimensions.&nbsp;.&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span style="font-size: 12px;"><span><span>First,&nbsp;</span></span></span><span style="font-size: 12px;">Yifeng Liu (the PI before changing) has accompolished two articles on the BB conjecture&nbsp; for unitary Shimura varieties, joint with Chao Li. They established&nbsp;<span>&nbsp;an arithmetic inner product formula, generalizing of the Gross--Zagier formula from a new angle.&nbsp;</span></span><span style="font-size: 12px;">Second, &nbsp;</span><span style="font-size: 12px;">Congling Qiu (the PI after changing)&nbsp;has written an article</span><span style="font-size: 12px;">&nbsp;on the higher weight&nbsp;Gross--Zagier formula for&nbsp;&nbsp;Kuga-Sato varieties over any modular curves. &nbsp;Third,&nbsp;<span>Congling Qiu (the PI after changing)&nbsp;has written an article about&nbsp;</span></span><span style="font-size: 12px;">an arithmetic mixed Siegel-Weil formula for unitary Shimura varieties, analogous to the key formula in the work of Gross and Zagier that directly leads to &nbsp;the Gross--Zagier formula</span><span style="font-size: 12px;">.&nbsp;A direct application of the arithmetic mixed Siegel-Weil formula&nbsp;is&nbsp;</span><span style="font-size: 12px;">a solution to Kudla&rsquo;s modularity problem for&nbsp;</span><span style="font-size: 12px;">the arithmetic algebraic cycles.&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span style="font-size: 12px;">.</span><span style="font-size: 12px;">Another conjecture of Beilinson--Bloch predicts that the Abel--Jacobi maps from Chow groups to the intermediate Jacobians are injective modulo torsion, i.e., algebraic cycles modulo rational equivalence and torsion can be determined Hodge-theoreticly.&nbsp;</span><span style="font-size: 12px;">Congling Qiu (the PI after changing)&nbsp;has written an article with Wei Zhang about this conjecture for &nbsp;diagonal cycles on powers of curves. They also have a paper in preparation, when the curves are specialized to Shimura curves (generalizatios of modular curves). It completely solves a complement of Gross--Kudla's conjectural&nbsp;generalizations of the Gross--Zagier formula to triple product of&nbsp;Shimura curves. Finally,&nbsp;Congling Qiu (the PI after changing) has&nbsp;a paper in preparation, solving this conjecture for &nbsp;<span>CM zero cycles on squares of elliptic curves, and partially for Shimura&nbsp;curves.&nbsp;</span></span></p> <p><strong><span style="font-size: 12px;">Broader impacts</span></strong></p> <div class="page" title="Page 1"> <div class="layoutArea"> <div class="column"> <p><span>The research of the PIs are disseminated through respected journals and through conferences, seminars and lectures. Parts of the research are joint works with other mathematicians. Some problems in the research are made into research projects of graduate students. Certain aspects of this research&nbsp;could generate several undergraduate projects. The PIs plan to organize workshops or conferences related to the research, which will provide students, postdocs, and other mathematicians in the area substantial opportunities for instruction, discussion and collaboration.</span></p> </div> </div> </div> <p><span style="font-size: 12px;"><span><span><br /></span></span></span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><span style="font-size: 12px;"><span><br /></span></span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><span style="font-size: 12px;"><span><br /></span></span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><span style="font-size: 12px;"><br /></span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><span style="font-size: 12px;"><br /></span></p> <dl class="clearing"><dd> </dd></dl></div> </div> </div> </div> </div> </div><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/27/2022<br>      Modified by: Congling&nbsp;Qiu</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[    Intellectual merit  One origin of number theory is to solve polynomial equations over the field Q of rational numbers, i.e., to find Q-points on algebraic varieties over Q. In modern number theory, we want to quantify these points or to investigate their configuration and distribution. A natural extension is to study algebraic cycles, i.e., formal linear combinations of closed subvarieties, on algebraic varieties over fields closely related to Q.   Chow groups are abelian groups of algebraic cycles modulo rational equivalence. Here, rational equivalence identifies algebraic cycles via "defor- mation" along the projective line.     Starting with a polynomial equation y^2=f(x) that defines a curve C. If f(x) is cubic,  there is a natural abelian group law on C and C is an elliptic curve. Moreover, the Birch--Swinnerton-Dyer (BSD) conjecture &mdash; one of the most important problems in number theory &mdash; equates the rank of C(Q) and the central vanishing order of  the L-function of C.  In the case of vanishing order 1, Gross and Zagier showed that an earlier construction of Heegner using CM points on some modular curves (i.e., moduli spaces of Elliptic curves) actually gives a point in C(Q) of infinite order. The key ingredient is the Gross&ndash; Zagier formula that relates  heights of CM points and derivatives of L-functions for modular forms.  This is the most important tool we have for the BSD conjecture. One of the Beilinson--Bloch (BB) conjecture vastly generalizes the Birch and Swinnerton-Dyer conjecture using Chow groups. The major outcomes of the project are on the BB conjecture, via establishing generalizations of the Gross--Zagier formula in higher dimensions. .   First, Yifeng Liu (the PI before changing) has accompolished two articles on the BB conjecture  for unitary Shimura varieties, joint with Chao Li. They established  an arithmetic inner product formula, generalizing of the Gross--Zagier formula from a new angle. Second,  Congling Qiu (the PI after changing) has written an article on the higher weight Gross--Zagier formula for  Kuga-Sato varieties over any modular curves.  Third, Congling Qiu (the PI after changing) has written an article about an arithmetic mixed Siegel-Weil formula for unitary Shimura varieties, analogous to the key formula in the work of Gross and Zagier that directly leads to  the Gross--Zagier formula. A direct application of the arithmetic mixed Siegel-Weil formula is a solution to Kudla’s modularity problem for the arithmetic algebraic cycles.   .Another conjecture of Beilinson--Bloch predicts that the Abel--Jacobi maps from Chow groups to the intermediate Jacobians are injective modulo torsion, i.e., algebraic cycles modulo rational equivalence and torsion can be determined Hodge-theoreticly. Congling Qiu (the PI after changing) has written an article with Wei Zhang about this conjecture for  diagonal cycles on powers of curves. They also have a paper in preparation, when the curves are specialized to Shimura curves (generalizatios of modular curves). It completely solves a complement of Gross--Kudla's conjectural generalizations of the Gross--Zagier formula to triple product of Shimura curves. Finally, Congling Qiu (the PI after changing) has a paper in preparation, solving this conjecture for  CM zero cycles on squares of elliptic curves, and partially for Shimura curves.   Broader impacts     The research of the PIs are disseminated through respected journals and through conferences, seminars and lectures. Parts of the research are joint works with other mathematicians. Some problems in the research are made into research projects of graduate students. Certain aspects of this research could generate several undergraduate projects. The PIs plan to organize workshops or conferences related to the research, which will provide students, postdocs, and other mathematicians in the area substantial opportunities for instruction, discussion and collaboration.                                               Last Modified: 11/27/2022       Submitted by: Congling Qiu]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
