<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Singularities in Harmonic Analysis and the Calculus of Variations]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>178483.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>178483</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Marian Bocea</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mbocea@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922595</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Harmonic analysis and the calculus of variations are two of the oldest branches of mathematical analysis. Harmonic analysis is the study of the scale invariant properties of functions such as the oscillation of violin strings; it underpins much of modern image and signal processing. The calculus of variations is the study of energy minimizers; for example, a soap film hanging off a wire forms a shape which minimizes the surface tension. The purpose of this project is twofold: first to use harmonic analysis to study the behavior of energy minimizers under perturbations (like a soap film in a mild wind). Second, to use techniques from the calculus of variations to study a central problem in harmonic analysis, namely how does diffusion (i.e. heat spreading through a room) detect geometry. This synergy should not only lead to mathematical breakthroughs but also refine our ability to use these mathematical ideas to predict physical phenomena. The project provides research training opportunities for graduate students.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The investigator is interested in singularities of minimizers (places where the minimizer fails to be smooth, like the corners soap bubbles form when they touch each other). In particular, the investigator wants to develop tools to study these singularities which are persistent under perturbations (either of the energy or the initial conditions). To develop these tools, new ideas from harmonic analysis and geometric measure theory are necessary. The investigator is also interested in the problem of how solutions to elliptic differential equations (which model diffusion) detect the geometry of domains in Euclidean space. Recently, there have been major breakthroughs showing that homogeneous diffusion can detect some geometric features. The investigator believes that ideas from the calculus of variations can extend this breakthrough to understand what finer geometric details inhomogeneous diffusion can detect.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/31/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/27/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2000288</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Max</FirstName>
<LastName>Engelstein</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Max D Engelstein</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mengelst@umn.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000731627</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/31/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Minnesota-Twin Cities</Name>
<CityName>MINNEAPOLIS</CityName>
<ZipCode>554552009</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6126245599</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>200 OAK ST SE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>KABJZBBJ4B54</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MINNESOTA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Minnesota-Twin Cities]]></Name>
<CityName>Minneapolis</CityName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>554550488</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1281</Code>
<Text>ANALYSIS PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0122</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002223DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~56751</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~64613</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2022~57119</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project carried out research in two fields of mathematics originally developed to study the natural world. The calculus of variations was developed to give a mathematical underpinning to the ``principle of least action"; the idea that physical phenomena try to minimize some underlying energy. Harmonic analysis was developed to better understand diffusions (such as the spread of heat in a metal rod). The PI is interested in building surprising connections between these fields and proving theorems which have physical relevance. <br /><br />The PI's work on the calculus of variations focuses on the behavior of minimizers under perturbations; that is, small changes in the object or the energy. With O. Chodosh, R. Neumayer and L. Spolaor, the PI showed how to prove quantitatively estimate the change in energy when the object changes slightly (think a wobbly soap bubble), even when the precise shape of the minimizing objects is not known. The PI's work on almost-minimizers (which minimize some energy up to a small error) gives mathematical underpinning to the efficacy of models even when lower order terms are discarded. With G. David, M. Smit Vega Garcia and T. Toro, the PI has shown that these almost-minimizer display the same "first order" behavior as minimizers but can wildly different finer qualities. Interestingly, these last results use tools from harmonic analysis and geometric measure theory (the study of rough sets). <br /><br />In harmonic analysis the PI showed that the behavior of distance like objects and diffusions in the complement of a rough set can determine the shape of that set. Physical phenomena that are trying to be understood include the shape of a membrane between two different liquids, the structure of mammalian lungs and the twists of a strand of RNA in fluid. With M. Badger, S. Bortz, M. Goering, T. Toro and Z. Zhao, the PI has adapted variational tools to understand two phase free boundary problems. With S. Mayboroda and his PhD student, C. Jeznach, the PI has discovered a surprisingly large family of non-local distance like functions that characterize geometric regularity in higher co-dimension. This touches on some of the largest open problems at the intersection of harmonic analysis and geometric measure theory, such as the David-Semmes conjecture. <br /><br />This project resulted in six publications, two papers to appear and two preprints (which are submitted and awaiting review). The results that have been accepted are in high quality journals such as the Journal of the European Math Society, Ars Inveniendi Analytica, Crelle's Journal and the Transactions of the American Math Society. The results produced during this period have been disseminated through numerous invited talks at research seminars and conferences across the United States and in Europe. This includes a plenary talk at the Midwest PDE Seminar in Columbia Missouri in the Fall of 2022 and a plenary talk at a conference on free boundary problems in Levico, Italy in Spring 2023. The broader impacts include the participation of a PhD student and a masters student in the research projects as well as (partially) funding the PDE seminar at the University of Minnesota. The PI has also mentored several undergraduate students during the period of this project on topics related to his research.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/05/2023<br>      Modified by: Max&nbsp;D&nbsp;Engelstein</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project carried out research in two fields of mathematics originally developed to study the natural world. The calculus of variations was developed to give a mathematical underpinning to the ``principle of least action"; the idea that physical phenomena try to minimize some underlying energy. Harmonic analysis was developed to better understand diffusions (such as the spread of heat in a metal rod). The PI is interested in building surprising connections between these fields and proving theorems which have physical relevance.   The PI's work on the calculus of variations focuses on the behavior of minimizers under perturbations; that is, small changes in the object or the energy. With O. Chodosh, R. Neumayer and L. Spolaor, the PI showed how to prove quantitatively estimate the change in energy when the object changes slightly (think a wobbly soap bubble), even when the precise shape of the minimizing objects is not known. The PI's work on almost-minimizers (which minimize some energy up to a small error) gives mathematical underpinning to the efficacy of models even when lower order terms are discarded. With G. David, M. Smit Vega Garcia and T. Toro, the PI has shown that these almost-minimizer display the same "first order" behavior as minimizers but can wildly different finer qualities. Interestingly, these last results use tools from harmonic analysis and geometric measure theory (the study of rough sets).   In harmonic analysis the PI showed that the behavior of distance like objects and diffusions in the complement of a rough set can determine the shape of that set. Physical phenomena that are trying to be understood include the shape of a membrane between two different liquids, the structure of mammalian lungs and the twists of a strand of RNA in fluid. With M. Badger, S. Bortz, M. Goering, T. Toro and Z. Zhao, the PI has adapted variational tools to understand two phase free boundary problems. With S. Mayboroda and his PhD student, C. Jeznach, the PI has discovered a surprisingly large family of non-local distance like functions that characterize geometric regularity in higher co-dimension. This touches on some of the largest open problems at the intersection of harmonic analysis and geometric measure theory, such as the David-Semmes conjecture.   This project resulted in six publications, two papers to appear and two preprints (which are submitted and awaiting review). The results that have been accepted are in high quality journals such as the Journal of the European Math Society, Ars Inveniendi Analytica, Crelle's Journal and the Transactions of the American Math Society. The results produced during this period have been disseminated through numerous invited talks at research seminars and conferences across the United States and in Europe. This includes a plenary talk at the Midwest PDE Seminar in Columbia Missouri in the Fall of 2022 and a plenary talk at a conference on free boundary problems in Levico, Italy in Spring 2023. The broader impacts include the participation of a PhD student and a masters student in the research projects as well as (partially) funding the PDE seminar at the University of Minnesota. The PI has also mentored several undergraduate students during the period of this project on topics related to his research.       Last Modified: 09/05/2023       Submitted by: Max D Engelstein]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
