<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[CAREER: Novel Photonic Structures Using Non-Hermitian Exceptional Points]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>290799.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>290799</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ECCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ruyan Guo</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Abstract Title: Novel Photonic Structures for Lasers and Sensing by Using Gain and Loss &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical Description: &lt;br/&gt;The proposed research aims to introduce a new paradigm in optics by utilizing the unconventional properties of exceptional points arising in systems with gain and loss. These features can be employed to build structures with customized properties and functionalities- previously thought to be unattainable. The applications of such developments range from on-chip communication systems, to high power semiconductor lasers, to sensing. This research will result in a better understanding of how amplification and attenuation can be independently manipulated and harnessed in both optically and electrically pumped arrangement and will shed light on the role and the fundamentals of exceptional points in optics. In addition, the proposed work provides a bridge between mathematics, quantum physics, and engineering while promoting the concept of exceptional points in optics. These ideas could lead to new design tools that can be deployed to address some of the long-standing problems in laser physics. If successful, this effort could potentially transform chip-scale integrated photonics and high power semiconductor laser technologies. Due to the interdisciplinary nature of the proposed activity, the students engaged in this project will have the opportunity to prepare for a broad range of future careers by experiencing all the steps involved in a scientific endeavor, starting from conceiving an idea that perhaps originates from mathematics, to experimentally demonstrating the anticipated behavior, and finally building a prototype device. By means of presentations, publications, and classroom/laboratory teaching, the knowledge acquired during the course of this project will be disseminated to a broader audience. This program will provide research opportunities not only to graduate, but also to undergraduate, and K-12 students. Finally, students from minority and under-represented groups will be proactively integrated into the research environment. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Non-Technical Description: &lt;br/&gt;The proposed effort will make use of the physics and peculiarities of non-Hermitian exceptional points (EPs) in order to develop alternative strategies in designing novel photonic devices that complement and/or improve existing integrated photonic circuits. In a photonic system, exceptional points can be advantageously introduced through a judicious interplay between refractive index shaping and gain-loss contrast. Along these lines, two endeavors associated with chip-scale photonic components and networks will be pursued: (i) demonstrating a new class of single mode integrated lasers with increased brightness and/or spectral purity, (ii) enhancing the sensing characteristics of active photonic molecules by exploiting the inherent features of higher-order exceptional points. The prospect of using InP technologies as a versatile platform to explore the physics and applications of exceptional points in optics will also be investigated.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>10/16/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/16/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2000538</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mercedeh</FirstName>
<LastName>Khajavikhan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mercedeh Khajavikhan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[khajavik@usc.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000629246</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>10/16/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Southern California</Name>
<CityName>LOS ANGELES</CityName>
<ZipCode>900894304</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2137407762</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3720 S FLOWER ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[FL 3]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>37</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA37</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>G88KLJR3KYT5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF SOUTHERN CALIFORNIA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Southern California]]></Name>
<CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>900890001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3720 S. Flower Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>37</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA37</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1517</Code>
<Text>EPMD-ElectrnPhoton&amp;MagnDevices</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>091E</Code>
<Text>Light generation &amp; detection</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1517</Code>
<Text>ELECT, PHOTONICS, &amp; DEVICE TEC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01001516DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~290799</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>One of the main objectives of this effort was to advance the science and applications of non-Hermitian photonics by devising new arrangements, devices and systems with novel or enhanced functionalities through utilizing the unique properties of non-Hermitian systems.&nbsp;Another equally important goal of this work was to train students and postdocs as future workforce (either in industry, research labs, or academia) to drive innovation.&nbsp;</p> <p>Towards the first goal, several ideas have been pursued that includes:</p> <p>1-&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Broad area PT-symmetric lasers, where it was shown that PT-symmetry can be used to filter out higher order modes from a broad area laser, allowing single transverse mode operation.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>2-&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Electrically pumped PT symmetric lasers &ndash; where it was shown that PT symmetric lasers can work under electrical pumping</p> <p>3-&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Supersymmetric lasers- where the principles of supersymmetry transformation were used to design an array of coupled waveguide lasers that operated in a single transverse mode fashion through coupling to a standard and unpumped array.</p> <p>4-&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Topological lasers where an array of ring lasers in a lattice that shows synthetic magnetic field phase locked and show single transverse and longitudinal mode operation&nbsp;</p> <p>5-&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Orbital angular momentum laser- where inserting an S-shape construct inside an active resonator promotes the emission of a beam with a non-zero orbital angular momentum from a ring laser.&nbsp;</p> <p>6-&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Demonstrating enhanced sensitivity at higher order exceptional points in non-Hermitian systems</p> <p>7-&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Proposing and demonstrating a gyroscope that works based on the enhanced sensitivity observed in systems designed to operate at exceptional points.&nbsp;</p> <p>On the other hand, over the years, several graduate students and postdocs worked on this project. The project provided remarkable opportunities for those involved to build a strong foundation for their future careers through learning a broad spectrum of skills and grow their knowledge of the field, while working on their interpersonal, communication and writing skills. The project has resulted in a large number of publications and conference presentations. &nbsp;</p> <p>Towards the second goal, the PI also put a large effort to disseminate the knowledge gathered in the project to the communities of interest by presenting invited and plenary talks, seminars, colloquium talks, as well as tutorials on the subject. She has also organized a workshop on &ldquo;Non-Hermitian, Topological and Active Photonics&rdquo; as part of a IEEE Summer Topicals in 2018.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/26/2022<br>      Modified by: Mercedeh&nbsp;Khajavikhan</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ One of the main objectives of this effort was to advance the science and applications of non-Hermitian photonics by devising new arrangements, devices and systems with novel or enhanced functionalities through utilizing the unique properties of non-Hermitian systems. Another equally important goal of this work was to train students and postdocs as future workforce (either in industry, research labs, or academia) to drive innovation.   Towards the first goal, several ideas have been pursued that includes:  1-    Broad area PT-symmetric lasers, where it was shown that PT-symmetry can be used to filter out higher order modes from a broad area laser, allowing single transverse mode operation.    2-    Electrically pumped PT symmetric lasers &ndash; where it was shown that PT symmetric lasers can work under electrical pumping  3-    Supersymmetric lasers- where the principles of supersymmetry transformation were used to design an array of coupled waveguide lasers that operated in a single transverse mode fashion through coupling to a standard and unpumped array.  4-    Topological lasers where an array of ring lasers in a lattice that shows synthetic magnetic field phase locked and show single transverse and longitudinal mode operation   5-    Orbital angular momentum laser- where inserting an S-shape construct inside an active resonator promotes the emission of a beam with a non-zero orbital angular momentum from a ring laser.   6-    Demonstrating enhanced sensitivity at higher order exceptional points in non-Hermitian systems  7-    Proposing and demonstrating a gyroscope that works based on the enhanced sensitivity observed in systems designed to operate at exceptional points.   On the other hand, over the years, several graduate students and postdocs worked on this project. The project provided remarkable opportunities for those involved to build a strong foundation for their future careers through learning a broad spectrum of skills and grow their knowledge of the field, while working on their interpersonal, communication and writing skills. The project has resulted in a large number of publications and conference presentations.    Towards the second goal, the PI also put a large effort to disseminate the knowledge gathered in the project to the communities of interest by presenting invited and plenary talks, seminars, colloquium talks, as well as tutorials on the subject. She has also organized a workshop on "Non-Hermitian, Topological and Active Photonics" as part of a IEEE Summer Topicals in 2018.              Last Modified: 06/26/2022       Submitted by: Mercedeh Khajavikhan]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
