<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RUI: Holographic Stars and Stripes]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>91135.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>91135</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Keith Dienes</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kdienes@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925314</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This RUI award funds the research activities of Professor Matthew Lippert at Long Island University Brooklyn.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;String theory has emerged in recent years as a powerful tool, not just for understanding quantum gravity and extremely high-energy physics, but also for studying a wide range of strongly interacting systems exhibiting a variety of length scales, from electrons in exotic superconductors to the ultra-dense cores of neutron stars. Professor Lippert will conduct research into these systems with the goal of developing interdisciplinary connections between string theory and gravitational physics, nuclear physics, astrophysics, and condensed matter physics. Such bridges enable the exchange of ideas and techniques between different fields of physics, enriching and advancing them all.   As such, this research advances the national interest by fostering the development of basic science within the United States.  This grant will also support the research of African-American and Hispanic students, thereby increasing the diversity of students in STEM fields and thereby allowing these students to improve their practical quantitative and computing skills, to gain a hands-on appreciation for how actual science is done, and to glimpse the exciting frontier of human knowledge.&lt;br/&gt;  &lt;br/&gt;More specifically, this research uses holographic gauge/gravity duality to investigate open questions in strongly coupled quantum field theories, organized around four topics.  First, the poorly understood behavior of cold, dense nuclear matter at the core of neutron stars will be investigated using holographic models of QCD in order to test predictions against the recent and ongoing observations of binary neutron star mergers.  Second, strongly coupled striped states, such as charge density waves, will be studied using holographic models, including their response to applied electromagnetic fields and the interplay between spontaneous and explicit spatial symmetry breaking.  Third, anyons, whose unusual behavior is poorly understood even at weak coupling, will be analyzed at strong coupling using a holographic dual description.  Finally, using holographic duality, this research will explore the out-of-equilibrium dynamics by which certain strongly interacting systems relax to ground states with spontaneously broken symmetry.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>10/25/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/15/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2000398</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Matthew</FirstName>
<LastName>Lippert</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Matthew Lippert</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[lippertm@oldwestbury.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000737798</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>10/25/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>SUNY College at Old Westbury</Name>
<CityName>OLD WESTBURY</CityName>
<ZipCode>11568</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5168763125</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>CAMPUS RM H402</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>JJ2FXBDGWMG5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>THE RESEARCH FOUNDATION FOR THE STATE UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[SUNY College at Old Westbury]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>115680210</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1286</Code>
<Text>Elem. Particle Physics/Theory</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9229</Code>
<Text>RES IN UNDERGRAD INST-RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01001819DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01001920DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~11135</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~40000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~40000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="p1">String theory is emerging as a powerful tool, not just for understanding quantum gravity and extremely high-energy physics, but also for studying a wide range of strongly interacting systems at a variety of length scales, from electrons in exotic superconductors to the ultra-dense cores of neutron stars.<span>&nbsp; </span>The new tool is a duality, a translation between two very different descriptions of the same physical system.<span>&nbsp; </span>On one side of the duality is string theory, a gravitational theory, and the other is a gauge theory, a common type of quantum field theory.<span>&nbsp; </span>The duality is called ``holographic" because the gravitational description has one more spatial dimension than the gauge theory description, in analogy with a two-dimensional hologram encoding a three-dimensional image.</p> <p class="p1">There are many examples of materials in which, at high density and low temperature, the electrons self-organize into a pattern of stripes.<span>&nbsp; </span>Such spontaneous striped states have interesting properties and rich dynamics.<span>&nbsp; </span>In some cases, the underlying physics can be understood in a conventional description in terms of weakly interacting electrons.<span>&nbsp; </span>However, other examples are found in materials where the interactions between electrons are strong, such as the high-temperature superconductors, and require new tools, such as holographic duality.</p> <p class="p1">The use of string theory to study these types of striped phases has been a subject of much attention in recent years. We have focussed on a particular model of strongly interacting electrons, which exhibits a spontaneously striped phase. Our most recent project was a thorough analysis of the unusual magnetic properties of this model, in particular the electrical conductivity in the presence of an applied magnetic field, both in the striped and non-striped phases.</p> <p class="p1">The extremely dense nuclear matter at the cores of a large neutron stars is not well understood. However, dense, strongly interacting nuclear matter is one of the earliest and most successful applications of string theory. We investigated how changes to the equation of state describing the nuclear matter making up the star affect observable properties, such as the relation between the mass and the radius and, particularly, the maximum possible mass, above which the star collapses, becoming a black hole.</p> <p class="p1">Observable effects of string theory and quantum gravity have proven highly elusive.<span>&nbsp; </span>One reason is that the energies and length scales where exotic phenomena are expected to be manifest are well beyond the reach of current experiments.<span>&nbsp; </span>As an alternative to terrestrial experiments, we are investigating extreme astrophysical systems, with strong gravity or high energy, as natural cosmic laboratories.</p> <p class="p1">Black holes are unique astrophysical laboratories for investigating new physics.<span>&nbsp; </span>The high curvature near the horizon provides a natural setting in which to explore the physics of strong gravity and high energy. We showed how black holes, particularly those in binary systems, can serve as detectors of axions and other extremely light particles, which are generic predictions of string theory.</p> <p class="p1">We investigated magnetically charged black holes and how such objects, if they exist, could be astronomically observed.<span>&nbsp; </span>Large numbers of small black holes may have been created just after the Big Bang, when the universe was very hot and dense.<span>&nbsp; </span>Any such black holes which were magnetically charged would be very stable and would therefore still exist today.<span>&nbsp; </span>Black holes are generally quite difficult to observe, except when they collide with other objects.<span>&nbsp; </span>We analyzed the consequences of a small magnetically charged black hole colliding with a much larger neutron star.<span>&nbsp; </span>If a black hole is captured, it falls to the center of the neutron star, and then begins slowly swallowing it.<span>&nbsp; </span>However, the black hole then starts emitting large amounts of Hawking radiation, which we found can stabilize stabilize the neutron star, resulting in a long-lived object neutron star with a black hole in its core.<span>&nbsp;</span></p> <p class="p1">LIU Brooklyn and SUNY Old Westbury, where this research was conducted, are both exceptionally diverse, federally recognized minority-serving institutions. This grant supported the research of students from minority groups which are severely underrepresented in STEM fields, allowing them to improve their practical quantitative and computing skills, gain a hands-on appreciation for how actual science is done, and glimpse the exciting frontier of human knowledge.</p> <p class="p1">This research advances the national interest of promoting scientific progress by forging broad interdisciplinary connections between string theory and gravitational physics, nuclear physics, astrophysics, and condensed matter physics. Such bridges enable the exchange of ideas and techniques between different fields of physics, enriching and advancing them all.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/02/2023<br>      Modified by: Matthew&nbsp;Lippert</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[String theory is emerging as a powerful tool, not just for understanding quantum gravity and extremely high-energy physics, but also for studying a wide range of strongly interacting systems at a variety of length scales, from electrons in exotic superconductors to the ultra-dense cores of neutron stars.  The new tool is a duality, a translation between two very different descriptions of the same physical system.  On one side of the duality is string theory, a gravitational theory, and the other is a gauge theory, a common type of quantum field theory.  The duality is called ``holographic" because the gravitational description has one more spatial dimension than the gauge theory description, in analogy with a two-dimensional hologram encoding a three-dimensional image. There are many examples of materials in which, at high density and low temperature, the electrons self-organize into a pattern of stripes.  Such spontaneous striped states have interesting properties and rich dynamics.  In some cases, the underlying physics can be understood in a conventional description in terms of weakly interacting electrons.  However, other examples are found in materials where the interactions between electrons are strong, such as the high-temperature superconductors, and require new tools, such as holographic duality. The use of string theory to study these types of striped phases has been a subject of much attention in recent years. We have focussed on a particular model of strongly interacting electrons, which exhibits a spontaneously striped phase. Our most recent project was a thorough analysis of the unusual magnetic properties of this model, in particular the electrical conductivity in the presence of an applied magnetic field, both in the striped and non-striped phases. The extremely dense nuclear matter at the cores of a large neutron stars is not well understood. However, dense, strongly interacting nuclear matter is one of the earliest and most successful applications of string theory. We investigated how changes to the equation of state describing the nuclear matter making up the star affect observable properties, such as the relation between the mass and the radius and, particularly, the maximum possible mass, above which the star collapses, becoming a black hole. Observable effects of string theory and quantum gravity have proven highly elusive.  One reason is that the energies and length scales where exotic phenomena are expected to be manifest are well beyond the reach of current experiments.  As an alternative to terrestrial experiments, we are investigating extreme astrophysical systems, with strong gravity or high energy, as natural cosmic laboratories. Black holes are unique astrophysical laboratories for investigating new physics.  The high curvature near the horizon provides a natural setting in which to explore the physics of strong gravity and high energy. We showed how black holes, particularly those in binary systems, can serve as detectors of axions and other extremely light particles, which are generic predictions of string theory. We investigated magnetically charged black holes and how such objects, if they exist, could be astronomically observed.  Large numbers of small black holes may have been created just after the Big Bang, when the universe was very hot and dense.  Any such black holes which were magnetically charged would be very stable and would therefore still exist today.  Black holes are generally quite difficult to observe, except when they collide with other objects.  We analyzed the consequences of a small magnetically charged black hole colliding with a much larger neutron star.  If a black hole is captured, it falls to the center of the neutron star, and then begins slowly swallowing it.  However, the black hole then starts emitting large amounts of Hawking radiation, which we found can stabilize stabilize the neutron star, resulting in a long-lived object neutron star with a black hole in its core.  LIU Brooklyn and SUNY Old Westbury, where this research was conducted, are both exceptionally diverse, federally recognized minority-serving institutions. This grant supported the research of students from minority groups which are severely underrepresented in STEM fields, allowing them to improve their practical quantitative and computing skills, gain a hands-on appreciation for how actual science is done, and glimpse the exciting frontier of human knowledge. This research advances the national interest of promoting scientific progress by forging broad interdisciplinary connections between string theory and gravitational physics, nuclear physics, astrophysics, and condensed matter physics. Such bridges enable the exchange of ideas and techniques between different fields of physics, enriching and advancing them all.          Last Modified: 01/02/2023       Submitted by: Matthew Lippert]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
