<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Rocky Mountain Mathematics Consortium Summer School on Free Probability, Random Matrices, and Applications]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>31000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>31000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Marian Bocea</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mbocea@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922595</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This award will provide support for the Rocky Mountain Mathematics Consortium (RMMC) Summer School: Free Probability, Random Matrices, and Applications, that will be held from July 13-17, 2020, at the University of Wyoming. This week-long summer school will expose both graduate students and early-career researchers to important mathematics, foster collaboration, and build ties between the participants. Support for this summer school will provide a great opportunity for early-career researchers, members of underrepresented groups, and researchers lacking federal support to interact with some of the best researchers in the field.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Free probability, introduced by Voiculescu, is a noncommutative probability theory based on free independence that takes the place of classical independence. It is an extremely rich theory with deep applications to operator algebras and random matrix theory. It has became an essential tool for researchers working on operator algebras, random matrix theory and related fields. At the summer school there will be several mini-courses together as well as research talks. These lectures will bring topics in free probability and random matrix theory to a diverse audience and will help the participants move to the frontiers of this research field.  The website of the conference can be found at http://zhuang.snowyrange.science/RMMC2020/index.html.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/29/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/29/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2000372</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Zhuang</FirstName>
<LastName>Niu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Zhuang Niu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[zniu@uwyo.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000654525</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/29/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ping</FirstName>
<LastName>Zhong</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ping Zhong</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[pzhong@uwyo.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000788563</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/29/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Wyoming</Name>
<CityName>LARAMIE</CityName>
<ZipCode>820712000</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3077665320</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1000 E UNIVERSITY AVE DEPARTMENT</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wyoming</StateName>
<StateCode>WY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WY00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>FDR5YF2K32X5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF WYOMING</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>FDR5YF2K32X5</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Wyoming]]></Name>
<CityName>Laramie</CityName>
<StateCode>WY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>820712000</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1000 E. University Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wyoming</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WY00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1281</Code>
<Text>ANALYSIS PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~31000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Rocky Mountain Mathematics Consortium (RMMC) Summer School is an annual meeting organized by the faculty from the Department of Mathematics and Statistics at the University of Wyoming. This RMMC summer school was held from June 6 to 10, 2022. The summer school was originally scheduled in 2020 and was postponed due to Covid-19. The main themes of the summer school were free probability, random matrices, and their applications. This award covered travel and local expenses for invited speakers, graduate students, and young researchers.</p> <p>There were four mini-courses and two survey talks given by main speakers. The list of main speakers and titles is below.</p> <ul> <li>Hari Bercovici (Indiana University), Complex analysis in free probability.</li> <li>Benoit Collins (Kyoto University), Around the operator norm convergence of random matrices in free probability.</li> <li>Ken Dykema (Texas A&amp;M), On spectral distributions and decompositions of operators in finite von Neumann algebras.</li> <li>Alexandru Nica (University of Waterloo), Recent developments related to the use of cumulants in free probability.</li> <li>Dimitri Shlyakhtenko (UCLA), Introduction to Free Entropy Dimension.</li> <li>Dan Voiculescu (UC, Berkeley), Topological free entropy.</li> </ul> <p class="cdt4ke">In addition to these lectures, there were sixteen research talks given by other participants. The speakers included established researchers and a good number of early-career researchers and graduate students.&nbsp;</p> <p>It was an in-person meeting, but all lectures had hybrid components for remote participation. There were 78 participants&nbsp;(36 in-person and 42 remote participants) from all over the world.&nbsp;This summer school provided a wonderful platform for young researchers networking and collaborating with junior as well as senior researchers.</p> <p>The free probability theory, introduced by Voiculescu in 1980s, is an extremely rich theory with many deep interactions with operator algebras, random matrix theory, combinatorics, quantum information theory, statistics, and many other fields. The summer school covered a wide range of important topics. The video recordings of talks and other details are available at the conference website (https://sites.google.com/view/rmmc2022/home).&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;</p> <p>This Project Outcomes Report for the General Public is displayed verbatim as submitted by the Principal Investigator (PI) for this award. Any opinions, findings, and conclusions or recommendations expressed in this Report are those of the PI and do not necessarily reflect the views of the National Science Foundation; NSF has not approved or endorsed its content.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/18/2023<br>      Modified by: Ping&nbsp;Zhong</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Rocky Mountain Mathematics Consortium (RMMC) Summer School is an annual meeting organized by the faculty from the Department of Mathematics and Statistics at the University of Wyoming. This RMMC summer school was held from June 6 to 10, 2022. The summer school was originally scheduled in 2020 and was postponed due to Covid-19. The main themes of the summer school were free probability, random matrices, and their applications. This award covered travel and local expenses for invited speakers, graduate students, and young researchers.  There were four mini-courses and two survey talks given by main speakers. The list of main speakers and titles is below.  Hari Bercovici (Indiana University), Complex analysis in free probability. Benoit Collins (Kyoto University), Around the operator norm convergence of random matrices in free probability. Ken Dykema (Texas A&amp;M), On spectral distributions and decompositions of operators in finite von Neumann algebras. Alexandru Nica (University of Waterloo), Recent developments related to the use of cumulants in free probability. Dimitri Shlyakhtenko (UCLA), Introduction to Free Entropy Dimension. Dan Voiculescu (UC, Berkeley), Topological free entropy.  In addition to these lectures, there were sixteen research talks given by other participants. The speakers included established researchers and a good number of early-career researchers and graduate students.   It was an in-person meeting, but all lectures had hybrid components for remote participation. There were 78 participants (36 in-person and 42 remote participants) from all over the world. This summer school provided a wonderful platform for young researchers networking and collaborating with junior as well as senior researchers.  The free probability theory, introduced by Voiculescu in 1980s, is an extremely rich theory with many deep interactions with operator algebras, random matrix theory, combinatorics, quantum information theory, statistics, and many other fields. The summer school covered a wide range of important topics. The video recordings of talks and other details are available at the conference website (https://sites.google.com/view/rmmc2022/home).               This Project Outcomes Report for the General Public is displayed verbatim as submitted by the Principal Investigator (PI) for this award. Any opinions, findings, and conclusions or recommendations expressed in this Report are those of the PI and do not necessarily reflect the views of the National Science Foundation; NSF has not approved or endorsed its content.       Last Modified: 01/18/2023       Submitted by: Ping Zhong]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
