<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Beyond Hyperbolicity at the Ohio State University]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>30000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>30000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Krishnan Shankar</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This award supports participation in the Beyond Hyperbolicity Conference at the Ohio State University, which will be held July 6-10, 2020. The theme of the conference is in geometric group theory, a field that uses algebraic techniques to understand complicated geometric spaces. The Ohio State University has long been a hub for research in geometric group theory, and this conference will continue in this tradition.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Although hyperbolic groups and spaces are a common topic at geometric group theory conferences, the goal of this conference is to highlight work being done in other areas of combinatorial and geometric group theory. Whereas there have are many conferences focused on hyperbolic and acylindrically hyperbolic groups, mapping class groups, and cubical groups, there have been relatively few conferences devoted to a variety of other groups relevant to geometric group theory such as nilpotent and solvable groups, amenable groups, Thompson’s groups, groups of dynamical origins, self-similar groups, and more. These other categories of groups have a long history in the study of geometric group theory. The focus of this conference is to bring together researchers who specialize in these topics to encourage fruitful discussions regarding open questions in geometric group theory outside of the realm of hyperbolic groups.  The conference website is at https://sites.google.com/view/beyondhyperbolicity.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/16/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/16/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2000885</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nicholas</FirstName>
<LastName>Miller</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nicholas Miller</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[nickmbmiller@gmail.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000812027</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/16/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rachel</FirstName>
<LastName>Skipper</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Rachel Skipper</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[rachel.skipper@utah.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000810905</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/16/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
<LastName>Pengitore</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mark A Pengitore</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[waj9cr@virginia.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000788652</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/16/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Ohio State University</Name>
<CityName>COLUMBUS</CityName>
<ZipCode>432101016</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6146888735</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1960 KENNY RD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OH03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>DLWBSLWAJWR1</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OHIO STATE UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>MN4MDDMN8529</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Ohio State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Columbus</CityName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>432101016</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OH03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1267</Code>
<Text>TOPOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~30000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="p1">This award supports participation in the 2021 Beyond Hyperbolicity conference held at the Ohio State University in Columbus, Ohio from June 28th-July 2nd. This conference will highlight several important advances in the study of non-hyperbolic groups in the fields of combinatorial and geometric group theory. This includes exciting new developments in the study of nilpotent and solvable groups, amenable groups and groups of intermediate growth, Thompson groups, and more. The format of the conference includes plenary talks by established mathematicians in these fields as well as contributed talks by early career participants.</p> <p class="p1">The goal of this conference is to promote a week of interaction between its participants. In particular, this conference will provide a setting to discuss modern advances from leading experts in the area, as well as serve as a venue to help promote junior mathematicians and their work.<span>&nbsp;</span>The funding for this conference will be used to support the travel of the conference participants with an emphasis on students/early career mathematicians, women, and historically excluded scholars. The funding will also partially be used to publish a conference proceedings, where recent work from both early career and established mathematicians can be disseminated to the broader field. The PIs are hopeful that Beyond Hyperbolicity at OSU will lead to new discoveries and ideas in combinatorial and geometric group theory and therefore advance current scientific knowledge in the field. The conference website can be found at: https://sites.google.com/view/beyondhyperbolicity.</p> <p class="p1">&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/15/2022<br>      Modified by: Nicholas&nbsp;Miller</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[This award supports participation in the 2021 Beyond Hyperbolicity conference held at the Ohio State University in Columbus, Ohio from June 28th-July 2nd. This conference will highlight several important advances in the study of non-hyperbolic groups in the fields of combinatorial and geometric group theory. This includes exciting new developments in the study of nilpotent and solvable groups, amenable groups and groups of intermediate growth, Thompson groups, and more. The format of the conference includes plenary talks by established mathematicians in these fields as well as contributed talks by early career participants. The goal of this conference is to promote a week of interaction between its participants. In particular, this conference will provide a setting to discuss modern advances from leading experts in the area, as well as serve as a venue to help promote junior mathematicians and their work. The funding for this conference will be used to support the travel of the conference participants with an emphasis on students/early career mathematicians, women, and historically excluded scholars. The funding will also partially be used to publish a conference proceedings, where recent work from both early career and established mathematicians can be disseminated to the broader field. The PIs are hopeful that Beyond Hyperbolicity at OSU will lead to new discoveries and ideas in combinatorial and geometric group theory and therefore advance current scientific knowledge in the field. The conference website can be found at: https://sites.google.com/view/beyondhyperbolicity.         Last Modified: 03/15/2022       Submitted by: Nicholas Miller]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
