<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Young Mathematicians in C*-Algebras 2020]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>31454.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>31454</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Marian Bocea</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mbocea@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922595</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This award provides funding for US participation in the conference "Young Mathematicians in C*-Algebras" that will be held August 10-15, 2020 at the University of Münster, Germany. This conference is organized for and by Master's/Ph.D. students and postdocs in operator algebras and related areas, with the goal of fostering scientific interaction between young researchers. Young Mathematicians in C*-Algebras focuses on recent developments in operator algebras (both von Neumann and C*-algebras), noncommutative geometry, and related areas of mathematical analysis, with a particular emphasis on the interplay between operator algebras and the fields of geometric group theory, logic, and dynamical systems. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The conference will feature three mini-courses by established researchers (Jesse Peterson, Astrid an Huef, and Christopher Schafhauser) alongside many contributed talks by participants, as well as mentoring activities designed to increase retention of underrepresented groups in operator algebras and a keynote address by Betül Tanbay. This award gives US-based early career researchers and members of underrepresented groups an opportunity to attend and participate in this conference. The organizing committee will strive to make this funding opportunity known to target groups via advertising in a variety of venues. More information will be made available at: https://ymcstara.org/.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/06/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/17/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2000335</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Zhizhang</FirstName>
<LastName>Xie</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Zhizhang Xie</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[xie@math.tamu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000601196</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/11/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Brannan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael Brannan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mbrannan@math.tamu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000677828</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/06/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate>06/11/2021</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ian</FirstName>
<LastName>Charlesworth</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ian L Charlesworth</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ilc@math.berkeley.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000731400</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/06/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kari</FirstName>
<LastName>Eifler</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kari Eifler</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[keifler@math.tamu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000808453</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/06/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate>05/17/2022</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Texas A&amp;M University</Name>
<CityName>COLLEGE STATION</CityName>
<ZipCode>778454375</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9798626777</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>400 HARVEY MITCHELL PKY S STE 30</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>JF6XLNB4CDJ5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TEXAS A &amp; M UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>HH6VX5XDL284</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Texas A&M University Main Campus]]></Name>
<CityName>College Station</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>778433368</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3368 TAMU]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1281</Code>
<Text>ANALYSIS PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~31454</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><div class="page" title="Page 1"> <div class="layoutArea"> <div class="column"> <p><span>YMC*A is an annual conference arranged by junior researchers (graduate students and recent PhDs) for junior researchers, with the goal of fostering scientific and social interaction between young researchers. It covers the area of operator algebras (</span><span>C*</span><span>- algebras as well as von Neumann algebras, despite the name) as well as applications and other interactions with adjacent fields. Senior researchers may be invited to contribute. </span></p> <p><span>YMC*A 2021 was hosted at Westfalische Wilhelms-Universitat Munster (also with Zoom option) during August 2-13, 2021. The meeting took place over two weeks in order to acommodate covid protocols. There were three minicourses (Goulnara Arzhantseva, Chris Schafhauser, Jesse Peterson) and two career panels. There were also many shorter twenty-minute contributed talks by junior participant from accross the world. There were also a few three-minute poster session/micro-talks.&nbsp;</span></p> <div class="page" title="Page 1"> <div class="layoutArea"> <div class="column"> <p><span>The three minicourses given by </span></p> <ol> <li> <p><span>Goulnara Arzhantseva (University of Vienna): Constructions of non </span><span>C*</span><span>-exact groups </span></p> </li> <li> <p><span>Christopher Schafhauser (University of Nebraska&nbsp; - Lincoln): On the classification of simple nuclear </span><span>C*</span><span>-algebras </span></p> </li> <li> <p><span>Jesse Peterson (Vanderbilt University): Von Neumann algebras and lattices in higher-rank groups</span></p> </li> </ol> <div class="column">Here is a list of speakers.</div> <div class="column"> <p>1. Anshu: Connected Stable Rank of C*-algebras</p> <p>2. Kevin Aguyar Brix: C*-algebras from Symbolic Dynamics</p> <p>3. Sayan Das: On the free group factor problem, and Popa?s MV-property</p> <p>4. Alonso Delfin: C*-like Modules</p> <p>5. Alon Dogon: Hilbert Schmidt stability and characters on amenable groups</p> <p>6. Daniel Drimbe: New examples of W* and C*-superrigid groups</p> <p>7. Srivatsav Kunnawalkam Elayavalli: Proper proximality for groups acting on trees</p> <p>8. Marzieh Forough: Lifts of completely positive equivariant maps</p> <p>9. Priyanga Ganesan: Quantum Graphs</p> <p>10. Jan Gundelach: Leavitt path algebras as Cohn localisations</p> <p>11. Zahra Hassanpour: Morita Equivalence and Partial Actions</p> <p>12. Paul Herstedt: AT-algebras associated to zero-dimensional dynamical systems</p> <p>13. Shuler Hopkins: Deformations of commuting squares and complex Hadamard matrices</p> <p>14. Cristian Ivanescu: Cu-nuclearity and applications</p> <p>15. Collin Mark Joseph: Topological Insulators</p> <p>16. Emily Korfanty: Etale equivalence relations and C*-algebras for iterated function systems</p> <p>17. Jacek Krajczok: On the radial subalgebra for the quantum group OF+</p> <p>18. Alistair Miller: Groupoid Correspondences and the ABC Spectral Sequence</p> <p>19. Devarshi Mukherjee: Cyclic homology and non-commutative geometry in positive characteristic</p> <p>20. Robert Neagu: Amenable and Quasidiagonal traces - behaviour under homotopy</p> <p>21. Sergio Giron Pacheco: Anomalous symmetries of simple operator algebras</p> <p>22. Roberto Hernandez Palomares: Q-system completion for C*-algebras</p> <p>23. Samantha Pilgrim: Isometric Actions and Finite Approximations</p> <p>24. Ali Raad: Existence and uniqueness of inductive limit Cartan subalgebras in inductive limit C*-algebras</p> <p>25. Eduardo Scarparo: A torsion-free C*-unique group</p> <p>26. Apurva Seth: AF-algebras and rational homotopy theory</p> <p>27. &nbsp;Sushil Singla: Orthogonality, Gateaux derivative and ideals in C*-algebras</p> <p>28. &nbsp;Joel Right Dzokou Talla: Quantum SL(2;R) and its irreducible representations</p> <p>29. &nbsp;Dan Ursu: The ideal intersection property for essential groupoid C*-algebras</p> <p>30. &nbsp;Andrea Vaccaro: Games on AF-algebras</p> <p>31. Bram Verjans: Bernoulli actions of type III and their von Neumann algebras</p> <p>32. &nbsp;Gerrit Vos: BMO spaces in sigma-finite von Neumann algebras</p> <p>33. &nbsp;Lise Wouters: Equivariant Z-stability for automorphisms</p> <p>Beyond facilitating the dissemination of the most significant recent work and the identification of the most promising new research directions, the conference provided a forum for the younger generation of mathematicians -- graduate students, postdocs, and early career mathematicians -- to immerse themselves in current research, interact with senior researchers, and disseminate their own work.&nbsp;</p> </div> </div> </div> </div> <p><span><span>The grant provided support for traveling and conference participation of graduate students, postdocs, and collaborators/visitors.</span><br /></span></p> </div> </div> </div> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/20/2023<br>      Modified by: Zhizhang&nbsp;Xie</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[    YMC*A is an annual conference arranged by junior researchers (graduate students and recent PhDs) for junior researchers, with the goal of fostering scientific and social interaction between young researchers. It covers the area of operator algebras (C*- algebras as well as von Neumann algebras, despite the name) as well as applications and other interactions with adjacent fields. Senior researchers may be invited to contribute.   YMC*A 2021 was hosted at Westfalische Wilhelms-Universitat Munster (also with Zoom option) during August 2-13, 2021. The meeting took place over two weeks in order to acommodate covid protocols. There were three minicourses (Goulnara Arzhantseva, Chris Schafhauser, Jesse Peterson) and two career panels. There were also many shorter twenty-minute contributed talks by junior participant from accross the world. There were also a few three-minute poster session/micro-talks.      The three minicourses given by     Goulnara Arzhantseva (University of Vienna): Constructions of non C*-exact groups     Christopher Schafhauser (University of Nebraska  - Lincoln): On the classification of simple nuclear C*-algebras     Jesse Peterson (Vanderbilt University): Von Neumann algebras and lattices in higher-rank groups   Here is a list of speakers.   1. Anshu: Connected Stable Rank of C*-algebras  2. Kevin Aguyar Brix: C*-algebras from Symbolic Dynamics  3. Sayan Das: On the free group factor problem, and Popa?s MV-property  4. Alonso Delfin: C*-like Modules  5. Alon Dogon: Hilbert Schmidt stability and characters on amenable groups  6. Daniel Drimbe: New examples of W* and C*-superrigid groups  7. Srivatsav Kunnawalkam Elayavalli: Proper proximality for groups acting on trees  8. Marzieh Forough: Lifts of completely positive equivariant maps  9. Priyanga Ganesan: Quantum Graphs  10. Jan Gundelach: Leavitt path algebras as Cohn localisations  11. Zahra Hassanpour: Morita Equivalence and Partial Actions  12. Paul Herstedt: AT-algebras associated to zero-dimensional dynamical systems  13. Shuler Hopkins: Deformations of commuting squares and complex Hadamard matrices  14. Cristian Ivanescu: Cu-nuclearity and applications  15. Collin Mark Joseph: Topological Insulators  16. Emily Korfanty: Etale equivalence relations and C*-algebras for iterated function systems  17. Jacek Krajczok: On the radial subalgebra for the quantum group OF+  18. Alistair Miller: Groupoid Correspondences and the ABC Spectral Sequence  19. Devarshi Mukherjee: Cyclic homology and non-commutative geometry in positive characteristic  20. Robert Neagu: Amenable and Quasidiagonal traces - behaviour under homotopy  21. Sergio Giron Pacheco: Anomalous symmetries of simple operator algebras  22. Roberto Hernandez Palomares: Q-system completion for C*-algebras  23. Samantha Pilgrim: Isometric Actions and Finite Approximations  24. Ali Raad: Existence and uniqueness of inductive limit Cartan subalgebras in inductive limit C*-algebras  25. Eduardo Scarparo: A torsion-free C*-unique group  26. Apurva Seth: AF-algebras and rational homotopy theory  27.  Sushil Singla: Orthogonality, Gateaux derivative and ideals in C*-algebras  28.  Joel Right Dzokou Talla: Quantum SL(2;R) and its irreducible representations  29.  Dan Ursu: The ideal intersection property for essential groupoid C*-algebras  30.  Andrea Vaccaro: Games on AF-algebras  31. Bram Verjans: Bernoulli actions of type III and their von Neumann algebras  32.  Gerrit Vos: BMO spaces in sigma-finite von Neumann algebras  33.  Lise Wouters: Equivariant Z-stability for automorphisms  Beyond facilitating the dissemination of the most significant recent work and the identification of the most promising new research directions, the conference provided a forum for the younger generation of mathematicians -- graduate students, postdocs, and early career mathematicians -- to immerse themselves in current research, interact with senior researchers, and disseminate their own work.       The grant provided support for traveling and conference participation of graduate students, postdocs, and collaborators/visitors.              Last Modified: 07/20/2023       Submitted by: Zhizhang Xie]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
