<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Providing Work-based Experiences for Community College Biotechnology Students by Developing a Biotechnology Educational Materials Supply Chain]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>444414.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>444414</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Virginia Carter</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>vccarter@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924651</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This project proposes to provide work-based educational experiences to help prepare community college students for careers in biotechnology. Project partners include Skyline Community College, Laney Community College, regional high school science teachers, and a nonprofit community partner, Bay Area Bioscience Education Community. The project will provide community college students with skills-based job training by involving them in preparation, quality testing, and packaging of low-cost biotechnology materials for use in high school biology courses. Examples of these materials include solutions and mixtures that are commonly used in processes such as DNA analysis in both biotechnology and biological research.  As they prepare these educational materials for use in high school classes, community college students learn industry bio-manufacturing procedures and quality control processes.  Production of these materials via community college biotechnology classrooms will result in savings that will be passed on, helping high school teachers to more readily provide biotechnology educational experiences in their high school science classrooms. Through these efforts, the project aims to make biotechnology science education materials more affordable to high schools and provide community college students with work-based learning experiences that prepare them for jobs as skilled biotechnicians. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Building on prior work that developed a successful plan to recruit high school students into community college biotechnology programs, this project aims to: 1) Expand and improve the pilot program by building upon past success and lessons learned; 2) Create stronger linkages and educational pathways between high schools and community colleges; 3) Provide professional development for faculty and collaborate with high schools to co-develop a new high school biotechnology curriculum; and 4) Scale the project regionally, engage industry in partnerships, and incorporate long-term sustainability measures. If successful, the project will provide a workable and scalable template for sustainable technician education that incorporates best practices across multiple sectors and institutions.  In providing pathways to careers in biotechnology, the project has included approaches intended to ensure that all students have equitable access to participate.  An important feature of the project is its plan to expand into introductory high school science courses that are required for all students.  Such an expansion will enable them to reach all students, not just those who self-select into biotechnology electives. This approach is likely to help the nation to develop a more diverse pipeline of employees into the highly skilled technician workforce. This project is funded by the Advanced Technological Education program that focuses on the education of technicians for the advanced-technology fields that drive the nation's economy.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/11/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/25/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2000965</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ying-Tsu</FirstName>
<LastName>Loh</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ying-Tsu Loh</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[yingtsu@babec.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000812236</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/22/2022</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kristen</FirstName>
<LastName>Wolslegel</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kristen Wolslegel</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[kristen@babec.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000785910</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/11/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate>05/25/2022</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nick</FirstName>
<LastName>Kapp</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>V</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nick V Kapp</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[kapp@smccd.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000679473</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/11/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Leslie</FirstName>
<LastName>Blackie</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Leslie Blackie</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[lblackie@peralta.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000809954</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/11/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>San Mateo County Community College District</Name>
<CityName>SAN MATEO</CityName>
<ZipCode>944023651</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6503586755</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3401 CSM DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>15</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA15</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>QB6NNZ72CPH5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SAN MATEO COUNTY COMMUNITY COLLEGE DISTRICT</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Skyline College]]></Name>
<CityName>San Bruno</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>940661662</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3300 College Blvd]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>15</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA15</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7412</Code>
<Text>Advanced Tech Education Prog</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1032</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED TECHNOLOGY EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0420</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~444414</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-54351427-7fff-7e5c-1cfc-2c483f99d00f">&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><strong>Project Outcomes Report</strong><span><strong>:</strong> Strengthening Education and Bridging Communities</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><strong>Introduction</strong><span>: We are delighted to share the outcomes and impact of our project, Providing Work-based Experiences for Community College Biotechnology Students by Developing a Biotechnology Educational Materials Supply Chain, that was supported by the National Science Foundation (NSF). Our journey aimed to enhance education, foster leadership, and create meaningful connections within our community. Here, we summarize the key outcomes of our project, spanning the entire duration of the award.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><strong>Project Overview</strong><span>: Our project revolved around empowering students and educators in the field of biotechnology. With NSF's support, we embarked on a mission to promote student leadership and real work experience by bridging the gap between high schools and community colleges.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Intellectual Merit</span><span>: Our project's intellectual merit is reflected in various aspects:</span></p> <ul> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><strong>Student Leadership</strong><span>: We recognized the importance of student site coordinators with management and leadership roles. These student leaders played a pivotal role in facilitating inventory management, student recruitment, quality compliance, and packaging. They also organized regional BioSCOPE meetings, fostering collaboration among students, faculty, volunteers, and customers.</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><strong>Hands-On Learning</strong><span>: Community college (CC) and High school students benefited significantly from our project. With the assistance of CC students, High school students were able to access over 20,000 LB agar plates, and hundreds of covid simulation kits for hands-on biotech lab experiences. This not only expanded their knowledge but also ignited their passion for biotechnology.</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><strong>Automation and Quality</strong><span>: Our project exposed students to advanced biotech equipment like liquid handlers and automated plate pourers, equipping them with valuable skills for the future job market. Students actively engaged in discussions about quality improvement, ensuring that the products met the highest standards.</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><strong>Sharing and Sustainability</strong><span>: A culture of sharing materials, standard operating procedures (SOPs), and documentation was fostered throughout the project. This collaborative approach created a sustainable ecosystem where materials and knowledge could benefit other programs and students.</span></p> </li> </ul> <p dir="ltr"><strong>Broader Impacts</strong><span>: Our project's broader impacts have extended well beyond the educational realm:</span></p> <ul> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><strong>Community Engagement</strong><span>: The satisfaction of our customers was a testament to the quality of the products delivered. Furthermore, our project facilitated connections between high schools, their families, and students with the CC, creating a stronger sense of community and collaboration.</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><strong>Pathway Developmen</strong><span><strong>t</strong>: We successfully developed pathways between high schools and the CC's biotechnology program. This not only eased the transition for high school students pursuing higher education but also ensured that our local workforce was better prepared for biotech careers.</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><strong>Local Adaptation</strong><span>: Our experience working with different community colleges, such as Laney and Skyline, highlighted the need for adaptability. One-size-fits-all models did not work in each school, emphasizing the importance of tailoring workforce experiences to local conditions.</span></p> </li> </ul> <p><strong>Conclusion</strong><span>: Our NSF-supported project has been a journey of growth, education, and community building. It has empowered the students, enriched their educational experiences, and strengthened ties between high schools and community colleges. As we move forward, we remain committed to nurturing a culture of learning, collaboration, and adaptability, ensuring that our efforts continue to make a lasting impact on the lives of students and the vitality of our community by providing a cadre of students who work to support Biotechnology in both the high schools and community colleges.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/06/2023<br>      Modified by: Nick&nbsp;V&nbsp;Kapp</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2000965/2000965_10669867_1693526623296_Summer2022studentinterns--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2000965/2000965_10669867_1693526623296_Summer2022studentinterns--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Biomanufacturing Interns Summer 2022"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2000965/2000965_10669867_1693526623296_Summer2022studentinterns--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Biomanufacturing Interns Summer 2022"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Skyline Biomanufacturing summer internship.  Students from Skyline have an opportunity to work in the lab over the summer.   These students made media, solutions and other consumables for other biology classes.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jing Folsom</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Nick&nbsp;V&nbsp;Kapp</div> <div class="imageTitle">Biomanufacturing Interns Summer 2022</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2000965/2000965_10669867_1693526773100_LaneySkylineandBABECpartnerspresentatATEPIConference--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2000965/2000965_10669867_1693526773100_LaneySkylineandBABECpartnerspresentatATEPIConference--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Skyline Laney and BABEC repes at ATE PI conference"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2000965/2000965_10669867_1693526773100_LaneySkylineandBABECpartnerspresentatATEPIConference--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Skyline Laney and BABEC repes at ATE PI conference"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Partners Skyline, Laney and BABEC present at the ATE PI conference.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Nick Kapp</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Nick&nbsp;V&nbsp;Kapp</div> <div class="imageTitle">Skyline Laney and BABEC repes at ATE PI conference</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   Project Outcomes Report: Strengthening Education and Bridging Communities Introduction: We are delighted to share the outcomes and impact of our project, Providing Work-based Experiences for Community College Biotechnology Students by Developing a Biotechnology Educational Materials Supply Chain, that was supported by the National Science Foundation (NSF). Our journey aimed to enhance education, foster leadership, and create meaningful connections within our community. Here, we summarize the key outcomes of our project, spanning the entire duration of the award. Project Overview: Our project revolved around empowering students and educators in the field of biotechnology. With NSF's support, we embarked on a mission to promote student leadership and real work experience by bridging the gap between high schools and community colleges. Intellectual Merit: Our project's intellectual merit is reflected in various aspects:   Student Leadership: We recognized the importance of student site coordinators with management and leadership roles. These student leaders played a pivotal role in facilitating inventory management, student recruitment, quality compliance, and packaging. They also organized regional BioSCOPE meetings, fostering collaboration among students, faculty, volunteers, and customers.   Hands-On Learning: Community college (CC) and High school students benefited significantly from our project. With the assistance of CC students, High school students were able to access over 20,000 LB agar plates, and hundreds of covid simulation kits for hands-on biotech lab experiences. This not only expanded their knowledge but also ignited their passion for biotechnology.   Automation and Quality: Our project exposed students to advanced biotech equipment like liquid handlers and automated plate pourers, equipping them with valuable skills for the future job market. Students actively engaged in discussions about quality improvement, ensuring that the products met the highest standards.   Sharing and Sustainability: A culture of sharing materials, standard operating procedures (SOPs), and documentation was fostered throughout the project. This collaborative approach created a sustainable ecosystem where materials and knowledge could benefit other programs and students.   Broader Impacts: Our project's broader impacts have extended well beyond the educational realm:   Community Engagement: The satisfaction of our customers was a testament to the quality of the products delivered. Furthermore, our project facilitated connections between high schools, their families, and students with the CC, creating a stronger sense of community and collaboration.   Pathway Development: We successfully developed pathways between high schools and the CC's biotechnology program. This not only eased the transition for high school students pursuing higher education but also ensured that our local workforce was better prepared for biotech careers.   Local Adaptation: Our experience working with different community colleges, such as Laney and Skyline, highlighted the need for adaptability. One-size-fits-all models did not work in each school, emphasizing the importance of tailoring workforce experiences to local conditions.    Conclusion: Our NSF-supported project has been a journey of growth, education, and community building. It has empowered the students, enriched their educational experiences, and strengthened ties between high schools and community colleges. As we move forward, we remain committed to nurturing a culture of learning, collaboration, and adaptability, ensuring that our efforts continue to make a lasting impact on the lives of students and the vitality of our community by providing a cadre of students who work to support Biotechnology in both the high schools and community colleges.             Last Modified: 09/06/2023       Submitted by: Nick V Kapp]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
