<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Spectrum Innovates Pathway: Preparing Autistic Students to Enter Higher Education and Careers in Advanced Technological Fields]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>599836.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>599836</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Virginia Carter</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>vccarter@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924651</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Based on recent estimates, about 1 in 60 children born in the United States are diagnosed with autism spectrum disorder.   Autism Speaks (autismspeaks.org) currently reports that as many as 90% of autistic individuals are unemployed or underemployed.  To address the autistic community's employment needs and the forecasted shortage of technicians in the aeronautics industry over the next twenty years, nfpNEXUS, Inc. will partner with Vaughn College of Aeronautics and Technology, Inc. to develop and implement the Spectrum Innovates Pathway project.  Design of this Pathway is informed by the findings of the National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine (2018) on best practices for learning, as well as recent research that has led to modified and new cognitive models for autism. The Spectrum Innovates Pathway will support autistic students who share a common passion for aeronautics. The primary goal of the Pathway is to prepare autistic students to succeed in higher education and to enter the workforce in advanced technician roles.  This project will provide full immersion of autistic students in a STEM learning environment designed to support them as they acquire the knowledge and certifications needed for their entry into advanced technical careers.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will develop and implement a bridge year for autistic students who have completed their high school requirements. The project will leverage experiential learning to support students’ acclimation to the collegiate and work environments and development of critical life and practical skills. A robust recruitment process for students will increase awareness of the availability of the advanced technician options for autistic individuals. Students will be included in a cohort for the duration of the program, which is expected to contribute to creating a supportive learning environment. Student projects will model real world challenges to reinforce existing knowledge and skills. Industry partners will serve a dual role as advisors on emergent work force skills as well as identifying and promoting opportunities for autistic individuals in the job market. The Innovation Hub at Vaughn College of Aeronautics and Technology includes the Maker Space, Composite Prototyping Center, Robotics Lab, Flight Simulators, and Air Traffic Control Simulators.  This Hub will inform and drive the project and its methodology. Dissemination strategies will include postings about project activities and results on the project website and the Autism Speaks website, as well as through local workshops and presentations at conferences.  This project is funded by the Advanced Technological Education program that focuses on the education of technicians for the advanced-technology fields that drive the nation's economy.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/07/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/23/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2000670</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
<LastName>LaVergne</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Paul LaVergne</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[paul.lavergne@vaughn.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000161376</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/07/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Eleanore</FirstName>
<LastName>Bednarsh</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Eleanore Bednarsh</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ebednarsh@nfpnexus.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000789975</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/07/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate>03/23/2022</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Patrick</FirstName>
<LastName>Waters</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Patrick Waters</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[woodshopcowboy@gmail.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000811648</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/23/2022</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Patrick</FirstName>
<LastName>Waters</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Patrick Waters</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[woodshopcowboy@gmail.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000811648</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/07/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate>03/23/2022</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Hope</FirstName>
<LastName>Chafiian</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Hope R Chafiian</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[hchafiian@gmail.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000811531</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/07/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>NFP NEXUS INC</Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<ZipCode>100033912</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7183357353</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>200 E 15TH ST APT 9E</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>LBEWBDG6N2P8</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SPECTRUM INNOVATES, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[VAUGHN COLLEGE OF AERONAUTICS AND TECHNOLOGY]]></Name>
<CityName>EAST ELMHURST</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>113691000</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[8601 23RD AVE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>14</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY14</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7412</Code>
<Text>Advanced Tech Education Prog</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1032</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED TECHNOLOGY EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0420</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~599836</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-4abf9c10-7fff-cdfb-3b1a-804f9cadfcb4">&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>To address the autistic community's employment crisis and the forecast shortage of technicians in the aeronautics industry over the next twenty years, Spectrum Innovates, Inc. developed the Spectrum Innovates Pathway Program (SIPP). SIPP, a prototypal transition pathway program for those on the autism spectrum who share a common passion for aeronautics. The primary goals of the SIPP program are to prepare students to succeed in higher education and enter the workforce in advanced technician roles. Our partner in this initiative is Vaughn College of Aeronautics and Technology, Inc. (Vaughn), whose vision is to change the world one student at a time with a transformational education that creates a lifetime of opportunity.</span><span><br /></span><span><br /></span><span>As of April 2022, the SI Team completed development of the curriculum framework for integration of the components of the scaffold.&nbsp; The Innovation Hub provides reinforcement and application of academic content and social emotional skills.&nbsp; The Team created projects that are complementary to the academic portion of the program. These projects also help the student to develop and hone &ldquo;soft skills'' and via reflections, assessment, feedback loops and benchmarks guiding student engagement and progress. Projects and simulations have been structured to reflect industry needs and expand the student&rsquo;s breadth of understanding of possible career paths.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The six-week orientation has been finalized.&nbsp; It provides introductory projects to the students that inform on workspace safety, how to ask for help, facility awareness and the opportunity to adjust to a new learning experience. For the program, it provides the ability to assess strengths, social dynamics and social emotional skills as well as cohort dynamics in absentia of a concurrent academic load.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The Team finalized the two-semester curriculum, which includes modified delivery and blended observational and practical assessment of competency.&nbsp; The content of the curriculum meets the requirements for college credits but monitors learning through short-term assessment.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The six-week residency experience section of the program is completed. During the six weeks students will live on campus, propose, design, and execute an industry-defined project, utilizing the maker, math and English skills honed over the previous nine months. They may work in teams or individually, and will provide ongoing feedback and review of their project&rsquo;s progress. At the end of the sixth week, students will present their projects to an audience and discuss their professional growth and the development and relevance of their project,</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Due to insurmountable personnel issues and the timing of the COVID-19 pandemic, Spectrum Innovates was unable to make the transition from program design to implementation.&nbsp; </span></p> <div><span><br /></span></div> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/01/2023<br>      Modified by: Patrick&nbsp;Waters</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   To address the autistic community's employment crisis and the forecast shortage of technicians in the aeronautics industry over the next twenty years, Spectrum Innovates, Inc. developed the Spectrum Innovates Pathway Program (SIPP). SIPP, a prototypal transition pathway program for those on the autism spectrum who share a common passion for aeronautics. The primary goals of the SIPP program are to prepare students to succeed in higher education and enter the workforce in advanced technician roles. Our partner in this initiative is Vaughn College of Aeronautics and Technology, Inc. (Vaughn), whose vision is to change the world one student at a time with a transformational education that creates a lifetime of opportunity.  As of April 2022, the SI Team completed development of the curriculum framework for integration of the components of the scaffold.  The Innovation Hub provides reinforcement and application of academic content and social emotional skills.  The Team created projects that are complementary to the academic portion of the program. These projects also help the student to develop and hone "soft skills'' and via reflections, assessment, feedback loops and benchmarks guiding student engagement and progress. Projects and simulations have been structured to reflect industry needs and expand the student’s breadth of understanding of possible career paths. The six-week orientation has been finalized.  It provides introductory projects to the students that inform on workspace safety, how to ask for help, facility awareness and the opportunity to adjust to a new learning experience. For the program, it provides the ability to assess strengths, social dynamics and social emotional skills as well as cohort dynamics in absentia of a concurrent academic load.  The Team finalized the two-semester curriculum, which includes modified delivery and blended observational and practical assessment of competency.  The content of the curriculum meets the requirements for college credits but monitors learning through short-term assessment.  The six-week residency experience section of the program is completed. During the six weeks students will live on campus, propose, design, and execute an industry-defined project, utilizing the maker, math and English skills honed over the previous nine months. They may work in teams or individually, and will provide ongoing feedback and review of their project’s progress. At the end of the sixth week, students will present their projects to an audience and discuss their professional growth and the development and relevance of their project, Due to insurmountable personnel issues and the timing of the COVID-19 pandemic, Spectrum Innovates was unable to make the transition from program design to implementation.                 Last Modified: 11/01/2023       Submitted by: Patrick Waters]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
