<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[A Regression Discontinuity Study of the Impact of Mathematics Achievement Fund on Student Outcomes]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>939673.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>939673</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DGE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Graduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Andrea Nixon</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>anixon@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922321</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Socioeconomic and racial gaps in STEM (science, technology, engineering, and mathematics) participation can sometimes be traced back to discrepancies in mathematics skills that emerge at kindergarten entry. Importantly, children who exhibit early lags in mathematics development may also demonstrate lower growth rates in mathematics skills later. Consequently, early gaps in mathematics skills may widen over the course of schooling. How to diagnose and correct mathematics shortcomings early is a challenge that K–12 schools must confront systematically. Unlike reading, few states currently have a coherent statewide program for early mathematics intervention. Kentucky’s Mathematics Achievement Fund (MAF)—a statewide K-3 mathematics intervention program—is a prime example of a state’s effort to intervene early on to change a student’s mathematics development trajectory. By using a quasi-experimental design with data gathered during the implementation of MAF, this study will provide valuable information on how states can structure and provide resources to support early mathematics intervention efforts. The project will connect research and practice and add much-needed information to the existing knowledge base that states can use when considering early-grade mathematics programs. The proposed project is a joint effort between the American Institutes for Research and the Kentucky Department of Education and is supported by the EHR Core Research (ECR) program, which supports work that advances fundamental research on STEM learning and learning environments, broadening participation in STEM, and STEM workforce development.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Existing early-grade mathematics interventions tend to be one-off, localized efforts, usually without a coherent or sustainable strategy, and often implemented by experimenters or supported by vendors of prepackaged interventions. Interventions that show promising results are typically small-scale studies, whereas large-scale studies often find null benefits. This project is designed to examine the causal effects of MAF on student outcomes in a regression discontinuity framework. In particular, the project will use student-level administrative data and original data collected through surveys and interviews to examine the causal effects of MAF on students’ academic and non-academic outcomes both immediately after the intervention and in later grades. The project will also investigate who is likely to benefit from MAF and under what conditions and conduct a cost-effectiveness analysis of the program. The project will contribute to the existing literature in several ways. First, most existing studies on early mathematics interventions focus on student outcomes at the end of the intervention. There is evidence that large, short-run effects on student scores in early grades could dissipate over time. By tracking some 3rd-grade students into high school, the project plans to examine the extent to which the short-term benefits of the MAF program, if any, persist over time. Further, the project will also explore how MAF may affect other aspects of children’s schooling experiences such as possible spillover effects of MAF on other subjects and non-test outcomes like middle school course-taking and student engagement. In this way, the proposed project seeks to catalyze new knowledge that will help inform the discussion on systematic, coherent early-grade mathematics policies at the state level.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/29/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/29/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2000483</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Zeyu</FirstName>
<LastName>Xu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Zeyu Xu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[zxu@air.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000648796</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/29/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Umut</FirstName>
<LastName>Ozek</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Umut Ozek</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[uozek@air.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000648901</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/29/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>American Institutes for Research in the Behavioral Sciences</Name>
<CityName>ARLINGTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>222023289</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2024035000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1400 CRYSTAL DR FL 10</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>VA08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>MCN6J5L6M3T4</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>AMERICAN INSTITUTES FOR RESEARCH IN THE BEHAVIORAL SCIENCES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[American Institutes for Research]]></Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>200073835</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1000 Thomas Jefferson Street, NW]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7980</Code>
<Text>ECR-EDU Core Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8212</Code>
<Text>Broaden Particip STEM Resrch</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8817</Code>
<Text>STEM Learning &amp; Learning Environments</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0420</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~939673</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Large socioeconomic gaps in mathematics skills emerge at kindergarten entry. Research shows that children who exhibit early delays in mathematical development also tend to learn at a slower rate. As a result, early gaps in mathematics skills often widen further over the course of schooling. How to diagnose and correct mathematics deficiencies early is a challenge that K-12 schools must confront systematically.</p> <p>Early-grade mathematics interventions tend to be one-off, local efforts. Unlike reading, few states have a coherent statewide mathematics intervention program for early elementary grades. This project examines the effects of Kentucky's Math Achievement Fund (MAF)--the only fully implemented statewide K-3 mathematics intervention program known to us at the time of this project--on student outcomes. A key feature of MAF is that it not only provides supplemental support to children who are struggling to meet grade level or benchmark expectations for mathematics, but also emphasizes schoolwide capacity building by overhauling mathematics instructional strategy and practice and strengthening collaboration among teachers. Through renewable, two-year local grants to approximately 90 schools per year, MAF provides funding to support the hiring of one full-time mathematics intervention teacher (MIT) and training for the MIT and two classroom mathematics teachers (known as the Plus 2 teachers) each year.</p> <p>Using a quasi-experimental method, the project found no difference in mathematics scores between students in MAF grantee schools and students in similar non-grantee schools at the end of the first year of the award. However, students in MAF grantee schools scored higher than similar students in non-grantee schools by 0.05 standard deviation after 2 years, 0.08 standard deviation after 3 years, and 0.09 standard deviation after 4 years (Figure 1). To put the size of the MAF effect into perspective, the 4th year effect is equivalent to the effect of a class size reduction of 4 to 5 students or the effect of replacing all novice teachers with teachers with 3 to 5 years of experience. The project also found positive spillover effects on reading achievement as well as reduced disciplinary incidents and absences.&nbsp;These benefits were found in both targeted grades (K-3) and untargeted elementary grades, and the benefits sustained even after grantee schools stopped receiving MAF support (Figure 2). The impacts are consistent across racial/ethnic and socioeconomic groups with slightly larger benefits for racial minorities (Figure 3).</p> <p>Findings from this study suggest that small-group instruction, personalized support for students, peer-coaching, and close collaboration among teachers--key features of the MAF program--could improve the overall mathematics learning environment when implemented at scale. The findings are also consistent with the theory that mathematics interventions need to be paired with improved regular classroom teaching to maintain the gains in mathematics skills achieved during the interventions. At an estimated four-year per-pupil cost of $750 (in 2018-19 dollars), programs like MAF could provide a cost-effective blueprint to address the educational needs of students in mathematics in early grades.</p> <p>The project identified several potential challenges to implementing MAF-like programs. First, MAF supports just over 90 grantee schools. The extent to which a program like MAF can be further scaled up remains an open question. Second, even at the current scale, grantee schools reported several implementation challenges including difficulty in recruiting qualified MITs, turnovers of MIT and Plus 2 teachers, insufficient number of training slots, and difficulty in creating an intervention schedule that did not conflict with any core classes.</p> <p>One particular concern shared by mathematics teachers is whether mathematics screeners such as the <em>MAP</em>, <em>iReady</em>, and <em>Star</em> can accurately identify mathematics deficiencies among K-3 children. The project used a machine learning technique and found that typically recommended grade-level screener cut scores severely under-identify student needs in mathematics. Using the estimated optimal cut scores, the likelihood of under-identification of at-risk students in mathematics development decreases by an average of 16 percentage points. These improvements can be achieved without having to collect new data or administer new assessments.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/25/2023<br>      Modified by: Zeyu&nbsp;Xu</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2000483/2000483_10681186_1695648276442_Figure1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2000483/2000483_10681186_1695648276442_Figure1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 1. Effects of MAF Designation on Student Outcomes: Event Study Estimates"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2000483/2000483_10681186_1695648276442_Figure1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 1. Effects of MAF Designation on Student Outcomes: Event Study Estimates"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 1. Effects of MAF Designation on Student Outcomes: Event Study Estimates</div> <div class="imageCredit">Authors' estimation</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Zeyu&nbsp;Xu</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 1. Effects of MAF Designation on Student Outcomes: Event Study Estimates</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2000483/2000483_10681186_1695648490095_Figure2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2000483/2000483_10681186_1695648490095_Figure2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 2. Effects of MAF Designation on Student Outcomes: Event Study Estimates, by School Duration in MAF"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2000483/2000483_10681186_1695648490095_Figure2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 2. Effects of MAF Designation on Student Outcomes: Event Study Estimates, by School Duration in MAF"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 2. Effects of MAF Designation on Student Outcomes: Event Study Estimates, by School Duration in MAF</div> <div class="imageCredit">Authors' estimation</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Zeyu&nbsp;Xu</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 2. Effects of MAF Designation on Student Outcomes: Event Study Estimates, by School Duration in MAF</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2000483/2000483_10681186_1695648697734_Figure3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2000483/2000483_10681186_1695648697734_Figure3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 3. Effects of MAF Designation on Student Outcomes: Event Study Estimates, by Student Race/Ethnicity"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2000483/2000483_10681186_1695648697734_Figure3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 3. Effects of MAF Designation on Student Outcomes: Event Study Estimates, by Student Race/Ethnicity"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 3. Effects of MAF Designation on Student Outcomes: Event Study Estimates, by Student Race/Ethnicity</div> <div class="imageCredit">Authors' estimation</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Zeyu&nbsp;Xu</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 3. Effects of MAF Designation on Student Outcomes: Event Study Estimates, by Student Race/Ethnicity</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Large socioeconomic gaps in mathematics skills emerge at kindergarten entry. Research shows that children who exhibit early delays in mathematical development also tend to learn at a slower rate. As a result, early gaps in mathematics skills often widen further over the course of schooling. How to diagnose and correct mathematics deficiencies early is a challenge that K-12 schools must confront systematically.  Early-grade mathematics interventions tend to be one-off, local efforts. Unlike reading, few states have a coherent statewide mathematics intervention program for early elementary grades. This project examines the effects of Kentucky's Math Achievement Fund (MAF)--the only fully implemented statewide K-3 mathematics intervention program known to us at the time of this project--on student outcomes. A key feature of MAF is that it not only provides supplemental support to children who are struggling to meet grade level or benchmark expectations for mathematics, but also emphasizes schoolwide capacity building by overhauling mathematics instructional strategy and practice and strengthening collaboration among teachers. Through renewable, two-year local grants to approximately 90 schools per year, MAF provides funding to support the hiring of one full-time mathematics intervention teacher (MIT) and training for the MIT and two classroom mathematics teachers (known as the Plus 2 teachers) each year.  Using a quasi-experimental method, the project found no difference in mathematics scores between students in MAF grantee schools and students in similar non-grantee schools at the end of the first year of the award. However, students in MAF grantee schools scored higher than similar students in non-grantee schools by 0.05 standard deviation after 2 years, 0.08 standard deviation after 3 years, and 0.09 standard deviation after 4 years (Figure 1). To put the size of the MAF effect into perspective, the 4th year effect is equivalent to the effect of a class size reduction of 4 to 5 students or the effect of replacing all novice teachers with teachers with 3 to 5 years of experience. The project also found positive spillover effects on reading achievement as well as reduced disciplinary incidents and absences. These benefits were found in both targeted grades (K-3) and untargeted elementary grades, and the benefits sustained even after grantee schools stopped receiving MAF support (Figure 2). The impacts are consistent across racial/ethnic and socioeconomic groups with slightly larger benefits for racial minorities (Figure 3).  Findings from this study suggest that small-group instruction, personalized support for students, peer-coaching, and close collaboration among teachers--key features of the MAF program--could improve the overall mathematics learning environment when implemented at scale. The findings are also consistent with the theory that mathematics interventions need to be paired with improved regular classroom teaching to maintain the gains in mathematics skills achieved during the interventions. At an estimated four-year per-pupil cost of $750 (in 2018-19 dollars), programs like MAF could provide a cost-effective blueprint to address the educational needs of students in mathematics in early grades.  The project identified several potential challenges to implementing MAF-like programs. First, MAF supports just over 90 grantee schools. The extent to which a program like MAF can be further scaled up remains an open question. Second, even at the current scale, grantee schools reported several implementation challenges including difficulty in recruiting qualified MITs, turnovers of MIT and Plus 2 teachers, insufficient number of training slots, and difficulty in creating an intervention schedule that did not conflict with any core classes.  One particular concern shared by mathematics teachers is whether mathematics screeners such as the MAP, iReady, and Star can accurately identify mathematics deficiencies among K-3 children. The project used a machine learning technique and found that typically recommended grade-level screener cut scores severely under-identify student needs in mathematics. Using the estimated optimal cut scores, the likelihood of under-identification of at-risk students in mathematics development decreases by an average of 16 percentage points. These improvements can be achieved without having to collect new data or administer new assessments.          Last Modified: 09/25/2023       Submitted by: Zeyu Xu]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
