<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Doctoral Dissertation Research: Impact of Geography and Social Ties on Health and Well-being]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>3697.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>3697</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joseph Whitmeyer</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jwhitmey@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927808</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This project examines how the social and spatial environments in which people live either jointly or separately and independently affect their mental and physical health. A fundamental social and biological fact about human beings is that where people live shapes who they become, and their health and economic prospects in particular. The reasons for this are still not fully understood but one key reason is that people do not live on their own; relationships to others give rise to face-to-face social networks, and these social connections generally occupy the same places. Research has established the connections between networks and place, and between networks and health, but this doctoral dissertation research project explores the intersection of all three (people in networks in places).  Results may help practitioners and decision makers create new ways of thinking about geographically contextualized networks and new ways of addressing important public health concerns.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research uses extremely detailed data on 24,812 individuals in 176 communities in a setting in which people live in close proximity to members of their social networks.  Statistical methods such as multilevel models are employed to answer a variety of questions related to networks, geography, and health. The researcher investigates the following questions: 1) Is network centrality associated with geographic centrality and how do these locations impact health? 2) Are negative ties between individuals spatially patterned such that individuals “keep their enemies closer” than their friends, and how does this proximity influence health? 3) Using the ecological concept of “ecotones,” do individuals in particular locations experience higher variability in health outcomes?&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/12/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/12/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2001777</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nicholas</FirstName>
<LastName>Christakis</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nicholas Christakis</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[nicholas.christakis@yale.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000789311</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/12/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Margaret</FirstName>
<LastName>Traeger</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Margaret Traeger</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[margaret.traeger@yale.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000783088</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/12/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Yale University</Name>
<CityName>NEW HAVEN</CityName>
<ZipCode>065118917</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2037854689</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>105 WALL ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CT03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>FL6GV84CKN57</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>YALE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>FL6GV84CKN57</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Yale University]]></Name>
<CityName>New Haven</CityName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>065118965</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[17 Hillhouse]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CT03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1331</Code>
<Text>Sociology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~3697</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This doctoral dissertation research explored how social networks and geographic place can jointly and separately impact health. The co-PI explored how different types of social ties, and their positions between people within geographic space, are associated with health outcomes.</p> <p>This research a) evaluated the overlap between neighborhoods and networks and the degree to which each context contributes to health outcomes; b) determined how geographic relationships are related to the ties that form between people and how these ties influence health outcomes; and c) began to establish whether those living on the periphery of a community have more variation in their health outcomes than those who live centrally.<em>&nbsp;</em></p> <p>First, the co-PI pursued a basic exploration of whether there is an association between geographic and network centrality. In other words, does living at the edge of a village geographically translate into living on the periphery of the village network. The co-PI found that those who are more geographically distant are also less socially connected. Furthermore, the co-PI found that, across a variety of health outcomes (e.g. self-reported mental and physical health), network position (e.g. degree) played a larger role in each health outcome than geographic location (e.g. distance from village centroid).</p> <p>Second, the co-PI examined the spatial clustering of antagonistic ties and how geographic proximity to antagonistic ties shapes health. The co-PI found that villages with a great deal of antagonism were near other villages with a lot of antagonism (positive spatial autocorrelation). Furthermore, in contrast to other studies, the co-PI found that those who live at intermediate elevations have more antagonistic ties than those at either elevation extreme. The co-PI also found that villages with higher household densities have <em>less</em> antagonism. These antagonistic ties are related to health outcomes, too - having even one antagonistic tie, increasing numbers of antagonistic ties (and more that are geographically close), and more negative ties relative to friendly ties are all associated with worse mental health. However, the farther away a respondent's nearest antagonistic tie, the more likely the respondent is to report that their mental health is good.</p> <p>Third, the co-PI attempted to determine how health outcomes vary by network and geographic zone. Across a variety of network centrality metrics, the co-PI found, surprisingly, that those who were more central in their networks smoked less, described their mental and physical health as being poorer, and were more likely to report a recent respiratory illness. Geographic position was not associated with most health outcomes, though those who were more geographically peripheral were slightly more likely to smoke and reported better mental and physical health. The co-PI also found that variability in health outcomes is patterned by position in both geographic and geodesic space. Specifically, those who are more central in their networks have more variation in self-reported depression and respiratory illness. Those who are more central in their networks also have <em>less</em> variance in their overall mental and physical health, and in their current smoking status. Increasing geographic distance (being less central geographically) is associated with less variance in mental health outcomes and reports of recent respiratory illness. However, living in more geographically remote areas is also associated with more variance in smoking status.</p> <p>This research project resulted in the completion of the co-PIs doctoral dissertation, titled "Impact of Geography and Social Ties on Health and Well-being," which was successfully defended in May 2021. The results of this research will be shared with the research team in both the United States and Honduras, as well as with other stakeholders (public health practitioners and policy makers) in Honduras (Ministry of Health of Honduras and with the Inter-American Development Bank). Overall, the research presented in this dissertation can be used to inform public health and public policy interventions, while affording many opportunities to explore new questions in the social networks and geography space. Using extraordinarily novel and expansive data, this research shows that, without accounting for the context in which networks take form, we may overlook the influence of place on health and well-being. In short, social network structure and geographic location influences human experiences. Human social behavior and social connections are profoundly shaped by actors and situations outside of themselves, and as such we must account for this effect.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/28/2021<br>      Modified by: Margaret&nbsp;Traeger</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This doctoral dissertation research explored how social networks and geographic place can jointly and separately impact health. The co-PI explored how different types of social ties, and their positions between people within geographic space, are associated with health outcomes.  This research a) evaluated the overlap between neighborhoods and networks and the degree to which each context contributes to health outcomes; b) determined how geographic relationships are related to the ties that form between people and how these ties influence health outcomes; and c) began to establish whether those living on the periphery of a community have more variation in their health outcomes than those who live centrally.   First, the co-PI pursued a basic exploration of whether there is an association between geographic and network centrality. In other words, does living at the edge of a village geographically translate into living on the periphery of the village network. The co-PI found that those who are more geographically distant are also less socially connected. Furthermore, the co-PI found that, across a variety of health outcomes (e.g. self-reported mental and physical health), network position (e.g. degree) played a larger role in each health outcome than geographic location (e.g. distance from village centroid).  Second, the co-PI examined the spatial clustering of antagonistic ties and how geographic proximity to antagonistic ties shapes health. The co-PI found that villages with a great deal of antagonism were near other villages with a lot of antagonism (positive spatial autocorrelation). Furthermore, in contrast to other studies, the co-PI found that those who live at intermediate elevations have more antagonistic ties than those at either elevation extreme. The co-PI also found that villages with higher household densities have less antagonism. These antagonistic ties are related to health outcomes, too - having even one antagonistic tie, increasing numbers of antagonistic ties (and more that are geographically close), and more negative ties relative to friendly ties are all associated with worse mental health. However, the farther away a respondent's nearest antagonistic tie, the more likely the respondent is to report that their mental health is good.  Third, the co-PI attempted to determine how health outcomes vary by network and geographic zone. Across a variety of network centrality metrics, the co-PI found, surprisingly, that those who were more central in their networks smoked less, described their mental and physical health as being poorer, and were more likely to report a recent respiratory illness. Geographic position was not associated with most health outcomes, though those who were more geographically peripheral were slightly more likely to smoke and reported better mental and physical health. The co-PI also found that variability in health outcomes is patterned by position in both geographic and geodesic space. Specifically, those who are more central in their networks have more variation in self-reported depression and respiratory illness. Those who are more central in their networks also have less variance in their overall mental and physical health, and in their current smoking status. Increasing geographic distance (being less central geographically) is associated with less variance in mental health outcomes and reports of recent respiratory illness. However, living in more geographically remote areas is also associated with more variance in smoking status.  This research project resulted in the completion of the co-PIs doctoral dissertation, titled "Impact of Geography and Social Ties on Health and Well-being," which was successfully defended in May 2021. The results of this research will be shared with the research team in both the United States and Honduras, as well as with other stakeholders (public health practitioners and policy makers) in Honduras (Ministry of Health of Honduras and with the Inter-American Development Bank). Overall, the research presented in this dissertation can be used to inform public health and public policy interventions, while affording many opportunities to explore new questions in the social networks and geography space. Using extraordinarily novel and expansive data, this research shows that, without accounting for the context in which networks take form, we may overlook the influence of place on health and well-being. In short, social network structure and geographic location influences human experiences. Human social behavior and social connections are profoundly shaped by actors and situations outside of themselves, and as such we must account for this effect.          Last Modified: 08/28/2021       Submitted by: Margaret Traeger]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
