<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Doctoral Dissertation Research: Households and the Future of Work: The Rise of Industrious Households After the Decline of the Family Wage, 1970-2008.]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>15999.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>15999</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joseph Whitmeyer</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jwhitmey@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927808</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[As jobs become increasingly flexible, contingent, and automated, social research and governmental concern has centered on the future of work. Responding to these changes in the labor market since the 1970s, a growing number of American families pursued money outside of labor markets. In this project, three case studies will follow the rise of direct selling (Avon, Amway, Herbalife), leasing of accessory dwelling units within homes, and the rise of home equity extraction. Direct sellers in the 1980s and 1990s carefully balanced attempts to marketize kinship and social ties, without severing them irreparably, that provided housewives an avenue to pursue secondary incomes without fully abandoning the ideal of the breadwinner-homemaker model. Families who began leasing spare bedrooms and garages in the 1990s sought to avoid the stigma of immigrant informality by leasing “granny flats” and “in-law units,” portraying their marketization of the single-family home as a natural extension of the nuclear family. Extractions of home-equity in the early 2000s tapped into long-time associations between property ownership and landed independence, allowing homeowners to interpret equity loans as tapping into their wealth, rather than as taking on risky loans. These cases illustrate household strategies to generate resources outside standard wages—providing a lens into a rearrangement of household economic life since the 1970s. Findings will inform governmental policies, particularly those governing dwelling leasing and home equity extraction, to maximize their appropriate use balanced against risk.   &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;As American households faced uncertain returns to waged labor, its members grew likely to embrace three strategies of industriousness: (1) labor-intensive industriousness characterized by increases in the number of wage earners or the time devoted to wage work by a household; (2) distributive industriousness, characterized by entrepreneurial turns toward kinship and social networks in attempts to siphon small but regular access to cash resources; and (3) rentier industriousness, characterized by attempts at securing incomes from claims on household goods or assets. Because most social research on labor restructuring focuses on labor-intensive industriousness, the core of this project are case studies of the distributive and rentier household activity.  Leveraging administrative and archival data from municipalities, federal regulators, congressional records, newspapers, and industry publications, each of the three case studies analyzes: (1) the motivations driving early industrious activity; (2) regulatory challenges and incorporation; and (3) trajectories of socio-economic, racial, and gendered diffusion across groups of households. This project suggests that at the root of recent expansions in economic informality are not new technology platforms, but rather changes in labor market organization dating back to the 1980s. The findings of this research illuminate sociological theories regarding the family and its intersection with the U.S. economy in the late 20th and early 21st centuries. Findings will also provide insight into related changes as work continues to evolve in the United States and the world.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/19/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/19/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2001720</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Greta</FirstName>
<LastName>Krippner</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Greta Krippner</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[krippner@umich.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000569606</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/19/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Luis</FirstName>
<LastName>Flores</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME>Jr</PI_SUFX_NAME>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Luis Flores</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jrluisf@umich.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000812826</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/19/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Regents of the University of Michigan - Ann Arbor</Name>
<CityName>ANN ARBOR</CityName>
<ZipCode>481091079</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1109 GEDDES AVE, SUITE 3300</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>GNJ7BBP73WE9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MICHIGAN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Michigan Ann Arbor]]></Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>481091340</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3003 South State St. Room 1062]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1331</Code>
<Text>Sociology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>063Z</Code>
<Text>FW-HTF Futr Wrk Hum-Tech Frntr</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~15999</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project examined the regulatory contests through which American homes became sites of economic production, exchange, and speculation&mdash;what this project terms the rise of &ldquo;home-based moneymaking&rdquo; since the 1970s. What is the link between labor restructuring and rising household economic informality? How did these practices go from being regulated as racialized informality to solutions to rising economic insecurity? Finally, how do these practices reflect efforts to navigate the demands of care work in a changing economy?</p> <p>This project consisted of two case studies of regulatory conflict. A first concerned labor protections enshrined in the Fair Labor Standards Acts (FLSA). First passed in 1938, the FLSA includes minimum wage regulations, as well as restrictions on child labor and industrial homework. In the 1980s, diverse forms of home-based work fueled public support for the lifting of the FLSAs homework ban; while labor unions defended the ban arguing that it was the keystone of labor protections. A second case concerned local-level zoning laws that restricted the rental of rooms, garages, or basements in single-family homes to tenants. In the 1970s and 1980s, a proliferation of illegal &ldquo;garage conversions&rdquo; or &ldquo;bootleg apartments,&rdquo; resulted initially in expansions of code enforcement and strike forces, aiming to curb the practice. However, by the late 1980s, the &ldquo;granny flat&rdquo; and the &lsquo;accessory dwelling unit&rdquo; emerged as more acceptable versions of this practice. States, like California in 1982, and advocacy organizations for elderly Americans supported the relaxation of land-use zoning restrictions on accessory dwellings in the 1990s.</p> <p>This research found that these practices were initially confined to groups at the margins of the most stable labor markets&mdash;&ldquo;displaced homemakers,&rdquo; workers of color, immigrants, and the &ldquo;home rich but cash poor&rdquo; elderly. As labor market restructuring broadened experiences of precarity, the appeal of once-marginal moneymaking practices spread. For the on industrial homework, this meant the formation of unlikely coalitions of middle-class women, conservative rural women, and advocacy organizations for elderly Americans. Analysis of this case traced how in the process of public contestation over labor law, homebased work shifted from being regulated a as a <em>threat </em>to the American family, to a solution to rising economic precarity. In the analysis of zoning debates over accessory dwelling units, this project discovered the proliferation of &ldquo;strike forces&rdquo; in the 1980s, and local resistance to state-level pressure from the California legislature to allow the rental of accessory dwelling units. Local governments responded to this pressure with age-restrictive &ldquo;granny flat&rdquo; variances for second units.</p> <p>Moreover, in this project&rsquo;s study of regulatory debates over labor law restrictions on industrial homework, researchers came across parallel efforts to relax restrictions on child labor laws in the 1970s and 1980s. While these were successful at the state level, efforts to amend restrictions on underage work gained less traction at the federal level. This unexpected finding helps to extend their focus on the restructuring of the boundary between the home and the marketplace during the 1980s. Similarly, this study&rsquo;s examination of code enforcement records related to the rental of accessory dwelling units uncovered a parallel development for this case too. Alongside neighbor complaints over the rental of garages to immigrant tenants were numerous complaints about the operation of home-based auto mechanic operations, often in the garages of immigrant homes. This unexpected finding alerted researchers to distinct modes of making commercial use of garages during the same period in the 1980s.</p> <p><strong>Intellectual Merit</strong> - This project revisits a question at the origin of sociological thinking. At least since Max Weber, sociologists of industrialization have posited the departure of productive and market-oriented activity from the household as a hallmark of modern society. This NSF-funded dissertation research sheds light into this under-examined but increasingly discussed dimension of post-industrial America: the commercialization of homes. To sociological researchers, this project offers an alternative to technological determinist accounts of this transition, by showing the origins of these practices in the decades before the emergence of digital platforms that enabled gig work. Rather, this project highlights social contradictions and conflicts over the regulatory infrastructure of the post-war family wage, which became the object of contestation as households sought to engage in household economic informality in response to changes in the labor market.</p> <p><strong>Broader Impact</strong> - The findings from this project, which will be turned into a book manuscript in the coming years, is likely to generate popular interest given discussions over the rise and desirability of &ldquo;work from home.&rdquo; The longer-term account of the commercialization of home life that will be presented by this book manuscript will help contextualize the current trend in a longer line of regulatory contests over the stakes of protecting the family and the single-family home against commercialization. This work will highlight the contrast between <em>waged </em>homeworkers and the longer lineage of non-wage home-based workers.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/28/2022<br>      Modified by: Luis&nbsp;Flores</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project examined the regulatory contests through which American homes became sites of economic production, exchange, and speculation&mdash;what this project terms the rise of "home-based moneymaking" since the 1970s. What is the link between labor restructuring and rising household economic informality? How did these practices go from being regulated as racialized informality to solutions to rising economic insecurity? Finally, how do these practices reflect efforts to navigate the demands of care work in a changing economy?  This project consisted of two case studies of regulatory conflict. A first concerned labor protections enshrined in the Fair Labor Standards Acts (FLSA). First passed in 1938, the FLSA includes minimum wage regulations, as well as restrictions on child labor and industrial homework. In the 1980s, diverse forms of home-based work fueled public support for the lifting of the FLSAs homework ban; while labor unions defended the ban arguing that it was the keystone of labor protections. A second case concerned local-level zoning laws that restricted the rental of rooms, garages, or basements in single-family homes to tenants. In the 1970s and 1980s, a proliferation of illegal "garage conversions" or "bootleg apartments," resulted initially in expansions of code enforcement and strike forces, aiming to curb the practice. However, by the late 1980s, the "granny flat" and the ‘accessory dwelling unit" emerged as more acceptable versions of this practice. States, like California in 1982, and advocacy organizations for elderly Americans supported the relaxation of land-use zoning restrictions on accessory dwellings in the 1990s.  This research found that these practices were initially confined to groups at the margins of the most stable labor markets&mdash;"displaced homemakers," workers of color, immigrants, and the "home rich but cash poor" elderly. As labor market restructuring broadened experiences of precarity, the appeal of once-marginal moneymaking practices spread. For the on industrial homework, this meant the formation of unlikely coalitions of middle-class women, conservative rural women, and advocacy organizations for elderly Americans. Analysis of this case traced how in the process of public contestation over labor law, homebased work shifted from being regulated a as a threat to the American family, to a solution to rising economic precarity. In the analysis of zoning debates over accessory dwelling units, this project discovered the proliferation of "strike forces" in the 1980s, and local resistance to state-level pressure from the California legislature to allow the rental of accessory dwelling units. Local governments responded to this pressure with age-restrictive "granny flat" variances for second units.  Moreover, in this project’s study of regulatory debates over labor law restrictions on industrial homework, researchers came across parallel efforts to relax restrictions on child labor laws in the 1970s and 1980s. While these were successful at the state level, efforts to amend restrictions on underage work gained less traction at the federal level. This unexpected finding helps to extend their focus on the restructuring of the boundary between the home and the marketplace during the 1980s. Similarly, this study’s examination of code enforcement records related to the rental of accessory dwelling units uncovered a parallel development for this case too. Alongside neighbor complaints over the rental of garages to immigrant tenants were numerous complaints about the operation of home-based auto mechanic operations, often in the garages of immigrant homes. This unexpected finding alerted researchers to distinct modes of making commercial use of garages during the same period in the 1980s.  Intellectual Merit - This project revisits a question at the origin of sociological thinking. At least since Max Weber, sociologists of industrialization have posited the departure of productive and market-oriented activity from the household as a hallmark of modern society. This NSF-funded dissertation research sheds light into this under-examined but increasingly discussed dimension of post-industrial America: the commercialization of homes. To sociological researchers, this project offers an alternative to technological determinist accounts of this transition, by showing the origins of these practices in the decades before the emergence of digital platforms that enabled gig work. Rather, this project highlights social contradictions and conflicts over the regulatory infrastructure of the post-war family wage, which became the object of contestation as households sought to engage in household economic informality in response to changes in the labor market.  Broader Impact - The findings from this project, which will be turned into a book manuscript in the coming years, is likely to generate popular interest given discussions over the rise and desirability of "work from home." The longer-term account of the commercialization of home life that will be presented by this book manuscript will help contextualize the current trend in a longer line of regulatory contests over the stakes of protecting the family and the single-family home against commercialization. This work will highlight the contrast between waged homeworkers and the longer lineage of non-wage home-based workers.       Last Modified: 11/28/2022       Submitted by: Luis Flores]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
