<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[PostDoctoral Research Fellowship]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>150000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>150000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Stefaan De Winter</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sgdewint@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922599</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This award is made as part of the FY 2020 Mathematical Sciences Postdoctoral Research Fellowships Program. Each of the fellowships supports a research and training project at a host institution in the mathematical sciences, including applications to other disciplines, under the mentorship of a sponsoring scientist. The title of the project for this fellowship to Madeline Brandt is "Tropical Geometry." The host institution for the fellowship is Brown University , and the sponsoring scientist is Melody Chan.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/12/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/12/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2001739</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Madeline</FirstName>
<LastName>Brandt</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>V</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Madeline V Brandt</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<NSF_ID>000811476</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/12/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Brandt, Madeline Virginia</Name>
<CityName>Berkeley</CityName>
<ZipCode>94704</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Brown University]]></Name>
<CityName>Providence</CityName>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>029129091</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>RI01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>060Y</Code>
<Text>Workforce (MSPRF) MathSciPDFel</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9219</Code>
<Text>POSTDOCTORAL FELLOWSHIPS IN MATH SCIENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~150000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="p1">Intellectual Merit:<span>&nbsp;</span></p> <p class="p1">This project focused on a field of math called combinatorial algebraic geometry. Algebraic geometry studies zero sets of polynomial equations. Such objects, called varieties, may be quite complicated but many aspects of their geometry are governed by discrete data. In turn, combinatorial structures arising from particularly meaningful varieties, such as moduli spaces, are interesting in their own right. In recent years a new subject called tropical geometry has emerged as a tool for studying these objects. As a result, many rich connections between algebraic geometry and combinatorics have developed. Tropical geometry associates polyhedral complexes, like <em>tropical varieties </em>and <em>skeletons</em>, to algebraic varieties. These encode information about the variety or the equations they came from. This connection is the main focus of my research. In this project, I used tropical geometry to reveal the combinatorics of interesting varieties. I used tropical geometry to study the topology of moduli spaces of curves, I advanced tropical counting techniques for binodal cubic surfaces, and I used<em> </em>tropical analogs of realization spaces of matroids to understand obstructions to matroid realizability.</p> <p class="p2"><strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p class="p1">Broader Impacts:</p> <p class="p1">I am committed to making the mathematics community an inclusive one. I worked with other mathematicians to create a poster series of modern mathematical role models. The posters highlight the accomplishments and ideas of a diverse set of mathematicians. You can see the posters featured in math departments around the world. I believe that it is important to communicate mathematical research to the public. In this project, I made several YouTube videos aimed at communicating my research to a broad audience. In total, the videos have over 130,000 views.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/14/2023<br>      Modified by: Madeline&nbsp;V&nbsp;Brandt</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[Intellectual Merit:  This project focused on a field of math called combinatorial algebraic geometry. Algebraic geometry studies zero sets of polynomial equations. Such objects, called varieties, may be quite complicated but many aspects of their geometry are governed by discrete data. In turn, combinatorial structures arising from particularly meaningful varieties, such as moduli spaces, are interesting in their own right. In recent years a new subject called tropical geometry has emerged as a tool for studying these objects. As a result, many rich connections between algebraic geometry and combinatorics have developed. Tropical geometry associates polyhedral complexes, like tropical varieties and skeletons, to algebraic varieties. These encode information about the variety or the equations they came from. This connection is the main focus of my research. In this project, I used tropical geometry to reveal the combinatorics of interesting varieties. I used tropical geometry to study the topology of moduli spaces of curves, I advanced tropical counting techniques for binodal cubic surfaces, and I used tropical analogs of realization spaces of matroids to understand obstructions to matroid realizability.   Broader Impacts: I am committed to making the mathematics community an inclusive one. I worked with other mathematicians to create a poster series of modern mathematical role models. The posters highlight the accomplishments and ideas of a diverse set of mathematicians. You can see the posters featured in math departments around the world. I believe that it is important to communicate mathematical research to the public. In this project, I made several YouTube videos aimed at communicating my research to a broad audience. In total, the videos have over 130,000 views.          Last Modified: 01/14/2023       Submitted by: Madeline V Brandt]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
