<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Doctoral Dissertation Research:  Cooperation in Uncertainty during Migration]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>16000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>16000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joseph Whitmeyer</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jwhitmey@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927808</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Doctoral Dissertation Research:  Cooperation in Uncertainty during Migration&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project investigates the experiences of migrants as they journey from one country to another.  Prior research indicates that the experience of migrants varies: some migrants describe experiences of harshness and neglect, while others perceive protection and support. But what account for these differences?   This project will examine how migrants negotiate the relationships with those who assist in the journeys. How do they work to safeguard themselves, and what conditions do they observe when these safeguards fail?  How do these process self-organize when laws are unenforced? And how do social networks facilitate migration?  Governments frequently ponder how to lower the risks for migrants.  Underlying some governmental policies may also be the assumption that if risks are high, migration will decrease, but current research indicates that many migrants persist in their attempts despite the risks. Identifying what conditions increase the risk of victimization for migrants will inform governmental policies to assist in safe passage for those who choose to migrate.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In order to understand what explains differential experiences of migrants, this project will analyze what conditions the migrants experience and when safety is supported or violated.  The project will conduct fieldwork in locales where many migration journeys begin and will rely on semi-structured, qualitative interviews of prospective migrants and returnees, i.e., those migrants who return to countries of origin. The project will stay in contact with prospective migrants through social media apps and re-interview them within a month of their migration attempt. Interview topics include the route migrants chose, who assisted them, the extent to which they relied on their social networks in these decisions, and, finally, whether they experienced support versus harshness or neglect. Returnees will provide data on the various risks they encountered. The project will interview 50 potential migrants and 50 returnees in each of several different locales. Within this group, the interviews will sample for diversity, especially rural versus urban origins, but also socioeconomic, gender and ethnic diversity in order to ensure capture a diverse range of perspectives. The project will use a snowball sampling strategy and gain access to migration-affected communities through partnerships with local service NGOs. The analysis of migrant journeys not only speaks to how humans create institutions to facilitate cooperation, but also how culture, social cleavages, and local context influence these institutional choices.  Findings from the project will contribute to sociological theories regarding migration, the law, social networks and global inequality.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/15/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/15/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2001910</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Adrienne</FirstName>
<LastName>LeBas</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Adrienne LeBas</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[lebas@american.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000716024</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/15/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Natalie</FirstName>
<LastName>Chwalisz</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Natalie C Chwalisz</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[NC5011b@student.american.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000813181</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/15/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>American University</Name>
<CityName>WASHINGTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>200168002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2028853440</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4400 MASSACHUSETTS AVE, NW</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>H4VNDUN2VWU5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>AMERICAN UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>H4VNDUN2VWU5</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[American University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>200168200</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1331</Code>
<Text>Sociology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1331</Code>
<Text>SOCIOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~16000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This research was conducted by Natalie Chwalisz, a doctoral student in the Department of Justice, Law, and Criminology at American University. It carries both intellectual merit and has broader impacts for society.</p> <p>I conducted field work in The Gambia in June of 2022. While in The Gambia, I interviewed returnees: migrants, who attempted to migrate illicitly to Europe, and either succeeded or failed, but ultimately returned to The Gambia. The interviews focus on how migrants find smugglers, how they negotiate with smugglers, how they build trust with a smuggler, their experiences being smuggled, and finally, how they perceive smugglers. I also interviewed prospective migrants, who already paid a smuggler. Cumulatively, I collected 32 interviews. In addition to this qualitative research, I analyzed survey data on West African migrants, compiled by the Mixed Migration Centre, a migration-focused research institute with regional hubs around the globe. The survey data spans three years and is collected on the West African migration routes. A network of 33 monitors carries out an average of 500 surveys per month with refugees and migrants in Mali, Burkina Faso, and Niger. Questions pertain to the background of migrants, migratory drivers, means of movement, conditions of movement, the smuggler economy, aspirations, and destination choices.</p> <p>The interviews provided new information on the migrant-smuggler relationship. Field workers in other contexts have found that smugglers at times offer accountability mechanisms, or that a shared sense of kinship and morality structure the migrant smuggler relationship. One of the main findings is that the accountability systems that field researchers described in some other contexts were not present in The Gambian case.</p> <p>An additional finding is that the act of criminalizing human smuggling, which includes tactics as locking up smugglers and migrants, changes the smuggler-migrant relationship profoundly. The Gambia has increasingly pursued a law enforcement approach to clamp down on human smuggling. This criminalization of the act of smuggling is driving the business more underground. Since these changes, even the intention to migrate now is stigmatized, and a closely kept secret. In the past, migrants&rsquo; families would support the migrants. Additionally, the smuggler was embedded in the social networks: a migrant would know the smuggler, their family, and their village compound. That kind of embeddedness of the smuggler in the migrants&rsquo; social network meant that the migrants&rsquo; family could always find the smugglers&rsquo; family in case, providing some limited social accountability. In contrast, now migrants only find out about the smuggler through rumors and will not be able to ask around for the smuggler&rsquo;s reputation. Migrants keep their contact with smugglers a secret from their families and friends as they worry that The Gambian government find out about their intention of migrating, and the smugglers&rsquo; operation. Migrants also leave in secret, and do not tell their families until they have already left the country. This increases the migrants&rsquo; vulnerabilities.</p> <p>A final finding is that migrants appear well informed about the dangers of the journey. There is a belief among some European policy makers that migrants only start the journey because they do not know the dangers. Thus, Europe has invested in information campaigns across West Africa, including in The Gambia. However, my interviews shows that migrants are aware of the dangers, including kidnapping and potential torture in Libya, and drowning at sea, and for woman, rape. Migrants persist in the journey despite these dangers because livelihood pressures on them and their family.</p> <p>This research contributes to the discipline of sociology. For example, with regards to the sociology of trust, my research illuminates how marginalized communities organize to facilitate social and geographic mobility. I explore how people build trust in these illicit economies and the conditions under which humans are prone to violate that trust problematize dichotomies, which dominate public discourse, such as migrants as victims versus smugglers as an abuser. Instead, I show the relationship is more complicated than a friend or foe relationship and that all options in between can exist as well. Trust in these situations is tenuous and highly dependent on shared social networks or identities.</p> <p>My hope is that understanding the conditions that lead to more violent journeys will lead to better-informed and humanistic migration policies in sending, transit and receiving countries. Studying migration, and particularly the human smuggling industry, addresses a phenomenon that affects the politics in destination countries and between destination countries and sending countries. My research goes to the heart of an issue that is of growing political and humanistic importance.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/30/2023<br>      Modified by: Adrienne&nbsp;Lebas</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This research was conducted by Natalie Chwalisz, a doctoral student in the Department of Justice, Law, and Criminology at American University. It carries both intellectual merit and has broader impacts for society.  I conducted field work in The Gambia in June of 2022. While in The Gambia, I interviewed returnees: migrants, who attempted to migrate illicitly to Europe, and either succeeded or failed, but ultimately returned to The Gambia. The interviews focus on how migrants find smugglers, how they negotiate with smugglers, how they build trust with a smuggler, their experiences being smuggled, and finally, how they perceive smugglers. I also interviewed prospective migrants, who already paid a smuggler. Cumulatively, I collected 32 interviews. In addition to this qualitative research, I analyzed survey data on West African migrants, compiled by the Mixed Migration Centre, a migration-focused research institute with regional hubs around the globe. The survey data spans three years and is collected on the West African migration routes. A network of 33 monitors carries out an average of 500 surveys per month with refugees and migrants in Mali, Burkina Faso, and Niger. Questions pertain to the background of migrants, migratory drivers, means of movement, conditions of movement, the smuggler economy, aspirations, and destination choices.  The interviews provided new information on the migrant-smuggler relationship. Field workers in other contexts have found that smugglers at times offer accountability mechanisms, or that a shared sense of kinship and morality structure the migrant smuggler relationship. One of the main findings is that the accountability systems that field researchers described in some other contexts were not present in The Gambian case.  An additional finding is that the act of criminalizing human smuggling, which includes tactics as locking up smugglers and migrants, changes the smuggler-migrant relationship profoundly. The Gambia has increasingly pursued a law enforcement approach to clamp down on human smuggling. This criminalization of the act of smuggling is driving the business more underground. Since these changes, even the intention to migrate now is stigmatized, and a closely kept secret. In the past, migrants’ families would support the migrants. Additionally, the smuggler was embedded in the social networks: a migrant would know the smuggler, their family, and their village compound. That kind of embeddedness of the smuggler in the migrants’ social network meant that the migrants’ family could always find the smugglers’ family in case, providing some limited social accountability. In contrast, now migrants only find out about the smuggler through rumors and will not be able to ask around for the smuggler’s reputation. Migrants keep their contact with smugglers a secret from their families and friends as they worry that The Gambian government find out about their intention of migrating, and the smugglers’ operation. Migrants also leave in secret, and do not tell their families until they have already left the country. This increases the migrants’ vulnerabilities.  A final finding is that migrants appear well informed about the dangers of the journey. There is a belief among some European policy makers that migrants only start the journey because they do not know the dangers. Thus, Europe has invested in information campaigns across West Africa, including in The Gambia. However, my interviews shows that migrants are aware of the dangers, including kidnapping and potential torture in Libya, and drowning at sea, and for woman, rape. Migrants persist in the journey despite these dangers because livelihood pressures on them and their family.  This research contributes to the discipline of sociology. For example, with regards to the sociology of trust, my research illuminates how marginalized communities organize to facilitate social and geographic mobility. I explore how people build trust in these illicit economies and the conditions under which humans are prone to violate that trust problematize dichotomies, which dominate public discourse, such as migrants as victims versus smugglers as an abuser. Instead, I show the relationship is more complicated than a friend or foe relationship and that all options in between can exist as well. Trust in these situations is tenuous and highly dependent on shared social networks or identities.  My hope is that understanding the conditions that lead to more violent journeys will lead to better-informed and humanistic migration policies in sending, transit and receiving countries. Studying migration, and particularly the human smuggling industry, addresses a phenomenon that affects the politics in destination countries and between destination countries and sending countries. My research goes to the heart of an issue that is of growing political and humanistic importance.          Last Modified: 05/30/2023       Submitted by: Adrienne Lebas]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
