<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Digitization PEN: Addition of the Yale Peabody Museum to the Terrestrial Parasite Tracker (TPT) Network]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>58075.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>58075</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DBI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Reed Beaman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rsbeaman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927163</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Arthropod parasites (specifically, insects and their relatives) are responsible for economically critical issues in human health, wildlife conservation, and livestock productivity. Because natural history collections are permanent repositories for past and present parasite specimens, these collections and their data can help address these significant societal challenges in human and animal health and safety. Natural history collections often contain specimens and ancillary materials that are completely unknown to the broader community, yet represent irreplaceable knowledge about organismal habitats, distributions, and parasite-host associations. Further, these collections yield information that can be used to model ecological processes and changes in species distributions, predict the future spread of human and animal disease, update taxonomy, and help identify under-represented parasite groups in urgent need of sampling and threatened parasite diversity in need of conservation. This project will provide digital records (i.e., specimen label data and images) of invaluable arthropod parasite collections to make research-ready baseline data accessible online, catalyzing new research and education initiatives. These newly digitized data will have immediate and long-lasting benefits for our understanding of organismal associations, biodiversity, and beyond.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Terrestrial Parasite Tracker Thematic Collection Network (TPT-TCN) will digitize over one million arthropod specimens representing species that are significant parasites and disease vectors of vertebrates in the United States. The TPT-TCN is a collaboration among 26 research collections, and includes vertebrate and invertebrate taxonomists and curators, epidemiologists, ecologists, data-scientists, and biodiversity informatics specialists.  This Partners to Existing Networks (PEN) grant allows the Yale Peabody Museum to join the collaboration, and digitize specimens that fill critical gaps in geographic and taxonomic coverage in the existing TPT-TCN. This project will integrate arthropod data with millions of vertebrate host records with vector and disease monitoring data shared by state and federal agency collaborators, creating a novel foundation for integrative, long-term research.  It will also empower ongoing citizen science and public awareness campaigns with tools for understanding distribution changes of arthropod vectors and associated diseases due to environmental change and global movement. Educational initiatives include partnering with natural history museums to educate the public about parasites via science-focused lectures, exhibits, summer youth programs, informal presentations, and developing new online educational resources for teachers in underserved communities. All specimen images generated by this project will be shared with iDigBio.org and used in developing a rapid parasite identification tool, which will be accessible over the internet and smartphone apps. The TPT-TCN will also develop and implement undergraduate teaching modules focused on data held in natural history collections. These modules will be disseminated to academic institutions across the United States and made available online.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/18/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/15/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2001547</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lawrence</FirstName>
<LastName>Gall</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>F</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lawrence F Gall</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[lawrence.gall@yale.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000114079</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/18/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Stephen</FirstName>
<LastName>Cameron</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Stephen L Cameron</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[cameros@purdue.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000493393</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/18/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Yale University</Name>
<CityName>NEW HAVEN</CityName>
<ZipCode>065118917</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2037854689</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>105 WALL ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CT03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>FL6GV84CKN57</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>YALE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>FL6GV84CKN57</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Yale University]]></Name>
<CityName>New Haven</CityName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>065208118</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[170 Whitney Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CT03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6895</Code>
<Text>Digitization</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>6895</Code>
<Text>DIGITIZATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~58075</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Digitization PEN: Addition of the Yale Peabody Museum to the Terrestrial Parasite Tracker (TPT) Network</strong></p> <p><strong>Project Outcomes </strong></p> <p>Terrestrial arthropod parasites are responsible for economically critical issues in human health, wildlife conservation, and livestock productivity. &nbsp;From a scientific perspective, parasites represent a broad spectrum of close ecological interactions with vertebrates, but a full understanding and appreciation of the overarching ecological relevance of parasites is hampered by the current lack of comprehensive specimen-level data. &nbsp;Natural history collections are the primary and permanent repositories for past and present parasite specimens and represent irreplaceable knowledge about organismal habitats, distributions, and parasite-host associations.&nbsp; These collections can be used to model ecological processes and changes in species distributions, predict the future spread of human and animal disease, update taxonomy, help identify under-represented parasite groups in urgent need of sampling, and highlight threatened parasite diversity in need of conservation. &nbsp;Digitization of terrestrial arthropod parasite collections will allow for an exponential increase in enumerating the number of known biotic associations, thus transforming downstream multidisciplinary research by making research-ready baseline data accessible, and catalyzing new research and education initiatives. These newly digitized parasite data will have immediate and long-lasting benefits for our understanding of organismal associations, biodiversity, and other issues.</p> <p>The Terrestrial Parasite Tracker Network (TPT) is aggregating data and images for 1,200,000 parasitic arthropod specimens from 22 collaborating institutions into a comprehensive digital database/portal that relates parasite-host associations and vector distributions.&nbsp; The TPT is also integrating vertebrate host records with vector and disease monitoring data shared by state and federal agency collaborators. &nbsp;The TPT is informing existing research on arthropod parasites, pathogens and hosts, and providing resources to a wide range of users to increase the visibility, accessibility, and relevance of arthropod parasite collections.&nbsp; To date, the TPT has digitized 850,000 records from the collaborating collections, connected these collections to SCAN (Symbiota Collections of Arthropods Network), and published the data and associated digital assets to both the public and scientific community via the SCAN portal.&nbsp; The Yale Peabody Museum joined the TPT as a one-year PEN in 2020, to mobilize complementary information for parasites from geographic areas and taxonomic groups poorly represented among the other TPT collections.&nbsp; Yale completed its PEN in 2021 and contributed 17,797 data records and 3,491 digital images to TPT (110 percent of its projected total).&nbsp; In addition, the TPT collaboration is empowering ongoing citizen science and public awareness campaigns to understand distributional changes of arthropod vectors and associated diseases due to climate change and global trade.&nbsp; A principal strategy for doing so is through educating scientific and public communities on the importance of collections and data literacy, as well as exposing students to the process of digitizing museum specimens, transcribing data from labels, and georeferencing those data.&nbsp; Yale engaged five undergraduate and two graduate students to produce its digital products over the course of its PEN, providing them with professional training in museum principles, bioinformatics, and insect taxonomy.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/14/2022<br>      Modified by: Lawrence&nbsp;F&nbsp;Gall</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Digitization PEN: Addition of the Yale Peabody Museum to the Terrestrial Parasite Tracker (TPT) Network  Project Outcomes   Terrestrial arthropod parasites are responsible for economically critical issues in human health, wildlife conservation, and livestock productivity.  From a scientific perspective, parasites represent a broad spectrum of close ecological interactions with vertebrates, but a full understanding and appreciation of the overarching ecological relevance of parasites is hampered by the current lack of comprehensive specimen-level data.  Natural history collections are the primary and permanent repositories for past and present parasite specimens and represent irreplaceable knowledge about organismal habitats, distributions, and parasite-host associations.  These collections can be used to model ecological processes and changes in species distributions, predict the future spread of human and animal disease, update taxonomy, help identify under-represented parasite groups in urgent need of sampling, and highlight threatened parasite diversity in need of conservation.  Digitization of terrestrial arthropod parasite collections will allow for an exponential increase in enumerating the number of known biotic associations, thus transforming downstream multidisciplinary research by making research-ready baseline data accessible, and catalyzing new research and education initiatives. These newly digitized parasite data will have immediate and long-lasting benefits for our understanding of organismal associations, biodiversity, and other issues.  The Terrestrial Parasite Tracker Network (TPT) is aggregating data and images for 1,200,000 parasitic arthropod specimens from 22 collaborating institutions into a comprehensive digital database/portal that relates parasite-host associations and vector distributions.  The TPT is also integrating vertebrate host records with vector and disease monitoring data shared by state and federal agency collaborators.  The TPT is informing existing research on arthropod parasites, pathogens and hosts, and providing resources to a wide range of users to increase the visibility, accessibility, and relevance of arthropod parasite collections.  To date, the TPT has digitized 850,000 records from the collaborating collections, connected these collections to SCAN (Symbiota Collections of Arthropods Network), and published the data and associated digital assets to both the public and scientific community via the SCAN portal.  The Yale Peabody Museum joined the TPT as a one-year PEN in 2020, to mobilize complementary information for parasites from geographic areas and taxonomic groups poorly represented among the other TPT collections.  Yale completed its PEN in 2021 and contributed 17,797 data records and 3,491 digital images to TPT (110 percent of its projected total).  In addition, the TPT collaboration is empowering ongoing citizen science and public awareness campaigns to understand distributional changes of arthropod vectors and associated diseases due to climate change and global trade.  A principal strategy for doing so is through educating scientific and public communities on the importance of collections and data literacy, as well as exposing students to the process of digitizing museum specimens, transcribing data from labels, and georeferencing those data.  Yale engaged five undergraduate and two graduate students to produce its digital products over the course of its PEN, providing them with professional training in museum principles, bioinformatics, and insect taxonomy.       Last Modified: 11/14/2022       Submitted by: Lawrence F Gall]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
