<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Doctoral Dissertation Research: The Effects of Wildfire Damage on Housing Access and Migration]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>15808.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>15808</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Melanie Hughes</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mehughes@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927318</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Scholars and policy-makers have predicted that large-scale changes to migration patterns will significantly impact human communities. While migration scholarship has proliferated in attempt to better understand these dynamics, the field has overlooked one of the major factors reshaping landscapes: wildfires. The first aim of this project is to describe how wildfires affect migration patterns in the United States. The second aim is to examine the role of the built environment in mediating whether and how wildfire damage impacts migration patterns. It is well-established that housing access plays a crucial role in determining disaster recovery; initial damage to homes influences whether or not a household is displaced, and reconstruction or the availability of alternative housing is a major factor that affects longer-term return migration. Greater attention to the built environment can therefore improve scholars’ understanding of not just whether fires may influence migration, but how they may do so. The core topics investigated by this research – disaster displacement and post-disaster housing access - are immediately relevant to policymakers working in emergency management settings and to municipal and state officials working in regions at high fire risk, thus providing important input into policy and preparedness in these jurisdictions.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This study utilizes mixed-methods to examine questions of disaster preparedness from wildfires at multiple scales, and will involve three primary components. First, difference-in-difference econometric and network approaches will be used to analyze the relationships between fire damage and mobility patterns at a national scale. Data sources include the Internal Revenue Service’s County-to-County Migration Data, Arizona State University’s Spatial Hazards Events and Losses Database for the United States, and the U.S. National Incident Management System. Second, qualitative fieldwork in Butte County, California - including 50 semi-structured interviews and participant observation - will be used to illustrate from the ground-level how individuals and families navigated post-disaster housing access in the aftermath of the 2018 Camp Fire. This fieldwork will further examine what factors facilitated and what factors prevented return migration and post-fire reconstruction. Third, geospatial analysis of satellite imagery will be used to describe and quantify post-fire building reconstruction rates, which will in turn be compared between four major fire sites. Data sources include Microsoft’s U.S. Building Footprint Data, the multi-agency Monitoring Trends in Burn Severity database, and remote sensing images from DigitalGlobe. This research will contribute to a growing body of sociological theory on threats to the built environment by blending social and environmental data, incorporating spatial methods, and drawing from literatures on migration and urban environments.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/12/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/12/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2001261</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Justin</FirstName>
<LastName>Farrell</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Justin Farrell</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[justin.farrell@yale.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000743650</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/12/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kathryn</FirstName>
<LastName>McConnell</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kathryn A McConnell</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[kathryn_mcconnell@brown.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000809854</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/12/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Yale University</Name>
<CityName>NEW HAVEN</CityName>
<ZipCode>065118917</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2037854689</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>105 WALL ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CT03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>FL6GV84CKN57</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>YALE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>FL6GV84CKN57</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Yale University]]></Name>
<CityName>New Haven</CityName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>065118499</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[195 Prospect Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CT03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1331</Code>
<Text>Sociology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~15808</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The dissertation research funded by this grant aimed to describe how wildfires affect human mobility and how the built environment mediates this relationship. The project is situated primarily in the sociological subfields of environmental migration and disaster studies, contributing new knowledge on the social impacts of wildfires, a hazard that has been understudied in past research.</p> <p>The scale of wildfire destruction has grown rapidly in recent years, destroying nearly 25,000 buildings in the U.S. during 2018 alone. How will these growing levels of damage affect human mobility patterns? The first dissertation chapter supported by this grant pairs measures of residential mobility with measures of wildfire building destruction to evaluate the effects of wildfire destruction on migration probabilities in the U.S. between 1999 and 2018. Findings indicate that only the most destructive wildfires increased the probability of out-migration. The majority of destructive wildfires directly damaged very few structures, and, in these cases, residents largely remained in the area rather than migrating. These findings suggest that direct population displacement occurs in cases of high structure loss, but, when less destruction occurs, there is no evidence that residents are preemptively leaving high fire-risk regions to avoid future wildfires. A secondary outcome from the first chapter was the creation of a national wildfire destruction dataset at the Census tract scale. These data will allow social scientists to analyze relationships between wildfire metrics and socioeconomic variables.</p> <p>How will now routine seasons of wildfire destruction affect human settlement patterns? The second funded dissertation chapter examines wildfire damage and post-fire building reconstruction among the approximately 23,000 buildings located in the burn footprint of the 2018 Camp Fire, one of the most destructive wildfires in U.S. history. I find that mobile homes, lower-value, and renter-occupied homes were significantly more likely to be destroyed compared to single-family homes, higher-value homes, and owner-occupied homes. These findings suggest that filtering of housing took place, wherein less valuable residential buildings were physically more susceptible to hazard damage. To map post-fire building reconstruction patterns, I train a support vector machine algorithm using data from the National Aerial Imagery Program and Microsoft's Building Footprints database. Applying this algorithm to post-fire imagery, I identify which buildings had been reconstructed 20 months after the fire, and show that reconstructed buildings were more likely to be owner-occupied and had, on average, higher pre-fire value. These findings provide evidence for the theory of cost-burden climate gentrification, wherein wealthier households have a greater capacity to remain in a hazardous area than less affluent households.</p> <p>Following the Camp Fire, more than 56,000 residents evacuated from communities in the foothills of Butte County, California, known as "the Ridge." While some remained in the area, others permanently relocated. The third chapter draws on 24 in-depth interviews with former Ridge residents who migrated away following the fire and describes the combination of drivers that influenced their decisions to move. While the fire acted as a precipitating event, I show how limited affordable housing was the primary constraint on many residents' ability to rebuild or remain in the area. Additionally, the concurrent loss of embedded social networks on the Ridge and the presence of social ties elsewhere inclined many to leave. After the fire, environmental conditions continued to influence migration decision-making. Radical changes to the Ridge's landscape and concerns over future wildfires pushed residents to leave, while the prospect of environmental amenities elsewhere was a consideration for many when they chose their new destination. This constellation of push and pull factors suggests that post-disaster migration is not exclusively involuntary and shaped by material deprivation, as writing on disaster displacement has often assumed.</p> <p>Model projections suggest that wildfire destruction will likely continue to increase in the coming decades. A scientific understanding of wildfires' socioeconomic impacts is critical for addressing the societal and public policy issues that are emerging from this new wildfire regime. To ensure the funded project had a broader impact beyond academic settings, I presented this research in venues where practitioners were able to access the work, including the University of Colorado Boulder's Natural Hazards Workshop, Columbia University's Managed Retreat Conference, the University of California Los Angeles' Climate Adaptation Workshop, and at an invited internal presentation at the U.S. Department of Housing and Urban Development. I have also discussed this research with journalists from national and local news organizations, and at a workshop hosted by the Institute for Journalism &amp; Natural Resources. Finally, I presented this work in several student-oriented settings, including at a wildfire-focused panel hosted by Cal Poly Pomona and to an undergraduate environmental studies course at Boise State University.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/03/2022<br>      Modified by: Kathryn&nbsp;A&nbsp;Mcconnell</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The dissertation research funded by this grant aimed to describe how wildfires affect human mobility and how the built environment mediates this relationship. The project is situated primarily in the sociological subfields of environmental migration and disaster studies, contributing new knowledge on the social impacts of wildfires, a hazard that has been understudied in past research.  The scale of wildfire destruction has grown rapidly in recent years, destroying nearly 25,000 buildings in the U.S. during 2018 alone. How will these growing levels of damage affect human mobility patterns? The first dissertation chapter supported by this grant pairs measures of residential mobility with measures of wildfire building destruction to evaluate the effects of wildfire destruction on migration probabilities in the U.S. between 1999 and 2018. Findings indicate that only the most destructive wildfires increased the probability of out-migration. The majority of destructive wildfires directly damaged very few structures, and, in these cases, residents largely remained in the area rather than migrating. These findings suggest that direct population displacement occurs in cases of high structure loss, but, when less destruction occurs, there is no evidence that residents are preemptively leaving high fire-risk regions to avoid future wildfires. A secondary outcome from the first chapter was the creation of a national wildfire destruction dataset at the Census tract scale. These data will allow social scientists to analyze relationships between wildfire metrics and socioeconomic variables.  How will now routine seasons of wildfire destruction affect human settlement patterns? The second funded dissertation chapter examines wildfire damage and post-fire building reconstruction among the approximately 23,000 buildings located in the burn footprint of the 2018 Camp Fire, one of the most destructive wildfires in U.S. history. I find that mobile homes, lower-value, and renter-occupied homes were significantly more likely to be destroyed compared to single-family homes, higher-value homes, and owner-occupied homes. These findings suggest that filtering of housing took place, wherein less valuable residential buildings were physically more susceptible to hazard damage. To map post-fire building reconstruction patterns, I train a support vector machine algorithm using data from the National Aerial Imagery Program and Microsoft's Building Footprints database. Applying this algorithm to post-fire imagery, I identify which buildings had been reconstructed 20 months after the fire, and show that reconstructed buildings were more likely to be owner-occupied and had, on average, higher pre-fire value. These findings provide evidence for the theory of cost-burden climate gentrification, wherein wealthier households have a greater capacity to remain in a hazardous area than less affluent households.  Following the Camp Fire, more than 56,000 residents evacuated from communities in the foothills of Butte County, California, known as "the Ridge." While some remained in the area, others permanently relocated. The third chapter draws on 24 in-depth interviews with former Ridge residents who migrated away following the fire and describes the combination of drivers that influenced their decisions to move. While the fire acted as a precipitating event, I show how limited affordable housing was the primary constraint on many residents' ability to rebuild or remain in the area. Additionally, the concurrent loss of embedded social networks on the Ridge and the presence of social ties elsewhere inclined many to leave. After the fire, environmental conditions continued to influence migration decision-making. Radical changes to the Ridge's landscape and concerns over future wildfires pushed residents to leave, while the prospect of environmental amenities elsewhere was a consideration for many when they chose their new destination. This constellation of push and pull factors suggests that post-disaster migration is not exclusively involuntary and shaped by material deprivation, as writing on disaster displacement has often assumed.  Model projections suggest that wildfire destruction will likely continue to increase in the coming decades. A scientific understanding of wildfires' socioeconomic impacts is critical for addressing the societal and public policy issues that are emerging from this new wildfire regime. To ensure the funded project had a broader impact beyond academic settings, I presented this research in venues where practitioners were able to access the work, including the University of Colorado Boulder's Natural Hazards Workshop, Columbia University's Managed Retreat Conference, the University of California Los Angeles' Climate Adaptation Workshop, and at an invited internal presentation at the U.S. Department of Housing and Urban Development. I have also discussed this research with journalists from national and local news organizations, and at a workshop hosted by the Institute for Journalism &amp; Natural Resources. Finally, I presented this work in several student-oriented settings, including at a wildfire-focused panel hosted by Cal Poly Pomona and to an undergraduate environmental studies course at Boise State University.          Last Modified: 08/03/2022       Submitted by: Kathryn A Mcconnell]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
