<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Conference on Homological Mirror Symmetry]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>20000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>20000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>James Matthew Douglass</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mdouglas@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922467</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This award supports participation in a conference on Homological Mirror Symmetry to be held at the University of Miami from January 27 through February 31, 2020. Mirror symmetry originated in physics as a duality between superconformal quantum field theories. This duality has been interpreted in a consistent, powerful mathematical framework called Homological Mirror Symmetry (HMS) that has led to dramatic developments in how the mathematical community approaches ideas from theoretical physics, and indeed our conception of space itself. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Today HMS is established as one of the most powerful frameworks for building bridges between seemingly unrelated parts of modern geometry.  Traditionally HMS has been incredibly successful in discovering novel phenomena and proving unexpected results in symplectic and contact topology informed by algebraic geometry. The goal of this conference is to highlight the flow of ideas in the opposite direction: from symplectic to complex geometry. The conference will summarize recently developed connections between Hodge Theory and HMS which have striking algebraic applications and give new insights into rationality problems. In particular, the conference will focus on new cutting-edge directions of investigation: (1) birational invariants and gluing of D-modules; (2) extending the scope of Homological Mirror Symmetry; (3) categorical Kaehler geometry; and (4) topological recursion. The conference website is https://schms.math.berkeley.edu/events/miami2020/.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/28/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/24/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2001614</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ludmil</FirstName>
<LastName>Katzarkov</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>V</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ludmil V Katzarkov</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[lkatzarkov@gmail.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000206486</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/28/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Miami</Name>
<CityName>CORAL GABLES</CityName>
<ZipCode>331462919</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3052843924</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1320 SOUTH DIXIE HIGHWAY STE 650</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>27</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL27</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>RQMFJGDTQ5V3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MIAMI</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Miami]]></Name>
<CityName>Coral Gables</CityName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>331462926</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>27</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL27</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1264</Code>
<Text>ALGEBRA,NUMBER THEORY,AND COM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~20000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This is a report on the conference</p> <p><strong>&nbsp;Homological Mirror Symmetry</strong></p> <p>&nbsp;<strong>Dates:</strong> April 4-8, 2022</p> <p>This was one of the first events during COVID.</p> <p>It was in a hybrid format concentrating on Gromov Witten theory, Derived categories of Fano and Calabi Manifolds, Fukaya, Fukaya Seidel , Fukaya Seidel categories with wrapping , Stability conditions, Stroniger Yau Zaslov Construction, It was a very good conference.</p> <p>Special lectures were given by:</p> <p>M. Konstevich IHES</p> <p><em>Stability Structures in Holomorphic Morse-Novikov Theory</em></p> <p>Y. Soibelman KSU</p> <p><em>Holomorphic Floer Theory, Quantum Wave Functions and Resurgence</em></p> <p>&nbsp;S. Gukov Caltech</p> <p><em>Spectra, Dynamical Systems, and RG Flows</em></p> <p>B. Sibert UTexas</p> <p><em>Canonical Wall Structures via Punctured Gromov-Witten Theory</em></p> <p>D. Nadler UBerkeley</p> <p><em>Functions on Commuting Stacks via Mirror Symmetry</em></p> <p>K. Fukaya SCGP</p> <p><em>Gromov-Hausdorff Convergence of Filtered A Infinity Categories</em></p> <p>V. Shende UC Berkeley</p> <p><em>Quantum Mirror Symmetry for the Conifold</em></p> <p><strong>Ernesto Lupercio Cinvestav</strong></p> <p>Progress on Quantum Toric Geometry </p> <p>A. Harder Lehaigh University</p> <p><em>Mixed Hodge Structures Attached to Hybrid Landau&ndash;Ginzburg Models</em> </p> <p>G. Kerr KSU</p> <p><em>Lagrangian Intersections in Phase Tropical Hypersurfaces</em> </p> <p>Several new direction were instiated </p> <p>Spectra as invariant of 3 manifolds </p> <p>Spectra as a birational invariant</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Special efforts were made to help participation of</p> <p>under represented groups;</p> <p>M. Liu, E Beccera,&nbsp; Y. Wu. R. Barbosa, E. Lipercio</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/05/2023<br>      Modified by: Ludmil&nbsp;V&nbsp;Katzarkov</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This is a report on the conference   Homological Mirror Symmetry   Dates: April 4-8, 2022  This was one of the first events during COVID.  It was in a hybrid format concentrating on Gromov Witten theory, Derived categories of Fano and Calabi Manifolds, Fukaya, Fukaya Seidel , Fukaya Seidel categories with wrapping , Stability conditions, Stroniger Yau Zaslov Construction, It was a very good conference.  Special lectures were given by:  M. Konstevich IHES  Stability Structures in Holomorphic Morse-Novikov Theory  Y. Soibelman KSU  Holomorphic Floer Theory, Quantum Wave Functions and Resurgence   S. Gukov Caltech  Spectra, Dynamical Systems, and RG Flows  B. Sibert UTexas  Canonical Wall Structures via Punctured Gromov-Witten Theory  D. Nadler UBerkeley  Functions on Commuting Stacks via Mirror Symmetry  K. Fukaya SCGP  Gromov-Hausdorff Convergence of Filtered A Infinity Categories  V. Shende UC Berkeley  Quantum Mirror Symmetry for the Conifold  Ernesto Lupercio Cinvestav  Progress on Quantum Toric Geometry   A. Harder Lehaigh University  Mixed Hodge Structures Attached to Hybrid Landau&ndash;Ginzburg Models   G. Kerr KSU  Lagrangian Intersections in Phase Tropical Hypersurfaces   Several new direction were instiated   Spectra as invariant of 3 manifolds   Spectra as a birational invariant        Special efforts were made to help participation of  under represented groups;  M. Liu, E Beccera,  Y. Wu. R. Barbosa, E. Lipercio       Last Modified: 10/05/2023       Submitted by: Ludmil V Katzarkov]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
