<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Demographics of the Youngest Protostars and their Disks]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>300000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>241944</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AST</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Andrea Prestwich</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>aprestwi@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922210</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Patrick Sheehan is awarded an NSF Astronomy and Astrophysics Postdoctoral Fellowship to conduct a program of research and education at Northwestern University.  He will study the structures and properties of disks, which are formed when clouds of gas and dust in space collapse to form protostars.  Observational evidence suggests that planets and their precursors are formed very early during the onset of star formation, and the results from this project will allow astronomers to understand just how soon planet formation begins.  Along with this research, Sheehan will conduct a summer educational program designed to provide experience in programming, data analysis, and astronomical research to high school students.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Recent observations of substructures in protoplanetary disks surrounding nearly every 1-5 Myr-old pre-main sequence star suggest that these disks may already have undergone a significant amount of planet or planetesimal formation. To understand the initial conditions before significant dust processing or planet formation has occurred, this project will investigate the structures of younger disks (&lt; 1 Myr old) and their central protostars using observations done at very high angular resolution from centimeter to submillimeter wavelengths. The observations will include every known protostellar disk in the Taurus star-forming region, enabling Sheehan to place constraints on the structure of gas and dust and on the growth of early dust grains. Sheehan will also use high-resolution imaging to study a known population of young disks in the Orion star-forming region with substructures possibly related to early planet formation. Finally, he will directly measure the dynamical masses of young protostars to place these disks within the context of their stars and place robust constraints on pre-main sequence evolutionary tracks.  This project will generate the largest sample of directly measured protostellar masses, and the measurements will provide information on how disk mass depends on protostellar mass. The resulting comprehensive picture will advance our understanding of the potential for planet formation in disks, as well as the precise location of the forming planets.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/27/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/29/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2001830</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Patrick</FirstName>
<LastName>Sheehan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Patrick D Sheehan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<NSF_ID>000733160</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/27/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Sheehan                 Patrick        D</Name>
<CityName>Evanston</CityName>
<ZipCode>602013777</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Northwestern University]]></Name>
<CityName>Evanston</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>602013777</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1609</Code>
<Text>NSF ASTRON &amp; ASTROPHY PSTDC FE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1207</Code>
<Text>OBSERVATIONAL ASTRONOMY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002223DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~100000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~100000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2022~41944</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The overarching goal of this project was to better characterize the environments in which planets form by studying the conditions in the youngest known "protoplanetary disks", the birthplaces of planets. The work funded by this grant led to the largest detailed study of young (&lt;1 million year-old) protoplanetary disks to-date, which let to a number of new insights into their properties and how they might fuel planet formation:</p> <ul> <li>We found that young (&lt;1 million year-old) protoplanetary disks are less massive than older (&gt;1 million year-old) disks. This is counter to previous results, and raises questions about where the mass for planet formation comes from. We did, however, find tenative evidence that disk masses may grow with time.</li> <li>We further found that magnetic fields are important in regulating the sizes of protoplanetary disks, and therefore for regulating the conditions for planet formation, as they form from a cloud collapsing under the force of gravity.</li> <li>Finally, we found that these disks are entirely stable against the force of their own gravity. Though the collapse of a disk that is unstable to its own gravity has been thought to be a way to form planets, it does not seem to be a major source of planet formation in general.</li> </ul> <p>In addition to that work, this grant funded the discovery of seven young (&lt;1 million year-old) disks with "substructures" - rings and gaps that are thought to be created by forming planets carving up the disk in which they live. Through a careful characterization of these systems, we found that they are among the youngest known disks to show such features that have been discovered, to-date, potentially demonstrating that planets can form very early in the lifetime of protoplanetary disks.</p> <p>Finally, this grant also funded a study of the distribution of "large" grains of dust - the building blocks of planets - in a particularly young disk. The observations were particularly sensitive to dust gains ~1 cm in size, which we tend to refer to as "pebbles" (though these pebbles are much more tenuous and porous than the image you may be conjuring). These pebbles are crucial building blocks of planets, and we believe one of the first steps of the planet formation process is to have these pebbles all settle to the middle of the disk. Our study of one particularly young (~100 thousand years old) disk, found that this had not yet happened yet, meaning at such young ages it may be the case that it is too early for planets to form.</p> <p>Finally, this grant helped to sponser the Center for Interdisciplinary Exploration and Research (CIERA) Research Experiences in Astronomy at CIERA for High School Students (REACH) program. The REACH program brings students from the greater Chicagoland area to CIERA/Northwestern University to learn the skills needed to participate in research, and to conduct an independent research project under the supervision of a CIERA Astronomer. This grant helped to sponsor three iterations of the program, one during the summer of 2020 and two during the summer of 2021, that collectively included ~50 students from a diverse set of backgrounds.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/17/2023<br>      Modified by: Patrick&nbsp;D&nbsp;Sheehan</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The overarching goal of this project was to better characterize the environments in which planets form by studying the conditions in the youngest known "protoplanetary disks", the birthplaces of planets. The work funded by this grant led to the largest detailed study of young (&lt;1 million year-old) protoplanetary disks to-date, which let to a number of new insights into their properties and how they might fuel planet formation:  We found that young (&lt;1 million year-old) protoplanetary disks are less massive than older (&gt;1 million year-old) disks. This is counter to previous results, and raises questions about where the mass for planet formation comes from. We did, however, find tenative evidence that disk masses may grow with time. We further found that magnetic fields are important in regulating the sizes of protoplanetary disks, and therefore for regulating the conditions for planet formation, as they form from a cloud collapsing under the force of gravity. Finally, we found that these disks are entirely stable against the force of their own gravity. Though the collapse of a disk that is unstable to its own gravity has been thought to be a way to form planets, it does not seem to be a major source of planet formation in general.   In addition to that work, this grant funded the discovery of seven young (&lt;1 million year-old) disks with "substructures" - rings and gaps that are thought to be created by forming planets carving up the disk in which they live. Through a careful characterization of these systems, we found that they are among the youngest known disks to show such features that have been discovered, to-date, potentially demonstrating that planets can form very early in the lifetime of protoplanetary disks.  Finally, this grant also funded a study of the distribution of "large" grains of dust - the building blocks of planets - in a particularly young disk. The observations were particularly sensitive to dust gains ~1 cm in size, which we tend to refer to as "pebbles" (though these pebbles are much more tenuous and porous than the image you may be conjuring). These pebbles are crucial building blocks of planets, and we believe one of the first steps of the planet formation process is to have these pebbles all settle to the middle of the disk. Our study of one particularly young (~100 thousand years old) disk, found that this had not yet happened yet, meaning at such young ages it may be the case that it is too early for planets to form.  Finally, this grant helped to sponser the Center for Interdisciplinary Exploration and Research (CIERA) Research Experiences in Astronomy at CIERA for High School Students (REACH) program. The REACH program brings students from the greater Chicagoland area to CIERA/Northwestern University to learn the skills needed to participate in research, and to conduct an independent research project under the supervision of a CIERA Astronomer. This grant helped to sponsor three iterations of the program, one during the summer of 2020 and two during the summer of 2021, that collectively included ~50 students from a diverse set of backgrounds.       Last Modified: 01/17/2023       Submitted by: Patrick D Sheehan]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
