<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Advanced fouling detection for district cooling facilities treated with a novel nano-engineered surface treatment]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>224675.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>249675</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anna Brady</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>abrady@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927077</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) project will reduce the energy demands of district cooling (DC) plants via state-of-the-art monitoring and analysis of system operations. District cooling systems are a more efficient, cost-effective way to produce chilled water across campuses compared to traditional building air conditioning units. Fouling accumulation in DC systems is an inevitable byproduct of environment, water source, and operating conditions; it contributes to inefficiencies that lead to increased power costs. This project’s aim is to improve the understanding and analysis of fouling using a machine learning, algorithm-based system performance indicator (SPI) in conjunction with a nanomaterial that reduces fouling accumulation and improves heat transfer. The SPI will provide value to DC operators by enabling them to be proactive instead of reactive in their maintenance protocols, which will improve the efficiency of their cooling systems and reduce their operating costs. Together, this innovative technology package will optimize DC operations and contribute to reduced energy demand and emissions. An average size DC plant can realize an estimated savings of $300,000 annually.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This SBIR Phase I project proposes to improve the efficiency of district cooling (DC) systems by increasing their system analysis capabilities through the following activities: 1) Integrate machine learning techniques into DC system data analysis to generate a system performance indicator (SPI). Instead of signaling that fouling has already occurred, the SPI will predict fouling onset to signal the need for retreatment with the nanomaterial and conduct other maintenance.  2) Optimize a system by integrating additional sensors for system performance diagnostics. The proposed project will conduct verification and validation for a system that could retrofit a single diagnostic sensor in the absence of a full sensor suite.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/15/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/15/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2001669</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Noah</FirstName>
<LastName>Snyder</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Noah Snyder</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[noahsnyder@interphasematerials.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000808849</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/15/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Interphase Materials, Inc.</Name>
<CityName>PITTSBURGH</CityName>
<ZipCode>15238</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4124471085</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>370 WILLIAM PITT WAY BLDG A4 #32</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>14</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA14</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NC92CVFR9ZP9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>INTERPHASE MATERIALS, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Interphase Materials, Inc.]]></Name>
<CityName>Pittsburgh</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>152381329</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[370 William Pitt Way]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<Institution>
<Name>Interphase Materials, Inc.</Name>
<CityName>PITTSBURGH</CityName>
<ZipCode>15238</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4124471085</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>370 WILLIAM PITT WAY BLDG A4 #32</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NC92CVFR9ZP9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>INTERPHASE MATERIALS, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Interphase Materials, Inc.]]></Name>
<CityName>Pittsburgh</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>152381329</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[370 William Pitt Way]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8091</Code>
<Text>SBIR Outreach &amp; Tech. Assist</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1769</Code>
<Text>Other Nano</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8033</Code>
<Text>Hardware Software Integration</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8040</Code>
<Text>Energy and Environment</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~249675</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>During the Phase I Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) grant funded by the National Science Foundation (NSF), Interphase Materials (IPM) worked on further development of the company?s <strong>INTELLIPHASE</strong> platform to detect and predict biosignals impacting district energy cooling operational efficiency. IPM was established in 2015 and has been working towards commercialization of its? technologies in the district energy market. One of IPM?s products, <strong><em>THERMOPHASE</em></strong>, is a nano-coating that reduces fouling of heat exchangers. During initial trials of <strong><em>THERMOPHASE</em></strong>, it was important to validate the efficiency improvements with customers. It was at this time that IPM developed the concept for <strong><em>INTELLIPHASE</em></strong>, a data analytics platform to help district cooling facilities operators make decisions about maintenance, operations, and validate new technology solutions. Together, IPM believes that <strong><em>THERMOPHASE</em> </strong>and <strong><em>INTELLIPHASE </em></strong>could provide substantial efficiency benefits to owners and operators of district cooling facilities. To translate this vision into reality, the NSF funded this effort to determine the feasibility of utilizing Artificial Intelligence/Machine Learning (AI/ML) techniques for predicting fouling of chillers in district cooling facilities. The effort was divided into two tasks. The objective of <strong>Task 1</strong> was to attempt to utilize existing data from customers to build an AI/ML model for fouling prediction. The objective for <strong>Task 2</strong> was to evaluate a sensor solution that could be used in replace of customer data or potentially in conjunction with existing data. Interphase Materials was extremely fortunate to have a partner in Enwave Chicago for this project to provide real-world chiller data from one of the largest district cooling facilities in the country.</p> <p>In reviewing the low-dimensional data supplied from the District Cooling plants during <strong>Task 1</strong>, we concluded that it will likely be possible to use supervised machine learning methods to build predictive models of fouling.&nbsp; Unfortunately, unsupervised method PCA showed that there was a source of variability in the Chiller data that was greater than the variability of cleaning vs fouling states.&nbsp; However, supervised classification methods, such as LDA and random forest classification succeeded in yielding high classification accuracies between clean, fouling, fouled states.&nbsp; We were successful in creating multiple linear regression models to predict the chiller approach temperature 48-hours into the future using the sensor data.&nbsp; This suggests that the sensor data does contain information related fouling, as it relates to increasing approach temperature.&nbsp; Unfortunately, this prediction, and the general metric of using approach temperature as a proxy for fouling, is not consistent enough to be used as an objective measure of fouling.</p> <p>While District Cooling facilities have access to large quantities of data, we found the data from customer sites to be unreliable and difficult to obtain. This presented a large problem to our initial concept for <strong>INTELLIPHASE</strong>. In anticipation of this outcome, we designed <strong>Task 2</strong> to provide a proof-of-concept feasibility test for a custom sensor that could collect a continuous data stream. We were able to demonstrate that the prototype electrochemical sensor setup could discern between relevant water concentrations of common biofouling organisms. The goal now is to have a similar sensor installed on-site to communicate data directly back to IPM for analysis. This will overcome the access and reliability concerns. From an access point of view, owning the sensor is extremely favorable. While the chillers in a district cooling facility have in theory all the data, many times the data is not trended. Even if the data is not trended, there is no guarantee that the sensors are accurate.</p> <p>In summary, IPM was able to successfully advance its <strong><em>INTELLIPHASE</em> </strong>technology and understanding of the district cooling market. In <strong>Task 1</strong> we utilized AI/ML techniques to build a model for predicting chiller fouling from approach temperature. However, the utility of these projections are more difficult to understand. From our experience in the market, the accuracy and reliability of the data makes ongoing prediction extremely challenging. To that end, in <strong>Task 2</strong> we demonstrated a proof-of-concept sensor setup for biofilm detection. In addition, through our customer discovery we found the market to be complex and not always aligned with efficiency gains. The financial balance between energy efficiency and maintenance costs is complex and shared between the provider of the cooling and the consumer, making investments in energy efficiency nuanced and non-trivial. Meanwhile, smaller chiller plant owners/operators are often too busy ?putting out fires? to be concerned with efficiency. While there may still be a market for <strong><em>INTELLIPHASE</em> </strong>in district cooling facilities it will require modification of our initial product hypothesis. Feedback from customers suggests that <strong>INTELLIPHASE </strong>may provide more value if we apply the technology to a true pain in the market, prevention and monitoring of legionella in cooling systems. The latter IPM would like to continue to explore with customers moving forward and hopefully in a Phase II effort.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/29/2021<br>      Modified by: Noah&nbsp;Snyder</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2001669/2001669_10670991_1635535589060_InterphaseMaterialsDCProducts--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2001669/2001669_10670991_1635535589060_InterphaseMaterialsDCProducts--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Interphase Materials Products"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2001669/2001669_10670991_1635535589060_InterphaseMaterialsDCProducts--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Interphase Materials Products"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Interphase Materials District Energy Products in Development</div> <div class="imageCredit">Noah Snyder</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Noah&nbsp;Snyder</div> <div class="imageTitle">Interphase Materials Products</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ During the Phase I Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) grant funded by the National Science Foundation (NSF), Interphase Materials (IPM) worked on further development of the company?s INTELLIPHASE platform to detect and predict biosignals impacting district energy cooling operational efficiency. IPM was established in 2015 and has been working towards commercialization of its? technologies in the district energy market. One of IPM?s products, THERMOPHASE, is a nano-coating that reduces fouling of heat exchangers. During initial trials of THERMOPHASE, it was important to validate the efficiency improvements with customers. It was at this time that IPM developed the concept for INTELLIPHASE, a data analytics platform to help district cooling facilities operators make decisions about maintenance, operations, and validate new technology solutions. Together, IPM believes that THERMOPHASE and INTELLIPHASE could provide substantial efficiency benefits to owners and operators of district cooling facilities. To translate this vision into reality, the NSF funded this effort to determine the feasibility of utilizing Artificial Intelligence/Machine Learning (AI/ML) techniques for predicting fouling of chillers in district cooling facilities. The effort was divided into two tasks. The objective of Task 1 was to attempt to utilize existing data from customers to build an AI/ML model for fouling prediction. The objective for Task 2 was to evaluate a sensor solution that could be used in replace of customer data or potentially in conjunction with existing data. Interphase Materials was extremely fortunate to have a partner in Enwave Chicago for this project to provide real-world chiller data from one of the largest district cooling facilities in the country.  In reviewing the low-dimensional data supplied from the District Cooling plants during Task 1, we concluded that it will likely be possible to use supervised machine learning methods to build predictive models of fouling.  Unfortunately, unsupervised method PCA showed that there was a source of variability in the Chiller data that was greater than the variability of cleaning vs fouling states.  However, supervised classification methods, such as LDA and random forest classification succeeded in yielding high classification accuracies between clean, fouling, fouled states.  We were successful in creating multiple linear regression models to predict the chiller approach temperature 48-hours into the future using the sensor data.  This suggests that the sensor data does contain information related fouling, as it relates to increasing approach temperature.  Unfortunately, this prediction, and the general metric of using approach temperature as a proxy for fouling, is not consistent enough to be used as an objective measure of fouling.  While District Cooling facilities have access to large quantities of data, we found the data from customer sites to be unreliable and difficult to obtain. This presented a large problem to our initial concept for INTELLIPHASE. In anticipation of this outcome, we designed Task 2 to provide a proof-of-concept feasibility test for a custom sensor that could collect a continuous data stream. We were able to demonstrate that the prototype electrochemical sensor setup could discern between relevant water concentrations of common biofouling organisms. The goal now is to have a similar sensor installed on-site to communicate data directly back to IPM for analysis. This will overcome the access and reliability concerns. From an access point of view, owning the sensor is extremely favorable. While the chillers in a district cooling facility have in theory all the data, many times the data is not trended. Even if the data is not trended, there is no guarantee that the sensors are accurate.  In summary, IPM was able to successfully advance its INTELLIPHASE technology and understanding of the district cooling market. In Task 1 we utilized AI/ML techniques to build a model for predicting chiller fouling from approach temperature. However, the utility of these projections are more difficult to understand. From our experience in the market, the accuracy and reliability of the data makes ongoing prediction extremely challenging. To that end, in Task 2 we demonstrated a proof-of-concept sensor setup for biofilm detection. In addition, through our customer discovery we found the market to be complex and not always aligned with efficiency gains. The financial balance between energy efficiency and maintenance costs is complex and shared between the provider of the cooling and the consumer, making investments in energy efficiency nuanced and non-trivial. Meanwhile, smaller chiller plant owners/operators are often too busy ?putting out fires? to be concerned with efficiency. While there may still be a market for INTELLIPHASE in district cooling facilities it will require modification of our initial product hypothesis. Feedback from customers suggests that INTELLIPHASE may provide more value if we apply the technology to a true pain in the market, prevention and monitoring of legionella in cooling systems. The latter IPM would like to continue to explore with customers moving forward and hopefully in a Phase II effort.       Last Modified: 10/29/2021       Submitted by: Noah Snyder]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
