<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Doctoral Dissertation Research: How Congregational Participation Shapes Higher Education Pathways in a Subpopulation]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>14116.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>14116</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Melanie Hughes</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mehughes@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927318</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This project provides information on how students from a growing subpopulation and their parents understand the connection between religiosity and higher education attainment.  This is a subpopulation with high levels of religious adherence and low levels of higher education attainment.  The role of these students’ religious perspectives in influencing their higher education achievement has been largely overlooked yet may be a vitally important piece of understanding educational stratification in this subpopulation.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project uses existing national and local administrative data and further conducts semi-structured interviews to investigate behaviors and attitudes toward education, the relationship between religious affiliation and college pathways, and the influence of faith leaders.  The administrative data will be used to examine the association between religious affiliation and advanced course-taking patterns, college applications, enrollment and college choice.  The interviews, with clergy, parents and young adults from three congregations, will explore the extent to which congregational dynamics have an impact on youths’ decisions about college.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/21/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/21/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2001983</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Esmeralda</FirstName>
<LastName>Salazar</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Esmeralda S Salazar</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[es47@rice.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000812300</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/21/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Elaine</FirstName>
<LastName>Howard Ecklund</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Elaine Howard Ecklund</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ehe@rice.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000188869</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/21/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>William Marsh Rice University</Name>
<CityName>Houston</CityName>
<ZipCode>770051827</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7133484820</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>6100 MAIN ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>K51LECU1G8N3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WILLIAM MARSH RICE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>K51LECU1G8N3</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[William Marsh Rice University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>770051827</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1331</Code>
<Text>Sociology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~14116</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The primary goal of the project, "Doctoral Dissertation Research: How Congregational Participation Shapes Higher Education Pathways in a Subpopulation" is to examine to what extent religious affiliation and congregational contexts either enable or constrain higher education attainment among Latino youth. Latinos represent a growing student population in U.S. schools who are highly religious and have low college completion rates compared to other racial and ethnic groups. To address the lack of research exploring how or whether religion shapes the way Latinos think about and make decisions about college, I sought to use three case studies of Latino congregations in Houston (Pentecostal, evangelical and Catholic) to conduct in-depth interviews with clergy, faith leaders, parents and young adults. The in-depth interviews compliment an analysis of administrative data from a large urban school district which aims to examine the extent to which Latino students' religious affiliation shapes their advanced course-taking patterns, college enrollment and college choice.</p> <p>To date, I achieved my goal of securing three Latino case study congregations and conducted in-depth interviews with young adults, parents, clergy and other congregational faith leaders. I completed a total of 31 interviews at the three case study congregations, two interviews at an additional congregation site and four pilot interviews at a pilot congregation. Analyses of these data are ongoing.</p> <p>One of the primary findings of the qualitative study is that religiously-involved Latino young adults consider church as family and as such formulate their college decisions based, in part, on their congregational ties. Young adults spent a considerable amount of time at their church and described the shared experiences with church members and their volunteer involvement with their church communities as fostering family-like ties. These strong church ties both enabled and constrained the college choice options of Latino young adults.</p> <p>Seeing church as family shaped how Latino religious youth planned for college. That is proximity to their faith community mattered for their college decision-making. Specifically, Latino young adults considered the following factors: 1) how close a college is to their local church, 2) how likely they are to be surrounded by same-faith believers within a college and 3) to whom they were closest to in their congregation mattered for how they talked about the importance of a college education and their college choices. For evangelical and Pentecostal youth highly engaged in congregational activities (e.g., church band, youth groups), church served as a "second home" and a "second family," which often constrained students' college choices as several opted to attend local colleges. For these youth, the decision to stay close to home for college was tied not simply to family or financial constraints but to a strong preference for remaining active in their local church. Other Latino young adults, particularly Pentecostal young adults, communicated that their church leadership promotes students attending a college that is closely aligned with their Christian faith. By this, young adults meant that some leaders expressed a preference for them to attend a faith-based institution or college that would allow them to be surrounded by other students and professors who share the same faith. Across all faith traditions, it mattered to whom young adults were close to within their congregation for how they talked about college and how they made their college decisions. Several young adults shared that they spoke with their pastor, priest or youth ministers during their college planning. These ministers provided needed guidance for choosing a college and in cases like those of the Catholic youth interviewed, youth ministers provided practical resources like recommendation letters and help with college essays. Overall, these themes highlight how congregational contexts can at times constrain college choices, but in many ways, also provide the practical guidance and resources Latino youth need in accessing and making decisions about their college journey. Indeed, religious leaders, peers and adult congregants serve as trusted sources and resources for Latino young adults as they think about whether and where they will attend college.</p> <p>As analyses continue, I have begun disseminating findings to religious leaders, educators and the academic community. To date, I have one article nearly ready for submission to an academic journal and two more in progress. I completed seven academic conference presentations and one webinar geared toward a general audience. I co-hosted one and presented at another religious and civic leader gathering. Further, I presented two professional development workshops for educators representing 13 different school districts. In addition, I presented findings to Latino faith leaders representing 12 states and 14 regions of the U.S. and have held meetings with key denomination leaders to discuss results and implications of the study. I will continue to disseminate findings in the months and years ahead. I aim to continue to use project findings to work with educators, faith communities and the academy to improve educational attainment within this subpopulation.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/15/2022<br>      Modified by: Esmeralda&nbsp;S&nbsp;Salazar</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The primary goal of the project, "Doctoral Dissertation Research: How Congregational Participation Shapes Higher Education Pathways in a Subpopulation" is to examine to what extent religious affiliation and congregational contexts either enable or constrain higher education attainment among Latino youth. Latinos represent a growing student population in U.S. schools who are highly religious and have low college completion rates compared to other racial and ethnic groups. To address the lack of research exploring how or whether religion shapes the way Latinos think about and make decisions about college, I sought to use three case studies of Latino congregations in Houston (Pentecostal, evangelical and Catholic) to conduct in-depth interviews with clergy, faith leaders, parents and young adults. The in-depth interviews compliment an analysis of administrative data from a large urban school district which aims to examine the extent to which Latino students' religious affiliation shapes their advanced course-taking patterns, college enrollment and college choice.  To date, I achieved my goal of securing three Latino case study congregations and conducted in-depth interviews with young adults, parents, clergy and other congregational faith leaders. I completed a total of 31 interviews at the three case study congregations, two interviews at an additional congregation site and four pilot interviews at a pilot congregation. Analyses of these data are ongoing.  One of the primary findings of the qualitative study is that religiously-involved Latino young adults consider church as family and as such formulate their college decisions based, in part, on their congregational ties. Young adults spent a considerable amount of time at their church and described the shared experiences with church members and their volunteer involvement with their church communities as fostering family-like ties. These strong church ties both enabled and constrained the college choice options of Latino young adults.  Seeing church as family shaped how Latino religious youth planned for college. That is proximity to their faith community mattered for their college decision-making. Specifically, Latino young adults considered the following factors: 1) how close a college is to their local church, 2) how likely they are to be surrounded by same-faith believers within a college and 3) to whom they were closest to in their congregation mattered for how they talked about the importance of a college education and their college choices. For evangelical and Pentecostal youth highly engaged in congregational activities (e.g., church band, youth groups), church served as a "second home" and a "second family," which often constrained students' college choices as several opted to attend local colleges. For these youth, the decision to stay close to home for college was tied not simply to family or financial constraints but to a strong preference for remaining active in their local church. Other Latino young adults, particularly Pentecostal young adults, communicated that their church leadership promotes students attending a college that is closely aligned with their Christian faith. By this, young adults meant that some leaders expressed a preference for them to attend a faith-based institution or college that would allow them to be surrounded by other students and professors who share the same faith. Across all faith traditions, it mattered to whom young adults were close to within their congregation for how they talked about college and how they made their college decisions. Several young adults shared that they spoke with their pastor, priest or youth ministers during their college planning. These ministers provided needed guidance for choosing a college and in cases like those of the Catholic youth interviewed, youth ministers provided practical resources like recommendation letters and help with college essays. Overall, these themes highlight how congregational contexts can at times constrain college choices, but in many ways, also provide the practical guidance and resources Latino youth need in accessing and making decisions about their college journey. Indeed, religious leaders, peers and adult congregants serve as trusted sources and resources for Latino young adults as they think about whether and where they will attend college.  As analyses continue, I have begun disseminating findings to religious leaders, educators and the academic community. To date, I have one article nearly ready for submission to an academic journal and two more in progress. I completed seven academic conference presentations and one webinar geared toward a general audience. I co-hosted one and presented at another religious and civic leader gathering. Further, I presented two professional development workshops for educators representing 13 different school districts. In addition, I presented findings to Latino faith leaders representing 12 states and 14 regions of the U.S. and have held meetings with key denomination leaders to discuss results and implications of the study. I will continue to disseminate findings in the months and years ahead. I aim to continue to use project findings to work with educators, faith communities and the academy to improve educational attainment within this subpopulation.          Last Modified: 07/15/2022       Submitted by: Esmeralda S Salazar]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
