<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Doctoral Dissertation Research: The distribution of costs and opportunities in amenity development communities]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>15960.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>15960</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Melanie Hughes</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mehughes@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927318</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This project investigates population changes in communities that shift to economies centered around national amenities.  Over the last four decades some regions have moved from dependence on extractive industries, such as ranching, farming, mining, or logging, to economies centered around natural amenities.  This transition is accompanied by population change, which can have widespread effects on socioeconomic, cultural, political, and environmental aspects of a community.  This research will investigate conditions under which amenity development fosters gentrification, the effects of amenity development and resulting population shifts on the distribution of opportunity and influence, and practices that lead communities down alternative paths.  Findings of this research will help communities identify opportunities and strategies to transition to an economy centered around amenity development while minimizing negative impacts. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Data for this project will be collected through interviews in three locations: a long-time amenity destination, a new amenity destination, and an emerging amenity destination.  Informants will be chosen to reflect three kinds of amenity development: bedroom communities, tourism destinations, and retirement destinations. Data will be coded using grounded theory coding methods.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/10/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/10/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2001828</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Brian</FirstName>
<LastName>Thiede</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Brian Thiede</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[bct11@psu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000718879</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kathryn</FirstName>
<LastName>Brasier</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kathryn Brasier</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[kbrasier@psu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000812841</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Grace</FirstName>
<LastName>Wildermuth</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Grace Wildermuth</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[gvw5117@psu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000811966</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Pennsylvania State Univ University Park</Name>
<CityName>UNIVERSITY PARK</CityName>
<ZipCode>168021503</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8148651372</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>201 OLD MAIN</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>15</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA15</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NPM2J7MSCF61</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>THE PENNSYLVANIA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Pennsylvania State Univ University Park]]></Name>
<CityName>UNIVERSITY PARK</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>168027000</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[110 Technology Center Building]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT/>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA"</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1331</Code>
<Text>Sociology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~15960</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="p1">Media attention and reports have highlighted the rush to rural amenity destinations for quarantine or work from home during the pandemic, and we have seen preliminary reports from rental companies to confirm this trend. This research sought to determine how COVID-19 has impacted short-term and long-term amenity migration to rural communities in Pennsylvania.&nbsp;In doing so, the project has investigated how rural tourism communities have been affected differently by this pandemic across a variety of characteristics such as amenity level, location, resources, and type of tourism, how pandemic migration affected the communities&rsquo; resources and residents as they also experienced the pandemic, and what lasting effects of amenity-migration during the pandemic might remain after the COVID-19 pandemic is over.</p> <p class="p2">To reach its objectives, this mixed-methods project designed and implemented a survey of 8,000 Pennsylvania residents, conducted twenty-two follow-up interviews with survey respondents, conducted thirty-eight interviews in two case study counties in Pennsylvania, and purchased short-term rental data showing changes across time and space for Pennsylvania.&nbsp;</p> <p class="p2">Taken together, these survey and interivew results suggest that Pennsylvanians continued traveling during the pandemic, but decreased their amount of travel and prioritized seeing friends and family over other travel reasons. Those who were most concerned about COVID and particularly vulnerable to Covid (retired or disabled individuals) were most likely to curtail their travel. While urban residents decreased their travel, visitors to rural areas did not tend to decrease. This trend was corroborated by interview results that noted explosions of visitors to rural areas.</p> <p class="p1">Pennsylvanians tended to feel safest in rural areas during the pandemic, making it no surprise that they sought them out to vacation or relocate. Follow-up interviews showed that people sought out rural areas due to their remote and non-crowded nature, and often felt like they were in a &ldquo;safe space&rdquo; devoid of covid or risk, and had left the virus behind. In addition, rural areas offered many opportunities for outdoor recreation, which interview respondents noted became a huge draw for themselves and others during the pandemic.</p> <p class="p1">Finally, in our analysis of living preferences, very few survey respondents suggested that the pandemic changed their opinions about where they want to live. This trend is consistent with interview data as well. However, for those that did report that the pandemic had changed their living preferences, in both cases they noted less populated areas with more outdoor recreation (or in some cases, simply rural areas) were more desirable. What does seem to be changing where people plan to live, according to the follow-up interviews conducted for this research, is remote work. The survey results showed us that those from urban areas were much more likely to have worked from home than those in rural areas, along with high income and highly educated individuals. And large number of respondents to both the survey and interviews, mostly from urban environments (according to the survey), were still working from home with no set date to return at the time of this research. Interview respondents noted the ways that remote work will allow them to travel more, and to a greater extent, to keep their job and move wherever they would like, mostly more rural locations with amenities and lower costs of living.</p> <p class="p1">The results of this research suggest that the pandemic led to a trend of both short- and long-term migration of urban, middle or upper class, well-educated and politically liberal migrants towards rural areas with more space, natural amenities, and outdoor recreation opportunities. These findings are consistent with amenity migration patterns, except for one clear difference: age. While amenity migrants tend to be near or at retirement age, this research found that those migrating were not retirement-age individuals, but rather working-age employed individuals who are able to relocate either temporarily or permanently, due to remote work. This urban to rural migration trend is counter to almost all accounts of disaster migration, which flows from rural to urban areas. This research found an almost exclusive migration from urban to rural areas due to disaster&nbsp;<em>everywhere</em>.</p> <p class="p1">This new group of work-from-home employees represents a&nbsp;<em>substantial</em>&nbsp;group of people that will now be untethered to their workplace when making decisions about where to live. This represents potential changes in the number and composition of residents in a subset of rural amenity communities, as well as the economic opportunities before them.</p> <p class="p2">&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/26/2022<br>      Modified by: Grace&nbsp;Wildermuth</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[Media attention and reports have highlighted the rush to rural amenity destinations for quarantine or work from home during the pandemic, and we have seen preliminary reports from rental companies to confirm this trend. This research sought to determine how COVID-19 has impacted short-term and long-term amenity migration to rural communities in Pennsylvania. In doing so, the project has investigated how rural tourism communities have been affected differently by this pandemic across a variety of characteristics such as amenity level, location, resources, and type of tourism, how pandemic migration affected the communities’ resources and residents as they also experienced the pandemic, and what lasting effects of amenity-migration during the pandemic might remain after the COVID-19 pandemic is over. To reach its objectives, this mixed-methods project designed and implemented a survey of 8,000 Pennsylvania residents, conducted twenty-two follow-up interviews with survey respondents, conducted thirty-eight interviews in two case study counties in Pennsylvania, and purchased short-term rental data showing changes across time and space for Pennsylvania.  Taken together, these survey and interivew results suggest that Pennsylvanians continued traveling during the pandemic, but decreased their amount of travel and prioritized seeing friends and family over other travel reasons. Those who were most concerned about COVID and particularly vulnerable to Covid (retired or disabled individuals) were most likely to curtail their travel. While urban residents decreased their travel, visitors to rural areas did not tend to decrease. This trend was corroborated by interview results that noted explosions of visitors to rural areas. Pennsylvanians tended to feel safest in rural areas during the pandemic, making it no surprise that they sought them out to vacation or relocate. Follow-up interviews showed that people sought out rural areas due to their remote and non-crowded nature, and often felt like they were in a "safe space" devoid of covid or risk, and had left the virus behind. In addition, rural areas offered many opportunities for outdoor recreation, which interview respondents noted became a huge draw for themselves and others during the pandemic. Finally, in our analysis of living preferences, very few survey respondents suggested that the pandemic changed their opinions about where they want to live. This trend is consistent with interview data as well. However, for those that did report that the pandemic had changed their living preferences, in both cases they noted less populated areas with more outdoor recreation (or in some cases, simply rural areas) were more desirable. What does seem to be changing where people plan to live, according to the follow-up interviews conducted for this research, is remote work. The survey results showed us that those from urban areas were much more likely to have worked from home than those in rural areas, along with high income and highly educated individuals. And large number of respondents to both the survey and interviews, mostly from urban environments (according to the survey), were still working from home with no set date to return at the time of this research. Interview respondents noted the ways that remote work will allow them to travel more, and to a greater extent, to keep their job and move wherever they would like, mostly more rural locations with amenities and lower costs of living. The results of this research suggest that the pandemic led to a trend of both short- and long-term migration of urban, middle or upper class, well-educated and politically liberal migrants towards rural areas with more space, natural amenities, and outdoor recreation opportunities. These findings are consistent with amenity migration patterns, except for one clear difference: age. While amenity migrants tend to be near or at retirement age, this research found that those migrating were not retirement-age individuals, but rather working-age employed individuals who are able to relocate either temporarily or permanently, due to remote work. This urban to rural migration trend is counter to almost all accounts of disaster migration, which flows from rural to urban areas. This research found an almost exclusive migration from urban to rural areas due to disaster everywhere. This new group of work-from-home employees represents a substantial group of people that will now be untethered to their workplace when making decisions about where to live. This represents potential changes in the number and composition of residents in a subset of rural amenity communities, as well as the economic opportunities before them.            Last Modified: 08/26/2022       Submitted by: Grace Wildermuth]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
