<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research to Explore the Spatial/Temporal Statistical-Physical Structures of Rain in the Vertical Plane]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>394580.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>394580</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06020105</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AGS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Chungu Lu</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>clu@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927110</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[A good understanding of rain in time and space is important for improved public safety and productivity. With regard to public safety, this means better water control designs for reducing the impact of flooding from smaller urban to larger regional scales as well as for improved spatial and temporal warnings of flooding in order to reduce damage and fatalities. With regard to productivity in rural areas, such information has the potential for reducing the impacts of soil erosion through the better design of field run-off and water storage. In more urban areas, productivity depends in part upon good wireless communication. However, the advent of 5G wireless networks will be more subject to signal loss due to rain, a loss that also depends upon the largely unknown spatial structure of rainfall particularly above the ground. All of these improvements, however, depend upon the proper translation of radar measurements and numerical model outputs to many different scales. This in turn requires that radar measurements above the ground as well as numerical model products be correctly transferred to what appears at the surface where people live. This, then, is a central objective of this project.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;More specifically with regard to the science, this project allows a more complete description of rain structure in a multi-dimensional context including height with the additional benefit of developing a better multi-dimensional understanding of drop interactions and evolution. Furthermore, the project is directed toward a more comprehensive investigation into the prevalence and the importance of statistical homogeneity in all three spatial dimensions as well as in time. Statistical homogeneity is important for the proper scaling of rainfall measurements, but, of course, not all rain is statistically homogeneous. However, it often appears that when the data are statistically heterogeneous, such data may be subdivided into statistically homogeneous sections which can then be properly treated analytically. This project develops this approach. In addition, wind tower measurements as well as simultaneous measurements between two 2DVD disdrometers will be used to explore further the reported deviations of drop fall speeds from their nominal terminal values both aloft and at the surface. This is potentially quite important for the proper understanding of the evolution of rain.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/27/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/27/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2001343</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Arthur</FirstName>
<LastName>Jameson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Arthur R Jameson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[arjameson@verizon.net]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000370470</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/27/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>RJH Scientific Incorporated</Name>
<CityName>EL CAJON</CityName>
<ZipCode>920208227</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6194421407</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1594 HILLTOP DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>48</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA48</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>ELJLKEWNJP99</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RJH SCIENTIFIC INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[RJH Scientific Incorporated]]></Name>
<CityName>Arlington</CityName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>222071560</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5625 32nd St N]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>VA08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1525</Code>
<Text>Physical &amp; Dynamic Meteorology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~394580</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>For water resources management and planning of human activities, it is useful to have a scaling of the rainfall over a wide range of spatial dimensions. Determining such a scaling relation, however, is not trivial since it requires high resolution observations over a wide range of scales from meters to kilometers. While in principle this could be achieved using an extensive network of closely spaced rainfall measurement tools such as disdrometers or rain gages, such an approach is neither practical nor cost effective. Instead, we have developed a method for using vertical pointing Doppler radar measurements at high spatial (10 m) and temporal (every 10 s) resolutions to calculate the equivalent to a network of rainfall measurements consisting of thousands of instruments. This research has demonstrated the feasibility of this approach using Micro-Rain Radar (MRR) observations in four different meteorological settings so that catalogs of such scaling relations can be developed in different locations experience different characteristic meteorological conditions for improved water management such as flood control and planning of picnics and outdoor sports events.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>In order to achieve this, a method to account for the vertical motion of the air was developed so that the raindrop fall speed Doppler spectra could be more accurately converted in drop size distributions and, hence, rainfall fall rates for the development of scaling relations. This represents a solution to a 60 year-old outstanding problem in radar meteorology. Furthermore, a method was developed for better estimating the speed of advection of the rain over a radar so that its temporal observations could be more accurately converted into spatial dimensions for the construction of the rainfall scaling relations.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/01/2023<br>      Modified by: Arthur&nbsp;R&nbsp;Jameson</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ For water resources management and planning of human activities, it is useful to have a scaling of the rainfall over a wide range of spatial dimensions. Determining such a scaling relation, however, is not trivial since it requires high resolution observations over a wide range of scales from meters to kilometers. While in principle this could be achieved using an extensive network of closely spaced rainfall measurement tools such as disdrometers or rain gages, such an approach is neither practical nor cost effective. Instead, we have developed a method for using vertical pointing Doppler radar measurements at high spatial (10 m) and temporal (every 10 s) resolutions to calculate the equivalent to a network of rainfall measurements consisting of thousands of instruments. This research has demonstrated the feasibility of this approach using Micro-Rain Radar (MRR) observations in four different meteorological settings so that catalogs of such scaling relations can be developed in different locations experience different characteristic meteorological conditions for improved water management such as flood control and planning of picnics and outdoor sports events.     In order to achieve this, a method to account for the vertical motion of the air was developed so that the raindrop fall speed Doppler spectra could be more accurately converted in drop size distributions and, hence, rainfall fall rates for the development of scaling relations. This represents a solution to a 60 year-old outstanding problem in radar meteorology. Furthermore, a method was developed for better estimating the speed of advection of the rain over a radar so that its temporal observations could be more accurately converted into spatial dimensions for the construction of the rainfall scaling relations.       Last Modified: 04/01/2023       Submitted by: Arthur R Jameson]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
