<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[NRI: FND: COLLAB: RAPID: Targeted Sampling of an Unanticipated Harmful Algal Bloom in Lake Anna, Virginia with Aerial and Aquatic Robots]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>68968.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>68968</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Erion Plaku</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[An unanticipated harmful algal bloom (HAB) appeared in Lake Anna, Virginia in early August, 2019. Lake Anna is one of the largest freshwater reservoirs in VA. Research is needed to understand threats, manage risks, mitigate incidents, develop capabilities, and strengthen collaborations for our water safety and security. Aerial and aquatic robots will work alongside health and water quality experts from VDH and DEQ to (1) help inform their regular sampling efforts, and (2) provide critical and timely information to guide regulatory decisions.  The HAB is still going at Lake Anna, and it is expected to continue until the first freeze at the Lake. Once the first freeze occurs, most of the cyanobacteria will explode and unload a large amount of toxins, requiring further analysis.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Since the first report of the harmful algal boom (HAB) on Lake Anna, the bloom has reportedly intensified, and the Virginia Department of Health (VDH) has issued multiple advisories. The most recent VDH advisory (issued on Sept 20, 2019) showed the HAB extending down both northern branches of the lake. The VDH advisories are based in part on water quality data from the VA Department of Environmental Quality (DEQ), which collects samples from a series of stations (GPS waypoints where a manned boat is used to collect samples by hand) across the lake. The research team will work alongside water quality experts (DEQ and VDH) to make targeted collections of the HAB at Lake Anna using aerial robots (a drone equipped with multispectral sensors to image the bloom and a device to sample the water) and aquatic robots (a remotely operated underwater vehicle equipped with underwater GPS, sensors to track the plume in situ, and a device to collect underwater samples). These samples will be analyzed for toxins and nutrients, and the data will be shared with water quality experts and members of the Lake Anna Civic Association. Based on 10 years of seasonal toxin data for Grand Lake St. Marys in Ohio, the research team hypothesize that (1) the HAB at Lake Anna, VA will continue to progress and produce high toxin levels through the coming winter months and (2) aerial and aquatic robots can identify, localize, and sample targeted areas of the HAB in the lake. The specific objectives of this project are to (1) use aerial and aquatic robots to target the HAB in Lake Anna, VA and collect samples at strategic locations; and (2) determine toxin concentrations and nutrient loads in samples collected by robots working alongside humans. This information is critical for determining time-sensitive health advisories, and for the communities of people that live in and around the lake. This work will also show the value of unmanned systems to assist stakeholders in tracking HABs in the water; resulting field-tested technology will provide decision-makers with co-robots that can provide rapid and detailed information on the dispersal of HABs in the environment.  The HAB is still going at Lake Anna, and it is expected to continue until the first freeze at the Lake. Once the first freeze occurs, most of the cyanobacteria will lyse and unload a copious amount of cyanotoxins.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/28/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/28/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2001119</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Schmale</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>G</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David G Schmale</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[dschmale@vt.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000495745</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/28/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University</Name>
<CityName>BLACKSBURG</CityName>
<ZipCode>240603359</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5402315281</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>300 TURNER ST NW</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[STE 4200]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>VA09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>QDE5UHE5XD16</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>VIRGINIA POLYTECHNIC INSTITUTE &amp; STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>X6KEFGLHSJX7</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>240610001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>VA09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8013</Code>
<Text>NRI-National Robotics Initiati</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8086</Code>
<Text>Natl Robotics Initiative (NRI)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~68968</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The overall goal of this project was to work alongside water quality experts (Virginia Department of Health, VDH, and the Virginia Department of Environmental Quality, DEQ) and homeowners (members of the Lake Anna Civic Association, LACA) to make targeted collections of a harmful algal bloom (HAB) at Lake Anna, Virginia with aerial and aquatic robots. The specific objectives of the project were to (1) use robots (drones) to target the HAB in Lake Anna, VA and collect samples at strategic locations and (2) determine toxin concentrations and nutrient loads in samples collected by robots working alongside humans. Despite significant challenges associated with the COVID-19 pandemic, we were able to conduct three field campaigns at Lake Anna in 2020 (June, July, and October). LACA identified critical locations (stations) for monitoring the HAB at Lake Anna, and some of these stations included regular monitoring sites by state agencies. Aerial robot sampling efforts were focused on land-based operations on the northern branches of Lake Anna. Water samples were collected with aerial robots along transects extending 100 meters from the shore. Ground-based instruments were also deployed at these sites to capture potential cyanobacteria and toxins in the air. Wind profiles were estimated with drones up to about 80 m above ground level. Water samples collected with the robots were analyzed for toxins and nutrients. Most of the water samples contained low levels of the potent neurotoxin anatoxin-a. Total phosphorus in drone water samples ranged from 0.01 mg/L to 0.21 mg/L, with a mean phosphorus concentration of 0.06 mg/L. Analyses on aerosol sample collection and wind profiles are ongoing, but indicate a potential for cyanobacteria and associated toxins in the lake to become aerosolized and transported inland. Our observations from aerial robots were critical for determining time-sensitive health advisories, and for the communities of people that live in and around the lake. This includes members of the Lake Anna Civic Association, representing over 800 homeowners on Lake Anna.<br />&nbsp;&nbsp; &nbsp;Resulting field-tested technology provided decision-makers with co-robots that can provide rapid and detailed information on the dispersal of HABs in the environment. Such co-robots, working alongside local government agencies and citizen scientists, have the potential to be used as part of regular monitoring efforts at lakes and communities around the world. Our work has contributed new unmanned systems technology to track the movement of HABs (and hazardous agents in general) in the water and air. Members of the public were able to see our robotic technologies in action, and ultimately appreciate the value of these technologies for water quality monitoring efforts. Data from this project have been shared with civic groups and state government agencies, paving the way for data sharing and access across the academic-citizen-government continuum.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/27/2022<br>      Modified by: David&nbsp;G&nbsp;Schmale</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2001119/2001119_10655333_1643329206608_Image_Outcomes_Schmale_NRI_RAPID_Anna--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2001119/2001119_10655333_1643329206608_Image_Outcomes_Schmale_NRI_RAPID_Anna--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Targeted sampling of the HAB at Lake Anna with aerial and aquatic robotics"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2001119/2001119_10655333_1643329206608_Image_Outcomes_Schmale_NRI_RAPID_Anna--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Targeted sampling of the HAB at Lake Anna with aerial and aquatic robotics"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Composite image showing LACA planning (top left), drone sampling of the lake (top right), aerosol monitoring of the lake (bottom left and bottom center), and wind profiles of the lake to determine potential transport of the HAB cells and toxins (bottom right).</div> <div class="imageCredit">David Schmale</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">David&nbsp;G&nbsp;Schmale</div> <div class="imageTitle">Targeted sampling of the HAB at Lake Anna with aerial and aquatic robotics</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The overall goal of this project was to work alongside water quality experts (Virginia Department of Health, VDH, and the Virginia Department of Environmental Quality, DEQ) and homeowners (members of the Lake Anna Civic Association, LACA) to make targeted collections of a harmful algal bloom (HAB) at Lake Anna, Virginia with aerial and aquatic robots. The specific objectives of the project were to (1) use robots (drones) to target the HAB in Lake Anna, VA and collect samples at strategic locations and (2) determine toxin concentrations and nutrient loads in samples collected by robots working alongside humans. Despite significant challenges associated with the COVID-19 pandemic, we were able to conduct three field campaigns at Lake Anna in 2020 (June, July, and October). LACA identified critical locations (stations) for monitoring the HAB at Lake Anna, and some of these stations included regular monitoring sites by state agencies. Aerial robot sampling efforts were focused on land-based operations on the northern branches of Lake Anna. Water samples were collected with aerial robots along transects extending 100 meters from the shore. Ground-based instruments were also deployed at these sites to capture potential cyanobacteria and toxins in the air. Wind profiles were estimated with drones up to about 80 m above ground level. Water samples collected with the robots were analyzed for toxins and nutrients. Most of the water samples contained low levels of the potent neurotoxin anatoxin-a. Total phosphorus in drone water samples ranged from 0.01 mg/L to 0.21 mg/L, with a mean phosphorus concentration of 0.06 mg/L. Analyses on aerosol sample collection and wind profiles are ongoing, but indicate a potential for cyanobacteria and associated toxins in the lake to become aerosolized and transported inland. Our observations from aerial robots were critical for determining time-sensitive health advisories, and for the communities of people that live in and around the lake. This includes members of the Lake Anna Civic Association, representing over 800 homeowners on Lake Anna.     Resulting field-tested technology provided decision-makers with co-robots that can provide rapid and detailed information on the dispersal of HABs in the environment. Such co-robots, working alongside local government agencies and citizen scientists, have the potential to be used as part of regular monitoring efforts at lakes and communities around the world. Our work has contributed new unmanned systems technology to track the movement of HABs (and hazardous agents in general) in the water and air. Members of the public were able to see our robotic technologies in action, and ultimately appreciate the value of these technologies for water quality monitoring efforts. Data from this project have been shared with civic groups and state government agencies, paving the way for data sharing and access across the academic-citizen-government continuum.       Last Modified: 01/27/2022       Submitted by: David G Schmale]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
