<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Doctoral Dissertation Research: Differentiating Effects of Particularistic Performance Standards in the Workplace]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>15521.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>15521</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joseph Whitmeyer</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jwhitmey@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927808</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This research investigates how performance standards in the workplace create barriers to inclusion.  The specific focus is on how sound and voice criteria for broadcasters have constrained plans of inclusion in broadcasting organizations in different regions.  The project investigates 1) the creation of public radio broadcast standards, 2) the endurance of these standards despite demographic changes, and 3) how broadcasters experience these standards.  This work will contribute to understanding of how obstacles to opportunity can exist in organizations.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Data will be collected from relevant documents and interviews, as follows.  Memoranda about language usage  in national archives will be examined to identify foundational policies and practices for radio networks.  Board documents at broadcasting organizations will be examined to analyze inclusion efforts and their relationship to existing rules.  Listener complaints will be analyzed to identify audience demands.  Lastly, 100 radio broadcasters will be interviewed about challenges they face and tools they use.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/14/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/14/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2001868</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jose</FirstName>
<LastName>Itzigsohn</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jose Itzigsohn</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[Jose_Itzigsohn@Brown.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000233026</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/14/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Laura</FirstName>
<LastName>Garbes</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Laura Garbes</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[laura_garbes@brown.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000810490</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/14/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Brown University</Name>
<CityName>PROVIDENCE</CityName>
<ZipCode>029129127</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4018632777</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1 PROSPECT ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>RI01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>E3FDXZ6TBHW3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>BROWN UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>E3FDXZ6TBHW3</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Brown University]]></Name>
<CityName>Providence</CityName>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>029129002</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Box 1929]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>RI01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1331</Code>
<Text>Sociology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~15521</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-6c7e0a42-7fff-69a5-732f-c9cf0061f86a"> <p dir="ltr"><span>This research project interrogated the white dominant management, listenership, and sound of public radio in the United States and Australia. </span><span>The increasing number of nonwhite broadcasters in public radio in these white settler nations has brought to light a norm where "neutral" broadcaster voices most closely resemble those of well-educated white professionals. </span><span>How did this norm get entrenched in public radio, and what are its material and psychic impacts on workers of color within the industry?&nbsp;&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>To understand how policies within American noncommercial radio shaped white dominance in the emerging public radio industry of the 1960s-1970s, the co-PI conducted an archival analysis of the industries in both contexts. Using DDRI funding, the co-PI visited the National Public Broadcasting Archives in Washington, D.C., and three different locations of the National Archives of Australia. The co-PI then conducted an analysis of 20th century archival data, public radio founder memoirs, financial histories of the public radio networks, and marketing materials.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>To understand how nonwhite public radio professionals navigate the contemporary public radio industry, the co-PI conducted 83 semi-structured interviews with American public radio employees of color, COVID-19 travel restrictions delayed the interview process in the Australian context; however, a fieldwork trip in April 2022 enabled the co-PI to conduct 12 semi-structured interviews with Australian public radio employees of color and establish connections for future Zoom interviews beyond the grant period. Each interview ranges from 75 to 130 minutes and focuses on story production, relationships to listeners, and employee reflections on their own performance in a historically white dominant space.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Across five chapters, I use the above data sources to analyze how race and sound are co-naturalized in our social world.&#8239; Within my existing research, I argue that public radio&rsquo;s founders and managers adopted seemingly non-racial policies that had racially exclusionary consequences for workforce and audience participation in the network, despite a stated mission to serve all Americans. The focus on a white, well-educated set of donors, and their notions of whose voices are warm and authoritative, created a sustainable financial model for the public radio industry. However, these same factors limit the creative freedoms of nonwhite public radio workers and have alienated nonwhite, working class audiences. From within the workplace to the broader American public sphere, these racially exclusionary processes weaken possibilities of a true and open democracy.&nbsp;&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr">The co-PI disseminated these findings through academic writing in the <em>Sociology of Race and Ethnicity </em>journal and public writing in <em>The American Prospect.</em>&nbsp;The co-PI also presented these findings to academics at the <em>American Sociological Association Annual Meeting</em>, to audio practitioners at the <em>Third Coast International Audio Conference</em>, and to a mixture of both at an invited lecture at the <em>University of Sydney</em>, which will be converted into a podcast.</p> <span>The project offers a sociological case study that uncovers a new perspective to understanding organizational life. In centering the auditory construction of race and analyzing the sonic construction of racial difference within organizations, the project explains how linguistic discrimination is </span><span>formed</span><span> and maintained through institutional processes. More broadly, the project destabilizes our assumptions about how we sense racial difference, and in doing so, opens up further possibilities for deeper institutional change. </span></span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/19/2022<br>      Modified by: Laura&nbsp;Garbes</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  This research project interrogated the white dominant management, listenership, and sound of public radio in the United States and Australia. The increasing number of nonwhite broadcasters in public radio in these white settler nations has brought to light a norm where "neutral" broadcaster voices most closely resemble those of well-educated white professionals. How did this norm get entrenched in public radio, and what are its material and psychic impacts on workers of color within the industry?   To understand how policies within American noncommercial radio shaped white dominance in the emerging public radio industry of the 1960s-1970s, the co-PI conducted an archival analysis of the industries in both contexts. Using DDRI funding, the co-PI visited the National Public Broadcasting Archives in Washington, D.C., and three different locations of the National Archives of Australia. The co-PI then conducted an analysis of 20th century archival data, public radio founder memoirs, financial histories of the public radio networks, and marketing materials.  To understand how nonwhite public radio professionals navigate the contemporary public radio industry, the co-PI conducted 83 semi-structured interviews with American public radio employees of color, COVID-19 travel restrictions delayed the interview process in the Australian context; however, a fieldwork trip in April 2022 enabled the co-PI to conduct 12 semi-structured interviews with Australian public radio employees of color and establish connections for future Zoom interviews beyond the grant period. Each interview ranges from 75 to 130 minutes and focuses on story production, relationships to listeners, and employee reflections on their own performance in a historically white dominant space.  Across five chapters, I use the above data sources to analyze how race and sound are co-naturalized in our social world.&#8239; Within my existing research, I argue that public radio’s founders and managers adopted seemingly non-racial policies that had racially exclusionary consequences for workforce and audience participation in the network, despite a stated mission to serve all Americans. The focus on a white, well-educated set of donors, and their notions of whose voices are warm and authoritative, created a sustainable financial model for the public radio industry. However, these same factors limit the creative freedoms of nonwhite public radio workers and have alienated nonwhite, working class audiences. From within the workplace to the broader American public sphere, these racially exclusionary processes weaken possibilities of a true and open democracy.   The co-PI disseminated these findings through academic writing in the Sociology of Race and Ethnicity journal and public writing in The American Prospect. The co-PI also presented these findings to academics at the American Sociological Association Annual Meeting, to audio practitioners at the Third Coast International Audio Conference, and to a mixture of both at an invited lecture at the University of Sydney, which will be converted into a podcast. The project offers a sociological case study that uncovers a new perspective to understanding organizational life. In centering the auditory construction of race and analyzing the sonic construction of racial difference within organizations, the project explains how linguistic discrimination is formed and maintained through institutional processes. More broadly, the project destabilizes our assumptions about how we sense racial difference, and in doing so, opens up further possibilities for deeper institutional change.           Last Modified: 07/19/2022       Submitted by: Laura Garbes]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
