<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Doctoral Dissertation Research:  Experiences of Youth at the Intersection of the Child Welfare and Juvenile Justice Systems.]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>15896.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>15896</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joseph Whitmeyer</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jwhitmey@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927808</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Crossover youth are a unique population of children involved in both the child welfare and the juvenile justice systems. Crossover youth are disproportionately likely to experience social and economic disadvantage, and the dual system involvement may fundamentally shape their adolescence and transition to adulthood. This project investigates how juvenile court institutions characterize and respond to crossover youth, how crossover youth experience their dual status as “dependent” and “delinquent,” and how crossover youths’ experiences in court influence their well-being as they proceed through adolescence. In addition to investigating the relationship between state institutions and inequality in the United States, the project will show how the state distinguishes between victims and offenders and how it interacts with the families so affected. Findings will inform state policies affecting the operation of both child welfare and juvenile justice systems.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will combine longitudinal interviews and ethnographic observation to examine how juvenile court institutions respond to crossover youth and how crossover youth experience the court process themselves. Data will be drawn from repeated interviews with 35 to 40 crossover youth over the course of a year, as well as ethnographic observation in juvenile court and interviews with key decision makers in both dependency and delinquency courts. Longitudinal follow-ups with crossover youth will grant insight into how young people experience the court process, and court observation will provide a unique opportunity to observe interactions between court actors and youth and compare what happens in court to how individuals describe their court experiences in interviews. Findings will inform sociological theories regarding juvenile justice and the law, as well as the sociology of childhood and transition to adulthood.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/19/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/26/2023</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2001733</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Florencia</FirstName>
<LastName>Torche</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Florencia Torche</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[torche@stanford.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000529769</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/19/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Catherine</FirstName>
<LastName>Sirois</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Catherine Sirois</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[csirois@stanford.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000707721</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/19/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Stanford University</Name>
<CityName>STANFORD</CityName>
<ZipCode>943052004</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6507232300</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>450 JANE STANFORD WAY</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>16</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA16</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>HJD6G4D6TJY5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>THE LELAND STANFORD JUNIOR UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Stanford University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>943052020</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>16</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA16</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1331</Code>
<Text>Sociology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~15896</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The state relies on bureaucratic institutions to govern marginalized groups, but the complexity of people's lives defies institutional boundaries. Given this inherent mismatch, how does the state govern marginalized groups, and what are the consequences of governance processes for group members? This research project expands our understanding of governance at the margins--meaning both groups pushed to the margins of mainstream society and those at the margins of state institutions--by studying the unique case of crossover youth, children at the junction of child welfare and juvenile justice systems. Because crossover youth--perceived as both dependent and delinquent--challenge the legal, administrative, and moral boundaries of these two institutions, they present an ideal case for illuminating interlocking processes of state governance.</p> <p>I draw on the findings of this project to make three primary claims. First, I argue that bureaucratic governance is driven by the efforts of institutional actors--from frontline workers to administrators--to optimize resources and minimize blame. Second, I contend that when institutional actors perceive eligible tasks or clients to unduly strain the resources at their disposal and expose them to blame, they will seek to transfer or deflect responsibility across institutional lines, a process I term <em>institutional offloading</em>. Third, I argue that we can better understand the consequences of bureaucratic governance for marginalized groups by attending to the departures of bureaucratic actors from institutional rules and norms, which I refer to as<em> institutional deviations</em>.</p> <p>I offer empirical evidence for these claims through an analysis of over 300 hours of ethnographic observation from a California juvenile court and 40 interviews with court actors. In the primary article from this project, published in <em>American Sociological Review</em>, I demonstrate how both Social Services and Probation--representing, respectively, the county's child welfare and juvenile justice institutions--attempt to offload responsibility for crossover youth. When social workers believe a crossover client has exhausted the resources at their disposal and put them at risk of blame, they emphasize the child's status as delinquent to facilitate a transfer to Probation. But despite being responsible for public protection, Probation administrators, via a series of bureaucratic protocols, deflect responsibility for nearly all crossover cases given their financial and political cost to the institution. Although probation officers often privately agree with their frontline counterparts, they exercise little discretion and publicly emphasize crossover youths' status as dependent. When institutional conditions shift, so too do institutional actors' construction and classification of crossover youth as dependent or delinquent.</p> <p>The findings contribute to existing research and policy by advancing a more comprehensive framework for analyzing the interlocking processes of bureaucratic governance; showing how punishment--from macro-level decisions to micro-level interactions--is produced by bureaucratic processes; and illuminating mechanisms by which the pipeline to prison for marginalized groups may be perpetuated and potentially disrupted.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/26/2023<br>      Modified by: Catherine&nbsp;Sirois</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The state relies on bureaucratic institutions to govern marginalized groups, but the complexity of people's lives defies institutional boundaries. Given this inherent mismatch, how does the state govern marginalized groups, and what are the consequences of governance processes for group members? This research project expands our understanding of governance at the margins--meaning both groups pushed to the margins of mainstream society and those at the margins of state institutions--by studying the unique case of crossover youth, children at the junction of child welfare and juvenile justice systems. Because crossover youth--perceived as both dependent and delinquent--challenge the legal, administrative, and moral boundaries of these two institutions, they present an ideal case for illuminating interlocking processes of state governance.  I draw on the findings of this project to make three primary claims. First, I argue that bureaucratic governance is driven by the efforts of institutional actors--from frontline workers to administrators--to optimize resources and minimize blame. Second, I contend that when institutional actors perceive eligible tasks or clients to unduly strain the resources at their disposal and expose them to blame, they will seek to transfer or deflect responsibility across institutional lines, a process I term institutional offloading. Third, I argue that we can better understand the consequences of bureaucratic governance for marginalized groups by attending to the departures of bureaucratic actors from institutional rules and norms, which I refer to as institutional deviations.  I offer empirical evidence for these claims through an analysis of over 300 hours of ethnographic observation from a California juvenile court and 40 interviews with court actors. In the primary article from this project, published in American Sociological Review, I demonstrate how both Social Services and Probation--representing, respectively, the county's child welfare and juvenile justice institutions--attempt to offload responsibility for crossover youth. When social workers believe a crossover client has exhausted the resources at their disposal and put them at risk of blame, they emphasize the child's status as delinquent to facilitate a transfer to Probation. But despite being responsible for public protection, Probation administrators, via a series of bureaucratic protocols, deflect responsibility for nearly all crossover cases given their financial and political cost to the institution. Although probation officers often privately agree with their frontline counterparts, they exercise little discretion and publicly emphasize crossover youths' status as dependent. When institutional conditions shift, so too do institutional actors' construction and classification of crossover youth as dependent or delinquent.  The findings contribute to existing research and policy by advancing a more comprehensive framework for analyzing the interlocking processes of bureaucratic governance; showing how punishment--from macro-level decisions to micro-level interactions--is produced by bureaucratic processes; and illuminating mechanisms by which the pipeline to prison for marginalized groups may be perpetuated and potentially disrupted.       Last Modified: 10/26/2023       Submitted by: Catherine Sirois]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
