<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Doctoral Dissertation Research: Reputational Consequences of Scholarships]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>15798.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>15798</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joseph Whitmeyer</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jwhitmey@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927808</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This project will investigate whether association with particular scholarship programs generates negative reputational consequences for labor market outcomes.  It also will examine if and how employer characteristics are related to the potentially stigmatizing effects of such awards. In recent decades, many universities and companies have used scholarships, fellowships, and pipeline programs to achieve organizational goals. These programs offer members of some groups additional opportunities and resources but in doing so may label the recipients.  Prior research has found that beneficiaries may be seen as less warm and less competent.  The findings from this project will provide greater understanding of how opportunity-enhancing programs and awards may have unintended negative effects on their beneficiaries’ outcomes.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project uses a survey experiment to measure employer perceptions of scholarship winners. The sample consists of hiring managers and other professionals with recruiting and hiring experience. Respondents are randomly assigned resumés to review and are asked to answer questions about their perceptions of the job applicants represented by the resumés. The resumés experimentally manipulate the demographic group of the applicant and kind of scholarship received. The survey experiment will be complemented by a field experiment with similar experimental manipulations.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/28/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/28/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2001853</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jiayi</FirstName>
<LastName>Xu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jiayi J Xu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jjxu@princeton.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000810994</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/28/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Matthew</FirstName>
<LastName>Salganik</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Matthew J Salganik</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mjs3@princeton.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000110903</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/28/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Princeton University</Name>
<CityName>PRINCETON</CityName>
<ZipCode>085442001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6092583090</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1 NASSAU HALL</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NJ12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NJ1YPQXQG7U5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>THE TRUSTEES OF PRINCETON UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Princeton University]]></Name>
<CityName>Princeton</CityName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>085442020</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Off. of Research & Proj. Admin.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NJ12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1331</Code>
<Text>Sociology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~15798</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>In recent decades, many universities and companies have used selective scholarships, fellowships, and pipeline programs to achieve organizational diversity goals. Although these organizational initiatives are designed to recruit specific individuals, existing research has mostly focused on the impact of diversity initiatives on the organizations, rather than their effects on the targeted individuals. This project set out to inspect one aspect of how selective scholarships and pipeline programs may influence targets&rsquo; future labor market outcomes by investigating how prospective employers evaluated diversity scholarship recipients. A survey experiment and complementary field experiment examined if putatively Black and White job applicants with diversity merit scholarships are more or less likely to receive an interview invite than comparable candidates with other types of merit scholarships or candidates with no merit scholarships at all.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Results indicate that the reputational effects of merit scholarships differ based on applicants&rsquo; racial cues. For putatively White applicants, diversity-specific scholarships and non-diversity-related scholarships send similar positive signals to employers; candidates with either type of award are more likely to advance to the next stage of the hiring process than candidates without scholarships. For putatively Black applicants, however, only non-diversity-related scholarships send a positive signal to employers; candidates with diversity merit scholarships are evaluated similarly to candidates without scholarships. Furthermore, while all applicants with non-diversity-related scholarships are more likely to receive a job interview than applicants without scholarships, the effect of this signal is larger for putatively White applicants than it is for putatively Black applicants. Additional evidence from the survey experiment suggest that these awards do not significantly influence perceptions of warmth and competence, but employers view non-diversity-related scholarships as more selective than diversity scholarships.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>This project contributes to sociological knowledge on economic sociology, organizations, inequality, and race/ethnicity in several ways. First, by focusing on how employers interpret awards from other organizations, this project sheds insight on the interplay between organizational structures and individual actions in the production of racial discrimination. Second, this project contributes new evidence to existing research on cumulative advantage and school-to-work transitions. Finally, results from this project contribute to ongoing research in cultural sociology about the fluid definition of &ldquo;diversity&rdquo; in institutional settings, and how a diffuse understanding of diversity contributes to racial inequality.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Broader impacts of this project include significant implications for policy design and human resources development of a diverse workforce. Like organizations in other industries, many STEM organizations have recently made avowed commitments to diversity and created opportunity-enhancing programs like selective diversity scholarships and fellowships. Results from this project suggest that human resources development in STEM organizations, like those in other fields, should be careful about publicizing and presenting these diversity awards to avoid the devaluation of underrepresented minorities&rsquo; accomplishments. (Note that this project only investigated the reputational effects of such awards; other aspects of these awards, such as material support and mentoring, may have positive effects of their own.)</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/01/2021<br>      Modified by: Jiayi&nbsp;J&nbsp;Xu</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ In recent decades, many universities and companies have used selective scholarships, fellowships, and pipeline programs to achieve organizational diversity goals. Although these organizational initiatives are designed to recruit specific individuals, existing research has mostly focused on the impact of diversity initiatives on the organizations, rather than their effects on the targeted individuals. This project set out to inspect one aspect of how selective scholarships and pipeline programs may influence targets’ future labor market outcomes by investigating how prospective employers evaluated diversity scholarship recipients. A survey experiment and complementary field experiment examined if putatively Black and White job applicants with diversity merit scholarships are more or less likely to receive an interview invite than comparable candidates with other types of merit scholarships or candidates with no merit scholarships at all.     Results indicate that the reputational effects of merit scholarships differ based on applicants’ racial cues. For putatively White applicants, diversity-specific scholarships and non-diversity-related scholarships send similar positive signals to employers; candidates with either type of award are more likely to advance to the next stage of the hiring process than candidates without scholarships. For putatively Black applicants, however, only non-diversity-related scholarships send a positive signal to employers; candidates with diversity merit scholarships are evaluated similarly to candidates without scholarships. Furthermore, while all applicants with non-diversity-related scholarships are more likely to receive a job interview than applicants without scholarships, the effect of this signal is larger for putatively White applicants than it is for putatively Black applicants. Additional evidence from the survey experiment suggest that these awards do not significantly influence perceptions of warmth and competence, but employers view non-diversity-related scholarships as more selective than diversity scholarships.     This project contributes to sociological knowledge on economic sociology, organizations, inequality, and race/ethnicity in several ways. First, by focusing on how employers interpret awards from other organizations, this project sheds insight on the interplay between organizational structures and individual actions in the production of racial discrimination. Second, this project contributes new evidence to existing research on cumulative advantage and school-to-work transitions. Finally, results from this project contribute to ongoing research in cultural sociology about the fluid definition of "diversity" in institutional settings, and how a diffuse understanding of diversity contributes to racial inequality.     Broader impacts of this project include significant implications for policy design and human resources development of a diverse workforce. Like organizations in other industries, many STEM organizations have recently made avowed commitments to diversity and created opportunity-enhancing programs like selective diversity scholarships and fellowships. Results from this project suggest that human resources development in STEM organizations, like those in other fields, should be careful about publicizing and presenting these diversity awards to avoid the devaluation of underrepresented minorities’ accomplishments. (Note that this project only investigated the reputational effects of such awards; other aspects of these awards, such as material support and mentoring, may have positive effects of their own.)          Last Modified: 11/01/2021       Submitted by: Jiayi J Xu]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
