<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Doctoral Dissertation Research: A Case Study of How Consumer Innovations Disrupt Markets]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>12972.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>12972</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joseph Whitmeyer</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jwhitmey@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927808</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This project studies the interaction between social movements and markets in the information technology (IT) sector.  Using the specific case of the adoption of free and open source software (FOSS) by the IT industry between 1998-2006, three processes are investigated: 1) the transition of FOSS from the fringes of the IT industry, to being the cornerstone of IT development; 2) the reconciliation in companies of market motives with the morality often connected with FOSS; 3) the cultural effects of FOSS on the IT industry.  Findings will increase understanding of the relationship between consumers, innovators, and large companies.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research questions will be investigated through analysis of primary and secondary documents associated both with the FOSS movement and the firms which first adopted the approach and through interviews.  A wide assortment of documents from various sources related to the history of FOSS, alongside white papers, advertising materials, and other documents produced by a key firm regarding its early involvement with FOSS, will be collected, categorized, and analyzed. Document analysis will be supplemented by 60 in-depth, semi-structured interviews of executives involved with FOSS, as well as participants in select FOSS projects.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/14/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/14/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2001834</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Akos</FirstName>
<LastName>Rona-tas</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>N</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Akos N Rona-tas</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[aronatas@ucsd.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000332582</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/14/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Davide</FirstName>
<LastName>Carpano</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Davide Carpano</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[dcarpano@ucsd.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000720222</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/14/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-San Diego</Name>
<CityName>LA JOLLA</CityName>
<ZipCode>920930021</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8585344896</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>9500 GILMAN DRIVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>50</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA50</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>UYTTZT6G9DT1</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, SAN DIEGO</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-San Diego]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>920930533</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>50</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA50</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1331</Code>
<Text>Sociology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~12972</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project analyzed the relationship between social movements and markets in the information technology (IT) sector. Through a detailed case study of IBM's adoption of free and open source software (FOSS) from 1998-2006 I demonstrate how IT companies embraced open systems and standards in the early 2000s. Aside from contributions to the fields of economic sociology and science and technology studies, this dissertation as implications for how we think about power in contemporary digital capitalism.<br /><br />While most research on corporate participation in FOSS highlights the extractive dynamics, in which companies seek out free labor, my case study demonstrates how IBM's embrace of the Linux operating system (a central FOSS project) followed a different logic. Rather than seeking to extract value from FOSS, IBM pioneered an approach to the movement through which they sought to influence the direction of Linux development through the mobilization of resources towards developing the operating system.<br /><br />My central finding is that corporate participation in FOSS is often carried out with the purpose of gaining logistical power to influence the formation of otherwise open standards. Instead of attempting to extract as much value from Linux with as little labor as possible, IBM poured billions of dollars into developing the operating system, reassigning and hiring thousands of developers in the process. This, I argue, was done in an attempt to shape the trajectory of Linux, which by the early 2000s was on its way to being the de facto standard operating across much of the Internet. <br /><br />My findings are relevant to recent debates regarding the power of big tech companies like Google and Amazon. While most policy debates focus on issues of antitrust, my research suggests that such actions alone cannot address the problems associated with corporate dominance of digital infrastructure that results from logistical power. Unless the privatization of this infrastructure is contested through the creation of public alternatives, antitrust action will likely only result in a rearranging of which private interests are able to attain the logistical power to influence the form that our digital infrastructures take.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/30/2023<br>      Modified by: Davide&nbsp;Carpano</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project analyzed the relationship between social movements and markets in the information technology (IT) sector. Through a detailed case study of IBM's adoption of free and open source software (FOSS) from 1998-2006 I demonstrate how IT companies embraced open systems and standards in the early 2000s. Aside from contributions to the fields of economic sociology and science and technology studies, this dissertation as implications for how we think about power in contemporary digital capitalism.  While most research on corporate participation in FOSS highlights the extractive dynamics, in which companies seek out free labor, my case study demonstrates how IBM's embrace of the Linux operating system (a central FOSS project) followed a different logic. Rather than seeking to extract value from FOSS, IBM pioneered an approach to the movement through which they sought to influence the direction of Linux development through the mobilization of resources towards developing the operating system.  My central finding is that corporate participation in FOSS is often carried out with the purpose of gaining logistical power to influence the formation of otherwise open standards. Instead of attempting to extract as much value from Linux with as little labor as possible, IBM poured billions of dollars into developing the operating system, reassigning and hiring thousands of developers in the process. This, I argue, was done in an attempt to shape the trajectory of Linux, which by the early 2000s was on its way to being the de facto standard operating across much of the Internet.   My findings are relevant to recent debates regarding the power of big tech companies like Google and Amazon. While most policy debates focus on issues of antitrust, my research suggests that such actions alone cannot address the problems associated with corporate dominance of digital infrastructure that results from logistical power. Unless the privatization of this infrastructure is contested through the creation of public alternatives, antitrust action will likely only result in a rearranging of which private interests are able to attain the logistical power to influence the form that our digital infrastructures take.       Last Modified: 04/30/2023       Submitted by: Davide Carpano]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
