<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Dynamic Duos: Supermassive Black Hole Pairs in Galaxy Mergers]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>300000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>255669</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AST</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Andrea Prestwich</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>aprestwi@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922210</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Michael Tremmel is awarded an NSF Astronomy and Astrophysics Postdoctoral Fellowship to conduct a program of research and education at Yale University.  He will perform large-scale cosmological simulations to study how pairs of supermassive black holes (SMBH) are formed during the merger of two galaxies.  The simulations will predict observational electromagnetic signatures of galaxy mergers and identify how galaxy formation and mergers are related to the growth of SMBHs.  Along with this research, Tremmel will provide an interactive research experience in computational astrophysics to local high school students who are traditionally underrepresented in science.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;High-resolution simulations performed in this project will include a new physical model and a powerful new algorithm to identify the connections between the assembly history of galaxies and their coevolution with SMBHs.  Using two complementary simulation suites, the project will investigate how the masses and mass ratios of galaxy mergers are related to the evolution of SMBHs, as well as the early accretion and merger histories of massive halos and the long term coevolution of their central galaxies and SMBHs.  Results from this project will allow astronomers to understand how galaxy assembly influences SMBH formation.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/28/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/04/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2001810</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Tremmel</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael J Tremmel</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<NSF_ID>000733207</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/28/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Tremmel                 Michael        J</Name>
<CityName>New Haven</CityName>
<ZipCode>065208101</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CT03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Yale University]]></Name>
<CityName>New Haven</CityName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>065208120</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CT03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1609</Code>
<Text>NSF ASTRON &amp; ASTROPHY PSTDC FE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1206</Code>
<Text>THEORETICAL &amp; COMPUTATIONAL ASTROPHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002223DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~100000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~100000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2022~55669</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>During this project, I implemented an updated model for the evolution of massive black holes (&gt;10^5 solar masses) into high resolution galaxy simulations. These simulations came in two flavors: a Milky Way-mass galaxy and a low mass (dwarf) galaxy in the early Universe. Both sets of simulations were run multiple times to test the effect of different physics models for massive black holes. We also used the genetic modification technique to manipulare each galaxy's formation history. For the Mikly Way, we changed the final mass of the galaxy, and for the dwarf galaxy we changed the properties of a major merger event .</p> <p>Preliminary results from these simulations are incredibly interesting. In the Milky Way mass galaxy, we find that the black hole growth history has a strong dependence on both black hole model and galaxy mass. We also find that the early evolution of black holes is critically important. These are some of the only simulations that model the formation of massive black holes at very early times based entirely on the local gas properties. The black holes form at low masses in small proto-galaxies before any stars form. But, at early times, those galaxies have a rather chaotic life, experiencing many merger events and it is likely that the black holes get perturbed away from the centers of their forming host galaxy. Because they are so small and the early formation of galaxies is so messy, it ends up being very difficult for these black holes to find their way back to the center. Further, the gas in these galaxies has a lot of structure, so while at low resolution the black holes near the center of galaxies are able to grow happily, at higher resolution black holes require chance encounters with small, dense clouds of gas which occur much more rarely. Together these findings solidify a growing problem in the community: growing low mass black holes at early times is even more difficult than we thought as we get better at resolving galaxies.</p> <p>The dwarf galaxy simulations have also produced very interesting results. Again, the growth history of black holes is very dependent on the details of the black hole model. Unexpectedly, we find that gas within these galaxies quickly develops significant rotation. We also find that the growth of black holes can be significantly suppressed by supernovae explosions removing gas from the centers of galaxies. Finally, we find that the timing and mass of the merger is important. A larger mass ratio (more similar mass galaxies) results in quicker black hole mergers, but not necessarily more black hole growth. Earlier mergers, don't necessarily result in earlier black hole mergers, rather we found the early merger case to produce a forever-wandering black hole that never merges with its partner. Similar to the higher mass galaxy simulations, this is due to very early evolution of the black hole host galaxy which undergoes a merger that kicks its black hole off center at early times and it never recovers. These results also show that the properties of merging galaxies can have important impacts on the evolution of binary black holes. Black holes that form binaries a few hundred million years apart will be evolving in drastically different environments. These mergers, we predict, are also taking place within cored dark matter halos. During the merger event, star formation events result in many supernovae explosions which cause dark matter to be redistributed in galaxies. These lower density cores mean that the black hole dynamical evolution might be slower, potentially decreasing the merger rate we'd expect.</p> <p>During this project I also developed an educational program for high school students in the New Haven, CT, area through Yale's Pathways to Science Program. Students got to explore real galaxy simulation data and answer science questions like "where do you find the biggest black holes" and "what happens to galaxies in different environments". This was the first such course in the program to feature computational astrophysics as a theme.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/10/2023<br>      Modified by: Michael&nbsp;J&nbsp;Tremmel</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2001810/2001810_10673268_1683723137332_MergerSim_GM_BHDynamics--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2001810/2001810_10673268_1683723137332_MergerSim_GM_BHDynamics--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Genetically Modified Dwarf Galaxy Mergers"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2001810/2001810_10673268_1683723137332_MergerSim_GM_BHDynamics--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Genetically Modified Dwarf Galaxy Mergers"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">We selected a galaxy merger taking place when the Universe was ~1 Billion years old and re-ran it at very high resolution. We then used a numerical technique called Genetic Modification to manipulate the mass and timing of the merger to study the effect on the evolution of massive black hole pairs</div> <div class="imageCredit">Michael Tremmel</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Michael&nbsp;J&nbsp;Tremmel</div> <div class="imageTitle">Genetically Modified Dwarf Galaxy Mergers</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ During this project, I implemented an updated model for the evolution of massive black holes (&gt;10^5 solar masses) into high resolution galaxy simulations. These simulations came in two flavors: a Milky Way-mass galaxy and a low mass (dwarf) galaxy in the early Universe. Both sets of simulations were run multiple times to test the effect of different physics models for massive black holes. We also used the genetic modification technique to manipulare each galaxy's formation history. For the Mikly Way, we changed the final mass of the galaxy, and for the dwarf galaxy we changed the properties of a major merger event .  Preliminary results from these simulations are incredibly interesting. In the Milky Way mass galaxy, we find that the black hole growth history has a strong dependence on both black hole model and galaxy mass. We also find that the early evolution of black holes is critically important. These are some of the only simulations that model the formation of massive black holes at very early times based entirely on the local gas properties. The black holes form at low masses in small proto-galaxies before any stars form. But, at early times, those galaxies have a rather chaotic life, experiencing many merger events and it is likely that the black holes get perturbed away from the centers of their forming host galaxy. Because they are so small and the early formation of galaxies is so messy, it ends up being very difficult for these black holes to find their way back to the center. Further, the gas in these galaxies has a lot of structure, so while at low resolution the black holes near the center of galaxies are able to grow happily, at higher resolution black holes require chance encounters with small, dense clouds of gas which occur much more rarely. Together these findings solidify a growing problem in the community: growing low mass black holes at early times is even more difficult than we thought as we get better at resolving galaxies.  The dwarf galaxy simulations have also produced very interesting results. Again, the growth history of black holes is very dependent on the details of the black hole model. Unexpectedly, we find that gas within these galaxies quickly develops significant rotation. We also find that the growth of black holes can be significantly suppressed by supernovae explosions removing gas from the centers of galaxies. Finally, we find that the timing and mass of the merger is important. A larger mass ratio (more similar mass galaxies) results in quicker black hole mergers, but not necessarily more black hole growth. Earlier mergers, don't necessarily result in earlier black hole mergers, rather we found the early merger case to produce a forever-wandering black hole that never merges with its partner. Similar to the higher mass galaxy simulations, this is due to very early evolution of the black hole host galaxy which undergoes a merger that kicks its black hole off center at early times and it never recovers. These results also show that the properties of merging galaxies can have important impacts on the evolution of binary black holes. Black holes that form binaries a few hundred million years apart will be evolving in drastically different environments. These mergers, we predict, are also taking place within cored dark matter halos. During the merger event, star formation events result in many supernovae explosions which cause dark matter to be redistributed in galaxies. These lower density cores mean that the black hole dynamical evolution might be slower, potentially decreasing the merger rate we'd expect.  During this project I also developed an educational program for high school students in the New Haven, CT, area through Yale's Pathways to Science Program. Students got to explore real galaxy simulation data and answer science questions like "where do you find the biggest black holes" and "what happens to galaxies in different environments". This was the first such course in the program to feature computational astrophysics as a theme.       Last Modified: 05/10/2023       Submitted by: Michael J Tremmel]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
