<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research: Digitization PEN: Expanding and enhancing the California Phenology TCN]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>12346.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>12346</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DBI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Reed Beaman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rsbeaman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927163</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Flowering time is an important biological phenomenon, affecting human societies through its effects on agricultural crops, pollinators, pests, and biodiversity. Given the sensitivity of flowering times to climatic conditions, a thorough understanding of how plants respond to changing environments is necessary for predicting the consequences for pollinators, herbivores, parasites, and plant populations. A record of historical flowering times is found within the nation's herbaria – collections of dried and pressed plants. In 2018, the California Phenology Thematic Collections Network (CAP-TCN) was established to advance our understanding of flowering time changes over time. The network brought together 22 California universities, research stations, natural history collections, and botanical gardens, with the goal of imaging and recording the flowering status of approximately one million herbarium specimens collected over the past 150 years. These data are freely available through the newly established Consortium of California Herbaria (CCH2) portal. This project will add a partnership of seven new collections and six new institutions to the CAP-TCN, contributing an additional 150,000 herbarium specimens. The project participants will be fully integrated into CAP-TCN training and outreach activities including Notes from Nature online expeditions, which educate and involve members of the public in learning about herbarium specimens and flowering phenology. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;By expanding the geographic scope to encompass Oregon and the northern Baja California peninsula, the CAP-TCN will now cover the entire California Floristic Province, a biodiversity hotspot of global significance. This will increase the number of species with imaged specimens across their entire range from 1,217 to 1,850, a 55% increase. The addition of 80,000 Oregon and Baja California specimens to CCH2 will facilitate efficient specimen-based analyses of the entire California Floristic Province and for the first time allow a more objective and reproducible specimen-based delineation of its geographic boundaries. Three institutions in California and Nevada will fill key geographic gaps for northwestern California, the northern San Joaquin Valley, and the Mojave Desert. Two additional institutions will significantly increase CAP-TCN representation of 1) the ecologically important and taxonomically complex genus Arctostaphylos (manzanita); and 2) introduced and invasive species of importance to California agriculture, rangelands, and native ecosystems. An estimated 25 additional undergraduates will participate in digitizing activities. Ongoing public outreach efforts about the floras of Oregon and Baja California at Oregon State University and the San Diego Natural History Museum will also benefit from the newly imaged specimens.  Data will be shared through online resources, including iDigBio.org.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/22/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/22/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2001535</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jon</FirstName>
<LastName>Rebman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jon P Rebman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jrebman@sdnhm.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000301560</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/22/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Layla</FirstName>
<LastName>Aerne Hains</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Layla Aerne Hains</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[laerne@sdnhm.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000705240</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/22/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>San Diego Society of Natural History</Name>
<CityName>SAN DIEGO</CityName>
<ZipCode>921011624</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6192550216</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1788 EL PRADO</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>50</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA50</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>SRMEDYXMNF53</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>THE SAN DIEGO SOCIETY OF NATURAL HISTORY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[San Diego Natural History Museum]]></Name>
<CityName>San Diego</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>921121390</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[P.O. Box 121390]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>50</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA50</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6895</Code>
<Text>Digitization</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>6895</Code>
<Text>DIGITIZATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~12346</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><div class="OutlineElement Ltr SCXW186346573 BCX0"> <p class="Paragraph SCXW186346573 BCX0" lang="EN-US" xml:lang="EN-US"><span class="TextRun SCXW186346573 BCX0" lang="EN-US" xml:lang="EN-US"><span class="NormalTextRun SCXW186346573 BCX0">The </span><span class="NormalTextRun SCXW186346573 BCX0">overall </span><span class="NormalTextRun SCXW186346573 BCX0">goal of the </span><span class="NormalTextRun SCXW186346573 BCX0">California Phenology PEN project is to image 148,180 herbarium specimens collected in the California Floristic Province and housed at six west coast herbaria. The project adds six new collaborators to the California Phenology (CAP) TCN and fills important digitization gaps across the floristic province. The project aims to transcribe full label data for 22,200 specimens and georeference 36,000 specimens</span><span class="NormalTextRun SCXW186346573 BCX0"> </span><span class="NormalTextRun SCXW186346573 BCX0">Th</span><span class="NormalTextRun SCXW186346573 BCX0">is project supports the </span><span class="NormalTextRun SCXW186346573 BCX0">goal of </span><span class="NormalTextRun SCXW186346573 BCX0">the original CAP TCN</span><span class="NormalTextRun SCXW186346573 BCX0"> &nbsp;to initiate a massive imaging effort that will increase our understanding of the direction and magnitude of phenological shifts of California&rsquo;s flora. </span></span><span class="EOP SCXW186346573 BCX0">&nbsp;</span></p> </div> <div class="OutlineElement Ltr SCXW186346573 BCX0"> <p class="Paragraph SCXW186346573 BCX0" lang="EN-US" xml:lang="EN-US"><span class="TextRun SCXW186346573 BCX0" lang="EN-US" xml:lang="EN-US"><span class="NormalTextRun SCXW186346573 BCX0">The goal of the SD Herbarium (SD)&nbsp;</span><span class="NormalTextRun SCXW186346573 BCX0">was</span><span class="NormalTextRun SCXW186346573 BCX0"> to image 15,000 herbarium specimens from Baja California in addition to the 2018 TCN goals. SD has achieved our imaging goal by imaging </span><span class="NormalTextRun SCXW186346573 BCX0">over 50,000</span><span class="NormalTextRun SCXW186346573 BCX0">&nbsp;specimens over the past 3 years, including 13,</span><span class="NormalTextRun SCXW186346573 BCX0">35</span><span class="NormalTextRun SCXW186346573 BCX0">6 specimens from Baja California.</span></span><span class="EOP SCXW186346573 BCX0">&nbsp;</span></p> </div> <div class="OutlineElement Ltr SCXW186346573 BCX0"> <p class="Paragraph SCXW186346573 BCX0"><span class="TextRun SCXW186346573 BCX0" lang="EN-US" xml:lang="EN-US"><span class="NormalTextRun SCXW186346573 BCX0">SD has disseminated results of this project through </span><span class="NormalTextRun SCXW186346573 BCX0">Member&rsquo;s Open House, several behind the scenes tours, and numerous curator talks in which we have been able to highlight the project to museum members, donors and the genera</span><span class="NormalTextRun SCXW186346573 BCX0">l public. </span></span><span class="TextRun SCXW186346573 BCX0" lang="EN-US" xml:lang="EN-US"><span class="NormalTextRun SCXW186346573 BCX0">According to GBIF, our data have been cited </span><span class="NormalTextRun SCXW186346573 BCX0">over 500</span><span class="NormalTextRun SCXW186346573 BCX0"> times since October 2019, including publications in the topics of species distribution modeling, phylogeography, ecophysiology, and climate change biology. This diversity of uses illustrates the wide utility of our data for the broader community, science, and society.</span></span><span class="EOP SCXW186346573 BCX0">&nbsp;</span></p> </div> <div class="OutlineElement Ltr SCXW186346573 BCX0"> <p class="Paragraph SCXW186346573 BCX0" lang="EN-US" xml:lang="EN-US"><span class="TextRun SCXW186346573 BCX0" lang="EN-US" xml:lang="EN-US">The images and associated data that we are producing through this project are essential for understanding shifts in flowering and fruiting times under climate change. For example, research on California poppy phenology by Pearson et al. (2021) used spatiotemporal and phenological data from over 290 SD specimens (https://doi.org/10.3120/0024-9637-68.4.343). This information will be used by climate scientists, botanists, ecologists, agronomists, farmers, and land managers to predict and prepare for effects of future plant phenological responses to climate.</span><span class="EOP SCXW186346573 BCX0">&nbsp;</span></p> </div> <div class="OutlineElement Ltr SCXW186346573 BCX0"> <p class="Paragraph SCXW186346573 BCX0"><span class="TextRun SCXW186346573 BCX0" lang="EN-US" xml:lang="EN-US"><span class="NormalTextRun SCXW186346573 BCX0">The SD Herbarium has long maintained webpages </span><span class="NormalTextRun SCXW186346573 BCX0">(bajaflora.org, sdplantatlas.org) </span><span class="NormalTextRun SCXW186346573 BCX0">which allowed access to the specimen data from certain regions where we focus our research and our involvement in the Consortium of California Herbaria help facilitate access to specimen data from across California. Our participation in this project allows us to make specimen data from our entire collection accessible and a large percentage of the collection will have images by the end of the project. </span><span class="NormalTextRun SCXW186346573 BCX0"> </span></span><span class="EOP SCXW186346573 BCX0">&nbsp;</span></p> </div> <div class="OutlineElement Ltr SCXW186346573 BCX0"> <p class="Paragraph SCXW186346573 BCX0"><span class="TextRun SCXW186346573 BCX0" lang="EN-US" xml:lang="EN-US"><span class="NormalTextRun SCXW186346573 BCX0">Over the course of the original TCN and the PEN, i</span><span class="NormalTextRun SCXW186346573 BCX0">maging </span><span class="NormalTextRun SCXW186346573 BCX0">approximately</span><span class="NormalTextRun SCXW186346573 BCX0">&nbsp;</span><span class="NormalTextRun SCXW186346573 BCX0">80,000</span><span class="NormalTextRun SCXW186346573 BCX0">&nbsp;specimens of the SD herbarium has provided a critical resource for botanical researchers and educators. Some of SD&rsquo;s specimens date back to the mid-1800s and are found in under-collected and often difficult-to-reach regions. SD&rsquo;s collections are particularly rich in southern California and </span><span class="NormalTextRun SCXW186346573 BCX0">northwestern </span><span class="NormalTextRun SCXW186346573 BCX0">Mexico, which are diverse regions with many endemic species. These data are being used by a broad community of researchers.&nbsp;</span></span><span class="EOP SCXW186346573 BCX0">&nbsp;</span></p> </div><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/27/2023<br>      Modified by: Layla&nbsp;Aerne Hains</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The overall goal of the California Phenology PEN project is to image 148,180 herbarium specimens collected in the California Floristic Province and housed at six west coast herbaria. The project adds six new collaborators to the California Phenology (CAP) TCN and fills important digitization gaps across the floristic province. The project aims to transcribe full label data for 22,200 specimens and georeference 36,000 specimens This project supports the goal of the original CAP TCN  to initiate a massive imaging effort that will increase our understanding of the direction and magnitude of phenological shifts of California’s flora.     The goal of the SD Herbarium (SD) was to image 15,000 herbarium specimens from Baja California in addition to the 2018 TCN goals. SD has achieved our imaging goal by imaging over 50,000 specimens over the past 3 years, including 13,356 specimens from Baja California.    SD has disseminated results of this project through Member’s Open House, several behind the scenes tours, and numerous curator talks in which we have been able to highlight the project to museum members, donors and the general public. According to GBIF, our data have been cited over 500 times since October 2019, including publications in the topics of species distribution modeling, phylogeography, ecophysiology, and climate change biology. This diversity of uses illustrates the wide utility of our data for the broader community, science, and society.    The images and associated data that we are producing through this project are essential for understanding shifts in flowering and fruiting times under climate change. For example, research on California poppy phenology by Pearson et al. (2021) used spatiotemporal and phenological data from over 290 SD specimens (https://doi.org/10.3120/0024-9637-68.4.343). This information will be used by climate scientists, botanists, ecologists, agronomists, farmers, and land managers to predict and prepare for effects of future plant phenological responses to climate.    The SD Herbarium has long maintained webpages (bajaflora.org, sdplantatlas.org) which allowed access to the specimen data from certain regions where we focus our research and our involvement in the Consortium of California Herbaria help facilitate access to specimen data from across California. Our participation in this project allows us to make specimen data from our entire collection accessible and a large percentage of the collection will have images by the end of the project.      Over the course of the original TCN and the PEN, imaging approximately 80,000 specimens of the SD herbarium has provided a critical resource for botanical researchers and educators. Some of SD’s specimens date back to the mid-1800s and are found in under-collected and often difficult-to-reach regions. SD’s collections are particularly rich in southern California and northwestern Mexico, which are diverse regions with many endemic species. These data are being used by a broad community of researchers.          Last Modified: 09/27/2023       Submitted by: Layla Aerne Hains]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
