<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research: Understanding the Evolution of High-latitude Permo-Triassic Paleoenvironments and their Vertebrate Communities.]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/27/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>61286.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>61286</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06090300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OPP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Polar Programs (OPP)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Michael E. Jackson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mejackso@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927120</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Around 252 million years ago, a major mass extinction wiped out upwards of 90% of species on Earth.  Coincident with this extinction, the Antarctic portion of the supercontinent of Pangea transitioned to a warmer climatic regime and became devoid of glaciers.  Little is known about the survivors of the extinction in Antarctica, although it has been hypothesized that the continent?s more polar location shielded it from the worst of the extinction?s effects.  The Shackleton Glacier region is the best place to study this extinction in Antarctica because it exposes the correct age rocks in abundance and relevant fossils were found there in the 1960s and 1980s.  For this research, paleontologists will study fossil vertebrates that span from about 260?240 million years ago to understand how life evolved at high latitudes in the face of massive climate change.  In addition, geologists will use fossil soils and fossil plant matter to more precisely understand the climate of Antarctica across this extinction boundary.  These data will allow for a more complete understanding of ancient climates and how Antarctic life compared to that at lower latitudes.  Undergraduate and graduate students will be actively involved in this research.  Public engagement in Antarctic science will be accomplished at several natural history museums.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This three-year project will examine the evolution of Permo-Triassic paleoenvironments and their vertebrate communities by conducting fieldwork in the Shackleton Glacier region of Antarctica.  The team will characterize the Permo-Triassic boundary within Shackleton area strata and correlate it to other stratigraphic successions in the region (e.g. via stable carbon isotope stratigraphy of fossilized plant organic matter).  The researchers will use multiple types of data to assess the paleoenvironment, including: 1) paleosol morphology; 2) paleosol geochemistry; 3) pedogenic organic matter; and 4) fossil wood chronology and stable isotopes.  The Fremouw Formation of Antarctica preserves the highest paleolatitude (~70° S) tetrapod fauna of the entire Triassic and thus has the potential to shed important light on the evolution of polar life during the early Mesozoic.  The biology of Triassic vertebrates from Antarctica will be compared to conspecifics from lower paleolatitudes through analysis of growth in bone and tusk histology.  An interdisciplinary approach will be used to address relationships between environmental change, faunal composition, and biogeographic patterns in the context of the high-latitude strata preserved in the Buckley and Fremouw formations in the Shackleton Glacier region.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/04/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/04/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.078</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2001033</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
<LastName>Makovicky</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Peter J Makovicky</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[pmakovicky@fieldmuseum.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000233097</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/04/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Minnesota-Twin Cities</Name>
<CityName>MINNEAPOLIS</CityName>
<ZipCode>554552009</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6126245599</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>200 OAK ST SE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>KABJZBBJ4B54</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MINNESOTA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Minnesota-Twin Cities]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>554552070</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5112</Code>
<Text>ANT Earth Sciences</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>02XX</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>0100XXXXDB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~61286</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Early Triassic (252-247 million years ago) marks a period of recovery from the largest recorded mass extinction in Earth history, driven by massive volcanism and associated release of climate-altering volatiles and gasses. Early Triassic terrestrial vertebrate faunas from around the world are broadly similar with low species diversity and few species larger than 100 kg. Fossil assemblages from different regions have traditionally been interpreted as a single 'global' post-extinction fauna. However, this interpretation has been largely driven by comparisons between regional faunas from the Early Triassic of South Africa and Russia, with much less information available for other regions. A region of particular interest is Antarctica, which represents the highest latitude fauna preserved from that time. Although initially regarded as identical to contemporaneous well-sampled South African faunas, recent research by members of our research team has indicated compositional differences between the faunas in these regions.</p> <p>This project set out to increase our knowledge of the poorly known vertebrate fossil fauna of the Early Triassic of Antarctica, and to better understand the environments these animals lived in. Key questions include determining if Antarctic faunas include unique, endemic species and environmental differences can explain patterns of species diversity and faunal differences between different, latitudinally separated regions of Pangea. Another goal was to examine whether are differences in the paleobiology of widespread species at higher versus lower latitude regions of Pangea during the Early Triassic as observed in some living species.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Fieldwork during the austral summer of 2017-18 in Transantarctic Mountains resulted in the collection of over 200 fossils including vertebrate skeletal material, trackways, and plants from the Lower Triassic Fremouw Formation. This collection represents a significant improvement in our knowledge of Antarctic Traissic fossil faunas, both in terms of quantity and quality. Critical stratigraphic and geochemical data providing temporal and environmental contexts to the fossils were also collected to allow finer scale comparisons with faunas regionally and globally. All fossils have been reposited at public museums and are currently under preparation and/ or study. Papers have been published identifying new species unique to Antarctica, others that are shared with the South African faunas, and reinterpreting and correcting historical records. Research to reconstruct the physiology and growth of Antarctic vertebrates and contrast them to members of the same genus or species from lower latitude faunas are underway, and will incorporate environmental information currently being analyzed by other team members.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;This award has had tremendous public outreach and educational footprint, reaching millions of people. Content in the form of fossils, video and photographs, and narratives derived from the fieldwork were incorporated into the traveling museum exhibit ?Antarctic Dinosaurs? produced by the Field Museum in partnership with three other institutions. This immersive 7500 square foot exhibit featuring real fossils, reconstructions, historical artifacts, and physical and digital interactives is currently at its sixth venue and has been seen by close to a million visitors. Our Antarctic fieldwork and its results, and interviews with PIs, were featured in the Omnimax/IMAX film ?Dinosaurs of Antarctica? co-produced by NSF through an AISL grant, and currently reaching audiences at dozens of museums, science centers, and theaters around the world. Both the exhibit and the movie provided numerous opportunities for PIs to engage directly with lay audiences through lectures and other informal programming. Media and data from this project are regularly incorporated by PIs in teaching university courses on Earth history and paleontology, and undergraduate and graduate students and post-docs have gained research experience on the collected fossils.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/28/2022<br>      Modified by: Peter&nbsp;J&nbsp;Makovicky</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2001033/2001033_10456782_1659027668348_Grant_report_pix--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2001033/2001033_10456782_1659027668348_Grant_report_pix--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Fossils from the Early Triassic of Antarctica"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2001033/2001033_10456782_1659027668348_Grant_report_pix--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Fossils from the Early Triassic of Antarctica"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">A) Partial skeleton of Lystrosaurus sp. B) Complete skeleton of Lystrosaurus cf. murrayi. C) Partial skeleton of Thrinaxodon liorhinus. These fossils will be sample histologically and compared to conspecific specimens from South Africa to investigate latitudinal differences in growth and paleobiolog</div> <div class="imageCredit">P. Makovicky</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Peter&nbsp;J&nbsp;Makovicky</div> <div class="imageTitle">Fossils from the Early Triassic of Antarctica</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2001033/2001033_10456782_1659028535551_IMG_6884(1)--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2001033/2001033_10456782_1659028535551_IMG_6884(1)--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Panoramic view of &quot;Antarctic Dinosaurs&quot; exhibit at Field Museum."><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2001033/2001033_10456782_1659028535551_IMG_6884(1)--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Panoramic view of &quot;Antarctic Dinosaurs&quot; exhibit at Field Museum."></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">This 7500 square foot exhibit features real fossils, skeletal reconstructions and life dioramas of Antarctic fossil species, as shown here. Historical artifacts, and physical and digital interactives round out the immersive visitor experience.</div> <div class="imageCredit">P. Makovicky</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Peter&nbsp;J&nbsp;Makovicky</div> <div class="imageTitle">Panoramic view of "Antarctic Dinosaurs" exhibit at Field Museum.</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2001033/2001033_10456782_1659029448470_PetesawingatThrinaxodonsite--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2001033/2001033_10456782_1659029448470_PetesawingatThrinaxodonsite--rgov-800width.jpg" title="P. Makovicky collecting a Lystrosaurus fossil."><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2001033/2001033_10456782_1659029448470_PetesawingatThrinaxodonsite--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="P. Makovicky collecting a Lystrosaurus fossil."></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">This site produced several Thrinaxodon specimens in 1970 and also in 2018. It also yields the common anomodont Lystrosaurus being collected here. Contact metamorphism has hardened the sedimentary rocks, necessitating use of power tools.</div> <div class="imageCredit">A. Shinya</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Peter&nbsp;J&nbsp;Makovicky</div> <div class="imageTitle">P. Makovicky collecting a Lystrosaurus fossil.</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Early Triassic (252-247 million years ago) marks a period of recovery from the largest recorded mass extinction in Earth history, driven by massive volcanism and associated release of climate-altering volatiles and gasses. Early Triassic terrestrial vertebrate faunas from around the world are broadly similar with low species diversity and few species larger than 100 kg. Fossil assemblages from different regions have traditionally been interpreted as a single 'global' post-extinction fauna. However, this interpretation has been largely driven by comparisons between regional faunas from the Early Triassic of South Africa and Russia, with much less information available for other regions. A region of particular interest is Antarctica, which represents the highest latitude fauna preserved from that time. Although initially regarded as identical to contemporaneous well-sampled South African faunas, recent research by members of our research team has indicated compositional differences between the faunas in these regions.  This project set out to increase our knowledge of the poorly known vertebrate fossil fauna of the Early Triassic of Antarctica, and to better understand the environments these animals lived in. Key questions include determining if Antarctic faunas include unique, endemic species and environmental differences can explain patterns of species diversity and faunal differences between different, latitudinally separated regions of Pangea. Another goal was to examine whether are differences in the paleobiology of widespread species at higher versus lower latitude regions of Pangea during the Early Triassic as observed in some living species.              Fieldwork during the austral summer of 2017-18 in Transantarctic Mountains resulted in the collection of over 200 fossils including vertebrate skeletal material, trackways, and plants from the Lower Triassic Fremouw Formation. This collection represents a significant improvement in our knowledge of Antarctic Traissic fossil faunas, both in terms of quantity and quality. Critical stratigraphic and geochemical data providing temporal and environmental contexts to the fossils were also collected to allow finer scale comparisons with faunas regionally and globally. All fossils have been reposited at public museums and are currently under preparation and/ or study. Papers have been published identifying new species unique to Antarctica, others that are shared with the South African faunas, and reinterpreting and correcting historical records. Research to reconstruct the physiology and growth of Antarctic vertebrates and contrast them to members of the same genus or species from lower latitude faunas are underway, and will incorporate environmental information currently being analyzed by other team members.              This award has had tremendous public outreach and educational footprint, reaching millions of people. Content in the form of fossils, video and photographs, and narratives derived from the fieldwork were incorporated into the traveling museum exhibit ?Antarctic Dinosaurs? produced by the Field Museum in partnership with three other institutions. This immersive 7500 square foot exhibit featuring real fossils, reconstructions, historical artifacts, and physical and digital interactives is currently at its sixth venue and has been seen by close to a million visitors. Our Antarctic fieldwork and its results, and interviews with PIs, were featured in the Omnimax/IMAX film ?Dinosaurs of Antarctica? co-produced by NSF through an AISL grant, and currently reaching audiences at dozens of museums, science centers, and theaters around the world. Both the exhibit and the movie provided numerous opportunities for PIs to engage directly with lay audiences through lectures and other informal programming. Media and data from this project are regularly incorporated by PIs in teaching university courses on Earth history and paleontology, and undergraduate and graduate students and post-docs have gained research experience on the collected fossils.             Last Modified: 07/28/2022       Submitted by: Peter J Makovicky]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
