<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[2020 Bioinspired Materials GRC/GRS]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>20000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>20000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Abraham Joy</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ajoy@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922913</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[1. Non technical abstract.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Bioinspired materials are materials that are designed or assembled using the inspiration of biology as a guide. Biological systems have developed exquisite ways of assembling functional materials to achieve goals such as sensing, secretion, motion, and response. In the field of Bioinspired Materials, scientists from many different backgrounds use chemistry, biochemistry, materials science and mathematics to design new materials that have the structure of biological systems, but which can achieve new goals, such as motion or communication.&lt;br/&gt;The goal of the proposed work is to sponsor a meeting as part of the Gordon Reseeacrh Conferences on Bioinspired Materials. The meeting will be held in Les Diablerets, Switzerland, June 7-12, 2020. A significant number of the participants will be U.S. researchers, and 2/3 of the meeting partcipants are early stage investigators (graduate students, postdoctoral associates, and early stage professors). Gordon Research Conferences are week-long immersive experiences in which cutting edge, unpublished science is presented, with long question and answer periods, poster sessions, discussion of science over meals, and social engagement between sessions. This particular meeting will also have a Gordon Research Seminar, two days before the main meeting, for solely graduate students and postdoctoral associates to present their work, and a Power Hour, dedicated to discussion the main challenges for women in science. In all, the meeting is designed to address the important ideas and concepts in the field of Bioinspired Materials by international leaders in the field, with significant participation by a new generation of scientists.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;2. Technical Abstract.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The emerging, interdisciplinary field of Bioinspired Materials focuses on developing a fundamental understanding of the synthesis, directed self-assembly and hierarchical organization of natural occurring materials, and uses this understanding to design new synthetic materials whose structure, properties and function and response mimic those of natural materials or living matter. The fundamental concepts behind bioinspired design are becoming increasingly integrated into a wide range of materials and devices intended for the industrial, biological, medical, military and energy sectors, and represent a core focus of research activity of several programs at NSF. Planned sessions include Protocell Engineering (both a Keynote and an Early Career Investigator session), Novel Membrane Design, Active Matter and Motility, Membraneless Organelles, Functional Bioinspired Assemblies, Peptide &amp; Protein Assembly, Tissues &amp; Organoids, and Immune Engineering. These are important current concepts in biomaterials that are at the forefront of our discipline. The meeting will focus on the fundamental challenges of the design of bioinspired materials.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This proposal is to support the registration of 37 participants in the Gordon Research Conference on Bioinspired Materials. The format and structure of the GRC is designed for immersion of scientists into new and emerging concepts in Biomaterials Science – with an emphasis on breaking results and unpublished data - through long question and answer periods, interactive discussion, significant poster sessions and social activities between sessions. This particular meeting will also have a Gordon Research Seminar, two days before the main meeting, for solely graduate students and post-doctoral associates to present their work, and a Power Hour on “Strategies for leveling the playing field for the advancement of women in science,” dedicated to a discussion on the main challenges for women in science. The emphasis on early stage investigators and underrepresented groups will significantly enhance the broader impact of this meeting.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/21/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/21/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2001234</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
<LastName>Hammer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Daniel A Hammer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[hammer@seas.upenn.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000187747</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/21/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Gordon Research Conferences</Name>
<CityName>EAST GREENWICH</CityName>
<ZipCode>028183454</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4017834011</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5586 POST RD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[UNIT 2]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>RI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>XL5ANMKWN557</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GORDON RESEARCH CONFERENCES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Gordon Research Conferences]]></Name>
<CityName>West Kingston</CityName>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>028921502</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[512 Liberty Lane]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>RI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1710</Code>
<Text>CONDENSED MATTER PHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7623</Code>
<Text>BIOMATERIALS PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7623</Code>
<Text>BIOMATERIALS PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~20000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>The emerging, interdisciplinary field of Bioinspired Materials focuses on developing a fundamental understanding of the synthesis, directed self-assembly, and hierarchical organization of naturally occurring and synthetic materials that mimic and manipulate biological systems. A diverse array of bioinspired materials was discussed, ranging from lipid and synthetic membranes, peptides and proteins, tailored dynamic active matter, protein condensates, and polymer-cell hybrids that mimic functional tissues. Speakers described how these materials could be used to engineer materials for diverse applications ranging from the development of artificial membranes and synthetic cells (protocells), the systematic delivery of therapeutics, the assembly of functional organoids, and the design of materials that can manipulate the immune system intelligently.</span></p> <p><span>The 2022 meeting was postponed from 2020 due to the COVID-19 pandemic. By mutual agreement among the meeting chair and co-chairs, we tried to carry forward the same themes and speakers from the 2020 meeting. This meeting emphasized early stage investigators, and provided an open and inclusive environment for the exchange of ideas, with vibrant poster sessions from which short talks were selected. The meeting was preceded by a Gordon Research Seminar for graduate students and postdoctoral associates to present their work to each other before the conference, as well as a Power Hour to address the challenges that women encounter in developing their independent careers.</span></p> <p><span>The Gordon Research Seminar on Bioinspired Materials was a unique forum for graduate students and post-docs to not only present and discuss their unpublished cutting edge research but also network and build collaborations with colleagues with a shared interest in bioinspired materials.&nbsp;</span><span><br /></span><span>We invited all applications that are related to the design or application of synthetic or natural materials for diverse applications. We attracted a diverse, multidisciplinary field of presenters that addressed both fundamental understanding and practical applications of such biological and bioinspired materials. The 2022 GRS meeting consisted of a presentation by a distinguished scientist followed by GRS attendee presentations and discussions on research in the field of bioinspired materials. The GRS hosted informal poster sessions that facilitated stimulating discussions and exchange of ideas. To conclude the meeting, we had a mentorship panel to give participants more insight into the potential career opportunities and diversity in research within this field of science.</span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/03/2023<br>      Modified by: Daniel&nbsp;A&nbsp;Hammer</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The emerging, interdisciplinary field of Bioinspired Materials focuses on developing a fundamental understanding of the synthesis, directed self-assembly, and hierarchical organization of naturally occurring and synthetic materials that mimic and manipulate biological systems. A diverse array of bioinspired materials was discussed, ranging from lipid and synthetic membranes, peptides and proteins, tailored dynamic active matter, protein condensates, and polymer-cell hybrids that mimic functional tissues. Speakers described how these materials could be used to engineer materials for diverse applications ranging from the development of artificial membranes and synthetic cells (protocells), the systematic delivery of therapeutics, the assembly of functional organoids, and the design of materials that can manipulate the immune system intelligently.  The 2022 meeting was postponed from 2020 due to the COVID-19 pandemic. By mutual agreement among the meeting chair and co-chairs, we tried to carry forward the same themes and speakers from the 2020 meeting. This meeting emphasized early stage investigators, and provided an open and inclusive environment for the exchange of ideas, with vibrant poster sessions from which short talks were selected. The meeting was preceded by a Gordon Research Seminar for graduate students and postdoctoral associates to present their work to each other before the conference, as well as a Power Hour to address the challenges that women encounter in developing their independent careers.  The Gordon Research Seminar on Bioinspired Materials was a unique forum for graduate students and post-docs to not only present and discuss their unpublished cutting edge research but also network and build collaborations with colleagues with a shared interest in bioinspired materials.  We invited all applications that are related to the design or application of synthetic or natural materials for diverse applications. We attracted a diverse, multidisciplinary field of presenters that addressed both fundamental understanding and practical applications of such biological and bioinspired materials. The 2022 GRS meeting consisted of a presentation by a distinguished scientist followed by GRS attendee presentations and discussions on research in the field of bioinspired materials. The GRS hosted informal poster sessions that facilitated stimulating discussions and exchange of ideas. To conclude the meeting, we had a mentorship panel to give participants more insight into the potential career opportunities and diversity in research within this field of science.       Last Modified: 04/03/2023       Submitted by: Daniel A Hammer]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
