<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID/Collaborative Research: Households Immediate Response During a Night Time Earthquake]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>12201.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>12201</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Daan Liang</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dliang@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922441</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This Rapid Response Research (RAPID) project examines household earthquake risk perceptions and immediate responses during a nighttime earthquake, in particular, the 2018 Eastern Taiwan (Haulien) earthquake that occurred on February 6, 2018. This project is innovative because most of the data on immediate response to earthquakes has been collected from daytime earthquakes, and this study can identify patterns of protective action that differ from those in daytime earthquakes. Better understanding of responses can help emergency management agencies provide appropriate emergency services to their communities and help households to better prepare for future events. In addition, this project will use an earthquake immediate response questionnaire that has been used in other earthquakes, including a US territory. This standardized questionnaire will be used to assess cultural differences in variables such as risk perception, self-reported shaking intensity, and emotional responses. The results of this study can be used to examine how cultural differences impact US residents' disaster response in culturally diverse regions of the US. Another earthquake impacting the US is inevitable and understanding people's response is critical to protecting our national health, prosperity, and welfare when the event occurs.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project tests the Protective Action Decision Model (PADM), which supposes that people's risk perceptions and responses are shaped by environmental/social cues and physical/household/social context when warnings are absent. In addition, this project tests the degree to which households' environmental/social cues, risk perceptions, and earthquake immediate response differ in urban and rural areas that vary in their shaking intensity and duration. This data expands a multinational earthquake response dataset that will allow investigators to conduct a statistical meta-analysis that will identify commonalities and differences in household response across different earthquakes throughout the Pacific Rim. The results of this study can provide an important empirical test of the degree to which research support for the PADM from hurricanes and flash floods also extends to nighttime earthquakes.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/13/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/13/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2001957</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Hao-Che</FirstName>
<LastName>Wu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Hao-Che Wu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[tristan.wu@unt.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000662562</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/13/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of North Texas</Name>
<CityName>DENTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>762035017</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9405653940</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1155 UNION CIR #305250</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>G47WN1XZNWX9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF NORTH TEXAS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>WXELJHR4N3S6</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of North Texas]]></Name>
<CityName>Denton</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>762035017</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1155 Union Circle #305250]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1638</Code>
<Text>HDBE-Humans, Disasters, and th</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>041E</Code>
<Text>HAZARD AND DISASTER REDUCTION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>042E</Code>
<Text>HAZARD AND DISASTER RESPONSE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>043E</Code>
<Text>EARTHQUAKE ENGINEERING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01001819DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~12201</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>The belief that individuals are more vulnerable to nighttime earthquake events is a common preconception. One reason for this belief is the assumption that people might have limited capacity to react and protect themselves during the time of resting at night. To better understand this issue, this project surveyed households that were impacted by the 2018 Eastern Taiwan Earthquake, a magnitude 6.4 event that struck Taiwan at 11:50 PM local time.</span></p> <p><span>This project examines structural, environmental, social, and household contexts during the nighttime earthquake. A household survey was conducted few months after the 2019 Eastern Taiwan Earthquake. The survey data were used to conduct an inter-correlation analysis among the contexts, perceived shaking intensity, risk perceptions, individual preparedness, earthquake experience, demographic characteristics, and people's immediate protective actions. These results were analyzed together with two comparable daytime earthquake events (the 2011 Christchurch Earthquake and the 2011 Great East Japan Earthquake).</span></p> <p><span>The findings suggest that a larger proportion of respondents who experienced the 2018 Eastern Taiwan (Hualien) Nighttime Earthquake (49.5%) did not take any protective actions. This number is higher when compared with toher two daytime earthquake events: the 2011 Christchurch (44.9%) and 2011 Great East Japan Tohoku (2.4%) earthquakes. Similarly, only 3.2% of Eastern Taiwan earthquake respondents reported the adoption of the recommended protective action (drop, cover, and hold-on), a proportion that is smaller than the two comparable daytime earthquakes events (18.2% and 8.4%, respectively). </span></p> <p><span>In addition, the regression analysis found that respondents? social and environmental contexts affect individuals' emotional response, and, in turn, their adoption of protective actions. The ability to form accurate expectations with regard to the rate of recommended protective action compliance based on earthquake intensity, population demographics, and contextual factors, is of particular practical importance during disaster preparedness and response operations.</span></p> <p><span>The results of this project are intended to encourage researchers to design preparedness and response exercises that account for earthquakes under different circumstances (e.g. nighttime events). This project also provides findings regarding individual behavioral and emotional responses during earthquake events. These findings can better inform policy decisions and structural regulations in earthquake-prone areas to reduce injury/death and promote household and community resilience.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/29/2021<br>      Modified by: Hao-Che&nbsp;Wu</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The belief that individuals are more vulnerable to nighttime earthquake events is a common preconception. One reason for this belief is the assumption that people might have limited capacity to react and protect themselves during the time of resting at night. To better understand this issue, this project surveyed households that were impacted by the 2018 Eastern Taiwan Earthquake, a magnitude 6.4 event that struck Taiwan at 11:50 PM local time.  This project examines structural, environmental, social, and household contexts during the nighttime earthquake. A household survey was conducted few months after the 2019 Eastern Taiwan Earthquake. The survey data were used to conduct an inter-correlation analysis among the contexts, perceived shaking intensity, risk perceptions, individual preparedness, earthquake experience, demographic characteristics, and people's immediate protective actions. These results were analyzed together with two comparable daytime earthquake events (the 2011 Christchurch Earthquake and the 2011 Great East Japan Earthquake).  The findings suggest that a larger proportion of respondents who experienced the 2018 Eastern Taiwan (Hualien) Nighttime Earthquake (49.5%) did not take any protective actions. This number is higher when compared with toher two daytime earthquake events: the 2011 Christchurch (44.9%) and 2011 Great East Japan Tohoku (2.4%) earthquakes. Similarly, only 3.2% of Eastern Taiwan earthquake respondents reported the adoption of the recommended protective action (drop, cover, and hold-on), a proportion that is smaller than the two comparable daytime earthquakes events (18.2% and 8.4%, respectively).   In addition, the regression analysis found that respondents? social and environmental contexts affect individuals' emotional response, and, in turn, their adoption of protective actions. The ability to form accurate expectations with regard to the rate of recommended protective action compliance based on earthquake intensity, population demographics, and contextual factors, is of particular practical importance during disaster preparedness and response operations.  The results of this project are intended to encourage researchers to design preparedness and response exercises that account for earthquakes under different circumstances (e.g. nighttime events). This project also provides findings regarding individual behavioral and emotional responses during earthquake events. These findings can better inform policy decisions and structural regulations in earthquake-prone areas to reduce injury/death and promote household and community resilience.          Last Modified: 09/29/2021       Submitted by: Hao-Che Wu]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
