<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[I-Corps: Accurate, Contiguous and Portable Wireless Intraocular Contact Lens Pressure Sensors]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ruth Shuman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rshuman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922160</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this I-Corps project is the development of a device to monitor high eye pressure (intraocular pressure or IOP), the only known sign of glaucoma, which could cause vision loss and influence patients’ quality of life. Glaucoma is a leading  cause of blindness for people over 60 years old and affects approximately 3 million people in the USA. The incidence of glaucoma is expected to rise to 76 million by 2020 and 112 million people by 2040 worldwide.  Unfortunately, glaucoma is not curable, but it is manageable with proper treatments. Although IOP is a highly dynamic parameter, conventional measurements fail to track it for a 24-hour period. A compact and portable wireless contact lens sensor (CLS) system can enable continuous, real-time monitoring of IOP and ensure clinical safety and patient comfort. This type of system could be adapted for other pressure measurements in other parts of the body as well. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project is based on the development of parity-time (PT) symmetry in quantum mechanics into radio-frequency (RF) telemetric sensing systems, enabling new ways to enhance resolution, accuracy, and sensitivity of versatile zero-power wireless pressure sensors (e.g., intraocular, intracranial and other biological pressures). Specifically, the team’s PT telemetry technologies employed an active loss-compensation circuit, which not only can compensate the power dissipation in minimally-invasive microsensors, but also allows a large shift of peak frequency under changes in vital physiological factors (i.e., a higher sensitivity), thanks to the eigenvalue bifurcation effect around the exceptional points found in PT systems. This wireless readout technology will be exploited to continuously record IOP levels from a biocompatible, monolithically microfabricated CLS, with enhanced sensitivity and resolvability. In addition, machine learning and signal processing algorithms will be exploited to address the long-term stability and signal drift issues in the practical IOP monitoring.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/21/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/21/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2001328</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Pai-Yen</FirstName>
<LastName>Chen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Pai-Yen Chen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[pychen@uic.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000682445</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/21/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Illinois at Chicago</Name>
<CityName>CHICAGO</CityName>
<ZipCode>606124305</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3129962862</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>809 S MARSHFIELD AVE M/C 551</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>W8XEAJDKMXH3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ILLINOIS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Illinois at Chicago]]></Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>606124305</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[809 S. Marshfield Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This I-Corps project helped the team formed by entrepreneurial lead (EL), technical lead (TL) and mentor to gain a deep understanding of entrepreneurship and starting a business that suits the needs and challenges of the medical electronics and ophthalmic markets. The project provided the necessary survey, analysis, and strategic foundation from which the TL&rsquo;s previous NSF support can be leveraged to develop the lightweight, zero-power wireless intraocular pressure (IOP) sensor to meet the needs of glaucoma patients. In the beginning stage of our entrepreneurship, this project helped the team systematically and effectively investigate the market and potential partnerships. The training through I-Corps activities is crucial because it greatly accelerates the knowledge building process and promote the progress of start-ups, linking the previously federally funded research to commercialization and entrepreneurship. The project provided the team with the opportunity to conduct large-scale interviews with potential customers, partners, and competitors. Through this, the team conducted a thorough customer discovery for our laboratory prototype - a portable wireless IOP monitoring device for glaucoma diagnostic purposes. This project also helped us establish connections with industry, hospitals, university, institutions, and national labs. The team has fully clarified the pros and cons of the current available products and the main hurdles towards its practical uses. The customer discovery outcomes unveil that ophthalmologists and optometrists are looking for reliable, fast and portable glaucoma diagnostic equipment/device, but there is still no such equipment on the market, which may be the advantage of our product.</p> <p>After this I-Corps project, the team continued to carry out the R&amp;D efforts to solve the cost and clinic challenges that were concerned by the interviewees and potential partners. Through the I-Corps program, the EL realized the importance of intellectual property protection and began to be interested in IP law and legal practice. He started his career with preparation and prosecution of patent applications, as well as freedom-to-operate and patentability analyses. The team is still working together toward implementation of the new vision of the laboratory prototype to seek SBIR/STTR fund and venture capital investment. Some of the latest R&amp;D results integrated with the knowledge gained through this program had led to one US patent and international journal articles.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/10/2021<br>      Modified by: Pai-Yen&nbsp;Chen</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This I-Corps project helped the team formed by entrepreneurial lead (EL), technical lead (TL) and mentor to gain a deep understanding of entrepreneurship and starting a business that suits the needs and challenges of the medical electronics and ophthalmic markets. The project provided the necessary survey, analysis, and strategic foundation from which the TL’s previous NSF support can be leveraged to develop the lightweight, zero-power wireless intraocular pressure (IOP) sensor to meet the needs of glaucoma patients. In the beginning stage of our entrepreneurship, this project helped the team systematically and effectively investigate the market and potential partnerships. The training through I-Corps activities is crucial because it greatly accelerates the knowledge building process and promote the progress of start-ups, linking the previously federally funded research to commercialization and entrepreneurship. The project provided the team with the opportunity to conduct large-scale interviews with potential customers, partners, and competitors. Through this, the team conducted a thorough customer discovery for our laboratory prototype - a portable wireless IOP monitoring device for glaucoma diagnostic purposes. This project also helped us establish connections with industry, hospitals, university, institutions, and national labs. The team has fully clarified the pros and cons of the current available products and the main hurdles towards its practical uses. The customer discovery outcomes unveil that ophthalmologists and optometrists are looking for reliable, fast and portable glaucoma diagnostic equipment/device, but there is still no such equipment on the market, which may be the advantage of our product.  After this I-Corps project, the team continued to carry out the R&amp;D efforts to solve the cost and clinic challenges that were concerned by the interviewees and potential partners. Through the I-Corps program, the EL realized the importance of intellectual property protection and began to be interested in IP law and legal practice. He started his career with preparation and prosecution of patent applications, as well as freedom-to-operate and patentability analyses. The team is still working together toward implementation of the new vision of the laboratory prototype to seek SBIR/STTR fund and venture capital investment. Some of the latest R&amp;D results integrated with the knowledge gained through this program had led to one US patent and international journal articles.          Last Modified: 12/10/2021       Submitted by: Pai-Yen Chen]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
