<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Cosmology with Millimeter-Wave Intensity Mapping: Developing A New Probe of Large-Scale Structure]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>300000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>242500</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AST</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Andrea Prestwich</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>aprestwi@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922210</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Kirit Karkare is awarded an NSF Astronomy and Astrophysics Postdoctoral Fellowship to conduct a program of research and education at the University of Chicago.  He will play a lead role in developing instrumentation and conducting observations to study the large-scale structure of the distant universe.  Results from this project will advance our understanding of the physics of the early universe.  Along with this research, he will develop a program of public outreach that connects artists from underserved Chicago communities to scientists at the University of Chicago.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will advance the instrumentation and analysis necessary to develop line intensity mapping (IM) as a probe of large-scale structure.  It will test the performance of the millimeter-wave spectrometer and kinetic inductance detectors on the SuperSpec instrument and analyze IM observations of singly ionized carbon and carbon monoxide.  It will also develop a software pipeline to assess scan and noise reduction, and it will test a novel foreground cleaning algorithm to isolate the cosmological signal.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/15/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/30/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2001802</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kirit</FirstName>
<LastName>Karkare</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kirit S Karkare</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<NSF_ID>000730242</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/15/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Karkare                 Kirit          S</Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<ZipCode>606370000</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT/>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG/>
<ORG_UEI_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Chicago]]></Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>606371433</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF/>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1609</Code>
<Text>NSF ASTRON &amp; ASTROPHY PSTDC FE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1207</Code>
<Text>OBSERVATIONAL ASTRONOMY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7697</Code>
<Text>INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002223DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~100000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~100000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2022~42500</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The purpose of this fellowship was to advance instrumentation and  analysis tools to develop mm-wave line intensity mapping (LIM) as a new  probe of cosmology. Measurements of large-scale structure (LSS) as  traced by far-IR emission lines have the potential to test our  cosmological model to higher precision than the cosmic microwave  background and galaxy surveys by extending the redshift reach of LSS  measurements. During this fellowship, progress was made in three areas:<br /><br />First,  the PI led the UChicago lab testing program for the SuperSpec project,  which is pioneering the on-chip spectrometers that will be used for  mm-wave LIM. Characterization of the filter-bank response fed into  detector development and improved the spectrometer design. In  preparation for SuperSpec's first demonstration at the Large Millimeter  Telescope in 2023, the PI also co-led development of a readout system  for the kinetic inductance detectors and built cryogenic and  room-temperature optical components.<br /><br />Second, the PI started a new  project: the South Pole Telescope Summertime Line Intensity Mapper  (SPT-SLIM), which will demonstrate the LIM measurement using detectors  based on the SuperSpec design. The cryostat was designed to fit into the  South Pole Telescope receiver cabin and hold a focal plane array of 36  spectrometers. Prototype detectors were fabricated and tested at  UChicago. The instrument is on track to deploy during the 2023-2024  austral summer season.<br /><br />Third, the PI worked on projects  to forecast the science reach of future LIM experiments. One analyzed  the ability of LIM measurements to constrain the properties of neutrinos  and other relativistic species, while another projected limits on  theories of modified gravity using LSS as probed by LIM. <br /><br />As a  part of this fellowship, progress was made towards developing a diverse  STEM workforce: three graduate students were trained in projects ranging  from detector design to cosmological simulations, and two  undergraduates were mentored in experimental microwave techniques. A  collaboration with the UChicago Arts + Public Life initiative was also  started, resulting in a recorded conversation between artists and  scientists and preparations for hosting high school students in UChicago  labs.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/29/2022<br>      Modified by: Kirit&nbsp;S&nbsp;Karkare</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The purpose of this fellowship was to advance instrumentation and  analysis tools to develop mm-wave line intensity mapping (LIM) as a new  probe of cosmology. Measurements of large-scale structure (LSS) as  traced by far-IR emission lines have the potential to test our  cosmological model to higher precision than the cosmic microwave  background and galaxy surveys by extending the redshift reach of LSS  measurements. During this fellowship, progress was made in three areas:  First,  the PI led the UChicago lab testing program for the SuperSpec project,  which is pioneering the on-chip spectrometers that will be used for  mm-wave LIM. Characterization of the filter-bank response fed into  detector development and improved the spectrometer design. In  preparation for SuperSpec's first demonstration at the Large Millimeter  Telescope in 2023, the PI also co-led development of a readout system  for the kinetic inductance detectors and built cryogenic and  room-temperature optical components.  Second, the PI started a new  project: the South Pole Telescope Summertime Line Intensity Mapper  (SPT-SLIM), which will demonstrate the LIM measurement using detectors  based on the SuperSpec design. The cryostat was designed to fit into the  South Pole Telescope receiver cabin and hold a focal plane array of 36  spectrometers. Prototype detectors were fabricated and tested at  UChicago. The instrument is on track to deploy during the 2023-2024  austral summer season.  Third, the PI worked on projects  to forecast the science reach of future LIM experiments. One analyzed  the ability of LIM measurements to constrain the properties of neutrinos  and other relativistic species, while another projected limits on  theories of modified gravity using LSS as probed by LIM.   As a  part of this fellowship, progress was made towards developing a diverse  STEM workforce: three graduate students were trained in projects ranging  from detector design to cosmological simulations, and two  undergraduates were mentored in experimental microwave techniques. A  collaboration with the UChicago Arts + Public Life initiative was also  started, resulting in a recorded conversation between artists and  scientists and preparations for hosting high school students in UChicago  labs.       Last Modified: 12/29/2022       Submitted by: Kirit S Karkare]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
