<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Moduli of Differentials]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>150000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>150000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Andrew Pollington</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>adpollin@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924878</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The concept of differentials dates back to the origin of calculus.  For instance, integration of differentials can tell us about distance, area, volume, etc, for the physical world.  Nowadays the study of differentials has broad connections to a number of fields in and outside of mathematics.  It has been proven extremely useful that one should collect differentials with similar structures into a parameter space (called moduli space) and study the global properties of this space, which can in turn determine crucial information about each individual differential.  The principal investigator plans to explore new, fascinating properties of differentials as well as their moduli spaces.  Moreover, he plans to discover hidden connections between initially unrelated subjects in which differentials appear from different aspects.  The proposed project also opens many gates for student and postdoctoral research.  The principal investigator will continue to integrate his research with undergraduate, graduate and postdoctoral training as well as conference organizations.  In particular, he plans to advise student research projects, design new courses, and organize a series of workshops, with a focus on increasing diversity and supporting underrepresented groups.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The moduli space of differentials on Riemann surfaces can be stratified according to the types of zeros and poles.  Each stratum is equipped with a group action by varying the polygonal structure induced by a differential.  Various questions about surface geometry reduce to understanding the strata of differentials and orbits under the action.  The principal investigator plans to employ his expertise in algebraic geometry, combined with mixing techniques from analysis, dynamics and topology, to study these strata and orbits, such as their volumes, geodesics, and boundary behavior.  An ultimate goal is to establish a correspondence between dynamical invariants of differentials and intersection theory on moduli spaces.  Moreover, the PI plans to use the obtained results to analyze algebro-geometric properties of moduli spaces, such as birational types, compactifications, and tautological rings.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/11/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/11/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2001040</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dawei</FirstName>
<LastName>Chen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Dawei Chen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[dawei.chen@bc.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000511957</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/11/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Boston College</Name>
<CityName>CHESTNUT HILL</CityName>
<ZipCode>024673800</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6175528000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>140 COMMONWEALTH AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>MJ3JH8CRJBZ7</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF BOSTON COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Boston College]]></Name>
<CityName>Chestnut Hill</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>024673800</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[140 Commonwealth Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1264</Code>
<Text>ALGEBRA,NUMBER THEORY,AND COM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~150000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><div class="page" title="Page 1"> <div class="layoutArea"> <div class="column"> <p>This project explores the fascinating world of differentials on surfaces, defining a flat structure on the underlying surface and allowing it to be represented as a polygon equipped with the Euclidean metric. Conical singularities arise at the zeros of the differential, and the shape of the polygon can be varied to induce a matrix group action on moduli spaces of differentials while preserving the zero orders.</p> <p>The study of differentials and their orbits under the group action sheds light on various questions about geometry and dynamics on surfaces. The Principal Investigator (PI) achieved significant breakthroughs in several areas, including compactification, birational geometry, affine geometry, tautological geometry, and dynamical invariants for moduli spaces of differentials. These findings resulted in the completion of over ten papers, including publications in esteemed journals.<br />Furthermore, the PI's dedication to mentorship and education played a vital role in nurturing the next generation of mathematicians. He advised and supported two graduate students and three undergraduate projects, providing invaluable guidance to these aspiring researchers.</p> <p>Despite the challenges posed by the pandemic, the PI exhibited exceptional leadership and inclusivity. Organizing several online workshops, he ensured that students, junior researchers, and underrepresented groups had access to valuable resources and opportunities. Additionally, the PI contributed to outreach efforts, writing expository articles, and participating in activities to promote mathematics education among K-5 students.</p> <p>Overall, this project has not only advanced the understanding of differentials and their role in geometry and dynamics but has also made a significant impact on the mathematical community through research, mentorship, and outreach efforts.</p> </div> </div> </div><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/02/2023<br>      Modified by: Dawei&nbsp;Chen</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[    This project explores the fascinating world of differentials on surfaces, defining a flat structure on the underlying surface and allowing it to be represented as a polygon equipped with the Euclidean metric. Conical singularities arise at the zeros of the differential, and the shape of the polygon can be varied to induce a matrix group action on moduli spaces of differentials while preserving the zero orders.  The study of differentials and their orbits under the group action sheds light on various questions about geometry and dynamics on surfaces. The Principal Investigator (PI) achieved significant breakthroughs in several areas, including compactification, birational geometry, affine geometry, tautological geometry, and dynamical invariants for moduli spaces of differentials. These findings resulted in the completion of over ten papers, including publications in esteemed journals. Furthermore, the PI's dedication to mentorship and education played a vital role in nurturing the next generation of mathematicians. He advised and supported two graduate students and three undergraduate projects, providing invaluable guidance to these aspiring researchers.  Despite the challenges posed by the pandemic, the PI exhibited exceptional leadership and inclusivity. Organizing several online workshops, he ensured that students, junior researchers, and underrepresented groups had access to valuable resources and opportunities. Additionally, the PI contributed to outreach efforts, writing expository articles, and participating in activities to promote mathematics education among K-5 students.  Overall, this project has not only advanced the understanding of differentials and their role in geometry and dynamics but has also made a significant impact on the mathematical community through research, mentorship, and outreach efforts.          Last Modified: 08/02/2023       Submitted by: Dawei Chen]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
