<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Modeling Black Hole Dynamics in Dense Star Clusters in the Era of LIGO, LISA, and LSST]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>300000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>233000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AST</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Andrea Prestwich</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>aprestwi@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922210</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Kyle Kremer is awarded an NSF Astronomy and Astrophysics Postdoctoral Fellowship to conduct a program of research and education at the California Institute of Technology and the Carnegie Observatories.  Over the next few years, the list of gravitational wave (GW) detections from merging black holes (BHs) and neutron stars is expected to grow enormously, and interpreting the properties of these sources requires a detailed understanding of the role of dense star clusters.  Forthcoming transient surveys will also provide new constraints on the formation and populations of compact remnants.  One important channel, and the focus of this research, is dynamical formation in dense stellar environments like globular clusters (GCs).  The Cosmos in Concert program of multimedia shows combining astronomy education and music performance has already successfully presented 16 concerts in 6 states, and will be extended to the southern California area with performances at K-12 schools and universities, and with local symphony orchestras.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This is a broad study of the dynamics of BHs in dense star clusters with applications to GW and high-energy astrophysics, covering (i) the rates of massive star collisions and tidal disruption events in realistic GCs; (ii)  the dynamical effect of massive BHs on cluster dynamics; (iii) a side-by-side analysis of the differences between compact binary formation in GCs and isolated binary evolution in the galactic field; and (iv) the public release of an extensive database of realistic GC models.  The work will significantly aid the development of improved data analysis and detection strategies for next-generation GW observatories and transient surveys.  This project advances the goals of the NSF Windows on the Universe Big Idea.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/26/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/29/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2001751</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kyle</FirstName>
<LastName>Kremer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kyle Kremer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<NSF_ID>000812963</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/26/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Kremer, Kyle</Name>
<CityName>Evanston</CityName>
<ZipCode>60201</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[California Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>Pasadena</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>911250001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>28</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA28</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>107Y</Code>
<Text>WoU-Windows on the Universe: T</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1609</Code>
<Text>NSF ASTRON &amp; ASTROPHY PSTDC FE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>069Z</Code>
<Text>Windows on the Universe (WoU)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1206</Code>
<Text>THEORETICAL &amp; COMPUTATIONAL ASTROPHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~233000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="p1"><span> </span>Over the past few years, the groundbreaking detections of gravitational-wave (GW) signals from merging binary black holes (BHs) and neutron stars (NSs) by LIGO/Virgo have opened a new window to the cosmos. One key question regarding these GW sources concerns the nature of their origin. Dynamical formation in dense stellar environments like globular clusters (GCs) has emerged as an important formation channel, competing with more traditional scenarios based on the evolution of isolated binaries in the galactic field. As an NSF Astronomy &amp; Astrophysics Postdoctoral Fellow at Caltech and Carnegie Observatories, I have conducted a broad study of the dynamics of BHs in dense star clusters, exploring in particular the applications to GW and high-energy astrophysics. This work consisted of four primary components: (1) Explore the rates of massive star collisions and tidal disruption events in realistic GCs, the electromagnetic signatures associated with these high-energy events, and the subsequent stellar evolution of the collision products; (2) Explore the formation of intermediate-mass BHs (IMBHs; with masses in excess of 100 solar masses) in dense star clusters to explore the dynamical effect of massive BHs on cluster dynamics and specifically examine how current and future GW observations may constrain the presence of IMBHs in clusters; (3) Perform a &ldquo;side-by-side'' analysis of compact binary formation in GCs and the galactic field to explore in detail the differences between stellar dynamics and isolated binary evolution in GW source formation; (4) Construct and publicly release an extensive database of realistic GC models and accompanying cluster dynamics code.</p> <p class="p1"><span> </span>In the coming years, the list of GW detections by LIGO/Virgo is expected to grow to the thousands. In order to successfully interpret the properties of these sources, a detailed understanding of the role of dense star clusters in GW source formation, and critically, a detailed understanding of the differences between this channel and other proposed BH merger channels, is essential. Furthermore, the success of LIGO/Virgo has laid the groundwork for future GW missions, such as LISA, that will enable constraints and characterization of these source formation processes across the GW spectrum. My work on GW source formation in GCs is essential in the development of improved data analysis and detection strategies for these next-generation GW observatories. Finally, the upcoming transient survey LSST promises to complement the emerging field of GW astronomy by providing new constraints upon compact remnant populations and their formation scenarios. For this, understanding the implications of BH dynamics upon transient formation in GCs is crucial. By exploring the specific implications of stellar dynamics for LIGO, LISA, and LSST, my work conducted as an NSF fellow has and will play a pivotal role in leveraging the exciting era ahead.</p> <p class="p2"><span class="s1"><span> </span></span><span class="s2">In parallel with my research initiatives, I conducted educational outreach efforts through my Cosmos in Concert program. This program presents multimedia shows combining astronomy education and music performance with the goal of making astronomy (and science in general) accessible to a broader and more diverse demographic.&nbsp;In 2022, I performed my program &ldquo;Celestial Suite&rdquo; at the Colburn School of Music in Los Angeles. Students from the conservatory performed in the program which was presented (free of charge) for the broader community. Additionally, I have continued my ongoing work to develop a new astronomy-inspired musical composition to be performed by the Axiom Brass Quintet. This multimedia piece will be performed both on standard concert programs and as part of educational concerts. In addition to my music-themed outreach efforts, I presented two public astronomy lectures and mentored two undergraduate students in the summers of 2020 and 2021 as part of the Carnegie CASSI Summer Research Program.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/06/2023<br>      Modified by: Kyle&nbsp;Kremer</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Over the past few years, the groundbreaking detections of gravitational-wave (GW) signals from merging binary black holes (BHs) and neutron stars (NSs) by LIGO/Virgo have opened a new window to the cosmos. One key question regarding these GW sources concerns the nature of their origin. Dynamical formation in dense stellar environments like globular clusters (GCs) has emerged as an important formation channel, competing with more traditional scenarios based on the evolution of isolated binaries in the galactic field. As an NSF Astronomy &amp; Astrophysics Postdoctoral Fellow at Caltech and Carnegie Observatories, I have conducted a broad study of the dynamics of BHs in dense star clusters, exploring in particular the applications to GW and high-energy astrophysics. This work consisted of four primary components: (1) Explore the rates of massive star collisions and tidal disruption events in realistic GCs, the electromagnetic signatures associated with these high-energy events, and the subsequent stellar evolution of the collision products; (2) Explore the formation of intermediate-mass BHs (IMBHs; with masses in excess of 100 solar masses) in dense star clusters to explore the dynamical effect of massive BHs on cluster dynamics and specifically examine how current and future GW observations may constrain the presence of IMBHs in clusters; (3) Perform a "side-by-side'' analysis of compact binary formation in GCs and the galactic field to explore in detail the differences between stellar dynamics and isolated binary evolution in GW source formation; (4) Construct and publicly release an extensive database of realistic GC models and accompanying cluster dynamics code.  In the coming years, the list of GW detections by LIGO/Virgo is expected to grow to the thousands. In order to successfully interpret the properties of these sources, a detailed understanding of the role of dense star clusters in GW source formation, and critically, a detailed understanding of the differences between this channel and other proposed BH merger channels, is essential. Furthermore, the success of LIGO/Virgo has laid the groundwork for future GW missions, such as LISA, that will enable constraints and characterization of these source formation processes across the GW spectrum. My work on GW source formation in GCs is essential in the development of improved data analysis and detection strategies for these next-generation GW observatories. Finally, the upcoming transient survey LSST promises to complement the emerging field of GW astronomy by providing new constraints upon compact remnant populations and their formation scenarios. For this, understanding the implications of BH dynamics upon transient formation in GCs is crucial. By exploring the specific implications of stellar dynamics for LIGO, LISA, and LSST, my work conducted as an NSF fellow has and will play a pivotal role in leveraging the exciting era ahead.  In parallel with my research initiatives, I conducted educational outreach efforts through my Cosmos in Concert program. This program presents multimedia shows combining astronomy education and music performance with the goal of making astronomy (and science in general) accessible to a broader and more diverse demographic. In 2022, I performed my program "Celestial Suite" at the Colburn School of Music in Los Angeles. Students from the conservatory performed in the program which was presented (free of charge) for the broader community. Additionally, I have continued my ongoing work to develop a new astronomy-inspired musical composition to be performed by the Axiom Brass Quintet. This multimedia piece will be performed both on standard concert programs and as part of educational concerts. In addition to my music-themed outreach efforts, I presented two public astronomy lectures and mentored two undergraduate students in the summers of 2020 and 2021 as part of the Carnegie CASSI Summer Research Program.          Last Modified: 01/06/2023       Submitted by: Kyle Kremer]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
