<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: An Improved Understanding of Mesoscale Wind and Precipitation Variability in the Ross Island Region Based on Radar Observations]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>11/15/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>125070.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>125070</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06090300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OPP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Polar Programs (OPP)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Allen Pope</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>apope@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928030</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Despite several decades of successful Antarctic aviation, centered upon flight operations  in the McMurdo (Phoenix Field, Ross Island; RsI) area, systemized description of radar  observations such as are normally found essential in operational  aviation settings are notably lacking. The Ross Island region of Antarctica is a topographically complex region that results in large variations in the mesoscale high wind and precipitation features across the region.  The goals of this project are to increase the understanding of the three-dimensional structure of these mesoscale meteorology features. Of particular interest are those features observed with radar signals.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will leverage observations from the scanning X-band radar installed during the AWARE field campaign in 2016 and the installation of an EWR Radar Systems X-band scanning radar (E700XD) to be deployed during the 2019-20 field season, at McMurdo. Several science questions and case studies will be addressed during the season.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>10/22/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/22/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.078</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2001430</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Cassano</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John J Cassano</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[john.cassano@colorado.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000181851</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>10/22/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
<LastName>Seefeldt</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mark W Seefeldt</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mark.seefeldt@colorado.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000505594</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>10/22/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Kingsmill</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David E Kingsmill</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[David.Kingsmill@Colorado.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000466833</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>10/22/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Colorado at Boulder</Name>
<CityName>BOULDER</CityName>
<ZipCode>803090001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3034926221</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3100 MARINE ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[STE 481 572 UCB]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>SPVKK1RC2MZ3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>THE REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF COLORADO</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Colorado at Boulder]]></Name>
<CityName>Boulder</CityName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>803090481</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3100 Marine Street, Room 481]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5113</Code>
<Text>ANT Ocean &amp; Atmos Sciences</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5113</Code>
<Text>ANTARCTIC OCEAN &amp; ATMOSPH SCI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>02XX</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>0100XXXXDB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~125070</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Weather radars are widely used in weather forecasting and research in the mid-latitudes but similar radar data is typically not available in the polar regions. Two different weather radars were installed near the main United States Antarctic research base, McMurdo Station, as part of a year-long field campaign in 2016 and as a trial of an operational weather radar during the Antarctic summer of 2019-2020. &nbsp;In this project we assessed the utility of this radar data for studying small-scale patterns in precipitation and winds around McMurdo Station.&nbsp;</p> <p>Due to technical problems with the operational radar deployed in 2019-2020 little useable data was collected but our project identified types of data that should be archived if similar radar systems are installed near McMurdo Station in the future.</p> <p>The field campaign radar data from 2016 allowed us to analyze the precipitation and wind associated with a storm that took place from 16-20 January 2016 and compare these radar observations to operational weather forecasts produced by the Antarctic Mesoscale Prediction System (AMPS). The radar data revealed large spatial gradients in precipitation and winds in the vicinity of McMurdo Station, related to the complex terrain in this area. The AMPS forecasts accurately simulated much of the spatial variability although a dry bias in the model resulted in much less precipitation being forecast by the model than was actually observed.&nbsp;</p> <p>The radar observations have given us our first fully resolved observations of the small-scale patterns of precipitation and winds around McMurdo Station. Regular availability of radar data like this will help improve weather forecasts and operational safety at the main United States logistics hub on the Antarctic continent.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/20/2023<br>      Modified by: John&nbsp;J&nbsp;Cassano</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2001430/2001430_10644223_1676942395544_precip--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2001430/2001430_10644223_1676942395544_precip--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Radar and AMPS precipitation"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2001430/2001430_10644223_1676942395544_precip--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Radar and AMPS precipitation"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Radar observed precipitation (top left) and 4 estimates of precipitation from the Antarctic Mesoscale Prediction System (AMPS) (right panels). The radar (and AMPS) precipitation reveal areas of enhanced precipitation on the upwind side of the terrain with lighter precipitation on the downwind side.</div> <div class="imageCredit">David Kingsmill</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">John&nbsp;J&nbsp;Cassano</div> <div class="imageTitle">Radar and AMPS precipitation</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2001430/2001430_10644223_1676942568723_wind--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2001430/2001430_10644223_1676942568723_wind--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Radar and AMPS wind"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2001430/2001430_10644223_1676942568723_wind--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Radar and AMPS wind"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Radial wind velocity from the radar (left column) and several AMPS forecasts (middle and right column). Areas of stronger wind (purple colors) are seen funneling around the terrain of Black and White Islands in the middle of these images with weaker winds further to the north.</div> <div class="imageCredit">David Kingsmill</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">John&nbsp;J&nbsp;Cassano</div> <div class="imageTitle">Radar and AMPS wind</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Weather radars are widely used in weather forecasting and research in the mid-latitudes but similar radar data is typically not available in the polar regions. Two different weather radars were installed near the main United States Antarctic research base, McMurdo Station, as part of a year-long field campaign in 2016 and as a trial of an operational weather radar during the Antarctic summer of 2019-2020.  In this project we assessed the utility of this radar data for studying small-scale patterns in precipitation and winds around McMurdo Station.   Due to technical problems with the operational radar deployed in 2019-2020 little useable data was collected but our project identified types of data that should be archived if similar radar systems are installed near McMurdo Station in the future.  The field campaign radar data from 2016 allowed us to analyze the precipitation and wind associated with a storm that took place from 16-20 January 2016 and compare these radar observations to operational weather forecasts produced by the Antarctic Mesoscale Prediction System (AMPS). The radar data revealed large spatial gradients in precipitation and winds in the vicinity of McMurdo Station, related to the complex terrain in this area. The AMPS forecasts accurately simulated much of the spatial variability although a dry bias in the model resulted in much less precipitation being forecast by the model than was actually observed.   The radar observations have given us our first fully resolved observations of the small-scale patterns of precipitation and winds around McMurdo Station. Regular availability of radar data like this will help improve weather forecasts and operational safety at the main United States logistics hub on the Antarctic continent.       Last Modified: 02/20/2023       Submitted by: John J Cassano]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
