<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[PostDoctoral Research Fellowship]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>150000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>150000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Stefaan De Winter</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sgdewint@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922599</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This award is made as part of the FY 2020 Mathematical Sciences Postdoctoral Research Fellowships Program. Each of the fellowships supports a research and training project at a host institution in the mathematical sciences, including applications to other disciplines, under the mentorship of a sponsoring scientist.  The title of the project for this fellowship to Maggie Miller is "Knotted surfaces in 3- and 4-manifolds via geometric techniques."  The host institution for the fellowship is Massachusetts Institute of Technology, and the sponsoring scientist is Tomasz Mrowka.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/16/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/16/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2001675</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Maggie</FirstName>
<LastName>Miller</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Maggie Miller</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<NSF_ID>000811898</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/16/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Miller, Maggie</Name>
<CityName>Princeton</CityName>
<ZipCode>085406145</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NJ12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Department of Mathematics]]></Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021394301</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>060Y</Code>
<Text>Workforce (MSPRF) MathSciPDFel</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9219</Code>
<Text>POSTDOCTORAL FELLOWSHIPS IN MATH SCIENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~150000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The total funding period of this grant was July 2020 -- July 2021. All research was conducted at Massachusetts Institute of Technology. During this period, the PI prepared four new preprints (one of which was published during the course of this grant), started two additional preprints that were still in progress as of the end of the period, and further edited several additional earlier preprints that were accepted for publication during this time.&nbsp;<br /><br />The title of this project was "Knotted surfaces in three- and four-manifolds via geometric techniques." The PI was particularly interested in the subfield of surfaces knotted in four-dimensional spaces. These surfaces can be though of as higher-dimensional analogues to knots in three-dimensional spaces (and are interesting for many of the same reasons), but additionally can encode subtle four-dimensional information like obstructions to four-dimensional spaces being smoothly equivalent.</p> <p>One long-standing goal accomplished by the PI during the course of this grant was to develop a diagrammatic theory of surfaces immersed (i.e. with self-intersections) in four-dimensional spaces, as joint work with M. Hughes and S. Kim. This involved understanding generic behavior of projections of such surfaces to three-dimensional cross-sections, what behavior is expected during the course of a one-parameter family of surfaces.&nbsp;</p> <p>This project was partly motivated by the PI's desire to create explicit examples of pairs of surfaces achieving interesting behavior. During this funding period, the PI (with M. Klug) studied the Kervaire--Milnor invariant of Stong, which is defined for a pair of two-spheres in a four-dimensional space and can obstruct the two-spheres from being concordant, which is a weak notion of equivalence studied by topologists. One can compute this invariant if they can construct a homotopy between the two two-spheres, i.e. a one-parameter family of immersed spheres between the two desired 2-spheres. During the course of this grant, the PI and Klug published a joint paper including an example of a pair of two-spheres with nontrivial Kervaire--Milnor invariant, which is the first such example in the literature. The PI and Klug are continuing this work to better understand the Kervaire--Milnor invariant, making use of the diagrammatic theory described above to achieve explicit constructions.</p> <p>In addition, during the entire funding period the PI organized an online seminar ("Geometric Topology Grad and Postdoc Seminar") aimed at graduate students interested in topology; this seminar was publicly advertised and students at many universities worldwide participated. In June 2021, the PI also began mentoring an undergraduate project in the area of four-dimensional topology that was based on ongoing work of the PI conducted during the course of this grant.</p> <p>The PI co-organized a special session on low-dimensional topology at the 2020 AMS Fall Western Sectional Meeting and during spring and summer 2021 co-organized the the American Institute of Mathematics' Virtual Research Community on 4-dimensional topology (an online group of &gt;100 mathematics studying low-dimensional topology based around small working groups and occasional bigger meetings). During the course of this grant, the PI also co-authored successful proposals to co-organize an AMS special session on surfaces in 4-manifolds at the 2022 Joint Mathematics Meetings and a workshop on 4-dimensional topology at the Banff International Research Station in 2022.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/15/2021<br>      Modified by: Maggie&nbsp;Miller</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The total funding period of this grant was July 2020 -- July 2021. All research was conducted at Massachusetts Institute of Technology. During this period, the PI prepared four new preprints (one of which was published during the course of this grant), started two additional preprints that were still in progress as of the end of the period, and further edited several additional earlier preprints that were accepted for publication during this time.   The title of this project was "Knotted surfaces in three- and four-manifolds via geometric techniques." The PI was particularly interested in the subfield of surfaces knotted in four-dimensional spaces. These surfaces can be though of as higher-dimensional analogues to knots in three-dimensional spaces (and are interesting for many of the same reasons), but additionally can encode subtle four-dimensional information like obstructions to four-dimensional spaces being smoothly equivalent.  One long-standing goal accomplished by the PI during the course of this grant was to develop a diagrammatic theory of surfaces immersed (i.e. with self-intersections) in four-dimensional spaces, as joint work with M. Hughes and S. Kim. This involved understanding generic behavior of projections of such surfaces to three-dimensional cross-sections, what behavior is expected during the course of a one-parameter family of surfaces.   This project was partly motivated by the PI's desire to create explicit examples of pairs of surfaces achieving interesting behavior. During this funding period, the PI (with M. Klug) studied the Kervaire--Milnor invariant of Stong, which is defined for a pair of two-spheres in a four-dimensional space and can obstruct the two-spheres from being concordant, which is a weak notion of equivalence studied by topologists. One can compute this invariant if they can construct a homotopy between the two two-spheres, i.e. a one-parameter family of immersed spheres between the two desired 2-spheres. During the course of this grant, the PI and Klug published a joint paper including an example of a pair of two-spheres with nontrivial Kervaire--Milnor invariant, which is the first such example in the literature. The PI and Klug are continuing this work to better understand the Kervaire--Milnor invariant, making use of the diagrammatic theory described above to achieve explicit constructions.  In addition, during the entire funding period the PI organized an online seminar ("Geometric Topology Grad and Postdoc Seminar") aimed at graduate students interested in topology; this seminar was publicly advertised and students at many universities worldwide participated. In June 2021, the PI also began mentoring an undergraduate project in the area of four-dimensional topology that was based on ongoing work of the PI conducted during the course of this grant.  The PI co-organized a special session on low-dimensional topology at the 2020 AMS Fall Western Sectional Meeting and during spring and summer 2021 co-organized the the American Institute of Mathematics' Virtual Research Community on 4-dimensional topology (an online group of &gt;100 mathematics studying low-dimensional topology based around small working groups and occasional bigger meetings). During the course of this grant, the PI also co-authored successful proposals to co-organize an AMS special session on surfaces in 4-manifolds at the 2022 Joint Mathematics Meetings and a workshop on 4-dimensional topology at the Banff International Research Station in 2022.          Last Modified: 10/15/2021       Submitted by: Maggie Miller]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
