<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Doctoral Dissertation Research: Latinidad in Precision Medicine: Emergence of Imagined Genetic Communities]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>15970.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>15970</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joseph Whitmeyer</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jwhitmey@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927808</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Precision medicine efforts aim to tailor healthcare to individuals by devising the most effective treatments based on genetic profiles.  But how are these efforts implemented within genetically diverse populations who nonetheless share perceived common ethnicities?  This project investigates these issues within the context of the Latinx population, which is very diverse genetically, but is one that the medical community often mischaracterizes as they provide research reports, recruit medical study participants and devise public educational materials.  The project analyzes how precision medicine investigators think about and act upon attributes of the Latinx population as a target community.  It will analyze the approaches, logics, and frameworks used to make sense of group identity.  It will also investigate how these factors may contribute to racialized concepts of human difference among and within populations.  More broadly, the project considers how the concepts of biology and race might affect broader political understandings and processes pertaining to Latinx people, and thus provides input to policy makers in medical communities and beyond as they strive to acknowledge and support racial diversity in the United States.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;We know that racialized concepts of human, and therefore genomic, differences persist in biomedicine, yet the relevance of race and ethnicity in genomics is contested. Focusing on Latinx populations for precision medicine presents a paradox because the Latinx label is a broad one that nonetheless contains strong diversity in genetic profiles. The first study phase will be a content analysis of 100 precision medicine texts, such as research reports, public education materials, and participant recruitment materials, which reflect racial and ethnic identities of participants, data, or bio-specimens.  The second study phase will include ethnographic observations at 15-20 precision medicine events as well as in-depth key-informant interviews with a target of 40 precision medicine investigators.  Finally, the project will conduct semi-structured interviews with 60 Latinx community members relating to genomics, precision medicine and Latinx identity.  Through examination of investigator and research participant perspectives, this study will address how social categorizations are constructed in biomedicine and in contemporary life more broadly. Findings from the project will provide insight into sociological theories regarding how social categorizations are engaged, reinforced, and/or constructed in biomedicine; it will also inform sociological theories of racial identity and medical practice.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/11/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/11/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2001954</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rebecca</FirstName>
<LastName>Jordan-Young</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Rebecca Jordan-Young</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ryoung@barnard.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000615583</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/11/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sonia</FirstName>
<LastName>Mendoza-Grey</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sonia Mendoza-Grey</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[sm3482@columbia.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000795713</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/11/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Barnard College</Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<ZipCode>100276909</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2128542708</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3009 BROADWAY</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>LPQ1NHRK78M9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>BARNARD COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Barnard College]]></Name>
<CityName>New York</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>100276598</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3009 BROADWAY]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1331</Code>
<Text>Sociology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~15970</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This study extends recent sociological work that examines genomics as a site for remaking racial and ethnic identity. Drawing on data from precision medicine efforts (recruitment sessions, seminars, and scientific publications) and interviews with precision medicine investigators, project staff, and Latinx people in targeted communities, this study scrutinizes the geneticization of the social identity of Latinx and how the Latinx population is reimagined as a genetic community to be analyzed and acted upon within precision medicine. Current nationwide efforts in precision medicine, such as <em>All of Us</em>, create a case-study through which to examine the co-production, re-inscription, and assembling of social factors and categories -- as they pertain to race, ethnicity, and cultural practices -- into biomedically significant data.&nbsp;</p> <p>Through<strong> </strong>content analysis, ethnographic observations, and key-informant interviews, this project evaluates how precision medicine investigators (i.e. researchers, recruiters, genetic counselors) conceptualize <em>Latinidad </em>as a racial, ethnic, and/or imagined genetic community. Specifically, the research begins to untangle and demonstrate how the construct of <em>Latinidad</em> is established in research endeavors, what the minimum standards of what constitutes a Latinx participant are, and illuminates the acceptable range of diversity within Latinx participant cohorts.&nbsp; Moreover, this work scrutinizes whether investigators believe there is an &ldquo;ideal&rdquo; Latinx participant or data point, and the extent to which a study participant or data point&rsquo;s <em>Latinidad</em> is co-produced and tied with geographic and racial ancestry, nationality, social experiences, and biological elements.&nbsp; Ethnographic analyses and key informant interviews specifically address and highlight discourses of racial, cultural, and genomic links between participant <em>Latinidad</em> and specific research objectives.&nbsp; Across research interests, most but not all, precision medicine endeavors took into consideration genetics, race, culture and social factors when addressing the Latinx participant or data point.&nbsp; This project probes the varying degrees at which these factors came into effect across research interests and how they come about. This is especially important given that at the conclusion of data collection for this project, there were public efforts to address the problematic and misleading use of race as a proxy for describing human genetic variation in genetics and omics research.</p> <p>Lastly, this work also examines how lay Latinx individuals make sense of their identity and how it comes into consideration when addressing health factors such as health behaviors or understandings of health risks.&nbsp; Through candid interviews, Latinx participants disclose how their nationality, racial identity, health care experiences, social experiences, and personal family histories affected their self-identity as Latinx.&nbsp; Moreover, this work also uncovers how recent clinical research, popular media, and direct to consumer genetic mapping discourses influence these self-conceptualizations for Latinx individuals.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/28/2023<br>      Modified by: Sonia&nbsp;Mendoza-Grey</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This study extends recent sociological work that examines genomics as a site for remaking racial and ethnic identity. Drawing on data from precision medicine efforts (recruitment sessions, seminars, and scientific publications) and interviews with precision medicine investigators, project staff, and Latinx people in targeted communities, this study scrutinizes the geneticization of the social identity of Latinx and how the Latinx population is reimagined as a genetic community to be analyzed and acted upon within precision medicine. Current nationwide efforts in precision medicine, such as All of Us, create a case-study through which to examine the co-production, re-inscription, and assembling of social factors and categories -- as they pertain to race, ethnicity, and cultural practices -- into biomedically significant data.   Through content analysis, ethnographic observations, and key-informant interviews, this project evaluates how precision medicine investigators (i.e. researchers, recruiters, genetic counselors) conceptualize Latinidad as a racial, ethnic, and/or imagined genetic community. Specifically, the research begins to untangle and demonstrate how the construct of Latinidad is established in research endeavors, what the minimum standards of what constitutes a Latinx participant are, and illuminates the acceptable range of diversity within Latinx participant cohorts.  Moreover, this work scrutinizes whether investigators believe there is an "ideal" Latinx participant or data point, and the extent to which a study participant or data point’s Latinidad is co-produced and tied with geographic and racial ancestry, nationality, social experiences, and biological elements.  Ethnographic analyses and key informant interviews specifically address and highlight discourses of racial, cultural, and genomic links between participant Latinidad and specific research objectives.  Across research interests, most but not all, precision medicine endeavors took into consideration genetics, race, culture and social factors when addressing the Latinx participant or data point.  This project probes the varying degrees at which these factors came into effect across research interests and how they come about. This is especially important given that at the conclusion of data collection for this project, there were public efforts to address the problematic and misleading use of race as a proxy for describing human genetic variation in genetics and omics research.  Lastly, this work also examines how lay Latinx individuals make sense of their identity and how it comes into consideration when addressing health factors such as health behaviors or understandings of health risks.  Through candid interviews, Latinx participants disclose how their nationality, racial identity, health care experiences, social experiences, and personal family histories affected their self-identity as Latinx.  Moreover, this work also uncovers how recent clinical research, popular media, and direct to consumer genetic mapping discourses influence these self-conceptualizations for Latinx individuals.          Last Modified: 08/28/2023       Submitted by: Sonia Mendoza-Grey]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
