<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Workshop to Develop a Framework for Community-Engaged Environmental Engineering Research]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>11/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>45791.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>45791</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Mamadou Diallo</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mdiallo@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924257</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The number of grant proposals including some sort of community engagement in engineering research has vastly accelerated in the past decade. Despite this great interest in "citizen science", there are currently no guidelines for effective coordination of community-engaged engineering research. The purpose of this workshop is to bring together experts in engineering, community relations, and ethics to define a framework for community engagement in engineering research. Workshop participants will examine the recent history and practice of engagement in communities by engineering researchers with a focus on effective and ethical research collaboration. The outcome of this workshop will be a new framework for the practice of community-engaged research. Through these efforts, the workshop contributes to the advancement of STEM research in service of the American public. To maximize policy impact, the workshop will be held in Washington, DC. Staff from Federal STEM agencies and professional societies will be invited to attend.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Community-engaged research creates opportunities for the public to be directly involved with forming research questions, participating in research activities of relevance to the community, and acquiring subject-matter technical expertise. However, without standards of practice, community-engaged research poses risks to both engineering researchers and, even more importantly, the communities they engage. The purpose of this workshop is to remedy this situation by defining a working framework for community engagement in engineering research. The workshop will include experts in engineering, community relations, and ethics, as well as representatives from Federal STEM agencies and engineering professional societies to maximize outreach and impact to stakeholders. This workshop will draw on the critical lessons learned from research involving human subjects to adapt to the different situations of community-engaged research. Workshop participants will examine the recent history and practice of engagement in communities by engineering researchers with the purpose of producing a new framework of engagement. This as a critical step in developing a better understanding of the protections community members and researchers need when participating in community-engaged research. The development of this framework will facilitate effective collaboration to produce scientifically defensible results and advance STEM research impact through engaged communities. As such, it will improve the scientific literacy of the Nation and increase public understanding of engineering science.&lt;br/&gt;public understanding of engineering science.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/06/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/06/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2002824</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Debbie</FirstName>
<LastName>Niemeier</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Debbie A Niemeier</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[niemeier@umd.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000230252</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/06/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Maryland, College Park</Name>
<CityName>College Park</CityName>
<ZipCode>207420001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3014056269</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3112 LEE BLDG 7809 REGENTS DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MD04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NPU8ULVAAS23</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MARYLAND, COLLEGE PARK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>KMGEN62NKEM9</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Maryland College Park]]></Name>
<CityName>College Park</CityName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>207425141</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3112 Lee Building 7809 Regents D]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MD04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1440</Code>
<Text>EnvE-Environmental Engineering</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01001920DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~45791</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>This workshop brought together experts in engineering, community relations, and ethics to define a working framework for community engagement in engineering research.</strong></p> <p>The number of grant proposals including some sort of community  engagement in engineering research has vastly accelerated the past 10  years. Community-engaged research creates opportunities for the public  to be directly involved with forming research questions, participating  in research activities of relevance to the community and acquiring  subject-matter technical expertise.&nbsp; Engineers and scientists are  increasingly serving as subject-matter experts for community-engaged  research efforts where they: guide communities on how to collect data  and samples (i.e., for traffic studies, or water and air quality  surveys); define experimental protocols appropriate for community use,  and advise on data analysis or research progress. While  relatively new in science and engineering, there is a long (and mostly  successful) history of practicing community-engaged research in fields  like public health; however, the existence of standards of  practice and norms in one discipline will not directly translate to the  needs of other fields. As the practice of community engagement increases  in engineering research, it is important to explicate the underlying  ethics of this engagement and to define the risks and protections to  both community members and researchers.</p> <p><strong>Motivation for Workshop</strong></p> <p>When science and engineering subject-matter experts collaborate with communities of non-expert citizens, it is reasonable to expect that citizens face an epistemic power imbalance. The presumption is that scientific and technical experts know more, in general, and possess more pertinent knowledge than do non-expert citizens<em></em>. Expertise often contributes to other power imbalances, such as researchers having a greater weight in decision-making or policy formation<em></em>. Such power imbalances put members of the public at a disadvantage should conflicts arise.</p> <p>In many of these research-community scenarios, community members are not <em>research subjects</em>. Instead, community members have a variety of roles. Community members may be the client (when the community asks the researcher to come in and perform a study <em>for </em>them). Community members can serve as co-researchers (when the researcher asks community members to take air samples). Community members are non-expert stakeholder-subjects (though they are not being studied, they are dependent, in some sense, on the results of the study). Finally, some community members might actually become research subjects (if, say, they needed to give urine or blood samples to test for chemical or pathogen exposure). In other words, community community-engaged research <em>can affect</em> a community member in a myriad of ways.</p> <p>Only when a community member becomes a research subject is there a legal framework for ethically approaching their involvement in the biosolids study. In every other example of how community members might be involved with community-engaged research, such a framework is lacking. Members of the public must currently rely on scientists and engineers respecting their <em>morally binding </em>duties to engage in research with integrity and hold paramount the welfare of the public. Indeed, although they may instinctively trust scientists and engineers to do the right thing, people may not even be aware what morally binding duties exist, or that such duties are not legally binding.</p> <p>This workshop produced <em>The West End Report</em>, modeled after the Belmont Report, to serve as a blueprint for guiding the formation of more specific policies and rules. Research involving communities is so fundamentally different from research involving human subjects that workshop participants agreed to follow the basic Belmont approach but insisted on developing principles designed specifically to guide research involving communities.</p> <p>In the West End Report, three ethical principles are elucidated: respect for communities, beneficence, and avoiding injustice. The report also provides three applications of these principles.</p> <p>Engineering innovations change the world in remarkable ways, often for the better. But the great power of engineering entails great responsibility. Because engineers recognize the potential for harm, as well as the benefits, to society, engineering professional societies have developed numerous codes to govern engineering practice. These engineering codes of ethics govern engineering <em>practice </em>and are not suitable to guide engineering <em>research</em>. The West End Report does not replace engineering codes of ethics. Instead, it provides a set of general ethical principles to guide engineering research, especially when that research involves communities.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/09/2022<br>      Modified by: Debbie&nbsp;A&nbsp;Niemeier</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This workshop brought together experts in engineering, community relations, and ethics to define a working framework for community engagement in engineering research.  The number of grant proposals including some sort of community  engagement in engineering research has vastly accelerated the past 10  years. Community-engaged research creates opportunities for the public  to be directly involved with forming research questions, participating  in research activities of relevance to the community and acquiring  subject-matter technical expertise.  Engineers and scientists are  increasingly serving as subject-matter experts for community-engaged  research efforts where they: guide communities on how to collect data  and samples (i.e., for traffic studies, or water and air quality  surveys); define experimental protocols appropriate for community use,  and advise on data analysis or research progress. While  relatively new in science and engineering, there is a long (and mostly  successful) history of practicing community-engaged research in fields  like public health; however, the existence of standards of  practice and norms in one discipline will not directly translate to the  needs of other fields. As the practice of community engagement increases  in engineering research, it is important to explicate the underlying  ethics of this engagement and to define the risks and protections to  both community members and researchers.  Motivation for Workshop  When science and engineering subject-matter experts collaborate with communities of non-expert citizens, it is reasonable to expect that citizens face an epistemic power imbalance. The presumption is that scientific and technical experts know more, in general, and possess more pertinent knowledge than do non-expert citizens. Expertise often contributes to other power imbalances, such as researchers having a greater weight in decision-making or policy formation. Such power imbalances put members of the public at a disadvantage should conflicts arise.  In many of these research-community scenarios, community members are not research subjects. Instead, community members have a variety of roles. Community members may be the client (when the community asks the researcher to come in and perform a study for them). Community members can serve as co-researchers (when the researcher asks community members to take air samples). Community members are non-expert stakeholder-subjects (though they are not being studied, they are dependent, in some sense, on the results of the study). Finally, some community members might actually become research subjects (if, say, they needed to give urine or blood samples to test for chemical or pathogen exposure). In other words, community community-engaged research can affect a community member in a myriad of ways.  Only when a community member becomes a research subject is there a legal framework for ethically approaching their involvement in the biosolids study. In every other example of how community members might be involved with community-engaged research, such a framework is lacking. Members of the public must currently rely on scientists and engineers respecting their morally binding duties to engage in research with integrity and hold paramount the welfare of the public. Indeed, although they may instinctively trust scientists and engineers to do the right thing, people may not even be aware what morally binding duties exist, or that such duties are not legally binding.  This workshop produced The West End Report, modeled after the Belmont Report, to serve as a blueprint for guiding the formation of more specific policies and rules. Research involving communities is so fundamentally different from research involving human subjects that workshop participants agreed to follow the basic Belmont approach but insisted on developing principles designed specifically to guide research involving communities.  In the West End Report, three ethical principles are elucidated: respect for communities, beneficence, and avoiding injustice. The report also provides three applications of these principles.  Engineering innovations change the world in remarkable ways, often for the better. But the great power of engineering entails great responsibility. Because engineers recognize the potential for harm, as well as the benefits, to society, engineering professional societies have developed numerous codes to govern engineering practice. These engineering codes of ethics govern engineering practice and are not suitable to guide engineering research. The West End Report does not replace engineering codes of ethics. Instead, it provides a set of general ethical principles to guide engineering research, especially when that research involves communities.       Last Modified: 06/09/2022       Submitted by: Debbie A Niemeier]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
