<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Networking Microbiome Research: A Symposium for a Microbiome Center Consortium]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>38608.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>38608</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Matthew Kane</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mkane@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927186</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Microbes inhabit all of Earth’s environments from the human body to oceans and soils. They are comprised of bacteria, archaea, viruses, and single-celled eukaryotes. Microbiomes reside in every known ecosystem around the globe, including many plants and animals that also host microbiomes. Microbiome research is an area of deep interest and rapid discovery across multiple institutions in the USA. As a result, microbiome centers have been established at universities, research institutes, and national labs supporting local research and education. Microbiome research is interdisciplinary in nature, cutting across ecosystems and species and scaling from microscopic entities to human health to global cycles. It also encompasses a diversity of disciplines including computer science, chemistry, organismal biology, molecular biology and more, making communication and synthesis challenging. In order to better connect both microbiome researchers and microbiome centers, a consortium of centers is proposed. This award will be used to host a conference at the University of Chicago on 16-17 Jun 2020 to begin to network microbiome centers nationally, leveraging the network for increased progress in microbiome research and its application to education and outreach. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;To achieve the goal of networking microbiome centers nationally, the conference will focus on defining a microbiome center consortium, discussing the objectives of the consortium, and developing a plan to sustain a consortium into the future. Key areas where conference proceedings will focus include: (1) Prepare researchers for the field’s rapid methodological advances by addressing where microbiome research needs new methodologies, and where existing methods require standardization and interpretation. (2) Discuss the bioinformatic challenges facing microbiome researchers to accelerate discovery and application in microbiome research. Microbiome-related data presents investigators with unique analysis challenges, both in terms of the quantity and the disparate types of data from DNA sequence data to spatial images. (3) Develop strategies for networking microbiome centers through a session with successful networked organizations that already exist in biology. Finally, the conference will seek to engage the next generation of leadership through both an undergraduate and a graduate student internship as part of the conference, as well as direct invitations to junior faculty leadership at existing microbiome centers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/18/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/18/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2002104</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Catherine</FirstName>
<LastName>Pfister</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Catherine A Pfister</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[cpfister@uchicago.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000310421</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/18/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Chicago</Name>
<CityName>CHICAGO</CityName>
<ZipCode>606375418</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7737028669</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5801 S ELLIS AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>ZUE9HKT2CLC9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CHICAGO</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>ZUE9HKT2CLC9</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Chicago]]></Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>606372612</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[6054 S. Drexel Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>085Y</Code>
<Text>ICB: Infrastructure Capacity f</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1127</Code>
<Text>Evolutionary Processes</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1128</Code>
<Text>Population &amp; Community Ecology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1440</Code>
<Text>EnvE-Environmental Engineering</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1650</Code>
<Text>BIOLOGICAL OCEANOGRAPHY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7374</Code>
<Text>Systematics &amp; Biodiversity Sci</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7381</Code>
<Text>Ecosystem Science</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~38608</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The principal goal of this award was to host a Microbiome Center Conference that would advance and network microbiome centers at the national level. Microbiome research accelerates across our country, but is often divided into those researchers in biomedical areas versus the environment. Researchers across these systems confront similar methodologies, questions and challenges. The increase in microbiome centers nationally has tried to address these challenges at the level of their institution or university. Our conference funding was designed to unite these centers and help researchers and educators form a national network. Specifically, our aims were to: 1. Prepare researchers for the field&rsquo;s rapid methodological advances, 2. Confront the bioinformatic challenges facing microbiome researchers to accelerate discovery and application in microbiome research, and 3. Develop a national network of microbiome centers. During the Covid-19 pandemic, we worked on these aims in small virtual groups, culminating in a hybrid conference in March 2022.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>We convened 85 individuals that represented a diverse group center directors and agency and NGO representatives that bridged human to environmental microbiome research and education in a hybrid format. We discussed the significant challenges of bridging microbiome research across diverse disciplines, including interagency funding, microbiome standards, and interdisciplinary research.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The principal outcome from this award included setting up a structure that allows for synergy among institutions in this critical and emerging area of science. We termed the group the <a href="https://microbiomecenters.org/">Microbiome Centers Consortium</a> (MCC), with a mission statement: "The MCC will coordinate and build on the collaborative strengths of each center in an integrated effort to accelerate advances in understanding the mechanisms underlying the structure and function of human, animal, plant, and environmental microbiomes, and to harness the power of this unseen world for positive outcomes." The MCC now includes 40 participating centers. Other significant project outcomes of the Conference included the formation of key committees, including a steering committee for the MCC. Working groups in Education, Communication, Data Standards, Mentoring/Workforce, Outreach and Advocacy, &amp; Science research were also formed. &nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/13/2023<br>      Modified by: Catherine&nbsp;A&nbsp;Pfister</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2002104/2002104_10653893_1673614960574_mcc--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2002104/2002104_10653893_1673614960574_mcc--rgov-800width.jpg" title="MCC participants"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2002104/2002104_10653893_1673614960574_mcc--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="MCC participants"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The in person participants to the Microbiome Center Consortium in March 2022 at the University of Chicago</div> <div class="imageCredit">Eddie Quinones</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Catherine&nbsp;A&nbsp;Pfister</div> <div class="imageTitle">MCC participants</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The principal goal of this award was to host a Microbiome Center Conference that would advance and network microbiome centers at the national level. Microbiome research accelerates across our country, but is often divided into those researchers in biomedical areas versus the environment. Researchers across these systems confront similar methodologies, questions and challenges. The increase in microbiome centers nationally has tried to address these challenges at the level of their institution or university. Our conference funding was designed to unite these centers and help researchers and educators form a national network. Specifically, our aims were to: 1. Prepare researchers for the field’s rapid methodological advances, 2. Confront the bioinformatic challenges facing microbiome researchers to accelerate discovery and application in microbiome research, and 3. Develop a national network of microbiome centers. During the Covid-19 pandemic, we worked on these aims in small virtual groups, culminating in a hybrid conference in March 2022.     We convened 85 individuals that represented a diverse group center directors and agency and NGO representatives that bridged human to environmental microbiome research and education in a hybrid format. We discussed the significant challenges of bridging microbiome research across diverse disciplines, including interagency funding, microbiome standards, and interdisciplinary research.     The principal outcome from this award included setting up a structure that allows for synergy among institutions in this critical and emerging area of science. We termed the group the Microbiome Centers Consortium (MCC), with a mission statement: "The MCC will coordinate and build on the collaborative strengths of each center in an integrated effort to accelerate advances in understanding the mechanisms underlying the structure and function of human, animal, plant, and environmental microbiomes, and to harness the power of this unseen world for positive outcomes." The MCC now includes 40 participating centers. Other significant project outcomes of the Conference included the formation of key committees, including a steering committee for the MCC. Working groups in Education, Communication, Data Standards, Mentoring/Workforce, Outreach and Advocacy, &amp; Science research were also formed.            Last Modified: 01/13/2023       Submitted by: Catherine A Pfister]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
