<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[CAREER: Tissue Microstructure Characterization through Exchange Mapping with Magnetic Resonance Fingerprinting]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>305774.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>305774</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Stephanie George</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>stgeorge@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927825</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[PI: Seiberlich, Nicole E.&lt;br/&gt;Proposal Number: 1553441 &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Tissue microstructure properties have been shown to change in the presence of disease, but these properties are difficult to measure quickly and accurately in vivo. The goal of this project is to develop and test a new technique, known as MRF-X, to probe in vivo tissue microstructure by using standard Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI) scanners to collect data in a new way. After optimizing the MRF-X method, the properties of both skeletal muscle and brain tissue will be measured, and differences between healthy and abnormal tissue quantified. This technique will enable researchers to study how diseases progress as well as allow physicians to examine tissue microstructure to better diagnose disease in their patients.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of this five-year project is to develop, validate, and deploy novel techniques for in vivo tissue microstructure characterization. These tissue microstructure measurements will be performed by collecting Magnetic Resonance (MR) imaging data that have been encoded to contain information about multiple tissue properties simultaneously in a manner similar to the recently introduced MR Fingerprinting technique. By optimizing the MR pulse sequence to be sensitive to variations between tissue compartments, it will be possible to collect information about microstructure which cannot currently be measured directly in vivo, including water exchange rates between tissue compartments and intracellular/extracellular volume fractions.  The specific objectives of the proposal are to: 1) Develop a technique (MRF-X) for rapid and robust in vivo quantification of volume fractions and exchange properties, 2) Characterize and validate water exchange rates and volume fraction in healthy skeletal muscle and brain tissue, 3) Explore the use of water exchange as a biomarker for disease in the brain by comparing properties of normal brain tissue and multiple sclerosis (MS) lesions, and 4) Develop formal course work and laboratory experiences linking signal processing and medical imaging for undergraduate and graduate students, introduce K-12 students to biomedical imaging and engineering, and encourage women and underrepresented minorities to pursue science and engineering. The proposed research plan involves the development of new imaging techniques with the goal of addressing fundamental questions about the nature of interactions between tissue compartments and how they are modified under pathological conditions. Using MRF-X, it will be possible to explore tissue structure and function in healthy living tissue, and also to use these new biomarkers to aid in the understanding and diagnosis of disease. The development of a robust and rapid technique for in vivo tissue microstructure characterization will ensure that the technique is immediately translatable for clinical use, potentially leading to earlier and more accurate diagnosis of disease. Moreover, it will be possible to probe the underlying mechanisms of various diseases, including but not limited to Alzheimer?s disease and MS, using MRF-X. The education and mentorship of K-12, undergraduate, and graduate students will be integrated into the research to engage students, especially women and underrepresented minorities, in biomedical imaging.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award was made by the Biomedical Engineering program of CBET was co-funded by the Mathematical Biology program of the Division of Mathematical Sciences.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/10/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/10/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2002887</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nicole</FirstName>
<LastName>Seiberlich</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nicole E Seiberlich</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[nse@med.umich.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000632345</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Regents of the University of Michigan - Ann Arbor</Name>
<CityName>ANN ARBOR</CityName>
<ZipCode>481091079</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1109 GEDDES AVE, SUITE 3300</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>GNJ7BBP73WE9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MICHIGAN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Michigan]]></Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>481091382</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[500 S. State Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5345</Code>
<Text>Engineering of Biomed Systems</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7334</Code>
<Text>MATHEMATICAL BIOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7454</Code>
<Text>MSPA-INTERDISCIPLINARY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8007</Code>
<Text>BioMaPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8091</Code>
<Text>BRAIN Initiative Res Support</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01001617DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~305773</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>In this project, my lab developed methods to measure multiple properties of tissues simultaneously using Magnetic Resonance Fingerprinting, a novel Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI) technique which was introduced in 2011.&nbsp;&nbsp;Instead of assuming that tissues are homogeneous and can be represented by a single set of tissue properties (as is commonly done in tissue property mapping with MRI), in this project we modelled tissues to be a combination of multiple compartments which may interact through chemical exchange. In this way, we were able to measure not only a composite set of tissue properties, but to differentiate different types of tissues within a single pixel of an MRI scan. This project involved first designing MRI pulse sequences that were sensitive to the presence of the different tissue components (i.e. protons at different resonance frequencies, or with different relaxation times), modeling the signals that would arise from these components, testing data collection and image reconstruction strategies, validating the results in phantoms at the MRI scanner, and finally collecting data in vivo in healthy subjects and patients to measure these different tissue properties. These methods were used to assess myelin water fraction in the brain (and exchange between different compartments in brain tissues) as well as fat/water fraction in several organs.&nbsp;&nbsp;Moreover, the idea that Magnetic Resonance Fingerprinting may be used to separate different tissue types was explored in organs such as the prostate.&nbsp;&nbsp;As a result of this project, we published four journal papers, 11 conference abstracts, and three book chapters. Four additional papers are currently in the manuscript stage, and this research has paved the way for a variety of additional research projects.</p> <p>Additionally, this project provided multiple training opportunities for graduate students, undergraduates, and high school students. Three graduate students in Biomedical Engineering at Case Western Reserve University and the University of Michigan were directly supported by this work; these students learned the basics of MRI physics, performed simulations and experiments at the MRI scanner, optimized data collection and image reconstruction strategies, and presented their work in national and international meetings.&nbsp;&nbsp;As part of the mentorship they received, we met once a week to discuss progress on their research and also make plans for their professional development.&nbsp;&nbsp;Multiple high school students and undergraduates also participated in the development of learning resources, including physical and digital phantoms to aid in the understanding of medical imaging and image reconstruction.&nbsp;</p> <p>In addition to research, several educational tools were developed as a part of this project.&nbsp;&nbsp;1) The first was a course for undergraduate students which was designed to be an inverted classroom; this course was offered at Case Western Reserve University as EBME 320:&nbsp;&nbsp;Fundamentals of Medical Imaging, and resources from this course were also provided to educators at the University of Michigan for integration into medical imaging classes here.&nbsp;&nbsp;This course was offered three times by me, and twice by a different professor at CWRU, and was rated highly by undergraduates who participated in it due to the hands-on nature of the learning process.&nbsp;&nbsp;2) A specialized tool for the visualization of magnetization in MRI using augmented reality (specifically Hololens) was designed by graduate students in the Case Western Reserve University course EBME 460: NMR Spectroscopy and Imaging.&nbsp;&nbsp;This Hololens tool was extended for teaching residents and fMRI students at the University of Michigan. 3) An outreach presentation was designed for K-12 students (with different variants depending on student age and whether the format is on-line or in person) called ?Medical Imaging: The Inside Story.? While sections of this program were meant to bring middle school students to the university campus in order to introduce them to the college setting, this portion of the project was curtailed due to COVID-19. However, this program was adapted for virtual use, and now has been presented to students in Ohio, Michigan, and Missouri; this set of presentations enables our lab to take advantage of any opportunity to connect with students that becomes available to us.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/13/2022<br>      Modified by: Nicole&nbsp;E&nbsp;Seiberlich</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ In this project, my lab developed methods to measure multiple properties of tissues simultaneously using Magnetic Resonance Fingerprinting, a novel Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI) technique which was introduced in 2011.  Instead of assuming that tissues are homogeneous and can be represented by a single set of tissue properties (as is commonly done in tissue property mapping with MRI), in this project we modelled tissues to be a combination of multiple compartments which may interact through chemical exchange. In this way, we were able to measure not only a composite set of tissue properties, but to differentiate different types of tissues within a single pixel of an MRI scan. This project involved first designing MRI pulse sequences that were sensitive to the presence of the different tissue components (i.e. protons at different resonance frequencies, or with different relaxation times), modeling the signals that would arise from these components, testing data collection and image reconstruction strategies, validating the results in phantoms at the MRI scanner, and finally collecting data in vivo in healthy subjects and patients to measure these different tissue properties. These methods were used to assess myelin water fraction in the brain (and exchange between different compartments in brain tissues) as well as fat/water fraction in several organs.  Moreover, the idea that Magnetic Resonance Fingerprinting may be used to separate different tissue types was explored in organs such as the prostate.  As a result of this project, we published four journal papers, 11 conference abstracts, and three book chapters. Four additional papers are currently in the manuscript stage, and this research has paved the way for a variety of additional research projects.  Additionally, this project provided multiple training opportunities for graduate students, undergraduates, and high school students. Three graduate students in Biomedical Engineering at Case Western Reserve University and the University of Michigan were directly supported by this work; these students learned the basics of MRI physics, performed simulations and experiments at the MRI scanner, optimized data collection and image reconstruction strategies, and presented their work in national and international meetings.  As part of the mentorship they received, we met once a week to discuss progress on their research and also make plans for their professional development.  Multiple high school students and undergraduates also participated in the development of learning resources, including physical and digital phantoms to aid in the understanding of medical imaging and image reconstruction.   In addition to research, several educational tools were developed as a part of this project.  1) The first was a course for undergraduate students which was designed to be an inverted classroom; this course was offered at Case Western Reserve University as EBME 320:  Fundamentals of Medical Imaging, and resources from this course were also provided to educators at the University of Michigan for integration into medical imaging classes here.  This course was offered three times by me, and twice by a different professor at CWRU, and was rated highly by undergraduates who participated in it due to the hands-on nature of the learning process.  2) A specialized tool for the visualization of magnetization in MRI using augmented reality (specifically Hololens) was designed by graduate students in the Case Western Reserve University course EBME 460: NMR Spectroscopy and Imaging.  This Hololens tool was extended for teaching residents and fMRI students at the University of Michigan. 3) An outreach presentation was designed for K-12 students (with different variants depending on student age and whether the format is on-line or in person) called ?Medical Imaging: The Inside Story.? While sections of this program were meant to bring middle school students to the university campus in order to introduce them to the college setting, this portion of the project was curtailed due to COVID-19. However, this program was adapted for virtual use, and now has been presented to students in Ohio, Michigan, and Missouri; this set of presentations enables our lab to take advantage of any opportunity to connect with students that becomes available to us.            Last Modified: 04/13/2022       Submitted by: Nicole E Seiberlich]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
