<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Workshop: Real Enumerative Geometry and Beyond; Nashville, TN; March 6-7, 2020]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>9000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>9000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Swatee Naik</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>snaik@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924876</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This award supports the Shanks workshop “Real Enumerative Geometry and Beyond”  that will take place on March 6-7, 2020, at Vanderbilt University, Nashville, TN. The workshop will address the latest advances in the field of mathematics known as the real enumerative geometry, with senior and junior researchers of different expertise reporting on topics of common interests. The main goal of the meeting is to facilitate discussions and collaborations in a focused setting. The small size of the workshop provides an ideal environment for graduate students and early career researchers to interact with experts in the field. A diverse group of researchers will report on new advances in the field, assuring that a vast amount of techniques are shared among its participants. The intensive and substantial exchange of a broad spectrum of ideas during the workshop is expected to stimulate further research with the aim of pushing the boundaries of this field.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;Real enumerative geometry is an area of research with a long history, which has been rapidly evolving in the recent years. The main impetus in present-day developments comes from ideas of J.-Y. Welschinger, who proposed a signed counting in the enumerative geometry of curves defined over the field of real numbers. These ideas were used to answer many long-standing questions in the enumerative geometry of real algebraic varieties through their implementation in the symplectic, tropical or algebraic geometry framework. Very recently, these ideas were adapted in the A1-homotopy theory in an attempt to answer questions in enumerative geometry over arbitrary fields. The workshop is expected to lift the barriers between the seemingly unrelated fields of real enumerative geometry and A1-homotopy theory and build bridges between these fields. Classical aspects of real enumerative geometry will be addressed by V. Kharlamov, tropical aspects by O. Viro, a symplectic geometry approach will be discussed by X. Chen and S. Tukachinsky, while recent results in A1-enumerative geometry will be presented by J. Kass, S. Pauli and I. Vogt. For more details, see the webpage of the workshop:  https://my.vanderbilt.edu/rag2020/ .&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/09/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/09/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2002974</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ioana</FirstName>
<LastName>Suvaina</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ioana Suvaina</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ioana.suvaina@vanderbilt.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000543618</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/09/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rares</FirstName>
<LastName>Rasdeaconu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Rares Rasdeaconu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[rares.rasdeaconu@vanderbilt.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000577777</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/09/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Vanderbilt University</Name>
<CityName>NASHVILLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>372032416</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6153222631</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>110 21ST AVE S</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>GTNBNWXJ12D5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>VANDERBILT UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Vanderbilt University]]></Name>
<CityName>Nashville</CityName>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>372400001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1326 Stevenson Center]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TN07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1264</Code>
<Text>ALGEBRA,NUMBER THEORY,AND COM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1267</Code>
<Text>TOPOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~9000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The workshop "Real Enumerative Geometry and Beyond" took place at Vanderbilt University on March 6-7, 2020.&nbsp;The award partially supported the travel expenses of the participants, with priority given to junior researchers and member of under-represented groups.</p> <p>The understanding of the enumerative geometry of real algebraic varieties is a long-lasting challenge. New achievements were obtained in the last decade by means of emerging new tools coming from symplectic geometry and tropical geometry combined with more traditional tools such as complex algebraic geometry and topology of manifolds. Recently, the ideas in real enumerative geometry were pushed beyond the framework of varieties defined over the field of real numbers to varieties defined over arbitrary fields via&nbsp;A1-homotopy methods.&nbsp;</p> <p>The workshop&nbsp;featured 6 contributed talks and one short presentation and&nbsp;addressed the state-of-art of the field of enumerative geometry over the reals and beyond. The talks were all of high quality and a wide variety of topics were covered. The workshop concluded with a problem session addressed to the graduate students by the senior researchers, in which several new avenues of research were proposed, and many ideas exchanged. The problem session fostered several collaborations among the attending participants. &nbsp;</p> <p>The early manifestations of the Covid-19 pandemic in the United States impacted the participation of several invited speakers and workshop participants&nbsp;and only a part of the award was spent. The remaining funds where used in the one-year, no-cost extension of the award to support the travel and lodging for young researchers attending the workshop "Interactions in Complex Geometry" organized at Vanderbilt University, Nashville, December 11-12, 2021.&nbsp;</p> <p>The NSF award was used to provide funding for 12 junior researchers (of whom 8 were graduate students and 4 were post-doctoral fellows). In the two workshops supported by the award, 5 of the invited speakers were female mathematicians (1 senior professor, 2 graduate students and 2 postdocs).</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/11/2022<br>      Modified by: Rares&nbsp;Rasdeaconu</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The workshop "Real Enumerative Geometry and Beyond" took place at Vanderbilt University on March 6-7, 2020. The award partially supported the travel expenses of the participants, with priority given to junior researchers and member of under-represented groups.  The understanding of the enumerative geometry of real algebraic varieties is a long-lasting challenge. New achievements were obtained in the last decade by means of emerging new tools coming from symplectic geometry and tropical geometry combined with more traditional tools such as complex algebraic geometry and topology of manifolds. Recently, the ideas in real enumerative geometry were pushed beyond the framework of varieties defined over the field of real numbers to varieties defined over arbitrary fields via A1-homotopy methods.   The workshop featured 6 contributed talks and one short presentation and addressed the state-of-art of the field of enumerative geometry over the reals and beyond. The talks were all of high quality and a wide variety of topics were covered. The workshop concluded with a problem session addressed to the graduate students by the senior researchers, in which several new avenues of research were proposed, and many ideas exchanged. The problem session fostered several collaborations among the attending participants.    The early manifestations of the Covid-19 pandemic in the United States impacted the participation of several invited speakers and workshop participants and only a part of the award was spent. The remaining funds where used in the one-year, no-cost extension of the award to support the travel and lodging for young researchers attending the workshop "Interactions in Complex Geometry" organized at Vanderbilt University, Nashville, December 11-12, 2021.   The NSF award was used to provide funding for 12 junior researchers (of whom 8 were graduate students and 4 were post-doctoral fellows). In the two workshops supported by the award, 5 of the invited speakers were female mathematicians (1 senior professor, 2 graduate students and 2 postdocs).          Last Modified: 07/11/2022       Submitted by: Rares Rasdeaconu]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
