<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Evaluation of Pre and Post Blast Liquefaction Soil and Site Parameters]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>49447.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>49447</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Giovanna Biscontin</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>gibiscon@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922339</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Soil liquefaction is a phenomenon that can occur in saturated, loose sand and silt sediments during earthquake shaking which causes these soils to behave as a viscous fluid.  This results in loss of strength and stiffness, often causing significant damage to civil infrastructure, such as buildings, bridges, and dams.  Advances in soil liquefaction engineering have aided engineers in prediction of the initiation of liquefaction (triggering) and its consequences, thereby reducing casualties and damage to infrastructure. However, changes in soil properties both during and following liquefaction, and the affect that these changes can have on soil stiffness and settlement require further study to improve prediction of both post-liquefaction response and behavior during future earthquake events. This Grant for Rapid Response Research (RAPID) project will leverage existing field-testing equipment available from the Natural Hazards Engineering Research Infrastructure (NHERI) RAPID facility and blast testing already occurring as part of another NSF award to measure changes in soil parameters as a result of liquefaction. Measurements will be taken before, during, and after blast-induced liquefaction tests that are scheduled in New Zealand. The blast-liquefaction testing will occur at two locations: one with natural soils and one with soils that have been improved by resin injection. The site offers the opportunity to evaluate both native soils that liquefied during the 2010-2011 Canterbury Earthquake Sequence, as well as improved soils that represent a promising ground improvement technique to mitigate differential settlements and surface manifestations of liquefaction.  The results have immediate application to regions of the United States which are prone to liquefaction.  This project will enhance international collaboration among scientists and will involve students in an international research experience.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The objective of this RAPID project is to further understand liquefaction effects on soil (e.g., shear wave velocity [VS], settlement) and site (e.g., fundamental frequency, amplification, vulnerability index) parameters by utilizing equipment from the RAPID facility to measure properties during blast-induced liquefaction testing occurring in New Zealand. Equipment that will be utilized from the NHERI RAPID facility includes: Seismometers, an instrumented dynamic cone penetrometer (DCP), multi-channel analysis of surface waves (MASW), and a 3D terrestrial laser scanner. The outcomes of this research will result in measurements of: (1) fundamental frequency and amplification factors before, immediately following liquefaction as the pore pressures dissipate, and after liquefaction when pore pressures have fully dissipated, (2) VS and DCP resistance before, immediately following, and after liquefaction, and (3) spatial ground deformations (i.e., settlement and lateral movement) at the liquefaction site using lidar scanners. A unique dataset of soil and site parameters will be created for pre and post liquefaction scenarios at two varying sites, enabling evaluation of changes in soil and site parameters as a result of liquefaction and improving our understanding of the effect of these changes on design of earthquake resilient infrastructure.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/13/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/13/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2002382</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jonathan</FirstName>
<LastName>Hubler</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jonathan Hubler</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jonathan.hubler@villanova.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000811351</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/13/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Villanova University</Name>
<CityName>VILLANOVA</CityName>
<ZipCode>190851603</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6105194220</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>800 LANCASTER AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>EYNYSU6L8ZX6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>VILLANOVA UNIVERSITY IN THE STATE OF PENNSYLVANIA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>EYNYSU6L8ZX6</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Villanova University]]></Name>
<CityName>Villanova</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>190851603</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[800 Lancaster Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>073Y</Code>
<Text>ECI-Engineering for Civil Infr</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>036E</Code>
<Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>037E</Code>
<Text>GEOTECHNICAL ENGINEERING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>038E</Code>
<Text>FOUNDATION ENGINEERING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>041E</Code>
<Text>HAZARD AND DISASTER REDUCTION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>043E</Code>
<Text>EARTHQUAKE ENGINEERING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1576</Code>
<Text>NATIONL EARTHQK HZRD REDCT PRG</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>172E</Code>
<Text>Geomechanics</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5941</Code>
<Text>NEW ZEALAND</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~49447</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The objective of this project was to measure changes in soil and site parameters (e.g., shear wave velocity, cone tip resistance) as a result of soil liquefaction. Measurements were performed before, during, and after blast liquefaction testing at a test site in Christchurch, New Zealand, using field testing equipment available from the Natural Hazards Engineering Research Infrastructure (NHERI) RAPID facility. The blast liquefaction testing was performed at two locations at the test site: one with natural soils and one with soils that were improved by resin injection. A research team comprised of both US and international collaborators collected data to evaluate performance of the natural and resin injected soils. Equipment that was used for testing from the RAPID facility in this project included seismometers, an instrumented dynamic cone penetrometer (DCP), a multi-channel analysis of surface waves (MASW) setup, and a 3D terrestrial laser scanner.</p> <p>The results from multiple field testing methods contribute to advancing our understanding of soil liquefaction. Instrumented dynamic cone penetration tests were performed in both the natural and resin injected soils and showed good agreement with conventional cone penetration tests performed at the site. Cone tip resistance of the soil decreased following liquefaction in the natural soil; however, cone tip resistance in the resin injected soil showed little to no decrease following liquefaction. Shear wave velocity was measured 0.5, 4, and 24 hours following blast liquefaction and compared to pre-blast values. Shear wave velocity of the natural soils was found to decrease after blasting and not fully recover to pre-blast values for some layers. The measurement of shear wave velocity over a 24-hour period provides more data in the literature on the post-liquefaction behavior of soils. The findings from this project have the potential to improve our understanding of liquefaction induced changes, leading to updates in design approaches for liquefaction testing and mitigation.</p> <p>One graduate student gained international research experience by traveling to New Zealand to perform field testing. The student was trained to use research equipment and involved in data collection, analysis, and results dissemination. Additionally, one female undergraduate student aided in data analysis. Further research collaborations with international partners have been pursued as a result of this project.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/30/2023<br>      Modified by: Jonathan&nbsp;Hubler</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2002382/2002382_10647207_1680223398310_Image3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2002382/2002382_10647207_1680223398310_Image3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Blast Test Site"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2002382/2002382_10647207_1680223398310_Image3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Blast Test Site"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">MASW Setup at Blast Test Site - Christchurch, NZ</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jonathan Hubler</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jonathan&nbsp;Hubler</div> <div class="imageTitle">Blast Test Site</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2002382/2002382_10647207_1680224231986_Image4--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2002382/2002382_10647207_1680224231986_Image4--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Instrumented DCP"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2002382/2002382_10647207_1680224231986_Image4--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Instrumented DCP"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">PANDA DCP in use following Blast Testing - Christchurch, NZ</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jonathan Hubler</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jonathan&nbsp;Hubler</div> <div class="imageTitle">Instrumented DCP</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The objective of this project was to measure changes in soil and site parameters (e.g., shear wave velocity, cone tip resistance) as a result of soil liquefaction. Measurements were performed before, during, and after blast liquefaction testing at a test site in Christchurch, New Zealand, using field testing equipment available from the Natural Hazards Engineering Research Infrastructure (NHERI) RAPID facility. The blast liquefaction testing was performed at two locations at the test site: one with natural soils and one with soils that were improved by resin injection. A research team comprised of both US and international collaborators collected data to evaluate performance of the natural and resin injected soils. Equipment that was used for testing from the RAPID facility in this project included seismometers, an instrumented dynamic cone penetrometer (DCP), a multi-channel analysis of surface waves (MASW) setup, and a 3D terrestrial laser scanner.  The results from multiple field testing methods contribute to advancing our understanding of soil liquefaction. Instrumented dynamic cone penetration tests were performed in both the natural and resin injected soils and showed good agreement with conventional cone penetration tests performed at the site. Cone tip resistance of the soil decreased following liquefaction in the natural soil; however, cone tip resistance in the resin injected soil showed little to no decrease following liquefaction. Shear wave velocity was measured 0.5, 4, and 24 hours following blast liquefaction and compared to pre-blast values. Shear wave velocity of the natural soils was found to decrease after blasting and not fully recover to pre-blast values for some layers. The measurement of shear wave velocity over a 24-hour period provides more data in the literature on the post-liquefaction behavior of soils. The findings from this project have the potential to improve our understanding of liquefaction induced changes, leading to updates in design approaches for liquefaction testing and mitigation.  One graduate student gained international research experience by traveling to New Zealand to perform field testing. The student was trained to use research equipment and involved in data collection, analysis, and results dissemination. Additionally, one female undergraduate student aided in data analysis. Further research collaborations with international partners have been pursued as a result of this project.          Last Modified: 03/30/2023       Submitted by: Jonathan Hubler]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
