<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[I-Corps: Smart Compression Garments for Fitness and Athletics]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ruth Shuman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rshuman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922160</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this I-Corps project is to commercialize smart compression garments for enhancing performance gains during fitness, athletic training, and rehabilitation.  The products to be commercialized are intended to address important needs in health and training that may be of interest to many fitness enthusiasts, amateur or professional athletes, and individuals recovering from physical challenges. This could include millions of individuals in the United States.  The potential benefits for society and the economy are commensurately high.  In the long term, this project may hold benefits for a large number of individuals that personally or professionally engage in physically demanding activities in the workplace, or that require physical assistance for activities of daily living. The underlying technology holds the potential to enable applications in healthcare and assistive and rehabilitative devices that could improve quality of life.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project is based on the development of a fabric technology that consists of a soft, muscle-like robotic fabric, that uses an actuated composite polymer textile.  These actuated textiles consist of composite fabric structures that integrate an elastic-hydraulic transmission. Previous research revealed that the textiles are capable of supplying large, dynamic forces or displacements via soft fabrics that may be fashioned into wearable garments, which may be fabricated using facile textile manufacturing methods. This technology holds the potential to enable a wide variety of wearable garments with applications in fitness, healthcare, and many other areas.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/30/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/30/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2002529</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yon</FirstName>
<LastName>Visell</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Yon Visell</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[yonvisell@ece.ucsb.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000640346</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/30/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Santa Barbara</Name>
<CityName>SANTA BARBARA</CityName>
<ZipCode>931060001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8058934188</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3227 CHEADLE HALL</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>24</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA24</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>G9QBQDH39DF4</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, SANTA BARBARA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>NUDGYLBB4S99</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Santa Barbara]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>931062050</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>24</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA24</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="p1">This NSF I-Corps Project was directed at commercializing smart compression garments for increasing the gains that athletes experience during training. Findings from the project, obtained through extensive mentoring by I-Corps staff and via interviews with more than 100 stakeholders, highlight the important needs this product and technology could meet in supporting the activities of thousands of athletes, stakeholders, and teams, both professional and amateur.<span>&nbsp; </span>During the course of the project, the team was able to select a sector of athletics that was determined to be most suitable for initial commercialization activities, based on a combination of unmet needs reported by stakeholders and economic analyses.<span>&nbsp; </span>The number of individual beneficiaries and the economic dimensions, as analyzed during the project, further highlight the large potential benefits for society and the economy that could results from this commercialization activity.<span>&nbsp; </span>Future devices similar to the one the team aims to commercialize, also enabled by the technology that this project was focused on, have significant potential broader impacts through their application in related areas of great societal and economic significance.<span>&nbsp; </span>These include potential applications for improving rehabilitation of injuries sustained by millions of athletes and non-athletes each year, thus reducing costs and improving quality of life for many individuals.<br /><br />This I-Corps project was directed at commercializing a fabric technology previously developed in the lab of the principal investigator. This fabric technology enables soft, muscle-like robotic textiles that integrate an elastic-hydraulic transmission. Previous research revealed that the textiles are capable of supplying large, dynamic forces or displacements via soft fabrics that may be fashioned into wearable garments, which may be fabricated using facile textile manufacturing methods. This technology holds the potential to enable a wide variety of wearable garments with applications in fitness, healthcare, and many other areas.<br /><br />This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/27/2021<br>      Modified by: Yon&nbsp;Visell</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[This NSF I-Corps Project was directed at commercializing smart compression garments for increasing the gains that athletes experience during training. Findings from the project, obtained through extensive mentoring by I-Corps staff and via interviews with more than 100 stakeholders, highlight the important needs this product and technology could meet in supporting the activities of thousands of athletes, stakeholders, and teams, both professional and amateur.  During the course of the project, the team was able to select a sector of athletics that was determined to be most suitable for initial commercialization activities, based on a combination of unmet needs reported by stakeholders and economic analyses.  The number of individual beneficiaries and the economic dimensions, as analyzed during the project, further highlight the large potential benefits for society and the economy that could results from this commercialization activity.  Future devices similar to the one the team aims to commercialize, also enabled by the technology that this project was focused on, have significant potential broader impacts through their application in related areas of great societal and economic significance.  These include potential applications for improving rehabilitation of injuries sustained by millions of athletes and non-athletes each year, thus reducing costs and improving quality of life for many individuals.  This I-Corps project was directed at commercializing a fabric technology previously developed in the lab of the principal investigator. This fabric technology enables soft, muscle-like robotic textiles that integrate an elastic-hydraulic transmission. Previous research revealed that the textiles are capable of supplying large, dynamic forces or displacements via soft fabrics that may be fashioned into wearable garments, which may be fabricated using facile textile manufacturing methods. This technology holds the potential to enable a wide variety of wearable garments with applications in fitness, healthcare, and many other areas.  This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.          Last Modified: 12/27/2021       Submitted by: Yon Visell]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
