<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research: Women of Color and Computing Conference Wahine: Culturally Responsive Collective Catalysts]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>48933.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>48933</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jeffrey Forbes</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jforbes@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925301</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This project supports a March 2020 conference, Women of Color in STEM Entrepreneurship Conference.  The conference focuses on both underrepresented adults and girls of color from Hawaii, Alaska, Saipan and Guam. Arizona State will participate in a 5-day, residential camp at Kohala Institute. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The contribution to the field will include: capturing the views of women and girls of color regarding the design of inclusive culturally responsive practices in computing, and enabling inter-generational perspectives to inform theory and practice.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/21/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/21/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2002734</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kimberly</FirstName>
<LastName>Scott</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kimberly A Scott</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[kascott3@asu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000190727</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/21/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Arizona State University</Name>
<CityName>TEMPE</CityName>
<ZipCode>852813670</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4809655479</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>660 S MILL AVENUE STE 204</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AZ04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NTLHJXM55KZ6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ARIZONA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Arizona State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Tempe</CityName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>852813665</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[660 S Mill Ave, Suite 312]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AZ04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>134Y</Code>
<Text>CSforAll-Computer Sci for All</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~48933</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The 4th Women of Color in Science, Technology, Engineering and Math (STEM) Entrepreneurship Conference: Wahine: Culturally Responsive Collective Catalyst, was held in the cultural context of Hawai&#699;i. The proposed plan was to interweave a successful recurring Women of Color in STEM conference with a(separately funded) Girls in Tech residential camp experience for middle and high school girls, with shared activities and purposeful interaction. The Women of Color in STEM community has a record of tracking participation trends in computer science courses and careers, examining innovations and strategies to accelerate career advancement, investment and entrepreneurship practices, and ways to counter negative ideological, institutional, and relational biases that influence tech experiences.</p> <p>The Covid pandemic significantly altered the original plan.&nbsp; Instead of two co-located, synergistic projects, each proceeded independently.&nbsp; This project shifted changed from an in-person conference scheduled for March 2020 to a 3-day virtual conference in March 2021. Despite the format change, the conference fostered numerous connections and collaborations among attendees working across the system to increase STEM participation among girls and women of color. Already known as a hub for individuals working across the system to transform STEM for an inclusive future, the conference asked attendees to formulate a future where girls and women of color leading as techno-social change agents aren't the exception; they are the expectation. The multicultural context of Hawai&#699;i was an appropriate location to begin to address these challenges. Local mana wahine had been engaged at the outset as both advisors and planning team members. Various features, such as &#699;&#332;iwi protocol, were included in the agenda, along with plans for local STEM professionals to present or moderate substantive sessions.&nbsp; Grounded in a spirit of aloha, attendees represented 21 states, Ireland, New Zealand, and Saipan. Most participants identified as White, followed by African American, Mixed, Asian, Pacific Islander, and American Indian. Most came from university settings, the next largest groups identified as educators, then researchers, students, the non-profit sector, and other.</p> <p>Attendees learned about challenges and solutions from multiple perspectives as they deliberated with others to advance innovative ideas in a range of interactive sessions. Presenters represented a range of fields including STEM, the social sciences, education, law, strategic planning, and culturally responsive computing. Attendees found inspiration, support, and solidarity in their common goal to transform STEM for an inclusive future. The shared goal was to create a decade-long systems ecology that would define a more equitable system for underrepresented girls and women of color to embrace leadership roles in computer science as techno-social change agents. The 10-year plan was initiated by attendees. At the close of meeting, participants agreed to nominate a planning team, who would secure partners and begin to identify key areas of focus to help close gender and diversity gaps in STEM. Initial strategies put forward included: supporting girls across their lifespans in STEM professions; collaborating to create culturally sustaining and revitalizing curricula; calling out the -isms (racism, sexism, ableism, homophobia); engaging worthwhile funding agents for education and basic needs; changing hiring practices (quota are essential); enlisting role models and mentors on a large scale; showcasing women of color in STEM in media initiatives; targeting funding support for women of color who are students and their support groups; strategic networking to connect women of color with peers and companies for internships and job openings; outreaching directly to companies who support/are stakeholders in STEM activities.</p> <p>Going forward, convening a conference addressing these issues that includes professional women in STEM and pre-professional youth would realize the vision of the originally proposed model, and would be a satisfying check on our progress toward the 10-year plan that includes early exposure to computing opportunities, relevant curriculum, and access to appropriate role models and mentors, including industry experts, computer science practitioners, and academic leaders who can immerse them in real tech world experiences, while utilizing strategies listed above.&nbsp; &nbsp;Building this system and reinforcing this network promises to provide the sustained support throughout the STEM education and career pipeline for underrepresented women and non-binary people.&nbsp; This in turn holds great promise for broader participation in STEM professions, ultimately invigorating and offering long term diversity and stability to this sector of our economy.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/07/2023<br>      Modified by: Kimberly&nbsp;A&nbsp;Scott</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The 4th Women of Color in Science, Technology, Engineering and Math (STEM) Entrepreneurship Conference: Wahine: Culturally Responsive Collective Catalyst, was held in the cultural context of Hawai&#699;i. The proposed plan was to interweave a successful recurring Women of Color in STEM conference with a(separately funded) Girls in Tech residential camp experience for middle and high school girls, with shared activities and purposeful interaction. The Women of Color in STEM community has a record of tracking participation trends in computer science courses and careers, examining innovations and strategies to accelerate career advancement, investment and entrepreneurship practices, and ways to counter negative ideological, institutional, and relational biases that influence tech experiences.  The Covid pandemic significantly altered the original plan.  Instead of two co-located, synergistic projects, each proceeded independently.  This project shifted changed from an in-person conference scheduled for March 2020 to a 3-day virtual conference in March 2021. Despite the format change, the conference fostered numerous connections and collaborations among attendees working across the system to increase STEM participation among girls and women of color. Already known as a hub for individuals working across the system to transform STEM for an inclusive future, the conference asked attendees to formulate a future where girls and women of color leading as techno-social change agents aren't the exception; they are the expectation. The multicultural context of Hawai&#699;i was an appropriate location to begin to address these challenges. Local mana wahine had been engaged at the outset as both advisors and planning team members. Various features, such as &#699;&#332;iwi protocol, were included in the agenda, along with plans for local STEM professionals to present or moderate substantive sessions.  Grounded in a spirit of aloha, attendees represented 21 states, Ireland, New Zealand, and Saipan. Most participants identified as White, followed by African American, Mixed, Asian, Pacific Islander, and American Indian. Most came from university settings, the next largest groups identified as educators, then researchers, students, the non-profit sector, and other.  Attendees learned about challenges and solutions from multiple perspectives as they deliberated with others to advance innovative ideas in a range of interactive sessions. Presenters represented a range of fields including STEM, the social sciences, education, law, strategic planning, and culturally responsive computing. Attendees found inspiration, support, and solidarity in their common goal to transform STEM for an inclusive future. The shared goal was to create a decade-long systems ecology that would define a more equitable system for underrepresented girls and women of color to embrace leadership roles in computer science as techno-social change agents. The 10-year plan was initiated by attendees. At the close of meeting, participants agreed to nominate a planning team, who would secure partners and begin to identify key areas of focus to help close gender and diversity gaps in STEM. Initial strategies put forward included: supporting girls across their lifespans in STEM professions; collaborating to create culturally sustaining and revitalizing curricula; calling out the -isms (racism, sexism, ableism, homophobia); engaging worthwhile funding agents for education and basic needs; changing hiring practices (quota are essential); enlisting role models and mentors on a large scale; showcasing women of color in STEM in media initiatives; targeting funding support for women of color who are students and their support groups; strategic networking to connect women of color with peers and companies for internships and job openings; outreaching directly to companies who support/are stakeholders in STEM activities.  Going forward, convening a conference addressing these issues that includes professional women in STEM and pre-professional youth would realize the vision of the originally proposed model, and would be a satisfying check on our progress toward the 10-year plan that includes early exposure to computing opportunities, relevant curriculum, and access to appropriate role models and mentors, including industry experts, computer science practitioners, and academic leaders who can immerse them in real tech world experiences, while utilizing strategies listed above.   Building this system and reinforcing this network promises to provide the sustained support throughout the STEM education and career pipeline for underrepresented women and non-binary people.  This in turn holds great promise for broader participation in STEM professions, ultimately invigorating and offering long term diversity and stability to this sector of our economy.       Last Modified: 09/07/2023       Submitted by: Kimberly A Scott]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
