<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[PostDoctoral Research Fellowship]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>150000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>150000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Andrew Pollington</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>adpollin@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924878</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This award is made as part of the FY 2020 Mathematical Sciences Postdoctoral Research Fellowships Program. Each of the fellowships supports a research and training project at a host institution in the mathematical sciences, including applications to other disciplines, under the mentorship of a sponsoring scientist.  The title of the project for this fellowship to David A Jekel is "PDE Methods in Free Probability."  The host institution for the fellowship is University of California San Diego, and the sponsoring scientist is Todd Kemp.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/20/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/20/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2002826</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Jekel</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David A Jekel</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<NSF_ID>000811099</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/20/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Jekel, David A</Name>
<CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
<ZipCode>90095</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>36</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA36</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[UCSD Department of Mathematics]]></Name>
<CityName>La Jolla</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>920930112</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>50</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA50</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>060Y</Code>
<Text>Workforce (MSPRF) MathSciPDFel</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9219</Code>
<Text>POSTDOCTORAL FELLOWSHIPS IN MATH SCIENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~150000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>David Jekel served as postdoctoral researcher at University of California, San Diego, supported by a grant from the NSF&rsquo;s <strong>Mathematical Sciences Postdoctoral Research Fellowship program.&nbsp; </strong>His supervisor was <strong>Todd Kemp</strong> and he also worked closely with <strong>Adrian Ioana</strong>.&nbsp; He submitted <strong>eleven papers </strong>(with various collaborators) since starting the postdoctoral fellowship, seven of which have already been accepted for publication, and there are many projects still ongoing.</p> <p>Jekel&rsquo;s research focused on <strong>free probability</strong>, which describes the behavior of large random matrices.&nbsp; Matrices are N x N grids of numbers that describe linear transformations of N-dimensional space (such as rotation, scaling, shearing, etc.).&nbsp; When choosing an N x N matrix (or several matrices) randomly according to certain laws, the behavior of the matrices in the limit as N goes to infinity can be described by free probability.&nbsp; In free probability, the matrices are replaced by infinite-dimensional operators, such as come up in the study of quantum mechanics.&nbsp; Jekel focused on bringing more tools from classical probability theory, optimal transport, partial differential equations, and stochastic analysis into free probability theory, which was one of his main research goals for this grant.&nbsp; He also explored new connections of free probability with other subjects in operator algebras, such as the model theory of von Neumann algebras.</p> <p>Jekel <strong>presented his research at conferences and local seminars</strong> in the US and in Europe.&nbsp; Jekel gained experience in <strong>event organization</strong> by co-organizing a special session at the International Workshop on Operator Theory and Applications in summer 2022 (with Janusz Wysoczan&#786;ski and Vitonofrio Crismalev) and a special session at the Joint Mathematics Meetings in 2023 (with Sarah Browne and Priyanga Ganesan).</p> <p>Jekel was active in <strong>networking with and mentoring</strong> <strong>other early-career researchers</strong>.&nbsp; He was active in OTTER (operator theory talks for early-career researchers) in 2020-2021 and the Operator Algebras Mentor Network in 2021-2023.&nbsp; In summer 2021, he gave a presentation at GOALS (groundwork for operator algebras lecture series), a summer school for graduate students. &nbsp;Jekel started online reading groups about several current research topics which fostered cross-institutional collaboration among graduate students and postdocs in operator algebras.&nbsp; He also spent a lot of time working with Kemp and Ioana&rsquo;s graduate students.&nbsp; Jekel collaborated with graduate students on three of the papers mentioned above.</p> <p>During the last two out of three years, Jekel served simultaneously as a lecturer (instructor) for the mathematics department at UCSD.&nbsp; He <strong>taught probability theory, introduction to proofs, and ordinary differential equations</strong>.&nbsp; His teaching style emphasized accessible and understandable lectures, class participation, interaction in office hours, and giving students multiple opportunities to demonstrate mastery.&nbsp; He also supervised reading courses for dozens of undergraduates.</p> <p>To better understand issues of <strong>social justice in mathematics</strong>, Jekel attended the paraDIGMS conference as well as Pamela Harris and Aris Winger&rsquo;s webinars on supporting students of color in mathematics, which have influenced both his course instruction and his mentoring.&nbsp; Jekel also volunteered as a tutor for San Diego Refugee Tutoring during his whole time in San Diego.&nbsp; When the JMM in 2022 was changed to remote because of covid, Jekel worked with Jaime Haddock and Christelle Vincent to organize aid for students dealing with plane ticket cancellation costs, and he has advocated for remote access and covid safety at conferences.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/17/2023<br>      Modified by: David&nbsp;A&nbsp;Jekel</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ David Jekel served as postdoctoral researcher at University of California, San Diego, supported by a grant from the NSF’s Mathematical Sciences Postdoctoral Research Fellowship program.  His supervisor was Todd Kemp and he also worked closely with Adrian Ioana.  He submitted eleven papers (with various collaborators) since starting the postdoctoral fellowship, seven of which have already been accepted for publication, and there are many projects still ongoing.  Jekel’s research focused on free probability, which describes the behavior of large random matrices.  Matrices are N x N grids of numbers that describe linear transformations of N-dimensional space (such as rotation, scaling, shearing, etc.).  When choosing an N x N matrix (or several matrices) randomly according to certain laws, the behavior of the matrices in the limit as N goes to infinity can be described by free probability.  In free probability, the matrices are replaced by infinite-dimensional operators, such as come up in the study of quantum mechanics.  Jekel focused on bringing more tools from classical probability theory, optimal transport, partial differential equations, and stochastic analysis into free probability theory, which was one of his main research goals for this grant.  He also explored new connections of free probability with other subjects in operator algebras, such as the model theory of von Neumann algebras.  Jekel presented his research at conferences and local seminars in the US and in Europe.  Jekel gained experience in event organization by co-organizing a special session at the International Workshop on Operator Theory and Applications in summer 2022 (with Janusz Wysoczan&#786;ski and Vitonofrio Crismalev) and a special session at the Joint Mathematics Meetings in 2023 (with Sarah Browne and Priyanga Ganesan).  Jekel was active in networking with and mentoring other early-career researchers.  He was active in OTTER (operator theory talks for early-career researchers) in 2020-2021 and the Operator Algebras Mentor Network in 2021-2023.  In summer 2021, he gave a presentation at GOALS (groundwork for operator algebras lecture series), a summer school for graduate students.  Jekel started online reading groups about several current research topics which fostered cross-institutional collaboration among graduate students and postdocs in operator algebras.  He also spent a lot of time working with Kemp and Ioana’s graduate students.  Jekel collaborated with graduate students on three of the papers mentioned above.  During the last two out of three years, Jekel served simultaneously as a lecturer (instructor) for the mathematics department at UCSD.  He taught probability theory, introduction to proofs, and ordinary differential equations.  His teaching style emphasized accessible and understandable lectures, class participation, interaction in office hours, and giving students multiple opportunities to demonstrate mastery.  He also supervised reading courses for dozens of undergraduates.  To better understand issues of social justice in mathematics, Jekel attended the paraDIGMS conference as well as Pamela Harris and Aris Winger’s webinars on supporting students of color in mathematics, which have influenced both his course instruction and his mentoring.  Jekel also volunteered as a tutor for San Diego Refugee Tutoring during his whole time in San Diego.  When the JMM in 2022 was changed to remote because of covid, Jekel worked with Jaime Haddock and Christelle Vincent to organize aid for students dealing with plane ticket cancellation costs, and he has advocated for remote access and covid safety at conferences.          Last Modified: 07/17/2023       Submitted by: David A Jekel]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
