<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[NSFGEO-NERC: Adjoint tomography of mantle viscosity using deglacial sea level observations]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>408003.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>408003</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Eva Zanzerkia</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ezanzerk@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924734</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Future sea level change in response to ongoing warming is of societal concern. Adapting to rising seas is a pressing challenge for public health, coastal infrastructure, and economic stability. Sea level today and in the past changes due to the addition of meltwater to the ocean basins, but also due to uplift or sinking of coastlines. One reason for the warping of Earth’s surface is that major ice sheets during the last glacial maximum have pressed down on Earth’s surface and released it as they melt. The investigators will use computational modeling to simulate how sea level and the solid Earth change in response to changing ice sheets over the past 25,000 years when Earth transitioned out of a glacial maximum. To calibrate their model, the team compares their predictions to more than 13,000 sea level observations from the geologic record. That allows them to improve the model and in particular better understand Earth’s internal viscosity, which is a key parameter in these sea level models. This work will allow the team to answer fundamental questions about how fast or slowly Earth’s interior deforms, but also how much solid Earth deformation contributes to sea level change along coastlines today. This is particularly relevant for cities along the U.S. East and West coast in which solid Earth deformation contributes a similar amount of sea level rise compared to warming oceans and melting ice sheets.  This project will train two postdoctoral research scientists and one graduate student in an international and highly interdisciplinary setting to understand Earth's internal structure, its climatic history and the pace and magnitude of global change.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The viscosity of Earth's mantle varies radially and laterally as a result of its complex thermal structure.  While it is known from seismology, geodynamics, mineral physics, and sea level observations that these variations exist, they are difficult to constrain. Through glacial isostatic adjustment (GIA) -- the viscoelastic response of the Earth to waxing and waning ice sheets -- this incomplete knowledge propagates into questions of past ice sheets and sea level change. This proposal constitutes an effort to better understand Earth rheology and its implications for cryosphere evolution. The novel aspect proposed here is to invert sea level, geodetic, and gravitational observations for rheology and deglacial ice sheet changes using gradient-based optimization. Model gradients will be efficiently calculated using the adjoint method. This framework allows the investigators to move beyond a limited set of forward simulations and enables them for the first time to efficiently assimilate sea level data and other GIA observations into a 3D GIA model. The international team will use a newly compiled dataset with over 13,000 datapoints of deglacial sea level to produce the first tomographic image of Earth's internal viscosity structure. They will furthermore use this approach to produce ice sheet reconstructions that are consistent with 3D Earth models. In addition to exploring trade-offs between the Earth and ice structure, the team will develop and implement second-order adjoint equations to assess uncertainty propagation. The model output will allow the investigators to address two targeted research questions, (1) the amount of melt or re-advance of different ice sheets during the Holocene and (2) the present-day contribution of GIA and its uncertainty to sea level change in major coastal cities.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This is a project that is jointly funded by the National Science Foundation’s Directorate of Geosciences (NSF/GEO) and the National  Environment Research Council (UKRI/NERC) of the United Kingdom (UK) via the NSF/GEO-NERC Lead Agency Agreement. This Agreement allows a single joint US/UK proposal to be submitted and peer-reviewed by the Agency whose investigator has the largest proportion of the budget. Upon successful joint determination of an award, each Agency funds the proportion of the budget and the investigators associated with its own investigators and component of the work.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/10/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/16/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2002352</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jacqueline</FirstName>
<LastName>Austermann</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jacqueline Austermann</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ja3170@columbia.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000728791</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Columbia University</Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<ZipCode>10027</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2128546851</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>202 LOW LIBRARY 535 W 116 ST MC</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>F4N1QNPB95M4</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF COLUMBIA UNIVERSITY IN THE CITY OF NEW YORK, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>F4N1QNPB95M4</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Lamont-Doherty Earth Observatory]]></Name>
<CityName>Palisades</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>109641707</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[61 Route 9W]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1574</Code>
<Text>Geophysics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1031</Code>
<Text>STUDIES OF THE EARTH'S DEEP INTERIOR</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~213603</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~194400</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The main goal of this proposal was to develop computational tools that allow us to better image properties of Earth&rsquo;s interior, specifically its viscosity. The viscosity of a material determines how (quickly) it deforms when pressure is applied. On Earth, ice sheets that grow and melt over the glacial cycle exert pressure on Earth&rsquo;s surface that deforms its interior and shape. A result of this deformation is uplift and subsidence along coastlines that is recorded as sea level change. We can therefore use sea level observations to image viscosity of Earth&rsquo;s interior.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>This proposal focused on the last deglaciation from approx. 26,000 years ago to present for which over 10,000 paleo sea level observations exist. First, we developed the theory and implemented code to calculate so-called sensitivity kernels. A sensitivity kernel for viscosity of a specific sea level observation is a 3D map of Earth&rsquo;s interior that indicates which part affects the observation. In other words, it shows where viscosity needs to increase or decrease in order to change the predicted sea level at the observation site. When sensitivity kernels are paired with observations they can guide where viscosity in Earth&rsquo;s interior needs to be changed in order to better match observations. In the second step we investigated how well the existing sea level data can possibly constrain or image Earth&rsquo;s internal viscosity with this approach. To do so we produced synthetic sea level data, meaning sea level data that have been produced with a target viscosity field. We then use these synthetic data to try to retrieve this target viscosity field back from the data. We find that the data can in fact recover some of the structure in the target viscosity field, namely viscosity near the observation site within the shallow Earth and globally at deeper depths. The development of this approach and its proof of concept lay the foundation for applying it to real observations and imaging Earth&rsquo;s viscosity.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>In a separate strand of this project, we used the over 10,000 datapoints over the deglaciation to further investigate ice sheet change over the last 11,700 years. This time period is particularly interesting because slightly elevated temperatures during parts of this time may have caused retreat of the Antarctic ice sheet beyond its present margin. We combined sea level observations, ice sheet reconstructions, and models of Earth deformation and found that it is indeed likely that global mean sea level was higher during the last 7,500 thousand years compared to early industrial levels. We also find that the Antarctic Ice Sheet was a likely contributor to this higher sea level and that its melting lagged air temperatures by around 250 years. Comparing our reconstruction to future projections indicates that even under the lowest emission scenario, global mean sea level rise in the next 125 years will very likely be the fastest in the last 5,000 years, and that by 2080 GMSL will as likely as not be the highest in 115,000 years.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>In this project we also developed a web interface that allows mapping predictions of sea level change over the deglaciation. The grant contributed directly to the educational training of one graduate student, one postdoctoral researcher, and two junior faculty. Results of this work have been disseminated at conferences, in publications, and during a summer school.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/13/2023<br>      Modified by: Jacqueline&nbsp;Austermann</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The main goal of this proposal was to develop computational tools that allow us to better image properties of Earth’s interior, specifically its viscosity. The viscosity of a material determines how (quickly) it deforms when pressure is applied. On Earth, ice sheets that grow and melt over the glacial cycle exert pressure on Earth’s surface that deforms its interior and shape. A result of this deformation is uplift and subsidence along coastlines that is recorded as sea level change. We can therefore use sea level observations to image viscosity of Earth’s interior.     This proposal focused on the last deglaciation from approx. 26,000 years ago to present for which over 10,000 paleo sea level observations exist. First, we developed the theory and implemented code to calculate so-called sensitivity kernels. A sensitivity kernel for viscosity of a specific sea level observation is a 3D map of Earth’s interior that indicates which part affects the observation. In other words, it shows where viscosity needs to increase or decrease in order to change the predicted sea level at the observation site. When sensitivity kernels are paired with observations they can guide where viscosity in Earth’s interior needs to be changed in order to better match observations. In the second step we investigated how well the existing sea level data can possibly constrain or image Earth’s internal viscosity with this approach. To do so we produced synthetic sea level data, meaning sea level data that have been produced with a target viscosity field. We then use these synthetic data to try to retrieve this target viscosity field back from the data. We find that the data can in fact recover some of the structure in the target viscosity field, namely viscosity near the observation site within the shallow Earth and globally at deeper depths. The development of this approach and its proof of concept lay the foundation for applying it to real observations and imaging Earth’s viscosity.     In a separate strand of this project, we used the over 10,000 datapoints over the deglaciation to further investigate ice sheet change over the last 11,700 years. This time period is particularly interesting because slightly elevated temperatures during parts of this time may have caused retreat of the Antarctic ice sheet beyond its present margin. We combined sea level observations, ice sheet reconstructions, and models of Earth deformation and found that it is indeed likely that global mean sea level was higher during the last 7,500 thousand years compared to early industrial levels. We also find that the Antarctic Ice Sheet was a likely contributor to this higher sea level and that its melting lagged air temperatures by around 250 years. Comparing our reconstruction to future projections indicates that even under the lowest emission scenario, global mean sea level rise in the next 125 years will very likely be the fastest in the last 5,000 years, and that by 2080 GMSL will as likely as not be the highest in 115,000 years.     In this project we also developed a web interface that allows mapping predictions of sea level change over the deglaciation. The grant contributed directly to the educational training of one graduate student, one postdoctoral researcher, and two junior faculty. Results of this work have been disseminated at conferences, in publications, and during a summer school.       Last Modified: 10/13/2023       Submitted by: Jacqueline Austermann]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
