<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Doctoral Dissertation Research: A Multi-Scalar Analysis of Environmental Variability Adaptation Projects]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>17984.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>17984</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jeffrey Mantz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jmantz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927783</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This doctoral dissertation research improvement project analyzes the long-term impacts of projects that address adaptation to environmental variability. The goal of these projects is to assist communities to respond to the impacts of current and future environmental variability, safeguarding livelihoods and economic development. However, there have been few evaluations done of their long-term impacts. This research integrates political ecology with adaptation impact studies to examine the long-term impacts. The research links the transnational scale of climate finance to national adaptation governance and local outcomes of related projects, and will provide critical insights into the efficacy of adaptation projects. Findings will be disseminated via research publications, reports to local communities that have benefited from investment in adaption projects, and via curriculum development for graduate studies in adaptation research. As a Doctoral Dissertation Research Improvement award, this project will provide critical support to a young scholar as they develop their independent research profile.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research poses the following questions: (1) At the national level, how do the organizations designing and implementing adaptation projects define and measure the success of these actions and translate lessons to future projects? (2) At the local level, what are the enduring impacts of internationally funded adaptation projects on the adaptive capacity of recipient communities? and (3) What alternative evaluation methodologies can provide additional insight into the long-term outcomes of adaptation projects? To answer these questions, this project uses mixed methods, integrating data derived from a systematic analysis of adaptation documents, semi-structured interviews with key informants, and participant observation, to build an institutional ethnography of adaptation governance to environmental variability. The project also advances a methodology by contributing to understanding the methods and analysis necessary for assessing the multi-dimensional outcomes of adaptation projects over time.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/11/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/11/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2002829</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Diana</FirstName>
<LastName>Liverman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Diana M Liverman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[liverman@u.arizona.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000417883</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/11/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Megan</FirstName>
<LastName>Mills-Novoa</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Megan Mills-Novoa</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mmillsnovoa@email.arizona.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000798734</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/11/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Arizona</Name>
<CityName>TUCSON</CityName>
<ZipCode>85721</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5206266000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>845 N PARK AVE RM 538</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AZ03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>ED44Y3W6P7B9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ARIZONA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Arizona]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>857194824</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AZ07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8857</Code>
<Text>Geography &amp; Spatial Sci-DDRI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1352</Code>
<Text>GEOGRAPHY AND SPATIAL SCIENCES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~17984</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Over the last decade, hundreds of climate change adaptation projects have been funded by countries in the Global North and implemented in the Global South. These projects last five to six years and then close, leaving local governments, organizations, and individuals to sustain the initiative into the future. For communities on the frontlines of climate change, these projects provide critical resources to respond to escalating impacts. Despite the importance of these projects for supporting vulnerable people and landscapes, very little is known about how climate change adaptation projects have endured, to what ends, and for whom.</p> <p>The project, &ldquo;A Multi-Scalar Analysis of Environmental Variability Adaptation Projects&rdquo; examined what happens after international funded climate change adaptation projects end. In particular, I focused on the legacy of a key pilot project for Ecuador and the Latin American region called <em>Adaptation to Climate Change through Effective Water Governance (</em>PACC for its acronym in Spanish) that ended in 2014. This three million dollar project helped to establish the regional adaptation project model in terms of both its measures and administrative structure. I merged an institutional ethnography of transnational adaptation governance with community-centered research. With support from the NSF DDRI and other funders, I completed 12 months of fieldwork in Ecuador, which led to the collection of 185 surveys with former beneficiaries, 96 interviews with adaptation stakeholders, hundreds of hours of participant observation, and the systematic review of adaptation project and policy documents.</p> <p>This study highlights that adaptation projects like PACC that were deemed highly successful at their closure have futures that differ substantially from the expectations of project designers, implementors, funders, and participants. Looking across PACC&rsquo;s varied outcomes, it is unlikely that many of these projects will still be functioning by 2025 without external financial support. The sustainability mechanisms that were envisioned by project implementors have not functioned and communities are shouldering the burden of sustaining initiatives. The current model of adaptation projects, with five years of investment and then no mechanisms of support, neglects the uncertain, escalating nature of climate change and the shifting needs of communities on the frontlines. Episodic funding for climate change adaptation projects and evaluation processes needs to be revisited to acknowledge this reality.</p> <p><strong>Intellectual Merit:</strong>&nbsp;Methodologically, this project advances an alternative epistemological orientation in research on climate change adaptation, wherein the individuals and collectives tasked with maintaining these initiatives define the metrics for adaptation success. This reorientation catalyzes a profound change in whose knowledge matters and how adaptation success is defined. It opens space for alternative epistemological and ontological frames for what climate change, adaptation, and success mean through the worldviews and priorities of marginalized communities on the frontlines of climate change. Empirically, this research is the first to my knowledge to examine what happens after adaptation ends. These important findings have been synthesized into my dissertation, which I defended in May 2022. The first paper from this project was published in&nbsp;<em>Geoforum.</em> Two additional papers are currently under review<em>. </em>Additionally I have presented my work in conferences including the 2020 Annual Meeting of European Association for the Study of Science and Technology, 2021 Annual Meeting of the American Association of Geographers, and 2021 Global Forum on Climate Justice.&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts: </strong>The findings my research contributes to the debate over the sustainability of adaptation investments by providing analytical tools and empirical evidence. Its findings can reshape adaptation project design, implementation, and evaluation. I have shared the findings of my research&nbsp; by publishing an essay called &ldquo;On the Space between Success and Failure&rdquo; in the environmental online magazine <em>Terrain.org</em>. Additionally, my research assistant and I produced &ldquo;community adaptation needs&rdquo; reports. These reports serve as a tool for local communities to communicate their adaptation needs to governmental officials, funders, and civil society groups.&nbsp;We also drafted a policy brief that summarized our findings, which we are currently submitting to Ecuador&rsquo;s Ministry of the Environment, Water, and Ecological Transition as an input document to the national system for climate change adaptation reporting and monitoring.&nbsp;</p> <p>I was awarded the NSF DDRI in early 2020. During that time, I used NSF DDRI funds to pay my research assistants to help with data analysis. This led to the co-drafting of community adaptation needs reports in spring and summer 2020. During this time, I also published my first article associated with project in <em>Geoforum</em>. I had planned to return to Ecuador in summer 2020 but was unable due to the COVID-19 pandemic. During the 2020-2021 school year, I drafted my dissertation and also worked with my research assistants to draft and design a Spanish-language policy brief based on our research. In May 2021, I defended my dissertation and submitted two papers for review in fall/winter 2021.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/21/2021<br>      Modified by: Megan&nbsp;Mills-Novoa</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Over the last decade, hundreds of climate change adaptation projects have been funded by countries in the Global North and implemented in the Global South. These projects last five to six years and then close, leaving local governments, organizations, and individuals to sustain the initiative into the future. For communities on the frontlines of climate change, these projects provide critical resources to respond to escalating impacts. Despite the importance of these projects for supporting vulnerable people and landscapes, very little is known about how climate change adaptation projects have endured, to what ends, and for whom.  The project, "A Multi-Scalar Analysis of Environmental Variability Adaptation Projects" examined what happens after international funded climate change adaptation projects end. In particular, I focused on the legacy of a key pilot project for Ecuador and the Latin American region called Adaptation to Climate Change through Effective Water Governance (PACC for its acronym in Spanish) that ended in 2014. This three million dollar project helped to establish the regional adaptation project model in terms of both its measures and administrative structure. I merged an institutional ethnography of transnational adaptation governance with community-centered research. With support from the NSF DDRI and other funders, I completed 12 months of fieldwork in Ecuador, which led to the collection of 185 surveys with former beneficiaries, 96 interviews with adaptation stakeholders, hundreds of hours of participant observation, and the systematic review of adaptation project and policy documents.  This study highlights that adaptation projects like PACC that were deemed highly successful at their closure have futures that differ substantially from the expectations of project designers, implementors, funders, and participants. Looking across PACC’s varied outcomes, it is unlikely that many of these projects will still be functioning by 2025 without external financial support. The sustainability mechanisms that were envisioned by project implementors have not functioned and communities are shouldering the burden of sustaining initiatives. The current model of adaptation projects, with five years of investment and then no mechanisms of support, neglects the uncertain, escalating nature of climate change and the shifting needs of communities on the frontlines. Episodic funding for climate change adaptation projects and evaluation processes needs to be revisited to acknowledge this reality.  Intellectual Merit: Methodologically, this project advances an alternative epistemological orientation in research on climate change adaptation, wherein the individuals and collectives tasked with maintaining these initiatives define the metrics for adaptation success. This reorientation catalyzes a profound change in whose knowledge matters and how adaptation success is defined. It opens space for alternative epistemological and ontological frames for what climate change, adaptation, and success mean through the worldviews and priorities of marginalized communities on the frontlines of climate change. Empirically, this research is the first to my knowledge to examine what happens after adaptation ends. These important findings have been synthesized into my dissertation, which I defended in May 2022. The first paper from this project was published in Geoforum. Two additional papers are currently under review. Additionally I have presented my work in conferences including the 2020 Annual Meeting of European Association for the Study of Science and Technology, 2021 Annual Meeting of the American Association of Geographers, and 2021 Global Forum on Climate Justice.   Broader Impacts: The findings my research contributes to the debate over the sustainability of adaptation investments by providing analytical tools and empirical evidence. Its findings can reshape adaptation project design, implementation, and evaluation. I have shared the findings of my research  by publishing an essay called "On the Space between Success and Failure" in the environmental online magazine Terrain.org. Additionally, my research assistant and I produced "community adaptation needs" reports. These reports serve as a tool for local communities to communicate their adaptation needs to governmental officials, funders, and civil society groups. We also drafted a policy brief that summarized our findings, which we are currently submitting to Ecuador’s Ministry of the Environment, Water, and Ecological Transition as an input document to the national system for climate change adaptation reporting and monitoring.   I was awarded the NSF DDRI in early 2020. During that time, I used NSF DDRI funds to pay my research assistants to help with data analysis. This led to the co-drafting of community adaptation needs reports in spring and summer 2020. During this time, I also published my first article associated with project in Geoforum. I had planned to return to Ecuador in summer 2020 but was unable due to the COVID-19 pandemic. During the 2020-2021 school year, I drafted my dissertation and also worked with my research assistants to draft and design a Spanish-language policy brief based on our research. In May 2021, I defended my dissertation and submitted two papers for review in fall/winter 2021.           Last Modified: 12/21/2021       Submitted by: Megan Mills-Novoa]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
