<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Ham Radio Science Citizen Investigation (HamSCI) Workshop 2020; Scranton, Pennsylvania; March 20-21, 2020]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>49944.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>49944</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06020201</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AGS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Alan Liu</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>zhualiu@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927051</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This award is to organize a 2-day Ham Radio Citizen Science Investigation (HamSCI) meeting at the University of Scranton, Pennsylvania, on March 20-21, 2020. The meeting aims to foster collaborations between amateur radio operators and the science community for the purpose of advancing scientific research and understanding of the ionosphere by leveraging radio propagation experiments, encourage development of new technologies to support ionospheric research, and provide educational opportunities for the amateur community and the general public.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The 2020 HamSCI Workshop theme will be "The Auroral Connection," and will feature prominent leaders in Auroral Citizen Science, Auroral Radio Science, and Auroral Amateur Radio Operations. Additionally, the 2020 workshop will continue to make headway on topics of past HamSCI meetings, including the use of amateur radio techniques for observing and understanding the physics behind traveling ionospheric disturbances, Sporadic E, the ionospheric response to solar flares and geomagnetic storms, and space weather effects on radio wave propagation. This year's meeting will also serve as a development meeting of the HamSCI Personal Space Weather Station (PSWS). Development of the PSWS will lead to a vast improvement of the scientific quality of citizen science observations currently made by the amateur radio community.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/12/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/19/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2002268</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mohammad</FirstName>
<LastName>Maktoomi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mohammad A Maktoomi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mohammad.maktoomi@scranton.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000813342</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/12/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nathaniel</FirstName>
<LastName>Frissell</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nathaniel A Frissell</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[nathaniel.frissell@scranton.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000667316</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/12/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Scranton</Name>
<CityName>SCRANTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>185102429</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5709416362</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>800 LINDEN ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>WV3XJPNFUL58</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF SCRANTON</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>WV3XJPNFUL58</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Scranton]]></Name>
<CityName>Scranton</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>185102429</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[800 Linden Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1521</Code>
<Text>AERONOMY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~49944</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The primary goal of this award was to host a 2-day Ham Radio Science Citizen Investigation (HamSCI) workshop in March 2020 that brings together members of the professional scientific and amateur radio communities for the purpose of sharing ideas and participating in activities that advance both scientific knowledge and the amateur radio hobby. Additionally, the HamSCI workshop was also to serve as a team meeting for the NSF Distributed Array of Small Instruments HamSCI Personal Space Weather Station (PSWS) project. While the original award was only supposed to support an in-person 2020 HamSCI Workshop, COVID-19 caused the workshop to become virtual and resulted in a significant cost savings. The remaining funds were able to support a number of related activities: a virtual 2021 HamSCI workshop, the University of Scranton Radio Blaster Physics summer camp, and undergraduate 2021 summer research.</p> <p>The 2020 HamSCI workshop was held virtually from March 20-21, 2020. The agenda consisted of 38 presentations from members of both the science and academic communities. Participation consisted of 290 attendees from 6 continents, comprising 23 countries and Puerto Rico. Many presenters were members of both. The demographics included people in many stages of their careers, including high school students, undergraduate and graduate students, research faculty and staff, tenure-track faculty, industry professionals, and retirees. The theme of the 2020 Workshop was &ldquo;The Auroral Connection&rdquo;, and featured invited talks by NASA&rsquo;s Dr. Elizabeth MacDonald (&ldquo;Aurorasaurus: Citizen Science Observations of the Aurora&rdquo;), Dartmouth&rsquo;s Dr. Jim LaBelle (&ldquo;Observing Radio Signals of Auroral Origin&rdquo;), and amateur radio operator Mr. David Hallidy (&ldquo;Operating Auroral Mode Ham Radio&rdquo;). A keynote address was given by amateur radio operator Mr. Tim Duffy (&ldquo;Let&rsquo;s Push the Exploration of the Ionosphere to The Next Level&rdquo;). Workshop agenda and recordings of presentations are available at <a href="https://hamsci.org/hamsci2020">https://hamsci.org/hamsci2020</a>.</p> <p>The 2021 HamSCI workshop was held virtually success from March 19-20, 2021 with almost 300 attendees. The agenda consisted of over 50 presentations from members of both the science and academic communities. Many presenters were members of both. The theme chosen for the 2021 workshop was &ldquo;Midlatitude Ionospheric Science&rdquo; and featured invited tutorials by Virginia Tech professor J. Michael Ruohoniemi, &ldquo;Midlatitude Ionospheric Physics,&rdquo; and amateur radio operator/citizen scientist Joseph Dzekevich, &ldquo;Amateur Radio Observations and The Science of Midlatitude Sporadic E&rdquo;. A keynote presentation was given by Dr. Elizabeth Bruton of the Science Museum, London, entitled &ldquo;The History of Radio.&rdquo; Workshop agenda and recordings of presentations are available at <a href="https://hamsci.org/hamsci2021">https://hamsci.org/hamsci2021</a>.</p> <p>A 3-day &ldquo;Radio Blaster Physics Summer Camp&rdquo; July 20-22, 2021 at The University of Scranton that was attended by 16 local high school students. The primary objective of the camp was to introduce students to advanced physics at an early age to help spark an interest and possibly encourage them to pursue these topics in college and eventually a career. Topics included waves, oscilloscopes, magnetic coils, loudspeakers, simple crystal radios and radio waves. Students were also introduced to the concepts of space weather and space physics through amateur and shortwave radio. Finally, funding from this grant was also used to create three undergraduate research experience positions during the summer of 2021 for students at the University of Scranton. Students worked on projects related to space science and ionospheric impacts to radio astronomy.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/09/2022<br>      Modified by: Nathaniel&nbsp;A&nbsp;Frissell</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The primary goal of this award was to host a 2-day Ham Radio Science Citizen Investigation (HamSCI) workshop in March 2020 that brings together members of the professional scientific and amateur radio communities for the purpose of sharing ideas and participating in activities that advance both scientific knowledge and the amateur radio hobby. Additionally, the HamSCI workshop was also to serve as a team meeting for the NSF Distributed Array of Small Instruments HamSCI Personal Space Weather Station (PSWS) project. While the original award was only supposed to support an in-person 2020 HamSCI Workshop, COVID-19 caused the workshop to become virtual and resulted in a significant cost savings. The remaining funds were able to support a number of related activities: a virtual 2021 HamSCI workshop, the University of Scranton Radio Blaster Physics summer camp, and undergraduate 2021 summer research.  The 2020 HamSCI workshop was held virtually from March 20-21, 2020. The agenda consisted of 38 presentations from members of both the science and academic communities. Participation consisted of 290 attendees from 6 continents, comprising 23 countries and Puerto Rico. Many presenters were members of both. The demographics included people in many stages of their careers, including high school students, undergraduate and graduate students, research faculty and staff, tenure-track faculty, industry professionals, and retirees. The theme of the 2020 Workshop was "The Auroral Connection", and featured invited talks by NASA’s Dr. Elizabeth MacDonald ("Aurorasaurus: Citizen Science Observations of the Aurora"), Dartmouth’s Dr. Jim LaBelle ("Observing Radio Signals of Auroral Origin"), and amateur radio operator Mr. David Hallidy ("Operating Auroral Mode Ham Radio"). A keynote address was given by amateur radio operator Mr. Tim Duffy ("Let’s Push the Exploration of the Ionosphere to The Next Level"). Workshop agenda and recordings of presentations are available at https://hamsci.org/hamsci2020.  The 2021 HamSCI workshop was held virtually success from March 19-20, 2021 with almost 300 attendees. The agenda consisted of over 50 presentations from members of both the science and academic communities. Many presenters were members of both. The theme chosen for the 2021 workshop was "Midlatitude Ionospheric Science" and featured invited tutorials by Virginia Tech professor J. Michael Ruohoniemi, "Midlatitude Ionospheric Physics," and amateur radio operator/citizen scientist Joseph Dzekevich, "Amateur Radio Observations and The Science of Midlatitude Sporadic E". A keynote presentation was given by Dr. Elizabeth Bruton of the Science Museum, London, entitled "The History of Radio." Workshop agenda and recordings of presentations are available at https://hamsci.org/hamsci2021.  A 3-day "Radio Blaster Physics Summer Camp" July 20-22, 2021 at The University of Scranton that was attended by 16 local high school students. The primary objective of the camp was to introduce students to advanced physics at an early age to help spark an interest and possibly encourage them to pursue these topics in college and eventually a career. Topics included waves, oscilloscopes, magnetic coils, loudspeakers, simple crystal radios and radio waves. Students were also introduced to the concepts of space weather and space physics through amateur and shortwave radio. Finally, funding from this grant was also used to create three undergraduate research experience positions during the summer of 2021 for students at the University of Scranton. Students worked on projects related to space science and ionospheric impacts to radio astronomy.          Last Modified: 02/09/2022       Submitted by: Nathaniel A Frissell]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
