<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[CHS: Small: Collaborative Research: Catalyzing Youth Civic Engagement Through Innovations in Social Computing]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>30259.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>30259</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>William Bainbridge</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>wbainbri@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927470</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This research will design, develop, and evaluate novel smartphone applications that help youth explore and leverage their social networks to engage in collective action, and assess the impact of this action.  From affiliation with social movements through the use of Twitter hashtags, to collective organizing through Facebook, social computing tools have catalyzed new and exciting forms of civic engagement (efforts taken by individuals and collectives to address issues of societal concern). While historically it has been challenging to engage youth in civic action, social computing platforms offer a media-relevant way for youth to address issues that matter to them. However, despite increased opportunities for civic engagement online, youth can have difficulty navigating their social networks, which creates challenges for understanding and putting to use the social capital within networks, that is, the beneficial resources that can support collective action. This research examines how interactive visualizations of youth's social networks can help youth more effectively understand and put to use the social capital within their networks. Such visualizations may support civic engagement by easing access to the rich and complex information about social ties, helping youth evaluate the impact they have through online civic action, preparing them to make effective decisions about future activities.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;The work will include the design, development, and evaluation of two novel smartphone applications. Although there is a large literature on how best to visualize these networks from an algorithmic perspective, very little is known about how people, especially young people, interpret network visualizations, nor whether or when network visualizations may enhance access to and utilization of social capital. This project will contribute new empirical findings and novel software tools to fill this research gap. Additionally, although complex network data is increasingly packaged for public consumption, there are few standards for how to do so effectively, particularly in the context of mobile visualizations where small screen real estate dramatically amplifies the visualization challenge. The research will contribute new knowledge regarding how best to visualize network data for lay audiences, on the mobile platforms that people are increasingly using to interact with data. This work will yield empirical assessments of how designed interfaces can best manage the complexities of networked data in order to amplify cognition, action, and feelings of empowerment. This work will culminate in a conceptual framework to guide the design of social computing tools for youth civic engagement.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/06/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/06/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2002324</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Catherine</FirstName>
<LastName>D'Ignazio</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Catherine S D'Ignazio</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[dignazio@mit.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000671241</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/06/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Massachusetts Institute of Technology</Name>
<CityName>CAMBRIDGE</CityName>
<ZipCode>021394301</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6172531000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>77 MASSACHUSETTS AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>E2NYLCDML6V1</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MASSACHUSETTS INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>E2NYLCDML6V1</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Massachusetts Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021394301</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7367</Code>
<Text>HCC-Human-Centered Computing</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7367</Code>
<Text>Cyber-Human Systems</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7923</Code>
<Text>SMALL PROJECT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01001819DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~30259</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p id="docs-internal-guid-aab053e7-7fff-3dc4-07cf-79275bc2362a" style="line-height: 1.2; margin-top: 0pt; margin-bottom: 0pt;" dir="ltr"><span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: 'Times New Roman'; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">Our work has contributed to the fields of HCI and CSCW by providing new knowledge around <span id="docs-internal-guid-7c5bfedf-7fff-ad45-8670-9aab11ccd4cc" style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: 'Times New Roman'; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">how youth and adults within empowerment organizations use social computing tools to engage in online activism, challenges that arise in doing so, and design implications for novel visualization tools that help youth activists think more critically about the social capital within their networks</span>. Our 2 CSCW papers present new empirical insights in this regard.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p style="line-height: 1.2; margin-top: 0pt; margin-bottom: 0pt;" dir="ltr"><span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: 'Times New Roman'; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">First, through our analysis of data from our focus groups with youth activists and interviews with adult staff members within a teen empowerment organization, we have generated findings characterizing how youth engage in online impression management in the context of youth activism. Our analysis demonstrates how youth try to &ldquo;hack&rdquo; social networking application algorithms, and their desire to better identify their audience online. Our findings further revealed how youth use social networking applications to create an authentic and unplanned image of themselves and connections with their audience online. In contrast, our findings characterize how adults within the organization desired to convey a unified and curated image of the organization online and challenges that arose. We used these findings to contribute a set of design implications that can guide future work, specifically explicating impression management considerations that should be made when seeking to create systems that support youth activism online.&nbsp;</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p style="line-height: 1.2; margin-top: 0pt; margin-bottom: 0pt;" dir="ltr"><span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: 'Times New Roman'; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">While much research has studied impression management online, this work has mainly focused on how individuals engage in this self-presentation. Our work takes a different approach, by using Goffman&rsquo;s dramaturgical theory to study collective impression management in a youth empowerment organizational context. As such, we impacted the fields of HCI and CSCW by introducing collective impression management as an important concept of study within the context of online activism.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p style="line-height: 1.2; margin-top: 0pt; margin-bottom: 0pt;" dir="ltr"><span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: 'Times New Roman'; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">Second, through our analysis of interviews with you exploring their perspectives on interactive social network visualization variants, we have contributed findings regarding youth making sense of social network visualizations and their perspectives on how such tools could support their activism efforts. Our findings characterize how participants made inferences about followers&rsquo; identities based on their hashtag use, and how they used those inferences in outreach decisions. To our knowledge, there has been no prior work exploring how interactive visualizations can support youth activists&rsquo; reasoning about their social networks. As such, our work contributes to the fields of HCI and CSCW by providing initial evidence for how social network visualizations can support youth activism.</span></p> <p style="line-height: 1.2; margin-top: 0pt; margin-bottom: 0pt;" dir="ltr"><span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: 'Times New Roman'; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;"><br /></span></p> <p style="line-height: 1.2; margin-top: 0pt; margin-bottom: 0pt;" dir="ltr"><span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: 'Times New Roman'; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">Through our analysis of the data collected from our interviews, our findings characterize the nuances of care within YEPs during the COVID-19 pandemic and the sociotechnical challenges therein. Building upon previous HCI and CSCW literature on community-based organizations (CBOs), youth development, and care research, we found youth empowerment programs (YEPs)&ndash;a form of CBOs&ndash;to be organizations rich in caring behaviors for supporting youth. From our work, we observed that caring for youth over computer-mediated communication was especially difficult and used Nel Noddings&rsquo; idea of interpersonal care to explain discrepancies in care between face-to-face and computer-mediated contexts. Our work contributes to understanding breakdowns in care over &#8203;&#8203;computer-mediated communication during community stressors when certain aspects of care are not supported in the design of ICTs. Additionally, we use our work to characterize opportunities for future innovation to better care for youth during moments of crisis. As such, our work extends prior work around studying care work, contributing to an empirical account of sociotechnical breakdowns of care during crisis and providing insights into designing better sociotechnical systems to facilitate care.</span></p> <p style="line-height: 1.2; margin-top: 0pt; margin-bottom: 0pt;" dir="ltr"><span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: 'Times New Roman'; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">&nbsp;</span></p> <p id="docs-internal-guid-79a35807-7fff-2169-7f3c-01a6300bc7e4" style="line-height: 1.2; margin-top: 0pt; margin-bottom: 0pt;" dir="ltr"><span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: 'Times New Roman'; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">During the course of this project, Dr. Parker developed a new course at Georgia Tech entitled Digital Health Equity. The course is open to undergraduate and graduate students. The work done as part of this project informed the development of curricular resources for this project. In particular, the course teaches students about different ways in which technology has and can be designed to address health inequities. One approach is through the use of technology for collective action, and the work and learnings from this project have directly informed this component of the course.</span></p> <p style="line-height: 1.2; margin-top: 0pt; margin-bottom: 0pt;" dir="ltr">&nbsp;</p> <p id="docs-internal-guid-030b87c2-7fff-a807-3aff-d9309043bec0" style="line-height: 1.2; margin-top: 0pt; margin-bottom: 0pt;" dir="ltr"><span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: 'Times New Roman'; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">Moteover, the youth at our partner organization regularly use social networking sites within their work, however in our prior work, we identified opportunities for technology to help them more strategically and effectively leverage their social network for their community organizing activities. We have developed a software tool, the Swag App, that augments youth activists&rsquo; ability to effectively leverage the social capital available to them on social networking sites, which we hope will make them more effective in their efforts to bring about change in their communities. We plan to release the app with an open source license, to facilitate its integration into the many youth civic engagement programs that exist throughout the world.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/04/2022<br>      Modified by: Catherine&nbsp;S&nbsp;D'ignazio</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[Our work has contributed to the fields of HCI and CSCW by providing new knowledge around how youth and adults within empowerment organizations use social computing tools to engage in online activism, challenges that arise in doing so, and design implications for novel visualization tools that help youth activists think more critically about the social capital within their networks. Our 2 CSCW papers present new empirical insights in this regard.    First, through our analysis of data from our focus groups with youth activists and interviews with adult staff members within a teen empowerment organization, we have generated findings characterizing how youth engage in online impression management in the context of youth activism. Our analysis demonstrates how youth try to "hack" social networking application algorithms, and their desire to better identify their audience online. Our findings further revealed how youth use social networking applications to create an authentic and unplanned image of themselves and connections with their audience online. In contrast, our findings characterize how adults within the organization desired to convey a unified and curated image of the organization online and challenges that arose. We used these findings to contribute a set of design implications that can guide future work, specifically explicating impression management considerations that should be made when seeking to create systems that support youth activism online.     While much research has studied impression management online, this work has mainly focused on how individuals engage in this self-presentation. Our work takes a different approach, by using Goffman’s dramaturgical theory to study collective impression management in a youth empowerment organizational context. As such, we impacted the fields of HCI and CSCW by introducing collective impression management as an important concept of study within the context of online activism.    Second, through our analysis of interviews with you exploring their perspectives on interactive social network visualization variants, we have contributed findings regarding youth making sense of social network visualizations and their perspectives on how such tools could support their activism efforts. Our findings characterize how participants made inferences about followers’ identities based on their hashtag use, and how they used those inferences in outreach decisions. To our knowledge, there has been no prior work exploring how interactive visualizations can support youth activists’ reasoning about their social networks. As such, our work contributes to the fields of HCI and CSCW by providing initial evidence for how social network visualizations can support youth activism.   Through our analysis of the data collected from our interviews, our findings characterize the nuances of care within YEPs during the COVID-19 pandemic and the sociotechnical challenges therein. Building upon previous HCI and CSCW literature on community-based organizations (CBOs), youth development, and care research, we found youth empowerment programs (YEPs)&ndash;a form of CBOs&ndash;to be organizations rich in caring behaviors for supporting youth. From our work, we observed that caring for youth over computer-mediated communication was especially difficult and used Nel Noddings’ idea of interpersonal care to explain discrepancies in care between face-to-face and computer-mediated contexts. Our work contributes to understanding breakdowns in care over &#8203;&#8203;computer-mediated communication during community stressors when certain aspects of care are not supported in the design of ICTs. Additionally, we use our work to characterize opportunities for future innovation to better care for youth during moments of crisis. As such, our work extends prior work around studying care work, contributing to an empirical account of sociotechnical breakdowns of care during crisis and providing insights into designing better sociotechnical systems to facilitate care.   During the course of this project, Dr. Parker developed a new course at Georgia Tech entitled Digital Health Equity. The course is open to undergraduate and graduate students. The work done as part of this project informed the development of curricular resources for this project. In particular, the course teaches students about different ways in which technology has and can be designed to address health inequities. One approach is through the use of technology for collective action, and the work and learnings from this project have directly informed this component of the course.   Moteover, the youth at our partner organization regularly use social networking sites within their work, however in our prior work, we identified opportunities for technology to help them more strategically and effectively leverage their social network for their community organizing activities. We have developed a software tool, the Swag App, that augments youth activists’ ability to effectively leverage the social capital available to them on social networking sites, which we hope will make them more effective in their efforts to bring about change in their communities. We plan to release the app with an open source license, to facilitate its integration into the many youth civic engagement programs that exist throughout the world.          Last Modified: 04/04/2022       Submitted by: Catherine S D'ignazio]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
