<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Travel Support for North American Summer School for Logic, Language, and Information (NASSLLI)]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>49012.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>49012</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tatiana Korelsky</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tkorelsk@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928729</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This project provides travel and lodging support for graduate and advanced undergraduate students to participate in the 10th biennial North American Summer School in Logic, Language, and Information (NASSLLI) at Brandeis University in July 2020. NASSLLI is a unique educational opportunity for students interested in the interfaces between logic, computer and information science, linguistics, psychology, and philosophy. It brings faculty and students in these disciplines together in courses and workshops, with the goal of furthering our understanding of how minds and machines represent, communicate, manipulate and reason with information expressed in natural language. It also seeks to broaden the research and development communities that are concerned with these issues to achieve gender equity among its practitioners, and become more inclusive of underrepresented groups. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The theme of NASSLI 2020 is on computational modeling of pragmatics and dialogue, and is the first NASSLLI event that focuses on the implementation of human and machine interactions using natural language. This more practical focus complements NASSLLI’s traditional theoretical concerns in the computer, information and cognitive sciences to include a range of questions in both human and machine intelligence that will be attractive to students. To facilitate the success of students in the week-long intensive courses and participation in the workshops that follow, intensive training in a set of foundational topics is provided during the weekend prior to the start of courses.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/18/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/18/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2002141</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Pustejovsky</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>James Pustejovsky</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[pustejovsky@gmail.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000369969</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/18/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sophia</FirstName>
<LastName>Malamud</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sophia A Malamud</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[smalamud@brandeis.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000537671</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/18/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Brandeis University</Name>
<CityName>WALTHAM</CityName>
<ZipCode>024532728</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7817362121</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>415 SOUTH ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>MXLZGAMFEKN5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>BRANDEIS UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Brandeis University]]></Name>
<CityName>Waltham</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>024532728</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[415 South Street MS-116]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1311</Code>
<Text>Linguistics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7495</Code>
<Text>Robust Intelligence</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1311</Code>
<Text>LINGUISTICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7495</Code>
<Text>ROBUST INTELLIGENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~49012</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-214c0de5-7fff-d89e-0531-f3d9d63e017a"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr">We originally planned to host an in-person North American Summer School for Logic, Language, and Information (NASSLLI) in the summer of 2020. With the pandemic intervening, we instead hosted a smaller virtual Web Summer School for Logic, Language, and Information (WeSSLLI) in the summer of 2020 as well as collaborated with USC to provide scholarships for students to attend the in-person NASSLLI hosted at USC in the summer of 2022.&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Both WeSSLLI 2020 and NASSLLI 2022 provided both students and faculty a venue to explore the latest in computational and theoretical work in the areas of logic, linguistics, cognitive science, NLP, and computational linguistics. By so doing, these schools acted as a hub for information that could be shared with colleagues at their home institutions. Students learned new skills and were exposed to new avenues for research, as well as computational and experimental work.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>NASSLLI has played an important role in graduate education in the areas of linguistics, logic, and related disciplines of information science and computer science. Through both WeSSLLI 2020 and NASSLLI 2022 (whose offerings were almost entirely inherited from the 25 courses we originally planned for 2020) we expanded the purview of the offerings by enhancing the computational focus of the school. This enabled the school to contribute more meaningfully to the areas of computer science, AI, NLP, language technologies, as well as the&nbsp; field of linguistics.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>For WeSSLLI, we had four invited instructor courses and the major week-long workshop for an online presentation venue. WeSSLLI 2020 was the second major virtual event in the field after CUNY.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The original objective to enhance the computational focus was still accomplished through WeSSLLI, in spite of the smaller and virtual school. We had 368 attendees who identified themselves as "students". We also had 67 attendees who identified themselves as "other" and 105 attendees who identified themselves at "faculty". The total registered attendees for the WESSLLI school was 540 participants. This is the largest NASSLLI summer school thus far.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Participants had not only lively discussions over Zoom, but also a productive offline set of interactions on Slack. Both students and faculty provided extremely positive feedback, and our methodology for running a virtual event like that has been fully shared with the community, and taken further by the USC team for NASSLLI 2020, which was a hybrid event.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The hybrid NASSLLI 2022 had 319 registered participants, 142 online-only and 177 in person. 52 were faculty or post-doctoral scholars, and 267 were students.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>This was the first fully hybrid NASSLLI school, and the first in-person school in 4 years. It took place while the COVID-19 pandemic was cooling but not over. Given that faculty were volunteering their time to participate in the school it was important that they be able to teach with little interference from having to manage the hybrid set-up. The USC team were able to secure 17 graduate student volunteers across Linguistics, Philosophy, and Psychology to help with the ordinary tasks of a conference and also managing the interface between our in-person and online experiences through Zoom. Despite the challenges, the school was a huge success, with many subsequently reporting something to the effect of "best NASSLLI ever", "best intellectual experience of my life".</span>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The bonus events were exceedingly well attended and helped to prepare graduate students for success in their graduate career and beyond, whether in academia or in industry. The student research session was fully organized by a group of interdisciplinary graduate students?from managing the call for papers, the submission website, requesting and collating reviews on papers, building the schedule, and managing its hybrid set-up. The 2-day event featured 6 talks by graduate students (</span><a href="https://ml-la.github.io/nasslli2022/forstudents.html"><span>https://ml-la.github.io/nasslli2022/forstudents.html</span></a><span>). For different students, these opportunities provided a mini-training in hosting conference/workshop-type events, as well as practice disseminating research to a broad interdisciplinary audience.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>We were able to fund 47 student grants with the NSF participant costs, whether $900 or $1350 (depending on severe financial need as selected by the USC organisers; see notes on selection). Students were evaluated on the combined basis of need, merit, and diversity considerations. Student grant winners were encouraged to use the USC's discounted on-site accommodations and given first priority alongside NASSLLI instructors for making use of these rooms. Los Angeles can be incredibly expensive even for short-term housing, so with this option students should have been able to cover most of the costs of their attending the school. The NASSLLI student grant awardees comprised 47/267 = 17.6% of the total student population of the school. International travel expenses amounted to 22% of the total award. In each case, it was clear from their application materials that these students would not have been able to attend the school without this funding support. But the school could not have been a success without the participation of these students.</span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/02/2023<br>      Modified by: James&nbsp;Pustejovsky</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   We originally planned to host an in-person North American Summer School for Logic, Language, and Information (NASSLLI) in the summer of 2020. With the pandemic intervening, we instead hosted a smaller virtual Web Summer School for Logic, Language, and Information (WeSSLLI) in the summer of 2020 as well as collaborated with USC to provide scholarships for students to attend the in-person NASSLLI hosted at USC in the summer of 2022.  Both WeSSLLI 2020 and NASSLLI 2022 provided both students and faculty a venue to explore the latest in computational and theoretical work in the areas of logic, linguistics, cognitive science, NLP, and computational linguistics. By so doing, these schools acted as a hub for information that could be shared with colleagues at their home institutions. Students learned new skills and were exposed to new avenues for research, as well as computational and experimental work.  NASSLLI has played an important role in graduate education in the areas of linguistics, logic, and related disciplines of information science and computer science. Through both WeSSLLI 2020 and NASSLLI 2022 (whose offerings were almost entirely inherited from the 25 courses we originally planned for 2020) we expanded the purview of the offerings by enhancing the computational focus of the school. This enabled the school to contribute more meaningfully to the areas of computer science, AI, NLP, language technologies, as well as the  field of linguistics. For WeSSLLI, we had four invited instructor courses and the major week-long workshop for an online presentation venue. WeSSLLI 2020 was the second major virtual event in the field after CUNY.  The original objective to enhance the computational focus was still accomplished through WeSSLLI, in spite of the smaller and virtual school. We had 368 attendees who identified themselves as "students". We also had 67 attendees who identified themselves as "other" and 105 attendees who identified themselves at "faculty". The total registered attendees for the WESSLLI school was 540 participants. This is the largest NASSLLI summer school thus far.  Participants had not only lively discussions over Zoom, but also a productive offline set of interactions on Slack. Both students and faculty provided extremely positive feedback, and our methodology for running a virtual event like that has been fully shared with the community, and taken further by the USC team for NASSLLI 2020, which was a hybrid event. The hybrid NASSLLI 2022 had 319 registered participants, 142 online-only and 177 in person. 52 were faculty or post-doctoral scholars, and 267 were students.  This was the first fully hybrid NASSLLI school, and the first in-person school in 4 years. It took place while the COVID-19 pandemic was cooling but not over. Given that faculty were volunteering their time to participate in the school it was important that they be able to teach with little interference from having to manage the hybrid set-up. The USC team were able to secure 17 graduate student volunteers across Linguistics, Philosophy, and Psychology to help with the ordinary tasks of a conference and also managing the interface between our in-person and online experiences through Zoom. Despite the challenges, the school was a huge success, with many subsequently reporting something to the effect of "best NASSLLI ever", "best intellectual experience of my life".  The bonus events were exceedingly well attended and helped to prepare graduate students for success in their graduate career and beyond, whether in academia or in industry. The student research session was fully organized by a group of interdisciplinary graduate students?from managing the call for papers, the submission website, requesting and collating reviews on papers, building the schedule, and managing its hybrid set-up. The 2-day event featured 6 talks by graduate students (https://ml-la.github.io/nasslli2022/forstudents.html). For different students, these opportunities provided a mini-training in hosting conference/workshop-type events, as well as practice disseminating research to a broad interdisciplinary audience.    We were able to fund 47 student grants with the NSF participant costs, whether $900 or $1350 (depending on severe financial need as selected by the USC organisers; see notes on selection). Students were evaluated on the combined basis of need, merit, and diversity considerations. Student grant winners were encouraged to use the USC's discounted on-site accommodations and given first priority alongside NASSLLI instructors for making use of these rooms. Los Angeles can be incredibly expensive even for short-term housing, so with this option students should have been able to cover most of the costs of their attending the school. The NASSLLI student grant awardees comprised 47/267 = 17.6% of the total student population of the school. International travel expenses amounted to 22% of the total award. In each case, it was clear from their application materials that these students would not have been able to attend the school without this funding support. But the school could not have been a success without the participation of these students.       Last Modified: 08/02/2023       Submitted by: James Pustejovsky]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
