<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[I-Corps: Wearable Intraoral Neuromodulation Device to Treat Swallowing Disorders]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ruth Shuman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rshuman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922160</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this I-Corps project will be the development of a wearable device to treat swallowing and speech disorders. The goal of this technology is to address swallowing and speech related problems, such as Dysphagia (i.e., swallowing problems).  The occurrence of Dysphagia is as high as 22% in people over 50 years of age and as many as 30% of them receive inpatient medical treatment. In addition, 8-9% of young children have a speech disorder and about 50% of the US children (3-17 years of age) receive intervention services for a voice, speech, language, or swallowing disorder. Further, the swallowing and speech problems result from other illnesses such as stroke, spinal cord injury, head neck cancer, and Parkinson’s disease.  The proposed device will be powered through a wireless system connected to a battery worn in a necklace-like non-invasive device. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project is based on the development of a wearable intraoral neuromodulation system to solve problems with intraoral sensorimotor loop operation that cause swallowing and speech disorders. By monitoring and stimulating the intraoral organs, this technology will provide high spatiotemporal resolution to favorably intervene in intraoral sensorimotor loop operations. For example, the technology is designed to monitor the beginning of the pharyngeal phase of swallowing and modulate the activity of pharyngeal muscles for swallowing by stimulating the soft palatal nerves. In another example, the technology will monitor the tongue movement during speech and modulate the movement or posture of the tongue by applying stimulation at specific times and specific locations of the tongue. This device also has a unique feature using real-time wireless power transfer between the intraoral coil and necklace coil, which can be easily maintained. The necklace electronics have a battery capacity that is able to power the intraoral electronics for a full day. This real-time power transfer may significantly reduce (or eliminate) the size of the battery for the intraoral device.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/03/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/03/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2002320</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Hangue</FirstName>
<LastName>Park</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Hangue Park</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[hangue.park@tamu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000782634</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/03/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Texas A&amp;M Engineering Experiment Station</Name>
<CityName>COLLEGE STATION</CityName>
<ZipCode>778433124</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9798626777</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3124 TAMU</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>QD1MX6N5YTN4</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TEXAS A&amp;M ENGINEERING EXPERIMENT STATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>QD1MX6N5YTN4</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[TEXAS A&M ENGINEERING EXPERIMENT STATION]]></Name>
<CityName>College Station</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>778433128</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3128 TAMU]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project significantly helped the investigators for value proposition of wearable intraoral neuromodulation system (WINS), to identify right customer segments, and to better pursue the protection of intellectual property by the patent application. Our proposed WINS device, with intraoral, non-invasive, wearable, and wireless features, flexible intraoral sensors and electrodes, and closed-loop electrical stimulation capability, has a very strong differentiation from any existing technologies for treating swallowing disorder.</p> <p>As being located intraorally, WINS has an advantage in both monitoring the beginning of the swallowing and accessing proper intraoral sensory nerves modulating the muscle activity for swallowing. We hypothesize that the electrical stimulation applied onto the intraoral sensory nerves augments sensory feedback triggering the swallowing process. We expect this invention to be novel, not only as a closed-loop swallowing therapy but also as a general closed-loop intraoral sensory modulation system that can access the intraoral nerves and apply stimulation to treat different clinical conditions associated with intraoral operations (<em>e.g.,</em> speech, drooling, and sleep apnea).</p> <p>We identified customer segments as patients, patients&rsquo; family, and care provider, in both speech therapy and swallowing disorder market and investigated the customer ecosystem in each market. We also identified the gap between the research outcome and the customer needs, as there is much higher resistance from the potential customers in accepting intraoral neuromodulation device. We learned a lot from the interviewees. For example, we made a major pivot from focusing on swallowing period to focusing on mastication period, after listening to the clinicians in the field of swallowing disorder and speech therapy. They suggested us that clinicians and patients will hardly accept any neuromodulation during swallow because of the high risk of choking and there will be less concern for neuromodulation during the mastication period.</p> <p>WINS will bring significant impact on the society of swallowing disorder and speech therapy, by customizing neuromodulation therapy with close access to the intraoral sensory nerves. WINS will change the paradigm of treatment from generalized palliative therapy to a customized and targeted neural-based therapy that selectively targets the intraoral sensory nerves for each patient, which will enhance the quality of life for people suffering from dysphagia or speech disorders.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/13/2022<br>      Modified by: Hangue&nbsp;Park</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project significantly helped the investigators for value proposition of wearable intraoral neuromodulation system (WINS), to identify right customer segments, and to better pursue the protection of intellectual property by the patent application. Our proposed WINS device, with intraoral, non-invasive, wearable, and wireless features, flexible intraoral sensors and electrodes, and closed-loop electrical stimulation capability, has a very strong differentiation from any existing technologies for treating swallowing disorder.  As being located intraorally, WINS has an advantage in both monitoring the beginning of the swallowing and accessing proper intraoral sensory nerves modulating the muscle activity for swallowing. We hypothesize that the electrical stimulation applied onto the intraoral sensory nerves augments sensory feedback triggering the swallowing process. We expect this invention to be novel, not only as a closed-loop swallowing therapy but also as a general closed-loop intraoral sensory modulation system that can access the intraoral nerves and apply stimulation to treat different clinical conditions associated with intraoral operations (e.g., speech, drooling, and sleep apnea).  We identified customer segments as patients, patients’ family, and care provider, in both speech therapy and swallowing disorder market and investigated the customer ecosystem in each market. We also identified the gap between the research outcome and the customer needs, as there is much higher resistance from the potential customers in accepting intraoral neuromodulation device. We learned a lot from the interviewees. For example, we made a major pivot from focusing on swallowing period to focusing on mastication period, after listening to the clinicians in the field of swallowing disorder and speech therapy. They suggested us that clinicians and patients will hardly accept any neuromodulation during swallow because of the high risk of choking and there will be less concern for neuromodulation during the mastication period.  WINS will bring significant impact on the society of swallowing disorder and speech therapy, by customizing neuromodulation therapy with close access to the intraoral sensory nerves. WINS will change the paradigm of treatment from generalized palliative therapy to a customized and targeted neural-based therapy that selectively targets the intraoral sensory nerves for each patient, which will enhance the quality of life for people suffering from dysphagia or speech disorders.       Last Modified: 06/13/2022       Submitted by: Hangue Park]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
