<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[STTR Phase I: Metal Free-Ring Opening Metathesis Polymerization]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>225000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>225000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Steven Konsek</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Technology Transfer (STTR) Phase I project will be a technology enabling 3D printing of high-performance materials. A rapid and versatile ability to fabricate 3D parts that are lightweight, heat-resistant, biocompatible, and chemically inactive would yield improved manufacturing capabilities across a range of potential commercial applications, such as medical devices, implants, dental materials, automotive parts, aircraft, and spacecraft materials.  This project will advance the development of new materials for the 3D printing community.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Technology Transfer Phase I Project will advance a technology based on a new chemical reactivity recently discovered for producing high-performance plastics and composites. This unique catalyst-resin system will be developed for use in 3D printing. The photoredox catalyst will be redesigned for efficient curing, within seconds per layer without a need for solvents. The resin systems will be formulated for rapid crosslinking, low volatility, and high-resolution 3D printing. Finally, the complete catalyst-resin combination will be optimized for use with commercial vat photopolymerization 3D printing equipment.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/08/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/28/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2002330</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
<LastName>Ediger</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mark D Ediger</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ediger@chem.wisc.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000407225</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/08/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Goldstone</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John Goldstone</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[john.goldstone@live.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000751964</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/08/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Boydston Chemical Innovations, Incorportated</Name>
<CityName>FEDERAL WAY</CityName>
<ZipCode>980233531</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2537321876</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>510 SW 295TH PL</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WA09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>KFXPPNVLLR53</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>BOYDSTON CHEMICAL INNOVATIONS INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Boydston Chemical Innovations]]></Name>
<CityName>Auburn</CityName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>980014213</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[215 Clay Street NW, B4-6]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WA08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1505</Code>
<Text>STTR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>123E</Code>
<Text>CENTERS: ADVANCED MATERIALS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~225000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project explored the ability to 3D print high-performance plastic materials by photopolymerization without using metal mediators. &nbsp;The products made in this way should have higher tensile strength, impact resistance, chemical resistance, and ductility than products currently 3D printed.&nbsp; Advantages of using metal-free polymerization include lower cost (metal catalysts are expensive), easier processing (some metal catalysts require air-free conditions), and final parts without metals, opening a broader set of applications, including human contact.</p> <p><em>Technical Objective 1: Discover and validate photocatalysts that can operate in bulk resin (no solvent)</em></p> <p>The current state of the art for this metal-free polymerization requires a solvent, which is not compatible with 3D printing.&nbsp; Therefore, our first objective was to remove the solvent from the system.&nbsp; With the help of The Boydston Research Group at the University of Wisconsin, Madison, we were successful in achieving this objective. &nbsp;We identified soluble catalysts, and our efforts further revealed fluorinated alcohols as functional groups that could obviate solvents as well as crosslinking agents that provided solid objects upon photocuring. &nbsp;Despite these advances, the system still faced challenges. &nbsp;The polymerization times were still too slow to be relevant for 3D printing. &nbsp;Also, the use of fluorinated alcohols in the formulation presents safety concerns. &nbsp;To address these challenges, we looked at making polymers in solvent and then including them into existing formulations.</p> <p><em>Technical Objective 2: Create formulations that can achieve photocuring relevant to 3DP applications</em></p> <p>Through a series of thin-film experiments, we were able to photocure single layers of resin made from our high-performance polymer product and acrylates that are currently used in 3D printing formulations.&nbsp; We experimented with light intensity, formulation composition, and cure times to find the best conditions.&nbsp; We found formulations that give good gel fractions in thin films at 1-10 seconds cure times.&nbsp; Thus, our next step was to prepare samples for mechanical testing, in order to test the hypothesis that these materials will provide superior properties to what is currently available in stereolithographic (SLA) printing.&nbsp; We have prepared a number of &ldquo;green&rdquo; tensile bars and characterized them for their tensile and thermal properties (Figure attached).&nbsp; These samples were made by injecting mixtures of our polymer product, acrylate, and photoinitiator into a silicone mold, and exposing the mold to the high-intensity light for several minutes.&nbsp; Our first formulations including our polymer product showed higher tensile strength than samples made without our product.</p> <p><em>Conclusion:</em></p> <p>The overall goal of the Phase I project was to expand BCI&rsquo;s metal-free polymerization technology into the 3D printing space, achieving vat photopolymerization of high-performance plastics.&nbsp; Our original plan to accomplish this goal was to develop our technology to work in the absence of solvent, at speeds that are relevant to 3D printing.&nbsp; Through modification of the polymerization catalyst system, we achieved bulk (no solvent) polymerization of dicyclopentadiene (DCPD) and related monomers.&nbsp; However, conversions of monomer in this system were low, and polymerization was still too slow to be practical in vat photopolymerization.&nbsp; This necessitated a change in approach.&nbsp; We transitioned to a system in which low molecular weight oligomers of DCPD are integrated into existing acrylate polymerization chemistry.&nbsp; This removed the requirement of fast polymerization, as the oligomers are made and incorporated into the 3D printing formulation.&nbsp; These Phase I results form a basis for work during Phase II, in which formulations will be tested and optimized to give resins with mechanical properties that will fill a commercial need not addressed by the current market.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/04/2021<br>      Modified by: John&nbsp;Goldstone</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2002330/2002330_10669402_1636045794734_WP_20201201_002dogbones--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2002330/2002330_10669402_1636045794734_WP_20201201_002dogbones--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Dog Bones made with BCI product"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2002330/2002330_10669402_1636045794734_WP_20201201_002dogbones--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Dog Bones made with BCI product"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Comparison of test bars made using BCI's oligoDCPD, HDDA and BAPO.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Boydston Chemical Innovations</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">John&nbsp;Goldstone</div> <div class="imageTitle">Dog Bones made with BCI product</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project explored the ability to 3D print high-performance plastic materials by photopolymerization without using metal mediators.  The products made in this way should have higher tensile strength, impact resistance, chemical resistance, and ductility than products currently 3D printed.  Advantages of using metal-free polymerization include lower cost (metal catalysts are expensive), easier processing (some metal catalysts require air-free conditions), and final parts without metals, opening a broader set of applications, including human contact.  Technical Objective 1: Discover and validate photocatalysts that can operate in bulk resin (no solvent)  The current state of the art for this metal-free polymerization requires a solvent, which is not compatible with 3D printing.  Therefore, our first objective was to remove the solvent from the system.  With the help of The Boydston Research Group at the University of Wisconsin, Madison, we were successful in achieving this objective.  We identified soluble catalysts, and our efforts further revealed fluorinated alcohols as functional groups that could obviate solvents as well as crosslinking agents that provided solid objects upon photocuring.  Despite these advances, the system still faced challenges.  The polymerization times were still too slow to be relevant for 3D printing.  Also, the use of fluorinated alcohols in the formulation presents safety concerns.  To address these challenges, we looked at making polymers in solvent and then including them into existing formulations.  Technical Objective 2: Create formulations that can achieve photocuring relevant to 3DP applications  Through a series of thin-film experiments, we were able to photocure single layers of resin made from our high-performance polymer product and acrylates that are currently used in 3D printing formulations.  We experimented with light intensity, formulation composition, and cure times to find the best conditions.  We found formulations that give good gel fractions in thin films at 1-10 seconds cure times.  Thus, our next step was to prepare samples for mechanical testing, in order to test the hypothesis that these materials will provide superior properties to what is currently available in stereolithographic (SLA) printing.  We have prepared a number of "green" tensile bars and characterized them for their tensile and thermal properties (Figure attached).  These samples were made by injecting mixtures of our polymer product, acrylate, and photoinitiator into a silicone mold, and exposing the mold to the high-intensity light for several minutes.  Our first formulations including our polymer product showed higher tensile strength than samples made without our product.  Conclusion:  The overall goal of the Phase I project was to expand BCI’s metal-free polymerization technology into the 3D printing space, achieving vat photopolymerization of high-performance plastics.  Our original plan to accomplish this goal was to develop our technology to work in the absence of solvent, at speeds that are relevant to 3D printing.  Through modification of the polymerization catalyst system, we achieved bulk (no solvent) polymerization of dicyclopentadiene (DCPD) and related monomers.  However, conversions of monomer in this system were low, and polymerization was still too slow to be practical in vat photopolymerization.  This necessitated a change in approach.  We transitioned to a system in which low molecular weight oligomers of DCPD are integrated into existing acrylate polymerization chemistry.  This removed the requirement of fast polymerization, as the oligomers are made and incorporated into the 3D printing formulation.  These Phase I results form a basis for work during Phase II, in which formulations will be tested and optimized to give resins with mechanical properties that will fill a commercial need not addressed by the current market.          Last Modified: 11/04/2021       Submitted by: John Goldstone]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
