<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research: Heme Distortion and Protein-Protein Contacts in Oxygen-Dependent Globin Coupled Sensor Signaling]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>163740.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>163740</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Pumtiwitt McCarthy</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>pmccarth@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032920000</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[With this award, the Chemistry of Life Processes Program in the Chemistry Division is funding Dr. Emily Weinert from Pennsylvania State University, Dr. Christine Dunham from Emory University, and Dr. James Kincaid from Marquette University to investigate bacterial oxygen sensing proteins. Bacteria are integral to the health of ecosystems, plants, animals, and humans, and have evolved to adapt to constantly changing conditions within their environment. However, the mechanisms by which bacteria sense and respond to changes in the levels of environmental gases are poorly understood. The research supported by this award examines the roles of environmental signals in controlling bacterial phenotypes; more specifically it examines the signaling mechanism and pathway of a family of proteins termed globin coupled sensors that are responsible for sensing oxygen. This project provides specialized training for students in protein chemistry, spectroscopy, and X-ray crystallography. Additionally, the participants in this project integrate research results into a board game and create lesson plans that make elementary and middle school students aware of how proteins help bacteria sense and react to changes in their environment. &lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;This research project seeks to characterize the intra- and inter-molecular protein interactions that control oxygen-dependent signaling by a family of bacterial heme proteins termed globin coupled sensors. Globin-coupled sensor proteins are widely distributed within bacteria and contain output domains that are linked to important phenotypes, including biofilm formation, motility, and virulence. A combination of research methods that includes mutagenesis/screening, enzyme kinetics, resonance Raman spectroscopy, and X-ray crystallography is being used to interrogate the oxygen-dependent signaling mechanism within globin coupled sensor proteins and the transmission of the signaling events to downstream partners. Results from this study provide new information about bacterial gas-sensing proteins, signal transduction pathways, and regulation of key bacterial enzymatic domains involved in controlling biofilm formation and virulence.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/14/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/28/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2003345</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Kincaid</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>James R Kincaid</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[james.kincaid@marquette.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000342114</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/14/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate>10/28/2022</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yilin</FirstName>
<LastName>Liu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Yilin Liu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[yilin.1.liu@marquette.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000906323</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>10/28/2022</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Marquette University</Name>
<CityName>MILWAUKEE</CityName>
<ZipCode>532332310</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4142887200</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>915 W WISCONSIN AVE RM 175</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WI04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>HKJCKTFJNBM7</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MARQUETTE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>YHYDXPLZHLW3</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Marquette University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>532011881</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WI04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6883</Code>
<Text>Chemistry of Life Processes</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>068Z</Code>
<Text>URoL-Understanding Rules of Life</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~163740</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong><em><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Significance and objective</span></em></strong></p> <p>The collaborative research aims to study Globin Coupled Sensors (GCS), heme-containing proteins widely distributed in prokaryotes that may act as in vivo oxygen sensors. Some GCSs include diguanylate cyclase domains, catalyzing c-di-GMP production, a bacterial second messenger regulating biofilm formation. The overall goals are to understand the physiological roles of GCS proteins, develop tools to regulate O<sub>2</sub>-dependent signaling, and design novel heme-based sensors. The specific objectives of the collaborative proposal involve investigating heme distortion (structural, including rR) and inter-domain/inter-protein interactions, which play a role in transmitting the O<sub>2</sub> binding signal within GCS proteins and downstream signaling partners. The essential hypothesis suggests that O<sub>2</sub> binding to the GCS globin domain causes heme deformation changes, which are then transmitted through heme edge residues, influencing specific protein-protein interactions and, consequently, modulating enzymatic activity. In this collaborative proposal, the objectives are to employ resonance Raman spectroscopy to document these crucial changes in heme deformation and active site structure during molecular oxygen binding.</p> <p><strong><em><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Scientific</span></em></strong><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;"> <em>accomplishment</em></span></strong></p> <p>The key outcomes of this reporting period are the identification of heme pocket residues involved in GCS O<sub>2</sub>-dependent signaling and the effects of heme active site residues on heme conformation.</p> <p><strong><em><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Investigating the effects of heme-edge residues on the DcpG heme active site structure. </span></em></strong></p> <p><strong><em><span style="text-decoration: underline;">&nbsp;</span></em></strong>Mutagenesis studies have demonstrated the significance of heme edge residues H62 and R79 in modulating DcpG gas sensing. The H62A and R79A mutations lead to decreased O<sub>2</sub> dissociation kinetics. In our resonance Raman spectra of the DcpG wild type and heme-edge mutants, we observed alterations in the heme electrostatic environment, vinyl group conformations, and spin state population. These findings offer valuable insights into the molecular interactions that regulate DcpG gas sensing and shed light on the mechanisms controlling multidomain bacterial signaling proteins.</p> <p><strong><em><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Resonance Raman Studies of Globin Coupled Sensors from Pectobacterium carotovorum </span></em></strong></p> <p><strong><em>&nbsp;</em></strong>Considering the significant role of heme pocket residues in controlling O<sub>2</sub>-dependent signaling in the <em>Pcc</em>GCS enzyme cyclase activity, we utilized resonance Raman (rR) spectroscopy to investigate the conformational changes associated with heme pocket variants, including S82A, Y57F, and V122Y <em>Pcc</em>GCS. Our results indicate that these mutations cause changes in the bending motions of heme peripheral groups, deactivated out-of-plane modes due to reduced heme macrocycle distortions, and disrupt the detailed H-bonding network in the active site. These findings highlight the critical impact of these residues on heme structure, with potential implications for functionality and reactivity.<strong><em></em></strong></p> <p><strong><em><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Professional accomplishments</span></em></strong></p> <p>This project was mainly conducted by a women scientist, the training provided in this project allowed her to prepare for studies involving heme sensor proteins, mentoring graduate students, generating periodic reports of results, and writing research proposals. The experience she is getting in participating in this NSF can certainly help to prepare her for an academic career.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/30/2023<br>      Modified by: Yilin&nbsp;Liu</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Significance and objective  The collaborative research aims to study Globin Coupled Sensors (GCS), heme-containing proteins widely distributed in prokaryotes that may act as in vivo oxygen sensors. Some GCSs include diguanylate cyclase domains, catalyzing c-di-GMP production, a bacterial second messenger regulating biofilm formation. The overall goals are to understand the physiological roles of GCS proteins, develop tools to regulate O2-dependent signaling, and design novel heme-based sensors. The specific objectives of the collaborative proposal involve investigating heme distortion (structural, including rR) and inter-domain/inter-protein interactions, which play a role in transmitting the O2 binding signal within GCS proteins and downstream signaling partners. The essential hypothesis suggests that O2 binding to the GCS globin domain causes heme deformation changes, which are then transmitted through heme edge residues, influencing specific protein-protein interactions and, consequently, modulating enzymatic activity. In this collaborative proposal, the objectives are to employ resonance Raman spectroscopy to document these crucial changes in heme deformation and active site structure during molecular oxygen binding.  Scientific accomplishment  The key outcomes of this reporting period are the identification of heme pocket residues involved in GCS O2-dependent signaling and the effects of heme active site residues on heme conformation.  Investigating the effects of heme-edge residues on the DcpG heme active site structure.    Mutagenesis studies have demonstrated the significance of heme edge residues H62 and R79 in modulating DcpG gas sensing. The H62A and R79A mutations lead to decreased O2 dissociation kinetics. In our resonance Raman spectra of the DcpG wild type and heme-edge mutants, we observed alterations in the heme electrostatic environment, vinyl group conformations, and spin state population. These findings offer valuable insights into the molecular interactions that regulate DcpG gas sensing and shed light on the mechanisms controlling multidomain bacterial signaling proteins.  Resonance Raman Studies of Globin Coupled Sensors from Pectobacterium carotovorum    Considering the significant role of heme pocket residues in controlling O2-dependent signaling in the PccGCS enzyme cyclase activity, we utilized resonance Raman (rR) spectroscopy to investigate the conformational changes associated with heme pocket variants, including S82A, Y57F, and V122Y PccGCS. Our results indicate that these mutations cause changes in the bending motions of heme peripheral groups, deactivated out-of-plane modes due to reduced heme macrocycle distortions, and disrupt the detailed H-bonding network in the active site. These findings highlight the critical impact of these residues on heme structure, with potential implications for functionality and reactivity.  Professional accomplishments  This project was mainly conducted by a women scientist, the training provided in this project allowed her to prepare for studies involving heme sensor proteins, mentoring graduate students, generating periodic reports of results, and writing research proposals. The experience she is getting in participating in this NSF can certainly help to prepare her for an academic career.          Last Modified: 08/30/2023       Submitted by: Yilin Liu]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
