<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[2020 Frontiers of Engineering Symposia (US FOE, Japan-America FOE and EU-US FOE)]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>110000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>110000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EFMA</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Emerging Frontiers &amp; Multidisciplinary Activities</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Louise R. Howe</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lhowe@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922548</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The Frontiers of Engineering (FOE) Symposia, organized by the National Academy of Engineering, provide emerging engineering leaders from academia, industry, and government laboratories the opportunity to share research insights to facilitate an interdisciplinary transfer of knowledge and research methodologies. The nature of emerging technologies and how they fit together to create products and processes that drive economic growth in an increasingly competitive environment makes it essential that engineers understand each other's disciplines. The symposia serve as a catalyst to spur engineering innovation and foster collaborative networks of researchers within the United States and between engineers from the United States and partnering countries. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award will provide partial support for three Frontiers of Engineering (FOE) symposia, to be held in 2020. These symposia, organized by the National Academy of Engineering (NAE) in concert with international partner organizations, are for early career researchers. The meetings to be held in 2020 are: Japan-America FOE (June, 2020; Irvine, California); US FOE (September, 2020; Golden, Colorado); and EU-US FOE (October, 2020; Murray Hill, New Jersey. The 2020 JAFOE will focus on Mitigating Sea Level Rise, Machine Learning and AI for Mental Health, Blockchain Technology, Soft Robotics. The 2020 US FOE symposium will focus on Bioengineering for Women’s Health, New Approaches to Food Production, Cleaning up Ocean Waste, and Next-generation Energy Systems Integration. Topics for the 2020 EU-US-FOE are Advances in Deep Learning for ICT Problems, Modernizing the Electrical Grid, Technologies for the Detection and Treatment of Dementia and Alzheimer’s Disease, Applications and Uses of Graphene. Approximately 100 outstanding young engineers for the U.S. symposium and 30 from each country for the bilateral symposia will participate. Each two and a half day symposium will include plenary sessions, tours, break-out and poster sessions, and opportunities for developing collaborative research partnerships. Sessions will consist of presentations on cutting-edge research, innovations, and emerging research opportunities in engineering fields relevant to the symposium. FOE symposium papers, abstracts, presentation videos, and slides will be made available on the FOE website (www.naefrontiers.org).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/13/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/13/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2003333</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Janet</FirstName>
<LastName>Hunziker</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Janet R Hunziker</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jhunzike@nae.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000390009</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/13/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>National Academy of Sciences</Name>
<CityName>WASHINGTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>204180007</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2023342254</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2101 CONSTITUTION AVE NW</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>PKFJZHG2MLG9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NATIONAL ACADEMY OF SCIENCES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>PKFJZHG2MLG9</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[National Academy of Sciences]]></Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>200012721</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[500 Fifth Street, NW]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7633</Code>
<Text>EFRI Research Projects</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~110000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Frontiers of Engineering (FOE) Symposia, organized by the National Academy of Engineering, provide highly accomplished early-career engineers from academia, industry, and government laboratories the opportunity to share their research and technical work, which facilitates interdisciplinary exchange across diverse engineering fields. The nature of emerging technologies and how they fit together to create products and processes that drive economic grown in an increasingly competitive environment have heightened the need for engineers to understand each other's disciplines. The&nbsp; symposia are a catalyst for innovation that fosters collaborative networks of researchers within the United States and across national boundaries. This award provided partial support for the 2020 FOE meetings that due to the Covid pandemic were postponed and held virtually in 2021. Those meetings are: US FOE held February 24-26, Japan-America FOE held June 23-25, and EU-US FOE, held November 15-17. Presentations and discussion focused on topics that included among others: next-generation energy systems integration, engineering innovation in women's health, soft robotics, blockchain, applications and uses of graphene, and machine learning for emerging networks. The virtual meetings also included informal networking time, poster sessions, and breakout groups. Presentation abstracts, videos or slides, and posters are available on the meeting websites at www.naefrontiers.org.</p> <p>The following results and comments were obtained from surveys of meeting attendees:</p> <p><strong>US FOE</strong><strong><br /></strong>Virtual meeting structure: good or excellent 93%<br />Quality of presentations: good or excellent 95%<br />Ability to interact virtually during networking times: good or excellent 84%<br />Range of topics: about right 95%<br />Gained something useful to work/research from presentations//informal discussion in other disciplines: Yes or possibly 91%//93%<br />Identified potential collaborative opportunities//applications of interdisciplinary approaches: 96%//84%<br />Usefulness to professional development: useful or very useful 95%<br /><br />Comments:</p> <p><em>The conference provided a fantastic opportunity for me to gather different engineering perspecties and to identify critical needs for advanced processes that enable breakthrough technologies. I was able to expand my scientific network with engineers from diverse backgrounds. I developed relationships that can lead to fruitful industrial and academic collaborations.</em></p> <p><em>Through discussion with brilliant engineers with AI and machine learning backgrounds, I was able to identify new opportunities to use novel optimization algorithms for process optimization to minimize energy, maximize yield, etc. at my company. I have already scheduled meetings with some of the researchers I met at FOE to discuss opportunities for collaboration.</em></p> <p><strong>Japan-America </strong><strong>FOE&nbsp;<br /></strong>Virtual meeting structure: good or excellent 84%<br />Quality of presentations: good or excellent 76%<br />Ability to interact virtually during networking times: good or excellent 75%<br />Range of topics: about right 86%<br />Gained something useful to work/research from presentations//informal discussion in other disciplines: Yes or possibly 100%//100%<br />Identified potential collaborative opportunities//applications of interdisciplinary approaches: 82%//96%<br />Usefulness to professional development: useful or very useful 100%</p> <p>Comments:</p> <p><em>Keren's presentation about how to make engineering meaningful for policymakers was very inspiring. It made me think about how I can work to make my research (wearable sensors, haptics, etc.) more understandable to policymakers both within Facebook as well as externally to the US government.</em></p> <p><em>The use of augmented reality to reveal sea-level rise is one potential space for collaboration for me. The system modeling of human impacts on ecoology is also a potentially useful tool in relating technology to social change.</em></p> <p><strong>EU-US&nbsp;FOE&nbsp;</strong></p> <p>Virtual meeting structure: good or excellent 87%<br />Quality of presentations: good or excellent 90%<br />Ability to interact virtually during networking times: good or excellent 88%<br />Range of topics: about right 87%<br />Gained something useful to work/research from presentations//informal discussion in other disciplines: Yes or possibly 86%//86%<br />Identified potential collaborative opportunities//applications of interdisciplinary approaches: 86%//86%<br />Usefulness to professional development: useful or very useful 93%</p> <p>Comments:</p> <p><em>This was one of the best remote conferences I have attended. The overall environment was very interactive. The talks were all very interesting and definitely served to broaden my perspective. Based on the talks, I sent a number of emails to students and other collaborators about things to keep in mind for the future.</em></p> <p><em>Being exposed to research problems and topics outside my current focus area helped widen my perspective. I also received a few interesting directions from some peers I met at the symposium.&nbsp;</em></p> <p><strong>GRAINGER GRANTS</strong></p> <p>Two grants of $30,000 from The Grainger Foundation were awarded to US FOE attendees who developed collaborative research projects. The recipients were:&nbsp;<br /><br />Anita Shukla (Brown University) and Arezoo Ardekani (Purdue University) for "A combined experimental and computational study of microbe-responsive antimicrobial hydrogels"</p> <p>Karthish Manthiram (California Institute of Technology) and Suman Khatiwada (Syzygy Plasmonics) for "Integrating light and voltage-driven reactions in chemical manufacturing"</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/21/2022<br>      Modified by: Janet&nbsp;R&nbsp;Hunziker</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Frontiers of Engineering (FOE) Symposia, organized by the National Academy of Engineering, provide highly accomplished early-career engineers from academia, industry, and government laboratories the opportunity to share their research and technical work, which facilitates interdisciplinary exchange across diverse engineering fields. The nature of emerging technologies and how they fit together to create products and processes that drive economic grown in an increasingly competitive environment have heightened the need for engineers to understand each other's disciplines. The  symposia are a catalyst for innovation that fosters collaborative networks of researchers within the United States and across national boundaries. This award provided partial support for the 2020 FOE meetings that due to the Covid pandemic were postponed and held virtually in 2021. Those meetings are: US FOE held February 24-26, Japan-America FOE held June 23-25, and EU-US FOE, held November 15-17. Presentations and discussion focused on topics that included among others: next-generation energy systems integration, engineering innovation in women's health, soft robotics, blockchain, applications and uses of graphene, and machine learning for emerging networks. The virtual meetings also included informal networking time, poster sessions, and breakout groups. Presentation abstracts, videos or slides, and posters are available on the meeting websites at www.naefrontiers.org.  The following results and comments were obtained from surveys of meeting attendees:  US FOE Virtual meeting structure: good or excellent 93% Quality of presentations: good or excellent 95% Ability to interact virtually during networking times: good or excellent 84% Range of topics: about right 95% Gained something useful to work/research from presentations//informal discussion in other disciplines: Yes or possibly 91%//93% Identified potential collaborative opportunities//applications of interdisciplinary approaches: 96%//84% Usefulness to professional development: useful or very useful 95%  Comments:  The conference provided a fantastic opportunity for me to gather different engineering perspecties and to identify critical needs for advanced processes that enable breakthrough technologies. I was able to expand my scientific network with engineers from diverse backgrounds. I developed relationships that can lead to fruitful industrial and academic collaborations.  Through discussion with brilliant engineers with AI and machine learning backgrounds, I was able to identify new opportunities to use novel optimization algorithms for process optimization to minimize energy, maximize yield, etc. at my company. I have already scheduled meetings with some of the researchers I met at FOE to discuss opportunities for collaboration.  Japan-America FOE  Virtual meeting structure: good or excellent 84% Quality of presentations: good or excellent 76% Ability to interact virtually during networking times: good or excellent 75% Range of topics: about right 86% Gained something useful to work/research from presentations//informal discussion in other disciplines: Yes or possibly 100%//100% Identified potential collaborative opportunities//applications of interdisciplinary approaches: 82%//96% Usefulness to professional development: useful or very useful 100%  Comments:  Keren's presentation about how to make engineering meaningful for policymakers was very inspiring. It made me think about how I can work to make my research (wearable sensors, haptics, etc.) more understandable to policymakers both within Facebook as well as externally to the US government.  The use of augmented reality to reveal sea-level rise is one potential space for collaboration for me. The system modeling of human impacts on ecoology is also a potentially useful tool in relating technology to social change.  EU-US FOE   Virtual meeting structure: good or excellent 87% Quality of presentations: good or excellent 90% Ability to interact virtually during networking times: good or excellent 88% Range of topics: about right 87% Gained something useful to work/research from presentations//informal discussion in other disciplines: Yes or possibly 86%//86% Identified potential collaborative opportunities//applications of interdisciplinary approaches: 86%//86% Usefulness to professional development: useful or very useful 93%  Comments:  This was one of the best remote conferences I have attended. The overall environment was very interactive. The talks were all very interesting and definitely served to broaden my perspective. Based on the talks, I sent a number of emails to students and other collaborators about things to keep in mind for the future.  Being exposed to research problems and topics outside my current focus area helped widen my perspective. I also received a few interesting directions from some peers I met at the symposium.   GRAINGER GRANTS  Two grants of $30,000 from The Grainger Foundation were awarded to US FOE attendees who developed collaborative research projects. The recipients were:   Anita Shukla (Brown University) and Arezoo Ardekani (Purdue University) for "A combined experimental and computational study of microbe-responsive antimicrobial hydrogels"  Karthish Manthiram (California Institute of Technology) and Suman Khatiwada (Syzygy Plasmonics) for "Integrating light and voltage-driven reactions in chemical manufacturing"       Last Modified: 03/21/2022       Submitted by: Janet R Hunziker]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
