<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Polyelectrolyte brushes: Stabilization through Controlled Charge Placement]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>442821.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>442821</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tomislav Pintauer</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tompinta@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927168</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[In this project funded by the Macromolecular, Supramolecular and Nanochemistry Program in the Division of Chemistry, Professor Christopher K. Ober at Cornell University is developing and studying polyelectrolyte brushes with controlled charged placement.  Polymer brushes are special, large molecular structures with polymer chains densely tethered to a surface.  They have unique and useful properties including wormlike conformation, compact molecular dimensions, and notable polymer chain end effects due to their compact and confined structures.  These particular polyelectrolyte brushes can interact with a biological environment actively or passively depending on the nature of a living system.  As such, the brushes are promising materials for biomedical devices, chemical sensors and drug-delivery systems.  In this research, synthetic methods are chosen to construct charged polyelectrolyte brushes, allowing systematic investigations of how charge placements changs the swelling, shape, mobility, and stability of the synthesized brushes.  Characterization is carried out using sophisticated chemical measurement techniques and also includes the effect of solution acidity and metal ions on brush behavior.  This research is interdisciplinary in nature and includes international collaborations with researchers in Germany and the United Kingdom.  The research program exposes graduate students and associated researchers to international science perspectives.  Graduate students serve as mentors and role models to undergraduate students, while at the same time gaini supervisory skills.  Undergraduates from Cornell University take part in the research during the academic year while students from other schools with an emphasis on underrepresented communities participate in research during the summer months.  Outreach activities include high school students and teachers through organized workshops.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research is focused on the preparation and study of a series of model poly(electrolyte)(PEL) brushes with carefully tailored placement of cationic and anionic groups used either alone or in combination in a single strand and bottle brush architecture based on acrylamide and styrene-maleimide polymers.  Characterization includes study of the effect of pH and metal ions on brush behavior of these new architecture PEL brushes.  Neutron and X-ray reflectometry studies of swollen polymer films are used as tools for understanding brush behavior.  Neutron reflectivity using labeled polymer chains to separately gather information about the different components (brush, sidearm, ions) of the polymer brush is also employed.  Brushes are grown from surfaces by means of controlled radical polymerization of charged or protected monomers.  Ionic groups are attached to acrylamide or maleimide backbones through tailored amine functional segments including peptoid units of selected lengths and ionic group content.  Longer peptoid side chains on a polymer backbone form bottle brush-like architectures while controlled charge spacing and location selectively add coulombic stress near to or away from the polymer backbone.  In addition to conventional vertically grown brushes, the research team is capitalizing on new lateral brush growth geometries through demonstrated microfabrication capabilities that enable parallel optical and X-ray or optical and neutron characterization of brush swelling under a range of wetting and electrolyte conditions.  This research addresses important questions on the conformation of dense polyelectrolyte brushes, including the effects of chain confinement and charge spacing.  The results have the potential to further advance fundamental understanding of the factors affecting the stability and stimulus-responsive nature of surface-grafted bottlebrush polymers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/23/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/23/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2003588</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Christopher</FirstName>
<LastName>Ober</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>K</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Christopher K Ober</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[cko3@cornell.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000101773</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/23/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Cornell University</Name>
<CityName>ITHACA</CityName>
<ZipCode>148502820</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6072555014</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>341 PINE TREE RD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>19</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY19</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>G56PUALJ3KT5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CORNELL UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Cornell University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>148531501</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>19</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY19</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6885</Code>
<Text>Macromolec/Supramolec/Nano</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~442821</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>In this project funded by the Macromolecular, Supramolecular and Nanochemistry Program in the Division of Chemistry, Professor Christopher K. Ober at Cornell University has developed polyelectrolyte brushes with controlled charged placement. Polymer brushes are special macromolecular structures with polymer chains densely tethered to a surface. They have some unique and useful applications including biomedical devices, chemical sensors, or drug-delivery systems, all due to the wormlike conformation, compact molecular dimension, and notable polymer chain end effects due to their compact and confined densely grafted structure. When loaded with either positively charged (cationic) or negatively charged (anionic) groups, these polyelectrolyte brushes can interact actively or passively with a biological environment depending on its nature.</p> <p>Intellectual Merit: In this research, chemistries were chosen to construct polyelectrolyte brushes with selected placement and spacing of charges, allowing systematic investigation of how charge placement changes the swelling, shape, mobility, and stability of the synthesized brushes. This research focused on preparation and study of a series of model poly(electrolyte) (PEL) brushes with carefully tailored placement of cationic or anionic groups used either alone or in combination in a single strand or bottle brush architecture based on acrylamide and styrene-maleimide polymers (Fig. 1). Characterization was carried out using sophisticated chemical measurement techniques and included the effect of solution acidity and metal ions on brush behavior, something a brush might encounter if used in a biological environment. Characterization included study of the effect of pH and metal ions on brush behavior of these new architecture PEL brushes, studied in part using neutron reflectometry studies of swollen polymer films. In addition, fluorescence measurements were introduced to explore the state of the polymer chains and examine the autofluorescence of these brushes. The brushes change their intrinsic fluorescence as a function of the local environment (see Fig. 2). The results have the potential to further advance fundamental understanding of the factors affecting the stability and stimulus-responsive nature of surface-grafted bottlebrush polymers. These brushes can also be patterned and made to respond differently to different stimuli for potential use in a biosensor (Fig. 3)</p> <p>Broader Impacts: This work is highly interdisciplinary in nature and includes international collaboration with researchers in Germany and England and involved research visits to both countries. The research program exposed post-doctoral researchers to a global research interaction while they also served as mentors and role models to undergraduate students, thus gaining supervisory skills. Undergraduates from Cornell University took part in the research during the academic year while students from other schools participated in research during summer months. These undergrads are co-authors on several published and upcoming publications. During these studies thanks to interactions with our German collaborator, we have become interested in the study of capture-release brushes that enable the concentration of low concentration analytes followed by release from the brush for analysis. Focused on diol and sugar capturing boronic caid containing brushes we are working on new sensors constructed from these polymer brushes and the use of fluorescence to monitor the capture process. This ongoing work may lead to new kinds of detection devices.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/22/2023<br>      Modified by: Christopher&nbsp;K&nbsp;Ober</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2003588/2003588_10679882_1697979279680_StablePEBswithalternatingsequence--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2003588/2003588_10679882_1697979279680_StablePEBswithalternatingsequence--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 1"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2003588/2003588_10679882_1697979279680_StablePEBswithalternatingsequence--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 1"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">(Middle) Schematic of reduced stress and enhanced stability poly(styrene-alt-N-maleimide) polyelectrolyte brushes. (Upper left) XPS signal showing nitrogen in charged cationic group (N+) and back bone (N0). (Upper right) Charged group on maleimide repeat with different back bone distance.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Gozde Aktes</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Christopher&nbsp;K&nbsp;Ober</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 1</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2003588/2003588_10679882_1697979158585_VisualizationofpHresponsevaiauto-fluorescentPEBs--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2003588/2003588_10679882_1697979158585_VisualizationofpHresponsevaiauto-fluorescentPEBs--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 2."><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2003588/2003588_10679882_1697979158585_VisualizationofpHresponsevaiauto-fluorescentPEBs--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 2."></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">(Upper) Schematic of pH-triggered conformational change and luminescence of the brushes. (Lower left) CLSM images of the brushes: collapsed state (pH 3); (Lower middle) swollen state (pH 11). (Lower right) Fluorescence emission spectra of the polymer brush surfaces in buffer solutions with</div> <div class="imageCredit">Gozde Aktes</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Christopher&nbsp;K&nbsp;Ober</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 2.</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2003588/2003588_10679882_1697979370889_NanopatternedAuto-fluorescentPEBs--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2003588/2003588_10679882_1697979370889_NanopatternedAuto-fluorescentPEBs--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 3"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2003588/2003588_10679882_1697979370889_NanopatternedAuto-fluorescentPEBs--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 3"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Fluorescence images of the nanopatterned brushes showing ability for integration into a small scale sensing device.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Gozde Aktes</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Christopher&nbsp;K&nbsp;Ober</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 3</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ In this project funded by the Macromolecular, Supramolecular and Nanochemistry Program in the Division of Chemistry, Professor Christopher K. Ober at Cornell University has developed polyelectrolyte brushes with controlled charged placement. Polymer brushes are special macromolecular structures with polymer chains densely tethered to a surface. They have some unique and useful applications including biomedical devices, chemical sensors, or drug-delivery systems, all due to the wormlike conformation, compact molecular dimension, and notable polymer chain end effects due to their compact and confined densely grafted structure. When loaded with either positively charged (cationic) or negatively charged (anionic) groups, these polyelectrolyte brushes can interact actively or passively with a biological environment depending on its nature.  Intellectual Merit: In this research, chemistries were chosen to construct polyelectrolyte brushes with selected placement and spacing of charges, allowing systematic investigation of how charge placement changes the swelling, shape, mobility, and stability of the synthesized brushes. This research focused on preparation and study of a series of model poly(electrolyte) (PEL) brushes with carefully tailored placement of cationic or anionic groups used either alone or in combination in a single strand or bottle brush architecture based on acrylamide and styrene-maleimide polymers (Fig. 1). Characterization was carried out using sophisticated chemical measurement techniques and included the effect of solution acidity and metal ions on brush behavior, something a brush might encounter if used in a biological environment. Characterization included study of the effect of pH and metal ions on brush behavior of these new architecture PEL brushes, studied in part using neutron reflectometry studies of swollen polymer films. In addition, fluorescence measurements were introduced to explore the state of the polymer chains and examine the autofluorescence of these brushes. The brushes change their intrinsic fluorescence as a function of the local environment (see Fig. 2). The results have the potential to further advance fundamental understanding of the factors affecting the stability and stimulus-responsive nature of surface-grafted bottlebrush polymers. These brushes can also be patterned and made to respond differently to different stimuli for potential use in a biosensor (Fig. 3)  Broader Impacts: This work is highly interdisciplinary in nature and includes international collaboration with researchers in Germany and England and involved research visits to both countries. The research program exposed post-doctoral researchers to a global research interaction while they also served as mentors and role models to undergraduate students, thus gaining supervisory skills. Undergraduates from Cornell University took part in the research during the academic year while students from other schools participated in research during summer months. These undergrads are co-authors on several published and upcoming publications. During these studies thanks to interactions with our German collaborator, we have become interested in the study of capture-release brushes that enable the concentration of low concentration analytes followed by release from the brush for analysis. Focused on diol and sugar capturing boronic caid containing brushes we are working on new sensors constructed from these polymer brushes and the use of fluorescence to monitor the capture process. This ongoing work may lead to new kinds of detection devices.       Last Modified: 10/22/2023       Submitted by: Christopher K Ober]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
