<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[STTR Phase I:  Multiuse Rural Photovoltaic Module]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>225000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>225000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rajesh Mehta</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rmehta@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922174</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial impact of this Small Business Technology Transfer (STTR) Phase I project is to enable simultaneous use of farmland for farming and solar energy production. This project will advance a technology to appropriately direct sunlight into solar cells and farm use.  This provides additional revenue to farmers and creates a controlled growth environment that requires less water, provides protection from hail and the elements, and extends the growing season.  The technology enhances feedback because growing crops below the solar modules cools the region of the solar cells and improves their efficiency. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This STTR Phase I project advances translation of new photovoltaic structures and physical mechanisms though the development of a new approach to semiconductor device, integrating advances on high efficiency with the robustness of silicon cells. This project will design an agrivoltaic module that optimizes the trade-offs between light to the photovoltaic module through optical concentration and light to the crops below. The R&amp;D plan comprises four parts: (1) development of a simulation model that includes regional solar and economic data; (2) determination of the design parameters of the optical film (e.g., optical concentration, wavelength range, etc); (3) design of the solar cell integrated with the optical film; and (4) construction and field testing of the new solar module to show its beneficial impact on crops and the farming ecosystem.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/26/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/15/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2003572</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
<LastName>Sampson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Robert Sampson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[bob@sunestasolar.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000718429</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/26/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>SUNESTA SOLAR, INC.</Name>
<CityName>PEORIA</CityName>
<ZipCode>853833187</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6023630285</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>29618 N 69TH LN</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AZ08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>GXPWECLN1GE9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SUNESTA SOLAR, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Arizona State University - Solar Power Lab]]></Name>
<CityName>TEMPE</CityName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>852841808</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[7700 S River Parkway]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AZ04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1505</Code>
<Text>STTR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1238</Code>
<Text>TECH FOR SUSTAINABLE ENVIRONMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8034</Code>
<Text>Hardware Components</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~225000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p style="text-align: center;">Multiuse Rural Photovoltaic Module</p> <p style="text-align: left;">Agrivoltaics, the dual use of land for growing crops and generating electricity at the same time by covering the crop with a solar field, is rapidly gaining interest.&nbsp; This approach is important due to its ability to meet the needs of farmers by preserving land for food production and the general population by providing large areas of land to generate electricity.&nbsp; Additionally, covering farmland with solar fields offers a symbiotic relationship between the crop and solar field.&nbsp; The crop is protected from elements such as wind, hail, freezing, frost, and snow, while utilizing less water and gaining protection from the sun. &nbsp;The solar field benefits from this relationship by cooling the modules through transpiration from the plants. Solar modules generate more electricity when they are cool.</p> <p>Despite the many benefits of agrivoltaics, there are multiple barriers to its widespread adoption, typically centered around the trade-off between cost factors and optimizing the light conditions for both plants and the PV modules. For example, presently used approaches typically involve spacing out the modules to allow more light for plants, but they still do not optimize the conditions for plant growth. Moreover, these approaches increase the cost of the system, particularly since agrivoltaics systems often are built higher off the ground, thereby increasing mounting costs per area. Unfortunately, this also reduces electricity generation, both of which increase the cost of electricity compared to a conventional system. Other approaches utilize tracking systems to manage sunlight to the crops, which also increases cost, and during certain periods of the year can substantially reduce electrical output.</p> <p>Overall, there are currently no solar modules on the market that optimize the conditions for crops and photovoltaics panels. Our research has shown that there is a tremendous need for a solar module that optimizes both the light to the plants and the amount of energy produced by the solar modules.&nbsp; Sunesta's solar module utilizes a unique approach that circumvents the competition for appropriate light between plants and the solar modules allowing better crop yield and higher electrical generation.&nbsp; The solar modules are constructed with an optical film which utilizes angular and wavelength selectivity, allowing optimal light within a range of incident angles and wavelengths vital to plant growth to reach the plants while light at other incident angles more beneficial to the solar cells, is diverted there.</p> <p>By growing various crops under solar modules and in a control group under direct sunlight, we were able to experimentally determine the benefits of agrivoltaics to several crops.&nbsp; Crops were grown with two conditions; one group being fully irrigated, and the other group with 50% irrigation.&nbsp; The photosynthesis rate for the crops were measured throughout the day.&nbsp; Photosynthesis is dependent on sunlight, temperature, water availability and the type of crop. When plants reach their light saturation point photosynthesis stops as the plant becomes heat- or water-stressed.&nbsp; All crops grown in the direct sunlight halted photosynthesis in the early morning and reached their peak level of photosynthesis between 8:00 and 10:00 a.m.&nbsp; In comparison, the crops grown under the solar modules reached a lower peak photosynthesis rate, but the crops did not halt photosynthesis due to heat- or water-stress and continued photosynthesis all day long.&nbsp; Additionally, we found those crops grown under solar modules with 50% irrigation grew similarly to crops grown at 100% irrigation.</p> <p>To demonstrate the feasibility of matching the angular selective solar module to the optimum plant response, we simulated the solar module with different optical responses.&nbsp; Crops were grown under solar modules with light altering film.&nbsp; Overall, the simulations, combined with the experimental results, demonstrated the feasibility of Sunesta's solar module and its ability to maximize crop yield and solar energy production. In addition, the development of this innovative solar module for agrivoltaics offers advantages for both agriculture and photovoltaics in that it yields a critical opportunity to develop American-based solar module manufacturing. This, in turn, benefits agriculture, manufacturing, and renewable energy sectors.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/30/2021<br>      Modified by: Robert&nbsp;Sampson</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[Multiuse Rural Photovoltaic Module Agrivoltaics, the dual use of land for growing crops and generating electricity at the same time by covering the crop with a solar field, is rapidly gaining interest.  This approach is important due to its ability to meet the needs of farmers by preserving land for food production and the general population by providing large areas of land to generate electricity.  Additionally, covering farmland with solar fields offers a symbiotic relationship between the crop and solar field.  The crop is protected from elements such as wind, hail, freezing, frost, and snow, while utilizing less water and gaining protection from the sun.  The solar field benefits from this relationship by cooling the modules through transpiration from the plants. Solar modules generate more electricity when they are cool.  Despite the many benefits of agrivoltaics, there are multiple barriers to its widespread adoption, typically centered around the trade-off between cost factors and optimizing the light conditions for both plants and the PV modules. For example, presently used approaches typically involve spacing out the modules to allow more light for plants, but they still do not optimize the conditions for plant growth. Moreover, these approaches increase the cost of the system, particularly since agrivoltaics systems often are built higher off the ground, thereby increasing mounting costs per area. Unfortunately, this also reduces electricity generation, both of which increase the cost of electricity compared to a conventional system. Other approaches utilize tracking systems to manage sunlight to the crops, which also increases cost, and during certain periods of the year can substantially reduce electrical output.  Overall, there are currently no solar modules on the market that optimize the conditions for crops and photovoltaics panels. Our research has shown that there is a tremendous need for a solar module that optimizes both the light to the plants and the amount of energy produced by the solar modules.  Sunesta's solar module utilizes a unique approach that circumvents the competition for appropriate light between plants and the solar modules allowing better crop yield and higher electrical generation.  The solar modules are constructed with an optical film which utilizes angular and wavelength selectivity, allowing optimal light within a range of incident angles and wavelengths vital to plant growth to reach the plants while light at other incident angles more beneficial to the solar cells, is diverted there.  By growing various crops under solar modules and in a control group under direct sunlight, we were able to experimentally determine the benefits of agrivoltaics to several crops.  Crops were grown with two conditions; one group being fully irrigated, and the other group with 50% irrigation.  The photosynthesis rate for the crops were measured throughout the day.  Photosynthesis is dependent on sunlight, temperature, water availability and the type of crop. When plants reach their light saturation point photosynthesis stops as the plant becomes heat- or water-stressed.  All crops grown in the direct sunlight halted photosynthesis in the early morning and reached their peak level of photosynthesis between 8:00 and 10:00 a.m.  In comparison, the crops grown under the solar modules reached a lower peak photosynthesis rate, but the crops did not halt photosynthesis due to heat- or water-stress and continued photosynthesis all day long.  Additionally, we found those crops grown under solar modules with 50% irrigation grew similarly to crops grown at 100% irrigation.  To demonstrate the feasibility of matching the angular selective solar module to the optimum plant response, we simulated the solar module with different optical responses.  Crops were grown under solar modules with light altering film.  Overall, the simulations, combined with the experimental results, demonstrated the feasibility of Sunesta's solar module and its ability to maximize crop yield and solar energy production. In addition, the development of this innovative solar module for agrivoltaics offers advantages for both agriculture and photovoltaics in that it yields a critical opportunity to develop American-based solar module manufacturing. This, in turn, benefits agriculture, manufacturing, and renewable energy sectors.          Last Modified: 11/30/2021       Submitted by: Robert Sampson]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
