<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research: Structure and function of flavin-dependent N-monooxygenases]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>198000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>198000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tingyu Li</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tli@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924949</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[With this award, the Chemistry of Life Processes Program in the Chemistry Division is funding Dr. Pablo Sobrado from Virginia Tech and John. J. Tanner from the University of Missouri to investigate the structure and chemistry of enzymes known as flavin-dependent-N-monooxygenases (NMOs). NMOs play integral parts in how microorganisms make numerous natural compounds for a variety of purposes.  These compounds can also have useful bioactivities that benefit society.  While many flavin-dependent enzymes are well known and have been thoroughly characterized, the NMOs are a relatively recently discovered branch on the family tree, and do not resemble the other members in common ways.  This leads to the hypothesis that new and interesting structures and chemistries are likely to be at play in the reactions catalyzed by the NMOs.  The investigators choose several examples of NMOs for in depth examination in order to compare and contrast their behaviors.  Further, a highly multidisciplinary approach is proposed to provide the broadest possible understanding of the enzymes.  The proposed experimental approach will provide a platform for the training of undergraduate and graduate students in modern enzymology and biophysical chemistry. The laboratories are also committed to strategies to enhance diversity in the scientific research workforce.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project expands our knowledge of the diversity of flavoenzymes through the structural and biochemical characterization of new N-monooxygenases. Because these enzymes have low similarity to proteins already in the Protein Data Bank, the structures are expected to exhibit novel features and reveal unanticipated relationships to other enzymes.  This further advances our understanding of the evolutionary relatedness of these enzymes.  Also addressed are key knowledge gaps in our understanding of flavoenzyme mechanisms by characterizing “double-hydroxylating” NMOs, exploring a newly discovered flavin “flapping” motion in Group B NMOs, and trapping heretofore-elusive flavoenzyme-ligand complexes in crystallo for structure determination.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/18/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/18/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2003986</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Tanner</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John J Tanner</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[tannerjj@missouri.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000400298</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/18/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Missouri-Columbia</Name>
<CityName>COLUMBIA</CityName>
<ZipCode>652113020</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5738827560</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>121 UNIVERSITY HALL</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MO03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>SZPJL5ZRCLF4</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MISSOURI SYSTEM</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Missouri-Columbia]]></Name>
<CityName>Columbia</CityName>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>652115100</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[117 Schweitzer Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MO03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6883</Code>
<Text>Chemistry of Life Processes</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~198000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project seeks to understand how the enzymes underlie the multitude of chemical reactions that support life. Our main approach is to use three-dimensional structure as a lens to understand enzyme function. The major outcome of this project is the X-ray crystal structure determination of the three-dimensional atomic structures of several enzymes that utilize a special form of vitamin B2 (known as flavin adenine dinucleotide) to catalyze chemical reactions involved in the biosynthesis and utilization of&nbsp;natural products in microorganisms and plants. These enzymes are responsible for key chemical steps in the biosynthesis of molecules called siderophores, which enable pathogenic bacteria to scavenge iron from the host during infection, the production of molecules that give garlic its unique flavor, and the synthesis of the antibiotic valanimycin in bacteria. The structures show how these enzymes recognize their substrates and provide insight into the chemical mechanism by which substrates are transformed into products. This information adds to our knowledge of the protein structure universe and the evolutionary relatedness of proteins, while providing insight into the mechanisms of microbial pathogenesis, which is useful for developing new strategies to combat microbial infections, and new information about natural products that contribute to the unique features of plants and serve as antibiotics.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/03/2023<br>      Modified by: John&nbsp;J&nbsp;Tanner</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2003986/2003986_10678644_1688407102128_figurex1v2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2003986/2003986_10678644_1688407102128_figurex1v2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Fold and oligomeric structure of FbsI."><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2003986/2003986_10678644_1688407102128_figurex1v2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Fold and oligomeric structure of FbsI."></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Fold and oligomeric structure of FbsI. (A) Protomer of FbsI complexed with FAD and NADP+. The protein is colored using a rainbow scheme with blue at the N-terminus and red at the C-terminus. FAD and NADP+ are shown in yellow and gray sticks, respectively. (B) The tetramer of FbsI viewed along its th</div> <div class="imageCredit">John Tanner doi: 10.1021/acs.biochem.2c00493</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">John&nbsp;J&nbsp;Tanner</div> <div class="imageTitle">Fold and oligomeric structure of FbsI.</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project seeks to understand how the enzymes underlie the multitude of chemical reactions that support life. Our main approach is to use three-dimensional structure as a lens to understand enzyme function. The major outcome of this project is the X-ray crystal structure determination of the three-dimensional atomic structures of several enzymes that utilize a special form of vitamin B2 (known as flavin adenine dinucleotide) to catalyze chemical reactions involved in the biosynthesis and utilization of natural products in microorganisms and plants. These enzymes are responsible for key chemical steps in the biosynthesis of molecules called siderophores, which enable pathogenic bacteria to scavenge iron from the host during infection, the production of molecules that give garlic its unique flavor, and the synthesis of the antibiotic valanimycin in bacteria. The structures show how these enzymes recognize their substrates and provide insight into the chemical mechanism by which substrates are transformed into products. This information adds to our knowledge of the protein structure universe and the evolutionary relatedness of proteins, while providing insight into the mechanisms of microbial pathogenesis, which is useful for developing new strategies to combat microbial infections, and new information about natural products that contribute to the unique features of plants and serve as antibiotics.          Last Modified: 07/03/2023       Submitted by: John J Tanner]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
