<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research: CAS-MNP: Understand and Predict the Adsorption of Organic Contaminants by Aging Microplastics]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>79000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>79000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anne-Marie Schmoltner</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>aschmolt@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924716</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This award from the Environmental Chemical Sciences Program in the Division of Chemistry supports Professors Francois Perreault and Jay Oswald at Arizona State University and Professor Onur Apul at the University of Maine for research on microplastics. These small plastic particles form during the breakdown of waste plastic. Because of their small size, microplastics accumulate more organic contaminants on their surface than larger plastic pieces. Microplastics age in the environment due to the action of sunlight or microorganisms, which changes their surface characteristics. To predict the environmental effects of microplastics, it is important to understand how aging of microplastics by sunlight or microorganisms affect contaminant adsorption. This project focuses on the aging of low-density polyethylene, one of the most abundant plastics. The exploratory scope of this project leads to insights for future in-depth studies of the nature of microplastics aging and their effect in complex natural systems. Graduate and undergraduate students at the two institutions have the opportunity to learn about interdisciplinary research, including experimental and theoretical work. The team also engages in age-appropriate outreach activities on the topic of plastic pollution for K-12 students in their communities.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;            This project combines experimental and theoretical approaches to identify the molecular-level mechanisms involved in organic contaminant adsorption on pristine and aged low-density polyethylene microplastics. Laboratory-based aging procedures, simulating the effect of sunlight or surface biofilms, are used to produce well-characterized low-density polyethylene microparticles representative of environmental microplastics. Using these model microplastics, adsorption isotherms are measured for a range of model organic contaminants to determine how biofilms or the change in surface chemistry affect the adsorption of different classes of contaminant. Molecular dynamics simulations are used to identify, based on the aged microplastics characterization, the molecular-level changes in surface chemistry that occur during environmental aging. This multidisciplinary approach provides a mechanistic insight into how environmental aging by sunlight or biofilms affect the role of microplastics as vectors of organic contaminants in the environment. The experimental framework developed in this project can be applied to a wide range of microplastic materials or mechanism of environmental aging to provide a comprehensive understanding of how organic contaminants will interact with microplastics in the environment over time.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/19/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/15/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2003859</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Onur</FirstName>
<LastName>Apul</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Onur Apul</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[onur.apul@maine.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000758858</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/19/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Maine</Name>
<CityName>ORONO</CityName>
<ZipCode>044695717</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2075811484</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5717 CORBETT HALL</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maine</StateName>
<StateCode>ME</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>ME02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>PB3AJE5ZEJ59</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MAINE SYSTEM</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Maine]]></Name>
<CityName>Orono</CityName>
<StateCode>ME</StateCode>
<ZipCode>044695703</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[168 College Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maine</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>ME02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6882</Code>
<Text>Environmental Chemical Science</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>090Z</Code>
<Text>CAS-Critical Aspects of Sustainability</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~79000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project was to understand the interactons between synthetic organic compounds and microplastics in natural source waters. Microplastics are small fragments of plastic waste that is found commonly in the nature. The project was predominantly driven by experiments to test the effect of sunlight-based aging on microplastic surfaces and whether it changes the interactions between microplastics and organic compounds. The project first started compiling all available literature data. This compilation was to understand the literature and organize the availability of experimental data; hence our new experiments can fill research gaps. After the literature review, the student researchers were trained to conduct UV-light simulations and age microplastics systematically in the lab. Next, the microplastics were put in contact with common organic pollutants and their interactions were observed experimentally. In certain instances, UV-aging was found to incerase the adsorption capacity of microplastics for organic pollutants. During UV-aging experiments, students noticed some changes in "aging solution" or "background water". Therefore, we investigated the effects of sunlight-based aging on the quality of background water. This lead to greater understanding of microplastic surface aging mechanisms. Also, the background water had noticible levels of microplastic-based leachate. Once experimental datasets and literautre database were sufficiently large, we created a predictive mathematical equation. This equation was to minimize the need for conducting tedious and costly experiments in the future for similar materials and pollutants. Overall, the student researchers experienced scientific research in the lab which was complemented with mathematical modeling. The research team presented their work in national and internatinal conferences and published some of these discoveries in five peer-reviewed journal articles. The project also resulted in training Girl Scouts of Maine during their campus visit on microplastic pollution. As a result of this project, new scientific knowledge was generated, students were trained in the lab and new research directions were established.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/29/2023<br>      Modified by: Onur&nbsp;Apul</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project was to understand the interactons between synthetic organic compounds and microplastics in natural source waters. Microplastics are small fragments of plastic waste that is found commonly in the nature. The project was predominantly driven by experiments to test the effect of sunlight-based aging on microplastic surfaces and whether it changes the interactions between microplastics and organic compounds. The project first started compiling all available literature data. This compilation was to understand the literature and organize the availability of experimental data; hence our new experiments can fill research gaps. After the literature review, the student researchers were trained to conduct UV-light simulations and age microplastics systematically in the lab. Next, the microplastics were put in contact with common organic pollutants and their interactions were observed experimentally. In certain instances, UV-aging was found to incerase the adsorption capacity of microplastics for organic pollutants. During UV-aging experiments, students noticed some changes in "aging solution" or "background water". Therefore, we investigated the effects of sunlight-based aging on the quality of background water. This lead to greater understanding of microplastic surface aging mechanisms. Also, the background water had noticible levels of microplastic-based leachate. Once experimental datasets and literautre database were sufficiently large, we created a predictive mathematical equation. This equation was to minimize the need for conducting tedious and costly experiments in the future for similar materials and pollutants. Overall, the student researchers experienced scientific research in the lab which was complemented with mathematical modeling. The research team presented their work in national and internatinal conferences and published some of these discoveries in five peer-reviewed journal articles. The project also resulted in training Girl Scouts of Maine during their campus visit on microplastic pollution. As a result of this project, new scientific knowledge was generated, students were trained in the lab and new research directions were established.       Last Modified: 09/29/2023       Submitted by: Onur Apul]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
