<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research: MLWiNS: Hyperdimensional Computing for Scalable IoT Intelligence Beyond the Edge]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>60000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>60000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Alhussein Abouzeid</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>aabouzei@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032920000</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The Internet of Things (IoT) generates large amounts of data that machine learning algorithms today process in the cloud.  The heterogeneity of the data types and devices, along with limited computing and communication capabilities of IoT devices, poses a significant challenge to real-time training and learning with classical machine learning algorithms. This project instead proposes to use Hyperdimensional (HD) computing for distributed machine learning. HD computing is a brain-inspired machine learning paradigm that transforms data into knowledge at very low cost, while being extremely robust to errors. When completed, this project has the potential to change the way machine learning is done today – instead of depending on the cloud, IoT systems will be able to make quality decisions on the spot, in real time, regardless of connectivity, with long battery lifetime.    This will be made possible by designing: i) novel HD encoding schemes to represent various data in IoT applications including numerical feature vectors, time-series data, and images, ii) a novel distributed learning framework for IoT networks by incorporating active learning to considerably reduce communication overhead and learning costs, and iii) a reliable learning solution based on the error-tolerant characteristic of HD computing.  The ideas developed in this project will be tested on both UCSD and SDSU using a fully instrumented testbed for human activity recognition.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/28/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/28/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2003277</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Baris</FirstName>
<LastName>Aksanli</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Baris Aksanli</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[baksanli@sdsu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000733290</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/28/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>San Diego State University Foundation</Name>
<CityName>SAN DIEGO</CityName>
<ZipCode>921821901</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6195945731</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5250 CAMPANILE DR MC1947</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>51</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA51</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>H59JKGFZKHL7</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SAN DIEGO STATE UNIVERSITY FOUNDATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[San Diego State University]]></Name>
<CityName>San Diego</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>921821309</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5500 Campanile Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>51</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA51</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7363</Code>
<Text>Networking Technology and Syst</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>021Z</Code>
<Text>Industry Partnerships</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1653</Code>
<Text>Adaptive &amp; intelligent systems</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8585</Code>
<Text>NSF/Intel Partnership Projects</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~60000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Overview: </strong>This is a collaborative project with NSF #2003279 (with the University of California San Diego). The main goal of the project is to develop accurate, fast, and reliable (secure) machine learning algorithms, using Hyperdimensional computing for scalable Internet of Things applications. Hyperdimensional (HD) computing is a new machine learning paradigm that can transform data into knowledge at very low cost and with comparable accuracy to state-of-the-art methods for diverse applications, e.g., language recognition, robotics, and general intelligence. It is also very robust to errors in communication - it can correctly infer even when as much as 50% of the bits are corrupted.&nbsp;&nbsp; HD computing encodes the raw data into high-dimensional vectors (hypervectors) which can have as many as 10,000 bits. Processing data requires simple arithmetic operations, rotation, and nearest neighbor search, all of which are easy to accelerate in hardware, thus leading to very low-power and high-performance implementations. Combining hypervectors facilitates aggregation of heterogeneous data collected from different devices.</p> <p><strong>Intellectual merit: </strong>The goal of our work is to realize energy-efficient, noise-resilient, and low-overhead distributed learning at the IoT edge using HD computing. To accomplish our goal, we:</p> <ul> <li>Develop new encoder and model quantization methods. These methods result in significant energy savings with high accuracy.</li> <li>Increase the robustness of machine learning models using HD. We demonstrate that our HD-based solutions are highly robust to errors in data, while being faster in computation.</li> <li>Increase the generalizability of HD models by providing support for multi-label classification. Our HD-based implementation reaches multiple orders of magnitude improvement in terms of energy consumption and computation time, while yielding high accuracy.</li> <li>Analyze the security of HD against adversarial attack scenarios. We demonstrate that HD is a more resilient and lightweight learning solution compared to the state-of-the-art machine learning models when adversarial attacks are present.</li> </ul> <p><strong>Broader impacts: </strong>The research outcomes from this project will enable more efficient machine learning mechanisms that can run on resource limited edge devices. This will improve the response time of the applications, providing a better real-time experience to the users. The work done in this project was disseminated through several journal and conference papers. These publications are publicly available and have been deposited in the NSF Public Access Repository. The project provided training and professional development opportunities to two JDP (Joint Doctoral Program between San Diego State University, SDSU, and the University of California San Diego, UCSD) students in the Electrical and Computer Engineering (ECE) Departments of SDSU and UCSD. The project also created collaboration opportunities between SDSU and UCSD students.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/22/2023<br>      Modified by: Baris&nbsp;Aksanli</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Overview: This is a collaborative project with NSF #2003279 (with the University of California San Diego). The main goal of the project is to develop accurate, fast, and reliable (secure) machine learning algorithms, using Hyperdimensional computing for scalable Internet of Things applications. Hyperdimensional (HD) computing is a new machine learning paradigm that can transform data into knowledge at very low cost and with comparable accuracy to state-of-the-art methods for diverse applications, e.g., language recognition, robotics, and general intelligence. It is also very robust to errors in communication - it can correctly infer even when as much as 50% of the bits are corrupted.   HD computing encodes the raw data into high-dimensional vectors (hypervectors) which can have as many as 10,000 bits. Processing data requires simple arithmetic operations, rotation, and nearest neighbor search, all of which are easy to accelerate in hardware, thus leading to very low-power and high-performance implementations. Combining hypervectors facilitates aggregation of heterogeneous data collected from different devices.  Intellectual merit: The goal of our work is to realize energy-efficient, noise-resilient, and low-overhead distributed learning at the IoT edge using HD computing. To accomplish our goal, we:  Develop new encoder and model quantization methods. These methods result in significant energy savings with high accuracy. Increase the robustness of machine learning models using HD. We demonstrate that our HD-based solutions are highly robust to errors in data, while being faster in computation. Increase the generalizability of HD models by providing support for multi-label classification. Our HD-based implementation reaches multiple orders of magnitude improvement in terms of energy consumption and computation time, while yielding high accuracy. Analyze the security of HD against adversarial attack scenarios. We demonstrate that HD is a more resilient and lightweight learning solution compared to the state-of-the-art machine learning models when adversarial attacks are present.   Broader impacts: The research outcomes from this project will enable more efficient machine learning mechanisms that can run on resource limited edge devices. This will improve the response time of the applications, providing a better real-time experience to the users. The work done in this project was disseminated through several journal and conference papers. These publications are publicly available and have been deposited in the NSF Public Access Repository. The project provided training and professional development opportunities to two JDP (Joint Doctoral Program between San Diego State University, SDSU, and the University of California San Diego, UCSD) students in the Electrical and Computer Engineering (ECE) Departments of SDSU and UCSD. The project also created collaboration opportunities between SDSU and UCSD students.       Last Modified: 09/22/2023       Submitted by: Baris Aksanli]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
