<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Macaulay2 Workshop at Cleveland State University]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>19973.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>19973</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>James Matthew Douglass</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mdouglas@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922467</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This grant supports an online software development workshop for the software Macaulay2 held May 11-15, 2020 and an in person conference to be held at Cleveland State University on a weekend in October or November 2020 (the exact dates depend on COVID-19 pandemic related restrictions). Macaulay2 is one of the world's leading software packages for supporting research in commutative algebra and algebraic geometry. Macaulay2 is open source, and researchers can extend its functionality by adding their own code in the form of packages. The workshop allowed new users to learn from experienced programmers how to develop high quality packages that will be made publicly available to support future research. The Fall conference will bring some of the May workshop participants together to discuss progress in their coding efforts and present related research results. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The workshop featured tutorial sessions on Macaulay2 and other tools for collaborative development. The organizers identified coding projects in active research areas of commutative algebra and algebraic geometry, including algebraic statistics, coding theory, fast linear algebra, invariants of reductive groups, and toric varieties. Participants formed small groups and collaborated on writing code for these and other packages. In addition, the workshop included professional development activities for early career mathematicians, such as panel discussions on jobs and developing a research program that successfully incorporates computational tools. The Fall conference will take place over a weekend (Friday afternoon to Sunday morning) and will feature invited speakers from the various coding groups. More details are available at the website: https://math.galetto.org/m2csu2020.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/27/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/27/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2003883</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Courtney</FirstName>
<LastName>Gibbons</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Courtney Gibbons</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[crgibbon@hamilton.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000757814</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/27/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Branden</FirstName>
<LastName>Stone</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Branden Stone</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[bstone@adelphi.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000732934</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/27/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Federico</FirstName>
<LastName>Galetto</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Federico Galetto</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[f.galetto@csuohio.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000812798</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/27/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Hiram</FirstName>
<LastName>Lopez Valdez</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Hiram H Lopez Valdez</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[hhlopez@vt.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000812836</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/27/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Cleveland State University</Name>
<CityName>CLEVELAND</CityName>
<ZipCode>441152214</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2166873630</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2121 EUCLID AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>11</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OH11</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>YKGMTXA2NVL6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CLEVELAND STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Cleveland State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Cleveland</CityName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>441152214</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2121 Euclid Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>11</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OH11</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1264</Code>
<Text>ALGEBRA,NUMBER THEORY,AND COM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8069</Code>
<Text>CDS&amp;E-MSS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9263</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL SCIENCE &amp; ENGING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~19973</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Macaulay2 is one of the leading software supporting research in commutative algebra and algebraic geometry, and it is free and open source. This grant helped fund the following events:</p> <ol> <li>a virtual workshop in May 2020 centered around development of new functionality for Macaulay2;</li> <li>a 2-day workshop at Cleveland State University in May 2022 on the internal development of Macaulay2;</li> <li>a 3-day conference at Cleveland State University in May 2022 on state-of-the-art research in computational commutative algebra, algebraic geometry, and related areas.</li> </ol> <p>All three events brought together early career and senior mathematicians, offering opportunities for training of new researchers.</p> <p>The 2020 virtual workshop followed the structure of many highly successful previous workshops. Younger and less experienced participants were paired with more experienced leaders to develop new functionality for Macaulay2. The work resulted in software packages enabling new computations in invariant theory, algebraic statistics, coding theory, toric varieties, numerical algebraic geometry, monomial integer programming, subalgebra bases, fast linear algebra, and numerical certification. These packages will support new research for years to come, and will offer additional teaching tools for topics in advanced mathematics. Two of the new packages have been published in scientific journals, and two more are under review as of July 2022. The code developed during the workshop is publicly available on Github.</p> <p>The 2022 conference was attended by 39 in person participants and 4 remote participants. Among the attendees, 2 were undergraduate students, 20 graduate students, and 9 postdocs (with the remaining being faculty). The conference included 14 research talks, which spurred lively conversations on topics of current interest and generated ideas for future research and coding projects. Conference speakers included: Michael Burr, Justin Chen, Henry Chimal Dzul, Francesca Gandini, Kriti Goel, Nicholas Iammarino, Selvi Kara, Kisun Lee, Anton Leykin, Nathan Nichols, Jose Israel Rodriguez, Mahrud Sayrafi, Gregory G. Smith, and Aleksandra Sobieska.</p> <p>The 2-day internals workshop preceded the conference and offered an opportunity to discuss several issues concerning the development of Macaulay2, including technical improvements, standards for future development, and ways to promote new projects and attract new developers. The workshop participants also presented their activities to the broader conference community in the form of a panel discussion.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/01/2022<br>      Modified by: Federico&nbsp;Galetto</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Macaulay2 is one of the leading software supporting research in commutative algebra and algebraic geometry, and it is free and open source. This grant helped fund the following events:  a virtual workshop in May 2020 centered around development of new functionality for Macaulay2; a 2-day workshop at Cleveland State University in May 2022 on the internal development of Macaulay2; a 3-day conference at Cleveland State University in May 2022 on state-of-the-art research in computational commutative algebra, algebraic geometry, and related areas.   All three events brought together early career and senior mathematicians, offering opportunities for training of new researchers.  The 2020 virtual workshop followed the structure of many highly successful previous workshops. Younger and less experienced participants were paired with more experienced leaders to develop new functionality for Macaulay2. The work resulted in software packages enabling new computations in invariant theory, algebraic statistics, coding theory, toric varieties, numerical algebraic geometry, monomial integer programming, subalgebra bases, fast linear algebra, and numerical certification. These packages will support new research for years to come, and will offer additional teaching tools for topics in advanced mathematics. Two of the new packages have been published in scientific journals, and two more are under review as of July 2022. The code developed during the workshop is publicly available on Github.  The 2022 conference was attended by 39 in person participants and 4 remote participants. Among the attendees, 2 were undergraduate students, 20 graduate students, and 9 postdocs (with the remaining being faculty). The conference included 14 research talks, which spurred lively conversations on topics of current interest and generated ideas for future research and coding projects. Conference speakers included: Michael Burr, Justin Chen, Henry Chimal Dzul, Francesca Gandini, Kriti Goel, Nicholas Iammarino, Selvi Kara, Kisun Lee, Anton Leykin, Nathan Nichols, Jose Israel Rodriguez, Mahrud Sayrafi, Gregory G. Smith, and Aleksandra Sobieska.  The 2-day internals workshop preceded the conference and offered an opportunity to discuss several issues concerning the development of Macaulay2, including technical improvements, standards for future development, and ways to promote new projects and attract new developers. The workshop participants also presented their activities to the broader conference community in the form of a panel discussion.       Last Modified: 09/01/2022       Submitted by: Federico Galetto]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
