<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Understanding the Formation and Utilization of Halogenated Metabolites in Natural Product Biosynthesis]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>435000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>435000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Pablo Sobrado</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[With this award, the Chemistry of Life Processes Program in the Chemistry Division is funding Dr. Emily Balskus from Harvard University to investigate microbial enzymes that catalyze previously unappreciated chemical transformations. Uncovering novel biosynthetic enzymes and strategies expands our knowledge of Nature’s chemical capabilities.  It also motivates the development of new synthetic methods and strategies and is a first step toward employing enzymes in practical applications. This research is providing detailed understanding of previously unknown enzymes that could ultimately impact society by enabling more efficient and environmentally friendly routes for the synthesis of pharmaceuticals and industrial chemicals.  Additionally, the research generates knowledge of enzymes that could streamline the identification of previously uncharacterized and potentially bioactive microbial natural products.  Such products could have future applications in drug discovery and even agriculture. Finally, the goals of this research synergize with ongoing education and outreach activities aimed at educating and communicating the importance of the chemistry of living systems to a diverse group of students. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The specific focus of this project is to characterize newly discovered enzymes involved in the biosynthesis of the cylindrocyclophanes, a family of structurally unusual cyanobacterial metabolites. Previous studies of this pathway revealed a new type of halogenating enzyme capable of functionalizing unactivated carbon atoms as well as a previously unknown ‘cryptic’ halogenation strategy that involves an enzymatic Friedel–Crafts alkylation. The proposed research elucidates how these newly discovered alkyl halide-generating and -utilizing enzymes accomplish these challenging reactions and develop an experimental workflow that could rapidly uncover additional microbial natural products constructed using analogous biosynthetic logic. Altogether, this research has the potential to enhance our understanding of enzymatic catalysis and facilitate the discovery of additional, structurally unusual microbial metabolites.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/29/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/29/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2003436</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Emily</FirstName>
<LastName>Balskus</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Emily Balskus</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[balskus@chemistry.harvard.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000620416</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/29/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Harvard University</Name>
<CityName>CAMBRIDGE</CityName>
<ZipCode>021385366</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6174955501</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1033 MASSACHUSETTS AVE STE 3</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>LN53LCFJFL45</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PRESIDENT AND FELLOWS OF HARVARD COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Harvard University]]></Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021382902</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[12 Oxford Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6883</Code>
<Text>Chemistry of Life Processes</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>068Z</Code>
<Text>URoL-Understanding Rules of Life</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8038</Code>
<Text>Biotechnology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~435000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Halogenated compounds are abundant in the world of pharmaceuticals, with 40% of the 200 most purchased drugs containing a C&ndash;X bond. In addition, halogen-containing compounds, especially those containing an alkyl halide, are reactive towards a variety of nucleophiles and transition metals commonly found in realm of synthetic chemistry. Halogenation is also widespread in microbial natural product biosynthesis. Cryptic halogenation describes a biosynthetic strategy in which a halogenated metabolite is used as a reactive intermediate in natural product production, meaning that the halogen substituent is not found in the final natural product. We previously discovered an unusual cryptic halogenation strategy in the biosynthesis of the cylindrocyclophanes, structurally complex natural products from cyanobacteria, aquatic photosynthetic microbes. One major goal of this project was to study the structures and mechanisms of key enzymes involved in this cryptic halogenation. A second goal was to leverage understanding of this biosynthetic process to develop a workflow to identify and characterize new halogenated (or cryptically halogenated) natural products from microbes.</p> <p><strong>Intellectual Merit: </strong>Our work has enhanced our understanding of two new families of cyanobacterial enzymes involved in the biosynthesis of halogenated natural products. CylC, a halogenase found in the cylindrocyclophane biosynthesis pathway in <em>Cylindrospermum lichenforme </em>ATCC 29412, activates a secondary C&ndash;H bond to perform a stereoselective chlorination reaction. Interestingly, CylC is distinct from all known, characterized halogenases, and represents first member of a new subfamily of metalloenzymes. Initial bioinformatics suggested that CylC is a diiron enzyme, and halogenation would represent a new activity for this class of enzymes. Analysis of cyanobacterial genomes revealed the CylC family of putative diiron halogenases are widespread and used in many distinct biosynthetic pathways. This analysis led to the discovery of NocO, a CylC homolog from a <em>Nodularia </em>species that is more tractable for <em>in vitro</em> studies. Biochemical experiments with NocO are providing an understanding of the halogenase metal binding site. The second enzyme of interest from cylindrocyclophane biosynthesis is the novel alkylating enzyme CylK. &nbsp;CylK performs an unprecedented C&ndash;C bond formation reaction to dimerize two chlorinated alkyl resorcinols in the final step of this pathway. We solved a crystal structure of this enzyme and performed biochemical studies of enzyme mutants, providing information about how CylK binds and activates both the alkyl chloride and resorcinol substrates for C&ndash;C bond formation. Collectively, the biochemical and structural studies we have performed with NocO and CylK greatly enhance our fundamental understanding of enzyme chemistry and mechanism. &nbsp;&nbsp;Finally, these studies also informed the development of a new workflow for identifying natural products derived from halogenation. The &lsquo;halide depletion&rsquo; strategy involves comparing molecules produced by microbial cultures in the presence and absence of halide anion, Using this workflow, we discovered a new class of cyanobacterial natural products called the nostochlorosides that unexpectedly are made using a new type of halide utilizing enzymatic reaction. These results show that this platform can not only guide the discovery of new natural products but can also uncover new enzymatic chemistry.</p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts: </strong>The enzymes we have characterized perform reactions (halogenation, aromatic ring alkylation) that are relevant to the production of pharmaceuticals and other important industrial chemicals. Our work may therefore inform approaches to design more environmentally friendly routes to access such molecules. Our natural product discovery workflow has the potential to uncover metabolites with biological activity that may benefit society (pharmaceutical candidates and agrochemicals). Finally, production of natural products is often important for the biology of the organisms that produce them, and our discovery workflow may provide exciting starting places to investigate the roles of natural products for cyanobacteria on an organismal and community scale.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/31/2023<br>      Modified by: Emily&nbsp;Balskus</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Halogenated compounds are abundant in the world of pharmaceuticals, with 40% of the 200 most purchased drugs containing a C&ndash;X bond. In addition, halogen-containing compounds, especially those containing an alkyl halide, are reactive towards a variety of nucleophiles and transition metals commonly found in realm of synthetic chemistry. Halogenation is also widespread in microbial natural product biosynthesis. Cryptic halogenation describes a biosynthetic strategy in which a halogenated metabolite is used as a reactive intermediate in natural product production, meaning that the halogen substituent is not found in the final natural product. We previously discovered an unusual cryptic halogenation strategy in the biosynthesis of the cylindrocyclophanes, structurally complex natural products from cyanobacteria, aquatic photosynthetic microbes. One major goal of this project was to study the structures and mechanisms of key enzymes involved in this cryptic halogenation. A second goal was to leverage understanding of this biosynthetic process to develop a workflow to identify and characterize new halogenated (or cryptically halogenated) natural products from microbes.  Intellectual Merit: Our work has enhanced our understanding of two new families of cyanobacterial enzymes involved in the biosynthesis of halogenated natural products. CylC, a halogenase found in the cylindrocyclophane biosynthesis pathway in Cylindrospermum lichenforme ATCC 29412, activates a secondary C&ndash;H bond to perform a stereoselective chlorination reaction. Interestingly, CylC is distinct from all known, characterized halogenases, and represents first member of a new subfamily of metalloenzymes. Initial bioinformatics suggested that CylC is a diiron enzyme, and halogenation would represent a new activity for this class of enzymes. Analysis of cyanobacterial genomes revealed the CylC family of putative diiron halogenases are widespread and used in many distinct biosynthetic pathways. This analysis led to the discovery of NocO, a CylC homolog from a Nodularia species that is more tractable for in vitro studies. Biochemical experiments with NocO are providing an understanding of the halogenase metal binding site. The second enzyme of interest from cylindrocyclophane biosynthesis is the novel alkylating enzyme CylK.  CylK performs an unprecedented C&ndash;C bond formation reaction to dimerize two chlorinated alkyl resorcinols in the final step of this pathway. We solved a crystal structure of this enzyme and performed biochemical studies of enzyme mutants, providing information about how CylK binds and activates both the alkyl chloride and resorcinol substrates for C&ndash;C bond formation. Collectively, the biochemical and structural studies we have performed with NocO and CylK greatly enhance our fundamental understanding of enzyme chemistry and mechanism.   Finally, these studies also informed the development of a new workflow for identifying natural products derived from halogenation. The ‘halide depletion’ strategy involves comparing molecules produced by microbial cultures in the presence and absence of halide anion, Using this workflow, we discovered a new class of cyanobacterial natural products called the nostochlorosides that unexpectedly are made using a new type of halide utilizing enzymatic reaction. These results show that this platform can not only guide the discovery of new natural products but can also uncover new enzymatic chemistry.  Broader Impacts: The enzymes we have characterized perform reactions (halogenation, aromatic ring alkylation) that are relevant to the production of pharmaceuticals and other important industrial chemicals. Our work may therefore inform approaches to design more environmentally friendly routes to access such molecules. Our natural product discovery workflow has the potential to uncover metabolites with biological activity that may benefit society (pharmaceutical candidates and agrochemicals). Finally, production of natural products is often important for the biology of the organisms that produce them, and our discovery workflow may provide exciting starting places to investigate the roles of natural products for cyanobacteria on an organismal and community scale.       Last Modified: 08/31/2023       Submitted by: Emily Balskus]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
