<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBP: Major Disadvantages: Career Ambitions and Inequality by College Field of Study in Early Careers]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>138000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>138000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SMA</Abbreviation>
<LongName>SBE Off Of Multidisciplinary Activities</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Josie Welkom Miranda</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jwmirand@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927376</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This award is provided as part of NSF's Social, Behavioral and Economic Sciences Postdoctoral Research Fellowships (SPRF) program. The goal of the SPRF program is to prepare promising, early career doctoral-level scientists for scientific careers in academia, industry or private sector, and government. SPRF awards involve two years of training under the sponsorship of established scientists and encourage Postdoctoral Fellows to perform independent research. NSF seeks to promote the participation of scientists from all segments of the scientific community, including those from underrepresented groups, in its research programs and activities; the postdoctoral period is considered to be an important level of professional development in attaining this goal. Each Postdoctoral Fellow must address important scientific questions that advance their respective disciplinary fields. Under the sponsorship of Dr. Elizabeth A. Armstrong at the University of Michigan, this postdoctoral fellowship award supports an early career scientist investigating workplace gender inequality among recent college graduates. We know a good deal about mid-career gender inequality in the labor force, such as discrimination limiting women’s advancement opportunities and how burdens of work/family conflicts are borne unequally by women. Exposure to this inequality may cause women to change their professional plans early in their careers, however we know little about how early career experiences might contribute to this outcome. This research will identify when people’s workplace expectations begin to shift and if these are related to inequality experienced or observed at work, family expectations, or other considerations. Findings will lend insight into how women can be better positioned in the labor market, broadening their participation in high status jobs, and closing gender gaps that exists across the occupational hierarchy.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will investigate men and women’s early career experiences from college internships to their fourth year in the workforce in order to learn when and how individuals begin to change their career plans and how these decisions are informed by workers observing or experiencing relational inequality at work. Relational inequality is a concept capturing how cognitive biases, along with explicit and implicit discrimination, explain how women are treated differently than their male co-workers throughout their careers. Research will be accomplished by collecting a third wave of longitudinal interviews with college graduates from four majors, two that are male-dominated (Engineering/Business), and two that are female-dominated (Communications/English). Previously, 91 college seniors were interviewed about their internships and 85 of them were retained for a second interview one year later after graduation. Research will meet three objectives: (1) uncover the pathways through which individuals change their career plans early in their careers, (2) explain how these pathways are shaped by experiences, or observations, of relational gender inequality, (3) investigate how these two processes vary by gender and college field of study.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/30/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/30/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2004274</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Elizabeth</FirstName>
<LastName>Armstrong</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Elizabeth A Armstrong</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<NSF_ID>000569603</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/30/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Corey</FirstName>
<LastName>Moss-Pech</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Corey Moss-Pech</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<NSF_ID>000705776</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/30/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Pech, Corey</Name>
<CityName>Columbus</CityName>
<ZipCode>43210</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OH03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Michigan]]></Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>481091382</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>110y</Code>
<Text>SBP-Science of Broadening Part</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8208</Code>
<Text>SPRF-Broadening Participation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7137</Code>
<Text>POSTDOCTORAL FELLOWSHIPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8050</Code>
<Text>Science of Broadening Participation</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~138000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Corey Moss-Pech, under the mentorship of Elizabeth A. Armstrong, completed data collection and analysis for the project Major Disadvantages: Career Ambitions and Inequality by College Field of Study in Early Careers, with the support of an NSF Broadening Participation Postdoctoral Research Fellowship. This research is a qualitative study of how experiences, or observations, of inequality at work shape individuals? ambitions and career trajectories. The research pays particular attention to variation by gender and college field of study. This was the third wave of a longitudinal interview project, with respondents who are now roughly five years into their career after college graduation. The original sample had 91 respondents. Eighty-five respondents participated in the second wave (roughly four years ago). Seventy-nine participants sat for interviews during the fellowship period. NSF support was used to pay respondents, purchase books and other research supplies, fund conference travel, and other related research expenditures.</p> <p>Though data analysis is not yet completed, initial findings show that men and women do indeed have very different labor market experiences. Most women observe or experience relational gender inequality (e.g., a boss that treats male colleagues more attentively or the paucity of women in organizational leadership). Men, on the other hand, rarely notice these processes. Further, data show that women are more likely than men to change fields entirely or pursue graduate education that does not build off their undergraduate degree. This is partially due to relational inequality, but also women feel more empowered to follow their dreams and do interesting work, whereas men are less likely to abandon stable work even if they do not enjoy it. Finally, analysis reveals that as workers change jobs, even if they were initially in a gender atypical field, they tend to switch into a <em>more </em>gender typical field. This shows that occupational segregation processes continue to play out after college ends.</p> <p>This project has generated intellectual merit by examining early career experiences, which is understudied despite the great deal of attention that researchers pay to gender inequality at work and the under-representation of women in Business and STEM. We know little about how people make sense of their early career experiences and how that impacts their future plans. Interviews fully linked respondents internships, field of study, and early career experiences. Doing so in early careers, a vital time period as gaps in wages and status emerge in workers mid-20s, allowed the researchers to identify four pathways through which people link their early employment experiences with their professional ambitions: (1) men and women experience meritocracy at work and stay on their initial career track, (2) perceived and observed relationship inequality cause people to change employment plans, (3) perceived and observed relational inequality cause people to lean in to their current career track, (4) people change employment tracks for reasons unrelated to inequality and meritocracy. The pathways vary in how mutually exclusive they are, but they are analytically distinct and findings will make significant contributions to research on gender inequality in school and work by showing the factors that help contribute to which pathway individuals take through their early careers.</p> <p>This research also has broader impacts for society. Findings have been shared informally with undergraduate and graduate students, experts in gender inequality at work, and stakeholders in the community. Once research products are drafted, they will be shared at academic conferences, in peer-reviewed journals, and in venues that appeal to non-academic audiences such as blogs and other media. Research output will lend insight into how women can be better positioned in the labor market, broadening their participation in high status STEM and Business jobs, and closing gender gaps that exist among Humanities and Social Science graduates. Finally, this research will serve as the basis of Dr. Moss-Pech?s second book, which will hopefully appeal to a wide audience interested in gender inequality at school and work.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/17/2022<br>      Modified by: Corey&nbsp;Moss-Pech</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Corey Moss-Pech, under the mentorship of Elizabeth A. Armstrong, completed data collection and analysis for the project Major Disadvantages: Career Ambitions and Inequality by College Field of Study in Early Careers, with the support of an NSF Broadening Participation Postdoctoral Research Fellowship. This research is a qualitative study of how experiences, or observations, of inequality at work shape individuals? ambitions and career trajectories. The research pays particular attention to variation by gender and college field of study. This was the third wave of a longitudinal interview project, with respondents who are now roughly five years into their career after college graduation. The original sample had 91 respondents. Eighty-five respondents participated in the second wave (roughly four years ago). Seventy-nine participants sat for interviews during the fellowship period. NSF support was used to pay respondents, purchase books and other research supplies, fund conference travel, and other related research expenditures.  Though data analysis is not yet completed, initial findings show that men and women do indeed have very different labor market experiences. Most women observe or experience relational gender inequality (e.g., a boss that treats male colleagues more attentively or the paucity of women in organizational leadership). Men, on the other hand, rarely notice these processes. Further, data show that women are more likely than men to change fields entirely or pursue graduate education that does not build off their undergraduate degree. This is partially due to relational inequality, but also women feel more empowered to follow their dreams and do interesting work, whereas men are less likely to abandon stable work even if they do not enjoy it. Finally, analysis reveals that as workers change jobs, even if they were initially in a gender atypical field, they tend to switch into a more gender typical field. This shows that occupational segregation processes continue to play out after college ends.  This project has generated intellectual merit by examining early career experiences, which is understudied despite the great deal of attention that researchers pay to gender inequality at work and the under-representation of women in Business and STEM. We know little about how people make sense of their early career experiences and how that impacts their future plans. Interviews fully linked respondents internships, field of study, and early career experiences. Doing so in early careers, a vital time period as gaps in wages and status emerge in workers mid-20s, allowed the researchers to identify four pathways through which people link their early employment experiences with their professional ambitions: (1) men and women experience meritocracy at work and stay on their initial career track, (2) perceived and observed relationship inequality cause people to change employment plans, (3) perceived and observed relational inequality cause people to lean in to their current career track, (4) people change employment tracks for reasons unrelated to inequality and meritocracy. The pathways vary in how mutually exclusive they are, but they are analytically distinct and findings will make significant contributions to research on gender inequality in school and work by showing the factors that help contribute to which pathway individuals take through their early careers.  This research also has broader impacts for society. Findings have been shared informally with undergraduate and graduate students, experts in gender inequality at work, and stakeholders in the community. Once research products are drafted, they will be shared at academic conferences, in peer-reviewed journals, and in venues that appeal to non-academic audiences such as blogs and other media. Research output will lend insight into how women can be better positioned in the labor market, broadening their participation in high status STEM and Business jobs, and closing gender gaps that exist among Humanities and Social Science graduates. Finally, this research will serve as the basis of Dr. Moss-Pech?s second book, which will hopefully appeal to a wide audience interested in gender inequality at school and work.           Last Modified: 08/17/2022       Submitted by: Corey Moss-Pech]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
