<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research: Permanent forearc strain partitioning in Northern Cascadia]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>251449.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>251449</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Stephen Harlan</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sharlan@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927707</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This work provides the first detailed characterization of the behavior of past earthquakes that have occurred on active, on-land, shallow faults in southern British Columbia, Canada. The research has important societal benefits that include providing key inputs needed for seismic hazard assessment in populated areas of Vancouver Island, British Columbia and northwestern Washington, USA. These types of data are necessary to help inform the development of public policy that can reduce the loss of life and property due to future earthquakes. Other important societal outcomes include contributions to STEM (science, technology, engineering and mathematics) education and the development of a diverse globally competitive STEM workforce by providing support for the training  of graduate and undergraduate students. The project also supports the research of two female, early career scientists, and facilitates international collaborations between industry partners, policy makers, scientists and students. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is evaluating the role of slab geometry and oblique convergence in the generation of forearc deformation in northern Cascadia by determining fault kinematics and the Holocene slip history of three prominent faults on Vancouver Island, British Columbia, Canada. Using a combination of bedrock mapping and structural analysis, surficial mapping of offset Quaternary deposits, and exploratory paleoseismic trenches, the research is testing the hypothesis that newly identified active crustal faults contribute to active oroclinal bending in response to the component of relative plate motion parallel to the strike of the slab. This work provides the first documentation of Quaternary activity on a set of faults previously thought to be last active in the Eocene, and provides fundamental kinematic and slip history data necessary to test models of plate boundary strain partitioning.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/20/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/20/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2004684</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Christine</FirstName>
<LastName>Regalla</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Christine A Regalla</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[christineregalla@gmail.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000648909</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/20/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Northern Arizona University</Name>
<CityName>FLAGSTAFF</CityName>
<ZipCode>86011</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9285230886</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>601 S KNOLES DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[ROOM 220]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AZ02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>MXHAS3AKPRN1</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORTHERN ARIZONA UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Northern Arizona University]]></Name>
<CityName>Flagstaff</CityName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>860110001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AZ02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1572</Code>
<Text>Tectonics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01001819DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~251449</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Overview</strong></p> <p>This collaborative project defined the kinematics and slip histories of Quaternary active faults on Vancouver Island, in the subduction zone forearc of Cascadia of southwestern British Columbia. The information gleaned from this study contributes to understanding of how plate boundary deformation is partitioned in the upper plate, and how crustal faults contribute to seismic hazard in heavy populated coastal areas.</p> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p><strong>Intellectual Merit</strong></p> <p>This project has identified two previously unrecognized active faults on Vancouver Island, southwestern British Columbia (Cascadia subduction zone) using a combination of field mapping, lidar elevation data analysis, fault excavations, geochronological dating, and fault slip modelling.&nbsp; We determined the slip styles of three faults, and constrained the number and timing of past earthquakes on three faults. Specifically, we found that the Leech River fault has right lateral conpressional kinematics and hosted up to three M6-7 earthquakes since15 ka; the XEOLXELEK-Elk Lake fault is a compressional fault that has hosted one M6-7 earthquake since 15 ka; and the Beaufort Range fault is a right lateral transtensional fault that hosted five M6-7 earthquakes since 15 ka. Modelling of failure along these and additional crustal faults in several imposed stress fields demonstrates that plate boundary tractions, forces originating at the subduction zone plate boundary, are unlikely to drive observed deformation. Instead background stresses from upper plate bending or other motions are most likely driving deformation.&nbsp; These field, kinematic, paleosiemic, and modelling results are the first contributions documenting how slip is partitioned along upper plate faults in the northernmost Cascadia subduction zone in southern British Columbia, Canada.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts</strong></p> <p>Results from this project have quantified paleo earthquake magnitude, timing, recurrence, and slip style along three fults. These are primary data used as inputs into seismic hazard models. These data have been communicated to the National Seismic Risk Profile for Canada, the Pacific Geoscience Center, the GEMS earthquake hazard model, BC Hydroelectric, Capitol Regions Watershed management, and the University of Victoria for use in seismic hazard and risk assessments. This project provided training opportunities for two PhD students whose research focused on these data, and has provided research and training opportunities for seven additional undergraduate and graduate students who gained field and research experience. Outcomes of this project have been shared in dozens of departmental seminars and conference presentations, two dissertations, and five manuscripts that are published or in review.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/28/2023<br>      Modified by: Christine&nbsp;A&nbsp;Regalla</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Overview  This collaborative project defined the kinematics and slip histories of Quaternary active faults on Vancouver Island, in the subduction zone forearc of Cascadia of southwestern British Columbia. The information gleaned from this study contributes to understanding of how plate boundary deformation is partitioned in the upper plate, and how crustal faults contribute to seismic hazard in heavy populated coastal areas.     Intellectual Merit  This project has identified two previously unrecognized active faults on Vancouver Island, southwestern British Columbia (Cascadia subduction zone) using a combination of field mapping, lidar elevation data analysis, fault excavations, geochronological dating, and fault slip modelling.  We determined the slip styles of three faults, and constrained the number and timing of past earthquakes on three faults. Specifically, we found that the Leech River fault has right lateral conpressional kinematics and hosted up to three M6-7 earthquakes since15 ka; the XEOLXELEK-Elk Lake fault is a compressional fault that has hosted one M6-7 earthquake since 15 ka; and the Beaufort Range fault is a right lateral transtensional fault that hosted five M6-7 earthquakes since 15 ka. Modelling of failure along these and additional crustal faults in several imposed stress fields demonstrates that plate boundary tractions, forces originating at the subduction zone plate boundary, are unlikely to drive observed deformation. Instead background stresses from upper plate bending or other motions are most likely driving deformation.  These field, kinematic, paleosiemic, and modelling results are the first contributions documenting how slip is partitioned along upper plate faults in the northernmost Cascadia subduction zone in southern British Columbia, Canada.     Broader Impacts  Results from this project have quantified paleo earthquake magnitude, timing, recurrence, and slip style along three fults. These are primary data used as inputs into seismic hazard models. These data have been communicated to the National Seismic Risk Profile for Canada, the Pacific Geoscience Center, the GEMS earthquake hazard model, BC Hydroelectric, Capitol Regions Watershed management, and the University of Victoria for use in seismic hazard and risk assessments. This project provided training opportunities for two PhD students whose research focused on these data, and has provided research and training opportunities for seven additional undergraduate and graduate students who gained field and research experience. Outcomes of this project have been shared in dozens of departmental seminars and conference presentations, two dissertations, and five manuscripts that are published or in review.          Last Modified: 07/28/2023       Submitted by: Christine A Regalla]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
