<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Neural and behavioral coordination in infant-caregiver communication across the socioeconomic spectrum]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>138000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>69000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SMA</Abbreviation>
<LongName>SBE Off Of Multidisciplinary Activities</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Josie Welkom Miranda</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jwmirand@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927376</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This award was provided as part of NSF's Social, Behavioral and Economic Sciences Postdoctoral Research Fellowships (SPRF) program. The goal of the SPRF program is to prepare promising, early career doctoral-level scientists for scientific careers in academia, industry or private sector, and government. SPRF awards involve two years of training under the sponsorship of established scientists and encourage Postdoctoral Fellows to perform independent research. NSF seeks to promote the participation of scientists from all segments of the scientific community, including those from underrepresented groups, in its research programs and activities; the postdoctoral period is considered to be an important level of professional development in attaining this goal. Each Postdoctoral Fellow must address important scientific questions that advance their respective disciplinary fields. Under the sponsorship of Dr. Casey Lew-Williams at Princeton University, this postdoctoral fellowship award supports an early career scientist investigating the neural mechanisms by which variation in the quality of infants early learning environment, across the full spectrum of socioeconomic status (SES), impacts infants’ language learning. Much of infants’ learning occurs through social interactions with others, and the quality of these early social interactions is consequential for linguistic and cognitive development. In particular, there is substantial variation in input quality across the SES spectrum, often putting infants from lower-SES families at risk for learning challenges. However, current investigations of how input impacts learning have had a dominant focus on language, undercutting current understanding of the full complexity of infants’ everyday communicative environments. Further, minimal research has studied the neural mechanisms through which input quality influences learning. This project will address both of these limitations, exploring relations between variation in input quality across the full SES spectrum, neural activity during caregiver-infant interactions, and language outcomes six months later.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project takes a novel approach to studying how infants learn in social interactions with caregivers. Objective 1 focuses on examining variation in “infant-directed communication” (IDC) across the SES spectrum. IDC includes a broad suite of interconnected signals that contribute to infants’ everyday learning environment: language, action, gesture, emotion, and touch. Objective 2 uses dual-brain functional near-infrared spectroscopy (fNIRS) to investigate relations between quality of IDC and the extent to which neural activity in caregivers’ and infants’ brains are correlated during communicative interactions. Finally, Objective 3 asks how IDC and neural coupling independently and jointly predict infants’ vocabulary growth. Together, these objectives will provide new insight into the mechanisms by which infants across the SES spectrum learn in interactions with their caregivers, with the ultimate goal of generating new ideas for interventions that aim to enhance learning.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/30/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/22/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2004983</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jessica</FirstName>
<LastName>Kosie</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jessica E Kosie</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<NSF_ID>000792863</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/30/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Casey</FirstName>
<LastName>Lew-Williams</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Casey Lew-Williams</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<NSF_ID>000760138</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/30/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Kosie, Jessica Elizabeth</Name>
<CityName>Princeton</CityName>
<ZipCode>085441111</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NJ12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Princeton University]]></Name>
<CityName>Princeton</CityName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>085441111</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NJ12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8208</Code>
<Text>SPRF-Broadening Participation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7137</Code>
<Text>POSTDOCTORAL FELLOWSHIPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~69000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>Much of infants&rsquo; learning occurs through social interactions with others, and the quality of these early social interactions is consequential for linguistic and cognitive development. However, current investigations into how input quality impacts learning have had a dominant focus on language, which underestimates the full complexity of infants&rsquo; everyday communicative environment. Further, little research has studied the mechanisms through which the quality of infants&rsquo; everyday input influences learning. The goal of the proposed research was to address both of these limitations, exploring relations between input quality (broadly defined) and neural activity during caregiver-infant interactions. While constraints imposed by the COVID-19 pandemic limited my ability to accomplish these goals, I was able to explore the full suite of interconnected communicative signals that caregivers use during interactions with their infants and how these signals relate to language learning. &nbsp;&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span>I investigated the dynamics of caregiver-infant interactions via an online study. Caregivers and infants were invited to a Zoom call. Before the session, caregivers were asked to complete a questionnaire about the words their infant knew, find a quiet place in their home to play, and gather a few toys to play with. During the session, caregivers and infants were asked to play as they naturally would for 10 minutes.</span></p> <p><span>The videos were coded for five dimensions of infant-directed communication: speech, action, gesture, emotion, and touch. These dimensions were chosen because previous research has demonstrated that caregivers modify each of these dimensions with infants and that these modifications relate to infants&rsquo; attention and learning. For example, caregivers use more repetitive, exaggerated actions with infants than adults, and infants attend longer to infant- over adult-directed action demonstrations. However, speech, action, gesture, emotion, and touch had all previously been studied in isolation, no research had examined the dynamics with which the full suite of behaviors occurs together during naturalistic caregiver-infant interactions.</span></p> <p><span>I found that, while caregivers used infant-directed speech frequently (as expected from previous research with similar populations), infant-directed action, gesture, emotion, and touch were also frequently used. Additionally, there was substantial variation across caregivers in their use of each dimension of infant-directed communication (we refer to this as IDC: the suite of interconnected signals &ndash; speech, action, gesture, emotion, and touch &ndash; that caregivers use in interactions with infants). Importantly, the dimensions of IDC rarely occur in isolation &ndash; more than half of the speech directed to infants is accompanied by at least one other communicative signal. I also found that caregivers&rsquo; use of IDC was negatively correlated with infants&rsquo; scores on the vocabulary assessment. This negative relationship appeared to primarily be driven by caregivers&rsquo; use of emotion, and suggests that caregivers use more infant-directed emotion with infants who know fewer words.</span></p> <p><span>The results of present study underscore the fact that focusing on infant-directed speech alone &ndash; as is common in studies of early language development &ndash; is likely to cause researchers to miss important communicative features of caregiver-infant interactions. Other dimensions of IDC occur frequently, together with infant-directed speech, and may be modulated with infants&rsquo; language skill.</span></p> <p><span>Through this fellowship, I was able to broaden the participation&nbsp;of underrepresented groups in psychological science in various ways. For example, I mentored ten undergraduate research assistants - a number of which were first-generation college students, members of racial and ethnic minority groups, and students from low SES backgrounds. These students gained experience with study design, recruiting and running participants, behavioral coding, analyzing and visualizing data, and writing and presenting results. One student in particular was mentored through Princeton&rsquo;s ReMatch+ program, which seeks to connect students from underrepresented backgrounds with research mentors. The ReMatch+ program additionally provided me with training in mentorship, with a particular focus on diversity and inclusion. I also contributed a summary of my findings to a lab newsletter that is sent annually to all families who have participated in the lab&rsquo;s research. Many of these families are also members of diverse and underrepresented groups. &nbsp;&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span>In sum, the novel approach I took to studying early social interactions with caregivers has allowed me to extend beyond an existing dominant focus on language to describe caregiver-infant interactions in a comprehensive and ecologically valid manner. The results of the current study set the stage for further exploration of how the dynamics of caregiver-infant interactions relate to neural measures of coordination between caregivers&rsquo; and infants&rsquo; brains as they interact. Altogether, this work will provide unique insight into the mechanisms that promote language learning. The experience I gained in working with and mentoring individuals from underrepresented groups was invaluable, and left me well-prepared to continue making diversity and inclusion a priority throughout my career. &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</span><span>&nbsp;</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/31/2021<br>      Modified by: Jessica&nbsp;E&nbsp;Kosie</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Much of infants’ learning occurs through social interactions with others, and the quality of these early social interactions is consequential for linguistic and cognitive development. However, current investigations into how input quality impacts learning have had a dominant focus on language, which underestimates the full complexity of infants’ everyday communicative environment. Further, little research has studied the mechanisms through which the quality of infants’ everyday input influences learning. The goal of the proposed research was to address both of these limitations, exploring relations between input quality (broadly defined) and neural activity during caregiver-infant interactions. While constraints imposed by the COVID-19 pandemic limited my ability to accomplish these goals, I was able to explore the full suite of interconnected communicative signals that caregivers use during interactions with their infants and how these signals relate to language learning.     I investigated the dynamics of caregiver-infant interactions via an online study. Caregivers and infants were invited to a Zoom call. Before the session, caregivers were asked to complete a questionnaire about the words their infant knew, find a quiet place in their home to play, and gather a few toys to play with. During the session, caregivers and infants were asked to play as they naturally would for 10 minutes.  The videos were coded for five dimensions of infant-directed communication: speech, action, gesture, emotion, and touch. These dimensions were chosen because previous research has demonstrated that caregivers modify each of these dimensions with infants and that these modifications relate to infants’ attention and learning. For example, caregivers use more repetitive, exaggerated actions with infants than adults, and infants attend longer to infant- over adult-directed action demonstrations. However, speech, action, gesture, emotion, and touch had all previously been studied in isolation, no research had examined the dynamics with which the full suite of behaviors occurs together during naturalistic caregiver-infant interactions.  I found that, while caregivers used infant-directed speech frequently (as expected from previous research with similar populations), infant-directed action, gesture, emotion, and touch were also frequently used. Additionally, there was substantial variation across caregivers in their use of each dimension of infant-directed communication (we refer to this as IDC: the suite of interconnected signals &ndash; speech, action, gesture, emotion, and touch &ndash; that caregivers use in interactions with infants). Importantly, the dimensions of IDC rarely occur in isolation &ndash; more than half of the speech directed to infants is accompanied by at least one other communicative signal. I also found that caregivers’ use of IDC was negatively correlated with infants’ scores on the vocabulary assessment. This negative relationship appeared to primarily be driven by caregivers’ use of emotion, and suggests that caregivers use more infant-directed emotion with infants who know fewer words.  The results of present study underscore the fact that focusing on infant-directed speech alone &ndash; as is common in studies of early language development &ndash; is likely to cause researchers to miss important communicative features of caregiver-infant interactions. Other dimensions of IDC occur frequently, together with infant-directed speech, and may be modulated with infants’ language skill.  Through this fellowship, I was able to broaden the participation of underrepresented groups in psychological science in various ways. For example, I mentored ten undergraduate research assistants - a number of which were first-generation college students, members of racial and ethnic minority groups, and students from low SES backgrounds. These students gained experience with study design, recruiting and running participants, behavioral coding, analyzing and visualizing data, and writing and presenting results. One student in particular was mentored through Princeton’s ReMatch+ program, which seeks to connect students from underrepresented backgrounds with research mentors. The ReMatch+ program additionally provided me with training in mentorship, with a particular focus on diversity and inclusion. I also contributed a summary of my findings to a lab newsletter that is sent annually to all families who have participated in the lab’s research. Many of these families are also members of diverse and underrepresented groups.     In sum, the novel approach I took to studying early social interactions with caregivers has allowed me to extend beyond an existing dominant focus on language to describe caregiver-infant interactions in a comprehensive and ecologically valid manner. The results of the current study set the stage for further exploration of how the dynamics of caregiver-infant interactions relate to neural measures of coordination between caregivers’ and infants’ brains as they interact. Altogether, this work will provide unique insight into the mechanisms that promote language learning. The experience I gained in working with and mentoring individuals from underrepresented groups was invaluable, and left me well-prepared to continue making diversity and inclusion a priority throughout my career.                 Last Modified: 10/31/2021       Submitted by: Jessica E Kosie]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
