<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Algebraic Statistics 2020]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>34200.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>34200</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Andrew Pollington</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>adpollin@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924878</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Algebraic Statistics 2020 (AS2020) will be held June 22--June 26, 2020 at the University of Hawaii at Manoa in Honlulu, HI.  The five-day conference at the University of Hawaii at Manoa aims to achieve four objectives: 1) provide a forum for algebraists, mathematical biologists, and statisticians to learn about recent advances in the field and share their current challenges; 2) broaden participation in algebraic statistics in terms of gender, race, ethnicity, institution type, geography, and scientific discipline; 3) train junior researchers in this interdisciplinary area, which requires exposure to both algebra and statistics; and 4) foster collaboration with international researchers, specifically those from Japan, who have been making fundamental progress in the field in the last two decades. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Algebraic statistics is an interdisciplinary field that uses tools from commutative algebra, geometry, and combinatorics to address problems in mathematical statistics.  The main applications in the last decade have focused on data science, biology, and engineering. Algebraic Statistics 2020 will feature nine keynote speakers, from the US and abroad, three problem sessions led by established researchers in the field to engage junior researchers and those interested in learning more about algebraic statistics, contributed talks, and a poster session.  The conference website is http://bit.ly/AlgebraicStatistics2020.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/10/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/10/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2004271</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Elizabeth</FirstName>
<LastName>Gross</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Elizabeth A Gross</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[egross@hawaii.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000628864</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sonja</FirstName>
<LastName>Petrovic</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sonja Petrovic</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[spetrov1@iit.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000650034</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Vishesh</FirstName>
<LastName>Karwa</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Vishesh Karwa</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[vishesh.karwa@temple.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000761864</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Hawaii</Name>
<CityName>HONOLULU</CityName>
<ZipCode>968222247</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8089567800</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2425 CAMPUS RD SINCLAIR RM 1</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Hawaii</StateName>
<StateCode>HI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>HI01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NSCKLFSSABF2</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF HAWAII</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Hawaii]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>HI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>968222234</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Hawaii</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>HI01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1264</Code>
<Text>ALGEBRA,NUMBER THEORY,AND COM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1269</Code>
<Text>STATISTICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7334</Code>
<Text>MATHEMATICAL BIOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~34200</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><div id="MathJax_Message" style="display: none;"></div> <p>The conference, Algebraic Statistics 2022, was held at the University of Hawaii at Manoa in Honolulu, HI from May 16, 2022 to May 20, 2022. The conference had 10 keynote talks, 21 shorter 20-minute contributed talks, and 8 posters. These talks introduced the audience to new work in algebraic statistics, ranging from algebraic methods for graphical models, sparse polynomial system solving, establishing parameter identifiability for models from evolutionary biology, geometry of polynomial optimization, and geometric principles of machine learning and statistical inference.</p> <p>The conference had 53 registered participants from 8 countries with the following fields represented (field determined by department of academic appointment): Mathematics, Statistics, Applied and Computational Math, Computer Science, Engineering, Operations Research, and Computational Biolgoy.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>In addition to the conference, we held two complementary activities: a graduate education luncheon to discuss and share best practices in mathematics graduate education and a week-long workshop on Algebra of Phylogenetic Networks aimed at junior researchers.</p> <p>For this conference, titles and abstracts have been posted on the&nbsp;&nbsp;<span class=" aw5Odc"><a class="XqQF9c" href="http://www.google.com/url?q=http%3A%2F%2Falgebraicstatistics.org%2Fas2022&amp;sa=D&amp;sntz=1&amp;usg=AOvVaw3WJKYuiBD61tk3zbKyRqoi" target="_blank">AS2022 conference</a>&nbsp;website:&nbsp;</span>https://algebraicstatistics.org/as2022</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p class="CDt4Ke zfr3Q" dir="ltr"><span>The organizers of the conference&nbsp;</span><span>invited submissions to the special issue of Algebraic Statistics on the occasion of the</span> <span>conference.</span></p> <p class="CDt4Ke zfr3Q" dir="ltr"><span>Journal Editors: Thomas Kahle and Sonja Petrovi&#263;<br />Special issue co-editor: Elizabeth Gross</span></p> <p>To date, there have been more than a dozen submissions that are currently under review. We expect at least one issue, possiblye a volume of two issues, to be published in 2023 containing these papers.&nbsp;</p> <p class="CDt4Ke zfr3Q" dir="ltr"><span class=" aw5Odc"><a class="XqQF9c" href="https://www.google.com/url?q=https%3A%2F%2Fmsp.org%2Fastat&amp;sa=D&amp;sntz=1&amp;usg=AOvVaw0Rfq3rRdmL4pLOYCPNSoNz" target="_blank">Algebraic Statistics</a></span><span>, published by the non-profit publisher </span><span class=" aw5Odc"><a class="XqQF9c" href="https://www.google.com/url?q=https%3A%2F%2Fmsp.org%2F&amp;sa=D&amp;sntz=1&amp;usg=AOvVaw1R6at-qxjtafugYBSL8x0C" target="_blank">MSP</a></span><span> (Mathematical Sciences Publishers), is an international journal devoted to algebraic aspects of statistical theory, methodology and applications. AStat seeks to publish a wide range of research and review papers that address one of the following:</span></p> <ul class="n8H08c UVNKR"> <li class="TYR86d zfr3Q" dir="ltr"> <p class="CDt4Ke zfr3Q" dir="ltr"><span>algebraic, geometric and combinatorial insights into statistical models or the behaviour of statistical procedures;</span></p> </li> <li class="TYR86d zfr3Q" dir="ltr"> <p class="CDt4Ke zfr3Q" dir="ltr"><span>development of new statistical models and methods with interesting algebraic or geometric properties;</span></p> </li> <li class="TYR86d zfr3Q" dir="ltr"> <p class="CDt4Ke zfr3Q" dir="ltr"><span>novel applications of algebraic and geometric methods in statistics.</span></p> </li> </ul> <script src="https://cdnjs.cloudflare.com/ajax/libs/mathjax/2.7.0/MathJax.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML&amp;delayStartupUntil=configured" type="text/javascript"></script> <script id="texAllTheThingsPageScript" src="chrome-extension:/cbimabofgmfdkicghcadidpemeenbffn/js/pageScript.js" type="text/javascript"></script> <script src="https://cdnjs.cloudflare.com/ajax/libs/mathjax/2.7.0/MathJax.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML&amp;delayStartupUntil=configured" type="text/javascript"></script> <script id="texAllTheThingsPageScript" src="chrome-extension:/cbimabofgmfdkicghcadidpemeenbffn/js/pageScript.js" type="text/javascript"></script> <script src="https://cdnjs.cloudflare.com/ajax/libs/mathjax/2.7.0/MathJax.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML&amp;delayStartupUntil=configured" type="text/javascript"></script> <script id="texAllTheThingsPageScript" src="chrome-extension:/cbimabofgmfdkicghcadidpemeenbffn/js/pageScript.js" type="text/javascript"></script> <script src="https://cdnjs.cloudflare.com/ajax/libs/mathjax/2.7.0/MathJax.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML&amp;delayStartupUntil=configured" type="text/javascript"></script> <script id="texAllTheThingsPageScript" src="chrome-extension://cbimabofgmfdkicghcadidpemeenbffn/js/pageScript.js" type="text/javascript"></script><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/02/2023<br>      Modified by: Sonja&nbsp;Petrovic</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  The conference, Algebraic Statistics 2022, was held at the University of Hawaii at Manoa in Honolulu, HI from May 16, 2022 to May 20, 2022. The conference had 10 keynote talks, 21 shorter 20-minute contributed talks, and 8 posters. These talks introduced the audience to new work in algebraic statistics, ranging from algebraic methods for graphical models, sparse polynomial system solving, establishing parameter identifiability for models from evolutionary biology, geometry of polynomial optimization, and geometric principles of machine learning and statistical inference.  The conference had 53 registered participants from 8 countries with the following fields represented (field determined by department of academic appointment): Mathematics, Statistics, Applied and Computational Math, Computer Science, Engineering, Operations Research, and Computational Biolgoy.    In addition to the conference, we held two complementary activities: a graduate education luncheon to discuss and share best practices in mathematics graduate education and a week-long workshop on Algebra of Phylogenetic Networks aimed at junior researchers.  For this conference, titles and abstracts have been posted on the  AS2022 conference website: https://algebraicstatistics.org/as2022    The organizers of the conference invited submissions to the special issue of Algebraic Statistics on the occasion of the conference. Journal Editors: Thomas Kahle and Sonja Petrovi&#263; Special issue co-editor: Elizabeth Gross  To date, there have been more than a dozen submissions that are currently under review. We expect at least one issue, possiblye a volume of two issues, to be published in 2023 containing these papers.  Algebraic Statistics, published by the non-profit publisher MSP (Mathematical Sciences Publishers), is an international journal devoted to algebraic aspects of statistical theory, methodology and applications. AStat seeks to publish a wide range of research and review papers that address one of the following:   algebraic, geometric and combinatorial insights into statistical models or the behaviour of statistical procedures;   development of new statistical models and methods with interesting algebraic or geometric properties;   novel applications of algebraic and geometric methods in statistics.                 Last Modified: 03/02/2023       Submitted by: Sonja Petrovic]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
