<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Adolescent neurodevelopment of memory-guided decision making]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>138000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>138000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SMA</Abbreviation>
<LongName>SBE Off Of Multidisciplinary Activities</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Josie Welkom Miranda</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jwmirand@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927376</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This award was provided as part of NSF's Social, Behavioral and Economic Sciences Postdoctoral Research Fellowships (SPRF) program. The goal of the SPRF program is to prepare promising, early career doctoral-level scientists for scientific careers in academia, industry or private sector, and government. SPRF awards involve two years of training under the sponsorship of established scientists and encourage Postdoctoral Fellows to perform independent research. NSF seeks to promote the participation of scientists from all segments of the scientific community, including those from underrepresented groups, in its research programs and activities; the postdoctoral period is considered to be an important level of professional development in attaining this goal. Each Postdoctoral Fellow must address important scientific questions that advance their respective disciplinary fields. Under the sponsorship of Dr. Daphna Shohamy at Columbia University, this postdoctoral fellowship award supports an early career scientist investigating how adolescent brain development shapes memory and decision-making. This project will examine how adolescents access memories to make adaptive decisions, and how the development of key brain regions that guide learning and memory supports this ability. This research has direct implications for education policy and practice. Specifically, if adolescents exhibit age-related differences in memory-guided decision making due to ongoing brain development, this could have direct consequences for how individuals learn in and out of the classroom. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Adolescence is a period of the lifespan when ongoing brain development supports continuous gains in cognitive abilities, and adolescents must learn how to navigate the world with increasing independence. Prior work has shown that memory and decision-making systems continue to mature during adolescence, however, developmental studies have traditionally tested these cognitive processes in isolation. As a result, remarkably little is known about how the development of memory and the corresponding neural processes influence the emergence of adaptive decision-making during adolescence. Specifically, it remains unclear whether the maturation of memory and learning systems in the brain give rise to effective memory-guided decision-making. This research project aims to address this gap by leveraging recent advances from computational neuroscience that have identified how adults use memory to navigate decision-making. By combining this approach with tools from developmental cognitive neuroscience, this research investigates how these memory-guided decision processes emerge with age during adolescence. Across two experiments, this project integrates behavioral indices of learning and memory, computational modeling, and functional neuroimaging (fMRI) to investigate the neurodevelopmental mechanisms of memory-guided decision-making. The first experiment tests the hypothesis that functional development of the hippocampus during adolescence shapes the ability to learn from a single experience. The second experiment tests the hypothesis that developing functional connectivity between the hippocampus and prefrontal cortex supports the ability to integrate and generalize across multiple memories to guide adaptive decision-making. The current research aims to identify when and how memory guides adolescent decision-making. By examining the computational foundations and neurodevelopmental trajectories of memory-guided decision-making, the proposed research has the potential to reveal how learning and decision-making processes refine with age during adolescence.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/27/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/27/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2004148</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Catherine</FirstName>
<LastName>Insel</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Catherine Insel</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<NSF_ID>000812875</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/27/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daphna</FirstName>
<LastName>Shohamy</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Daphna Shohamy</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<NSF_ID>000537709</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/27/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Insel, Catherine</Name>
<CityName>New York</CityName>
<ZipCode>10027</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Columbia University]]></Name>
<CityName>New York</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>100272327</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>040Y</Code>
<Text>(SPRF-FR) SBE Postdoctoral Res</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7137</Code>
<Text>POSTDOCTORAL FELLOWSHIPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~138000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Catherine Insel completed research for the NSF SBE SPRF postdoctoral award. Her research aimed to identify how adolescents use memories to help make decisions, and to understand how and why adolescents make different types of decisions than adults do. During the funding period, she collected multiple datasets in human subjects and developmental populations. She also collected fMRI data in adolescents and young adults to examine how brain development from childhood to early adulthood shapes learning, memory, and value-based decision making. Her research reveals exciting new insights about how and why adolescents make different decisions than adults. She found that adolescents are more likely to learn from single experiences, which is an adaptive strategy that helps them update their behavior quickly and flexibly in new situations. Additional findings suggest that as adolescents get older, they are more likely to average over many related experiences when making a decision, a process referred to as generalization. Ongoing work with fMRI is identifying the neurobiological mechanisms that support these developmental changes in decision-making across adolescence. This work will reveal how ongoing brain development shapes daily behaviors in youth, which has important implications for understanding how adolescents learn, both in and out of the classroom.</p> <p>Intellectual Merit:</p> <p>This work has advanced our understanding of how and why adolescents make different decisions than adults do. Catherine Insel's work has revealed novel insights into how memories are crucial for making decisions. This work demonstrates that compared to adults, adolescents use different types of memories to help guide their choices. These findings have formed the basis of a new conceptual framework that provides an important revision on contemporary theories of adolescent decision-making.</p> <p>Broader Impacts:</p> <div class="page" title="Page 5"> <div class="section"> <div class="layoutArea"> <div class="column"> <p><span>Understanding adolescent brain development is key to advancing juvenile justice policy and practice. Dr. Insel worked with the Center for Law Brain and Behavior at Massachusetts General Hospital to write a white paper for lawyers, judges, and policy makers with critical updates on adolescent brain science. The goal of this white paper is to translate the latest psychological and neuroscience research to help with advancing legal policy.&nbsp;</span></p> <div class="page" title="Page 8"> <div class="section"> <div class="layoutArea"> <div class="column"> <p><span>By extending her research to inform juvenile justice policy and practice, this work has the potential to make impactful change in society. Dr. Insel has worked with lawyers, judges, and legal advocates to help translate adolescent brain science into the courtroom. She is committed to building a bridge between science and society to promote positive change and legal reform for youth.</span></p> <p>Dr. Insel is also committed to the mentorship of early career scientists, and she is committed to i<span>ncreasing the representation of historically excluded identities in academia by promoting the training of minoritized and marginalized individuals. She is&nbsp;</span>committed to helping students navigate the &ldquo;hidden curriculum&rdquo; of science by coaching undergraduate students outside of her lab to help guide them through the graduate school admissions process. She is also&nbsp;committed to early education initiatives to promote diversity in science, and she has trained high school students from low- resourced backgrounds and traditionally underrepresented groups with hands-on research experience in neuroscience in order to promote early participation in STEM.&nbsp;</p> </div> </div> </div> </div> </div> </div> </div> </div><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/17/2023<br>      Modified by: Catherine&nbsp;Insel</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Catherine Insel completed research for the NSF SBE SPRF postdoctoral award. Her research aimed to identify how adolescents use memories to help make decisions, and to understand how and why adolescents make different types of decisions than adults do. During the funding period, she collected multiple datasets in human subjects and developmental populations. She also collected fMRI data in adolescents and young adults to examine how brain development from childhood to early adulthood shapes learning, memory, and value-based decision making. Her research reveals exciting new insights about how and why adolescents make different decisions than adults. She found that adolescents are more likely to learn from single experiences, which is an adaptive strategy that helps them update their behavior quickly and flexibly in new situations. Additional findings suggest that as adolescents get older, they are more likely to average over many related experiences when making a decision, a process referred to as generalization. Ongoing work with fMRI is identifying the neurobiological mechanisms that support these developmental changes in decision-making across adolescence. This work will reveal how ongoing brain development shapes daily behaviors in youth, which has important implications for understanding how adolescents learn, both in and out of the classroom.  Intellectual Merit:  This work has advanced our understanding of how and why adolescents make different decisions than adults do. Catherine Insel's work has revealed novel insights into how memories are crucial for making decisions. This work demonstrates that compared to adults, adolescents use different types of memories to help guide their choices. These findings have formed the basis of a new conceptual framework that provides an important revision on contemporary theories of adolescent decision-making.  Broader Impacts:      Understanding adolescent brain development is key to advancing juvenile justice policy and practice. Dr. Insel worked with the Center for Law Brain and Behavior at Massachusetts General Hospital to write a white paper for lawyers, judges, and policy makers with critical updates on adolescent brain science. The goal of this white paper is to translate the latest psychological and neuroscience research to help with advancing legal policy.       By extending her research to inform juvenile justice policy and practice, this work has the potential to make impactful change in society. Dr. Insel has worked with lawyers, judges, and legal advocates to help translate adolescent brain science into the courtroom. She is committed to building a bridge between science and society to promote positive change and legal reform for youth.  Dr. Insel is also committed to the mentorship of early career scientists, and she is committed to increasing the representation of historically excluded identities in academia by promoting the training of minoritized and marginalized individuals. She is committed to helping students navigate the "hidden curriculum" of science by coaching undergraduate students outside of her lab to help guide them through the graduate school admissions process. She is also committed to early education initiatives to promote diversity in science, and she has trained high school students from low- resourced backgrounds and traditionally underrepresented groups with hands-on research experience in neuroscience in order to promote early participation in STEM.                Last Modified: 01/17/2023       Submitted by: Catherine Insel]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
