<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Laws, Judiciaries, and National Security Agencies: Advancing Theory and Concepts of Civil Society Laws]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>143000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>143000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SMA</Abbreviation>
<LongName>SBE Off Of Multidisciplinary Activities</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Josie Welkom Miranda</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jwmirand@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927376</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This award was provided as part of NSF's Social, Behavioral and Economic Sciences (SBE) Postdoctoral Research Fellowships (SPRF) program and SBE's Law and Science program. The goal of the SPRF program is to prepare promising, early career doctoral-level scientists for scientific careers in academia, industry or private sector, and government. SPRF awards involve two years of training under the sponsorship of established scientists and encourage Postdoctoral Fellows to perform independent research. NSF seeks to promote the participation of scientists from all segments of the scientific community, including those from underrepresented groups, in its research programs and activities; the postdoctoral period is considered to be an important level of professional development in attaining this goal. Each Postdoctoral Fellow must address important scientific questions that advance their respective disciplinary fields. Under the sponsorship of Dr. Jeffrey K. Staton at Emory University, this postdoctoral fellowship award supports an early career scientist investigating how and why governments regulate civil society. The human rights community has grown increasingly concerned with legal crackdowns or regulatory restrictions of civil society organizations (CSOs) around the globe. The standard explanation is that these civil society laws and enforcement actions are less likely in open, democratic societies and more likely in undemocratic or authoritarian settings. The data generally accord with this expectation but there is a non-trivial number of exceptions, and data show many undemocratic regimes routinely enact liberal laws. In explaining these cases, we give special attention to the judiciary and national security agencies as actors that change and enforce these legal institutions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research makes substantive contributions to research topics in judicial politics, political economy, democratization and development, law and political institutions, legal processes, public policy, and comparative public administration. Its primary research objectives are to examine how the judiciary affects the evolution of civil society laws through court rulings. Depending on the context, courts have the power to declare laws unconstitutional, identify statutes as appropriate but enforcement actions unjust, or legitimize enforcement actions and legal institutions. Two, analyze the role of security agencies in the enforcement of civil society laws over a multi-decade period. Three, publish an original dataset on the Qualitative Data Repository created by coding a legal corpus used in the fellow's earlier research. These objectives are interconnected and rely on a mixed-methods research design. Deskwork codes primary source materials collected from [a country's] National Legislative Library, Commission on Laws and Judicial Reporting, and the Ministry of Laws and Justice. Fieldwork conducts in-depth interviews with instructors at [the country's] Centre for Training and Developing Judges.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/12/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/12/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2004520</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Anthony</FirstName>
<LastName>DeMattee</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Anthony J DeMattee</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<NSF_ID>000814295</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/12/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jeffrey</FirstName>
<LastName>Staton</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jeffrey Staton</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<NSF_ID>000189604</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/12/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>DeMattee, Anthony James</Name>
<CityName>BLOOMINGTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>474031470</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IN09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Emory University]]></Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>303221061</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>040Y</Code>
<Text>(SPRF-FR) SBE Postdoctoral Res</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>128Y</Code>
<Text>Law &amp; Science</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7137</Code>
<Text>POSTDOCTORAL FELLOWSHIPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~143000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>My NSF postdoctoral research fellowship was very successful from a research perspective. My proposed deliverables included two peer-reviewed research articles and one publicly available dataset. During my two-year postdoc, I published seven peer-reviewed articles, two book chapters, and currently have two other research articles under review. As of September 19th, 2022, I have several other working papers at various stages of completion, two of which I hope to submit for review before the end of the calendar year.&nbsp;</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><span>I used my NSF funding to conduct an inter-coder reliability assessment of the dataset I will make public. Two individuals with graduate-level education in law, public policy, and political science first received training on the coding protocol I developed and then individually coded laws randomly assigned to them. Coders then met to discuss their results and agree on each item, with the PI holding the tie-breaking vote. The intercoder-reliability assessment conducted on 12% of the legal corpus shows coders agreed on 1,956 of 2,030 occasions that specific legal provisions matched coding protocol items. This 96% convergence rate indicates that the coding instrument produces internally consistent measures. I thoroughly explain my coding procedure in two articles:&nbsp;</span><em>Qualitative and Multi-Method Research</em><span>&nbsp;(</span><em>QMMR</em><span>) accepted for publication late-April, and&nbsp;</span><em>Policy Studies Journal&nbsp;</em><span>(</span><em>PSJ</em><span>) accepted for publication mid-September. These two articles will accompany the dataset and codebook and provide the "how-to" behind the dataset's coding procedures.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><span>The&nbsp;</span><em>QMMR</em><span>&nbsp;and&nbsp;</span><em>PSJ</em><span>&nbsp;articles provide researchers with methodological instructions for comparative law and policy research. The former lays out a hybrid method for translating legal text that drastically reduces linguistic knowledge as a constraint on researchers; reducing time and translation costs opens new areas of research that would otherwise require large teams and grants. The latter presents a principled method for aggregating the legal rules coded in multiple laws into a single legal institution to help us understand and better characterize complex, interconnected, and sometimes contradictory bundles of legal rules. The methods are amenable to any legal topic and are especially appropriate when multiple statutes simultaneously comprise the legal institution in a single jurisdiction--e.g., civil rights, peaceful assembly, voting, business competition, welfare and financial regulation, tax and immigration policies, and environmental regulations.&nbsp;</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><span>Professional networking was a key aspect of my NSF postdoctoral research fellowship; COVID-19 both helped and hindered this goal. On the one hand, many academic conferences transitioned to online forums early in the pandemic. Online conferences save on travel costs (e.g., the Law and Society Association Annual Meetings) and allow me to regularly attend work groups with members from around the world (the monthly Global Law and Politics Research Group). On the other hand, online/hybrid meetings complicate efforts to establish new professional connections. For example, I attended the 2021 American Political Science Association (APSA) annual meeting in Seattle. Unfortunately, many of the participants either canceled their attendance or moved their panels online without notifying attendees. In hindsight, my postdoc overlapped with a period dominated by COVID, during which the profession embraced new technologies and established new norms.&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><span>The number one goal of my postdoc was to secure a tenure-track position at an American research university. Unfortunately, I could not secure such a position after three attempts on the job market (AY2019/20, AY2020/21, and AY2021/22). My record was strong--a dozen peer-reviewed articles and book chapters, an NSF postdoc, nearly $250K in competitive research funding, three APSA best dissertation awards, and a promising research agenda--and I applied broadly. Yet, for whatever reason, most schools did not want to interview me, and those few that did chose not to consider me as part of their short-list of candidates. It is a very disappointing outcome for me, and I am currently exploring opportunities to transition into an academic-adjacent position where I can apply my talents, energy, and research experience. &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;&nbsp;</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/20/2022<br>      Modified by: Anthony&nbsp;J&nbsp;Demattee</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ My NSF postdoctoral research fellowship was very successful from a research perspective. My proposed deliverables included two peer-reviewed research articles and one publicly available dataset. During my two-year postdoc, I published seven peer-reviewed articles, two book chapters, and currently have two other research articles under review. As of September 19th, 2022, I have several other working papers at various stages of completion, two of which I hope to submit for review before the end of the calendar year.      I used my NSF funding to conduct an inter-coder reliability assessment of the dataset I will make public. Two individuals with graduate-level education in law, public policy, and political science first received training on the coding protocol I developed and then individually coded laws randomly assigned to them. Coders then met to discuss their results and agree on each item, with the PI holding the tie-breaking vote. The intercoder-reliability assessment conducted on 12% of the legal corpus shows coders agreed on 1,956 of 2,030 occasions that specific legal provisions matched coding protocol items. This 96% convergence rate indicates that the coding instrument produces internally consistent measures. I thoroughly explain my coding procedure in two articles: Qualitative and Multi-Method Research (QMMR) accepted for publication late-April, and Policy Studies Journal (PSJ) accepted for publication mid-September. These two articles will accompany the dataset and codebook and provide the "how-to" behind the dataset's coding procedures.     The QMMR and PSJ articles provide researchers with methodological instructions for comparative law and policy research. The former lays out a hybrid method for translating legal text that drastically reduces linguistic knowledge as a constraint on researchers; reducing time and translation costs opens new areas of research that would otherwise require large teams and grants. The latter presents a principled method for aggregating the legal rules coded in multiple laws into a single legal institution to help us understand and better characterize complex, interconnected, and sometimes contradictory bundles of legal rules. The methods are amenable to any legal topic and are especially appropriate when multiple statutes simultaneously comprise the legal institution in a single jurisdiction--e.g., civil rights, peaceful assembly, voting, business competition, welfare and financial regulation, tax and immigration policies, and environmental regulations.      Professional networking was a key aspect of my NSF postdoctoral research fellowship; COVID-19 both helped and hindered this goal. On the one hand, many academic conferences transitioned to online forums early in the pandemic. Online conferences save on travel costs (e.g., the Law and Society Association Annual Meetings) and allow me to regularly attend work groups with members from around the world (the monthly Global Law and Politics Research Group). On the other hand, online/hybrid meetings complicate efforts to establish new professional connections. For example, I attended the 2021 American Political Science Association (APSA) annual meeting in Seattle. Unfortunately, many of the participants either canceled their attendance or moved their panels online without notifying attendees. In hindsight, my postdoc overlapped with a period dominated by COVID, during which the profession embraced new technologies and established new norms.            The number one goal of my postdoc was to secure a tenure-track position at an American research university. Unfortunately, I could not secure such a position after three attempts on the job market (AY2019/20, AY2020/21, and AY2021/22). My record was strong--a dozen peer-reviewed articles and book chapters, an NSF postdoc, nearly $250K in competitive research funding, three APSA best dissertation awards, and a promising research agenda--and I applied broadly. Yet, for whatever reason, most schools did not want to interview me, and those few that did chose not to consider me as part of their short-list of candidates. It is a very disappointing outcome for me, and I am currently exploring opportunities to transition into an academic-adjacent position where I can apply my talents, energy, and research experience.                   Last Modified: 09/20/2022       Submitted by: Anthony J Demattee]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
