<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Singularity Formation in Kahler Geometry and Yang-Mills Instantons]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>350000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>350000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Christopher Stark</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cstark@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924869</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This project will study singularity formation of some special geometric structures governed by non-linear partial differential equations. These structures are generalizations of solutions to the Einstein’s equation for gravity and Maxwell’s equation for electromagnetism, and play significant roles in modern theoretical physics (for example string theory and M-theory). The solution to these problems will enhance the understanding of deep interaction between various research directions in mathematics. In the meantime, there are many interesting related questions that may serve as research projects for the training of graduate students interested in this area.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The PI will study problems in two specific directions. First, the PI would like to study collapsing of Calabi-Yau metrics, and connections with algebraic geometry and moduli compactification. Previous work of the PI and collaborators has  yielded a satisfactory description in the case of minimal degenerations and the PI proposes to study the more general situation. This requires exploiting the existing techniques from collapsing theory, and further developing those. Secondly, the PI will study singularity analysis for Yang-Mills instantons. In the case of Hermitian-Yang-Mills connections over Kahler manifolds, recent work of the PI and Xuemiao Chen gives a complete algebro-geometric description of the tangent cones, and the PI wants to push these further by discovering more refined structures, and by investigating the case of G2 instantons. This requires building algebro-geometric framework, as well as extending some of these to the more analytic setting.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/06/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/06/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2004261</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Song</FirstName>
<LastName>Sun</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Song Sun</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[sosun@berkeley.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000653224</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/06/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Berkeley</Name>
<CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
<ZipCode>947101749</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5106433891</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1608 4TH ST STE 201</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>GS3YEVSS12N6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>NUDGYLBB4S99</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Berkeley]]></Name>
<CityName>Berkeley</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>947203840</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[839 Evans Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1265</Code>
<Text>GEOMETRIC ANALYSIS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~350000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The PI has made substantial progress towards the goals of the proposal, including both intellectual merit and broader impacts. <span>Throughout the course of this project, the PI has authored five research articles and one survey article, effectively addressing several of the questions raised in the original proposal.</span></p> <p><span>The research has yielded several noteworthy outcomes. One of these includes the collaborative work with Ruobing Zhang on the collapsing geometry of hyperkahler 4-manifolds, successfully resolving long-standing inquiries within this field. Additionally, the joint work with Junsheng Zhang on the structure at infinity of complete Calabi-Yau manifolds discovered an unexpected phenomenon of no-semistability at infinity. Further achievements include the classification of a specific class of gravitational instantons, the study of the bubbling structure of Kahler-Einstein metrics, and an expository article ``geometry of Calabi-Yau metrics" for the notices of the AMS.</span></p> <p><span>A significant contribution to the broader impact of this research lies in its successful integration with other disciplines in mathematics, notably algebraic geometry and mathematical physics.&nbsp; Furthermore, an important accomplishment in terms of broader impact is evident in the training of graduate students. The grant has provided support for three graduate students under the supervision of the PI, all of whom have made remarkable progress in advancing the proposed projects.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/03/2023<br>      Modified by: Song&nbsp;Sun</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The PI has made substantial progress towards the goals of the proposal, including both intellectual merit and broader impacts. Throughout the course of this project, the PI has authored five research articles and one survey article, effectively addressing several of the questions raised in the original proposal.  The research has yielded several noteworthy outcomes. One of these includes the collaborative work with Ruobing Zhang on the collapsing geometry of hyperkahler 4-manifolds, successfully resolving long-standing inquiries within this field. Additionally, the joint work with Junsheng Zhang on the structure at infinity of complete Calabi-Yau manifolds discovered an unexpected phenomenon of no-semistability at infinity. Further achievements include the classification of a specific class of gravitational instantons, the study of the bubbling structure of Kahler-Einstein metrics, and an expository article ``geometry of Calabi-Yau metrics" for the notices of the AMS.  A significant contribution to the broader impact of this research lies in its successful integration with other disciplines in mathematics, notably algebraic geometry and mathematical physics.  Furthermore, an important accomplishment in terms of broader impact is evident in the training of graduate students. The grant has provided support for three graduate students under the supervision of the PI, all of whom have made remarkable progress in advancing the proposed projects.          Last Modified: 08/03/2023       Submitted by: Song Sun]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
