<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Identification and alignment of interested actors around civil wars using the text of UN General Assembly speeches]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>138000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>138000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SMA</Abbreviation>
<LongName>SBE Off Of Multidisciplinary Activities</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Josie Welkom Miranda</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jwmirand@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927376</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This award was provided as part of NSF's Social, Behavioral and Economic Sciences Postdoctoral Research Fellowships (SPRF) program and SBE's Security and Preparedness program. The goal of the SPRF program is to prepare promising, early career doctoral-level scientists for scientific careers in academia, industry or private sector, and government. SPRF awards involve two years of training under the sponsorship of established scientists and encourage Postdoctoral Fellows to perform independent research. NSF seeks to promote the participation of scientists from all segments of the scientific community, including those from underrepresented groups, in its research programs and activities; the postdoctoral period is considered to be an important level of professional development in attaining this goal. Each Postdoctoral Fellow must address important scientific questions that advance their respective disciplinary fields. Under the sponsorship of Dr. Kyle Beardsley at Duke University, this postdoctoral fellowship award supports an early career scientist investigating the internationalization of civil conflicts, using United Nations (UN) General Assembly speeches to help identify politically interested countries and to measure their alignment around a given conflict. The project advances both the study of diplomacy at the United Nations and the study of third-party involvement in civil wars. Additionally, by focusing on the content of UN speeches as a predictor of risk, it provides a scalable framework for creating longer-term tracking and finer-grained forecasts as geopolitical interests develop, change, and evolve. Finally, it helps build enhanced infrastructure for future scholastic collaboration on data collection and forecasting, as well as for providing future generations of researchers with hands-on training in a large-scale research program.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Civil wars often escalate to envelop an entire region or, in some cases, the entire world. This process of internationalization involves both an assessment of whether countries actually have a political interest in the ongoing conflict, and also whether other countries have similar or conflicting interests. This project zooms into these two questions by setting out to both identify interested countries, and measure the alignment of interests across these parties, using the text of UN General Assembly speeches as a data source for both (in conjunction with other measures from the literature). Funding for this project supports three primary tasks. The first task leverages machine learning methods to match the content of individual UN General Assembly Speeches (from 1984-2014) to the discussion of a given civil war. The second task models the risk of whether an individual country has an identifiable political interest in this civil war, drawing on the content of the classified UN General Assembly speeches and also drawing on a systematic review of prior literature on the topic. Finally, given this political interest, the third task measures the alignment of interested countries to determine whether they are likely to cooperate or conflict surrounding that conflict. Output from this study are relevant for both scholars and policymakers, with implications for understanding diplomacy at the United Nations, and for modeling the intricate link between civil wars, inter-state conflict, and international institutions like the UN. It facilitates progress in both the scholarly understanding of conflict processes, and in the efficient allocation of national security resources following the outbreak of a politically relevant conflict with the potential for internationalization.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/27/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/27/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2004212</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Zuhaib</FirstName>
<LastName>Mahmood</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Zuhaib S Mahmood</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<NSF_ID>000813621</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/27/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Siegel</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David A Siegel</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<NSF_ID>000514003</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/27/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kyle</FirstName>
<LastName>Beardsley</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kyle Beardsley</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<NSF_ID>000555939</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/27/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Mahmood, Zuhaib Sheikh</Name>
<CityName>East Lansing</CityName>
<ZipCode>48824</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Duke University]]></Name>
<CityName>Durham</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>277089976</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>040Y</Code>
<Text>(SPRF-FR) SBE Postdoctoral Res</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>118Y</Code>
<Text>Security &amp; Preparedness</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7137</Code>
<Text>POSTDOCTORAL FELLOWSHIPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~138000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project uncovered three areas of guidance for researchers on the process of civil war intervention. First, that the process appears to be relatively heterogenous. Key variables--for example, intervener hard power or the dyadic distance between intervener and conflict country--flip in their directional sign depending on the year. Different models perform best on different conflicts, and in some cases the performance varies substantially. This suggests that across both time periods and across conflicts, there are <em>meaningfully different </em>incentive structures and correlates driving the relationship between the conflict and the decision to intervene by any given potential intervener. This raises an opportunity for improvement upon prior literature on this topic, since the majority of this literature models third-party intervention as a single, homogenous process upon which inferences about variable correlations can be made. There seems to be an opportunity for improvement around identifying the conditions under which a given theory predicts a positive or negative correlation between conflict/intervener characteristics and the eventual outcome of intervention.&nbsp;</p> <p>Second, the forecasting performance of the evaluated variables seems to be deteriorating over time. This points to another opportunity for future research, and dovetails from the previous note about heterogeneity. One possibility is that the actual politics behind third-party intervention are actually changing in recent years, such that the factors which performed well in predicting historical interventions are no longer as useful recently. The other possibility is that the structure of the model driving this intervention is becoming more complex: in other words, the actual model structure may be changing over time. In either case, uncovering how the politics behind this decision have changed over time--whether this entails new considerations previously not relevant, or whether this entails a more complex decision-making process which was previously simpler--seems to be an opportunity for future work.&nbsp;</p> <p>Finally, a third pattern uncovered in this paper is consistent with prior work leveraging forecasting methods to evaluate performance of features in Political Science/Conflict literature: namely, that high-resolution, precisely measured variables which identify specific characteristics over time and across countries add less leverage than broader, more slowly changing characteristics (e.g. major power status). This is not an indictment of these measures; rather, it is an opportunity for more precise work on <em>why </em>or <em>how&nbsp;</em>these broad characteristics are so strongly predicting intervention as compared to other, more narrowly focused--but more variable--measures do. This may be an opportunity for feature engineering or uncovering additional processes related to these broader, more static characteristics of countries that could provide more leverage in the overall exercise of predicting third-party intervention.&nbsp;</p> <p>In addition to these findings, data collection and analysis specific to UN speeches remains ongoing. Due to unforseen circumstances at the time of application, with the global Covid-19 pandemic (Jan 2021-Dec 2022), work on this portion of the data remains ongoing.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/01/2023<br>      Modified by: Zuhaib&nbsp;S&nbsp;Mahmood</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project uncovered three areas of guidance for researchers on the process of civil war intervention. First, that the process appears to be relatively heterogenous. Key variables--for example, intervener hard power or the dyadic distance between intervener and conflict country--flip in their directional sign depending on the year. Different models perform best on different conflicts, and in some cases the performance varies substantially. This suggests that across both time periods and across conflicts, there are meaningfully different incentive structures and correlates driving the relationship between the conflict and the decision to intervene by any given potential intervener. This raises an opportunity for improvement upon prior literature on this topic, since the majority of this literature models third-party intervention as a single, homogenous process upon which inferences about variable correlations can be made. There seems to be an opportunity for improvement around identifying the conditions under which a given theory predicts a positive or negative correlation between conflict/intervener characteristics and the eventual outcome of intervention.   Second, the forecasting performance of the evaluated variables seems to be deteriorating over time. This points to another opportunity for future research, and dovetails from the previous note about heterogeneity. One possibility is that the actual politics behind third-party intervention are actually changing in recent years, such that the factors which performed well in predicting historical interventions are no longer as useful recently. The other possibility is that the structure of the model driving this intervention is becoming more complex: in other words, the actual model structure may be changing over time. In either case, uncovering how the politics behind this decision have changed over time--whether this entails new considerations previously not relevant, or whether this entails a more complex decision-making process which was previously simpler--seems to be an opportunity for future work.   Finally, a third pattern uncovered in this paper is consistent with prior work leveraging forecasting methods to evaluate performance of features in Political Science/Conflict literature: namely, that high-resolution, precisely measured variables which identify specific characteristics over time and across countries add less leverage than broader, more slowly changing characteristics (e.g. major power status). This is not an indictment of these measures; rather, it is an opportunity for more precise work on why or how these broad characteristics are so strongly predicting intervention as compared to other, more narrowly focused--but more variable--measures do. This may be an opportunity for feature engineering or uncovering additional processes related to these broader, more static characteristics of countries that could provide more leverage in the overall exercise of predicting third-party intervention.   In addition to these findings, data collection and analysis specific to UN speeches remains ongoing. Due to unforseen circumstances at the time of application, with the global Covid-19 pandemic (Jan 2021-Dec 2022), work on this portion of the data remains ongoing.       Last Modified: 05/01/2023       Submitted by: Zuhaib S Mahmood]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
