<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Unlikely Alliances in Rural-Urban Water Conflicts]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>63250.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>63250</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SMA</Abbreviation>
<LongName>SBE Off Of Multidisciplinary Activities</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Josie Welkom Miranda</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jwmirand@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927376</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This award was provided as part of NSF's Social, Behavioral and Economic Sciences Postdoctoral Research Fellowships (SPRF) program. The goal of the SPRF program is to prepare promising, early career doctoral-level scientists for scientific careers in academia, industry or private sector, and government. SPRF awards involve two years of training under the sponsorship of established scientists and encourage Postdoctoral Fellows to perform independent research. NSF seeks to promote the participation of scientists from all segments of the scientific community, including those from underrepresented groups, in its research programs and activities; the postdoctoral period is considered to be an important level of professional development in attaining this goal. Each Postdoctoral Fellow must address important scientific questions that advance their respective disciplinary fields. Under the sponsorship of Dr. Kate Berry at University of Nevada, Reno, this postdoctoral fellowship award supports an early career scientist investigating rural-urban water conflicts in the Western United States. As cities increasingly look to rural areas for water supplies, they are often met with staunch resistance. Yet, the dynamics of conflict and cooperation over rural-urban water transfers are not well understood. This research addresses this gap by examining resistance to two large rural-urban water transfers. In particular, it seeks to understand the dynamics of alliance and alignment among diverse Indigenous and non-Indigenous actors resisting these transfers. The project aims to contribute a more nuanced understanding of what are called unlikely alliances. More broadly, it seeks to advance understandings of the role of contestation and collective action in water governance. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Specifically, this project engages scholarship on unlikely alliances, hydrosocial territory, and territorial pluralism to answer three research questions. First, why and when are Indigenous and non-Indigenous actors finding strategic alliance or alignment over shared resistance to rural-to-urban water transfers? Second, how is alliance or alignment among diverse actors shaping and shaped by the way hydrosocial territories are constructed, mobilized, and contested in water transfer conflicts? Third, how do assertions of Indigenous governance and tribal sovereignty shape the ways actors navigate territorial pluralism as they ally or align in pursuit of water justice? To address these questions, the project employs qualitative methods in a comparative case study of two water transfer conflicts in the Great Basin region. Methods for data collection include interviews, archival research and document review, participant observation of meetings and events, and focus groups that will be used to discuss and gather feedback about preliminary findings. The results of the study will inform key water policy debates and provide insights for activists and organizations interested in building more diverse coalitions. By examining the diverse visions of hydrosocial territory asserted in rural-urban water conflicts, this research will contribute to scholarly understandings of how actors pursue water justice and build new water regimes.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/26/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/26/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2004800</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sophia</FirstName>
<LastName>Borgias</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sophia L Borgias</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<NSF_ID>000767253</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/26/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kate</FirstName>
<LastName>Berry</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kate A Berry</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<NSF_ID>000449324</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/26/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Borgias, Sophia L</Name>
<CityName>Bishop</CityName>
<ZipCode>93514</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Nevada, Reno]]></Name>
<CityName>Reno</CityName>
<StateCode>NV</StateCode>
<ZipCode>895570001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Nevada</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NV02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>040Y</Code>
<Text>(SPRF-FR) SBE Postdoctoral Res</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7137</Code>
<Text>POSTDOCTORAL FELLOWSHIPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~63250</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project supported an early career scientist researching unlikely alliances in rural-urban water conflicts. The research focused on two cases in the Great Basin region of the Western U.S.; the ongoing conflicts over Los Angeles's extraction and export of water from the Owens and Mono basins in eastern California, and the 30-year struggle that led to the recent defeat of Southern Nevada Water Authority?s proposals to extract groundwater from rural eastern Nevada. More than 60 semi-structured interviews were conducted with environmentalists, ranchers, Indigenous leaders and activists, and others that have allied or aligned in resistance to these large inter-basin water transfers. Analysis of the interviews, along with data from document review, participant observation, and focus groups, produced key insights about unlikely alliances and water justice. These are being shared in two peer-reviewed journal articles, as well as presentations and a report for participants.</p> <p>The results from this research provide a more nuanced understanding of how unlikely alliances function in practice. We found that unlikely alliances can take many different forms but often hinge upon striking a delicate balance between togetherness and autonomy. This was particularly important in regard to the involvement of Tribes, which tended to act independently in their role as sovereign nations while also aligning with broader collective efforts. We also found divergent understandings of what it means to ally. Some approached it as a highly situational partnership against a common enemy or threat, while others sought to build deeper relationships of mutual support and solidarity that transcended any one conflict.</p> <p>Our analysis also underscored important relationships between coalition-building and visions of water justice. We found that individuals? visions of water justice were diverse and dynamic, such that working in coalition often required strategic decisions to focus on the common ground. While coalition members tended to share an interest in protecting existing landscapes and livelihoods from new threats and upholding existing systems of accountability, broader visions of repairing past harms or transforming underlying systems were understood as a source of tension. Individuals? visions of water justice inform how they build and maintain relationships, and those relationships in turn shape the way individuals pursue water justice both individually and collectively.</p> <p>While grounded in specific rural-urban water conflicts in the Great Basin, these findings are broadly relevant to studies of conflict, collaboration, and collective action in water governance. They highlight the diverse interests involved in rural-urban water conflicts and the role of coalition-building in bridging across historical divides. And they suggest great potential for more research that attends to not just how people fight <em>in</em>justice but how they envision and chart pathways toward change.</p> <p>Finally, in addition to supporting this research, the postdoctoral fellowship also helped to build and strengthen relationships with community partners in the Great Basin that have formed the basis for new projects and initiatives. The fellow helped organize the Great Basin Water Justice Summit in August 2022, an event that brought together participants from this project along with other communities working on water justice issues in the region. Based on community interests identified in a participatory workshop there, she is now developing a collaborative project about the intersections of water justice and climate justice.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/29/2022<br>      Modified by: Sophia&nbsp;L&nbsp;Borgias</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project supported an early career scientist researching unlikely alliances in rural-urban water conflicts. The research focused on two cases in the Great Basin region of the Western U.S.; the ongoing conflicts over Los Angeles's extraction and export of water from the Owens and Mono basins in eastern California, and the 30-year struggle that led to the recent defeat of Southern Nevada Water Authority?s proposals to extract groundwater from rural eastern Nevada. More than 60 semi-structured interviews were conducted with environmentalists, ranchers, Indigenous leaders and activists, and others that have allied or aligned in resistance to these large inter-basin water transfers. Analysis of the interviews, along with data from document review, participant observation, and focus groups, produced key insights about unlikely alliances and water justice. These are being shared in two peer-reviewed journal articles, as well as presentations and a report for participants.  The results from this research provide a more nuanced understanding of how unlikely alliances function in practice. We found that unlikely alliances can take many different forms but often hinge upon striking a delicate balance between togetherness and autonomy. This was particularly important in regard to the involvement of Tribes, which tended to act independently in their role as sovereign nations while also aligning with broader collective efforts. We also found divergent understandings of what it means to ally. Some approached it as a highly situational partnership against a common enemy or threat, while others sought to build deeper relationships of mutual support and solidarity that transcended any one conflict.  Our analysis also underscored important relationships between coalition-building and visions of water justice. We found that individuals? visions of water justice were diverse and dynamic, such that working in coalition often required strategic decisions to focus on the common ground. While coalition members tended to share an interest in protecting existing landscapes and livelihoods from new threats and upholding existing systems of accountability, broader visions of repairing past harms or transforming underlying systems were understood as a source of tension. Individuals? visions of water justice inform how they build and maintain relationships, and those relationships in turn shape the way individuals pursue water justice both individually and collectively.  While grounded in specific rural-urban water conflicts in the Great Basin, these findings are broadly relevant to studies of conflict, collaboration, and collective action in water governance. They highlight the diverse interests involved in rural-urban water conflicts and the role of coalition-building in bridging across historical divides. And they suggest great potential for more research that attends to not just how people fight injustice but how they envision and chart pathways toward change.  Finally, in addition to supporting this research, the postdoctoral fellowship also helped to build and strengthen relationships with community partners in the Great Basin that have formed the basis for new projects and initiatives. The fellow helped organize the Great Basin Water Justice Summit in August 2022, an event that brought together participants from this project along with other communities working on water justice issues in the region. Based on community interests identified in a participatory workshop there, she is now developing a collaborative project about the intersections of water justice and climate justice.         Last Modified: 12/29/2022       Submitted by: Sophia L Borgias]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
