<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Calorimetric Benchmark Energies of Adsorbed Intermediates, Solvent Effects and Solvent / Catalyst Bonding]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>453165.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>453165</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Robert McCabe</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rmccabe@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924826</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Better catalysts and electrocatalysts are essential for energy-efficient and environmentally benign manufacturing of fuels and chemicals, and for advanced processes to reduce carbon emissions and mitigate environmental pollutants.  Optimizing catalysts for specific applications, however, requires detailed knowledge of reaction steps and the mechanisms by which the catalyst accelerates those steps.  The project will generate data on the bonding strength of small molecules to catalytic metal surfaces, both in the presence and absence of solvents.  The bonding strength can then be used to refine theoretical models of catalyst performance and accelerate the discovery and design of improved catalysts and catalytic processes.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Specifically, the project will employ state-of-the-art calorimetric methods developed in the investigator’s laboratory to measure adsorption enthalpies of small molecules on single crystal surfaces, and estimate solvent effects that are relevant to various applications in heterogeneous catalysis and electrocatalysis. The project involves three main energy-measurement objectives: 1) adsorption of small molecular species on copper (Cu) single crystal surfaces, as a complement to the extensive work that has been done on earlier transition metal surfaces; 2) adhesion of condensed solvents on single crystal surfaces; and 3) adsorption of small molecular species in the presence of a co-adsorbed solvent. This work extends the investigator’s previous gas adsorption studies on platinum (Pt) and nickel (Ni) single-crystals to Cu single crystals, while furthering the Cu study to include solvent effects important in liquid-phase electrocatalytic reactions.  The study will advance a database of experimental adsorption energies that can be used to calibrate ab initio models and their basis sets, thereby strengthening links between experimental and theoretical catalysis.  The project is structured such that the investigator will provide in-depth training to both graduate and undergraduate students with respect to his unique calorimetric instrumentation and analysis tools.  He will also collaborate with a young associate professor as part of a succession plan to ensure long-term contributions to the critical database of adsorption enthalpies already established in his laboratory.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award is co-funded by the Catalysis Program in the Division of Chemical, Bioengineering, Environmental, and Transport Systems and the Chemical Catalysis Program in the Division of Chemistry.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/04/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/04/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2004757</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Charles</FirstName>
<LastName>Campbell</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>T</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Charles T Campbell</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[campbell@chem.washington.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000366409</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/04/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Washington</Name>
<CityName>SEATTLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>981951016</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2065434043</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4333 BROOKLYN AVE NE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>HD1WMN6945W6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF WASHINGTON</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Washington]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>981950001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1401</Code>
<Text>Catalysis</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6884</Code>
<Text>Chemical Catalysis</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8037</Code>
<Text>Advanced Manufacturing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8396</Code>
<Text>Clean Energy Technology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~453165</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Overview:</strong></p> <p>Better catalysts and electrocatalysts are essential for the efficient production and use of clean fuels, for energy efficient chemical synthesis with less environmental impact, for energy storage, for pollution abatement and for many other future technologies needed to achieve environmentally friendlier energy supply and chemical industry.&nbsp; Crucial for rational design of better catalyst and electrocatalyst materials is the knowledge of the energies of elementary chemical reactions on late transition metal surfaces. Experiments are performed which measure the energetics of selected elementary chemical reactions occurring on late transition metal surfaces, carefully chosen to enable development of new theoretical methods for more accurately predicting such energies, to improve basic understanding of catalytic action and the effect of liquid solvents on these, and to facilitate the design of better catalysts and electrocatalysts. The main accomplishment of this research has been to broaden the database of reliable experimental energies of adsorbed catalytic intermediates (and effects of liquid solvents on these) that can be used by theoreticians as benchmarks to guide development of computational methods with improved accuracy for calculating the energetics of chemical reactions at late transition metal surfaces in both liquid and gas phase.&nbsp;</p> <p>.&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Intellectual Merit:</strong></p> <p>Fast computational methods like density functional theory (DFT) offer our greatest promise for designing new catalysts, electrocatalysts, and batteries and new processes for energy and environmental technologies. However, their power at achieving this would be multiplied many fold if these methods could be improved to achieve higher accuracy in calculating the energies of adsorbed reaction intermediates and the effects of liquid solvents on these energies. This would be transformative for catalysis research, enabling greater reliability in computational prediction of reaction rates and mechanisms.&nbsp; Such improvement requires an accurate experimental database of adsorbate energies on a range of well-defined model catalyst surfaces, the effects of solvents on these energies, and the strengths of solvent bonding to well-defined catalyst surfaces. Developing such a database has been the main goal of this research program. In addition to guiding improvements in DFT, it will also help clarify the energetic basis for structure-reactivity correlations and solvent effects in transition metal catalysis and electrocatalysis. Specifically, the adsorption energies of several common adsorbed catalytic reaction intermediates have been measured by calorimetry on Cu(111) and Pt(111) in gas phase, for comparison to earlier results for these same adsorbates on Pt(111) and Ni(111). The adhesion energies of several liquid solvents to these metal surfaces were measured as well.&nbsp; A theoretical model was developed whereby these can be combined with gas-phase adsorption energies to estimate solvent effects on adsorption energies of reaction intermediates. The measurements performed in this program cannot be performed anywhere else in the world, yet they have provided crucial input to improve accuracy of computational methods and enable substantial progress in understanding and computationally predicting the differences in activity and selectivity between different catalyst materials and different solvents.</p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts: </strong></p> <p>This research will aid in designing more efficient and environmentally-clean catalysts, electrocatalysts and processes for energy technologies and chemical industry, and for storing solar and wind energy, all crucial for sustainable living.&nbsp; It has provided strong interdisciplinary, research-integrated education for numerous graduate and undergraduate students. These students got hands-on experience with state-of-the-art measurement instrumentation and learned to apply these to solve intellectually-challenging research problems on topics of great national interest. The students interacted with outstanding visiting scientists and researchers at national labs. They were mentored in scientific leadership, public speaking and responsible conduct of research. This research also provided new research opportunities for a young female Associate Professor at Oregon State University while on sabbatical. The PI was involved in extensive outreach to the broader community, through his frequent public lectures, numerous editorships and advisory board memberships, and service to university and external science and education initiatives.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/11/2023<br>      Modified by: Charles&nbsp;T&nbsp;Campbell</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Overview:  Better catalysts and electrocatalysts are essential for the efficient production and use of clean fuels, for energy efficient chemical synthesis with less environmental impact, for energy storage, for pollution abatement and for many other future technologies needed to achieve environmentally friendlier energy supply and chemical industry.  Crucial for rational design of better catalyst and electrocatalyst materials is the knowledge of the energies of elementary chemical reactions on late transition metal surfaces. Experiments are performed which measure the energetics of selected elementary chemical reactions occurring on late transition metal surfaces, carefully chosen to enable development of new theoretical methods for more accurately predicting such energies, to improve basic understanding of catalytic action and the effect of liquid solvents on these, and to facilitate the design of better catalysts and electrocatalysts. The main accomplishment of this research has been to broaden the database of reliable experimental energies of adsorbed catalytic intermediates (and effects of liquid solvents on these) that can be used by theoreticians as benchmarks to guide development of computational methods with improved accuracy for calculating the energetics of chemical reactions at late transition metal surfaces in both liquid and gas phase.   .   Intellectual Merit:  Fast computational methods like density functional theory (DFT) offer our greatest promise for designing new catalysts, electrocatalysts, and batteries and new processes for energy and environmental technologies. However, their power at achieving this would be multiplied many fold if these methods could be improved to achieve higher accuracy in calculating the energies of adsorbed reaction intermediates and the effects of liquid solvents on these energies. This would be transformative for catalysis research, enabling greater reliability in computational prediction of reaction rates and mechanisms.  Such improvement requires an accurate experimental database of adsorbate energies on a range of well-defined model catalyst surfaces, the effects of solvents on these energies, and the strengths of solvent bonding to well-defined catalyst surfaces. Developing such a database has been the main goal of this research program. In addition to guiding improvements in DFT, it will also help clarify the energetic basis for structure-reactivity correlations and solvent effects in transition metal catalysis and electrocatalysis. Specifically, the adsorption energies of several common adsorbed catalytic reaction intermediates have been measured by calorimetry on Cu(111) and Pt(111) in gas phase, for comparison to earlier results for these same adsorbates on Pt(111) and Ni(111). The adhesion energies of several liquid solvents to these metal surfaces were measured as well.  A theoretical model was developed whereby these can be combined with gas-phase adsorption energies to estimate solvent effects on adsorption energies of reaction intermediates. The measurements performed in this program cannot be performed anywhere else in the world, yet they have provided crucial input to improve accuracy of computational methods and enable substantial progress in understanding and computationally predicting the differences in activity and selectivity between different catalyst materials and different solvents.  Broader Impacts:   This research will aid in designing more efficient and environmentally-clean catalysts, electrocatalysts and processes for energy technologies and chemical industry, and for storing solar and wind energy, all crucial for sustainable living.  It has provided strong interdisciplinary, research-integrated education for numerous graduate and undergraduate students. These students got hands-on experience with state-of-the-art measurement instrumentation and learned to apply these to solve intellectually-challenging research problems on topics of great national interest. The students interacted with outstanding visiting scientists and researchers at national labs. They were mentored in scientific leadership, public speaking and responsible conduct of research. This research also provided new research opportunities for a young female Associate Professor at Oregon State University while on sabbatical. The PI was involved in extensive outreach to the broader community, through his frequent public lectures, numerous editorships and advisory board memberships, and service to university and external science and education initiatives.       Last Modified: 06/11/2023       Submitted by: Charles T Campbell]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
