<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Adapting to unsystematic variation in foreign-accented speech]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>143000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>143000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SMA</Abbreviation>
<LongName>SBE Off Of Multidisciplinary Activities</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Josie Welkom Miranda</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jwmirand@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927376</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This award was provided as part of NSF's Social, Behavioral and Economic Sciences (SBE) Postdoctoral Research Fellowships (SPRF) program and SBE's Linguistics program. The goal of the SPRF program is to prepare promising, early career doctoral-level scientists for scientific careers in academia, industry or private sector, and government. SPRF awards involve two years of training under the sponsorship of established scientists and encourage Postdoctoral Fellows to perform independent research. NSF seeks to promote the participation of scientists from all segments of the scientific community, including those from underrepresented groups, in its research programs and activities; the postdoctoral period is considered to be an important level of professional development in attaining this goal. Each Postdoctoral Fellow must address important scientific questions that advance their respective disciplinary fields. Under the sponsorship of Dr. Janet van Hell, Dr. Carrie Jackson, and Dr. Matthew Carlson at Penn State University, this postdoctoral fellowship award supports an early career scientist investigating how people adapt to foreign-accented pronunciation. Adaptation is the process by which listeners adjust to unfamiliar spoken sounds produced by an accented speaker. Existing research has shown that adaptation to accented speech often happens quickly and automatically. This project will extend such research to Mandarin Chinese. Mandarin is a lexical tone language that can use pitch patterns to differentiate syllables and words. Adult second language learners of Mandarin typically struggle to control and remember tones, leading them to make frequent tone errors. For listeners, these errors might affect adaptation to other aspects of foreign-accented Mandarin, either slowing their accommodation of accented pronunciation, or causing them to ignore all tones. This research may help us to understand why adaptation to accented speech sometimes fails to occur. By focusing on ways that second language pronunciation impacts listeners, this research also has the potential to inform language teachers and program administrators on how best to prioritize pronunciation in language training.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research addresses the occurrence of unsystematic tone errors within a foreign-accented speaker's Mandarin speech. Unsystematic tone errors are unpredictable for listeners in terms of both when and how they will occur. The focus on unsystematic pronunciation errors adds a critical dimension that must be accounted for in models of listener adaptation. Specifically, this project examines word recognition in native Mandarin listeners, by contrasting listener responses when a foreign-accented speaker produces frequent unsystematic tone errors compared to when a speaker produces few tone errors. Using a forced-choice word recognition paradigm, and measuring eye-movements during word recognition, two sets of experiments will test whether Mandarin listeners can ignore (i.e., down-weight) tones, and whether this down-weighting impacts the speed and outcome of word recognition. A further set of experiments will examine how previous experience teaching foreign language impacts listeners’ adaptive processes. Together, these experiments will shed light on accent adaption in tonal languages, and provide new insight into the importance of tonal accuracy in second language Mandarin speech. By involving language teachers directly in the research, the project has the potential to build bridges between laboratory science and classroom settings, which will lead to better informed language instructors, and may provide future opportunities to move scientific investigations into classrooms.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/06/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/06/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2004279</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Janet</FirstName>
<LastName>van Hell</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Janet van Hell</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<NSF_ID>000498478</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/06/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Eric</FirstName>
<LastName>Pelzl</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Eric Pelzl</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<NSF_ID>000683291</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/06/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Matthew</FirstName>
<LastName>Carlson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>T</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Matthew T Carlson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<NSF_ID>000112581</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/06/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Carrie</FirstName>
<LastName>Jackson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Carrie Jackson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<NSF_ID>000620440</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/06/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Pelzl                   Eric</Name>
<CityName>State College</CityName>
<ZipCode>168014545</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>15</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA15</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Penn State University]]></Name>
<CityName>University Park</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>168026203</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT/>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA"</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>040Y</Code>
<Text>(SPRF-FR) SBE Postdoctoral Res</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1311</Code>
<Text>Linguistics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7137</Code>
<Text>POSTDOCTORAL FELLOWSHIPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~143000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>As China&rsquo;s economic and political prominence in the world has grown, more people are studying Mandarin. Mandarin is a lexical tone language, where pitch differences between syllables can change the meaning of what is said. For example, the syllable &lsquo;shu&rsquo; spoken with a high pitch means &lsquo;book&rsquo;, but with a falling pitch means &lsquo;tree&rsquo;. Producing Mandarin with accurate tones is a challenge for many second language learners. As more people study Mandarin, there is an increasing need to understand the importance of tones for Chinese listeners&mdash;that is, the Chinese people who interact with second language speakers. If a second language speaker makes frequent tone errors, can listeners learn to ignore those errors? This research project investigated this question in a series of experiments.</p> <p>In order to understand whether Chinese listeners can learn to ignore tone errors in second language speech, we created an experimental situation where listeners would hear a speaker who made very frequent tone errors (75% of spoken words). This was contrasted with a speaker who made relatively few tone errors (25% of spoken words). By comparing how listeners responded to these two speakers during a word recognition task, we were able to measure the impact of tonal errors on their reliance on a speaker&rsquo;s tones. In our first experiment, we presented the speakers to listeners without any explanation. The pattern of results suggested that many listeners began to ignore the tones of the speaker who made frequent pronunciation errors. However, survey results carried out after the experiment suggested many listeners did not know that the speakers were second language learners. To make the identities of the speakers clear, in a second experiment, we showed listeners pictures of the speakers (who were clearly not Chinese) and also told them explicitly that the speakers were second language learners studying Chinese in a US college. Other than this change, the experiment was exactly the same. Once again, we found that listeners began to ignore the tones of the speaker who made more frequent tonal errors. Nevertheless, results were not entirely clear. In both of the first two experiments we found that listeners were only ignoring tones for some of the tones we tested (falling and low tones, but not high and rising tones). In a third experiment, we changed the words that listeners were exposed to so that we could determine whether only those specific tones were being ignored. Once again, we found the same pattern indicating that listeners would begin to ignore tones from a speaker who made frequent tone errors, but this time it affected different tones. Together these results demonstrate that when a speaker makes extremely frequent tone errors, and there is no additional context to help listeners make sense of the speech. They will start to ignore tones from that speaker.</p> <p>In the three experiments described above, the type of tonal errors that speakers made were unpredictable. The speaker might switch any one of the four Mandarin tones with any other tone. This is quite similar to the way we believe tone errors are made by second language speakers whose first language(s) are not tonal, because such speakers often forget or misremember the tones for specific Mandarin words. For people who have previous experience speaking a tonal language, their tonal errors may be of a different nature. They might tend to always switch one specific tone with another specific tone, for example, a falling tone might always be produced as a high-level tone. To investigate how listeners adapt to this type of speaker, we are currently carrying out a fourth experiment.</p> <p>Together, the experiments in this project have shed new light on whether and how Chinese listeners respond to tonal errors in spoken Mandarin. This line or research has pushed us to consider how people adapt to accented speech in languages with tones, which make up 40% or more of the world&rsquo;s extant languages, and are the first languages of a large portion of the world&rsquo;s population. Practically speaking, our study indicates that tones are an important feature of spoken language that second language speakers should not ignore&mdash;frequent tone errors may force listeners to start guessing at what words are intended. However, this is only a partial answer to the question how important are tones in second language speech. Future studies will need to consider how tones are used in contextualized speech.</p> <p>Results from our experiments have been shared at professional conferences, as well as in presentations to Chinese language teachers and second language learners, and will be available in a written publication in the near future. A chapter discussing findings in research on foreign-accented Chinese can be found in the book <em>The acquisition of Chinese as a second language pronunciation: Segments and prosody</em>.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/29/2022<br>      Modified by: Eric&nbsp;Pelzl</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ As China’s economic and political prominence in the world has grown, more people are studying Mandarin. Mandarin is a lexical tone language, where pitch differences between syllables can change the meaning of what is said. For example, the syllable ‘shu’ spoken with a high pitch means ‘book’, but with a falling pitch means ‘tree’. Producing Mandarin with accurate tones is a challenge for many second language learners. As more people study Mandarin, there is an increasing need to understand the importance of tones for Chinese listeners&mdash;that is, the Chinese people who interact with second language speakers. If a second language speaker makes frequent tone errors, can listeners learn to ignore those errors? This research project investigated this question in a series of experiments.  In order to understand whether Chinese listeners can learn to ignore tone errors in second language speech, we created an experimental situation where listeners would hear a speaker who made very frequent tone errors (75% of spoken words). This was contrasted with a speaker who made relatively few tone errors (25% of spoken words). By comparing how listeners responded to these two speakers during a word recognition task, we were able to measure the impact of tonal errors on their reliance on a speaker’s tones. In our first experiment, we presented the speakers to listeners without any explanation. The pattern of results suggested that many listeners began to ignore the tones of the speaker who made frequent pronunciation errors. However, survey results carried out after the experiment suggested many listeners did not know that the speakers were second language learners. To make the identities of the speakers clear, in a second experiment, we showed listeners pictures of the speakers (who were clearly not Chinese) and also told them explicitly that the speakers were second language learners studying Chinese in a US college. Other than this change, the experiment was exactly the same. Once again, we found that listeners began to ignore the tones of the speaker who made more frequent tonal errors. Nevertheless, results were not entirely clear. In both of the first two experiments we found that listeners were only ignoring tones for some of the tones we tested (falling and low tones, but not high and rising tones). In a third experiment, we changed the words that listeners were exposed to so that we could determine whether only those specific tones were being ignored. Once again, we found the same pattern indicating that listeners would begin to ignore tones from a speaker who made frequent tone errors, but this time it affected different tones. Together these results demonstrate that when a speaker makes extremely frequent tone errors, and there is no additional context to help listeners make sense of the speech. They will start to ignore tones from that speaker.  In the three experiments described above, the type of tonal errors that speakers made were unpredictable. The speaker might switch any one of the four Mandarin tones with any other tone. This is quite similar to the way we believe tone errors are made by second language speakers whose first language(s) are not tonal, because such speakers often forget or misremember the tones for specific Mandarin words. For people who have previous experience speaking a tonal language, their tonal errors may be of a different nature. They might tend to always switch one specific tone with another specific tone, for example, a falling tone might always be produced as a high-level tone. To investigate how listeners adapt to this type of speaker, we are currently carrying out a fourth experiment.  Together, the experiments in this project have shed new light on whether and how Chinese listeners respond to tonal errors in spoken Mandarin. This line or research has pushed us to consider how people adapt to accented speech in languages with tones, which make up 40% or more of the world’s extant languages, and are the first languages of a large portion of the world’s population. Practically speaking, our study indicates that tones are an important feature of spoken language that second language speakers should not ignore&mdash;frequent tone errors may force listeners to start guessing at what words are intended. However, this is only a partial answer to the question how important are tones in second language speech. Future studies will need to consider how tones are used in contextualized speech.  Results from our experiments have been shared at professional conferences, as well as in presentations to Chinese language teachers and second language learners, and will be available in a written publication in the near future. A chapter discussing findings in research on foreign-accented Chinese can be found in the book The acquisition of Chinese as a second language pronunciation: Segments and prosody.       Last Modified: 11/29/2022       Submitted by: Eric Pelzl]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
