<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Human-Centered, Augmented Intelligence Software for Water and Wastewater]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>224936.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>244936</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Peter Atherton</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>patherto@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928772</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project will result from development of augmented intelligence software improving planning and operational decisions for water and wastewater systems. The most challenging issues for water utilities include addressing aging infrastructure, adapting complex systems to changing regulations, and addressing the impacts of environmental change. They arise from interconnected infrastructure networks that interface with both the built and natural environment. Current artificial intelligence and machine learning solutions for water are narrowly defined for specific use cases. The proposed intelligence software will enable transformative changes in water management by seamless composition of hybrid models from simulators and data-driven models to overcome data and information silos, enabling decision-makers to integrate data in a system model that increases resilience at reduced customer costs. These improvements can lead to significant reductions in the roughly $4.7 B annual energy spend for water/wastewater, $50 B in combined sewer system programs, and up to $1 T in aging infrastructure needs.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project will develop methods for combining multi-fidelity simulation models and data-driven models to support decision-making for both long-term planning needs and real-time operational decision support for water and wastewater systems. Meta-modeling techniques for embedding physical system understanding from high-fidelity physics-based simulators to low-fidelity models will be evaluated. Accuracy and runtime tradeoffs will be evaluated for multiple reduced-order methods (e.g. linear and non-linear equations, projection-based methods) to enable more efficient optimization of large solution spaces. Domain applications include reduced-order versions of the St Venant equations for one-dimensional flow, and analytical solutions of biological, physical, and chemical processes in secondary wastewater treatment.  The project will evaluate multiple machine learning methods, including deep neural networks, reinforcement learning, random forest, support vector machines, and boosted learning algorithms, to detect patterns in observed data for near-term predictive power toward operational real-time decisions. Expert elicitation techniques will be used to quantify human expertise for subjective decision criteria, integrating valuable tacit human knowledge into the decision process. Meta-analysis of alternative hybrid modeling workflows will be evaluated to identify computationally efficient pathways to optimize complex planning challenges.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/06/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/18/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2004275</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mason</FirstName>
<LastName>Throneburg</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mason Throneburg</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mason@confluency.ai]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000814060</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/06/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>CONFLUENCY LLC</Name>
<CityName>CHICAGO</CityName>
<ZipCode>606404810</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3128606133</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4601 N MALDEN ST APT 3</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>KKFHDAYE5BN9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CONFLUENCY LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[CONFLUENCY LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>606404810</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4601 N Malden St, #3]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8091</Code>
<Text>SBIR Outreach &amp; Tech. Assist</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>6856</Code>
<Text>ARTIFICIAL INTELL &amp; COGNIT SCI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8032</Code>
<Text>Software Services and Applications</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~224936</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~20000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Execution of Confluency's Phase 1 SBIR award has deepened Confluency's understanding of water utility decision-support and digital transformation needs, and focused our research and innovation on a specific hybrid modeling approach (i.e., utility-specific problem formulation integrating machine learning and physics-based models) to support operational network optimization over a range of timescales. &nbsp;Participation in the SBIR bootcamp and Innovation-Corps program resulted in over 200 customer interviews, emphasizing the perceived value of advanced digital support tools for enhanced operational control and integrated planning, but also emphasizing the importance of explainability, efficient setup, change management, and cyber-security.</p> <p>Efficient setup and maintenance of operational decision support models was identified as an important enabler of customer adoption. Network simplification algorithms were defined to distil complex hydraulic networks into representative network topologies that serve specific operational and/or planning needs. This process led to an 88% reduction in the time required to develop the operational decision support network, and enables the simplification process to achieve specific levels of accuracy (calculated in reference to the high fidelity source model), with runtime and accuracy requirements varying by use-case. A range of machine learning algorithms and deep learning architectures were developed to provide flow and/or level forecasts at key hydraulic loading points of the system. These machine learning predictions together with the operational network (collectively termed a hybrid model) were then optimized for control decisions both under existing conditions and with alternative infrastructure in place. Results demonstrated the potential for a 29% reduction in sewage overflows through enhanced operations. These methods have applicability across a range of time-scales, including strategic planning horizons for increasing system resilience to changing climate, and risk-informed decision support under uncertainty.</p> <p>The augmented intelligence software that will utilize the technical findings from Phase 1 will assist engineers and operators to improve planning and operational decisions for better managing the nation's water and wastewater systems.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/27/2022<br>      Modified by: Mason&nbsp;Throneburg</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2004275/2004275_10682817_1643258903785_SBIR_P1_Research__Outcomes--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2004275/2004275_10682817_1643258903785_SBIR_P1_Research__Outcomes--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Collated Findings"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2004275/2004275_10682817_1643258903785_SBIR_P1_Research__Outcomes--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Collated Findings"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Prototpe dashboard developed for Utility partner MWRDGC showing the findings of the P1 outcomes as it relates to the WWTP Secondary Aeration Optimization blower requirements</div> <div class="imageCredit">Own Image</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Mason&nbsp;Throneburg</div> <div class="imageTitle">Collated Findings</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Execution of Confluency's Phase 1 SBIR award has deepened Confluency's understanding of water utility decision-support and digital transformation needs, and focused our research and innovation on a specific hybrid modeling approach (i.e., utility-specific problem formulation integrating machine learning and physics-based models) to support operational network optimization over a range of timescales.  Participation in the SBIR bootcamp and Innovation-Corps program resulted in over 200 customer interviews, emphasizing the perceived value of advanced digital support tools for enhanced operational control and integrated planning, but also emphasizing the importance of explainability, efficient setup, change management, and cyber-security.  Efficient setup and maintenance of operational decision support models was identified as an important enabler of customer adoption. Network simplification algorithms were defined to distil complex hydraulic networks into representative network topologies that serve specific operational and/or planning needs. This process led to an 88% reduction in the time required to develop the operational decision support network, and enables the simplification process to achieve specific levels of accuracy (calculated in reference to the high fidelity source model), with runtime and accuracy requirements varying by use-case. A range of machine learning algorithms and deep learning architectures were developed to provide flow and/or level forecasts at key hydraulic loading points of the system. These machine learning predictions together with the operational network (collectively termed a hybrid model) were then optimized for control decisions both under existing conditions and with alternative infrastructure in place. Results demonstrated the potential for a 29% reduction in sewage overflows through enhanced operations. These methods have applicability across a range of time-scales, including strategic planning horizons for increasing system resilience to changing climate, and risk-informed decision support under uncertainty.  The augmented intelligence software that will utilize the technical findings from Phase 1 will assist engineers and operators to improve planning and operational decisions for better managing the nation's water and wastewater systems.       Last Modified: 01/27/2022       Submitted by: Mason Throneburg]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
