<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBP: Can Teachers' "Psychological Affordances" Broaden Participation in Math and Science?]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>138000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>138000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SMA</Abbreviation>
<LongName>SBE Off Of Multidisciplinary Activities</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Josie Welkom Miranda</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jwmirand@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927376</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This award was provided as part of NSF's Social, Behavioral and Economic Sciences (SBE) Postdoctoral Research Fellowships (SPRF) program and SBE's Science of Broadening Participation program. The goal of the SPRF program is to prepare promising, early career doctoral-level scientists for scientific careers in academia, industry or private sector, and government. SPRF awards involve two years of training under the sponsorship of established scientists and encourage Postdoctoral Fellows to perform independent research. NSF seeks to promote the participation of scientists from all segments of the scientific community, including those from underrepresented groups, in its research programs and activities; the postdoctoral period is considered to be an important level of professional development in attaining this goal. Each Postdoctoral Fellow must address important scientific questions that advance their respective disciplinary fields. Under the sponsorship of Dr. David Yeager at The University of Texas at Austin, this postdoctoral fellowship award supports an early career scientist investigating how teachers’ practices can support (or undermine) high-school students’ growth mindsets, the role of these practices in shaping students’ long-term persistence in the STEM pipeline, and the implications of these practices for broadening participation in STEM for underrepresented students. Many 9th grade students fail to progress to the 10th grade math courses that would keep them on track to graduate with a strong portfolio of math and science courses. Students with a growth mindset – the belief that academic ability is not fixed and can improve – are more likely to seek academic challenges and may therefore complete more advanced math and science courses throughout high school. Growth-mindset beliefs may be especially beneficial for students of color and students from working-class backgrounds (termed underrepresented here), who face barriers to success in these fields. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Two factors may promote a growth mindset in 9th grade math courses: (a) exposure to a teacher's growth-affording practices, which reinforce and reward growth-oriented behavior, and (b) receipt of a growth-mindset intervention, which employs attitude-change techniques to facilitate adoption of growth-mindset beliefs. In addition, these factors may interact: growth-mindset interventions may be more powerful when complemented by teacher practices that reinforce the message. By encouraging students to seek academic challenges, growth-affording practices and growth-mindset interventions may propel students to take more advanced math and science courses through 12th grade. The proposed research has the following objectives: (a) to test whether growth-affording practices affect 9th grade students' challenge-seeking predisposition and subsequent course taking, (b) to test whether these practices moderate growth-mindset intervention effects on these outcomes, and (c) to investigate how these practices alter intervention effects. To address these objectives, the PI will first conduct secondary analyses of the National Study of Learning Mindsets, a nationally-representative randomized-controlled trial of a growth-mindset intervention. These analyses will assess the effects of teachers' growth-affording practices, provision of a growth-mindset intervention, and their interaction on math and science course taking through 12th grade, and examine whether such effects are driven by changes to students' challenge-seeking predisposition. Second, the PI will manipulate growth-affording practices and provision of a growth-mindset intervention in a laboratory study to test the causal effects of these practices on students' challenge seeking. In each of these studies, the PI will test whether promoting a growth mindset is more beneficial for underrepresented students. Together, these studies will address pressing questions about experiences that promote growth mindsets, and how these experiences can promote preparation to enter the STEM fields in college. In addition, these studies will inform the development of teacher professional development activities and help determine the contextual conditions necessary for growth-mindset interventions to be effective.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/30/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/30/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2004831</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Yeager</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David S Yeager</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<NSF_ID>000639699</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/30/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Cameron</FirstName>
<LastName>Hecht</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Cameron A Hecht</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<NSF_ID>000808324</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/30/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Hecht, Cameron A</Name>
<CityName>Madison</CityName>
<ZipCode>537034781</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[The University of Texas at Austin]]></Name>
<CityName>Austin</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>787121699</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>25</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX25</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>110y</Code>
<Text>SBP-Science of Broadening Part</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8208</Code>
<Text>SPRF-Broadening Participation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7137</Code>
<Text>POSTDOCTORAL FELLOWSHIPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8050</Code>
<Text>Science of Broadening Participation</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~138000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The objective of this research was to investigate the role of teachers in creating classroom cultures that support (or undermine) students&rsquo; ability to benefit from their growth mindset beliefs (i.e., that intellectual abilities can be developed). A series of four scenario experiments indicated that teachers&rsquo; growth mindset-supportive practices enable students to make learning-oriented choices that are consistent with their growth mindset beliefs. Across the four studies, students&rsquo; growth mindset beliefs were positively associated with making learning-oriented choices in the context of a teacher whose messages (i.e., what they said) and opportunities (i.e., their policies) were consistent with a growth mindset, but not with a teacher whose messages and opportunities supported a fixed mindset (i.e., that intellectual abilities are fixed). This pattern replicated in a nationally representative panel of adolescents, was found to be strongest when both messages and opportunities supported the growth mindset, and was not attributable to the warmth of the hypothetical teachers&rsquo; demeanors.</p> <p>Building on these studies, we developed an intervention that successfully motivated high-school teachers to adopt growth mindset-supportive classroom practices. The intervention used a &ldquo;values-aligned&rdquo; approach that helped teachers to see these practices as a means of achieving a core value. We tested the intervention in a large randomized controlled trial and found positive average effects on end-of-year pass rates and course grades, with substantially larger effects in classrooms with a high proportion of students from lower socioeconomic status (SES) backgrounds, reducing inequality in these achievement outcomes. This research provided a causal demonstration of the impact of teachers&rsquo; affordances for the growth mindset in the field.</p> <p>Initial follow-up analyses of the National Study of Learning Mindsets (NSLM) indicate that 9<sup>th</sup> grade students&rsquo; growth mindset beliefs and perceptions of their 9<sup>th</sup> grade math teachers&rsquo; growth mindset beliefs jointly contribute to their subsequent enrollment in college up to seven years post-intervention, with larger associations among students from lower-SES backgrounds. These findings suggest that math teachers may play a meaningful role in whether and to what degree students benefit from their personal growth mindset beliefs at the transition to high school.</p> <p>These findings have implications for educational strategies to promote equitable academic outcomes. First, this work sheds light on the specific teacher practices (e.g., communication practices, grading policies) that support students&rsquo; growth mindsets, which can be directly useful to teachers and help to inform future teacher training efforts. Second, this research demonstrates a method for motivating teachers to adopt growth mindset-supportive practices, which can be useful for professional development purposes. Finally, this research suggests that future growth mindset-based approaches to promoting equitable outcomes may be most successful when they target both students and teachers.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/20/2023<br>      Modified by: Cameron&nbsp;A&nbsp;Hecht</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The objective of this research was to investigate the role of teachers in creating classroom cultures that support (or undermine) students’ ability to benefit from their growth mindset beliefs (i.e., that intellectual abilities can be developed). A series of four scenario experiments indicated that teachers’ growth mindset-supportive practices enable students to make learning-oriented choices that are consistent with their growth mindset beliefs. Across the four studies, students’ growth mindset beliefs were positively associated with making learning-oriented choices in the context of a teacher whose messages (i.e., what they said) and opportunities (i.e., their policies) were consistent with a growth mindset, but not with a teacher whose messages and opportunities supported a fixed mindset (i.e., that intellectual abilities are fixed). This pattern replicated in a nationally representative panel of adolescents, was found to be strongest when both messages and opportunities supported the growth mindset, and was not attributable to the warmth of the hypothetical teachers’ demeanors.  Building on these studies, we developed an intervention that successfully motivated high-school teachers to adopt growth mindset-supportive classroom practices. The intervention used a "values-aligned" approach that helped teachers to see these practices as a means of achieving a core value. We tested the intervention in a large randomized controlled trial and found positive average effects on end-of-year pass rates and course grades, with substantially larger effects in classrooms with a high proportion of students from lower socioeconomic status (SES) backgrounds, reducing inequality in these achievement outcomes. This research provided a causal demonstration of the impact of teachers’ affordances for the growth mindset in the field.  Initial follow-up analyses of the National Study of Learning Mindsets (NSLM) indicate that 9th grade students’ growth mindset beliefs and perceptions of their 9th grade math teachers’ growth mindset beliefs jointly contribute to their subsequent enrollment in college up to seven years post-intervention, with larger associations among students from lower-SES backgrounds. These findings suggest that math teachers may play a meaningful role in whether and to what degree students benefit from their personal growth mindset beliefs at the transition to high school.  These findings have implications for educational strategies to promote equitable academic outcomes. First, this work sheds light on the specific teacher practices (e.g., communication practices, grading policies) that support students’ growth mindsets, which can be directly useful to teachers and help to inform future teacher training efforts. Second, this research demonstrates a method for motivating teachers to adopt growth mindset-supportive practices, which can be useful for professional development purposes. Finally, this research suggests that future growth mindset-based approaches to promoting equitable outcomes may be most successful when they target both students and teachers.       Last Modified: 07/20/2023       Submitted by: Cameron A Hecht]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
