<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBP: Harnessing Latinx Parents' Math Support to Increase Adolescents' Math Motivation and Achievement]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>138000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>138000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SMA</Abbreviation>
<LongName>SBE Off Of Multidisciplinary Activities</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Josie Welkom Miranda</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jwmirand@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927376</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This award was provided as part of NSF's Social, Behavioral and Economic Sciences (SBE) Postdoctoral Research Fellowships (SPRF) program and SBE's Science of Broadening Participation program. The goal of the SPRF program is to prepare promising, early career doctoral-level scientists for scientific careers in academia, industry or private sector, and government. SPRF awards involve two years of training under the sponsorship of established scientists and encourage Postdoctoral Fellows to perform independent research. NSF seeks to promote the participation of scientists from all segments of the scientific community, including those from underrepresented groups, in its research programs and activities; the postdoctoral period is considered to be an important level of professional development in attaining this goal. Each Postdoctoral Fellow must address important scientific questions that advance their respective disciplinary fields. Under the sponsorship of Dr. Sandra D. Simpkins at the University of California, Irvine, this postdoctoral fellowship award supports an early career scientist examining how Latinx families and organized after-school activities (ASAs) can build partnerships to foster students’ math motivation and achievement. Youths’ math achievement and motivation in middle school is a critical gateway to STEM aspirations and pursuits in high school and college. However, many Latinx and underrepresented minority youth turn away from STEM pursuits because they perceive math to be too challenging or unimportant to their lives. Adolescents need to have positive experiences in educational contexts that boost their interests, values, and ongoing mastery. Family environments and ASAs are informal educational settings that extend what youths are learning in school, which is particularly important for Latinx youth attending lower-quality schools. As ASAs increasingly put forth initiatives to increase parent involvement in Latinx youths’ education, successful partnerships between families and ASAs hinges on leveraging Latinx families’ cultural funds of knowledge and parents’ culturally-grounded support in math and STEM more broadly. These funds of knowledge can provide vital insights to how ASAs can make math and STEM relevant to youths’ lives and may help parents further enhance their math support at home. This project seeks to understand how Latinx parents’ support their adolescents in math and uncover the ways in which ASAs can better leverage Latinx parents’ cultural funds of knowledge to maximally increase youths’ competence and motivation in math. By studying how ASAs can harness parents’ math support to increase youths’ math motivation and achievement, this project hopes to bolster family-ASA partnerships to effect positive educational success among Latinx youths.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project seeks to understand Latinx parents’ cultural funds of knowledge in math; identify opportunities for ASAs to enhance their math support; develop a reliable, valid measure of Latinx parents’ math support that captures a more complete and culturally-grounded set of parental behaviors; and examine the links between parents’ math supports and youths’ math motivation and performance. To accomplish these research aims, data will be collected from both parents and youth participants of a math ASA through mixed methods approaches, including surveys and in-depth qualitative interviews. Study findings will guide efforts by researchers and ASA leaders to develop practical, cost-effective resources aimed at enhancing parents’ math support. The integration of basic and applied approaches will extend substantive knowledge on family influences within Latinx communities and provide vital, enriching information that illuminates the effective ways in which parents and ASAs may reciprocally inform one another to improve youths’ math motivation and achievement.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/19/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/19/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2004278</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nestor</FirstName>
<LastName>Tulagan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME>Jr</PI_SUFX_NAME>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nestor B Tulagan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<NSF_ID>000814656</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/19/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sandra</FirstName>
<LastName>Simpkins</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sandra Simpkins</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<NSF_ID>000528756</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/19/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Tulagan, Nestor B</Name>
<CityName>IRVINE</CityName>
<ZipCode>92617</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>47</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA47</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California, Irvine]]></Name>
<CityName>IRVINE</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>926173122</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>47</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA47</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>110y</Code>
<Text>SBP-Science of Broadening Part</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8208</Code>
<Text>SPRF-Broadening Participation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7137</Code>
<Text>POSTDOCTORAL FELLOWSHIPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8050</Code>
<Text>Science of Broadening Participation</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~138000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Globalization of the science/engineering workforce has spurred increased opportunities in science, technology, engineering and math (STEM) careers in the United States (US). The opportunity for social and economic advancement is especially important for underrepresented minority (URM) individuals, like &nbsp;Latinx adolescents, whose underrepresentation in STEM persists today. So, it is imperative to find practical pathways that can empower Latinx students to pursue STEM. Family support are vital yet often overlooked resources that shape adolescents&rsquo; STEM motivation and performance. Latinx parents are highly involved and use various strategies to help adolescents in their academic pursuits. Many of these behaviors are cultural practices that are central within Latinx families and may be key to supporting adolescents&rsquo; academic development. Yet, these culturally grounded assets are often ignored in research, as studies typically use frameworks based on knowledge gained from middle-class, White families. Additionally, many adolescents face challenges in STEM subjects like math, and parents encounter challenges when supporting their children. Yet, the ways in which Latinx parents respond to math challenges they and their adolescents face is understudied but has the potentially to provide insight into the ways to enhance Latinx parents&rsquo; support and adolescents&rsquo; achievement. Hence, gaining a more comprehensive inventory of Latinx parents&rsquo; math support in is important to understand family academic socialization processes within Latinx families. To address these gaps, this project had two overarching research aims: to document a more comprehensive understanding of the content and impacts of Latinx parents&rsquo; math support math; and to understand specific ways to enhance Latinx parents&rsquo; math support at home. Below we highlight the most relevant contributions of the project.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The first project aimed to get a more <strong>challenges contextualized understanding of the Latinx parents face when supporting adolescents in math.</strong> Beyond focusing on challenges, we also examined the strategies parents used to respond to these math support challenges. Findings showed that Latinx parents&rsquo; challenges went beyond those that are typically documented in research (e.g., lower knowledge, language gap, conflicting obligation). We found, for example, other challenges like problems navigating educational technologies used in schools and during the COVID-19 pandemic (e.g., remote learning, school websites). Furthermore, we found that parents responded to these challenges in varied ways, encompassing strategies like knowledge- and skill-building and using accessible resources. One contribution of this project is the finding that parents used certain strategies for specific challenges, illustrating how Latinx parents&rsquo; thoughtfully adapt to specific challenges. For example, parents also provided their children learning materials and spaces and used digital tools (e.g., YouTube, learning apps) to address lower math knowledge, language gap, and conflicting obligations. Finally, parents expressed wishes to build their knowledge and skills to address lower math knowledge, language gaps, and technological difficulties. Overall, extending prior studies, these findings provide insights into a fuller set of challenges Latinx parents encountered and the varied, purposeful ways parent adaptively respond to math support challenges.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Building on the first project, the second project focused on <strong>challenges that Latinx adolescents faced in their math learning and the ways in which their parents helped them overcome these challenges. </strong>This project aimed to extend prior works on how parents&rsquo; STEM support by specifically focusing on when adolescents faced math challenges. Latinx parents perceived a diverse array of math challenges including lower motivation, engagement, and performance, as well as understudied challenges like interpersonal issues with math teachers and non-ideal learning environments brought on by the COVID-19 pandemic (e.g., remote learning). We also found that Latinx parents responded to adolescents&rsquo; lower math motivation, engagement, and performance by working with adolescents, seeking help, using digital tools, and providing materials. Moreover, parents primarily used provision of materials and educational discussions to help adolescents overcome issues with math teachers and non-ideal learning environments. Overall, these findings have practical implications for practitioners and researchers when designing efforts to help Latinx parents promote adolescents&rsquo; STEM motivational beliefs.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Highlighting the perspectives of Latinx parents, this project uncovered notable areas where educators can help eliminate STEM challenges faced by adolescents and families, enhance family support, and promote Latinx adolescents&rsquo; STEM motivation. For example, efforts to enhance family support may benefit from consider the strategies parents already employ, including culturally-grounded (e.g., seeking help) and relatively understudied (e.g., using tools) strategies. Moreover, tailoring solutions based on what parents generate themselves, like knowledge- and skill-building in math, are paramount to empower Latinx families against the challenges they face. In addition to presentations to academic audiences, we have disseminated our research findings to local Latinx families in Orange County, CA via knowledge-building booklets and inquiry-based family workshops. We are also publishing empirical articles to academic journals. Finally, the project provided the postdoctoral fellow, as well as doctoral and undergraduate students, with opportunities to gain vital skills for the next phase of their careers (e.g., qualitative and quantitative methods, university-community partnerships).</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/30/2022<br>      Modified by: Nestor&nbsp;B&nbsp;Tulagan</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Globalization of the science/engineering workforce has spurred increased opportunities in science, technology, engineering and math (STEM) careers in the United States (US). The opportunity for social and economic advancement is especially important for underrepresented minority (URM) individuals, like  Latinx adolescents, whose underrepresentation in STEM persists today. So, it is imperative to find practical pathways that can empower Latinx students to pursue STEM. Family support are vital yet often overlooked resources that shape adolescents’ STEM motivation and performance. Latinx parents are highly involved and use various strategies to help adolescents in their academic pursuits. Many of these behaviors are cultural practices that are central within Latinx families and may be key to supporting adolescents’ academic development. Yet, these culturally grounded assets are often ignored in research, as studies typically use frameworks based on knowledge gained from middle-class, White families. Additionally, many adolescents face challenges in STEM subjects like math, and parents encounter challenges when supporting their children. Yet, the ways in which Latinx parents respond to math challenges they and their adolescents face is understudied but has the potentially to provide insight into the ways to enhance Latinx parents’ support and adolescents’ achievement. Hence, gaining a more comprehensive inventory of Latinx parents’ math support in is important to understand family academic socialization processes within Latinx families. To address these gaps, this project had two overarching research aims: to document a more comprehensive understanding of the content and impacts of Latinx parents’ math support math; and to understand specific ways to enhance Latinx parents’ math support at home. Below we highlight the most relevant contributions of the project.     The first project aimed to get a more challenges contextualized understanding of the Latinx parents face when supporting adolescents in math. Beyond focusing on challenges, we also examined the strategies parents used to respond to these math support challenges. Findings showed that Latinx parents’ challenges went beyond those that are typically documented in research (e.g., lower knowledge, language gap, conflicting obligation). We found, for example, other challenges like problems navigating educational technologies used in schools and during the COVID-19 pandemic (e.g., remote learning, school websites). Furthermore, we found that parents responded to these challenges in varied ways, encompassing strategies like knowledge- and skill-building and using accessible resources. One contribution of this project is the finding that parents used certain strategies for specific challenges, illustrating how Latinx parents’ thoughtfully adapt to specific challenges. For example, parents also provided their children learning materials and spaces and used digital tools (e.g., YouTube, learning apps) to address lower math knowledge, language gap, and conflicting obligations. Finally, parents expressed wishes to build their knowledge and skills to address lower math knowledge, language gaps, and technological difficulties. Overall, extending prior studies, these findings provide insights into a fuller set of challenges Latinx parents encountered and the varied, purposeful ways parent adaptively respond to math support challenges.     Building on the first project, the second project focused on challenges that Latinx adolescents faced in their math learning and the ways in which their parents helped them overcome these challenges. This project aimed to extend prior works on how parents’ STEM support by specifically focusing on when adolescents faced math challenges. Latinx parents perceived a diverse array of math challenges including lower motivation, engagement, and performance, as well as understudied challenges like interpersonal issues with math teachers and non-ideal learning environments brought on by the COVID-19 pandemic (e.g., remote learning). We also found that Latinx parents responded to adolescents’ lower math motivation, engagement, and performance by working with adolescents, seeking help, using digital tools, and providing materials. Moreover, parents primarily used provision of materials and educational discussions to help adolescents overcome issues with math teachers and non-ideal learning environments. Overall, these findings have practical implications for practitioners and researchers when designing efforts to help Latinx parents promote adolescents’ STEM motivational beliefs.     Highlighting the perspectives of Latinx parents, this project uncovered notable areas where educators can help eliminate STEM challenges faced by adolescents and families, enhance family support, and promote Latinx adolescents’ STEM motivation. For example, efforts to enhance family support may benefit from consider the strategies parents already employ, including culturally-grounded (e.g., seeking help) and relatively understudied (e.g., using tools) strategies. Moreover, tailoring solutions based on what parents generate themselves, like knowledge- and skill-building in math, are paramount to empower Latinx families against the challenges they face. In addition to presentations to academic audiences, we have disseminated our research findings to local Latinx families in Orange County, CA via knowledge-building booklets and inquiry-based family workshops. We are also publishing empirical articles to academic journals. Finally, the project provided the postdoctoral fellow, as well as doctoral and undergraduate students, with opportunities to gain vital skills for the next phase of their careers (e.g., qualitative and quantitative methods, university-community partnerships).          Last Modified: 12/30/2022       Submitted by: Nestor B Tulagan]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
