<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[1st COFI Workshop on the Intersection Between Dark Matter and Neurtrinos]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>14963.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>14963</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>William Wester</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>wwester@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924677</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This award will provide support for the "1st COFI Workshop on the Intersection Between Dark Matter and Neutrinos.” It will be held January 24-26, 2020 in Old San Juan, Puerto Rico, at the headquarters of the Colegio de Física Fundamental e Interdisciplinaria de las Américas (COFI) institute. The goal of this workshop is to discuss the challenges of research at the intersection between dark matter and non-accelerator based neutrino physics -- topics at the forefront of several fields.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The workshop has a particular focus on early career scientists and graduate students, including local (based in Puerto Rico) scientists and graduate students, and it will provide participant travel support for a fraction of PhD students and junior postdocs travelling domestically or internationally to enable them to participate in the workshop. The speakers will consist of top scientists, postdoctoral researchers and PhD students in physics in North America, Latin America and Europe. Priority will be given to female and junior talented individuals. This conference will be attended by a significant number of scientists belonging to under-represented minority groups. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The nature of the research covered by the workshop requires an interdisciplinary approach involving novel instrumentation and analysis and theoretical development, as well as inputs from particle physics, nuclear and atomic physics, astrophysics, cosmology, and computational science. The objective of the workshop is to bring these groups together -- not only to discuss current results and ongoing research, but also to develop a long-term collaboration scheme to further advance the interdisciplinary nature of this area and how to train the next generation to work across fields from the very beginning.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/23/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/23/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2004425</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mayda</FirstName>
<LastName>Velasco</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mayda M Velasco</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[m-velasco@northwestern.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000484715</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/23/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Enectali</FirstName>
<LastName>Figueroa-Feliciano</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Enectali Figueroa-Feliciano</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[enectali@northwestern.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000484720</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/23/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Northwestern University</Name>
<CityName>EVANSTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>602080001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3125037955</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>633 CLARK STREET</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>EXZVPWZBLUE8</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORTHWESTERN UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[COFI]]></Name>
<CityName>San Juan</CityName>
<StateCode>PR</StateCode>
<ZipCode>009011208</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[254 Norzagary Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Puerto Rico</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PR00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1221</Code>
<Text>HEP-High Energy Physics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1234</Code>
<Text>NUCLEAR PRECISION MEASUREMENTS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7235</Code>
<Text>Particle Astrophysics/Undergro</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7621</Code>
<Text>PHYSICS-BROADEN PARTICIPATION</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7483</Code>
<Text>PHYSICS OF THE UNIVERSE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~14963</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>We know that the Standard Model of Particle physics, although incredibly accurate at predicting particle interactions, is incomplete. The Standard Model does not predict the existence of Dark Matter, nor explain why neutrinos have mass. Understanding the structure of particle physics beyond the Standard Model is the most pressing question in particle physics today.&nbsp;</p> <p>Neutrinos are the only known particles that exhibit behavior not predicted by the Standard Model. Dark Matter makes up most of the matter in the Universe, and it is believed that Dark Matter is a new fundamental particle that has yet to be discovered. Both neutrinos and Dark Matter are extremely hard to detect, and advances in detector technology as well as new theory work have brought these two fields closer together. It is likely that the key to physics beyond the Standard Model likes somewhere in the intersection of these two particles, and this is the topic we wish to explore in the workshop proposed in this grant.</p> <p>The proposal was to hold a workshop in San Juan, Puerto Rico on topics in the Intersection between Dark Matter and Neutrino physics. Unfortunately the logistics problems due to the ongoing pandemic made it impossible for us to hold the in-person conference. We strongly believe that holding the conference in person is a necessary element for the success of the conference. Many of the attendies will be students, especially from Puerto Rico, and the chance to interact and network with the speakers in-person is a particualr objective of this conference.&nbsp;</p> <div class="accomplishments bottomBorder"> <div class="tinyMCEContent"> <p>We appreciate the continued support we have received by the NSF, and hope to be able to hold an in-person conference in the summer of 2023.</p> </div> <p>&nbsp;</p> </div><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/21/2022<br>      Modified by: Enectali&nbsp;Figueroa-Feliciano</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ We know that the Standard Model of Particle physics, although incredibly accurate at predicting particle interactions, is incomplete. The Standard Model does not predict the existence of Dark Matter, nor explain why neutrinos have mass. Understanding the structure of particle physics beyond the Standard Model is the most pressing question in particle physics today.   Neutrinos are the only known particles that exhibit behavior not predicted by the Standard Model. Dark Matter makes up most of the matter in the Universe, and it is believed that Dark Matter is a new fundamental particle that has yet to be discovered. Both neutrinos and Dark Matter are extremely hard to detect, and advances in detector technology as well as new theory work have brought these two fields closer together. It is likely that the key to physics beyond the Standard Model likes somewhere in the intersection of these two particles, and this is the topic we wish to explore in the workshop proposed in this grant.  The proposal was to hold a workshop in San Juan, Puerto Rico on topics in the Intersection between Dark Matter and Neutrino physics. Unfortunately the logistics problems due to the ongoing pandemic made it impossible for us to hold the in-person conference. We strongly believe that holding the conference in person is a necessary element for the success of the conference. Many of the attendies will be students, especially from Puerto Rico, and the chance to interact and network with the speakers in-person is a particualr objective of this conference.     We appreciate the continued support we have received by the NSF, and hope to be able to hold an in-person conference in the summer of 2023.            Last Modified: 07/21/2022       Submitted by: Enectali Figueroa-Feliciano]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
