<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Label-Free, High-Time Resolution, Single-Molecule Studies of RNA Folding and Dynamics]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>540000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>540000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Pumtiwitt McCarthy</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>pmccarth@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032920000</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[RNA is a class of biosynthetic molecules that plays central roles in gene expression, the process of using the genetic information stored in DNA to make functional proteins. How RNAs function in gene expression is dependent on their specific and complex three-dimensional shapes or structures and on their ability to undergo precisely timed and executed structural changes (their dynamic rearrangements). With this award, the Chemistry of Life Processes Program in the Chemistry Division is funding Dr. Ruben Gonzalez and Dr. Colin Nuckolls from Columbia University to study how RNAs fold and/or undergo structural rearrangements and how the dynamics of a particular RNA structural ‘switch’ controls the expression of a human gene. Drs. Gonzalez’s and Nuckolls’ research team uses carbon nanotube-based field-effect transistors (smFETs) to follow the detailed dynamics of individual RNA molecules in three-dimensional space and across time. Notably, the smFET method allows the study of RNA dynamics without the need to chemically modify the RNA or apply invasive external forces. A deeper understanding of how RNA-based structural switches function to control gene expression impacts the discovery and development of therapeutics that act on important biomolecular targets and/or functions. In addition, the project increases participation by women and underrepresented minorities in STEM by leveraging existing outreach programs in New York City. Kits are developed to demonstrate nucleic acid structures and single-molecule biophysics in K-12 community outreach, while education modules are developed to teach integrated concepts of chemistry, biology, and computer science at local high schools. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Using smFETs, Drs. Gonzalez’s and Nuckolls’ research team investigate the kinetic mechanisms with which RNA stem-loops, a fundamental class of RNA structures, fold and undergo functionally important, dynamic structural rearrangements at unparalleled molecular, spatial, and temporal resolutions. The resulting model is used to determine the mechanism through which the naturally occurring, post-transcriptional methylation of the N6 position of an adenosine in the stem of a RNA stem-loop found within a human precursor messenger RNA (pre-mRNA) regulates the dynamics of this RNA stem-loop as a means for controlling the splicing of the pre-mRNA. Specifically, the proposed studies characterize the folding and dynamics of this stem-loop and tests the hypothesis that the post-transcriptional, N6 methylation of the adenosine alters the dynamics of the stem-loop (i.e., throws the ‘switch’ on) so as to unmask the binding site of an RNA-binding protein that directs the differential splicing of the pre-mRNA. The results of these studies provide a general model for the function of RNA stem-loop based conformational switches and a detailed understanding of the mechanism through which a post-transcriptional modification of a stem-loop controls the alternative splicing of a pre-mRNA.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/29/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/29/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2004016</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Colin</FirstName>
<LastName>Nuckolls</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Colin Nuckolls</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[cn37@columbia.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000368874</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/29/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ruben</FirstName>
<LastName>Gonzalez</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ruben L Gonzalez</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[rlg2118@columbia.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000483041</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/29/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Columbia University</Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<ZipCode>10027</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2128546851</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>202 LOW LIBRARY 535 W 116 ST MC</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>F4N1QNPB95M4</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF COLUMBIA UNIVERSITY IN THE CITY OF NEW YORK, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>F4N1QNPB95M4</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Columbia University]]></Name>
<CityName>New York</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>100277922</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3000 Broadway]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6883</Code>
<Text>Chemistry of Life Processes</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~540000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This award encompassed four outcomes:&nbsp;</p> <ul> <li>We adapted and optimized a new technology we had invented and developed under a previous NSF award, single-molecule field effect transistors (smFETs), for use in studies of the mechanisms through which RNA molecules fold and undergo changes in their three-dimensional structures. smFETs are nanoscopic electronic devices that produce a conductance signal that is sensitive to the three-dimensional structure of an individual, electrostatically charged polymer (e.g., an RNA biopolymer) that is tethered to its surface. By monitoring how the conductance of an smFETs harboring a single, surface-tethered RNA molecule changes as a function of time, one can investigate the folding or conformational changes of that RNA at an unprecedented hundreds-to-thousands of microseconds time resolution.</li> </ul> <ul> <li>Using these smFET devices that we optimized for measurements of RNA folding and conformational changes, we characterized the folding of a set of RNA molecules encompassing the most fundamental unit of RNA structure, RNA stem-loops. Stem-loops are elements of RNA structure that fold in the hundreds-to-thousands of microseconds timescale and have important biological functions such serving as building blocks for much larger and complex RNA structures, biological &lsquo;switches&rsquo; that can alternate between two or more conformations, and/or as sites for the binding of RNA-binding proteins. To our knowledge, the studies completed under this award represent the highest-time-resolution investigations of the folding of individual RNA molecules that have been reported. Among other important new research directions our studies create, they bridge a longstanding, crucial gap between experimental and computational studies of RNA folding and conformational changes.</li> </ul> <ul> <li>In order to analyze single-molecule time series data in general, and the high time-resolution, long-observation-time conductance <em>versus</em> time trajectories that are generated by smFETs specifically, we developed new single-molecule time series modeling tools and implemented them in a new software platform that we call <span style="text-decoration: underline;">t</span>ime-series <span style="text-decoration: underline;">M</span>odeling, <span style="text-decoration: underline;">A</span>nalysis, and <span style="text-decoration: underline;">V</span>isualization <span style="text-decoration: underline;">EN</span>vironment (tMAVEN). This software platform is described in a publication, is open source, and has been made freely available to the research community via a GitHub repository.</li> </ul> <ul> <li>In order to increase the diversity of graduate student researchers participating in this and related, NSF-funded studies in their laboratory and department, the PI has been a leader in establishing and maintaining a departmental presence at the Society for the Advancement of Chicanos/Latinx and Native Americans in Science (SACNAS) annual meeting and the Annual Biomedical Research Conference for Minoritized Scientists (ABRCMS). These meetings have served to increase the diversity of prospective graduate students who apply to our graduate programs and all of the personnel associated with this award have contributed to subsequent recruitment efforts aimed at increasing the diversity of our laboratories and our departmental graduate program.</li> </ul> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Due to their advancing knowledge and understanding within the fields of single-molecule biophysics, RNA structure, dynamics, and function, and the analysis of single-molecule time-series data the first three bullet points primarily address the NSF&rsquo;s Intellectual Merit review criterion. Likewise, due to the data analysis tools it provides to the broader research community and the increase in the diversity of participating in STEM it represents, respectively, the third and fourth bullet points primarily address the NSF&rsquo;s Broader Impacts review criterion.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/28/2023<br>      Modified by: Ruben&nbsp;L&nbsp;Gonzalez</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This award encompassed four outcomes:   We adapted and optimized a new technology we had invented and developed under a previous NSF award, single-molecule field effect transistors (smFETs), for use in studies of the mechanisms through which RNA molecules fold and undergo changes in their three-dimensional structures. smFETs are nanoscopic electronic devices that produce a conductance signal that is sensitive to the three-dimensional structure of an individual, electrostatically charged polymer (e.g., an RNA biopolymer) that is tethered to its surface. By monitoring how the conductance of an smFETs harboring a single, surface-tethered RNA molecule changes as a function of time, one can investigate the folding or conformational changes of that RNA at an unprecedented hundreds-to-thousands of microseconds time resolution.   Using these smFET devices that we optimized for measurements of RNA folding and conformational changes, we characterized the folding of a set of RNA molecules encompassing the most fundamental unit of RNA structure, RNA stem-loops. Stem-loops are elements of RNA structure that fold in the hundreds-to-thousands of microseconds timescale and have important biological functions such serving as building blocks for much larger and complex RNA structures, biological ‘switches’ that can alternate between two or more conformations, and/or as sites for the binding of RNA-binding proteins. To our knowledge, the studies completed under this award represent the highest-time-resolution investigations of the folding of individual RNA molecules that have been reported. Among other important new research directions our studies create, they bridge a longstanding, crucial gap between experimental and computational studies of RNA folding and conformational changes.   In order to analyze single-molecule time series data in general, and the high time-resolution, long-observation-time conductance versus time trajectories that are generated by smFETs specifically, we developed new single-molecule time series modeling tools and implemented them in a new software platform that we call time-series Modeling, Analysis, and Visualization ENvironment (tMAVEN). This software platform is described in a publication, is open source, and has been made freely available to the research community via a GitHub repository.   In order to increase the diversity of graduate student researchers participating in this and related, NSF-funded studies in their laboratory and department, the PI has been a leader in establishing and maintaining a departmental presence at the Society for the Advancement of Chicanos/Latinx and Native Americans in Science (SACNAS) annual meeting and the Annual Biomedical Research Conference for Minoritized Scientists (ABRCMS). These meetings have served to increase the diversity of prospective graduate students who apply to our graduate programs and all of the personnel associated with this award have contributed to subsequent recruitment efforts aimed at increasing the diversity of our laboratories and our departmental graduate program.      Due to their advancing knowledge and understanding within the fields of single-molecule biophysics, RNA structure, dynamics, and function, and the analysis of single-molecule time-series data the first three bullet points primarily address the NSF’s Intellectual Merit review criterion. Likewise, due to the data analysis tools it provides to the broader research community and the increase in the diversity of participating in STEM it represents, respectively, the third and fourth bullet points primarily address the NSF’s Broader Impacts review criterion.       Last Modified: 09/28/2023       Submitted by: Ruben L Gonzalez]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
