<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[STTR Phase I:  Making Waves: Educational Technologies Combining STEM and Music Learning]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>225000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>225000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Diane Hickey</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact of this Small Business Technology Transfer (STTR) Phase I project is the enhancement of analytic and creative skills of children through the development of a educational delivery system, where students design and build musical instruments using hands-on science, technology, engineering, and math (STEM) learning, and then compose and perform original musical works on the instruments via music education.  Previous NSF research has shown strong correlations between achievement in the STEM fields and the study and practice of the arts, as well as greater academic success for at-risk youth.  The unique integration of physical hands-on activities with live, remote STEM and arts experts promise to engage students in ways that other approaches have failed to reach, without burdening the at-site instructor with unrealistic required professional development.  This project will enable systematic establishment of a distributed network of expert STEM and music instructors that can simultaneously reflect the cultural multiplicities of a broad range of students, while also supporting the on-site organizer with the level of instructional expertise and professional talent normally available to only to elite out-of-school programs in sophisticated urban centers.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed project will develop technology for an integrated STEM and music education program that will be highly engaging and rewarding for both students and instructors when delivered in a fully online or hybrid learning environment. The research objectives will focus on the development and assessment of learning modules that incorporate the use of physical hands-on kits and manipulatives as well as online tools and simulations, taught by remote instructors using videoconferencing with optional onsite adult facilitators.  The core content will center upon material drawn from the accepted national standards involving concepts which include fractions, wave properties, and the engineering design process as applied to both musical instrument analysis and design and music composition.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/12/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/12/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2005269</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jay</FirstName>
<LastName>Brockman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jay B Brockman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jbb@nd.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000105438</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/12/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Lindburg</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael R Lindburg</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mike@southbendwoodworks.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000803327</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/12/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>SOUTH BEND WOODWORKS LLC</Name>
<CityName>SOUTH BEND</CityName>
<ZipCode>466012825</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5742328875</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>707 S SCOTT ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IN02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>ZSQEUT2BLD76</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SOUTH BEND WOODWORKS LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>YSGSNYMW9K78</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[SOUTH BEND WOODWORKS LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>South Bend</CityName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>466012825</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[707 S. Scott St.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IN02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1505</Code>
<Text>STTR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1707</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED LEARNING TECHNOLOGIES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~225000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Making Waves is a new business unit created within educational toy manufacturer South Bend Woodworks to bring to market a modular educational package that integrates STEM and music learning.&nbsp; The Making Waves curriculum has students design, build, and analyze custom musical instruments, and then compose, arrange, and perform original musical works using those instruments.&nbsp; The main goal of this Phase I STTR grant was to use a research-based approach to develop and refine a "minimally viable" version of the product for use by educators across the country, and to evaluate its efficacy with a sample of a target market.&nbsp; The initial market focus was determined to be families educating children at home, either as part of a homeschool program or as an enrichment activity, with an emphasis on math, science, and music standards for grades 3-5.&nbsp; Four main activities were completed under this grant: (1) development/refinement of a prototype Making Waves curriculum and learning kits, (2) conducting trial online classes and evaluating outcomes for a sample student population, (3) exploring market potential via the SBIR/STTR ?Beat-the-Odds? Boot Camp program, and (4) early exploration of follow-on product technologies that could lead to additional products after the initial prototype.</p> <p>A complete 8-hour curriculum with instructor materials was developed for the Making Waves online home learning trials, using a student learning kit that includes parts for assembling a log drum, a chime set, and a novel manipulative called a "rhythm puzzle" where students apply knowledge of fractions to compose musical rhythms.&nbsp; It also included a workbook for activities that include music composition and exploring properties of soundwaves using an online oscilloscope app.&nbsp; The curriculum was developed in consultation with experts in math education from the Center for STEM Education at the University of Notre Dame and with members of the Grammy-winning ensemble Third Coast Percussion, who are experts in music composition and performance, as well as music education.&nbsp; Three instructors were trained to deliver classes with approximately 10 students per class via Zoom with a total enrollment of 58 students from across the United States, including a cluster of students from the South Side of Chicago through a collaboration with the University of Chicago Music Department.&nbsp;</p> <p>Researchers from the Center for Research and Evaluation at the Center of Science and Industry (COSI) of Columbus, OH conducted a comprehensive mixed-methods evaluation of the trials, that included the following items: impacts of the Making Waves classes and kits on student STEM and music content learning, creative problem solving, and building other social and cultural competencies; impressions of instructors on strengths and value of the program for other instructors; impressions of families and adults responsible for children on the strengths and value of the program; and overall areas of improvement from each group of stakeholders.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Results of this evaluation indicated a strongly positive response from each group of stakeholders to the Making Waves class experience, with solid recommendations for future refinements.&nbsp; Preliminary exploration of follow-on product technologies included early prototypes for kits incorporating software, electronic, and electromechanical components.</p> <p>The intellectual merit of the project is the research-based approach to the development and evaluation of a novel means for integrating STEM and music learning that emphasizes both creative and analytic skills in young learners.&nbsp; The broader impact of the project is developing a scalable and commercially sustainable approach to reaching a large audience of learners, including many who may not otherwise have access to such programming in person.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/06/2022<br>      Modified by: Jay&nbsp;B&nbsp;Brockman</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Making Waves is a new business unit created within educational toy manufacturer South Bend Woodworks to bring to market a modular educational package that integrates STEM and music learning.  The Making Waves curriculum has students design, build, and analyze custom musical instruments, and then compose, arrange, and perform original musical works using those instruments.  The main goal of this Phase I STTR grant was to use a research-based approach to develop and refine a "minimally viable" version of the product for use by educators across the country, and to evaluate its efficacy with a sample of a target market.  The initial market focus was determined to be families educating children at home, either as part of a homeschool program or as an enrichment activity, with an emphasis on math, science, and music standards for grades 3-5.  Four main activities were completed under this grant: (1) development/refinement of a prototype Making Waves curriculum and learning kits, (2) conducting trial online classes and evaluating outcomes for a sample student population, (3) exploring market potential via the SBIR/STTR ?Beat-the-Odds? Boot Camp program, and (4) early exploration of follow-on product technologies that could lead to additional products after the initial prototype.  A complete 8-hour curriculum with instructor materials was developed for the Making Waves online home learning trials, using a student learning kit that includes parts for assembling a log drum, a chime set, and a novel manipulative called a "rhythm puzzle" where students apply knowledge of fractions to compose musical rhythms.  It also included a workbook for activities that include music composition and exploring properties of soundwaves using an online oscilloscope app.  The curriculum was developed in consultation with experts in math education from the Center for STEM Education at the University of Notre Dame and with members of the Grammy-winning ensemble Third Coast Percussion, who are experts in music composition and performance, as well as music education.  Three instructors were trained to deliver classes with approximately 10 students per class via Zoom with a total enrollment of 58 students from across the United States, including a cluster of students from the South Side of Chicago through a collaboration with the University of Chicago Music Department.   Researchers from the Center for Research and Evaluation at the Center of Science and Industry (COSI) of Columbus, OH conducted a comprehensive mixed-methods evaluation of the trials, that included the following items: impacts of the Making Waves classes and kits on student STEM and music content learning, creative problem solving, and building other social and cultural competencies; impressions of instructors on strengths and value of the program for other instructors; impressions of families and adults responsible for children on the strengths and value of the program; and overall areas of improvement from each group of stakeholders.     Results of this evaluation indicated a strongly positive response from each group of stakeholders to the Making Waves class experience, with solid recommendations for future refinements.  Preliminary exploration of follow-on product technologies included early prototypes for kits incorporating software, electronic, and electromechanical components.  The intellectual merit of the project is the research-based approach to the development and evaluation of a novel means for integrating STEM and music learning that emphasizes both creative and analytic skills in young learners.  The broader impact of the project is developing a scalable and commercially sustainable approach to reaching a large audience of learners, including many who may not otherwise have access to such programming in person.          Last Modified: 07/06/2022       Submitted by: Jay B Brockman]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
