<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[IRES Track I: Exploring New Horizons in the Observable Universe at the Cosmic Dawn Center of Excellence in Copenhagen]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/23/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>250419.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>250419</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Maija Kukla</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mkukla@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924940</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The first stars, galaxies and black holes burst into existence only a few hundred million years after the Big Bang, bringing light to the cosmos and setting in motion processes that built the Universe as we see it today. Many mysteries remain about these early epochs, but not for too much longer: new and upcoming facilities such as the Atacama Large Millimeter Array and the James Webb Space Telescope are optimized to revolutionize our understanding of this time period, known as "Cosmic Dawn." The Cosmic Dawn Center of Excellence (DAWN, established 2018), an international research center in Copenhagen, Denmark, brings together scholars whose interests span a broad range of observational and theoretical inquiries into Cosmic Dawn. Their expertise, together with Copenhagen's beautiful and enriching setting, make DAWN an ideal host for budding US scholars. We will create the DAWN-IRES Scholars Program to empower future generations of US scientists through a once-in-a-lifetime opportunity of visiting Copenhagen to immerse themselves into this vibrant international research center. The DAWN-IRES scholars will join a cohort of 7 student researchers in a stimulating 10-week science program that merges research using next-generation telescopes with life in a thousand-year-old city. The program's structure will encourage students to build learning communities within their cohorts, equipping them with practical research and communication skills. At the same time, the international exposure and access to cutting-edge resources will help maintain US leadership within the global astronomical community.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Students will lead observational and/or theoretical projects that contribute towards understanding some of the most fundamental questions in astrophysics today: What caused the reionization of the Universe?  How do the first, massive galaxies form?  What is the origin of galaxy scaling relations? What quenches star formation in massive galaxies?  Over the next decade, the center's mission is to develop and test a physical model explaining the key processes responsible for the assembly of the earliest galaxies through to the present day. The DAWN-IRES Scholars will join this thriving international research network, bridging the world class research performed by the US-based associate faculty coordinating this program with the DAWN permanent faculty and the local program coordinator.  The key learning goals of this international research experience include: (1) building a learning community to stimulate personal and academic growth, (2) developing effective scientific communication skills, and (3) performing globally competitive research addressing an open question in astrophysics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The DAWN-IRES program is primarily designed to enhance the progress of science through a unique global educational training experience for a diverse cohort of US students.  The themes defining the broader impact of the program include diversity, training, dissemination, and community.  Through extensive proactive recruitment strategies (direct contact with faculty at minority-serving institutions, leveraging social media, widely circulating flyers, local announcements in STEM courses, and more), the PI will assemble diverse groups of scholars to stimulate excellence and innovation.  The program incorporates a wide range of professional development activities that are focused on advancing scientific communication skills (e.g., weekly seminars, hack days, oral presentations abroad and stateside).  The students will also build professional research toolkits, including learning programming, data analysis and presentation techniques.  Dissemination of research will occur through the DAWN-IRES Scholars Symposium at the end of each summer in Copenhagen, together with a presentation at the students' local institutions and the national American Astronomical Society meeting.  Working with the Center for Excellence in Teaching at UConn, the assessment strategy of DAWN-IRES will be tailored to the learning goals of the program.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/17/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/17/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.079</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2005578</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Katherine</FirstName>
<LastName>Whitaker</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Katherine E Whitaker</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[kwhitaker@astro.umass.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000654643</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/17/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Massachusetts Amherst</Name>
<CityName>AMHERST</CityName>
<ZipCode>01003</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4135450698</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>COMMONWEALTH AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>VGJHK59NMPK9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MASSACHUSETTS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>MLBQUML9JJT6</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Massachusetts Amherst]]></Name>
<CityName>Amherst</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>010039305</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[710 N Pleasant Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7727</Code>
<Text>IRES Track I: IRES Sites (IS)</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5980</Code>
<Text>WESTERN EUROPE PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01001819DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~250419</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="p1">a unique global educational training experience for diverse cohorts of US students at the Cosmic Dawn Center of Excellence in Copenhagen, Denmark.&nbsp;The 11-week summer program ran in 2019, 2021 and 2022, sending a total of 23 students to DAWN.<span>&nbsp; </span>The themes defining the broader impact of the program include&nbsp;diversity,&nbsp;training,&nbsp;dissemination, and&nbsp;community.&nbsp;&nbsp;The IRES program incorporated a wide range of professional development activities focused on advancing scientific communication skills (e.g., weekly seminars, professional development workshops, oral presentations).&nbsp;&nbsp;The students also built professional research toolkits, including learning programming, data analysis and presentation techniques.&nbsp;&nbsp;Dissemination of research occurred through the DAWN-IRES Scholars Symposium at the end of each summer in Copenhagen, together with a presentation at the national American Astronomical Society meeting.&nbsp;&nbsp;The key learning goals of the DAWN-IRES Scholars Program included: (1) building a learning community to stimulate personal and academic growth, (2) developing effective scientific communication skills, and (3) performing globally competitive research addressing an open question in astrophysics.<span>&nbsp; </span>DAWN-IRES scholars have been highly successful, with notable achievements and outcomes from the 23 students who have completed the program including 3 published papers, 1 Chambliss Astronomy Achievement Student Award (and 1 honorable mention) at the January 2019 AAS meeting, 1 student later returned to DAWN as a Fulbright Scholar, and 1 DAWN-IRES scholar was selected for a student-led press release of their research at the June 2022 AAS.<span>&nbsp; </span>87% of DAWN-IRES alumni from the first two cohorts have since been admitted into graduate programs to continue their astrophysics research, with 13% opting to pursue alternative career opportunities.<span>&nbsp; </span>Students in the DAWN-IRES Scholars Program are welcomed into the "DAWN family" not only during the summer of their internship but also for their future careers beyond, giving them access to a valuable international professional network.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/24/2023<br>      Modified by: Katherine&nbsp;E&nbsp;Whitaker</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2005578/2005578_10571061_1676642597345_DAWN-IRES_2022_Cohort--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2005578/2005578_10571061_1676642597345_DAWN-IRES_2022_Cohort--rgov-800width.jpg" title="DAWN-IRES 2022 Cohort"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2005578/2005578_10571061_1676642597345_DAWN-IRES_2022_Cohort--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="DAWN-IRES 2022 Cohort"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">8 students in the 2022 DAWN-IRES Scholars program attend the annual American Astronomical Society meeting in Seattle, Washington in January 2022.</div> <div class="imageCredit">John Weaver</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Katherine&nbsp;E&nbsp;Whitaker</div> <div class="imageTitle">DAWN-IRES 2022 Cohort</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2005578/2005578_10571061_1676641705452_DAWN-IRES_2021_Cohort--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2005578/2005578_10571061_1676641705452_DAWN-IRES_2021_Cohort--rgov-800width.jpg" title="DAWN-IRES 2021 Cohort (partial)"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2005578/2005578_10571061_1676641705452_DAWN-IRES_2021_Cohort--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="DAWN-IRES 2021 Cohort (partial)"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">4 students (out of 8 total) in the 2021 DAWN-IRES Scholars cohort at the annual American Astronomical Meeting in Pasadena, California in June 2022.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Bryan Scott</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Katherine&nbsp;E&nbsp;Whitaker</div> <div class="imageTitle">DAWN-IRES 2021 Cohort (partial)</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2005578/2005578_10571061_1676641605520_DAWN-IRES_2019_Cohort--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2005578/2005578_10571061_1676641605520_DAWN-IRES_2019_Cohort--rgov-800width.jpg" title="DAWN-IRES 2019 Cohort"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2005578/2005578_10571061_1676641605520_DAWN-IRES_2019_Cohort--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="DAWN-IRES 2019 Cohort"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">7 students in the 2019 cohort of the DAWN-IRES Scholars Program, plus PI Whitaker (far right), at the annual American Astronomical Society meeting in Honolulu, HI in January 2020.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Kate Whitaker</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Katherine&nbsp;E&nbsp;Whitaker</div> <div class="imageTitle">DAWN-IRES 2019 Cohort</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[a unique global educational training experience for diverse cohorts of US students at the Cosmic Dawn Center of Excellence in Copenhagen, Denmark. The 11-week summer program ran in 2019, 2021 and 2022, sending a total of 23 students to DAWN.  The themes defining the broader impact of the program include diversity, training, dissemination, and community.  The IRES program incorporated a wide range of professional development activities focused on advancing scientific communication skills (e.g., weekly seminars, professional development workshops, oral presentations).  The students also built professional research toolkits, including learning programming, data analysis and presentation techniques.  Dissemination of research occurred through the DAWN-IRES Scholars Symposium at the end of each summer in Copenhagen, together with a presentation at the national American Astronomical Society meeting.  The key learning goals of the DAWN-IRES Scholars Program included: (1) building a learning community to stimulate personal and academic growth, (2) developing effective scientific communication skills, and (3) performing globally competitive research addressing an open question in astrophysics.  DAWN-IRES scholars have been highly successful, with notable achievements and outcomes from the 23 students who have completed the program including 3 published papers, 1 Chambliss Astronomy Achievement Student Award (and 1 honorable mention) at the January 2019 AAS meeting, 1 student later returned to DAWN as a Fulbright Scholar, and 1 DAWN-IRES scholar was selected for a student-led press release of their research at the June 2022 AAS.  87% of DAWN-IRES alumni from the first two cohorts have since been admitted into graduate programs to continue their astrophysics research, with 13% opting to pursue alternative career opportunities.  Students in the DAWN-IRES Scholars Program are welcomed into the "DAWN family" not only during the summer of their internship but also for their future careers beyond, giving them access to a valuable international professional network.          Last Modified: 02/24/2023       Submitted by: Katherine E Whitaker]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
