<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Connected Isotropy Groups in the Grove Symmetry Program]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>181397.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>181397</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Christopher Stark</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cstark@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924869</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The PI seeks to advance understanding of the interaction between the local, geometric properties and the global, topological properties of smooth objects called manifolds. This continues work that goes back over 150 years to the origins of Riemannian geometry, and it involves questions asked decades ago that still have no answers. Fortunately viewing some of these problems through the lens of symmetry in the last 25 years has led to major advances, the development of new tools, and the construction of new examples. The PI collaborates widely and plays his part in tying together the world’s people and their economies. With an eye to the future, the PI is also actively involved in the growth, education, and diversification of tomorrow’s body of U.S.-based, STEM-focused researchers.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;In the past ten years, the PI and his collaborators have proved striking new results in the Grove symmetry program. This program was developed in the 1990s to provide a foothold into the basic but difficult questions in Riemannian geometry around positive curvature. These new results have required new tools. For example, the PI and his collaborators have recently obtained surprising results for torus representations with connected isotropy groups. The proofs use only elementary representation theory. In particular, they do not involve curvature assumptions and might therefore have wider applications in other areas of geometry. Completing this work and further investigating its applications are top priorities for this project period.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/23/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/23/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2005280</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lee</FirstName>
<LastName>Kennard</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>T</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lee T Kennard</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ltkennar@syr.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000604455</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/23/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Syracuse University</Name>
<CityName>SYRACUSE</CityName>
<ZipCode>132440001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3154432807</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>900 S CROUSE AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>22</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY22</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>C4BXLBC11LC6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SYRACUSE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Syracuse University]]></Name>
<CityName>Syracuse</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>132441270</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>22</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY22</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1265</Code>
<Text>GEOMETRIC ANALYSIS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~181397</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Major goals of this project include researching classes of smooth objects called manifolds and to advance our understanding of the interaction of symmetry, curvature, and topological assumptions. For example, a recurring theme is to measure how much symmetry a manifold can have under geometric conditions such as being positively curved or topological conditions such as having periodic cohomology. Tools involve the theory of transformation groups, representation theory, and combinatorics.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The outcomes for intellectual merit include the first proof of Hopf&rsquo;s Euler characteristic positivity conjecture under the assumption of torus symmetry where the torus rank is independent of the manifold dimension. Additionally, a surprising link was found between torus representations with connected isotropy groups and combinatorial objects called regular matroids. Both results were in joint work with Michael Wiemeler and Burkhard Wilking and led to additional progress in the Grove Symmetry Program. Further outcomes relate to the classification of manifolds that both admit cohomogeneity one symmetry and satisfy a topological condition called periodic cohomology, the classification of fundamental groups of positively curved manifolds with symmetry, and the classification of other finite groups that can act with a fixed point on positively curved manifolds.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The outcomes for broader impacts include the mentoring of an NSF postdoc who started at Syracuse University in 2022, the advising of a PhD student who graduated in 2021, the advising of three current PhD students, and the mentoring and in one case co-authorship on a paper with multiple undergraduates. In addition, the PI co-organized a special session at the JMM 2023 with Elahe Khalili Samani and Catherine Searle, in which half of the confirmed speakers were women and in which most were in early to middle stages of their career.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/06/2023<br>      Modified by: Lee&nbsp;T&nbsp;Kennard</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[    Major goals of this project include researching classes of smooth objects called manifolds and to advance our understanding of the interaction of symmetry, curvature, and topological assumptions. For example, a recurring theme is to measure how much symmetry a manifold can have under geometric conditions such as being positively curved or topological conditions such as having periodic cohomology. Tools involve the theory of transformation groups, representation theory, and combinatorics.     The outcomes for intellectual merit include the first proof of Hopf’s Euler characteristic positivity conjecture under the assumption of torus symmetry where the torus rank is independent of the manifold dimension. Additionally, a surprising link was found between torus representations with connected isotropy groups and combinatorial objects called regular matroids. Both results were in joint work with Michael Wiemeler and Burkhard Wilking and led to additional progress in the Grove Symmetry Program. Further outcomes relate to the classification of manifolds that both admit cohomogeneity one symmetry and satisfy a topological condition called periodic cohomology, the classification of fundamental groups of positively curved manifolds with symmetry, and the classification of other finite groups that can act with a fixed point on positively curved manifolds.     The outcomes for broader impacts include the mentoring of an NSF postdoc who started at Syracuse University in 2022, the advising of a PhD student who graduated in 2021, the advising of three current PhD students, and the mentoring and in one case co-authorship on a paper with multiple undergraduates. In addition, the PI co-organized a special session at the JMM 2023 with Elahe Khalili Samani and Catherine Searle, in which half of the confirmed speakers were women and in which most were in early to middle stages of their career.       Last Modified: 09/06/2023       Submitted by: Lee T Kennard]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
