<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Black Youth Understanding of Racial Inequality: Scale Development and Validation]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>138000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>129375</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SMA</Abbreviation>
<LongName>SBE Off Of Multidisciplinary Activities</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Josie Welkom Miranda</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jwmirand@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927376</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This award was provided as part of NSF's Social, Behavioral and Economic Sciences (SBE) Postdoctoral Research Fellowships (SPRF) program and the Social Psychology program. The goal of the SPRF program is to prepare promising, early career doctoral-level scientists for scientific careers in academia, industry or private sector, and government. SPRF awards involve two years of training under the sponsorship of established scientists and encourage Postdoctoral Fellows to perform independent research. NSF seeks to promote the participation of scientists from all segments of the scientific community, including those from underrepresented groups, in its research programs and activities; the postdoctoral period is considered to be an important level of professional development in attaining this goal. Each Postdoctoral Fellow must address important scientific questions that advance their respective disciplinary fields. Under the sponsorship of Drs. Riana Anderson and Enrique Neblett at the University of Michigan, this postdoctoral fellowship award supports an early career scientist examining the cognitive process through which Black youth know about, make meaning of, and understand racism, that is, their awareness of racism. Recent work has found that during early adolescence, Black youth can identify and articulate connections between systemic issues and inequities in their schooling experiences. Critical Consciousness theory suggests that without an awareness of oppression, marginalized groups cannot work to disrupt oppressive norms and societal inequities. To date, there has not been a psychometric tool that captures Black youth's cognitive understanding of racism, a specific form of oppression. An understanding of Black youth's cognitions around racism has the potential to provide empirical support for untested theoretical assumptions, enhance clinical approaches to addressing racial stress and trauma, and strengthen research approaches to examining the influence of racism in the lives of Black youth and their families. Finally, understanding how awareness of racism develops may serve as a catalyst to identify points of intervention that may draw on internal and external strengths to combat the negative consequences of racism. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of this research project is to contribute to theory and research seeking to understand the influence of racism on the lives of Black youth. The proposed study aims to address these current gaps by: (1) deconstructing the extent to which Black youth understand and can articulate their understanding of racism, and (2) developing a psychometric tool that can streamline and strengthen the connection between studies by using similar measurements and definitions to assess racism awareness. By understanding the extent to which Black youth are aware of the distinct forms of racism, within and across systems, this work can provide empirical support for intervention programs aimed at combating racism. The development of the forthcoming Racism Awareness Scale will be achieved using a three-phase model—item development, scale development, and scale evaluation—of scale development. The first two phases of the scale development consist of designing and testing the dimensionality of the Racism Awareness Scale. The final phase will consist of data collection and analyses for scale evaluation. During this phase of data collection, a survey will be developed that includes other related scales and tests the predictive, convergent, and discriminant validity of the scale. This evaluation will also spark new questions related to the associations between and divergences from experiencing racism and understanding racism.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/19/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/21/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2005140</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Natasha</FirstName>
<LastName>Johnson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Natasha C Johnson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<NSF_ID>000814392</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/19/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Riana</FirstName>
<LastName>Anderson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Riana E Anderson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<NSF_ID>000793092</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/19/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Enrique</FirstName>
<LastName>Neblett</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME>Jr</PI_SUFX_NAME>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Enrique W Neblett</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<NSF_ID>000196394</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/19/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Johnson, Natasha Cierra</Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<ZipCode>48109</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Michigan]]></Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>481091004</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1332</Code>
<Text>Social Psychology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8208</Code>
<Text>SPRF-Broadening Participation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7137</Code>
<Text>POSTDOCTORAL FELLOWSHIPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~129374</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-951a7644-7fff-002d-3bfb-3a6a99495db9"> <p dir="ltr"><span>As research identifies the health and educational consequences of and the resilient factors related to experiences of interpersonal racism (i.e., racial discrimination), more work is needed to understand the cognitive process through which Black adolescents know about, make meaning of, and understand distinct forms of racism (e.g., individual, interpersonal, institutional, historical), that is, their </span><span>awareness</span><span> </span><span>of racism</span><span>. </span><span>The aim of the research project was to investigate Black adolescents' awareness of racism.</span><span> As such, I conducted a pilot study that utilized open-ended questionnaires (N=11) and semi-structured interviews (n=3) with African American/Black high school students to examine their awareness of racism. Several patterns emerged that highlighted the nuanced ways Black adolescents understand and make meaning of the racial inequities to which they are exposed.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Key Finding</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Respondents used a variety of terms to define racism and racial inequality. Most respondents included some variation of the term </span><span>unfair treatment</span><span> in their definition. A third of respondents expressed </span><span>disappointment</span><span> or </span><span>sadness</span><span> for the mistreatment of Black people and baseless hatred. This preliminary finding suggests that Black adolescents are engaging in the complex task of developing their awareness of racism while simultaneously experiencing potentially challenging emotions related to this awareness. More work is needed to explore further the influence of racism awareness on mental health outcomes.&nbsp;</span></p> <br /> <p dir="ltr"><span>Three respondents</span><span> </span><span>completed a 75-minute semi-structured interview, which included questions that prompted adolescents to reflect on their experiences related to and perceptions of race and racism. Preliminary analysis revealed three major themes: 1)feelings of racial pride, 2)</span><span> </span><span>awareness of individual and interpersonal racism, and 3) awareness of institutional racism. Notably, without being prompted with a specific question about racial pride, all participants discussed their pride in being Black when describing their racial background. Respondents discussed gratitude for their physical features, the uniqueness of Black culture, and the collective strength of the Black community. These statements of cultural pride are a testament to the persistence of Black joy despite social conditions that threaten to dim its light. Additionally, respondents identified how others' negative thoughts and beliefs about Black people (e.g., individual racism) directly influence how Black people are treated (e.g., interpersonal racism). For example, one respondent linked negative stereotypes, which spread quickly &ldquo;like rumors,&rdquo; to a lack of safety for Black people at the hands (e.g., racial discrimination) of non-Black people who believe these stereotypes.</span></p> <br /> <p dir="ltr"><span>Often respondents&rsquo; discussions of racial discrimination were followed by discussions of institutional racism, which suggest that Black adolescents understand the distinction between and interconnectedness of various forms of racism. For example, all respondents discussed police brutality as a racially discriminatory practice, especially for Black men, that led to unfair treatment in the criminal legal system. One respondent discussed racially discriminatory practices in media coverage of people who commit crimes. Specifically, he discussed how news outlets consistently highlight the mental health challenges of a White person who committed a violent crime but do not do the same for a Black person who commits a crime, ultimately leading to racial disparities in sentencing and convictions.&nbsp;</span></p> <br /> <p dir="ltr"><span>Conclusion</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Taken together, the results from the open-ended responses and interviews highlighted the nuanced ways that Black youth are assessing racialized experiences to inform their understanding of racial inequality within and beyond the spaces they occupy. Furthermore, the results from this project highlighted the complexity of how Black youth make meaning of racial incidents, namely their critical analysis of incidents as racially oppressive (e.g., critical reflection). Some respondents were able to critically assess how racial disparities within institutions (e.g., education, criminal legal system) were connected to racially discriminatory practices (e.g., racial profiling). While racial profiling was consistently named as an unfair occurrence in their communities, respondents had built a language and understanding around its roots and meaning--often with the help of the adults in their lives.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Broader Impacts</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The current project had significant broader implications by broadening the participation of underrepresented scholars in research and contributing to the developing scholarship on critical consciousness. Specifically, this project offered Dr. Johnson an opportunity to advance her methodological and pedagogical skillsets. The pilot data will be used to continue the development of a psychometric tool that will measure racism awareness. Additionally, the project supported the research development of several undergraduate and graduate students from underrepresented groups in the academy.</span></p> </span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/10/2023<br>      Modified by: Natasha&nbsp;C&nbsp;Johnson</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  As research identifies the health and educational consequences of and the resilient factors related to experiences of interpersonal racism (i.e., racial discrimination), more work is needed to understand the cognitive process through which Black adolescents know about, make meaning of, and understand distinct forms of racism (e.g., individual, interpersonal, institutional, historical), that is, their awareness of racism. The aim of the research project was to investigate Black adolescents' awareness of racism. As such, I conducted a pilot study that utilized open-ended questionnaires (N=11) and semi-structured interviews (n=3) with African American/Black high school students to examine their awareness of racism. Several patterns emerged that highlighted the nuanced ways Black adolescents understand and make meaning of the racial inequities to which they are exposed. Key Finding Respondents used a variety of terms to define racism and racial inequality. Most respondents included some variation of the term unfair treatment in their definition. A third of respondents expressed disappointment or sadness for the mistreatment of Black people and baseless hatred. This preliminary finding suggests that Black adolescents are engaging in the complex task of developing their awareness of racism while simultaneously experiencing potentially challenging emotions related to this awareness. More work is needed to explore further the influence of racism awareness on mental health outcomes.    Three respondents completed a 75-minute semi-structured interview, which included questions that prompted adolescents to reflect on their experiences related to and perceptions of race and racism. Preliminary analysis revealed three major themes: 1)feelings of racial pride, 2) awareness of individual and interpersonal racism, and 3) awareness of institutional racism. Notably, without being prompted with a specific question about racial pride, all participants discussed their pride in being Black when describing their racial background. Respondents discussed gratitude for their physical features, the uniqueness of Black culture, and the collective strength of the Black community. These statements of cultural pride are a testament to the persistence of Black joy despite social conditions that threaten to dim its light. Additionally, respondents identified how others' negative thoughts and beliefs about Black people (e.g., individual racism) directly influence how Black people are treated (e.g., interpersonal racism). For example, one respondent linked negative stereotypes, which spread quickly "like rumors," to a lack of safety for Black people at the hands (e.g., racial discrimination) of non-Black people who believe these stereotypes.   Often respondents’ discussions of racial discrimination were followed by discussions of institutional racism, which suggest that Black adolescents understand the distinction between and interconnectedness of various forms of racism. For example, all respondents discussed police brutality as a racially discriminatory practice, especially for Black men, that led to unfair treatment in the criminal legal system. One respondent discussed racially discriminatory practices in media coverage of people who commit crimes. Specifically, he discussed how news outlets consistently highlight the mental health challenges of a White person who committed a violent crime but do not do the same for a Black person who commits a crime, ultimately leading to racial disparities in sentencing and convictions.    Conclusion Taken together, the results from the open-ended responses and interviews highlighted the nuanced ways that Black youth are assessing racialized experiences to inform their understanding of racial inequality within and beyond the spaces they occupy. Furthermore, the results from this project highlighted the complexity of how Black youth make meaning of racial incidents, namely their critical analysis of incidents as racially oppressive (e.g., critical reflection). Some respondents were able to critically assess how racial disparities within institutions (e.g., education, criminal legal system) were connected to racially discriminatory practices (e.g., racial profiling). While racial profiling was consistently named as an unfair occurrence in their communities, respondents had built a language and understanding around its roots and meaning--often with the help of the adults in their lives. Broader Impacts The current project had significant broader implications by broadening the participation of underrepresented scholars in research and contributing to the developing scholarship on critical consciousness. Specifically, this project offered Dr. Johnson an opportunity to advance her methodological and pedagogical skillsets. The pilot data will be used to continue the development of a psychometric tool that will measure racism awareness. Additionally, the project supported the research development of several undergraduate and graduate students from underrepresented groups in the academy.        Last Modified: 01/10/2023       Submitted by: Natasha C Johnson]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
