<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[A Contextual Examination of Ethnic-Racial Identity and Critical Consciousness among Diverse College Students]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>138000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>129000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SMA</Abbreviation>
<LongName>SBE Off Of Multidisciplinary Activities</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Josie Welkom Miranda</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jwmirand@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927376</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This award was provided as part of NSF's Social, Behavioral and Economic Sciences Postdoctoral Research Fellowships (SPRF) program. The goal of the SPRF program is to prepare promising, early career doctoral-level scientists for scientific careers in academia, industry or private sector, and government. SPRF awards involve two years of training under the sponsorship of established scientists and encourage Postdoctoral Fellows to perform independent research. NSF seeks to promote the participation of scientists from all segments of the scientific community, including those from underrepresented groups, in its research programs and activities; the postdoctoral period is considered to be an important level of professional development in attaining this goal. Each Postdoctoral Fellow must address important scientific questions that advance their respective disciplinary fields. Under the sponsorship of Dr. Leoandra Onnie Rogers at Northwestern and Dr. Margarita Azmitia at University of California Santa Cruz, this postdoctoral fellowship award supports an early career scientist examining the role of the sociopolitical context in the development of ethnic-racial identity and critical consciousness among college-going young adults. The current sociopolitical climate is fraught and can be psychologically taxing for everyone, though its implications are more dire for some individuals than others. Since 2016, the number of reported hate crimes has risen sharply (FBI, 2018). On university campuses, violence against marginalized groups has also increased (Watt, Costa, &amp; Quiason, 2018). In the wake of the coronavirus pandemic, racism against Asian Americans has spiked (Coates, 2020) and Black, indigenous, and other minoritized individuals are getting sick and dying at disproportionate rates (Dyer, 2020). A better understanding is needed of how young adults from diverse ethnic-racial and political backgrounds alternately endorse, accept, or resist such events in both the local and national contexts. How are their responses situated within their sense of identity and their views on the world? If young people engage with sociopolitical events online or in person, what does this look like and what meaning do they draw from it? This project investigates these questions, linking the micro-level of daily life with the macro-level of the sociopolitical climate, examining the development of college-going young adults’ identities, beliefs, and behaviors in context.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project focuses specifically on critical consciousness (CC), a construct originally developed by Paolo Freire (1970), which includes an awareness of and resistance to societal inequity. Both CC and clarity about one’s ethnic-racial identity (ERI) can buffer the negative effects of discrimination (Diemer, Rapa, Park, &amp; Perry, 2016; Yip, Wang, Mootoo, &amp; Mirpuri, 2019) and link to myriad positive outcomes, including academic achievement and wellbeing (El-Amin et al., 2017; Rivas‐Drake et al., 2014). ERI and CC have rarely been investigated in tandem, however, and their development remains understudied among college students (Mathews et al., 2019). This project addresses this empirical gap using a longitudinal, mixed-methods approach, with data collection occurring at four time points across the 2020-2021 academic year. Survey data will be analyzed using person-centered longitudinal transition analysis (LTA), first creating clusters based on responses to ERI and CC measures, then examining who is likely to be in which cluster, who changes, and how these changes relate to additional variables such as political conservatism and sense of belonging. Additionally, open-response prompts will be gathered for ten day periods, asking participants to describe their engagement with and make meaning about real-time events. Responses will be analyzed using narrative methods, illuminating within- and between-person differences. This mix of methods and analyses allows for a rich investigation of ERI and CC development in context, advancing theory and promoting equity-oriented outcomes among young people with diverse identities and experiences.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/31/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/17/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2005052</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Margarita</FirstName>
<LastName>Azmitia</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Margarita Azmitia</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<NSF_ID>000561815</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/31/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ursula</FirstName>
<LastName>Moffitt</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ursula E Moffitt</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<NSF_ID>000814349</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/31/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Leoandra</FirstName>
<LastName>Rogers</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>O</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Leoandra O Rogers</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<NSF_ID>000764638</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/31/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Moffitt, Ursula E</Name>
<CityName>Evanston</CityName>
<ZipCode>60208</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Northwestern University]]></Name>
<CityName>Evanston</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>602080828</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8208</Code>
<Text>SPRF-Broadening Participation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7137</Code>
<Text>POSTDOCTORAL FELLOWSHIPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~129000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>The aim of this project was to investigate how racially diverse young adults attending a predominantly white institution navigated the socio-political climate surrounding the 2020 U.S. presidential election as they developed their identities and beliefs about the world.</strong> To achieve this aim, survey data were collected in the fall of 2020 (Time 1) and spring of 2021 (Time 4), and qualitative, open-response data were collected across 10 days surrounding the U.S. presidential election in November 2020 (Time 2) and 10 days surrounding the U.S. presidential inauguration in January 2021 (Time 3).</p> <p><strong>Key Findings</strong></p> <p><strong>In an initial analysis of the qualitative data, we examined participants&rsquo; responses to a prompt asking them to recount and reflect on recent conversations related to race. Our sample for this study included </strong>47 students (<em>M</em><sub>age</sub>= 19.71, SD = 1.72; 81% female, 17% male, 2% other; 45% Asian/Asian American, 30% white, 13% Latinx/Hispanic, 4% Black/African American, 4% Multiracial, 2% Middle Eastern/Arab). <strong>Based on inductive coding, we found that a majority of participants reported conversations with peers, focused primarily on racial inequity and justice.</strong></p> <p>Subsequent deductive coding was guided by the theoretical frameworks of critical consciousness, which includes awareness of societal inequity (critical reflection), belief in the possibility of socio-political change (political efficacy), and individual action toward change (critical action), as well as racial identity meaning making, which includes reflection on one&rsquo;s own identity and role within their racial group. We found that among participants of color, links were drawn between events and issues such as the Black Lives Matter movement, anti-Asian violence, or the presidential election, and their own daily lives. For many of these students, talking about race in society was inextricable from talking about their own racial identities. This finding supports previous research showing that youth of color who experience racism and/or racial socialization may be prompted toward critical reflection, which may be strengthened by racial identity exploration.<strong> Thus</strong>, <strong>for many young People of Color, conversations with peers offered spaces for critical reflection, which led to meaning making about their racial identities. </strong>However, our participants narratives evidenced that these processes are interwoven, with reflections on individual experiences often embedded in reflection on socio-political and historical issues. This finding extends previous research and theory and makes clear that future longitudinal research should examine the reciprocal nature of these processes, paying attention to the role of the socio-political context.</p> <p><strong>In contrast, we did not find evidence of racial identity meaning making among white participants.</strong> Instead, most white participants situated race as outside of and disconnected from their lives&mdash;either not relevant or only relevant to &ldquo;other&rdquo; people. While many white participants wrote about their hopes, fears, or frustrations, especially related to the political sphere, whiteness generally remained unnamed and unexamined. <strong>Our findings show that more work is needed to better understand the ways in which positionality shapes developmental processes related to critical consciousness and racial identity development. </strong>Without taking the socio-political context into account, group-based differences can seem static and neutral&mdash;occurring <em>because</em> of one&rsquo;s racial group membership&mdash;rather than in relation to the racialized systems of power and oppression shaping our society.</p> <p>Dovetailing with these qualitative findings, our initial quantitative analysis pushes psychologists to reflect critically on the origins of the constructs they use and to examine the implications of &ldquo;trimming&rdquo; or &ldquo;accounting for&rdquo; measurement invariance, which occurs when participants of different groups (e.g., gender, age, race) systematically respond to scale items in different ways, indicating differences in interpretation. Based on an analysis of measurement invariance of our survey data related to critical consciousness (CC) and ethnic-racial identity (ERI), <strong>we found that</strong><strong> </strong>participants of color reported higher ERI exploration and commitment than white participants, and white participants showed greater variance on ERI exploration than participants of color. <strong>Differential item functioning was found on two ERI items and three CC items, suggesting a lack of measurement invariance across racial groups.</strong> <strong>We interpreted these results through the lens of QuantCrit, which draws on Critical Race Theory to guide and assess statistical analyses and results in sociocultural context. </strong>Rather than trimming or accounting for this type of measurement invariance, we propose that such differences can help elucidate possibilities for scales more attuned to participant positionality in the context of racial inequity.</p> <p><strong>Broader Impact</strong></p> <p><strong>This project offered Dr. Moffitt rigorous training in conducting longitudinal, mixed-methods data collection and analysis.</strong> Additionally, she was able to mentor and collaborate with multiple undergraduate and graduate students of diverse racial, gender, and socioeconomic backgrounds, helping prepare her for a career in academia while offering the students foundational research experience. <strong>The results of these initial analyses</strong> <strong>offer novel insights into the constructs of critical consciousness and ethnic-racial identity development, extending previous research and building theory.</strong></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/30/2022<br>      Modified by: Ursula&nbsp;E&nbsp;Moffitt</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The aim of this project was to investigate how racially diverse young adults attending a predominantly white institution navigated the socio-political climate surrounding the 2020 U.S. presidential election as they developed their identities and beliefs about the world. To achieve this aim, survey data were collected in the fall of 2020 (Time 1) and spring of 2021 (Time 4), and qualitative, open-response data were collected across 10 days surrounding the U.S. presidential election in November 2020 (Time 2) and 10 days surrounding the U.S. presidential inauguration in January 2021 (Time 3).  Key Findings  In an initial analysis of the qualitative data, we examined participants’ responses to a prompt asking them to recount and reflect on recent conversations related to race. Our sample for this study included 47 students (Mage= 19.71, SD = 1.72; 81% female, 17% male, 2% other; 45% Asian/Asian American, 30% white, 13% Latinx/Hispanic, 4% Black/African American, 4% Multiracial, 2% Middle Eastern/Arab). Based on inductive coding, we found that a majority of participants reported conversations with peers, focused primarily on racial inequity and justice.  Subsequent deductive coding was guided by the theoretical frameworks of critical consciousness, which includes awareness of societal inequity (critical reflection), belief in the possibility of socio-political change (political efficacy), and individual action toward change (critical action), as well as racial identity meaning making, which includes reflection on one’s own identity and role within their racial group. We found that among participants of color, links were drawn between events and issues such as the Black Lives Matter movement, anti-Asian violence, or the presidential election, and their own daily lives. For many of these students, talking about race in society was inextricable from talking about their own racial identities. This finding supports previous research showing that youth of color who experience racism and/or racial socialization may be prompted toward critical reflection, which may be strengthened by racial identity exploration. Thus, for many young People of Color, conversations with peers offered spaces for critical reflection, which led to meaning making about their racial identities. However, our participants narratives evidenced that these processes are interwoven, with reflections on individual experiences often embedded in reflection on socio-political and historical issues. This finding extends previous research and theory and makes clear that future longitudinal research should examine the reciprocal nature of these processes, paying attention to the role of the socio-political context.  In contrast, we did not find evidence of racial identity meaning making among white participants. Instead, most white participants situated race as outside of and disconnected from their lives&mdash;either not relevant or only relevant to "other" people. While many white participants wrote about their hopes, fears, or frustrations, especially related to the political sphere, whiteness generally remained unnamed and unexamined. Our findings show that more work is needed to better understand the ways in which positionality shapes developmental processes related to critical consciousness and racial identity development. Without taking the socio-political context into account, group-based differences can seem static and neutral&mdash;occurring because of one’s racial group membership&mdash;rather than in relation to the racialized systems of power and oppression shaping our society.  Dovetailing with these qualitative findings, our initial quantitative analysis pushes psychologists to reflect critically on the origins of the constructs they use and to examine the implications of "trimming" or "accounting for" measurement invariance, which occurs when participants of different groups (e.g., gender, age, race) systematically respond to scale items in different ways, indicating differences in interpretation. Based on an analysis of measurement invariance of our survey data related to critical consciousness (CC) and ethnic-racial identity (ERI), we found that participants of color reported higher ERI exploration and commitment than white participants, and white participants showed greater variance on ERI exploration than participants of color. Differential item functioning was found on two ERI items and three CC items, suggesting a lack of measurement invariance across racial groups. We interpreted these results through the lens of QuantCrit, which draws on Critical Race Theory to guide and assess statistical analyses and results in sociocultural context. Rather than trimming or accounting for this type of measurement invariance, we propose that such differences can help elucidate possibilities for scales more attuned to participant positionality in the context of racial inequity.  Broader Impact  This project offered Dr. Moffitt rigorous training in conducting longitudinal, mixed-methods data collection and analysis. Additionally, she was able to mentor and collaborate with multiple undergraduate and graduate students of diverse racial, gender, and socioeconomic backgrounds, helping prepare her for a career in academia while offering the students foundational research experience. The results of these initial analyses offer novel insights into the constructs of critical consciousness and ethnic-racial identity development, extending previous research and building theory.       Last Modified: 08/30/2022       Submitted by: Ursula E Moffitt]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
