<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Building Capacity for Inclusive Informal STEM Learning Opportunities for People with Autism Spectrum Disorder]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1041443.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1041443</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DRL</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Julie Johnson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jjohnson@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928624</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Over the past two decades the prevalence of Autism Spectrum Disorder (ASD) has nearly tripled and yet there is much to learn about serving this audience well. After high school exit, most are left to navigate the world without appropriate support or the requisite skills necessary for success. Educators working in informal science institutions (ISI) can better promote both social interaction and engagement in STEM education for individuals with ASD. A learning environment in which the learner chooses content aligned with their personal interests and where learning can be multifaceted (verbal, hands-on, fast or slow, social or solitary, directed or inquiry based, physical, etc.) is consistent with the central tenets of an evidence-based, outcome-driven approach for autism intervention. ISI educators have the desire but may not have sufficient and timely knowledge and skills to engage and support this audience. Currently, many are working at the local level to develop new programs and approaches for patrons with ASD, with little evaluation or research and not building on each other’s work. The project will develop a rigorous customized professional learning experience designed to enhance capacity of ISIs broadly in ASD support techniques and strategies. The goal is to enable more inclusive opportunities for people with ASD based on current and emerging promising practices. The project’s theory of action is that the ability of people with ASD to participate in traditional, mainstream experiences will improve their motivation to seek other similar opportunities, build interpersonal skills critical to successful interaction in society, formal education, and careers. This, in turn, will help individuals with ASD gain the skills and confidence needed to pursue STEM academically and professionally. The project is a collaboration between the Institute for Learning Innovation, the SciTech Institute, and the Southwest Autism Research &amp; Resource Center (SARRC). This project is funded by the Advanced Informal STEM Learning program which seeks to advance new approaches to, and evidence-based understanding of, the design and development of STEM learning in informal environments. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The pilot’s main research questions are: (1) To what degree does the professional learning program support the learning outcomes in knowledge, awareness, interest, skills, attitude, and behavior change in informal science education providers? and (2) What features of the program do educators consider most effective for improving their ability to serve this audience? Four Arizona ISIs will participate in a research-based design study; their staff will also comprise the founding members of a Community of Practice aimed at sharing promising practices and promoting broader engagement among the informal science education community. The professional development (PD) will be provided by SARRC. New formative evaluation skills will support ongoing innovation and build participant capacity. Leveraging this training, the ISIs will create and test new approaches and programs, apply new skills in formative evaluation, and develop internal workplace programs to create cultures of ASD understanding. A pilot research study will recruit 20 diverse individuals with ASD who will visit each institution prior to and after the PD for staff. The research will measure the degree to which the PD impacts attendee experience as well as assess the science learning that occurred because of their visit. This project will advance collaboration between ASD experts and ISI educators to iteratively develop effective museum learning strategies. Other goals of this work are to provide important insights into (a) the current state of accessibility programs in ISI venues nationally, (b) how PD can be leveraged to help institutions reach true inclusion, and (c) initial evidenced-based approaches for inclusion of individuals on the Autism spectrum in mainstream informal environments. In addition to the research findings, deliverables include an ASD PD model, national inventory of current practices and programs that support ASD learning and participation, and the establishment of a Community of Practice.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/19/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/06/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2005901</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jeremy</FirstName>
<LastName>Babendure</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jeremy R Babendure</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jbabendure@scitechinstitute.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000708704</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/19/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Judith</FirstName>
<LastName>Koke</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Judith M Koke</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[judy.koke@freechoicelearning.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000779419</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/19/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Christopher</FirstName>
<LastName>Smith</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Christopher J Smith</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[csmith@autismcenter.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000788611</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/19/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Institute for Learning Innovation</Name>
<CityName>PORTLAND</CityName>
<ZipCode>972174141</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4432230694</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5637 N GREELEY AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OR03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>HYX9HNCUQC35</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>INSTITUTE FOR LEARNING INNOVATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Institute for Learning Innovation]]></Name>
<CityName>Beaverton</CityName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<ZipCode>970087015</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[9450 SW Gemini Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OR06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7259</Code>
<Text>AISL</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8212</Code>
<Text>Broaden Particip STEM Resrch</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0420</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0422</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>04002223DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~845215</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2022~196228</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Institute for learning Innovation (ILI) project worked with a partner organization, the Southwestern Autism Research and Resource Center (SARRC), to adapt SARRC?s existing, respected training program, largely designed for teachers and parents, for four science museums in the Phoenix area. In addition to leading and developing an active Community of Practice comprising four representatives of each of four participating museums, a SARRC behavior specialist worked across all departments of four diverse ISE museums to ensure staff received in-person instruction and feedback on creating effective learning opportunities for individuals on the autism spectrum. Two research projects focused on understanding the culture shift required in museums to support the full integration of neurodiverse audiences beyond special times and programs, and to understand the impact of the training on the experience of visitor on the autism spectrum.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>By developing a model of Professional Development that offers a unique pathway to support Informal Science Learning (ISL) environments in broadening access to and engagement in STEM learning for ASD populations, participating museums are supported in building new approaches to the design and development of informal STEM learning offerings that are more broadly accessible and effective. ILI?s research demonstrated that the professional development offered by this project was indeed successful in shifting organizational culture in the awareness, interest, and skill in better supporting the ASD community. However, it became quicky apparent that sustaining this shift was more difficult than achieving it, largely due to high levels of staff turnover and the high level of in-person staff training needed for the training. This is why our next steps will be to create an embedded, hybrid training tool.</p> <p>In addition, the project worked to provide important insights into the current state of accessibility programs in ISL venues nationally. Four museum websites from two major cities in each of the fifty states were reviewed for their online communication regarding support of this audience. A series of case study interviews with a subset of eight museums allowed us to identify an important gap between what museums have developed to support neurodiverse audiences, and the public?s ability to find information about those supports. Museum professionals? have a growing awareness of that gap and spoke to ongoing work to bolster their online and onsite communications about accessibility offerings available at their institutions. Several museums interviewed mentioned long term plans to reorganize and establish consistency between their accessibility information online, exhibition signage, and staff training.</p> <p>The SARRC research identified areas of improvement to better support individuals on the autism spectrum (and inclusion for all patrons) in informal science learning venues. They identified that various practices in current usage (e.g., autism only nights, negative interactions with staff, poor signage, and negative impressions from other patrons) do not promote true inclusion, and changes that do promote inclusion are supportive staff interactions and hands-on activities. The interviews demonstrated that the learning environment and staff interactions benefit from training in inclusive practices.</p> <p>The broader impacts of this project are a deeper understanding of autism and inclusion in content, delivery, and support by ISL staff and organizations. In turn this deeper understanding is helping us to understand how to increase the inclusion of individuals on the autism spectrum in traditional, mainstream ISL environments. As well, the museums developed new relationships and skills in gathering visitor input through ASD youth advisory committees and front-end and formative evaluation learning.</p> <p>The overarching impact of this work will help museum staff assume the responsibility for providing a better learning experience not only for patrons with neuro-differences but for all patrons. If autistic adolescents see informal science learning environments as supportive and welcoming learning opportunities, they may be more likely to choose academic and occupational paths that are STEM-related. Additionally, creating inclusive spaces for neuroatypical individuals in public places creates a positive model for their neurotypical peers who then may be more tolerant of individual differences.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/30/2023<br>      Modified by: Judith&nbsp;M&nbsp;Koke</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2005901/2005901_10686912_1698674067312_1000002025--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2005901/2005901_10686912_1698674067312_1000002025--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Sharing Findings"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2005901/2005901_10686912_1698674067312_1000002025--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Sharing Findings"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Nicole Claudio presenting the results of the first phase of the National Inventory at Visitor Studies Association  2022 annual conference.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Nicole Claudio</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Judith&nbsp;M&nbsp;Koke</div> <div class="imageTitle">Sharing Findings</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Institute for learning Innovation (ILI) project worked with a partner organization, the Southwestern Autism Research and Resource Center (SARRC), to adapt SARRC?s existing, respected training program, largely designed for teachers and parents, for four science museums in the Phoenix area. In addition to leading and developing an active Community of Practice comprising four representatives of each of four participating museums, a SARRC behavior specialist worked across all departments of four diverse ISE museums to ensure staff received in-person instruction and feedback on creating effective learning opportunities for individuals on the autism spectrum. Two research projects focused on understanding the culture shift required in museums to support the full integration of neurodiverse audiences beyond special times and programs, and to understand the impact of the training on the experience of visitor on the autism spectrum.     By developing a model of Professional Development that offers a unique pathway to support Informal Science Learning (ISL) environments in broadening access to and engagement in STEM learning for ASD populations, participating museums are supported in building new approaches to the design and development of informal STEM learning offerings that are more broadly accessible and effective. ILI?s research demonstrated that the professional development offered by this project was indeed successful in shifting organizational culture in the awareness, interest, and skill in better supporting the ASD community. However, it became quicky apparent that sustaining this shift was more difficult than achieving it, largely due to high levels of staff turnover and the high level of in-person staff training needed for the training. This is why our next steps will be to create an embedded, hybrid training tool.  In addition, the project worked to provide important insights into the current state of accessibility programs in ISL venues nationally. Four museum websites from two major cities in each of the fifty states were reviewed for their online communication regarding support of this audience. A series of case study interviews with a subset of eight museums allowed us to identify an important gap between what museums have developed to support neurodiverse audiences, and the public?s ability to find information about those supports. Museum professionals? have a growing awareness of that gap and spoke to ongoing work to bolster their online and onsite communications about accessibility offerings available at their institutions. Several museums interviewed mentioned long term plans to reorganize and establish consistency between their accessibility information online, exhibition signage, and staff training.  The SARRC research identified areas of improvement to better support individuals on the autism spectrum (and inclusion for all patrons) in informal science learning venues. They identified that various practices in current usage (e.g., autism only nights, negative interactions with staff, poor signage, and negative impressions from other patrons) do not promote true inclusion, and changes that do promote inclusion are supportive staff interactions and hands-on activities. The interviews demonstrated that the learning environment and staff interactions benefit from training in inclusive practices.  The broader impacts of this project are a deeper understanding of autism and inclusion in content, delivery, and support by ISL staff and organizations. In turn this deeper understanding is helping us to understand how to increase the inclusion of individuals on the autism spectrum in traditional, mainstream ISL environments. As well, the museums developed new relationships and skills in gathering visitor input through ASD youth advisory committees and front-end and formative evaluation learning.  The overarching impact of this work will help museum staff assume the responsibility for providing a better learning experience not only for patrons with neuro-differences but for all patrons. If autistic adolescents see informal science learning environments as supportive and welcoming learning opportunities, they may be more likely to choose academic and occupational paths that are STEM-related. Additionally, creating inclusive spaces for neuroatypical individuals in public places creates a positive model for their neurotypical peers who then may be more tolerant of individual differences.                Last Modified: 10/30/2023       Submitted by: Judith M Koke]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
