<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Control and Optimization of Semi-Dissipative Systems]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>79759.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>79759</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Pedro Embid</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>pembid@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924859</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Transport and mixing play central roles in the circulation of the atmosphere and oceans, the spreading of environmental pollutants, the ventilation in buildings, the mixing of chemical substances, and many other phenomena in natural and engineered systems. The questions of what velocity fields effectively enhance or prevent transport and mixing, or steer quantities (such as mass concentration or density distribution) to a desired distribution, have attracted increasing attention. This project aims to use modern techniques from optimal control theory, nonlinear partial differential equations, and nonconvex and nonsmooth optimization to address these questions. The project will foster interdisciplinary collaboration and education efforts among different research groups and will also help train advanced undergraduate and graduate students across fields including mathematics, mechanical engineering, and chemical engineering to conduct collaborative research in optimal transport and mixing, flow control, and computational methods.  &lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;The objective of this research is to establish an innovative and rigorous mathematical framework for achieving optimal transport and mixing via active control of fluid flows. The project focuses on (1) optimizing transport and mixing via control of the incompressible Navier-Stokes equations, with internal (distributed) and boundary control designs employed for different physical applications; (2) investigating the transport behavior of non-dissipative scalars, both passive and active, governed by the transport equations and addressing active transport through buoyancy-driven flows, modeled by the 2D Boussinesq approximation; and (3) applying non-smooth regularization to improve the sparsity of the controls. Investigation of the existence of an optimal control, differentiability of the coupled nonlinear system, and derivation of optimality conditions promises to launch new directions in nonlinear control, nonconvex optimization, and nonsmooth analysis of semi-dissipative systems. It will also contribute to the development of effective computational methods. The optimal control synthesis developed in this project will enable the study of similar phenomena arising in other complex flows, such as mass transfer in electrically conducting fluids, heat exchange in compressible flows, and double diffusion in oceanography, that are of great interest to a broad range of scientists and engineers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/25/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/01/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2005696</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Weiwei</FirstName>
<LastName>Hu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Weiwei Hu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[Weiwei.Hu@uga.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000710911</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/25/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Georgia Research Foundation Inc</Name>
<CityName>ATHENS</CityName>
<ZipCode>306021589</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7065425939</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>310 E CAMPUS RD RM 409</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NMJHD63STRC5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF GEORGIA RESEARCH FOUNDATION, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Georgia]]></Name>
<CityName>Athens</CityName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>306021589</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Department of Mathematics Boyd Graduate Studies Research Center]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1266</Code>
<Text>APPLIED MATHEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01001819DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01001920DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~459</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~30085</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~49215</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The PI has establish an innovative and rigorous theoretical and computational&nbsp; framework for control and optimization of nonlinear semi-dissipative system governed by the coupled transport and fluid flow equations. Specifically, <br /><br />1.&nbsp; The PI has developed&nbsp; a&nbsp; rigorous&nbsp; control synthesis for&nbsp; optimal mixing of an inhomogeneous distribution of a scalar field&nbsp; via an active control of the flow velocity, governed by the incompressible Stokes or the&nbsp; Navier-Stokes equations in an open bounded and connected domain.&nbsp; The&nbsp; velocity field&nbsp; is steered by the control input exerted tangentially on the domain boundary through the&nbsp; Navier slip boundary conditions. This problem is motivated by&nbsp; mixing the fluids within a cavity or vessel&nbsp; by moving the walls or stirring at the boundaries. Our main objective&nbsp; is to design an optimal Navier&nbsp; slip boundary&nbsp; control&nbsp; that optimizes mixing at a given final time. Non-dissipative scalars, both passive and active, governed by the transport equation will be addressed.&nbsp; In the absence of diffusion, transport and mixing occur due to pure advection. This essentially leads to a nonlinear control problem of a semi-dissipative system.&nbsp; The uniqueness of the optimal solution in general does not hold. Sobolev norm of the dual space $(H^{1})'$ is adopted to quantify&nbsp; mixing due to the property of weak convergence.&nbsp;&nbsp; The challenge arises from the vanishing diffusivity&nbsp; and nonlinear coupling of the system, which results in&nbsp; high regularity requirement on the velocity.&nbsp; We have established&nbsp;&nbsp; a rigorous&nbsp; proof to show&nbsp;&nbsp; the existence of an&nbsp; optimal control for both passive and active scalars and that the compatibility conditions for initial and boundary data are not required for Navier slip boundary control. We also derived&nbsp; the first-order necessary conditions for optimality for both cases by using a variational inequality. However,&nbsp; the time derivative of&nbsp; the boundary&nbsp;&nbsp; input&nbsp; has to be penalized in&nbsp; the cost functional&nbsp; to meet the higher<br />&nbsp; regularity required for the velocity.&nbsp;&nbsp; As a result, the optimal control has to be solved from a&nbsp; two point boundary value problem.<br />&nbsp; <br />2. To lower the regularity required on the velocity field, our next work utilized an approximating control design to overcome this challenge and it led to&nbsp; a more transparent&nbsp; optimality system&nbsp; for characterizing and solving the optimal solution. This was achieved&nbsp; by first introducing a small diffusivity&nbsp; to the&nbsp; transport equation and then establishing&nbsp; a rigorous analysis of&nbsp; convergence of the approximating control problem to the original one as the diffusivity converges&nbsp;&nbsp; to zero.&nbsp; Moreover,&nbsp; uniqueness of the optimal solution&nbsp; was obtained for 2D problem under certain small conditions.</p> <p><br />3.&nbsp; To solve the resulting optimality system for an optimal control, however,&nbsp; one has to solve the governing system forward in time, coupled with&nbsp; the adjoint system backward in time together with a nonlinear optimality condition.&nbsp; Straightforward use of this theory can result in extremely to impossibly&nbsp; high computational costs.&nbsp; Therefore, we further considered&nbsp;&nbsp; closed-loop feedback controls&nbsp;&nbsp; and&nbsp; the corresponding feasible computational methods for optimization and stabilization of both passive and active transport and mixing.&nbsp; &nbsp;<br />The feedback laws were constructed based on the ideas of instantaneous control as well as a direct approximation of the optimality system derived from an optimal open-loop control problem. It can be shown that under appropriate&nbsp; numerical discretization&nbsp; schemes, two approaches generate the same sub-optimal feedback law. On the other hand, different discretization schemes may result in feedback laws of different regularity, which determine different mixing results.&nbsp; Finally, we applied mixed continuous Galerkin&nbsp; (CG) and&nbsp; discontinuous Galerkin (DG) methods to discretize&nbsp; the closed-loop system. Numerical&nbsp; experiments for&nbsp; mixing in Stoked flows were conducted&nbsp; to demonstrate our ideas and compare the effectiveness of&nbsp; different&nbsp; feedback laws.</p> <p><br />4. The PI also applied $L^1$-optimization for nonlinear control and parameter identification of&nbsp; repairable systems and network dynamics&nbsp; modeled by<br />the coupled integral and transport equations.<br /><br />Our control synthesis&nbsp; leads to novel insights into the understanding of nonlinear control and non-convex optimization of semi-dissipative systems and provides&nbsp; mathematical&nbsp; guidance for real life applications. Moreover, this project trained advanced undergraduate and graduate students to conduct research in optimal transport and&nbsp; flow control problems governed by infinite dimensional systems. There are total 13 journals papers and 6 conference papers published under the support of this grant.&nbsp; The results have been presented in several IEEE, SIAM and AMS conferences/workshops and departmental seminars.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/06/2023<br>      Modified by: Weiwei&nbsp;Hu</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The PI has establish an innovative and rigorous theoretical and computational  framework for control and optimization of nonlinear semi-dissipative system governed by the coupled transport and fluid flow equations. Specifically,   1.  The PI has developed  a  rigorous  control synthesis for  optimal mixing of an inhomogeneous distribution of a scalar field  via an active control of the flow velocity, governed by the incompressible Stokes or the  Navier-Stokes equations in an open bounded and connected domain.  The  velocity field  is steered by the control input exerted tangentially on the domain boundary through the  Navier slip boundary conditions. This problem is motivated by  mixing the fluids within a cavity or vessel  by moving the walls or stirring at the boundaries. Our main objective  is to design an optimal Navier  slip boundary  control  that optimizes mixing at a given final time. Non-dissipative scalars, both passive and active, governed by the transport equation will be addressed.  In the absence of diffusion, transport and mixing occur due to pure advection. This essentially leads to a nonlinear control problem of a semi-dissipative system.  The uniqueness of the optimal solution in general does not hold. Sobolev norm of the dual space $(H^{1})'$ is adopted to quantify  mixing due to the property of weak convergence.   The challenge arises from the vanishing diffusivity  and nonlinear coupling of the system, which results in  high regularity requirement on the velocity.  We have established   a rigorous  proof to show   the existence of an  optimal control for both passive and active scalars and that the compatibility conditions for initial and boundary data are not required for Navier slip boundary control. We also derived  the first-order necessary conditions for optimality for both cases by using a variational inequality. However,  the time derivative of  the boundary   input  has to be penalized in  the cost functional  to meet the higher   regularity required for the velocity.   As a result, the optimal control has to be solved from a  two point boundary value problem.    2. To lower the regularity required on the velocity field, our next work utilized an approximating control design to overcome this challenge and it led to  a more transparent  optimality system  for characterizing and solving the optimal solution. This was achieved  by first introducing a small diffusivity  to the  transport equation and then establishing  a rigorous analysis of  convergence of the approximating control problem to the original one as the diffusivity converges   to zero.  Moreover,  uniqueness of the optimal solution  was obtained for 2D problem under certain small conditions.   3.  To solve the resulting optimality system for an optimal control, however,  one has to solve the governing system forward in time, coupled with  the adjoint system backward in time together with a nonlinear optimality condition.  Straightforward use of this theory can result in extremely to impossibly  high computational costs.  Therefore, we further considered   closed-loop feedback controls   and  the corresponding feasible computational methods for optimization and stabilization of both passive and active transport and mixing.    The feedback laws were constructed based on the ideas of instantaneous control as well as a direct approximation of the optimality system derived from an optimal open-loop control problem. It can be shown that under appropriate  numerical discretization  schemes, two approaches generate the same sub-optimal feedback law. On the other hand, different discretization schemes may result in feedback laws of different regularity, which determine different mixing results.  Finally, we applied mixed continuous Galerkin  (CG) and  discontinuous Galerkin (DG) methods to discretize  the closed-loop system. Numerical  experiments for  mixing in Stoked flows were conducted  to demonstrate our ideas and compare the effectiveness of  different  feedback laws.   4. The PI also applied $L^1$-optimization for nonlinear control and parameter identification of  repairable systems and network dynamics  modeled by the coupled integral and transport equations.  Our control synthesis  leads to novel insights into the understanding of nonlinear control and non-convex optimization of semi-dissipative systems and provides  mathematical  guidance for real life applications. Moreover, this project trained advanced undergraduate and graduate students to conduct research in optimal transport and  flow control problems governed by infinite dimensional systems. There are total 13 journals papers and 6 conference papers published under the support of this grant.  The results have been presented in several IEEE, SIAM and AMS conferences/workshops and departmental seminars.       Last Modified: 10/06/2023       Submitted by: Weiwei Hu]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
