<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[NSF Student Travel Support for 2020 ACM Special Interest Group of Management of Data (ACM SIGMOD)]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>20929.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>20929</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Hector Munoz-Avila</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>hmunoz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924481</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This National Science Foundation award funds Student Travel Fellowships for US students attending SIGMOD 2020, the 2020 ACM SIGMOD International Conference on Management of Data, which will be held in Portland, Oregon, USA (https://sigmod2020.org/) from June 14 to June 19, 2020. The Student Fellowships will help cover the travel costs for 16 US students (out of which 8 will be females and from under-represented groups and at least 4 will be first-time undergraduate students), making it possible for them to attend the conference and discuss and disseminate their work. The conference also provides an opportunity for them to interact with future national and international scientific collaborators. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The SIGMOD conference, which was established in 1975, has a dynamic and comprehensive program for publication, education, and interaction, including research papers, tutorials, panels, industrial papers, technical demonstrations, and undergraduate research papers. The program includes publications relating to all aspects of data management defined broadly, and particularly encourages publications on topics of emerging interest in the research and development communities. The program also includes workshops that showcase dedicated coverage due to their relevance to the current data management research and development, industrial exhibits, and keynote talks by leaders in academia and industry. All these activities provide a unique opportunity for students to share their knowledge, experience, and research work with internationally recognized researchers from both academia and industry. In recent years, more than 800 attendees attended SIGMOD, and we expect the same this year as well.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/21/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/21/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2005422</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Min</FirstName>
<LastName>Chen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Min Chen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[minchen2@u.washington.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000558455</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/21/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Washington</Name>
<CityName>SEATTLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>981951016</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2065434043</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4333 BROOKLYN AVE NE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>HD1WMN6945W6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF WASHINGTON</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Washington]]></Name>
<CityName>Seattle</CityName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>981950001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4333 Brooklyn Ave NE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7364</Code>
<Text>Info Integration &amp; Informatics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7364</Code>
<Text>INFO INTEGRATION &amp; INFORMATICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~20929</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The grant was initially applied to support students&rsquo; travel to attend 2020 ACM SIGMOD conference. However, due to COVID-19, the conference was moved to online (<a title="https://sigmod2020.org/covid19.shtml" href="https://sigmod2020.org/covid19.shtml">https://sigmod2020.org/covid19.shtml</a>) with no travel cost. Therefore, the PI applied for no cost extension and was approved to use it for the 2022 SIGMOD conference (https://2022.sigmod.org/grants.shtml).</p> <p>We have successfully achieved outcomes as planned throughout the project. First, the PI joined the SIGMOD&nbsp;2022 Student Travel Award Selection Committee. We announced the travel scholarship opportunity broadly to ACM SIGMOD and other mailing lists in related fields (such as KDD, IR, AI, and HPC) to attract greater student participation, especially those who are <span>females and under-represented.&nbsp;</span>We reviewed a large number of student applications and recommended&nbsp;16 students currently matriculated in US institutions&nbsp;for the travel scholarship awards.&nbsp;This served the intended goal to provide opportunity for students to present their research results, learn the cutting-edge research, and interact with experts in the best data management conference. Second, among 16 awardees,&nbsp;8 are from females and under-represented groups. It&nbsp;encouraged and facilitated the participation of under-represented groups in the top-tier computer science conference.&nbsp;The conference itself and all conference attendees also benefited from the attendance of students and under-represented groups. It can lead to far-reaching benefit of&nbsp;training and developing the future generation of leaders and workforce in this increasingly critical field.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/02/2023<br>      Modified by: Min&nbsp;Chen</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The grant was initially applied to support students’ travel to attend 2020 ACM SIGMOD conference. However, due to COVID-19, the conference was moved to online (https://sigmod2020.org/covid19.shtml) with no travel cost. Therefore, the PI applied for no cost extension and was approved to use it for the 2022 SIGMOD conference (https://2022.sigmod.org/grants.shtml).  We have successfully achieved outcomes as planned throughout the project. First, the PI joined the SIGMOD 2022 Student Travel Award Selection Committee. We announced the travel scholarship opportunity broadly to ACM SIGMOD and other mailing lists in related fields (such as KDD, IR, AI, and HPC) to attract greater student participation, especially those who are females and under-represented. We reviewed a large number of student applications and recommended 16 students currently matriculated in US institutions for the travel scholarship awards. This served the intended goal to provide opportunity for students to present their research results, learn the cutting-edge research, and interact with experts in the best data management conference. Second, among 16 awardees, 8 are from females and under-represented groups. It encouraged and facilitated the participation of under-represented groups in the top-tier computer science conference. The conference itself and all conference attendees also benefited from the attendance of students and under-represented groups. It can lead to far-reaching benefit of training and developing the future generation of leaders and workforce in this increasingly critical field.       Last Modified: 05/02/2023       Submitted by: Min Chen]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
