<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Musculoskeletal modeling and simulation of hominin bipedal locomotion]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>138000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>124500</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SMA</Abbreviation>
<LongName>SBE Off Of Multidisciplinary Activities</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Josie Welkom Miranda</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jwmirand@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927376</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This award was provided as part of NSF's Social, Behavioral and Economic Sciences Postdoctoral Research Fellowships (SPRF) program. The goal of the SPRF program is to prepare promising, early career doctoral-level scientists for scientific careers in academia, industry or private sector, and government. SPRF awards involve two years of training under the sponsorship of established scientists and encourage Postdoctoral Fellows to perform independent research. NSF seeks to promote the participation of scientists from all segments of the scientific community, including those from underrepresented groups, in its research programs and activities; the postdoctoral period is considered to be an important level of professional development in attaining this goal. Each Postdoctoral Fellow must address important scientific questions that advance their respective disciplinary fields. Under the sponsorship of Dr. Ashley Heers at California State University, Los Angeles, this postdoctoral fellowship award supports an early career scientist creating a computer simulation of how human ancestors may have walked. While walking on two feet may seem mundane, this remarkable ability predates other uniquely human qualities, including a large brain, and separates us and our fossil lineage from other primates. All fossil human ancestors show some indication of walking on two feet, but several species, like 3.2 million-year-old Australopithecus afarensis, may have walked more like an upright chimpanzee than a modern human, or in a unique way all together.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Biomechanical modeling and simulation are quantitatively rigorous methods that have the unique ability to address this type of uncertainty. Modeling and simulation allow researchers to create realistic three-dimensional musculoskeletal models whose anatomical parameters can be individually manipulated to explicitly examine form-function relationships. By creating a musculoskeletal model of A. afarensis and bracketing parameters with data on humans and chimpanzees, this project will explore the hypotheses that A. afarensis was capable of chimp-like, human-like, or uniquely in-between bipedal walking, in conjunction with positive, stabilizing, or negative selection. Musculoskeletal modeling and simulation have previously been used to assess certain aspects of hominin locomotion, but a phylogenetically bracketed model based on the most up-to-date reconstructions has not yet been created or tested in a paleoanthropological context. This project will improve our understanding of locomotor potential in “mosaic”, “proto”, or “transitional” taxa during human evolution, and can inform evolutionary scenarios that will impact not only paleoanthropology, but also evolutionary biology. This project will also introduce data for future hypothesis testing, allowing researchers to explore how the locomotion of A. afarensis might have related to paleobiological variables like environment, diet, and social behavior.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/31/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/15/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2005009</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Anna</FirstName>
<LastName>Ragni</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Anna J Ragni</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<NSF_ID>000744277</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/31/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ashley</FirstName>
<LastName>Heers</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ashley M Heers</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<NSF_ID>000632014</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/31/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Ragni, Anna</Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<ZipCode>205600000</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT/>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG/>
<ORG_UEI_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[California State University, Los Angeles]]></Name>
<CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>900324206</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>34</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF/>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>040Y</Code>
<Text>(SPRF-FR) SBE Postdoctoral Res</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7137</Code>
<Text>POSTDOCTORAL FELLOWSHIPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~124500</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This postdoctoral project aimed to build a biomechanical model of the lower limb of Australopithecus afarensis, a ~3.2 million year old hominin. Using existing models of human (<em>Homo sapiens</em>) and chimpanzee (<em>Pan troglodytes</em>) lower limbs for reference, the goal was to establish limits of hominin locomotor capabilities at a critical stage of human evolution. Building this model explores the intersection of functional morphology, behavior, and biomechanics and is unique in that it uses a phylogenetically bracketed approach to better understand fossil hominin locomotion. At the end of the funding period, several goals were met. Three skeletal &lsquo;puppets&rsquo; were created: a human lower limb recreated from an existing model, a chimpanzee lower limb recreated from an existing model, and an <em>Australopithecus afarensis</em> lower limb using novel skeletal reconstructions. For each of these three models, joints were anatomically-defined based on articular surface morphology. Defining joints using the same protocols across the three models, allows kinematics to be compared and switched across models. Kinematics, or joint movements, were then taken from the literature and applied to the new human and chimpanzee skeletal puppets and their new joint definitions using a &lsquo;motion transfer protocol&rsquo; (Carney, 2016). &lsquo;Transitional&rsquo; kinematics were then interpolated from the human and chimpanzee kinematics to create the fossil joint movements. Remarkably, even when using a 50% blend of human and chimpanzee kinematics, the fossil lower limb appears to walk with a very human-like gait. Muscles were applied to the human and chimpanzee lower limb from existing models. Muscles for <em>Australopithecus afrensis</em> are in the process of being applied to the skeletal model. Once muscles have been applied to the model, analyses will begin to test whether this hominin was morphologically more suited to chimp-like, &lsquo;transitional&rsquo;, or human-like gaits. The broader impacts of this project involved the training of a female STEM scientist and several outreach activities. The PI mentored underrepresented undergraduate students in both biology and anthropology, delivered several scientific lectures open to the public, served on a panel open to undergraduates entitled &ldquo;What is graduate school?&rdquo;, and assisted an undergraduate academic club organize and host a research conference open to the entire California State Academic system.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/11/2022<br>      Modified by: Anna&nbsp;J&nbsp;Ragni</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This postdoctoral project aimed to build a biomechanical model of the lower limb of Australopithecus afarensis, a ~3.2 million year old hominin. Using existing models of human (Homo sapiens) and chimpanzee (Pan troglodytes) lower limbs for reference, the goal was to establish limits of hominin locomotor capabilities at a critical stage of human evolution. Building this model explores the intersection of functional morphology, behavior, and biomechanics and is unique in that it uses a phylogenetically bracketed approach to better understand fossil hominin locomotion. At the end of the funding period, several goals were met. Three skeletal ‘puppets’ were created: a human lower limb recreated from an existing model, a chimpanzee lower limb recreated from an existing model, and an Australopithecus afarensis lower limb using novel skeletal reconstructions. For each of these three models, joints were anatomically-defined based on articular surface morphology. Defining joints using the same protocols across the three models, allows kinematics to be compared and switched across models. Kinematics, or joint movements, were then taken from the literature and applied to the new human and chimpanzee skeletal puppets and their new joint definitions using a ‘motion transfer protocol’ (Carney, 2016). ‘Transitional’ kinematics were then interpolated from the human and chimpanzee kinematics to create the fossil joint movements. Remarkably, even when using a 50% blend of human and chimpanzee kinematics, the fossil lower limb appears to walk with a very human-like gait. Muscles were applied to the human and chimpanzee lower limb from existing models. Muscles for Australopithecus afrensis are in the process of being applied to the skeletal model. Once muscles have been applied to the model, analyses will begin to test whether this hominin was morphologically more suited to chimp-like, ‘transitional’, or human-like gaits. The broader impacts of this project involved the training of a female STEM scientist and several outreach activities. The PI mentored underrepresented undergraduate students in both biology and anthropology, delivered several scientific lectures open to the public, served on a panel open to undergraduates entitled "What is graduate school?", and assisted an undergraduate academic club organize and host a research conference open to the entire California State Academic system.           Last Modified: 07/11/2022       Submitted by: Anna J Ragni]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
