<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Student Support: Thirty-First Annual International Solid Freeform Fabrication (SFF) Symposium - An Additive Manufacturing Conference; Austin, Texas; 17-19 August 2020]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>49800.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>49800</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Bruce Kramer</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bkramer@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925348</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This NSF award will support student participation at the Thirty-First Solid Freeform Fabrication (SFF) Symposium, Austin, Texas, 17-19 August 2020. The SFF Symposium is a forum for transfer and dissemination of knowledge and understanding in the field of additive, freeform and hybrid manufacturing. The 2019 meeting drew 702 researchers from 25 different countries representing universities, companies and national laboratories. Similar attendance is expected in 2020 and students will have opportunities to interact and share ideas with top researchers from academia, research laboratories, industry, and students from both domestic and international universities.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In an effort to make the conference affordable, and therefore accessible to students, the travel award will contribute towards the conference registration fees of qualified awardees. The call for student support applications will be disseminated through: (1) emails to corresponding authors of submitted abstracts (due in April 2020), (2) emails to participants of recent SFF meetings (2017-2019), (3) SFF website and (4) social media (newsletter and LinkedIn posts). Submitted applications will go through a selection process by the conference committee using selection criteria that include (1) students must be from US institutions and (2) students must be actively participating in the conference through presenting a paper or poster, or participating in a competition, with preference given to students from underrepresented minorities. Student awardees will be invited to a luncheon panel discussing research and future career opportunities in additive manufacturing. This award will afford the next generation of leaders a global perspective, exposure to the latest cutting-edge ideas, and insights on future manufacturing challenges.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/17/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/17/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2005490</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Guhaprasanna</FirstName>
<LastName>Manogharan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Guhaprasanna Manogharan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[gum53@psu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000664451</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/17/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Pennsylvania State Univ University Park</Name>
<CityName>UNIVERSITY PARK</CityName>
<ZipCode>168021503</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8148651372</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>201 OLD MAIN</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>15</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA15</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NPM2J7MSCF61</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>THE PENNSYLVANIA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Pennsylvania State Univ University Park]]></Name>
<CityName>UNIVERSITY PARK</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>168027000</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[110 Technology Center Building]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT/>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA"</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>088Y</Code>
<Text>AM-Advanced Manufacturing</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>082E</Code>
<Text>MFG MACHINES &amp; METROLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>083E</Code>
<Text>MATERIAL TRANSFORMATION PROC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~49800</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This grant helped to support student participation in the 2021 Annual International Solid Freeform Fabrication (SFF) Symposium.&nbsp; The symposium took place virtually from August 2-4, 2021.&nbsp; It included papers on materials processing, modeling, process development, hybrid manufacturing and machine design for additive manufacturing. It should be noted that due to COVID-19 pandemic, the abstracts and papers from 2020 SFF (which was cancelled) that were accepted was automatically moved to 2021. Authors had the option to cancel/withdraw their 2020 submission. In addition, we actively solicited new submission for 2021 &ndash; 32<sup>nd</sup> SFF symposium.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>There were 465 registrants from 16 countries, including 167 students with 161 receiving NSF SFF student waiver (due to lower registration cost in 2021 &ndash; virtual only format, when compared to typical NSF SFF support of ~90 students in past years). The total number of oral and poster presentations was 403. The meeting consisted of a Monday morning plenary, 56 parallel technical sessions and a poster session. The organizers provided opportunities for networking and live interaction. There were a number of advantages to the virtual format, including elimination of parallel session time conflicts and reduced meeting cost. However, the consensus was that the in-person meeting format is strongly preferred.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>There are 140 papers in this conference proceedings. Papers marked &ldquo;REVIEWED&rdquo; in the title area were peer reviewed by two external reviewers. The Table of Contents file and Author-Attendee file have links to all the papers. We have sequentially numbered the pages of the papers to facilitate citation.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Manuscripts for this and all preceding SFF Symposia are available for free download at the conference website: https://www.sffsymposium.org/; select the &ldquo;Proceedings Archive&rdquo; pull-down menu item.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Thirteen materials-related papers were selected as best papers for inclusion in the journal JOM under the aegis of The Minerals, Metals &amp; Materials Society (TMS). Five of these papers were substantially improved for the journal with the original also appearing in this proceedings. Eight were moved with only minor modification; these do not appear in the proceedings. The abstracts of these eight papers appear in the proceedings with a note referring the reader to the JOM full article.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>These thirteen outstanding papers are notated in the Proceedings Table of Contents and were published in the March 2022 issue of JOM.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Intellectual Merit</strong></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Students experienced the multidisciplinary nature of the research, with various sessions emphasizing modeling, machine and process development, hybrid manufacturing, and materials processing for additive manufacturing.&nbsp; We believe that documenting the changing state of the art in additive manufacturing in the meeting presentations and proceedings provides a valuable service for not only seasoned researchers but also the flux of new researchers, users, and students entering the field. Information on the SFF Symposium was made available through a repository: http://sffsymposium.engr.utexas.edu/archive.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts</strong></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Wider dissemination was accomplished through the proceedings. The SFF Symposium serves as a primary forum for networking and dissemination of information dealing with research issues in freeform fabrication.&nbsp; According to Ian Campbell, senior editor of the<em> Rapid Prototyping Journal</em>, &ldquo;The SFF Symposium is to be regarded as the foremost international conference for rapid prototyping research (<em>RPJ</em>, 2003).&nbsp; On a recent tally by AM experts on the most significant milestones in the history of AM, with the exception of the invention of specific AM processes, the inauguration of the SFF Symposium ranks highest<em><sup>1</sup></em>.&nbsp; When asked which publications had greatest influence on the AM field, the Proceedings of the SFF Symposium tied with the only refereed archival journal dedicated solely to the AM field at the time, the British-based <em>Rapid Prototyping Journal<a href="https://pennstateoffice365-my.sharepoint.com/personal/gum53_psu_edu/Documents/NSF%20-%20SFF%202022/NSF%20-%20SFF%20-%202022/Project%20Outcomes%20+%20GPM.docx#_ftn1"><strong>[1]</strong></a></em>.&nbsp; This same group ranked the SFF Symposium highest by over 50% to the next conference when asked what meeting contributed most to the development of the AM field<em><sup>1</sup></em>. The SFF Symposium Conference Proceedings are heavily cited in the archival literature, and it is anticipated that the 2021 Proceedings will be as well.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><em>[1] Christopher L. Weber, et al., "The Role of the National Science Foundation in the Origin and Evolution of Additive Manufacturing in the United States", IDA Paper P-5091, IDA Science &amp; Technology Policy Institute, Washington, DC, 2013.</em></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Additive Manufacturing is an extremely broad and interdisciplinary field, encompassing mechanical engineering, electrical engineering, aerospace engineering, biomedical engineering, computer science and engineering, biology, design, materials science and engineering, and manufacturing science.&nbsp; The topics covered at the SFF symposium impact the automotive, aerospace, orthopedics, dentistry, gaming, surgical planning, implants, marine, architecture, furniture, and art industries, among others. The 2021 conference served as a forum for this diverse interdisciplinary group of researchers to present their research and learn from peer researchers. The networking aspect of the conference is strong and includes students who are able to meet and discuss research and tech transfer with world-class leading experts in the field.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <div> <hr size="1" /> <div> <p><a href="https://pennstateoffice365-my.sharepoint.com/personal/gum53_psu_edu/Documents/NSF%20-%20SFF%202022/NSF%20-%20SFF%20-%202022/Project%20Outcomes%20+%20GPM.docx#_ftnref1"></a>&nbsp;</p> </div> </div> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/04/2022<br>      Modified by: Guhaprasanna&nbsp;Manogharan</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This grant helped to support student participation in the 2021 Annual International Solid Freeform Fabrication (SFF) Symposium.  The symposium took place virtually from August 2-4, 2021.  It included papers on materials processing, modeling, process development, hybrid manufacturing and machine design for additive manufacturing. It should be noted that due to COVID-19 pandemic, the abstracts and papers from 2020 SFF (which was cancelled) that were accepted was automatically moved to 2021. Authors had the option to cancel/withdraw their 2020 submission. In addition, we actively solicited new submission for 2021 &ndash; 32nd SFF symposium.     There were 465 registrants from 16 countries, including 167 students with 161 receiving NSF SFF student waiver (due to lower registration cost in 2021 &ndash; virtual only format, when compared to typical NSF SFF support of ~90 students in past years). The total number of oral and poster presentations was 403. The meeting consisted of a Monday morning plenary, 56 parallel technical sessions and a poster session. The organizers provided opportunities for networking and live interaction. There were a number of advantages to the virtual format, including elimination of parallel session time conflicts and reduced meeting cost. However, the consensus was that the in-person meeting format is strongly preferred.     There are 140 papers in this conference proceedings. Papers marked "REVIEWED" in the title area were peer reviewed by two external reviewers. The Table of Contents file and Author-Attendee file have links to all the papers. We have sequentially numbered the pages of the papers to facilitate citation.     Manuscripts for this and all preceding SFF Symposia are available for free download at the conference website: https://www.sffsymposium.org/; select the "Proceedings Archive" pull-down menu item.     Thirteen materials-related papers were selected as best papers for inclusion in the journal JOM under the aegis of The Minerals, Metals &amp; Materials Society (TMS). Five of these papers were substantially improved for the journal with the original also appearing in this proceedings. Eight were moved with only minor modification; these do not appear in the proceedings. The abstracts of these eight papers appear in the proceedings with a note referring the reader to the JOM full article.     These thirteen outstanding papers are notated in the Proceedings Table of Contents and were published in the March 2022 issue of JOM.     Intellectual Merit     Students experienced the multidisciplinary nature of the research, with various sessions emphasizing modeling, machine and process development, hybrid manufacturing, and materials processing for additive manufacturing.  We believe that documenting the changing state of the art in additive manufacturing in the meeting presentations and proceedings provides a valuable service for not only seasoned researchers but also the flux of new researchers, users, and students entering the field. Information on the SFF Symposium was made available through a repository: http://sffsymposium.engr.utexas.edu/archive.      Broader Impacts     Wider dissemination was accomplished through the proceedings. The SFF Symposium serves as a primary forum for networking and dissemination of information dealing with research issues in freeform fabrication.  According to Ian Campbell, senior editor of the Rapid Prototyping Journal, "The SFF Symposium is to be regarded as the foremost international conference for rapid prototyping research (RPJ, 2003).  On a recent tally by AM experts on the most significant milestones in the history of AM, with the exception of the invention of specific AM processes, the inauguration of the SFF Symposium ranks highest1.  When asked which publications had greatest influence on the AM field, the Proceedings of the SFF Symposium tied with the only refereed archival journal dedicated solely to the AM field at the time, the British-based Rapid Prototyping Journal[1].  This same group ranked the SFF Symposium highest by over 50% to the next conference when asked what meeting contributed most to the development of the AM field1. The SFF Symposium Conference Proceedings are heavily cited in the archival literature, and it is anticipated that the 2021 Proceedings will be as well.     [1] Christopher L. Weber, et al., "The Role of the National Science Foundation in the Origin and Evolution of Additive Manufacturing in the United States", IDA Paper P-5091, IDA Science &amp; Technology Policy Institute, Washington, DC, 2013.     Additive Manufacturing is an extremely broad and interdisciplinary field, encompassing mechanical engineering, electrical engineering, aerospace engineering, biomedical engineering, computer science and engineering, biology, design, materials science and engineering, and manufacturing science.  The topics covered at the SFF symposium impact the automotive, aerospace, orthopedics, dentistry, gaming, surgical planning, implants, marine, architecture, furniture, and art industries, among others. The 2021 conference served as a forum for this diverse interdisciplinary group of researchers to present their research and learn from peer researchers. The networking aspect of the conference is strong and includes students who are able to meet and discuss research and tech transfer with world-class leading experts in the field.                        Last Modified: 05/04/2022       Submitted by: Guhaprasanna Manogharan]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
