<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research: The Development of Culturally Responsive Digital Media to Support STEM Knowledge Acquisition for English Learners]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>247881.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>247881</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DRL</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kevin A. Clark</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kevclark@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928191</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[As part of its overall strategy to enhance learning in informal environments, the Advancing Informal STEM Learning (AISL) program seeks to advance new approaches to, and evidence-based understanding of, the design and development of STEM learning in informal environments. This includes providing multiple pathways for broadening access to and engagement in STEM learning experiences, advancing innovative research on and assessment of STEM learning in informal environments, and developing understandings of deeper learning by participants. This project would expand the informal STEM learning field’s understanding of how to use digital science media to increase STEM educational experiences and opportunities for English language learners. Across the U.S. there are significant STEM opportunity and achievement gaps for English learners with varying levels of English proficiency. This is at a time when the U.S. is facing a shortage of STEM professionals in the workforce including the life and physical science fields. This project aims to close these gaps and improve English learners' STEM learning outcomes using digital media. Within community colleges, there are multiple site-based programs to provide content to help English learners to learn English and to improve their math and literacy skills. Involving the state community college networks is a critical strategy for gathering important feedback for the pedagogical approach as well as for recruiting English learner research participants. The team will initially study an existing YouTube chemistry series produced by Complexly then produce and test new videos in Spanish using culturally relevant instructional strategies. The target audience is 18-34-year-old English learners. Project partners are Complexly, a producer of digital STEM media and EDC, a research organization with experience in studying informal STEM learning. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project has the potential to advance knowledge about the use of culturally relevant media to improve STEM opportunities and success for English language learners. Using a Design-Based Implementation Research framework the research questions include: 1) what are the effective production and instructional strategies for creating digital media to teach science to English learners whose native language is Spanish? 2) what science content knowledge do English learners gain when the project’s approach is applied to a widely available set of YouTube videos? and 3) how might the findings from the research be applied to future efforts targeting English learners? The project has the potential to significantly broaden participation in science and engineering. Phase 1 of the research will be an exploration of how to apply strategic pedagogical approaches to digital media content development. Interviews will be conducted with educators in 3 focal states with high numbers of English language learners (NY, CA, TX) to reflect on pedagogical foundations for teaching science to English learners. A survey of 30 English learners will provide feedback on the perceived strengths and weaknesses of a selection of existing YouTube chemistry videos. Phase 2 will create/test prototypes of 6 adapted chemistry videos. Forty students (ages 18-34) will be recruited and participate in cognitive interviews with researchers after viewing these videos. Based on this input additional videos will be produced with revised instructional strategies for further testing. Additional rounds of production and testing will be conducted to develop an English learners mini chemistry series. Phase 3 will be a pilot study to gauge the science learning of 75 English learners who will view an 11-episode chemistry miniseries. It will also identify gaps in expected learning to determine whether any further adjustments are necessary to the instructional approach.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/26/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/23/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2005584</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kelsey</FirstName>
<LastName>Savage</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kelsey Savage</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[kelsey@complexly.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000813804</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/26/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ceridwen</FirstName>
<LastName>Riley</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ceridwen A Riley</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ceri@complexly.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000813967</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/26/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate>08/23/2021</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Stan</FirstName>
<LastName>Muller</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Stan Muller</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[stan@complexly.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000814018</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/26/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>COMPLEXLY LLC</Name>
<CityName>MISSOULA</CityName>
<ZipCode>598024202</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4066904863</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>224 W SPRUCE ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Montana</StateName>
<StateCode>MT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MT01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>F6CGN7N8MK63</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ECOGEEK LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[COMPLEXLY LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>Missoula</CityName>
<StateCode>MT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>598024202</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[224 W spruce st]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Montana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MT01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7259</Code>
<Text>AISL</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8212</Code>
<Text>Broaden Particip STEM Resrch</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0420</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~247881</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-4a6ce6bf-7fff-7d3e-f07c-a7dd4c00e1d7"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Education Development Center and Complexly collaborated on a project to advance strategies and cultural competencies that support ELs to develop STEM content knowledge. The project sought to adapt and improve content from </span><span>Crash Course</span><span>, a popular series based on the College Board&rsquo;s Advanced Placement curricula.&nbsp;</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Intellectual Merit:</span><span>&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>After reviewing the existing literature, the research team conducted a needs assessment to incorporate feedback from learners and educators. Fifteen Spanish-speaking community college students and nine ESL or science-based community college instructors participated. Both students and instructors provided feedback on existing Crash Course video clips and shared ideas for incorporating more culturally responsive teaching strategies. Key findings included the importance of using images and on-screen text to support learning for multilingual learners, making accessible connections to students&rsquo; lives, and providing real-world applications for complex content.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The production team used the needs assessment findings to inform an adapted syllabus for an 11-episode miniseries covering the foundational chemistry principles from the English-version and a series adaptation guide that created a plan for how to adapt the English version of the series into Spanish and incorpoate principles of culturally responsive teaching.&nbsp;</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Next, a formative research phase was designed to test the five initial prototype videos for the </span><span>Crash Course Qu&iacute;mica </span><span>series. The findings indicated that students and instructors appreciated the content a great deal, noting the value of the historical narratives, metaphors/analogies, and animations in supporting learning about chemistry. In large part, most students were able to respond correctly to the knowledge check questions for each of the videos, with few exceptions. In addition, students found the content interesting and enjoyable.&nbsp;Students suggested enhancing animations to better reflect students&rsquo; backgrounds and cultures, making the host&rsquo;s presentation style more relatable, and shortening the overall length of the episodes. </span><span><br /></span><span> </span><span><span> </span></span><span><span> </span></span><span><span> </span></span><span><span> </span></span><span><span> </span></span><span><span> </span></span><span><span> </span></span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Following the formative research, the Crash Course team revised the first five videos and developed an additional set of six videos to be used for the Pilot Study.&nbsp;Revisions included the addition of more visuals that used culturally relevant examples, editing the length of the videos by removing non-critical content for learning, and supporting the host during filming to maximize relatability and the use of more conversational and everyday language.&nbsp;</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>A final pilot study was conducted using the full 11-episode miniseries. The study was designed to test how students&rsquo; knowledge, interest, and self-efficacy in chemistry and science in general change because of watching Crash Course chemistry episodes. Fifty Spanish-speaking students were randomly assigned to one of three conditions. Data were collected via surveys and interviews. </span><span>Key findings include that Spanish-speaking students who watched the </span><span>Crash Course Qu&iacute;mica</span><span> videos in Spanish performed better on the knowledge check questions than the Spanish-speaking students who watched the videos in English. Spanish-speaking students who watched </span><span>Crash Course Qu&iacute;mica </span><span>reported higher interest in chemistry courses and enhanced enjoyment of learning about chemistry after watching the series. Most Spanish-speaking students who watched </span><span>Crash Course Qu&iacute;mica</span><span> reported that the episodes provided examples that reflected their background, experiences, and culture.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Taken together, the findings across this research have added to our evidence base that culturally responsive teaching strategies, as used in educational videos, can be supportive of learning above and beyond videos that do not contain the same connections and cultural relevancies. Furthermore, videos of this type can also be important in supporting learners' interest and in enhancing the enjoyment of learning about new topics.&nbsp;&nbsp;</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Broader Impact:</span><span>&nbsp;</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>As a result of this research we have created a set of recommendations for creating science learning content for multilingual learners.&nbsp;</span></p> <ul> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Avoid direct translation when adapting content from English to Spanish. Direct translation will miss many nuances that should be adapted when delivering content in another language.</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Carefully consider the relevance of examples that are being used to illustrate content or concepts. Who or what are the examples and how will they resonate with the intended audience?</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>When creating new Spanish content series based on the learning objectives of an English language series, develop and use an Adaptation Guide to communicate content objectives and important considerations for how content should be altered to maximize cultural relevance for Spanish-speaking video viewers.&nbsp;</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Support learners in their native language whenever possible when teaching complex content.</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Aim for a balance between appeal/entertainment and delivering content that has real-world applications. This combination resonates with adult learners regardless of language.</span></p> </li> </ul> <p dir="ltr"><span>&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The promising practices identified by this project have a strong potential to guide the development of engaging and rigorous digital media content for multilingual learners that focus on other STEM topics. The </span><span>Crash Course Qu&iacute;mica</span><span> miniseries has been posted to the Crash Course Youtube channel for access to the public.&nbsp;</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/31/2023<br>      Modified by: Kelsey&nbsp;Savage</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   Education Development Center and Complexly collaborated on a project to advance strategies and cultural competencies that support ELs to develop STEM content knowledge. The project sought to adapt and improve content from Crash Course, a popular series based on the College Board’s Advanced Placement curricula.     Intellectual Merit:  After reviewing the existing literature, the research team conducted a needs assessment to incorporate feedback from learners and educators. Fifteen Spanish-speaking community college students and nine ESL or science-based community college instructors participated. Both students and instructors provided feedback on existing Crash Course video clips and shared ideas for incorporating more culturally responsive teaching strategies. Key findings included the importance of using images and on-screen text to support learning for multilingual learners, making accessible connections to students’ lives, and providing real-world applications for complex content.    The production team used the needs assessment findings to inform an adapted syllabus for an 11-episode miniseries covering the foundational chemistry principles from the English-version and a series adaptation guide that created a plan for how to adapt the English version of the series into Spanish and incorpoate principles of culturally responsive teaching.     Next, a formative research phase was designed to test the five initial prototype videos for the Crash Course Qu&iacute;mica series. The findings indicated that students and instructors appreciated the content a great deal, noting the value of the historical narratives, metaphors/analogies, and animations in supporting learning about chemistry. In large part, most students were able to respond correctly to the knowledge check questions for each of the videos, with few exceptions. In addition, students found the content interesting and enjoyable. Students suggested enhancing animations to better reflect students’ backgrounds and cultures, making the host’s presentation style more relatable, and shortening the overall length of the episodes.           Following the formative research, the Crash Course team revised the first five videos and developed an additional set of six videos to be used for the Pilot Study. Revisions included the addition of more visuals that used culturally relevant examples, editing the length of the videos by removing non-critical content for learning, and supporting the host during filming to maximize relatability and the use of more conversational and everyday language.     A final pilot study was conducted using the full 11-episode miniseries. The study was designed to test how students’ knowledge, interest, and self-efficacy in chemistry and science in general change because of watching Crash Course chemistry episodes. Fifty Spanish-speaking students were randomly assigned to one of three conditions. Data were collected via surveys and interviews. Key findings include that Spanish-speaking students who watched the Crash Course Qu&iacute;mica videos in Spanish performed better on the knowledge check questions than the Spanish-speaking students who watched the videos in English. Spanish-speaking students who watched Crash Course Qu&iacute;mica reported higher interest in chemistry courses and enhanced enjoyment of learning about chemistry after watching the series. Most Spanish-speaking students who watched Crash Course Qu&iacute;mica reported that the episodes provided examples that reflected their background, experiences, and culture.    Taken together, the findings across this research have added to our evidence base that culturally responsive teaching strategies, as used in educational videos, can be supportive of learning above and beyond videos that do not contain the same connections and cultural relevancies. Furthermore, videos of this type can also be important in supporting learners' interest and in enhancing the enjoyment of learning about new topics.      Broader Impact:     As a result of this research we have created a set of recommendations for creating science learning content for multilingual learners.    Avoid direct translation when adapting content from English to Spanish. Direct translation will miss many nuances that should be adapted when delivering content in another language.   Carefully consider the relevance of examples that are being used to illustrate content or concepts. Who or what are the examples and how will they resonate with the intended audience?   When creating new Spanish content series based on the learning objectives of an English language series, develop and use an Adaptation Guide to communicate content objectives and important considerations for how content should be altered to maximize cultural relevance for Spanish-speaking video viewers.    Support learners in their native language whenever possible when teaching complex content.   Aim for a balance between appeal/entertainment and delivering content that has real-world applications. This combination resonates with adult learners regardless of language.     The promising practices identified by this project have a strong potential to guide the development of engaging and rigorous digital media content for multilingual learners that focus on other STEM topics. The Crash Course Qu&iacute;mica miniseries has been posted to the Crash Course Youtube channel for access to the public.           Last Modified: 07/31/2023       Submitted by: Kelsey Savage]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
