<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[I-Corps:   Low-weight Autonomous Underwater Vehicle (AUV) with Wireless Communication]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ruth Shuman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rshuman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922160</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this I-Corps project is the development of a high-bandwidth underwater wireless data communication for research and industry. Unlike communication in air where radio waves allow the transmission of data, voice or video wireless, a tether is required underwater to transmit similar information. The development of a new type of underwater vehicle that can send and receive data wirelessly will unlock new possibilities in ocean exploration and marine conservation as well as new economic development opportunities. This technology could provide a solution to efficiently map the seafloor, significantly improving search and rescue capabilities. Oceans cover 70% of the planet but more than 80% of the seafloor remains unmapped. This technology also could be used to better monitor offshore industrial activities and help to prevent environmental damage and ocean pollution. In addition, the vehicle could gather data that can be used to monitor ocean health and to better predict climate change. The technology may have application across all fields of the blue economy: offshore aquaculture, maritime defense, offshore energy, ocean observing and shipping. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project is based on the development of high-bandwidth underwater wireless data communication for seafloor mapping, environmental monitoring, underwater data collection and across all five fields of the blue economy. The technology is an underwater vehicle that can send and receive data using optical communication, which has a better range underwater than radio communication. This enables remote control the vehicle and it is possible to receive live feedback from the vehicle (e.g., live video stream) without the problems of using a tether. The vehicle also may be pre-programmed and operated in autonomous mode, and prototypes have been developed and tested in water tanks. Further development of the technology requires a better understanding of customer needs and requirements to achieve commercialization.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/21/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/27/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041, 47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2006307</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>M.-Reza</FirstName>
<LastName>Alam</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>M.-Reza Alam</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[reza.alam@berkeley.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000556127</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/21/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Berkeley</Name>
<CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
<ZipCode>947101749</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5106433891</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1608 4TH ST STE 201</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>GS3YEVSS12N6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>NUDGYLBB4S99</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Berkeley]]></Name>
<CityName>Berkeley</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>947201740</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[135 Hesse Hall, MC 1740]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>During the national i-Corps program, 164 interviews had been completed, 106 of which were in person, with potential customers and members of the ecosystem. The team attended three trade shows in New Orleans, San Antonio and Stamford specialized in underwater interventions, subsea operations and shipping. After carrying out a broad scan of the blue economy during the first 50 interviews, we realized that our swarm of Unmanned Underwater Vehicles (UUVs) could be useful in the maritime industry and focused our efforts in this customer segment by performing a deep dive in hull management practices for ships and coatings performance.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>At the end of the i-Corps curriculum, we decided to move ahead and incorporated a start-up to commercialize the technology investigated during the program. We found a beachhead market in the diving industry where our swarm of UUVs would provide an automated solution for hull inspection that would enable diving company managers to use their divers' time more efficiently on cleaning and repair jobs. This beachhead is a small market but is accessible for a small company and would be a path to the more lucrative market of hull performance management. Here, our technology could provide high-frequency visual biofouling data to enable coatings and ships performance managers to optimize cleaning schedule, shipping route and coating selection and save up to 25% in fuel and GHG emissions according to the International Maritime Organization.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Finally, the team applied to the NSF-SBIR program and received a Phase I award to build a first prototype for deployment in ports. EL/Dr. Alexandre Immas became CTO at Berkeley Marine Robotics and led the technical effort to bring this technology to market. Dr. A. Immas discussed Berkeley Marine Robotics commercialization roadmap, which is a result of the iCorps program, at a <em>TMA BlueTech Global Connect event &ldquo;Age of Autonomy: Swarm and Drone Tech</em>&rdquo; and presented Berkeley Marine Robotics technical and commercial development at the<em> 2nd Glofouling Partnerships R&amp;D Forum and Exhibition on Biofouling Prevention and Management for Maritime Industries </em>organized by the International Maritime Organization in London on October 11-14, 2022.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/18/2023<br>      Modified by: M.-Reza&nbsp;Alam</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ During the national i-Corps program, 164 interviews had been completed, 106 of which were in person, with potential customers and members of the ecosystem. The team attended three trade shows in New Orleans, San Antonio and Stamford specialized in underwater interventions, subsea operations and shipping. After carrying out a broad scan of the blue economy during the first 50 interviews, we realized that our swarm of Unmanned Underwater Vehicles (UUVs) could be useful in the maritime industry and focused our efforts in this customer segment by performing a deep dive in hull management practices for ships and coatings performance.     At the end of the i-Corps curriculum, we decided to move ahead and incorporated a start-up to commercialize the technology investigated during the program. We found a beachhead market in the diving industry where our swarm of UUVs would provide an automated solution for hull inspection that would enable diving company managers to use their divers' time more efficiently on cleaning and repair jobs. This beachhead is a small market but is accessible for a small company and would be a path to the more lucrative market of hull performance management. Here, our technology could provide high-frequency visual biofouling data to enable coatings and ships performance managers to optimize cleaning schedule, shipping route and coating selection and save up to 25% in fuel and GHG emissions according to the International Maritime Organization.     Finally, the team applied to the NSF-SBIR program and received a Phase I award to build a first prototype for deployment in ports. EL/Dr. Alexandre Immas became CTO at Berkeley Marine Robotics and led the technical effort to bring this technology to market. Dr. A. Immas discussed Berkeley Marine Robotics commercialization roadmap, which is a result of the iCorps program, at a TMA BlueTech Global Connect event "Age of Autonomy: Swarm and Drone Tech" and presented Berkeley Marine Robotics technical and commercial development at the 2nd Glofouling Partnerships R&amp;D Forum and Exhibition on Biofouling Prevention and Management for Maritime Industries organized by the International Maritime Organization in London on October 11-14, 2022.       Last Modified: 04/18/2023       Submitted by: M.-Reza Alam]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
