<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research: RAPID: Storm and tropical cyclone effects on the spawning activity, larval dispersal, and ecosystem impacts of an endangered marine predator]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/15/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>102138.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>102138</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06040300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OCE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Cynthia Suchman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>csuchman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922092</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Many species of reef fish form large seasonal gatherings at specific locations to spawn. Such aggregations may lead to population overfishing if not well managed. Additionally, spawning aggregations in shallow coastal areas may also be susceptible to prolonged surge, high volumes of freshwater run-off and potentially changes in salinity associated with large storms and tropical cyclones. Yet, the impact from such events, which are becoming increasingly prevalent, has not been studied. This study investigates the impacts of hurricane Dorian on spawning activity of the endangered goliath grouper (Epinephelus itajara) fish species off the southeast coast of Florida. The broader impacts of the project relate to its value to inform fisheries management plans for goliath grouper. The project supports two early career faculty members and training of a postdoctoral researcher, a graduate student, and several undergraduate students at Florida International University. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Hurricane Dorian occurred at the peak of goliath grouper's spawning aggregation in Florida's shallow waters. This project takes advantage of ongoing acoustic surveys since 2017, telemetry, biophysical modelling, and behavioral studies of goliath grouper at spawning sites to assess how hurricane Dorian: 1) influenced the duration of spawning events and the size of aggregations, 2) affected individual residency to spawning sites and spawning behavior, 3) changed the dispersal patterns of goliath grouper larvae and identify nursery habitats with/without storm or hurricane events, and 4) influenced trophic cascades at the reef ecosystem level due to goliath grouper spawning aggregations as determined by changes on lower trophic level foraging rates and the subsequent changes to the benthos. The combination of methods provide insight into how storms affects spawning behavior from the individual to the group level, and how subsequent larval recruitment may be influenced. Finally, this project tests the utility of acceleration sensors for identifying spawning behavior in free ranging fishes, which will be of major significance to spawning studies across taxa.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/05/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/05/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2006293</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kevin</FirstName>
<LastName>Boswell</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kevin Boswell</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[kevin.boswell@fiu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000650214</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/05/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yannis</FirstName>
<LastName>Papastamatiou</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Yannis P Papastamatiou</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ypapasta@fiu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000723322</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/05/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alastair</FirstName>
<LastName>Harborne</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alastair R Harborne</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[aharborn@fiu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000728131</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/05/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Florida International University</Name>
<CityName>MIAMI</CityName>
<ZipCode>331992516</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3053482494</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>11200 SW 8TH ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>26</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL26</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>Q3KCVK5S9CP1</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>FLORIDA INTERNATIONAL UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>D4GCCCMXR1H3</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Florida International University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>331990001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>26</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL26</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1650</Code>
<Text>BIOLOGICAL OCEANOGRAPHY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1097</Code>
<Text>DIVERSITY: ROLE IN ECOSYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8556</Code>
<Text>Coral Reefs</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~102138</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Fish may form spectacular seasonal aggregations, where 100&rsquo;s of individuals get together to spawn under certain environmental conditions. In addition to being a fascinating example of reproductive ecology, these spawning aggregations are of conservation concern. Large numbers of individuals aggregate in a small area and can be heavily targeted by fishing activity. Furthermore, there may only be a few spawning events per year so anything that disrupts spawning may have negative consequences for the population. Storm events are increasing in frequency and may impact the behavior of animals such as spawning fish in coastal areas if they cause significant surge activity. If the aggregating fish are also large marine predators, then seasonal formation of spawning aggregations may have a significant effect on local marine communities by consuming prey or changing prey behavior via risk effects.</p> <p>The Goliath grouper (<em>Epinephelus itijara</em>) can reach over 2 m in length and forms large spawning aggregations seasonally at wreck sites off southern Florida. Goliath grouper were overfished and listed as endangered but there are now plans to open the population up to limited fishing, although there remain conservation concerns. While the locations of goliath spawning aggregations are known, dynamics of spawning are less clear. For example, under what conditions does spawning occur and do all fish in the aggregation spawn at the same time? What effect do goliath grouper aggregations have on prey communities on the wrecks? We used acoustic telemetry to remotely measure spawning behavior in goliath grouper, by tagging fish with transmitters that measure swimming depth and acceleration. Data from these tags were detected by listening stations we placed on and around a wreck off southern Florida. We simultaneously measured current strength and water temperature using oceanographic equipment. Finally, we wanted to know the effects of goliath grouper on potential prey fishes, so we a) simultaneously tracked the movements of reef fish on the wreck and b) measured the feeding rates of surgeonfish on the wreck. In both cases, we compared our results within and outside of the known goliath grouper spawning period.</p> <p>We were able to identify spawning like behavior from goliath grouper, which occurred close to the new moon, when spawning is thought to occur. Fish tended to use the same areas suggesting a tight aggregation, but not all individuals in the group displayed spawning like behavior. Most fish would perform one spawning like behavior and then leave the region and swim to other wrecks or further north. We found that current had a strong effect on goliath grouper behavior, as fish had to stay close to the seafloor when currents were strong. Our results therefore suggest that spawning times may be based around lunar phase and current strength, and that fish may only spawn once within an aggregation before moving on. We have also sent our results on the likely depths of spawning, to colleagues at University of Miami, who are constructing models to predict where Goliath grouper larvae end up. By constructing this model, they can predict how storms, which may change water current patterns, may alter the dispersal of goliath grouper larvae.</p> <p>We found no change in the space use of reef fishes on the wrecks, during and outside of the goliath grouper spawning season. In other words, reef fish did not appear to avoid the space used by grouper even when they are in large numbers. We also found that reef fish foraging rates actually increased during the goliath grouper spawning season. If grouper were inducing risk effects, then we would expect reef fish to reduce foraging rates in their presence, so they can spend more time being vigilant. The increase in reef fish foraging rates when grouper are present may be due to warmer water temperatures (grouper aggregations occur in the summer). However, it may also suggest that groupers facilitate communities either by providing nutrients (e.g. through excretion or egestion) or by attracting planktivorous fishes which are foraging on the grouper eggs. Future research should investigate the potential for large spawning aggregations of grouper to facilitate marine communities.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/02/2022<br>      Modified by: Yannis&nbsp;P&nbsp;Papastamatiou</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2006293/2006293_10646470_1669932591003_GoliathgrouperJupiter--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2006293/2006293_10646470_1669932591003_GoliathgrouperJupiter--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Goliath grouper over wreck"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2006293/2006293_10646470_1669932591003_GoliathgrouperJupiter--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Goliath grouper over wreck"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Goliath grouper form aggregations over wrecks some of which are likely for spawning purposes.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Yannis Papastamatiou</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Yannis&nbsp;P&nbsp;Papastamatiou</div> <div class="imageTitle">Goliath grouper over wreck</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2006293/2006293_10646470_1669931802694_Goliathgrouperseptember1722084--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2006293/2006293_10646470_1669931802694_Goliathgrouperseptember1722084--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Goliath grouper with smaller fish"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2006293/2006293_10646470_1669931802694_Goliathgrouperseptember1722084--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Goliath grouper with smaller fish"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Smaller fish often aggregate around adult goliath grouper</div> <div class="imageCredit">Yannis Papastamatiou</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Yannis&nbsp;P&nbsp;Papastamatiou</div> <div class="imageTitle">Goliath grouper with smaller fish</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2006293/2006293_10646470_1669932087319_Goliathgrouperseptember2022052--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2006293/2006293_10646470_1669932087319_Goliathgrouperseptember2022052--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Acoustic receiver"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2006293/2006293_10646470_1669932087319_Goliathgrouperseptember2022052--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Acoustic receiver"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">An acoustic receiver is attached to the wreck. The receiver detects acoustic transmission from tagged goliath grouper, providing data on their position, swimming depth, and activity.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Yannis Papastamatiou</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Yannis&nbsp;P&nbsp;Papastamatiou</div> <div class="imageTitle">Acoustic receiver</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2006293/2006293_10646470_1669932348937_goliathgrouperjuly2020007--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2006293/2006293_10646470_1669932348937_goliathgrouperjuly2020007--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Installing current profiler"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2006293/2006293_10646470_1669932348937_goliathgrouperjuly2020007--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Installing current profiler"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">A researcher installs an ADCP at the goliath grouper aggregation which will continuously measure water currents and how they vary vertically.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Yannis Papastamatiou</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Yannis&nbsp;P&nbsp;Papastamatiou</div> <div class="imageTitle">Installing current profiler</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2006293/2006293_10646470_1669931623690_Goliathgrouperseptember1722127--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2006293/2006293_10646470_1669931623690_Goliathgrouperseptember1722127--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Goliath grouper aggregation"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2006293/2006293_10646470_1669931623690_Goliathgrouperseptember1722127--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Goliath grouper aggregation"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Goliath grouper aggregate off Southern Florida wreck during their spawning season</div> <div class="imageCredit">Yannis Papastamatiou</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Yannis&nbsp;P&nbsp;Papastamatiou</div> <div class="imageTitle">Goliath grouper aggregation</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Fish may form spectacular seasonal aggregations, where 100’s of individuals get together to spawn under certain environmental conditions. In addition to being a fascinating example of reproductive ecology, these spawning aggregations are of conservation concern. Large numbers of individuals aggregate in a small area and can be heavily targeted by fishing activity. Furthermore, there may only be a few spawning events per year so anything that disrupts spawning may have negative consequences for the population. Storm events are increasing in frequency and may impact the behavior of animals such as spawning fish in coastal areas if they cause significant surge activity. If the aggregating fish are also large marine predators, then seasonal formation of spawning aggregations may have a significant effect on local marine communities by consuming prey or changing prey behavior via risk effects.  The Goliath grouper (Epinephelus itijara) can reach over 2 m in length and forms large spawning aggregations seasonally at wreck sites off southern Florida. Goliath grouper were overfished and listed as endangered but there are now plans to open the population up to limited fishing, although there remain conservation concerns. While the locations of goliath spawning aggregations are known, dynamics of spawning are less clear. For example, under what conditions does spawning occur and do all fish in the aggregation spawn at the same time? What effect do goliath grouper aggregations have on prey communities on the wrecks? We used acoustic telemetry to remotely measure spawning behavior in goliath grouper, by tagging fish with transmitters that measure swimming depth and acceleration. Data from these tags were detected by listening stations we placed on and around a wreck off southern Florida. We simultaneously measured current strength and water temperature using oceanographic equipment. Finally, we wanted to know the effects of goliath grouper on potential prey fishes, so we a) simultaneously tracked the movements of reef fish on the wreck and b) measured the feeding rates of surgeonfish on the wreck. In both cases, we compared our results within and outside of the known goliath grouper spawning period.  We were able to identify spawning like behavior from goliath grouper, which occurred close to the new moon, when spawning is thought to occur. Fish tended to use the same areas suggesting a tight aggregation, but not all individuals in the group displayed spawning like behavior. Most fish would perform one spawning like behavior and then leave the region and swim to other wrecks or further north. We found that current had a strong effect on goliath grouper behavior, as fish had to stay close to the seafloor when currents were strong. Our results therefore suggest that spawning times may be based around lunar phase and current strength, and that fish may only spawn once within an aggregation before moving on. We have also sent our results on the likely depths of spawning, to colleagues at University of Miami, who are constructing models to predict where Goliath grouper larvae end up. By constructing this model, they can predict how storms, which may change water current patterns, may alter the dispersal of goliath grouper larvae.  We found no change in the space use of reef fishes on the wrecks, during and outside of the goliath grouper spawning season. In other words, reef fish did not appear to avoid the space used by grouper even when they are in large numbers. We also found that reef fish foraging rates actually increased during the goliath grouper spawning season. If grouper were inducing risk effects, then we would expect reef fish to reduce foraging rates in their presence, so they can spend more time being vigilant. The increase in reef fish foraging rates when grouper are present may be due to warmer water temperatures (grouper aggregations occur in the summer). However, it may also suggest that groupers facilitate communities either by providing nutrients (e.g. through excretion or egestion) or by attracting planktivorous fishes which are foraging on the grouper eggs. Future research should investigate the potential for large spawning aggregations of grouper to facilitate marine communities.          Last Modified: 12/02/2022       Submitted by: Yannis P Papastamatiou]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
