<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[NSF Postdoctoral Fellowship in Biology FY 2020]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>138000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>207000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DBI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>John Barthell</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jbarthel@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922618</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This action funds an NSF Postdoctoral Research Fellowship in Biology for FY 2020, Integrative Research Investigating the Rules of Life Governing Interactions Between Genomes, Environment and Phenotypes. The fellowship supports research and training of the fellow that will contribute to the area of Rules of Life in innovative ways. Here, the Fellow will explore microbial interactions within island ecosystems to shed light on coral reef health and function, which relies on both ocean- and land-based processes. Tropical islands and their proximity to adjacent reefs provide opportunities to explore the critical link between these seemingly different habitats. Invasive rats affect island and reef health through the predation of native seabird eggs and chicks, which disrupts the natural flow of nutrients to the reef. If removed, seabird recovery will restore the transfer of nutrients. As facilitators of this transferal, microbes may hold the key to determining a link between these habitats. Using clues from soil, seawater and coral microbiomes, this project will capitalize on a planned rat eradication event occurring on the island of Tetiaroa, French Polynesia, to assess the effects of a land-based conservation initiative across the land-sea interface. This project further supports education and diversity through student mentorship, while also creating outreach opportunities among local communities that will inform them of the scientific and social importance of the proposed work.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;Microbes play important roles in nutrient cycling and provision, and the signature of either disruption or reinstatement of the natural flow of nutrients is likely reflected in the microbial community. Shifts in the presence, abundance and function of nutrient-utilizing microbes across all connected habitats can provide evidence of a land-sea link. Thirty island and reef sites around Tetiaroa will be targeted for microbial sampling in soil, seawater and coral before, during and after rat eradication to determine the impacts on microbial communities and their functional role in nutrient cycling. Compositional and metagenomic analyses paired with macro-ecological surveys will highlight impacts of rat eradication on marine and terrestrial recovery across scales of biological organization from microbes to entire ecosystems. This fellowship will support the Fellow’s research, career and outreach objectives through advancement in analytical skills and scientific knowledge, mentorship and teaching, and local community engagement. Through the exploration of cross-ecosystem linkages, this research will expand on ecological theory by bridging the land-sea gap, while providing a key foundation for building policy and promoting simplified coral reef conservation initiatives.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/22/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/30/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2006244</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Hannah</FirstName>
<LastName>Epstein</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Hannah Epstein</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<NSF_ID>000814832</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/22/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Epstein, Hannah</Name>
<CityName>Victoria</CityName>
<ZipCode>V8P5C2</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>Canada</CountryName>
<StateName/>
<StateCode/>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT/>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG/>
<ORG_UEI_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Oregon State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Corvallis</CityName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<ZipCode>973318506</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF/>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7275</Code>
<Text>Cross-BIO Activities</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>068Z</Code>
<Text>URoL-Understanding Rules of Life</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>097Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Impacts on Existing Activities</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>102Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-Disproportionate Impcts Inst-Indiv</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>1V21</Code>
<Name>R&amp;RA ARP Act DEFC V</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>010V2122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[R&RA ARP Act DEFC V]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~138000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~69000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Invasive species are one of the most challenging threats to natural ecosystems. On tropical islands, invasive rats can decimate native populations of island-nesting seabirds. Through the deposition of guano, seabirds represent a crucial source of nutrients for coastal and nearshore coral reef habitats. Unlike nutrient pollution from agriculture or industry, these natural inputs are hypothesized to support coral growth and reef health, while buffering against environmental stress such as marine heatwaves. Thus, the removal of seabirds by invasive rats can result in cascading effects from land to sea.</p> <p>This project aimed to determine a causal link between terrestrial invasive species, their removal (i.e., eradication), and coral reef health through a microbial lens. The composition of microbes within natural island ecosystems can provide invaluable nutrient cycling capabilities that promote healthy organisms and ecosystems. It is these capabilities that provide insight into the effects of invasive species, as microbes essentially become the first responders to changes in nutrient availability that may have downstream impacts on coral and ecosystem health.</p> <p>To better understand and characterize the links between terrestrial invasive species, nutrient availability, and coral/reef health, I examined the microbial communities (e.g. bacteria, archaea) in reef habitats on Tetiaroa, a remote atoll located in French Polynesia. This atoll is made up of a series of small islets (<em>motu</em>) with varying rat invasion histories (historically rat-free, recently eradicated, and rats present), which allowed for a spatial characterization of the microbial communities in both reef water and corals themselves. I measured levels of seabird-derived nutrients in the marine habitats (through algal isotopes) and seabird populations based on these invasion histories. I identified significant differences in coral and water microbiome community structure across the islets with varying rat invasion histories, that further correlated strongly with seabird populations on each islet. In particular, corals located in areas with rats had microbiomes that were almost entirely dominated by a single bacterial group that is hypothesized to be beneficial to coral growth and health. While this may seem positive under some conditions, it is far better for the overall health of an organism to have a diverse microbiome with bacteria that can provide a myriad of functions. This dominance of one bacteria in areas with invasive rats suggests an ecological tradeoff: corals are preferentially associating with a known beneficial bacterium to help outweigh the negative impacts of rats.</p> <p>During this fellowship, Tetiaroa atoll underwent an island-wide rat eradication program. With samples collected before, during and after this eradication, I expected to see shifts in microbial communities at islets that had rats present toward looking more like the communities seen at historically rat-free and recently eradicated islets. While these data are still being processed at the publication of this report, the current results from this fellowship strongly suggest that invasive rats (and conversely seabird nutrient input) represent key drivers of microbial dynamics in marine environments, connecting nutrient dynamics across the land-sea boundary. This link can have significant impacts on how we measure the impact of terrestrial conservation initiatives like rat eradication and can allow us to not only encapsulate a broader view of conservation impact but predict cross-ecosystem recovery trajectories.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/27/2023<br>      Modified by: Hannah&nbsp;Epstein</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Invasive species are one of the most challenging threats to natural ecosystems. On tropical islands, invasive rats can decimate native populations of island-nesting seabirds. Through the deposition of guano, seabirds represent a crucial source of nutrients for coastal and nearshore coral reef habitats. Unlike nutrient pollution from agriculture or industry, these natural inputs are hypothesized to support coral growth and reef health, while buffering against environmental stress such as marine heatwaves. Thus, the removal of seabirds by invasive rats can result in cascading effects from land to sea.  This project aimed to determine a causal link between terrestrial invasive species, their removal (i.e., eradication), and coral reef health through a microbial lens. The composition of microbes within natural island ecosystems can provide invaluable nutrient cycling capabilities that promote healthy organisms and ecosystems. It is these capabilities that provide insight into the effects of invasive species, as microbes essentially become the first responders to changes in nutrient availability that may have downstream impacts on coral and ecosystem health.  To better understand and characterize the links between terrestrial invasive species, nutrient availability, and coral/reef health, I examined the microbial communities (e.g. bacteria, archaea) in reef habitats on Tetiaroa, a remote atoll located in French Polynesia. This atoll is made up of a series of small islets (motu) with varying rat invasion histories (historically rat-free, recently eradicated, and rats present), which allowed for a spatial characterization of the microbial communities in both reef water and corals themselves. I measured levels of seabird-derived nutrients in the marine habitats (through algal isotopes) and seabird populations based on these invasion histories. I identified significant differences in coral and water microbiome community structure across the islets with varying rat invasion histories, that further correlated strongly with seabird populations on each islet. In particular, corals located in areas with rats had microbiomes that were almost entirely dominated by a single bacterial group that is hypothesized to be beneficial to coral growth and health. While this may seem positive under some conditions, it is far better for the overall health of an organism to have a diverse microbiome with bacteria that can provide a myriad of functions. This dominance of one bacteria in areas with invasive rats suggests an ecological tradeoff: corals are preferentially associating with a known beneficial bacterium to help outweigh the negative impacts of rats.  During this fellowship, Tetiaroa atoll underwent an island-wide rat eradication program. With samples collected before, during and after this eradication, I expected to see shifts in microbial communities at islets that had rats present toward looking more like the communities seen at historically rat-free and recently eradicated islets. While these data are still being processed at the publication of this report, the current results from this fellowship strongly suggest that invasive rats (and conversely seabird nutrient input) represent key drivers of microbial dynamics in marine environments, connecting nutrient dynamics across the land-sea boundary. This link can have significant impacts on how we measure the impact of terrestrial conservation initiatives like rat eradication and can allow us to not only encapsulate a broader view of conservation impact but predict cross-ecosystem recovery trajectories.       Last Modified: 09/27/2023       Submitted by: Hannah Epstein]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
