<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research: A new model for producing science documentaries: Building collaborations between scientists and storytellers to test methods of communication in film]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>349225.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>349225</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DRL</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sandra Welch</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[As part of its overall strategy to enhance learning in informal environments, the Advancing Informal STEM Learning (AISL) program seeks to advance new approaches to, and evidence-based understanding of, the design and development of STEM learning in informal environments. This includes providing multiple pathways for broadening access to and engagement in STEM learning experiences, advancing innovative research on and assessment of STEM learning in informal environments, and developing understandings of deeper learning by participants. This project will research core methods of science documentary film production and impact on audience engagement and understanding.   The findings from this study will be used to later produce a film on how the CRISPR genome editing technology will shape agriculture, ecology, and the natural world.  The research study and film to be produced will be a collaboration of science communication practitioners and researchers.  The intended outcomes are to improve effective science filmmaking and increase impact on audiences.  Many people rely on documentary film and videos for science information outside of formal learning environments.  Research has shown that video programming can reduce knowledge gaps between those of higher and lower levels of education.  But there is little research with findings about what makes a particular style of storytelling effective for engagement and learning outcomes.  A recent report of the National Academies of Sciences, Engineering and Medicine identified a significant shortage of social science research with directly applicable lessons for filmmakers.  This project addresses this need by providing new frameworks for research and methods to produce science documentaries.  Project partners are iBiology, a producer of video resources for learning, and science communication researchers at the University of Wisconsin-Madison.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will examine two key questions:  1) In a science documentary film, how does the diversity of the scientists profiled and the use of a narrator shape audiences’ perception of content and scientists? and 2) What are effective methods in science filmmaking to visualize the invisible (i.e. explain scientific phenomena that are not easily visualized)?  The project begins by testing a recently produced film, Human Nature, that tells the story of the discovery of CRISPR (genome editing), told by the scientists who led the effort.  Phase 1 testing will include screenings, focus groups, and experiments run through Amazon Mechanical Turk to test what features of the film (editorial voice and visualization styles) are most effective for communicating scientific content.  In Phase 2 video test clips will be produced using a combination of narration and visualization strategies.  An experimental design run through Amazon Turk will randomly assign participants to watch a clip using different combinations.  Researchers will use this data to parse out what effect seems to be related to particular narration and visualization choices.  This quantitative experimental data will be supplemented by qualitative data from focus groups with participants with a diverse range of science experience and demographic backgrounds.   Researchers will design a survey-embedded experiment with a U.S. nationally representative sample to see how well the findings translate and change in a broader population.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/30/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/30/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2006034</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sarah</FirstName>
<LastName>Goodwin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sarah Goodwin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[sarah@scicommlab.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000710586</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/30/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Elliot</FirstName>
<LastName>Kirschner</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Elliot Kirschner</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[elliot@ibiology.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000814613</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/30/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Science Communication Lab, Inc.</Name>
<CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
<ZipCode>947041243</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4155458852</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1936 UNIVERSITY AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[STE 330]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>KREAAS7G2LB1</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SCIENCE COMMUNICATION LAB INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[iBiology, Inc]]></Name>
<CityName>San Francisco</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>941582140</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[600 16th St # N476D # 2240]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>11</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA11</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7259</Code>
<Text>AISL</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8212</Code>
<Text>Broaden Particip STEM Resrch</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0420</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~349225</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-460a0eae-7fff-9729-4dc5-5e5f3dfec8f2">&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr">This grant pioneered an iterative research-practice partnership between filmmakers that create science content (Science Communication Lab) and social scientists studying the science of science communication (University of Wisconsin - Madison). Despite several calls for increased collaboration between science communication practitioners and researchers, such partnerships have remained rare. This is partly a function of limited funding available for such work, and partly based on few blueprints being available for replicating or even scaling up such efforts. As a result, many of our group's approaches and experiences while scaling up such a partnership will provide important blueprints for future collaborations among social scientists and communication professionals.</p> <p dir="ltr">The teams faced unique challenges in balancing the creative process involved in filmmaking with the need for data-driven studies to achieve measurable outcomes. The emerging study represents a fruition of true collaboration in that teams from differing areas of expertise were able to learn from the other and tailor their workflows to achieve a common goal. Consequently, the innovations around process as well as the ultimate results represent a furthering of knowledge around science communication for both practitioners and researchers, but also an appreciation among all partners for seeing the research and practice of effective&nbsp;science communication as in service to and benefiting one another.</p> <p dir="ltr">In online survey experiments using film clips, we measured how American audiences responded to different representations of scientists as well as different framings of a science topic. We also examined how different clips from the documentary film about CRISPR and gene editing,&nbsp;Human Nature,&nbsp;impacted the audience's sense of narrative transportation and character identification.&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr">Across all audiences, people rated being highly engaged while watching the documentary clips. Open-ended responses also showed that the majority of people said they enjoyed watching the films, had learned a lot, and appreciated being part of the study. These responses further indicate the power of film as an effective method for communicating science to a wide range of publics.&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr">Our data also indicate that for Black audiences, seeing a Black scientist and main character led to greater knowledge gains about the topic of CRISPR and gene editing.&nbsp;However, our findings also suggest that dominant cultural stereotypes and implicitly racial attitudes remain in public perceptions of scientists. Our preliminary data indicate that Black women scientists are perceived to be less credible than their white and male counterparts. These findings make a strong case for further study and imply a need for more public representation of scientists from intersectional and marginalized backgrounds to counter existing stereotypes.&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr">The tool we developed, which intersperses question prompts throughout the video, allows for an interactive viewing experience while also serving as a tool for real-world data collection on viewer responses. This tool serves as a useful prototype for communication professionals and researchers, as well as the educational community.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/12/2023<br>      Modified by: Sarah&nbsp;Goodwin</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   This grant pioneered an iterative research-practice partnership between filmmakers that create science content (Science Communication Lab) and social scientists studying the science of science communication (University of Wisconsin - Madison). Despite several calls for increased collaboration between science communication practitioners and researchers, such partnerships have remained rare. This is partly a function of limited funding available for such work, and partly based on few blueprints being available for replicating or even scaling up such efforts. As a result, many of our group's approaches and experiences while scaling up such a partnership will provide important blueprints for future collaborations among social scientists and communication professionals. The teams faced unique challenges in balancing the creative process involved in filmmaking with the need for data-driven studies to achieve measurable outcomes. The emerging study represents a fruition of true collaboration in that teams from differing areas of expertise were able to learn from the other and tailor their workflows to achieve a common goal. Consequently, the innovations around process as well as the ultimate results represent a furthering of knowledge around science communication for both practitioners and researchers, but also an appreciation among all partners for seeing the research and practice of effective science communication as in service to and benefiting one another. In online survey experiments using film clips, we measured how American audiences responded to different representations of scientists as well as different framings of a science topic. We also examined how different clips from the documentary film about CRISPR and gene editing, Human Nature, impacted the audience's sense of narrative transportation and character identification.  Across all audiences, people rated being highly engaged while watching the documentary clips. Open-ended responses also showed that the majority of people said they enjoyed watching the films, had learned a lot, and appreciated being part of the study. These responses further indicate the power of film as an effective method for communicating science to a wide range of publics.  Our data also indicate that for Black audiences, seeing a Black scientist and main character led to greater knowledge gains about the topic of CRISPR and gene editing. However, our findings also suggest that dominant cultural stereotypes and implicitly racial attitudes remain in public perceptions of scientists. Our preliminary data indicate that Black women scientists are perceived to be less credible than their white and male counterparts. These findings make a strong case for further study and imply a need for more public representation of scientists from intersectional and marginalized backgrounds to counter existing stereotypes.  The tool we developed, which intersperses question prompts throughout the video, allows for an interactive viewing experience while also serving as a tool for real-world data collection on viewer responses. This tool serves as a useful prototype for communication professionals and researchers, as well as the educational community.              Last Modified: 04/12/2023       Submitted by: Sarah Goodwin]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
