<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[CAREER: Integrated Research and Education on Hot Carrier Effects in Plasmonics]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>107554.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>107554</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ECCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ruyan Guo</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rguo@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927718</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Abstract &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This CAREER award is jointly funded by the Electronics, Photonics, and Magnetic Devices Program (EPMD) in the Division of Electrical, Communications and Cyber Systems (ECCS) and by the Electronic and Photonic Materials Program (EPM) in the Division of Materials Research (DMR).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;NonTechnical: Nearly all modern technology, from cell phones and cameras to medical sensors, involves the interaction of light with electronic circuitry in order to perform specific functions. When light is absorbed in such a device, it can create electrons with more energy than needed to execute the desired function, so-called hot-electrons, which generally dissipate this energy as heat, resulting in power loss and device inefficiency. The first goal of this project is to advance the understanding of these hot-electrons, which will enable devices with unprecedented functionality and performance that can be applied to problems of global importance, e.g. solar energy generation, wireless communication, etc. The second goal of this project is to integrate the research into education by creating a suite of online learning tools for widespread dissemination of ideas and techniques in alternative energy. In conjunction with these online resources, this program will provide educational support to a wide range of audiences including the general community through public outreach and the mentoring of graduate, undergraduate and high school students.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical: Ohmic loss is one of the major hindrances to high efficiency plasmonic devices due to energy dissipation of excited charge carriers within the metal. A similar effect, known as thermalization, also limits photovoltaic efficiency in solar energy devices. It is thus important to understand and mitigate these various loss mechanisms in next-generation optoelectronic devices. Through this program the PI will investigate the optoelectronic properties of fabricated structures capable of generating and extracting these carriers before heat dissipation occurs.  These studies will encompass light absorption, carrier generation and collection, as well as material and surface interface engineering to modify energy barrier heights, leading to a new understanding of how hot electronic processes work in plasmonic nanostructures. This knowledge will be applied to a novel class of plasmonic devices based on hot carriers, which enable simultaneous control of optical and electronic properties.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/06/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/06/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2006102</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jeremy</FirstName>
<LastName>Munday</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jeremy Munday</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jnmunday@ucdavis.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000642596</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/06/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Davis</Name>
<CityName>DAVIS</CityName>
<ZipCode>956186153</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5307547700</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1850 RESEARCH PARK DR, STE 300</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>TX2DAGQPENZ5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, DAVIS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>NUDGYLBB4S99</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Davis]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>956186134</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1517</Code>
<Text>EPMD-ElectrnPhoton&amp;MagnDevices</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1775</Code>
<Text>ELECTRONIC/PHOTONIC MATERIALS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>091E</Code>
<Text>Light generation &amp; detection</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>094E</Code>
<Text>Optoelectronic devices</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>100E</Code>
<Text>Novel devices &amp; vacuum electronics</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8396</Code>
<Text>Clean Energy Technology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8609</Code>
<Text>Other Energy Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8990</Code>
<Text>Optics and Photonics</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01001617DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~107553</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Our project led to several advancements in both the fundamental understanding of light-matter interactions and its applications to optoelectronic devices. Specifically, we developed a variety of optical detectors that work over extended wavelength ranges as a result of new knowledge obtained under this project. Further, the results have been widely circulated through a variety of publications, seminars, and freely available online resources.</p> <p>The goal of this project was to generate and disseminate new knowledge in the burgeoning field of hot carrier plasmonics, where light incident on metal structures can result in energy transfer than can potentially be used for novel detectors and power generators. Light absorption in metallic nanostructures had previously been a hindrance to device operation, causing a loss of energy that was not recoverable. Through our work, we studied how the energy typically lost to absorption can be recovered through the generation of energetic charge carriers in the metal and used in their subsequent collection. The principles uncovered during this project were then used to create novel photodetectors that work in the telecom wavelength range, which is critical for many everyday optoelectronic devices.</p> <p>During the program, we advanced several related areas of research. We created thin metallic ultra-absorbers capable of absorbing &gt;90% of the incident light and found agreement between our models and experimental data. We further performed time-resolved measurements on sub-picosecond timescales to probe the time-dynamics and thermalization of excited charge carriers. We used the results of these studies to engineer the relaxation processes and tune the thermalization time and carrier collection efficiency. These studies also enabled us to make telecom photodetectors and imaging systems using silicon in conjunction with different metallic thin-films.</p> <p>This work has also been disseminated through a variety of outlets. Both the PI and students have given numerous lectures and written scientific papers resulting from this research. Several graduate and undergraduate students and been mentored, leading to a new generation of highly skilled individuals that are entering the workforce, and two female graduate students have completed their PhDs through this project. These students have acquired laboratory skills that are important for a number of career paths in optics, electronics, and computer engineering/programing. Finally, online resources have been developed to further disseminate the material, specifically a new website was constructed for third generation photovoltaics, which involves the utilization of hot carrier phenomena.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/18/2022<br>      Modified by: Jeremy&nbsp;Munday</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2006102/2006102_10408233_1660859995483_Munday_Cover_v3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2006102/2006102_10408233_1660859995483_Munday_Cover_v3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Hot carrier optoelectronics"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2006102/2006102_10408233_1660859995483_Munday_Cover_v3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Hot carrier optoelectronics"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Schematic of an hot carrier optoelectronic device within a circuit</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jeremy Munday</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jeremy&nbsp;Munday</div> <div class="imageTitle">Hot carrier optoelectronics</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Our project led to several advancements in both the fundamental understanding of light-matter interactions and its applications to optoelectronic devices. Specifically, we developed a variety of optical detectors that work over extended wavelength ranges as a result of new knowledge obtained under this project. Further, the results have been widely circulated through a variety of publications, seminars, and freely available online resources.  The goal of this project was to generate and disseminate new knowledge in the burgeoning field of hot carrier plasmonics, where light incident on metal structures can result in energy transfer than can potentially be used for novel detectors and power generators. Light absorption in metallic nanostructures had previously been a hindrance to device operation, causing a loss of energy that was not recoverable. Through our work, we studied how the energy typically lost to absorption can be recovered through the generation of energetic charge carriers in the metal and used in their subsequent collection. The principles uncovered during this project were then used to create novel photodetectors that work in the telecom wavelength range, which is critical for many everyday optoelectronic devices.  During the program, we advanced several related areas of research. We created thin metallic ultra-absorbers capable of absorbing &gt;90% of the incident light and found agreement between our models and experimental data. We further performed time-resolved measurements on sub-picosecond timescales to probe the time-dynamics and thermalization of excited charge carriers. We used the results of these studies to engineer the relaxation processes and tune the thermalization time and carrier collection efficiency. These studies also enabled us to make telecom photodetectors and imaging systems using silicon in conjunction with different metallic thin-films.  This work has also been disseminated through a variety of outlets. Both the PI and students have given numerous lectures and written scientific papers resulting from this research. Several graduate and undergraduate students and been mentored, leading to a new generation of highly skilled individuals that are entering the workforce, and two female graduate students have completed their PhDs through this project. These students have acquired laboratory skills that are important for a number of career paths in optics, electronics, and computer engineering/programing. Finally, online resources have been developed to further disseminate the material, specifically a new website was constructed for third generation photovoltaics, which involves the utilization of hot carrier phenomena.          Last Modified: 08/18/2022       Submitted by: Jeremy Munday]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
