<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Group Effects on Pile Downdrag Following Liquefaction]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>75011.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>75011</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Giovanna Biscontin</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>gibiscon@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922339</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Several of the earthquakes that occurred during the 1811-1812 New Madrid earthquake sequence were identified by the United States Geological Survey as being the largest earthquakes East of the Rocky Mountains and within the top 20 of the largest domestic earthquakes United States history.  The seismic waves from these earthquakes propagated for a great distance because of the competency of the surrounding bedrock, and because the earthquakes occurred in the middle of the continental plate.  Soil liquefaction, where soil below the water table temporarily becomes a viscous fluid following shaking, was observed to occur during the New Madrid earthquakes. Liquefaction results in a loss of strength in the soil that serves as the bearing material for most infrastructure. If the same size earthquake as the 1811-1812 sequence were to occur today, the United States Federal Emergency Management Agency warns that the earthquake could result in the highest economic losses due to a natural disaster in the United States.  Because the areas near the earthquake are now densely populated (St. Louis, Missouri, and Memphis, Tennessee) additional understanding of behavior of civil infrastructure when exposed earthquake induced liquefaction is needed to prevent loses.  To remedy this lack of understanding, small explosive charges will be used to produce liquefaction under full-scale conditions and measurements will be made of the foundation settlement and the downward friction force on the foundations. Tests will be performed on two pile groups a site in Arkansas. Primary support will be provided by Nucor Yamata Steel Corperation; however, supplemental funding from NSF will significantly expand the scope of the project. This Rapid Response Research (RAPID) grant will provide that supplemental funding. The results from these tests will allow engineers to evaluate the accuracy of existing design procedures and develop modifications to produce better agreement with measured behavior. Improved design procedures will allow engineers to design safer yet cost-effective foundation solutions that will remain stable during earthquakes. Limitations of the previous study at the Turrell Arkansas Test Site will be overcome by 1) testing groups of piles instead of individual piles, 2) leaving the deadload on the foundations for a longer period of time prior to blasting to allow the neutral plane to develop, and 3) leaving the deadload on the foundations for a longer period of time after blasting to allow the neutral plane to redevelop.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;To improve our understanding of liquefaction-induced downdrag/dragload on deep foundations, blast induced liquefaction tests will be performed on two different pile groups (steel pipe group, H-pile group) at a site in Arkansas. The objective is to measure negative skin friction and downdrag induced settlement. With the inclusion of a static load placed on top of the pile groups, the results from these tests will allow researchers to evaluate the accuracy of existing design recommendations and develop modifications to produce better agreement with measured response. Because deep foundations are a common approach for supporting structures in liquefiable sands, reliable design approaches are critical to provide cost-effective foundations that are safe in future earthquakes.  The results obtained from this project will be used to mitigate liquefaction induced damage at other earthquake prone sites with a similar geologic profile.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/17/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/17/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2006323</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
<LastName>Coffman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Richard Coffman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[rick@uark.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000544422</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/17/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Arkansas</Name>
<CityName>FAYETTEVILLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>727013124</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4795753845</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1125 W MAPLE ST STE 316</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arkansas</StateName>
<StateCode>AR</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AR03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>MECEHTM8DB17</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ARKANSAS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Arkansas]]></Name>
<CityName>Fayetteville</CityName>
<StateCode>AR</StateCode>
<ZipCode>727013124</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4183 Bell Engineering Center]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arkansas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AR03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>073Y</Code>
<Text>ECI-Engineering for Civil Infr</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>036E</Code>
<Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>037E</Code>
<Text>GEOTECHNICAL ENGINEERING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>038E</Code>
<Text>FOUNDATION ENGINEERING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>041E</Code>
<Text>HAZARD AND DISASTER REDUCTION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>043E</Code>
<Text>EARTHQUAKE ENGINEERING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1576</Code>
<Text>NATIONL EARTHQK HZRD REDCT PRG</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~75011</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The New Madrid Seismic Zone (NMSZ), located within the Mississippi Embayment, has produced large earthquakes with detrimental effects due to deep soil deposits and resulting high peak horizontal ground accelerations.&nbsp; The alluvial soil deposits within the Mississippi Embayment include loose sands that are located below the ground water table; these sands are susceptible to liquefaction.&nbsp; Deep foundations are commonly used to prevent direct and indirect economic losses from liquefaction. However, settlement (downdrag) within the liquefied sand can cause downward friction (dragload) to develop on the perimeter of the each deep foundation, increasing the load and leading to excessive settlement. In the absence of field measurements, engineers are uncertain about the amount of downward friction that will develop and how much settlement will occur.</p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Intellectual Merit</span></p> <p>To remedy this lack of understanding, small explosive charges were used to produce liquefaction under full-scale conditions and downdrag and dragload measurements were obtianed. Primary support for this project was provided by the Nucor Yamato Steel; however, supplemental funding from NSF was used to significantly expand the scope of the project. The results from these tests will allow engineers to evaluate the accuracy of existing design procedures and develop modifications to produce better agreement with measured behavior. Improved design procedures will allow engineers to design safe yet cost-effective foundation solutions that will remain stable during earthquakes. Limitations of the previous study at the Turrell Arkansas Test Site were overcome by 1) testing groups of piles instead of individual piles, 2) ensuring the neutral plane develops prior to blasting, and &nbsp;3) ensuring the neutral plane redevelops following blasting.</p> <p>Two pile groups were instrumented, installed, pre-loaded and subjected to a liquefaction event.&nbsp; Seven, closed-ended, 18-inch diameter pipe piles and seven, 14x102 H-piles were fabricated for this project.&nbsp; Strain gauges were bonded to each of the 14 piles, with intermittent delays associated with the COVID-19 shutdown.&nbsp; Due to the COVID-19 shutdown at the Nucor-Yamato plant, the piles were moved from the Nucor-Yamato site to the Nucor Hickman site where the piles were driven.&nbsp; Because the strain gauge installation was not complete for all piles at the time of movement, strain gauge application continued on the uncompleted piles while the completed piles were driven. A total of 14 strain gauges were attached to each of the pipe piles.&nbsp; Seven strain gauges were installed to diametrically opposed sides of the piles.&nbsp; A total of sixteen gauges were attached to each of the H-piles.&nbsp; Eight strain gauges were installed to the flange of each side of each pile.&nbsp; Each strain gauges was covered with waterproofing and angle to protect the gauges during driving and after installation.&nbsp; Following pile installation, the piles were prepared for application of the concrete pile cap, and the concrete pile cap was formed and poured.&nbsp; Installation of the piezometers and extensometers was delayed for nine months due to stoppage of work at the project site as associated with the COVID-19 pandemic.</p> <p>Deadweight (1.5 million pounds) was added to each of the pile groups.&nbsp; Blasting charges were placed in previously installed blasting casing and the charges were detonated to induce liquefaction in the soil.&nbsp; The soil was successfully liquefied as indicated by: the measure pore pressure ratios, ejecta being observed at the ground surface, and up to seven inches (178 mm) of ground surface settlement surrounding the pile groups.</p> <p>The residual load in the piles following driving and the increase in load transferred to the piles following liquefaction was measured.&nbsp; Based on these measurements, additional load was observed at the location of the neutral plane for all of the piles in each pile group.&nbsp; Following liquefaction, less soil settlement and less load was observed to develop in the pipe piles than in the H-piles; this was attributed to the densification of the soil surrounding the pipe piles during driving.&nbsp;</p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Broader Impacts</span></p> <p>To improve our understanding of liquefaction-induced downdrag on deep foundations, blast induced liquefaction tests were performed on two different pile groups (steel pipe group, H-pile group) at a site in Arkansas. NSF funding was used to purchase strain gauges to measure the load at various depths within each pile while soil settlement and pile settlement occurred following liquefaction. Specifically, the objective was to measure dragload and downdrag. With the inclusion of a static load placed on top of the pile groups, the results from these tests allowed researchers to evaluate the accuracy of existing neutral plane design recommendations and develop modifications to produce better agreement with the measured response.&nbsp;</p> <p>"This Project Outcomes Report for the General Public is displayed verbatim as submitted by the Principal Investigator (PI) for this award. Any opinions, findings, and conclusions or recommendations expressed in this Report are those of the PI and do not necessarily reflect the views of the National Science Foundation; NSF has not approved or endorsed its content."</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/04/2022<br>      Modified by: Richard&nbsp;Coffman</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2006323/2006323_10647521_1659617597861_IMG_1556--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2006323/2006323_10647521_1659617597861_IMG_1556--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Deadload on pile caps"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2006323/2006323_10647521_1659617597861_IMG_1556--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Deadload on pile caps"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">1.5 million pounds of deadload placed on top of the pile cap for each pile group at the Nucor Hickman testing site. H-pile group on the left and pipe pile group on the right. Sand bags at the locations of the blasting charges.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Richard A. Coffman</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Richard&nbsp;Coffman</div> <div class="imageTitle">Deadload on pile caps</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2006323/2006323_10647521_1659617501363_IMG_1571--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2006323/2006323_10647521_1659617501363_IMG_1571--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Liquefaction ejecta"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2006323/2006323_10647521_1659617501363_IMG_1571--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Liquefaction ejecta"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Liquefaction ejecta on the ground surface shortly after blasting.  Seven inches (178 mm) of soil settlement observed by painted line at the bottom of the pile cap.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Richard A. Coffman</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Richard&nbsp;Coffman</div> <div class="imageTitle">Liquefaction ejecta</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The New Madrid Seismic Zone (NMSZ), located within the Mississippi Embayment, has produced large earthquakes with detrimental effects due to deep soil deposits and resulting high peak horizontal ground accelerations.  The alluvial soil deposits within the Mississippi Embayment include loose sands that are located below the ground water table; these sands are susceptible to liquefaction.  Deep foundations are commonly used to prevent direct and indirect economic losses from liquefaction. However, settlement (downdrag) within the liquefied sand can cause downward friction (dragload) to develop on the perimeter of the each deep foundation, increasing the load and leading to excessive settlement. In the absence of field measurements, engineers are uncertain about the amount of downward friction that will develop and how much settlement will occur.  Intellectual Merit  To remedy this lack of understanding, small explosive charges were used to produce liquefaction under full-scale conditions and downdrag and dragload measurements were obtianed. Primary support for this project was provided by the Nucor Yamato Steel; however, supplemental funding from NSF was used to significantly expand the scope of the project. The results from these tests will allow engineers to evaluate the accuracy of existing design procedures and develop modifications to produce better agreement with measured behavior. Improved design procedures will allow engineers to design safe yet cost-effective foundation solutions that will remain stable during earthquakes. Limitations of the previous study at the Turrell Arkansas Test Site were overcome by 1) testing groups of piles instead of individual piles, 2) ensuring the neutral plane develops prior to blasting, and  3) ensuring the neutral plane redevelops following blasting.  Two pile groups were instrumented, installed, pre-loaded and subjected to a liquefaction event.  Seven, closed-ended, 18-inch diameter pipe piles and seven, 14x102 H-piles were fabricated for this project.  Strain gauges were bonded to each of the 14 piles, with intermittent delays associated with the COVID-19 shutdown.  Due to the COVID-19 shutdown at the Nucor-Yamato plant, the piles were moved from the Nucor-Yamato site to the Nucor Hickman site where the piles were driven.  Because the strain gauge installation was not complete for all piles at the time of movement, strain gauge application continued on the uncompleted piles while the completed piles were driven. A total of 14 strain gauges were attached to each of the pipe piles.  Seven strain gauges were installed to diametrically opposed sides of the piles.  A total of sixteen gauges were attached to each of the H-piles.  Eight strain gauges were installed to the flange of each side of each pile.  Each strain gauges was covered with waterproofing and angle to protect the gauges during driving and after installation.  Following pile installation, the piles were prepared for application of the concrete pile cap, and the concrete pile cap was formed and poured.  Installation of the piezometers and extensometers was delayed for nine months due to stoppage of work at the project site as associated with the COVID-19 pandemic.  Deadweight (1.5 million pounds) was added to each of the pile groups.  Blasting charges were placed in previously installed blasting casing and the charges were detonated to induce liquefaction in the soil.  The soil was successfully liquefied as indicated by: the measure pore pressure ratios, ejecta being observed at the ground surface, and up to seven inches (178 mm) of ground surface settlement surrounding the pile groups.  The residual load in the piles following driving and the increase in load transferred to the piles following liquefaction was measured.  Based on these measurements, additional load was observed at the location of the neutral plane for all of the piles in each pile group.  Following liquefaction, less soil settlement and less load was observed to develop in the pipe piles than in the H-piles; this was attributed to the densification of the soil surrounding the pipe piles during driving.   Broader Impacts  To improve our understanding of liquefaction-induced downdrag on deep foundations, blast induced liquefaction tests were performed on two different pile groups (steel pipe group, H-pile group) at a site in Arkansas. NSF funding was used to purchase strain gauges to measure the load at various depths within each pile while soil settlement and pile settlement occurred following liquefaction. Specifically, the objective was to measure dragload and downdrag. With the inclusion of a static load placed on top of the pile groups, the results from these tests allowed researchers to evaluate the accuracy of existing neutral plane design recommendations and develop modifications to produce better agreement with the measured response.   "This Project Outcomes Report for the General Public is displayed verbatim as submitted by the Principal Investigator (PI) for this award. Any opinions, findings, and conclusions or recommendations expressed in this Report are those of the PI and do not necessarily reflect the views of the National Science Foundation; NSF has not approved or endorsed its content."       Last Modified: 08/04/2022       Submitted by: Richard Coffman]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
