<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research: RAPID: Storm and tropical cyclone effects on the spawning activity, larval dispersal, and ecosystem impacts of an endangered marine predator]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/15/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>96729.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>96729</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06040300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OCE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Cynthia Suchman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>csuchman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922092</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Collaborative Research: RAPID: Storm and tropical cyclone effects on the spawning activity, larval dispersal, and ecosystem impacts of an endangered marine predator&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Dr. Yannis Papastamatiou (Florida International University), Dr. Alastair Harborne (FIU), Dr. Kevin Boswell (FIU), Dr. Claire Paris-Limouzy (University of Miami)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Many species of reef fish form large seasonal gatherings at specific locations to spawn. Such aggregations may lead to population overfishing if not well managed. Additionally, spawning aggregations in shallow coastal areas may also be susceptible to prolonged surge, high volumes of freshwater run-off and potentially changes in salinity associated with large storms and tropical cyclones. Yet, the impact from such events, which are becoming increasingly prevalent, has not been studied. This study investigates the impacts of hurricane Dorian on spawning activity of the endangered goliath grouper (Epinephelus itajara) fish species off the southeast coast of Florida. The broader impacts of the project relate to its value to inform fisheries management plans for goliath grouper. The project supports two early career faculty members and training of a postdoctoral researcher, a graduate student, and several undergraduate students at Florida International University. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Hurricane Dorian occurred at the peak of goliath grouper's spawning aggregation in Florida's shallow waters. This project will take advantage of ongoing acoustic surveys since 2017, telemetry, biophysical modelling, and behavioral studies of goliath grouper at spawning sites to assess how hurricane Dorian: 1) influence the duration of spawning events and the size of aggregations, 2) affect individual residency to spawning sites and spawning behavior, 3) change the dispersal patterns of goliath grouper larvae and identify nursery habitats with/without storm or hurricane events, and 4) assess the potential for trophic cascades at reef ecosystem level due to goliath grouper spawning aggregations as determined by changes on lower trophic level foraging rates and the subsequent changes to the benthos. Our combination of methods will provide insight into how storms affects spawning behavior from the individual to the group level, and how subsequent larval recruitment may be influenced. Finally, this project tests the utility of acceleration sensors for identifying spawning behavior in free ranging fishes, which will be of major significance to spawning studies across taxa.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/05/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/05/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2006295</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Claire</FirstName>
<LastName>Paris</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Claire Paris</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[cparis@rsmas.miami.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000482877</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/05/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Miami</Name>
<CityName>CORAL GABLES</CityName>
<ZipCode>331462509</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3054214089</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1251 MEMORIAL DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>27</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL27</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>KXN7HGCF6K91</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MIAMI</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>VNZZYCJ55TC4</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Miami - RSMAS]]></Name>
<CityName>Key Biscayne</CityName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>331491031</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4600 Rickenbacker Causeway]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>27</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL27</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1650</Code>
<Text>BIOLOGICAL OCEANOGRAPHY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1097</Code>
<Text>DIVERSITY: ROLE IN ECOSYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8556</Code>
<Text>Coral Reefs</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~96729</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="p1">Tropical coastal regions are home to a vast diversity of marine species living in some of the most biodiverse landscapes in the world. These ecosystems face serious environmental threats from climate-driven changes; they may be susceptible to prolonged surges, high volumes of freshwater run-off, and potential changes in salinity associated with large storms and tropical cyclones. Yet the impact of such increasingly prevalent events is largely unknown.&nbsp;We address this knowledge gap by exploring the effects of the powerful 2019 Hurricane Dorian, one of the most intense and devastating Atlantic tropical cyclones on record, on the endangered Goliath grouper, an iconic super-sized fish that forms large yearly spawning gatherings off the southeast U.S. coast.&nbsp;For this purpose, we built a state-of-the-art air-sea interaction model to reconstruct the track and strength of Hurricane Dorian (<strong>Figure 1</strong>). The connected atmospheric-wave-ocean (AWO) model allows for meticulous quantification of changes in current patterns, waves, tides, and storm surge days before and after landfall.</p> <p class="p1">We simulated Hurricane Dorian and generated high-resolution data products of winds, wave, and ocean circulation fields (AWO dataset documented and published in a NSF-approved open-data repository: https://zenodo.org/record/6127367). The model?s very high space-time resolution of a region as extensive as the western North Atlantic Ocean is unprecedented in the context of coupled AWO modeling of tropical cyclones. Our preliminary results show that the spatial patterns of ocean waves and storm surge are highly complex and sensitive to coastline morphology, bathymetry, tropical cyclone track and translation speed, and inner storm structure --key factors to the stalling of Hurricane Dorian on the Little Bahama Bank, just across the Florida Straits, before veering north and moving along the southeast U.S. coast (<strong>Figure 2</strong>). The largest surge in excess of 2.5 m occurred on the shallow Bahama Bank. The highest waves exceeding 9 m occurred south of the bank, where the ocean is deep. We also found that Dorian?s track played a crucial role in the slowing down and reversal of the Florida Current flowing north between Florida and the Bahamas. This is important since the Florida Current is part of the Gulf Stream system, the most powerful western boundary current in our world ocean. Indeed, the Gulf Stream stores and transports heat from the tropics to higher latitudes; a slowing down of this system could have catastrophic effects, essentially changing the climate.&nbsp;</p> <p class="p1">The category 5 hurricane crossed the Florida Straits before veering north and brushing the Central Florida Coast. This course generated pronounced surge and high tidal amplitude with disrupting effects on the Goliath grouper?s peak spawning season. To assess the impact of the superstorm passage on the fate of their offsprings, we coupled our AWO hurricane model with a larval tracking software (the University of Miami open-source Connectivity Modeling System <a href="https://github.com/beatrixparis/connectivity-modeling-system">https://github.com/beatrixparis/connectivity-modeling-system</a>) adapted to Goliath grouper traits. We simulated the release of embryos from a known spawning aggregation site in Jupiter, Florida. While our Florida International University partners on this NSF Collaborative project have gathered critical information on the spawning activities of the Goliath grouper (<strong>Figure 3</strong>), there is still a knowledge gap on fundamental larval traits, including buoyancy, vertical migration, and swimming. We then focused our simulation on the first few days of dispersal and performed sensitivity analyses on the vertical distribution of the virtual embryos. The simulations revealed that, independently of their initial depth, fish eggs and embryos are subject to downward transport to 100-200 m deep. This downwelling current is particularly strong at the continental shelf edge and is associated with the position of the Florida Current Front. However, as Hurricane Dorian moved closer to the coast, the wind patterns caused upwelling, a rising of deep waters. This brought the embryos near the surface, where they become vulnerable to UV radiations, turbulence, and northward transport into the Gulf Stream ?and loss to the population. We conclude that the transport and fate of the offspring is highly sensitive to air-sea-biology interactions. We posit that Goliath grouper target specific spawning aggregation sites that enhance the survival of their larvae and that superstorms like Hurricane Dorian have detrimental effects on already endangered marine predators. We also highlight the need for a better understanding of the early life history ecology of Goliath grouper</p> <p class="p1">In essence, our study advances the accuracy of hurricane modeling using an unprecedented coupled Atmosphere-Wave-Ocean approach. In this research, we provide new insights on the interactions of tropical cyclones with western boundary currents and on their disturbance on the larval transport and resilience of endangered marine predators.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/31/2022<br>      Modified by: Claire&nbsp;Paris</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2006295/2006295_10646472_1667197672397_ScreenShot2022-10-31at2.22.26AM--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2006295/2006295_10646472_1667197672397_ScreenShot2022-10-31at2.22.26AM--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 1 - Simulated Hurricane Dorian"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2006295/2006295_10646472_1667197672397_ScreenShot2022-10-31at2.22.26AM--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 1 - Simulated Hurricane Dorian"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Observed (black) and simulated (red) tracks of Dorian. Dashed and solid red lines show simulated tracks initialized on 00 UTC August 29 and 00 UTC September 1, respectively. Labels indicate the position of the storm center at 00 UTC of each respective day.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Milan Curcic</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Claire&nbsp;Paris</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 1 - Simulated Hurricane Dorian</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2006295/2006295_10646472_1667198335857_ScreenShot2022-10-31at2.38.28AM--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2006295/2006295_10646472_1667198335857_ScreenShot2022-10-31at2.38.28AM--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 2. Model evaluation with flight data"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2006295/2006295_10646472_1667198335857_ScreenShot2022-10-31at2.38.28AM--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 2. Model evaluation with flight data"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">A. Model surface ocean current velocity at landfall on September 2, 2019.  B. Map of model wind speed with flight track overlaid. C. azimuthally-averaged wind speed from both observed (black) and model (red).</div> <div class="imageCredit">Ana Vaz (A) and Milan Curcic (B,C)</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Claire&nbsp;Paris</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 2. Model evaluation with flight data</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2006295/2006295_10646472_1667198584918_ScreenShot2022-10-31at2.40.02AM--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2006295/2006295_10646472_1667198584918_ScreenShot2022-10-31at2.40.02AM--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 3 - Goliath grouper tagging"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2006295/2006295_10646472_1667198584918_ScreenShot2022-10-31at2.40.02AM--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 3 - Goliath grouper tagging"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Epinephelus itajara tagging is used to gather information on their spawning activities. These large marine predators are important for the health of coral reefs and mangrove ecosystems. Tagging was performed by our Florida International University partners.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Claire Paris</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Claire&nbsp;Paris</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 3 - Goliath grouper tagging</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[Tropical coastal regions are home to a vast diversity of marine species living in some of the most biodiverse landscapes in the world. These ecosystems face serious environmental threats from climate-driven changes; they may be susceptible to prolonged surges, high volumes of freshwater run-off, and potential changes in salinity associated with large storms and tropical cyclones. Yet the impact of such increasingly prevalent events is largely unknown. We address this knowledge gap by exploring the effects of the powerful 2019 Hurricane Dorian, one of the most intense and devastating Atlantic tropical cyclones on record, on the endangered Goliath grouper, an iconic super-sized fish that forms large yearly spawning gatherings off the southeast U.S. coast. For this purpose, we built a state-of-the-art air-sea interaction model to reconstruct the track and strength of Hurricane Dorian (Figure 1). The connected atmospheric-wave-ocean (AWO) model allows for meticulous quantification of changes in current patterns, waves, tides, and storm surge days before and after landfall. We simulated Hurricane Dorian and generated high-resolution data products of winds, wave, and ocean circulation fields (AWO dataset documented and published in a NSF-approved open-data repository: https://zenodo.org/record/6127367). The model?s very high space-time resolution of a region as extensive as the western North Atlantic Ocean is unprecedented in the context of coupled AWO modeling of tropical cyclones. Our preliminary results show that the spatial patterns of ocean waves and storm surge are highly complex and sensitive to coastline morphology, bathymetry, tropical cyclone track and translation speed, and inner storm structure --key factors to the stalling of Hurricane Dorian on the Little Bahama Bank, just across the Florida Straits, before veering north and moving along the southeast U.S. coast (Figure 2). The largest surge in excess of 2.5 m occurred on the shallow Bahama Bank. The highest waves exceeding 9 m occurred south of the bank, where the ocean is deep. We also found that Dorian?s track played a crucial role in the slowing down and reversal of the Florida Current flowing north between Florida and the Bahamas. This is important since the Florida Current is part of the Gulf Stream system, the most powerful western boundary current in our world ocean. Indeed, the Gulf Stream stores and transports heat from the tropics to higher latitudes; a slowing down of this system could have catastrophic effects, essentially changing the climate.  The category 5 hurricane crossed the Florida Straits before veering north and brushing the Central Florida Coast. This course generated pronounced surge and high tidal amplitude with disrupting effects on the Goliath grouper?s peak spawning season. To assess the impact of the superstorm passage on the fate of their offsprings, we coupled our AWO hurricane model with a larval tracking software (the University of Miami open-source Connectivity Modeling System https://github.com/beatrixparis/connectivity-modeling-system) adapted to Goliath grouper traits. We simulated the release of embryos from a known spawning aggregation site in Jupiter, Florida. While our Florida International University partners on this NSF Collaborative project have gathered critical information on the spawning activities of the Goliath grouper (Figure 3), there is still a knowledge gap on fundamental larval traits, including buoyancy, vertical migration, and swimming. We then focused our simulation on the first few days of dispersal and performed sensitivity analyses on the vertical distribution of the virtual embryos. The simulations revealed that, independently of their initial depth, fish eggs and embryos are subject to downward transport to 100-200 m deep. This downwelling current is particularly strong at the continental shelf edge and is associated with the position of the Florida Current Front. However, as Hurricane Dorian moved closer to the coast, the wind patterns caused upwelling, a rising of deep waters. This brought the embryos near the surface, where they become vulnerable to UV radiations, turbulence, and northward transport into the Gulf Stream ?and loss to the population. We conclude that the transport and fate of the offspring is highly sensitive to air-sea-biology interactions. We posit that Goliath grouper target specific spawning aggregation sites that enhance the survival of their larvae and that superstorms like Hurricane Dorian have detrimental effects on already endangered marine predators. We also highlight the need for a better understanding of the early life history ecology of Goliath grouper In essence, our study advances the accuracy of hurricane modeling using an unprecedented coupled Atmosphere-Wave-Ocean approach. In this research, we provide new insights on the interactions of tropical cyclones with western boundary currents and on their disturbance on the larval transport and resilience of endangered marine predators.          Last Modified: 10/31/2022       Submitted by: Claire Paris]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
