<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  A non-viral gene editing platform for cell therapies in the veterinary market]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>225000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>225000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Erik Pierstorff</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>epiersto@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922165</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is to advance a novel way to treat cancer.  The proposed project will use of reprogrammed, living immune cells to recognize and destroy cancer. The technology developed here can be used for treatment of this disease in dogs, and ultimately for humans.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed project is focused on application of novel gene editing technology to the engineering of cell therapies and demonstrating the safety of the resultant therapeutic modality in canines. This therapeutic modality is a human T immune cell reprogrammed with a Chimeric Antigen Receptor engineered to bind to CD20 (chCAR20-T cells), a protein found on the surface of cancerous B cells. Identifying optimal gene delivery and gene editing conditions is a primary focus towards enhanced manufacturing of CAR-T cells without the use of a virus. These optimal methods will be used to generate doses of allogeneic chCAR20-T cells and tested against multiple lines of CD20+ canine cancers in order to confirm their cytotoxic activity. The final objective of this proposal is to transplant chCAR20-T cells into laboratory canines to prove safety in vivo.  This manufacturing platform can be applied to the development of human cell therapies.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/08/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/08/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2006130</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Wesley</FirstName>
<LastName>Wierson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Wesley A Wierson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[wes@leahlabs.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000806736</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/08/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>LIFENGINE ANIMAL HEALTH LABORATORIES INCORPORATED</Name>
<CityName>ROCHESTER</CityName>
<ZipCode>559024504</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5159799851</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>221 1ST AVE SW STE 202-22</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MN01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>N8JEWCR8XZL4</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>LIFENGINE ANIMAL HEALTH LABORATORIES INCORPORATED</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[LIFENGINE ANIMAL HEALTH LABORATORIES INCORPORATED]]></Name>
<CityName>Rochester</CityName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>559040001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[14 4th Street SW Suite 203]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MN01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8038</Code>
<Text>Biotechnology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~225000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-f2127891-7fff-4d61-ccfb-466f496bffce"> <p dir="ltr"><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><strong>Project Outcomes Report for NSF SBIR Phase I Project #2006130 </strong></span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Project Outcomes<br /></span><span>Canine B cell lymphoma results in the death of more than 250,000 dogs in the USA every year. The standard-of-care treatment is a combination chemotherapy regimen originally developed to treat humans in the 1970s. Animals treated with this 12-16 vet visit protocol experience relapse post-treatment and succumb to their cancer within a year of the original diagnosis. Even with these pain points more than 50,000 dog owners elect treatment each year at a cost that ranges from $7,000-12,000, resulting in a ~$500,000,000 yearly market spend on this non-curative treatment for our canine family members. There is demand among both veterinarians and dog owners for alternative treatment options that can deliver a better outcome while remaining affordable compared to the current standard of care. Additionally, many canine cancers are analogous to human cancers in both physical (cell type, protein expression, and body location) and genetic (driven by the same mutations in DNA) characteristics. Thus, dogs and humans make great models for one another; a therapy that works for a specific type of cancer in one species may very well work in the other species. This allows scientists to test novel human therapies in dogs as a disease model that naturally mimics human cancers, rather than induced models of cancer in mice.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>In our NSF SBIR Phase I Project, LEAH Labs aimed to 1) build a platform technology that would permit the cost effective translation of novel cell therapies from humans to dogs for commercial application in veterinary medicine, and 2) lay the foundation of a model system to test novel therapeutic designs for human medicine. With this funding, we reduced to practice our platform technology to fight canine B cell lymphoma and, in the future, a litany of other canine cancers. To reduce costs of cell therapies, our platform relies on the use of CRISPR-based gene editing methods to reprogram living human immune cells to fight cancer in dogs. First, we translated patent-pending, non-viral gene editing technology from academic work in animal models and human cell lines to proof of concept cellular reprogramming of primary human T cells. We found that we can engineer human T cells with Chimeric Antigen Receptors (CARs), and use these CAR-T cells to specifically kill canine cancer in a test tube. These human cells are gene edited such that they do not express cellular receptors that would otherwise recognize and fight healthy dog cells. To validate that our human T cells do not cause toxicities in dogs, we demonstrated the safe transplant of these CAR-T cells into colony dogs, showing that gene edited human CAR-T cells do not cause acute or general toxicities in dogs whatsoever.</span></p> <span style="text-decoration: underline;">Broader Impacts<br /></span><span>The outcomes of this NSF Phase I SBIR have enabled LEAH Labs to begin our first proof-of-concept pilot trial in patient dogs with B cell lymphoma. We are enrolling up to 12 patient dogs in a Phase I/II safety/dose finding study. Demonstrating efficacy in this pilot trial will allow LEAH Labs to raise venture capital funding to bring our product through regulatory trials and ultimately to the market for dogs that desperately need new options to treat their cancer. Our innovative therapeutic platform will also permit the translation of similar CAR technologies for other types of cancers in dogs. Finally, because of our xenogeneic (across species) transplant platform, we are building the foundations to enable partnerships with human pharma companies to trial their novel human CAR assets in pets with spontaneous disease that better model human diseases than current state-of-the-art mice models. In this way, LEAH Labs will become a go-to partner for IND-enabling studies by trialing exact product designs in dogs that will someday be used in humans, while also bringing products to pets that have never before been possible.</span></span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/29/2022<br>      Modified by: Wesley&nbsp;A&nbsp;Wierson</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Project Outcomes Report for NSF SBIR Phase I Project #2006130  Project Outcomes Canine B cell lymphoma results in the death of more than 250,000 dogs in the USA every year. The standard-of-care treatment is a combination chemotherapy regimen originally developed to treat humans in the 1970s. Animals treated with this 12-16 vet visit protocol experience relapse post-treatment and succumb to their cancer within a year of the original diagnosis. Even with these pain points more than 50,000 dog owners elect treatment each year at a cost that ranges from $7,000-12,000, resulting in a ~$500,000,000 yearly market spend on this non-curative treatment for our canine family members. There is demand among both veterinarians and dog owners for alternative treatment options that can deliver a better outcome while remaining affordable compared to the current standard of care. Additionally, many canine cancers are analogous to human cancers in both physical (cell type, protein expression, and body location) and genetic (driven by the same mutations in DNA) characteristics. Thus, dogs and humans make great models for one another; a therapy that works for a specific type of cancer in one species may very well work in the other species. This allows scientists to test novel human therapies in dogs as a disease model that naturally mimics human cancers, rather than induced models of cancer in mice. In our NSF SBIR Phase I Project, LEAH Labs aimed to 1) build a platform technology that would permit the cost effective translation of novel cell therapies from humans to dogs for commercial application in veterinary medicine, and 2) lay the foundation of a model system to test novel therapeutic designs for human medicine. With this funding, we reduced to practice our platform technology to fight canine B cell lymphoma and, in the future, a litany of other canine cancers. To reduce costs of cell therapies, our platform relies on the use of CRISPR-based gene editing methods to reprogram living human immune cells to fight cancer in dogs. First, we translated patent-pending, non-viral gene editing technology from academic work in animal models and human cell lines to proof of concept cellular reprogramming of primary human T cells. We found that we can engineer human T cells with Chimeric Antigen Receptors (CARs), and use these CAR-T cells to specifically kill canine cancer in a test tube. These human cells are gene edited such that they do not express cellular receptors that would otherwise recognize and fight healthy dog cells. To validate that our human T cells do not cause toxicities in dogs, we demonstrated the safe transplant of these CAR-T cells into colony dogs, showing that gene edited human CAR-T cells do not cause acute or general toxicities in dogs whatsoever. Broader Impacts The outcomes of this NSF Phase I SBIR have enabled LEAH Labs to begin our first proof-of-concept pilot trial in patient dogs with B cell lymphoma. We are enrolling up to 12 patient dogs in a Phase I/II safety/dose finding study. Demonstrating efficacy in this pilot trial will allow LEAH Labs to raise venture capital funding to bring our product through regulatory trials and ultimately to the market for dogs that desperately need new options to treat their cancer. Our innovative therapeutic platform will also permit the translation of similar CAR technologies for other types of cancers in dogs. Finally, because of our xenogeneic (across species) transplant platform, we are building the foundations to enable partnerships with human pharma companies to trial their novel human CAR assets in pets with spontaneous disease that better model human diseases than current state-of-the-art mice models. In this way, LEAH Labs will become a go-to partner for IND-enabling studies by trialing exact product designs in dogs that will someday be used in humans, while also bringing products to pets that have never before been possible.          Last Modified: 01/29/2022       Submitted by: Wesley A Wierson]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
