<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research: Backyard Worlds - Characterizing Our Nearest Neighbors Through Citizen Science]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>11912.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>11912</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AST</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Zoran Ninkov</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>zninkov@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922533</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Brown dwarfs are objects that form like stars, but are not massive enough to shine with starlight. Recent discoveries point to an undiscovered population of brown dwarfs and rogue planets in the solar neighborhood. The Backyard Worlds: Planet 9 citizen science project (BYW) engages with volunteers from around the world using infrared images from the Wide-Field Infrared Survey Explorer to identify overlooked brown dwarfs in the immediate vicinity of the Sun. Over 150,000 volunteers have already contributed to the BYW project, identifying more than 1600 previously unknown brown dwarfs. The team will use this treasure trove of brown dwarf candidates uncovered through the BYW project to identify astrophysically interesting sources for detailed individual studies. The team will also extend the reach of the BYW project by creating educational materials based around the BYW science case and investigation strategy to be employed at the American Museum of Natural History and made available to the public.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will support a robust ground-based follow-up program to complement the Backyard Worlds (BYW) archival research project. Through a combination of photometry and spectroscopy, the team will observe an array of high-priority brown dwarf candidates for further analysis. These observations will allow for detailed individual studies of new exotic objects (e.g., extremely cold brown dwarfs, co-moving companions) to determine their physical parameters (e.g., effective temperatures, ages, approximate distances) and will provide the data needed for a more accurate determination of the local brown dwarf space density. These efforts will leverage the hard work of citizen scientists to identify the nearest, optimal brown dwarfs as targets for detailed characterizations with the forthcoming James Webb Space Telescope and ground-based extremely large telescopes (ELTs).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/21/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/01/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2007068</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Evgenya</FirstName>
<LastName>Shkolnik</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Evgenya L Shkolnik</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[shkolnik@asu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000856788</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/01/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Adam</FirstName>
<LastName>Schneider</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Adam C Schneider</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[aschneid10@gmail.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000789970</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/21/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate>07/01/2021</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Arizona State University</Name>
<CityName>TEMPE</CityName>
<ZipCode>852813670</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4809655479</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>660 S MILL AVENUE STE 204</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AZ04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NTLHJXM55KZ6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ARIZONA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Arizona State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Tempe</CityName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>852876004</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[ASU School of Earth and Space Ex]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AZ04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1215</Code>
<Text>STELLAR ASTRONOMY &amp; ASTROPHYSC</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1207</Code>
<Text>OBSERVATIONAL ASTRONOMY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~11912</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span style="color: #1d1c1d; font-family: Slack-Lato, Slack-Fractions, appleLogo, sans-serif; font-size: 15px; font-style: normal; font-variant-ligatures: common-ligatures; font-variant-caps: normal; font-weight: 400; letter-spacing: normal; orphans: 2; text-align: left; text-indent: 0px; text-transform: none; white-space: normal; widows: 2; word-spacing: 0px; background-color: #f8f8f8; text-decoration-thickness: initial; text-decoration-style: initial; text-decoration-color: initial; display: inline !important; float: none;">This program aimed to characterize new, nearby, brown dwarfs identified in the Backyard Worlds: Planet 9 (</span><a class="c-link" style="box-sizing: inherit; color: rgba(var(--sk_highlight,18,100,163),1); text-decoration: none; font-family: Slack-Lato, Slack-Fractions, appleLogo, sans-serif; font-size: 15px; font-style: normal; font-variant-ligatures: common-ligatures; font-variant-caps: normal; font-weight: 400; letter-spacing: normal; orphans: 2; text-align: left; text-indent: 0px; text-transform: none; white-space: normal; widows: 2; word-spacing: 0px; background-color: #f8f8f8;" rel="noopener noreferrer" tabindex="-1" href="http://www.backyardworlds.org/" target="_blank">http://www.backyardworlds.org</a><span style="color: #1d1c1d; font-family: Slack-Lato, Slack-Fractions, appleLogo, sans-serif; font-size: 15px; font-style: normal; font-variant-ligatures: common-ligatures; font-variant-caps: normal; font-weight: 400; letter-spacing: normal; orphans: 2; text-align: left; text-indent: 0px; text-transform: none; white-space: normal; widows: 2; word-spacing: 0px; background-color: #f8f8f8; text-decoration-thickness: initial; text-decoration-style: initial; text-decoration-color: initial; display: inline !important; float: none;">) citizen science project (BYW). Brown dwarfs are objects that are more massive than planets (like Jupiter), but are not massive enough to become stars (like the Sun). Their low-masses, and temperatures, mean that they shine brightest in infrared light. The BYW project uses infrared images to identify previously unknown brown dwarfs near to the sun, typically within a few hundred lightyears. Just like stars, brown dwarfs can form in binary systems. The architectures of brown dwarf binary systems help us to understand how they form. We examined existing astronomical images of BYW brown dwarf discoveries to search for evidence of widely separated binary systems. Several candidate systems were identified. One such system, named CWISE J0146-0508AB, was determined upon further study to have the widest separation amongst known brown dwarf binaries in the field (Softich et al. 2022, The Astrophysical Journal Letters, 926, 12). It was previously thought that such systems could not exist because they would be torn apart when they're young because of their dense birth environment. This surprising result implies that some systems must be capable of surviving such star-formation regions.</span><span style="color: #1d1c1d; font-family: Slack-Lato, Slack-Fractions, appleLogo, sans-serif; font-size: 15px; font-style: normal; font-variant-ligatures: common-ligatures; font-variant-caps: normal; font-weight: 400; letter-spacing: normal; orphans: 2; text-align: left; text-indent: 0px; text-transform: none; white-space: normal; widows: 2; word-spacing: 0px; background-color: #f8f8f8; text-decoration-thickness: initial; text-decoration-style: initial; text-decoration-color: initial; display: inline !important; float: none;">The main results of this study were led and published by a female undergraduate student. This work has helped to enable her to continue her academic career by pursuing an advanced degree in a graduate astronomy program. This program also enabled other BYW discoveries to be published, two of which were authored by citizen scientist collaborators (Bickle et al. 2022, Research Notes of the AAS, 6, 127; Kiwy et al. 2022, The Astronomical Journal, 16, 3).</span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/22/2022<br>      Modified by: Evgenya&nbsp;L&nbsp;Shkolnik</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This program aimed to characterize new, nearby, brown dwarfs identified in the Backyard Worlds: Planet 9 (http://www.backyardworlds.org) citizen science project (BYW). Brown dwarfs are objects that are more massive than planets (like Jupiter), but are not massive enough to become stars (like the Sun). Their low-masses, and temperatures, mean that they shine brightest in infrared light. The BYW project uses infrared images to identify previously unknown brown dwarfs near to the sun, typically within a few hundred lightyears. Just like stars, brown dwarfs can form in binary systems. The architectures of brown dwarf binary systems help us to understand how they form. We examined existing astronomical images of BYW brown dwarf discoveries to search for evidence of widely separated binary systems. Several candidate systems were identified. One such system, named CWISE J0146-0508AB, was determined upon further study to have the widest separation amongst known brown dwarf binaries in the field (Softich et al. 2022, The Astrophysical Journal Letters, 926, 12). It was previously thought that such systems could not exist because they would be torn apart when they're young because of their dense birth environment. This surprising result implies that some systems must be capable of surviving such star-formation regions.The main results of this study were led and published by a female undergraduate student. This work has helped to enable her to continue her academic career by pursuing an advanced degree in a graduate astronomy program. This program also enabled other BYW discoveries to be published, two of which were authored by citizen scientist collaborators (Bickle et al. 2022, Research Notes of the AAS, 6, 127; Kiwy et al. 2022, The Astronomical Journal, 16, 3).       Last Modified: 11/22/2022       Submitted by: Evgenya L Shkolnik]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
