<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[EAGER: SaTC: Collaborative: Addressing Social Media-Related Cybersecurity and Privacy Risks with Experiential Learning Interventions]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>19999.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>19999</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>James Joshi</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jjoshi@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928950</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The goal of this work is to create and evaluate experiential learning interventions to address privacy and cybersecurity risks at scale, particularly around populations with special privacy and security needs. These experiential learning interventions will provide both instructional content and customizable, realistic simulations of various social media environments in which to practice it; an initial platform for developing these interventions, along with a small set of pilot interventions aimed at general middle school audiences, have already been developed as part of the Social Media TestDrive initiative. Building on those resources, the first main aim of the project is to identify youth subgroups for whom the pilot interventions are less effective, then develop versions of those interventions targeted to the unique needs and characteristics of those subgroups. This will be done by integrating methods from inclusive privacy research and contextual inquiry, both of which aim to develop deep understanding of subgroups in a larger population. The second main aim is to explore the potential for experiential learning-based interventions across the lifespan, through doing formative work with older adults to identify their particular privacy needs and concerns and developing an intervention suited to those needs. The third main aim is to enhance the platform’s content creation and data collection capabilities, in order to make it more widely available for social media simulation-based interventions. Together, these activities expand the quality, scope, and impact of research around simulation-based educational interventions for privacy and security.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/10/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/10/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2008634</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dominic</FirstName>
<LastName>DiFranzo</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Dominic DiFranzo</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[djd219@lehigh.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000811406</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Lehigh University</Name>
<CityName>BETHLEHEM</CityName>
<ZipCode>180153008</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6107583021</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>526 BRODHEAD AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>E13MDBKHLDB5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>LEHIGH UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Lehigh University]]></Name>
<CityName>Bethlehem</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>180154731</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[113 Research Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8060</Code>
<Text>Secure &amp;Trustworthy Cyberspace</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>025Z</Code>
<Text>SaTC: Secure and Trustworthy Cyberspace</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~19999</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>&nbsp;</p> <div>This sub award focused on designed and building new technical features for Social Media TestDrive, an open source digital literacy education platform for middle school students. Social Media TestDrive uses simulated interactive social media experiences to provide students with a safe space to practice the digital literacy topics they learn in the classroom. It was been used by over 500,000 learners in middle school programs across the country.&nbsp;</div> <div><span>&nbsp;</span></div> <div>The main purpose of these new features was to assist in caring out large-scale long-term outcome evaluation study of Social Media TestDrive. This required rebuilding the platform to allow for the collection of user activity log data. A student dashboard was created to allow students to track their progress through their lesson plan and encourage them to complete their lessons. An instructor dashboard was also created to allow teachers to monitor their whole class and assist students that might need extra help. Voice overs were also added throughout the whole platform that would read aloud all instructions, lesson material, and social media posts. This helped to&nbsp;enhance accessibility of TestDrive for those with reading difficulties. Lastly new&nbsp;upgrades to the core organization of the platform codebase was completed to ensure TestDrive's longterm technical sustainability.&nbsp;</div> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/01/2023<br>      Modified by: Dominic&nbsp;Difranzo</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   This sub award focused on designed and building new technical features for Social Media TestDrive, an open source digital literacy education platform for middle school students. Social Media TestDrive uses simulated interactive social media experiences to provide students with a safe space to practice the digital literacy topics they learn in the classroom. It was been used by over 500,000 learners in middle school programs across the country.    The main purpose of these new features was to assist in caring out large-scale long-term outcome evaluation study of Social Media TestDrive. This required rebuilding the platform to allow for the collection of user activity log data. A student dashboard was created to allow students to track their progress through their lesson plan and encourage them to complete their lessons. An instructor dashboard was also created to allow teachers to monitor their whole class and assist students that might need extra help. Voice overs were also added throughout the whole platform that would read aloud all instructions, lesson material, and social media posts. This helped to enhance accessibility of TestDrive for those with reading difficulties. Lastly new upgrades to the core organization of the platform codebase was completed to ensure TestDrive's longterm technical sustainability.           Last Modified: 06/01/2023       Submitted by: Dominic Difranzo]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
