<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Simultaneous Remote Measurement of Skin and Sub-skin Temperature for Ships, USVs, &amp; Buoys]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>117007.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>117007</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06040300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OCE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Baris Uz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bmuz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924557</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This RAPID project is to develop IRISS (InfraRed In situ Skin and Subskin), an innovative infrared-based sensor system to measure skin and sub-skin sea surface temperatures from ships, Unmanned Surface Vehicles (USV), and buoys. Two cruises of opportunity will be used to validate this approach against other air-sea interaction measurements for a proof of concept. This unique system could be transformative because it has the potential to greatly increase the number and coverage of skin and subskin temperature measurements, which will enhance satellite validation, since these quantities correspond to the IR and microwave retrievals of sea surface temperatures, respectively. IRISS will also provide the first routine measurements of SSTsubskin. The resulting improvements to models for the cool skin and near surface temperature stratification will enhance topical oceanographic research, address current operational priorities, and improve satellite SST.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A significant strength of this approach is that SSTskin and SSTsubskin will be measured simultaneously with the same sensor. Furthermore, the system will provide the first radiometric measurement of SSTsubskin, which should be a more accurate representation than can be obtained by contact measurements. The availability of accurate skin and subskin temperature from USVs and buoy will provide new data with which to improve models for near-surface stratification. The team will participate in in two cruises of opportunity to validate the method and demonstrate that this new measurement technique can significantly improve models for the cool skin and warm layer effect. The cruises are the NSF-funded Breaking Bubbles (BB) on the R/V Sikuliaq in Dec 2019 and the NOAA-funded Atomic on the R/V Brown in Jan 2020.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/19/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/19/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2009985</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Andrew</FirstName>
<LastName>Jessup</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>T</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Andrew T Jessup</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jessup@apl.washington.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000323729</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/19/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Washington</Name>
<CityName>SEATTLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>981951016</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2065434043</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4333 BROOKLYN AVE NE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>HD1WMN6945W6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF WASHINGTON</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Applied Physics Laboratory, University of Washington]]></Name>
<CityName>Seattle</CityName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>981056698</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1013 NE 40th Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1610</Code>
<Text>PHYSICAL OCEANOGRAPHY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~117007</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>An infrared (IR) radiometer is a sensor that can measure the temperature of an object from a distance.&nbsp; When an IR radiometer is use to measure the temperature of the ocean, it measures the temperature right at the surface.&nbsp; This sea surface temperature is called the ocean skin temperature and is important for estimating the amount of heat exchanged between the atmosphere and the ocean, called the heat flux.&nbsp; Accurate measurements of heat flux are important for improving global climate models.&nbsp; Currently, IR radiometers used in oceanography can only go on ships because the complex calibration required makes them heavy, large, and power hungry.&nbsp; The advent of ocean drone known as Uncrewed Surface Vehicles (USVs) has motivated this project to simplify IR radiometer systems. The outcome of this award was to increase the capability of an existing laboratory facility for calibrating infrared radiometers and to develop techniques to characterize them.&nbsp; Previous experience with IR radiometer has shown that the measurement error depends on the temperature of the IR radiometer.&nbsp; The new goals were to (1) upgrade our existing infrared laboratory calibration facility to enable control and variation of the radiometer temperature and (2) establish techniques to characterize and parameterize the primary sources of error. In order to characterize the errors that depend on instrument temperature, we added a temperature-controlled instrument housing to our existing laboratory calibration system that uses a cone blackbody immersed in a precision water bath. The results are being applied to an ongoing effort to develop and test a simplified radiometer system that can be deployed in USV and buoys.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/22/2022<br>      Modified by: Andrew&nbsp;T&nbsp;Jessup</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ An infrared (IR) radiometer is a sensor that can measure the temperature of an object from a distance.  When an IR radiometer is use to measure the temperature of the ocean, it measures the temperature right at the surface.  This sea surface temperature is called the ocean skin temperature and is important for estimating the amount of heat exchanged between the atmosphere and the ocean, called the heat flux.  Accurate measurements of heat flux are important for improving global climate models.  Currently, IR radiometers used in oceanography can only go on ships because the complex calibration required makes them heavy, large, and power hungry.  The advent of ocean drone known as Uncrewed Surface Vehicles (USVs) has motivated this project to simplify IR radiometer systems. The outcome of this award was to increase the capability of an existing laboratory facility for calibrating infrared radiometers and to develop techniques to characterize them.  Previous experience with IR radiometer has shown that the measurement error depends on the temperature of the IR radiometer.  The new goals were to (1) upgrade our existing infrared laboratory calibration facility to enable control and variation of the radiometer temperature and (2) establish techniques to characterize and parameterize the primary sources of error. In order to characterize the errors that depend on instrument temperature, we added a temperature-controlled instrument housing to our existing laboratory calibration system that uses a cone blackbody immersed in a precision water bath. The results are being applied to an ongoing effort to develop and test a simplified radiometer system that can be deployed in USV and buoys.       Last Modified: 04/22/2022       Submitted by: Andrew T Jessup]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
