<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>I-Corps: A more efficient, more effective, portable oxygen concentrator</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ruth Shuman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rshuman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922160</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this I-Corps project is to improve the quality of life for patients on long term oxygen therapy (LTOT) as a result of chronic lung diseases through improved oxygen technology. Over 1 million Americans require LTOT to manage symptoms of hypoxemia and shortness of breath due to chronic lung disease. Although portable oxygen equipment exists, such as oxygen tanks or portable oxygen concentrators (POCs), many patients are faced with limitations with their equipment (oxygen duration, size and weight of devices, quantity of oxygen). More than a quarter of all oxygen users experience such challenges, severely affecting mobility, the ability to work and travel, and ultimately affecting quality of life. Improved technology in portable oxygen equipment can drastically improve the everyday lives of patients with the opportunity to rethink the current standards in managing oxygen delivery and improve patient care and quality of life.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project proposes novel oxygen delivery and management technology to improve the efficiency and efficacy of current POC technology. The proposed system incorporates a new delivery modality of mixed high-flow air with oxygen to increase the treatable range of oxygen flow rates while providing additional dyspnea relief. The proposed system also automatically titrates oxygen delivery based on patient needs (SpO2) to limit oxygen waste and increase efficiency of current POCs. Current research is investigating the safety and efficacy of the novel flow modality and automatic titration in patients through multiple in-human studies. Preliminary results suggest a potential increase in exercise capacity over standard LTOT and a decrease in shortness of breath with the novel flow modality.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/04/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/04/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2009716</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Soumyadipta</FirstName>
<LastName>Acharya</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Soumyadipta Acharya</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>acharya@jhu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4433266750</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000579774</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/04/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Johns Hopkins University</Name>
<CityName>BALTIMORE</CityName>
<ZipCode>212182608</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4439971898</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3400 N CHARLES ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MD07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>FTMTDMBR29C7</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>JOHNS HOPKINS UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>FTMTDMBR29C7</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Johns Hopkins University]]></Name>
<CityName>Baltimore</CityName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>212182682</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3400 N Charles Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MD07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-55eae476-7fff-5f5d-ed6f-8d9c8c32ed9b"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The project goal focuses on improving portable oxygen equipment for the 1.6 million patients on Long Term Oxygen Therapy in the US. Numerous limitations exist with portable oxygen equipment and management of oxygen therapy (inadequate oxygen flow rates, issues with portability and duration of oxygen supply, fragmented information flow regarding oxygen usage and management etc.), affecting mobility, independence, and ultimately quality of life of patients. We are working to develop more personalized and efficient equipment in order to meet the clinical and lifestyle needs of each patient. To achieve this, we&rsquo;ve incorporated automated oxygen titration to minimize oxygen waste and assure that patient oxygen needs are being met in combination with real time patient monitoring to inform respiratory care. In addition, we believe that the future of oxygen therapy requires better management of oxygen patients, who receive infrequent and often confusing information from multiple sources. We believe that our hardware and software ecosystem has the potential to transform the entire care experience by equipping both patients and their care team with better equipment and information about a patient&rsquo;s oxygen management and respiratory health.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Our venture originated out of the Johns Hopkins Center for Bioengineering Innovation and Design in 2018 as a Master&rsquo;s project and has since grown to include world experts in pulmonary medicine and oxygen technology. Through more than 500 hours of clinical observation and discussions within the field of pulmonology, our team discovered the unique challenges and burdens that patients face with portable oxygen and was compelled to create technology to enable&nbsp; active, healthy, and fulfilling lives for patients with chronic respiratory disease. Our conversations with oxygen patients, providers, advocacy organizations, government, and translational experts have guided us through the conception of an improved portable oxygen concentrator and built the foundation for the understanding of the oxygen patient experience.</span></p> <p><span id="docs-internal-guid-2d3319df-7fff-d246-a84b-ff1c6789603c"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>We have confirmed the value of a closed-loop concentrator following surveys with over 900 patients on oxygen therapy: 88% of oxygen users report wanting a closed loop device to help regulate their oxygen. Our concentrator therefore has the potential to transform the oxygen space by taking the burden of SpO</span><span><span>2</span></span><span> monitoring and oxygen adjustment off of the patient. With patients typically experiencing 10 periods of desaturation per day during daily activities, closed-loop titration of oxygen through continuous SpO2 monitoring can optimize oxygen delivery by minimizing critical desaturations and saving oxygen when higher flows are no longer needed for greater quality of life.&nbsp;<span id="docs-internal-guid-f6d69415-7fff-ec05-a626-3d4a53b3d9e6"><span>Building off of our core device, the continuous monitoring nature of our closed-loop POC creates the unique opportunity for personalized respiratory monitoring to inform respiratory care and improve health outcomes. Our original reseach is published in the Annals of the American Thoracic Society: Burden and Unmet Needs with Portable Oxygen in Patients on Long Terrm Oxygen Therapy, highlighting the urgent need for improved oxygen therapy and design targets for patient-driven equipment improvements.&nbsp;</span></span></span></p> <div><span><br /></span></div> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span><br /></span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr">&nbsp;</p> <div><span><br /></span></div> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/12/2021<br>      Modified by: Soumyadipta&nbsp;Acharya</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   The project goal focuses on improving portable oxygen equipment for the 1.6 million patients on Long Term Oxygen Therapy in the US. Numerous limitations exist with portable oxygen equipment and management of oxygen therapy (inadequate oxygen flow rates, issues with portability and duration of oxygen supply, fragmented information flow regarding oxygen usage and management etc.), affecting mobility, independence, and ultimately quality of life of patients. We are working to develop more personalized and efficient equipment in order to meet the clinical and lifestyle needs of each patient. To achieve this, we’ve incorporated automated oxygen titration to minimize oxygen waste and assure that patient oxygen needs are being met in combination with real time patient monitoring to inform respiratory care. In addition, we believe that the future of oxygen therapy requires better management of oxygen patients, who receive infrequent and often confusing information from multiple sources. We believe that our hardware and software ecosystem has the potential to transform the entire care experience by equipping both patients and their care team with better equipment and information about a patient’s oxygen management and respiratory health.    Our venture originated out of the Johns Hopkins Center for Bioengineering Innovation and Design in 2018 as a Master’s project and has since grown to include world experts in pulmonary medicine and oxygen technology. Through more than 500 hours of clinical observation and discussions within the field of pulmonology, our team discovered the unique challenges and burdens that patients face with portable oxygen and was compelled to create technology to enable  active, healthy, and fulfilling lives for patients with chronic respiratory disease. Our conversations with oxygen patients, providers, advocacy organizations, government, and translational experts have guided us through the conception of an improved portable oxygen concentrator and built the foundation for the understanding of the oxygen patient experience.    We have confirmed the value of a closed-loop concentrator following surveys with over 900 patients on oxygen therapy: 88% of oxygen users report wanting a closed loop device to help regulate their oxygen. Our concentrator therefore has the potential to transform the oxygen space by taking the burden of SpO2 monitoring and oxygen adjustment off of the patient. With patients typically experiencing 10 periods of desaturation per day during daily activities, closed-loop titration of oxygen through continuous SpO2 monitoring can optimize oxygen delivery by minimizing critical desaturations and saving oxygen when higher flows are no longer needed for greater quality of life. Building off of our core device, the continuous monitoring nature of our closed-loop POC creates the unique opportunity for personalized respiratory monitoring to inform respiratory care and improve health outcomes. Our original reseach is published in the Annals of the American Thoracic Society: Burden and Unmet Needs with Portable Oxygen in Patients on Long Terrm Oxygen Therapy, highlighting the urgent need for improved oxygen therapy and design targets for patient-driven equipment improvements.                            Last Modified: 10/12/2021       Submitted by: Soumyadipta Acharya]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
