<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Pre-Alliance Planning: Working Together ? Adelante!]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>124199.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>124199</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div. of Equity for Excellence in STEM</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sonja Montas-Hunter</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>smontash@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927404</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The Louis Stokes Alliances for Minority Participation (LSAMP) program assists universities and colleges in their efforts to significantly increase the numbers of students matriculating into and successfully completing high quality degree programs in science, technology, engineering and mathematics (STEM) disciplines in order to diversify the STEM workforce. Particular emphasis is placed on transforming undergraduate STEM education through innovative, evidence-based recruitment and retention strategies, and relevant educational experiences in support of racial and ethnic groups historically underrepresented in STEM disciplines: African Americans, Hispanic Americans, American Indians, Alaska Natives, Native Hawaiians, and Native Pacific Islanders. These strategies facilitate the production of well-prepared students highly-qualified and motivated to pursue graduate education or careers in STEM. The need for cultivating STEM talent has been well established. For the United States (U.S.) to remain globally competitive, it is vital that it taps into the talent of all its citizens and provides exceptional educational preparedness in STEM areas that underpin the knowledge-based economy. American students from diverse ethnic groups are underrepresented in STEM fields,and represent an untapped resource for the STEM workforce in the U.S.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;St. Mary’s University, Our Lady of the Lake University, Trinity University, and the University of the Incarnate Word, all Primarily Undergraduate Universities (PUIs) in San Antonio, aim to form a new Louis Stokes STEM Pathways Implementation-Only (SPIO) Alliance to increase the number of STEM baccalaureate and graduate degrees awarded to students that are underrepresented minority (URM) in the STEM workforce.  Three institutions participating in the pre-alliance planning project are Hispanic-Serving Institutions (HSIs).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will focus on identifying the causes of “leaks” in the STEM pipeline by first designing a collaborative and normalized metric to track student cohorts, identifying data gaps, and conducting a needs assessment among the Alliance students to identify barriers to URM student retention in STEM. Planning activities will include several workshops over the 18-month period.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Pre-Alliance Planning project seeks to ultimately increase the preparedness of URM students in STEM fields and increase their retention, through the evaluation of potential interventions and identification of student perceived barriers to retention. With regards to analyzing retention data, the Alliance will develop a plan, which will be disseminated through the higher education landscape, to document student retention in STEM majors beyond the first year and to track URM STEM majors who enter graduate/professional school.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The major outcome from this project will be the development of metrics, an evaluation design, and assessment methods to aid in development of the full alliance proposal.  Dissemination of project results have the potential for customization and application to other PUI and MSI institutions in the nation.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Support for this project is jointly provided by the Louis Stokes Alliances for Minority Participation and the Hispanic-Serving Institutions (HSI) Programs in the Division of Human Resource Development (HRD) and the Division of Undergraduate Education (DUE).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/17/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/17/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2009369</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Veronica</FirstName>
<LastName>Acosta</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Veronica Acosta</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[vgmartin@uiwtx.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000538950</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/17/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Ribble</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>O</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David O Ribble</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[dribble@trinity.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000367171</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/17/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Melissa</FirstName>
<LastName>Karlin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Melissa Karlin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mkarlin@stmarytx.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000741829</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/17/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Teresita</FirstName>
<LastName>Munguia</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Teresita Munguia</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[tmunguia@ollusa.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000598725</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/17/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>St Mary's University San Antonio</Name>
<CityName>SAN ANTONIO</CityName>
<ZipCode>782285433</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2104363720</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1 CAMINO SANTA MARIA</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>VGLPU3GKY6Q5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ST. MARY'S UNIVERSITY OF SAN ANTONIO, TEXAS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>VGLPU3GKY6Q5</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[St Mary's University San Antonio]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>782285433</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>077Y</Code>
<Text>HSI-Hispanic Serving Instituti</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9133</Code>
<Text>Alliances-Minority Participat.</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0420</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~124199</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>St. Mary's University, Our Lady of the Lake University, Trinity University, and University of the Incarnate Word are Primarily Undergraduate Institutions (PUIs) located in San Antonio, TX that formed an Alliance to increase the number of STEM baccalaureate and graduate degrees awarded to underrepresented minority (URM) students. Our Pre-Alliance Planning: Working Together- Adelante! program conducted a needs assessment among the Alliance students to identify barriers to URM student retention in STEM and opportunities to promote post-baccalaureate success. We conducted four workshops during the 18-month planning period and gathered input from faculty, staff and administrators on identifying: data gaps between the institutions, interventions currently in place that were successful, and potential interventions to address URM student persistence through graduation. The Alliance, along with an external evaluator, developed a survey that was administered to all undergraduate students at the four Alliance schools. This survey contained 21 questions that impacted a student's persistence in college, framed in the context of a student considering switching majors or leaving school entirely. The responses were analyzed by an external evaluation firm, and response elements were categorized into the three major themes of academic factors, belief factors and personal factors. A total of 600 students completed at least one question in the survey, but response rates decreased for additional questions. Examining the responses from URM STEM majors, analysis indicated that primary factors influencing decision making were similar between these groups, with the primary academic factors including courses too difficult or heavy course load; primary belief factors including fear of not living up the expectations of others or feeling out of place; and the personal primary factor of lack of money contributing to responses from three of the four institution respondents. &nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>After a thorough review of the literature on education research, STEM teaching and learning, and higher education, with a focus on interventions proven successful with first generation students and URM, this Alliance devised strategies to address the gaps identified in the survey. At the conclusion of this pre-Alliance planning grant period, the Alliance developed and submitted an Implementation proposal; this proposal incorporated the major themes and primary factors impacting STEM URM student retention and persistence, as identified in our survey results, and proposed strategies to address student-focused needs, tailored to freshman and sophomore students, faculty-focused needs, and institution-level adaptations. The proposed Alliance will focus on student development through multiple first-year experiences, increasing an "awareness of opportunities in STEM", such as guided mentoring and research experiences, followed by "engagement in STEM opportunities" that includes activities specific to the sophomore year, but continue throughout a student's undergraduate years. Student development activities will balance institution-specific activities, such as learning communities and first-year experience courses, and Alliance-wide activities, such as summer research and shared workshops. These activities will be designed to target issues identified in the survey results by focusing on academic needs related to course difficulty and academic mentoring needs; belief needs related to a student's sense of belonging and confidence; and personal needs by helping both the students and their families to understand the academic expectations and workload that comes with majoring in a STEM field. Faculty development will focus on leveraging existing resources to increase experiential learning pedagogy, improve faculty mentor training skills, increase technological abilities, and provide culturally responsive training to faculty. These training opportunities will be led by external professional facilitators and will bring together STEM faculty from all four institutions. We will develop an Alliance-wide website to disseminate our findings and demonstrate student achievement metrics.</p> <p>This Pre-Alliance Planning project sought to ultimately increase the preparedness of URM students in STEM fields and increase their retention, through the evaluation of potential interventions and identification of student perceived barriers to retention. We successfully developed a plan, which once implemented will be disseminated through the higher education landscape, to document student retention in STEM majors beyond the first year and to track URM STEM majors who enter graduate/professional school. We developed metrics, an evaluation design, and assessment methods for potential interventions, all designed to promote URM success in STEM. This Alliance has identified the tools and model design needed to increase the number of URM students in STEM, improve their retention through graduation, and increase their capacity for academic and professional success.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/14/2022<br>      Modified by: Melissa&nbsp;Karlin</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ St. Mary's University, Our Lady of the Lake University, Trinity University, and University of the Incarnate Word are Primarily Undergraduate Institutions (PUIs) located in San Antonio, TX that formed an Alliance to increase the number of STEM baccalaureate and graduate degrees awarded to underrepresented minority (URM) students. Our Pre-Alliance Planning: Working Together- Adelante! program conducted a needs assessment among the Alliance students to identify barriers to URM student retention in STEM and opportunities to promote post-baccalaureate success. We conducted four workshops during the 18-month planning period and gathered input from faculty, staff and administrators on identifying: data gaps between the institutions, interventions currently in place that were successful, and potential interventions to address URM student persistence through graduation. The Alliance, along with an external evaluator, developed a survey that was administered to all undergraduate students at the four Alliance schools. This survey contained 21 questions that impacted a student's persistence in college, framed in the context of a student considering switching majors or leaving school entirely. The responses were analyzed by an external evaluation firm, and response elements were categorized into the three major themes of academic factors, belief factors and personal factors. A total of 600 students completed at least one question in the survey, but response rates decreased for additional questions. Examining the responses from URM STEM majors, analysis indicated that primary factors influencing decision making were similar between these groups, with the primary academic factors including courses too difficult or heavy course load; primary belief factors including fear of not living up the expectations of others or feeling out of place; and the personal primary factor of lack of money contributing to responses from three of the four institution respondents.     After a thorough review of the literature on education research, STEM teaching and learning, and higher education, with a focus on interventions proven successful with first generation students and URM, this Alliance devised strategies to address the gaps identified in the survey. At the conclusion of this pre-Alliance planning grant period, the Alliance developed and submitted an Implementation proposal; this proposal incorporated the major themes and primary factors impacting STEM URM student retention and persistence, as identified in our survey results, and proposed strategies to address student-focused needs, tailored to freshman and sophomore students, faculty-focused needs, and institution-level adaptations. The proposed Alliance will focus on student development through multiple first-year experiences, increasing an "awareness of opportunities in STEM", such as guided mentoring and research experiences, followed by "engagement in STEM opportunities" that includes activities specific to the sophomore year, but continue throughout a student's undergraduate years. Student development activities will balance institution-specific activities, such as learning communities and first-year experience courses, and Alliance-wide activities, such as summer research and shared workshops. These activities will be designed to target issues identified in the survey results by focusing on academic needs related to course difficulty and academic mentoring needs; belief needs related to a student's sense of belonging and confidence; and personal needs by helping both the students and their families to understand the academic expectations and workload that comes with majoring in a STEM field. Faculty development will focus on leveraging existing resources to increase experiential learning pedagogy, improve faculty mentor training skills, increase technological abilities, and provide culturally responsive training to faculty. These training opportunities will be led by external professional facilitators and will bring together STEM faculty from all four institutions. We will develop an Alliance-wide website to disseminate our findings and demonstrate student achievement metrics.  This Pre-Alliance Planning project sought to ultimately increase the preparedness of URM students in STEM fields and increase their retention, through the evaluation of potential interventions and identification of student perceived barriers to retention. We successfully developed a plan, which once implemented will be disseminated through the higher education landscape, to document student retention in STEM majors beyond the first year and to track URM STEM majors who enter graduate/professional school. We developed metrics, an evaluation design, and assessment methods for potential interventions, all designed to promote URM success in STEM. This Alliance has identified the tools and model design needed to increase the number of URM students in STEM, improve their retention through graduation, and increase their capacity for academic and professional success.                      Last Modified: 03/14/2022       Submitted by: Melissa Karlin]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
