<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[2020 Conference on Question Formulation Technique in Higher Education]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>49763.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>49763</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EFMA</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Emerging Frontiers &amp; Multidisciplinary Activities</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Louise R. Howe</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lhowe@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922548</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This award will provide support for a one-day conference to be held at Northeastern University. The workshop will convene thought leaders, researchers, lecturers, and practitioners in higher education to learn how to more effectively teach the skill of question formulation in academic research settings, using the Question Formulation Technique (QFT) developed by the Right Question Institute.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Specific goals of the workshop include:&lt;br/&gt;1) Provide a hands-on experience of the QFT to practitioners in higher education.&lt;br/&gt;2) Increase dissemination of the QFT in academic research settings.&lt;br/&gt;3) Build a network of educators focused on developing question formulation skills.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This workshop will assist in building a community of practitioners committed to implementing new approaches for training academics to formulate research questions with substantive potential for societal impact. Successful scaling of QFT implementation offers the opportunity for broader impacts through catalyzing research directions that address pressing societal challenges and needs.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/06/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/20/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2010551</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sara</FirstName>
<LastName>Wadia-Fascetti</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sara Wadia-Fascetti</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[swf@neu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000441316</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/06/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Andrew</FirstName>
<LastName>Minigan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Andrew P Minigan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[Andrew.Minigan@rightquestion.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000751902</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/06/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate>03/08/2021</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
<LastName>Rothstein</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Daniel Rothstein</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[dan@rightquestion.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000750142</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/06/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Luz</FirstName>
<LastName>Santana</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Luz Santana</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[Luz@rightquestion.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000751903</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/06/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Margaret</FirstName>
<LastName>Wald</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Margaret Wald</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[m.wald@northeastern.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000805248</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/06/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate>12/20/2021</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tomoko</FirstName>
<LastName>Ouchi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Tomoko Ouchi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[tomoko.ouchi@rightquestion.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000850184</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/08/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Northeastern University</Name>
<CityName>BOSTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>021155005</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6173733004</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>360 HUNTINGTON AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>HLTMVS2JZBS6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORTHEASTERN UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Northeastern University]]></Name>
<CityName>Boston</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021155005</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[360 Huntington Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7633</Code>
<Text>EFRI Research Projects</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~49763</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-6c04d127-7fff-d8c4-5ab6-a30517dd0ae3"> </span></p> <h1 dir="ltr"><strong><span style="color: #000000; font-size: 12px;">Summary from the </span><em style="color: #000000; font-size: 12px; font-weight: normal;">Untapping the Power of Questions: Strengthening the Pratice and Culture of Question Formulation in Higher Education</em><span style="color: #000000; font-size: 12px;"> Conference</span></strong></h1> <p dir="ltr"><span>The Right Question Institute (RQI) and Northeastern University (NEU) held a working conference, <strong><em>Untapping the Power of Questions: Strengthening the Practice and Culture of Question Formulation in Higher Education</em></strong>&nbsp;(Untapping the Power of Questions Conference) virtually on two consecutive Fridays, September 17 and 24 in 2021, supported by the National Science Foundation</span><a href="https://www.nsf.gov/awardsearch/showAward?AWD_ID=2010551&amp;HistoricalAwards=false"><span> (NSF award number 2010551)</span></a><span>.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Untapping the Power of Questions Conference aimed to strengthen the culture and practice around question formulation and was a pioneering conference for this topic in higher education. The conference intended to address the gap related to teaching methods to generate questions for learning and research and lead to the recognition of the power of the skill of question formulation. The discrete skill of formulating questions, defined as generating questions divergently and then working to improve them through convergent and metacognitive thinking, is foundational and transformational for learning and research. Yet, the importance of teaching and learning the skill of question formulation is often overlooked.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The conference attracted interest from over 400 STEM faculty, administrators, postdoctoral research associates, and Ph.D. students. Due to capacity limitations, more than 80 participants convened, primarily as part of small teams from their institutions.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Applicant survey and preconference</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>As part of the application process for the conference, applicants completed a survey that consisted of six questions mainly about the practice of question formulation. The survey (N=173) shows that 1) there is a definite gap between the recognition of the importance of asking questions in higher education and the practice of teaching and learning how to generate research questions, 2) asking and working with questions in an initial stage of projects in applicants? work does not have high priority, 3) the majority of applicants did not have the opportunity to learn how to generate their own questions in their formal education, and 4) whether and how they were taught to ask and formulate questions has a great impact on how they teach to others.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>This survey reveals that 1) the current practice of asking questions in education is not consistent with the recognition of the importance of the skill of asking questions in higher education and 2) the current practice also does not accommodate the demand for teaching and learning how to generate one?s own questions.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Preceding the conference, a preconference workshop on the Question Formulation Technique for Research (QFT for Research) was held. Researchers can use QFT for Research to formulate better research questions. This preconference workshop stimulated the participants? interests in the conference topics and the potential impact of continuous use of QFT in research progress.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Untapping the Power of Questions Conference</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>In the Untapping the Power of Questions Conference, participants explored the power of question formulation for enhancing learning, for fostering transformative research, and for a better learning and working environment with greater equity and collaboration. They had an experience in using the Question Formulation Technique (QFT), a protocol to formulate one?s own questions, reflected on the practice of question formulation in higher education, reviewed and discussed the theory that explains the effectiveness of QFT, and prepared action plans to bring QFT to classrooms and research teams at their home institutions. Through active learning, participants recognized the power of question formulation and that higher education and research can be improved by deliberately teaching the skill of formulating questions.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The Untapping the Power of Questions Conference provided evidence that there is a new readiness among faculty and researchers to increase the use of question formulation in higher education classrooms and research efforts. </span></p> <hr /> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Participants' comments on the conference experience from the evaluation&nbsp;</span></p> <div dir="ltr"> <table> <colgroup><col></col></colgroup>  <tbody> <tr> <td> <p dir="ltr"><span>This is a transforming experience, and created many great connections.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>This has been a phenomenal conference, filled with immediately useful tools that can be implemented immediately! I've enjoyed learning about the process and meeting so many wonderful people. Thank you for making this opportunity available on a broader scale!!&nbsp;&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The benefits of question formulation go beyond a degree and extend to life in general.&nbsp; As a result, I think it is a very important skill that should be taught to students.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>There is value in having as many people understand the QF [question formulation] theory/method as possible, because people can hit the ground running in using it. It seems to me that it is so foundational it should at the very least be taught to all incoming undergraduates.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Having a predefined &amp; refined theory gives me as an educator a tool that is easier to implement. I see how this benefits my work but don?t have capacity to come up with ways to define or implement it, so the theory is much needed.</span></p> </td> </tr> </tbody> </table> </div> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/02/2022<br>      Modified by: Sara&nbsp;Wadia-Fascetti</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   Summary from the Untapping the Power of Questions: Strengthening the Pratice and Culture of Question Formulation in Higher Education Conference The Right Question Institute (RQI) and Northeastern University (NEU) held a working conference, Untapping the Power of Questions: Strengthening the Practice and Culture of Question Formulation in Higher Education (Untapping the Power of Questions Conference) virtually on two consecutive Fridays, September 17 and 24 in 2021, supported by the National Science Foundation (NSF award number 2010551).  Untapping the Power of Questions Conference aimed to strengthen the culture and practice around question formulation and was a pioneering conference for this topic in higher education. The conference intended to address the gap related to teaching methods to generate questions for learning and research and lead to the recognition of the power of the skill of question formulation. The discrete skill of formulating questions, defined as generating questions divergently and then working to improve them through convergent and metacognitive thinking, is foundational and transformational for learning and research. Yet, the importance of teaching and learning the skill of question formulation is often overlooked.  The conference attracted interest from over 400 STEM faculty, administrators, postdoctoral research associates, and Ph.D. students. Due to capacity limitations, more than 80 participants convened, primarily as part of small teams from their institutions.  Applicant survey and preconference As part of the application process for the conference, applicants completed a survey that consisted of six questions mainly about the practice of question formulation. The survey (N=173) shows that 1) there is a definite gap between the recognition of the importance of asking questions in higher education and the practice of teaching and learning how to generate research questions, 2) asking and working with questions in an initial stage of projects in applicants? work does not have high priority, 3) the majority of applicants did not have the opportunity to learn how to generate their own questions in their formal education, and 4) whether and how they were taught to ask and formulate questions has a great impact on how they teach to others.  This survey reveals that 1) the current practice of asking questions in education is not consistent with the recognition of the importance of the skill of asking questions in higher education and 2) the current practice also does not accommodate the demand for teaching and learning how to generate one?s own questions. Preceding the conference, a preconference workshop on the Question Formulation Technique for Research (QFT for Research) was held. Researchers can use QFT for Research to formulate better research questions. This preconference workshop stimulated the participants? interests in the conference topics and the potential impact of continuous use of QFT in research progress. Untapping the Power of Questions Conference In the Untapping the Power of Questions Conference, participants explored the power of question formulation for enhancing learning, for fostering transformative research, and for a better learning and working environment with greater equity and collaboration. They had an experience in using the Question Formulation Technique (QFT), a protocol to formulate one?s own questions, reflected on the practice of question formulation in higher education, reviewed and discussed the theory that explains the effectiveness of QFT, and prepared action plans to bring QFT to classrooms and research teams at their home institutions. Through active learning, participants recognized the power of question formulation and that higher education and research can be improved by deliberately teaching the skill of formulating questions.  The Untapping the Power of Questions Conference provided evidence that there is a new readiness among faculty and researchers to increase the use of question formulation in higher education classrooms and research efforts.      Participants' comments on the conference experience from the evaluation         This is a transforming experience, and created many great connections. This has been a phenomenal conference, filled with immediately useful tools that can be implemented immediately! I've enjoyed learning about the process and meeting so many wonderful people. Thank you for making this opportunity available on a broader scale!!   The benefits of question formulation go beyond a degree and extend to life in general.  As a result, I think it is a very important skill that should be taught to students. There is value in having as many people understand the QF [question formulation] theory/method as possible, because people can hit the ground running in using it. It seems to me that it is so foundational it should at the very least be taught to all incoming undergraduates.  Having a predefined &amp; refined theory gives me as an educator a tool that is easier to implement. I see how this benefits my work but don?t have capacity to come up with ways to define or implement it, so the theory is much needed.                     Last Modified: 07/02/2022       Submitted by: Sara Wadia-Fascetti]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
