<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[NSF Postdoctoral Fellowship in Biology FY 2020: Linking Micro- and  Macroevolutionary Approaches to Understand the Paradox of Polymorphism in  Plethodon]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>138000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>207000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DBI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joel Abraham</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jkabraha@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924694</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This action funds an NSF Postdoctoral Research Fellowship in Biology for FY 2020, Research Using Biological Collections. The fellowship supports research and training of the fellow that will utilize biological collections in innovative ways. Woodland salamanders can have different color patterns (color polymorphisms) in the same populations. Color types (morphs) are not simply different colors, they also vary in behavior, body form, and ecology. Long-term persistence of multiple color morphs remains an evolutionary puzzle, as previous studies have suggested that selection should either lead to one color morph dominating or formation of separate differently colored species. The aim of this project is to examine the evolution of a striped/unstriped color polymorphism in woodland salamanders using data collected from several U.S. natural history museums. Archived tissue samples will be used to understand the evolutionary relationships of salamanders. The fellow will also take digital images of polymorphic salamanders using high-throughput approaches, which will subsequently be identified as striped or unstriped by community scientists, and through machine learning approaches. The fellowship will facilitate mentorship training and foster opportunities for undergraduates who are interested in research. The fellow will collaborate with local high schools and participate in outreach events to share the results of this research. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Within the genus Plethodon, a striped/unstriped color pattern polymorphism has either independently originated 10 times or has been lost in 14 species that are fixed for a single morph. Extensive research on one polymorphic species (P. cinereus) suggests that the color morphs are associated with distinct sets of morphological and ecological traits. Thus, this system presents an ideal opportunity to test: 1) the origin and evolution of the polymorphism; 2) climatic niche overlap between morphs and species with divergent phenotypes; 3) whether there are non-random patterns of co-adapted trait complexes that evolved in Plethodon; and 4) how quickly those traits respond to fluctuating environmental conditions, including rapid environmental changes in the present. Using phylogenetic comparative approaches, the fellow will assess the relationship between intra-specific patterns and macroevolutionary outcomes within Plethodon, which represents a critical next step in understanding the evolution of this widespread polymorphism. This work is enabled by an interdisciplinary approach to use biological collections, while leveraging machine learning, and citizen scientist efforts. The end results will provide essential new knowledge about the evolution of color morphs and the relationship between polymorphism and diversity. Citizen science, mentoring of undergraduate students and outreach will broaden the impact of the project.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/09/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/18/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2010776</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Maggie</FirstName>
<LastName>Hantak</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Maggie M Hantak</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<NSF_ID>000731742</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/09/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Hantak, Maggie</Name>
<CityName>Gainesville</CityName>
<ZipCode>326016927</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Florida Museum of Natural History, University of Florida]]></Name>
<CityName>Gainesville</CityName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>326117800</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>001Y</Code>
<Text>Collections Postdocs</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7275</Code>
<Text>Cross-BIO Activities</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>097Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Impacts on Existing Activities</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>102Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-Disproportionate Impcts Inst-Indiv</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>1V21</Code>
<Name>R&amp;RA ARP Act DEFC V</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>010V2122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[R&RA ARP Act DEFC V]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~138000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~69000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Color polymorphic species are defined as having multiple, distinct color phenotypes (color morphs) within a given population. Across a species range, the frequencies of color morphs can shift dramatically, from an equal number of each color morph to fixation of one or another phenotype. How and why this intraspecific variation originated and persists remains unknown across most color polymorphic species. We assessed patterns of color morph frequency variation across space and time in the widespread Eastern Red-backed Salamander (<em>Plethodon</em>&nbsp;<em>cinereus</em>). Two common color morphs, striped and unstriped, are found across the range of&nbsp;<em>P. cinereus</em>&nbsp;and populations vary widely in the frequency of these two morphs. One hypothesis for the maintenance of the striped and unstriped color morphs across populations is niche differentiation related to temperature preference. To examine whether the two color morphs are associated with distinct climate variables across their geographic range, we developed a deep learning model to score color morphs from all images of&nbsp;<em>P. cinereus&nbsp;</em>on the community science platform, iNaturalist (N=20,318 images). Our model was highly accurate for scoring the two color morphs (~98%). We used this data to create separate ecological niche models of the two color morphs and found extensive niche overlap between the morphs, but striped color morphs had a wider niche breadth compared to unstriped morphs. To examine temporal variation in the frequency of the two color morphs, along with correlated traits that color is associated with (e.g., body size), we used extensive historical collections data at the National Museum of Natural history. We collected phenotypic data from&nbsp;<em>P. cinereus</em>&nbsp;spanning a 43 year time-period. With these data, we found that striped color morphs of&nbsp;<em>P. cinereus&nbsp;</em>were found at a higher frequency across time (and warmer temperatures), and these striped color morphs showed a simultaneous change of smaller body size. Conversely, the frequency of unstriped morphs declined over time (and warmer temperatures) and showed a correlated change of larger body size. Our results highlight that the color morphs of&nbsp;<em>P. cinereus&nbsp;</em>are differently affected by climate warming at both spatial and temporal scales. This research also shows that this color polymorphic system warrants further investigation as to the physiological, morphological, and ecological factors that contribute to the persistence of both morphs within and among populations. Two peer-reviewed articles have been published based on this work in the journals Scientific Reports and iScience. During this award period, I mentored multiple undergraduate students, during which they learned about the importance of natural history collections and the process of collecting and analyzing phenotypic data. In addition, I lead multiple amphibian and reptile-based nature hikes with members of the public through established and co-developed programs at the Florida Museum of Natural History. Lastly, during the award period, I participated in a panel discussion on using AI in the K-12 classroom for the University of Florida?s Thompson Earth Systems Institute (TESI) ? Scientist in Every Florida School AI teacher workshop.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/20/2023<br>      Modified by: Maggie&nbsp;M&nbsp;Hantak</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Color polymorphic species are defined as having multiple, distinct color phenotypes (color morphs) within a given population. Across a species range, the frequencies of color morphs can shift dramatically, from an equal number of each color morph to fixation of one or another phenotype. How and why this intraspecific variation originated and persists remains unknown across most color polymorphic species. We assessed patterns of color morph frequency variation across space and time in the widespread Eastern Red-backed Salamander (Plethodon cinereus). Two common color morphs, striped and unstriped, are found across the range of P. cinereus and populations vary widely in the frequency of these two morphs. One hypothesis for the maintenance of the striped and unstriped color morphs across populations is niche differentiation related to temperature preference. To examine whether the two color morphs are associated with distinct climate variables across their geographic range, we developed a deep learning model to score color morphs from all images of P. cinereus on the community science platform, iNaturalist (N=20,318 images). Our model was highly accurate for scoring the two color morphs (~98%). We used this data to create separate ecological niche models of the two color morphs and found extensive niche overlap between the morphs, but striped color morphs had a wider niche breadth compared to unstriped morphs. To examine temporal variation in the frequency of the two color morphs, along with correlated traits that color is associated with (e.g., body size), we used extensive historical collections data at the National Museum of Natural history. We collected phenotypic data from P. cinereus spanning a 43 year time-period. With these data, we found that striped color morphs of P. cinereus were found at a higher frequency across time (and warmer temperatures), and these striped color morphs showed a simultaneous change of smaller body size. Conversely, the frequency of unstriped morphs declined over time (and warmer temperatures) and showed a correlated change of larger body size. Our results highlight that the color morphs of P. cinereus are differently affected by climate warming at both spatial and temporal scales. This research also shows that this color polymorphic system warrants further investigation as to the physiological, morphological, and ecological factors that contribute to the persistence of both morphs within and among populations. Two peer-reviewed articles have been published based on this work in the journals Scientific Reports and iScience. During this award period, I mentored multiple undergraduate students, during which they learned about the importance of natural history collections and the process of collecting and analyzing phenotypic data. In addition, I lead multiple amphibian and reptile-based nature hikes with members of the public through established and co-developed programs at the Florida Museum of Natural History. Lastly, during the award period, I participated in a panel discussion on using AI in the K-12 classroom for the University of Florida?s Thompson Earth Systems Institute (TESI) ? Scientist in Every Florida School AI teacher workshop.           Last Modified: 09/20/2023       Submitted by: Maggie M Hantak]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
