<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[NSF Postdoctoral Fellowship in Biology FY 2020: Functional traits as indicators of  community structure and function]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>138000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>207000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DBI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joel Abraham</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jkabraha@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924694</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This action funds an NSF Postdoctoral Research Fellowship in Biology for FY 2020, Research Using Biological Collections. The fellowship supports research and training of the fellow that will use biological collections in innovative ways. Large mammal communities are being affected by climate change and habitat loss at a startling rate. This research will investigate how physical traits, such as teeth and skeletal elements, within mammalian communities are related to the specific environments where they are found. Using traits preserved in the fossil record, the fellow will explore how communities of mammals are naturally assembled and how those communities respond to environmental changes and human activities over long time scales. This research will contribute to conservation of biodiversity by providing a more complete understanding of ecosystems and how they change through time and across environments. While conducting this research, the fellow will be trained in novel methods of three-dimensional data collection from museum specimens, evidence-based techniques for teaching quantitative data analysis, and innovative strategies for communicating science to a public audience. The fellow will develop informational manuals local animals and how these change through time based on research results and will collaborate with 40 US biological field stations to use the manuals into their outreach programming.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Research objectives will use functional trait-environment relationships to connect trait patterns with mammalian community assembly and describe the related effects of ecological and evolutionary processes. First, the fellow will characterize trait-environment patterns in the fossil record by evaluating response lags in traits and functional groups in relation to the environment. Geographic, temporal, environmental, and faunal components of each lag will be used to identify patterns of primary and significant underpinning processes, such as speciation, extinction, and range shift. Second, the fellow will investigate how modern trait-environment patterns are affected by anthropogenic pressures, such as land use and non-native species including domestic and invasive species. Inclusion of land use patterns and replacement by or addition of new, non-native community members will be used to improve predictive trait-environment models of biodiversity change. With training from mentors, the fellow will integrate two research objectives and three training objectives to produce informal, place-based learning materials that incorporate the paleobiological results from this research. The fellow will gain mentoring experience by supervising two undergraduates who will participate in this project as student researchers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/23/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/18/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2010680</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rachel</FirstName>
<LastName>Short</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Rachel A Short</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<NSF_ID>000807472</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/23/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Short, Rachel A</Name>
<CityName>College Station</CityName>
<ZipCode>77843</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Texas A&M University]]></Name>
<CityName>College Station</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>778432120</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT/>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX"</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1127</Code>
<Text>Evolutionary Processes</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7275</Code>
<Text>Cross-BIO Activities</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>097Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Impacts on Existing Activities</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>102Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-Disproportionate Impcts Inst-Indiv</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>1V21</Code>
<Name>R&amp;RA ARP Act DEFC V</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>010V2122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[R&RA ARP Act DEFC V]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~138000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~69000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project supported a postdoctoral fellow under the Research Using Biological Collections focus area. The fellowship was terminated early because the fellow accepted a faculty position.</p> <p>Faunal communities will experience reassembly of their species as environmental and anthropogenic pressures continue. This project aimed to understand how community structure arises over evolutionary time scales and how functional traits respond to those pressures. Specifically, I proposed two research objectives: (1) characterize how mammalian community assemblages arise in deep time, and (2) assess the impact of anthropogenic effects on mammalian community structure and function. The first research objective was severely limited because museum data was not accessible during the COVID-19 pandemic. Once data collection is possible, this research will be continued as part of my faculty research program. The second research objective will be completed upon publication of manuscripts.</p> <p>To conduct this research, I focused on large mammals because they occur in most ecosystems today, often overlap geographically, and create communities that are uniquely related to their environments. These mammals are also well-represented in the Cenozoic fossil record and natural history museum collections making them valuable for understanding deep-time biological response to environmental change. This project supported the construction of novel models of functional trait-environment relationships and, in doing so, advanced the use of traits as a means for understanding community-level responses. One paper was published ("Trophically integrated ecometric models as tools for demonstrating spatial and temporal functional changes in mammal communities"). This project directly supported one other manuscript that will be submitted for publication soon. In addition to the products directly related to the proposed research, this fellowship supported the production of seven publications and nine conference presentations.</p> <p>I worked closely with undergraduate and graduate students in my host labs to contribute to broadening participation. Many of these students are women or identify as members of groups historically underrepresented in STEM fields. I provided graduate students with an 8-week training workshop focused on trait-environment analyses, coding modules, and research development. Four graduate students and two undergraduate students have been or will be included as co-authors on publications and presentations. I gave four invited talks to academic audiences ranging from an undergraduate class to a special topics roundtable. I was interviewed for a high school student's computer science blog and provided a short video for the National Buffalo Museum to celebrate International Day of Women and Girls in Science.</p> <p>This project also supported my training and professional development as an academic. I attended nine virtual trainings and workshops on topics such as analytical methods and science communication. I enhanced my skillset as a researcher by learning to collect and analyze 3D scans of specimens and as an instructor by learning strategies for teaching coding.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/02/2023<br>      Modified by: Rachel&nbsp;A&nbsp;Short</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project supported a postdoctoral fellow under the Research Using Biological Collections focus area. The fellowship was terminated early because the fellow accepted a faculty position.  Faunal communities will experience reassembly of their species as environmental and anthropogenic pressures continue. This project aimed to understand how community structure arises over evolutionary time scales and how functional traits respond to those pressures. Specifically, I proposed two research objectives: (1) characterize how mammalian community assemblages arise in deep time, and (2) assess the impact of anthropogenic effects on mammalian community structure and function. The first research objective was severely limited because museum data was not accessible during the COVID-19 pandemic. Once data collection is possible, this research will be continued as part of my faculty research program. The second research objective will be completed upon publication of manuscripts.  To conduct this research, I focused on large mammals because they occur in most ecosystems today, often overlap geographically, and create communities that are uniquely related to their environments. These mammals are also well-represented in the Cenozoic fossil record and natural history museum collections making them valuable for understanding deep-time biological response to environmental change. This project supported the construction of novel models of functional trait-environment relationships and, in doing so, advanced the use of traits as a means for understanding community-level responses. One paper was published ("Trophically integrated ecometric models as tools for demonstrating spatial and temporal functional changes in mammal communities"). This project directly supported one other manuscript that will be submitted for publication soon. In addition to the products directly related to the proposed research, this fellowship supported the production of seven publications and nine conference presentations.  I worked closely with undergraduate and graduate students in my host labs to contribute to broadening participation. Many of these students are women or identify as members of groups historically underrepresented in STEM fields. I provided graduate students with an 8-week training workshop focused on trait-environment analyses, coding modules, and research development. Four graduate students and two undergraduate students have been or will be included as co-authors on publications and presentations. I gave four invited talks to academic audiences ranging from an undergraduate class to a special topics roundtable. I was interviewed for a high school student's computer science blog and provided a short video for the National Buffalo Museum to celebrate International Day of Women and Girls in Science.  This project also supported my training and professional development as an academic. I attended nine virtual trainings and workshops on topics such as analytical methods and science communication. I enhanced my skillset as a researcher by learning to collect and analyze 3D scans of specimens and as an instructor by learning strategies for teaching coding.          Last Modified: 10/02/2023       Submitted by: Rachel A Short]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
