<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[NSF Postdoctoral Fellowship in Biology FY 2020]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>138000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>60000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DBI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>John Barthell</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jbarthel@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922618</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This action funds an NSF Postdoctoral Research Fellowship in Biology for FY 2020, Integrative Research Investigating the Rules of Life Governing Interactions Between Genomes, Environment and Phenotypes. The fellowship supports research and training of the fellow that will contribute to the area of Rules of Life in innovative ways. The Fellow will investigate developmental changes in the chemical composition of plant foliage and how these changes impact communities of plant-feeding insects over time. The project will use common milkweed, an iconic model plant known for its intimate association with monarch butterflies, as a study organism. Because climate change will affect the timing of interactions between species, it is vitally important to understand how organisms change over time and how that affects their interactions with other organisms. While performing this research, the Fellow will be mentored in cutting-edge research methods and contribute to local educational outreach and the professional development of undergraduate researchers.    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research will emphasize the interactive effects of plant ontogeny (i.e. development through life stages), climate variability, and genetic variation in structuring biological diversity across scales from molecules to communities. The Fellow will first explore the molecular mechanisms underlying variation in the timing of milkweed development through ontogenetic stages, and in ontogenetic changes in foliar chemistry, by linking phenotypic data with gene expression data. Next, the Fellow will investigate how climate variability interacts with plant ontogeny and genetic variation to drive phenotypic diversity within and among individual plants. This second objective will involve experimental manipulation of spring temperature variability and tracking of resultant changes in plant ontogeny and trait composition at population, organismal, and sub-organismal scales. Finally, the Fellow will determine the relationship between among-plant diversity in ontogenetic stage and community-scale arthropod diversity and trophic interactions, using experimental plant populations with different levels of ontogenetic diversity. The Fellow will receive mentorship from Dr. Will Wetzel and others at Michigan State University, including training in new molecular and statistical methods, and will also participate in mentorship of more junior colleagues. The Fellow will use concepts from this project to develop a professional development module for elementary teachers, with the aim of improving teachers’ ability to incorporate outdoor education and classroom-based research projects into their science curricula.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/10/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/26/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2010583</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Olivia</FirstName>
<LastName>Cope</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Olivia L Cope</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<NSF_ID>000814131</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Cope, Olivia L</Name>
<CityName>Madison</CityName>
<ZipCode>53706</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Michigan State University]]></Name>
<CityName>East Lansing</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>488246469</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7275</Code>
<Text>Cross-BIO Activities</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>068Z</Code>
<Text>URoL-Understanding Rules of Life</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~60000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Climate change is increasing not only mean temperatures around the globe, but the frequency and severity of extreme heat events. Although these events are of short duration, they may have long-lasting ecological effects. And because they are of short duration, they can occur at different times relative to the development of organisms. This research project investigated the ecological effects of heat wave events and how they interact with plant developmental trajectories and standing genetic variation.&nbsp;</p> <p>To achieve the project objectives, we installed a common garden of common milkweed (<em>Asclepias syriaca</em>) plants of different genotypes. We then subjected the plants to in-situ heat waves using portable heating chambers. Plants experienced heat events at different points in their seasonal development (May, June, or July). We tracked plant emergence and development, alongside herbivore colonization and herbivore-defense traits, for the rest of the season. &nbsp;</p> <p>Our results reveal that the interplay between heat wave timing and plant developmental timing is an important aspect of how extreme events will affect ecological populations and communities. In our study, heat waves that occurred before most milkweed plants had emerged caused developmental delays, whereas later-season heatwaves did not delay plant development. The timing of the heat wave thus effectively altered the developmental composition of the population.&nbsp;</p> <p>Changes in the developmental composition are important because plant development is a key driver of trait variation. For one defensive trait, leaf trichome density, a plant's developmental stage explained triple the amount of variation as did its genotype (30% vs. 10%). Trichome density decreases dramatically with development, and, interestingly, that decrease became even stronger when plants were exposed to an early season heatwave. Plants that experienced a May heatwave, although they had delayed emergence, reached a low level of trichome density sooner in their development than the later-heatwave or control plants. In summary, early heat waves appear to have the strongest ecological effects on both plant development and the interaction between development and trait variation. Understanding how plant developmental variation and extreme heat events interact will help shed light on the potential for resilience of plant populations and associated communities to environmental change.&nbsp;</p> <p>One postdoctoral researcher received training in research methods and career preparation as part of this project. In addition, three undergraduates had their first experiences in field research and gained skills and expertise in ecology. To date this project has resulted in two presentations, two manuscripts in preparation, and common garden and electrical infrastructure to facilitate future field-based heat wave studies. &nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/21/2021<br>      Modified by: Olivia&nbsp;L&nbsp;Cope</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Climate change is increasing not only mean temperatures around the globe, but the frequency and severity of extreme heat events. Although these events are of short duration, they may have long-lasting ecological effects. And because they are of short duration, they can occur at different times relative to the development of organisms. This research project investigated the ecological effects of heat wave events and how they interact with plant developmental trajectories and standing genetic variation.   To achieve the project objectives, we installed a common garden of common milkweed (Asclepias syriaca) plants of different genotypes. We then subjected the plants to in-situ heat waves using portable heating chambers. Plants experienced heat events at different points in their seasonal development (May, June, or July). We tracked plant emergence and development, alongside herbivore colonization and herbivore-defense traits, for the rest of the season.    Our results reveal that the interplay between heat wave timing and plant developmental timing is an important aspect of how extreme events will affect ecological populations and communities. In our study, heat waves that occurred before most milkweed plants had emerged caused developmental delays, whereas later-season heatwaves did not delay plant development. The timing of the heat wave thus effectively altered the developmental composition of the population.   Changes in the developmental composition are important because plant development is a key driver of trait variation. For one defensive trait, leaf trichome density, a plant's developmental stage explained triple the amount of variation as did its genotype (30% vs. 10%). Trichome density decreases dramatically with development, and, interestingly, that decrease became even stronger when plants were exposed to an early season heatwave. Plants that experienced a May heatwave, although they had delayed emergence, reached a low level of trichome density sooner in their development than the later-heatwave or control plants. In summary, early heat waves appear to have the strongest ecological effects on both plant development and the interaction between development and trait variation. Understanding how plant developmental variation and extreme heat events interact will help shed light on the potential for resilience of plant populations and associated communities to environmental change.   One postdoctoral researcher received training in research methods and career preparation as part of this project. In addition, three undergraduates had their first experiences in field research and gained skills and expertise in ecology. To date this project has resulted in two presentations, two manuscripts in preparation, and common garden and electrical infrastructure to facilitate future field-based heat wave studies.         Last Modified: 09/21/2021       Submitted by: Olivia L Cope]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
