<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[NSF Postdoctoral Fellowship in Biology FY 2020]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>138000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>207000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DBI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>John Barthell</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jbarthel@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922618</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This action funds an NSF Postdoctoral Research Fellowship in Biology for FY 2020, Integrative Research Investigating the Rules of Life Governing Interactions Between Genomes, Environment and Phenotypes. The fellowship supports research and training of the Fellow that will contribute to the area of Rules of Life in innovative ways. Most of our understanding of parental behavior comes from research on maternal care in mammals. As a result, we know very little about parental care in fathers, especially in cases where fathers alone care for offspring. Filling this gap is critical, as fathers vary in their expression of parental care, often with important consequences for their offspring. South American poison frogs show all three types of parental care: mother only, father only, and biparental care. These species therefore provide a unique opportunity to learn more about the causes and consequences of parental care. The goal of this project is to understand the mechanisms driving variation in parenting behavior by investigating hormone levels, neural activity, and brain gene expression. This research will add to our understanding of male parental behavior and the origins of individuality in behavior. In addition to innovative research involving students from diverse backgrounds, the project will expand an existing outreach program to bring hands-on learning of a wide range of biological topics to K-12 students.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Using the Dendrobates tinctorius (poison frog) study system, the mechanisms underlying individual variation in paternal behavior will be investigated by combining data from multiple hierarchical levels of biological organization. The Fellow will characterize individual variation in parental care in fathers and link this behavioral variation to hormone levels at time intervals, neural activity across brain regions, and gene expression specifically in neurons active during parental care. The work will also include conducting hormone manipulations and the use of gene editing techniques to modulate gene expression. Taken together, the project will address fundamental questions about the mechanisms underlying parental behavior and how individual variation propagates across levels of biological organization, from genes to behavior. Through the project the Fellow will gain research, mentoring, and professional skills for an independent research career. The Fellow will also participate in collaborative projects to mentor undergraduates and community college students, as well as to expand hands-on learning opportunities to K-12 classrooms through the Froggers School Program. The Froggers School Program will broaden the Fellow’s science communication skills and bring more STEM outreach to the traditionally underserved region of central Illinois.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/29/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/31/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2010714</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sarah</FirstName>
<LastName>Westrick</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sarah E Westrick</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<NSF_ID>000813711</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/29/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Westrick, Sarah E</Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<ZipCode>48109</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Illinois at Urbana Champaign]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>618013707</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7275</Code>
<Text>Cross-BIO Activities</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>068Z</Code>
<Text>URoL-Understanding Rules of Life</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>097Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Impacts on Existing Activities</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>102Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-Disproportionate Impcts Inst-Indiv</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>1V21</Code>
<Name>R&amp;RA ARP Act DEFC V</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>010V2122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[R&RA ARP Act DEFC V]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~138000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~69000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Individual variation in traits is essential for natural selection. Improving our understanding of how individuality in behavior is produced will guide our predictions and interpretation of how novel behaviors arise and are maintained. Parental behavior is of particular interest because it has important impacts on fitness through long-lasting effects on offspring. However, most of our understanding of parental care comes from studies on maternal or biparental species. In this project, I leveraged naturally occurring male-only parental care in a Neotropical poison frog to investigate individual variation in parental care. The central goal of this project was to better understand mechanisms of individuality in paternal behavior through linking individual behavioral variation in fathers to individual variation neuroendocrine responses, including circulating hormones and brain gene expression. I observed significant among-individual variation in parental care behavior among male frogs and have discovered many, but not all, female frogs are more involved in parental care than previously described. Additionally, preliminary results show increasing hormonal synchrony in mothers and fathers across the parental care period, potentially priming both sexes to perform tadpole transport after hatching. This observation of variation in maternal care in a male uniparental species led to exciting avenues of future research on sex differences in behavioral flexibility and the evolution of parental care. In addition to the intellectual merit of this project, poison frogs are an excellent charismatic animal to engage with community members outside of academia and teach about biological concepts big and small. Through this project, I led community engagement efforts through the development of a publicly accessible web stream of frogs in the lab and participation in multiple classroom visits. Funding from this project has provided invaluable research and professional training opportunities for the PI and undergraduate students. &nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/30/2023<br>      Modified by: Sarah&nbsp;E&nbsp;Westrick</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Individual variation in traits is essential for natural selection. Improving our understanding of how individuality in behavior is produced will guide our predictions and interpretation of how novel behaviors arise and are maintained. Parental behavior is of particular interest because it has important impacts on fitness through long-lasting effects on offspring. However, most of our understanding of parental care comes from studies on maternal or biparental species. In this project, I leveraged naturally occurring male-only parental care in a Neotropical poison frog to investigate individual variation in parental care. The central goal of this project was to better understand mechanisms of individuality in paternal behavior through linking individual behavioral variation in fathers to individual variation neuroendocrine responses, including circulating hormones and brain gene expression. I observed significant among-individual variation in parental care behavior among male frogs and have discovered many, but not all, female frogs are more involved in parental care than previously described. Additionally, preliminary results show increasing hormonal synchrony in mothers and fathers across the parental care period, potentially priming both sexes to perform tadpole transport after hatching. This observation of variation in maternal care in a male uniparental species led to exciting avenues of future research on sex differences in behavioral flexibility and the evolution of parental care. In addition to the intellectual merit of this project, poison frogs are an excellent charismatic animal to engage with community members outside of academia and teach about biological concepts big and small. Through this project, I led community engagement efforts through the development of a publicly accessible web stream of frogs in the lab and participation in multiple classroom visits. Funding from this project has provided invaluable research and professional training opportunities for the PI and undergraduate students.            Last Modified: 10/30/2023       Submitted by: Sarah E Westrick]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
