<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Interaction of Low-Energy Positrons with Atoms and Molecules]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>625230.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>625230</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>John D. Gillaspy</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jgillasp@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927173</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[General audience abstract:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research project focuses on science with positrons (the antiparticles of electrons). Positrons play an important role in basic science, including atomic, plasma and astrophysics, biology and medicine. They also have many technological applications such as new techniques for mass spectroscopy, the characterization of materials using positrons, and positron emission tomography (PET) to study metabolic processes and for drug design. While aspects of positron interactions with matter are well understood, there are many outstanding questions. When positrons and electrons collide, they can annihilate with the energy converted to gamma rays. Such processes are important facets in gaining an understanding of the physics and chemistry of the interaction of matter and antimatter. This research group has shown that positrons bind to many molecules (lifetimes before annihilation less than one hundred millionth of a second). The positron binding studies the group will be doing are relevant to positron surface states on materials and the fate of positrons in PET.  In terms of scientific education and training, the research will actively involve students and young researchers at all levels, from the planning of experiments to the dissemination of research results. The project involves small-scale experiments that are an excellent training ground for scientific and technical personnel.  The work will be communicated broadly, not only to physics audiences but also to those involved in plasma, chemical, and materials science, and gaseous electronics research. Antimatter in the laboratory is an important new frontier of science.  It is regarded with considerable fascination by lay audiences; and as such, it aids in helping broader segments of society to appreciate basic research in the physical sciences.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical audience abstract:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In previous research, the group showed that positrons bind to molecules. Two important intellectual challenges related to this phenomenon, and the modes of annihilation that result from it, are to develop methods to treat electron-positron correlations and to better understand the role of molecular dynamics in positron annihilation processes when a positron is in the proximity of neutral matter. The research being conducted under this award speaks to both of these issues. One focus of the project is gaining a better understanding of positron binding to molecules, the magnitudes of these binding energies, and what they depend upon. A second objective is gaining a better understanding of mechanisms for positron annihilation in molecules, which proceeds by a resonant process in which annihilation rates can be orders of magnitude greater than expected on the basis of simple collisions. While it is appreciated that molecular vibrations play an important role in this enhancement, the details are not understood.  The experiments will be conducted with a state-of-the-art, tunable, high-energy-resolution positron beam that was developed recently by the research team and is now coming to full capability. The excellent energy resolution of this new beam is expected to play an important role in making detailed annihilation spectral measurements as a function of incident positron energy. This can provide much more precise measurements of positron binding energies and key insights into the critical role molecular dynamics plays in producing greatly enhanced annihilation rates.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/08/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/08/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2010699</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>C.</FirstName>
<LastName>Surko</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>C. M Surko</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[csurko@ucsd.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000438030</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/08/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-San Diego</Name>
<CityName>LA JOLLA</CityName>
<ZipCode>920930021</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8585344896</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>9500 GILMAN DRIVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>50</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA50</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>UYTTZT6G9DT1</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, SAN DIEGO</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-San Diego]]></Name>
<CityName>La Jolla</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>920230319</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[9500 Gilman Drive, MHA 4581]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>49</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA49</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1241</Code>
<Text>AMO Experiment/Atomic, Molecul</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~625230</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The fundamental laws of physics, to the extent that they are currently understood, predict that for every particle of matter created in our universe, there will be a corresponding antiparticle. Examples of matter particles and their (antimatter) twins are the proton (antiproton) and electron (positron). One facet of our universe not currently understood is that antiparticles are far less numerous than particles of matter. Nevertheless, antimatter is important in many scientific and technological contexts. One common example is positron emission tomography (PET) to study metabolic processes in humans and other organisms and for use in drug design. Another is the use of positrons to study materials and material surfaces. The overall objective of the research done in this project was to better understand the ways that positrons interact with ordinary molecular matter, which is relevant for both fundamental and technological applications.</p> <p>Using techniques that the research group developed, it was discovered previously that positrons can bind to many molecules and that this process can occur by the excitation of a vibrational mode of the molecule. When this occurs, the positron can annihilate with an electron on the molecule producing a pair of gamma rays (in times ranging from picoseconds to nanoseconds). Such annihilation is a central feature of positron emission tomography (PET), for example. When the positron binds to a molecule, the annihilation rate is greatly enhanced. Many aspects of positron binding and the resulting enhanced annihilation are currently not well understood.</p> <p>Work during the present grant focused on understanding the mechanisms that determine positron binding to molecules and the magnitudes of the resulting binding energies. New measurements and reanalysis of older values resulted in much improved accuracy (in many cases, uncertainties of only a few millielectron volts) and tests of model calculations. The effects of molecular deformations (so-called conformers) were observed for the first time using binding energy measurements. The dependence of binding energies on isomerization was also studied, isolated from other parameters such as molecular polarizability and dipole moment. A theory of the change in binding energies upon chlorination of hydrocarbons was tested and found to be in good agreement with experimental measurements. Finally, two papers reported results for binding to ring molecules. They confirmed the unique and important contribution of molecular &pi;-bonds to positron-molecule binding. Good agreement was found between the predictions of a theory that included electron-positron correlations and so-called positronium formation to binding. This theory, thus validated, predicts the spatial location of the bound positron. It is dominated in the ring molecules by the competition between the &pi;-bonds and permanent dipole moments when present. Taken as a whole, the work on molecules done in this grant provides important new insights into positron interactions with a wide variety of ordinary matter systems including atoms, molecules, atomic clusters, and condensed matter systems. An important facet of this success was the new theories that were motivated by the availability of experimental measurements of binding energies.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/24/2023<br>      Modified by: C.&nbsp;M&nbsp;Surko</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The fundamental laws of physics, to the extent that they are currently understood, predict that for every particle of matter created in our universe, there will be a corresponding antiparticle. Examples of matter particles and their (antimatter) twins are the proton (antiproton) and electron (positron). One facet of our universe not currently understood is that antiparticles are far less numerous than particles of matter. Nevertheless, antimatter is important in many scientific and technological contexts. One common example is positron emission tomography (PET) to study metabolic processes in humans and other organisms and for use in drug design. Another is the use of positrons to study materials and material surfaces. The overall objective of the research done in this project was to better understand the ways that positrons interact with ordinary molecular matter, which is relevant for both fundamental and technological applications.  Using techniques that the research group developed, it was discovered previously that positrons can bind to many molecules and that this process can occur by the excitation of a vibrational mode of the molecule. When this occurs, the positron can annihilate with an electron on the molecule producing a pair of gamma rays (in times ranging from picoseconds to nanoseconds). Such annihilation is a central feature of positron emission tomography (PET), for example. When the positron binds to a molecule, the annihilation rate is greatly enhanced. Many aspects of positron binding and the resulting enhanced annihilation are currently not well understood.  Work during the present grant focused on understanding the mechanisms that determine positron binding to molecules and the magnitudes of the resulting binding energies. New measurements and reanalysis of older values resulted in much improved accuracy (in many cases, uncertainties of only a few millielectron volts) and tests of model calculations. The effects of molecular deformations (so-called conformers) were observed for the first time using binding energy measurements. The dependence of binding energies on isomerization was also studied, isolated from other parameters such as molecular polarizability and dipole moment. A theory of the change in binding energies upon chlorination of hydrocarbons was tested and found to be in good agreement with experimental measurements. Finally, two papers reported results for binding to ring molecules. They confirmed the unique and important contribution of molecular &pi;-bonds to positron-molecule binding. Good agreement was found between the predictions of a theory that included electron-positron correlations and so-called positronium formation to binding. This theory, thus validated, predicts the spatial location of the bound positron. It is dominated in the ring molecules by the competition between the &pi;-bonds and permanent dipole moments when present. Taken as a whole, the work on molecules done in this grant provides important new insights into positron interactions with a wide variety of ordinary matter systems including atoms, molecules, atomic clusters, and condensed matter systems. An important facet of this success was the new theories that were motivated by the availability of experimental measurements of binding energies.       Last Modified: 10/24/2023       Submitted by: C. M Surko]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
