<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[NSF Postdoctoral Fellowship in Biology FY 2020: Mechanisms driving food web dynamics in terrestrial ecosystems]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>138000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>129000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DBI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joel Abraham</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jkabraha@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924694</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This action funds an NSF Postdoctoral Research Fellowship in Biology for FY 2020, Research Using Biological Collections. The fellowship supports research and training of the Fellow that will utilize biological collections in innovative ways. Despite nearly a century of research, what regulates energy flow and food web structure remains one of the most elusive questions in ecology. Historically, food webs were classified as either “green” webs stemming from primary producers like plants or “brown” webs with decomposers fueled by decaying material. However, up to 90% of primary production escapes herbivores and is decomposed in brown webs that transform indigestible plant material into usable energy. The flow of green energy to brown food webs is well documented, but the flow of brown energy in the other direction to animal consumers is poorly understood. Moreover, this flow of brown energy has significant potential to impact food webs and could determine food chain length, especially in terrestrial ecosystems. This research will analyze plant, animal, and fungal specimens to measure the consumption of green and brown energy by small mammal consumers. Further, this work will assess food web structure across the “sky islands” of New Mexico and will test the impact of brown energy consumption on food chain length. This project will also strive to increase diversity in STEM by engaging K-12 and undergraduate students to promote collections-based education and outreach. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will use specimens from New Mexico sky islands across a gradient of primary production and ecosystem size to quantify the drivers of food web integration and trophic structure in terrestrial ecosystems. The project leverages extensive mammal and herbarium specimens at the University of New Mexico’s Museum of Southwestern Biology, as well as fungal collections from the USDA Center for Forest Mycology Research. The fellow will measure the assimilation of green (e.g., plant) and brown (e.g., bacterial, fungal) energy by small mammals using carbon isotope analysis of essential amino acids, and will estimate trophic position and food web structure using nitrogen isotope analysis of trophic and source amino acids. The fellow will then use mixed effects models to assess the drivers of food web structure and test the relative influence of brown energy assimilation on food chain length across terrestrial ecosystems. This project will also focus on increasing diversity in STEM, engaging K-12 education, and promoting collections-based education through the direct mentoring of minority undergraduates and through hands-on workshops for high school students. Lastly, the project will interface with an undergraduate mammalogy course to provide hands-on research experience and to develop online learning modules for collections-based education.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/13/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/08/2023</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2010712</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Philip</FirstName>
<LastName>Manlick</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Philip J Manlick</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<NSF_ID>000790283</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/13/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Manlick, Philip J</Name>
<CityName>Madison</CityName>
<ZipCode>53704</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of New Mexico]]></Name>
<CityName>Albuquerque</CityName>
<StateCode>NM</StateCode>
<ZipCode>871310001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Mexico</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NM01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>001Y</Code>
<Text>Collections Postdocs</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7275</Code>
<Text>Cross-BIO Activities</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>097Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Impacts on Existing Activities</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>102Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-Disproportionate Impcts Inst-Indiv</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>1V21</Code>
<Name>R&amp;RA ARP Act DEFC V</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>010V2122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[R&RA ARP Act DEFC V]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~129000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~0</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project uses specimens from New Mexico sky islands to quantify the drivers of food web integration and trophic structure in terrestrial ecosystems. Specifically, the project uses cutting-edge compound-specific stable isotope analysis of individual amino acids (&delta;13C, &delta;15N) from biological collections at the&nbsp;University of New Mexico Museum of Southwestern Biology (UNM-MSB) to quantify the integration of green and brown food webs and the consequences for trophic position and food chain length. The project also focuses on increasing diversity in STEM and promoting collections-based education through the direct mentoring of high school and undergraduate students (e.g., interface with an undergraduate mammalogy course to provide hands-on research experience).</p> <p>I developed methods to quantify food web coupling using consumer tissues and then applied these approaches to museum collections in New Mexico and Alaska. I found that amino acid isotope analysis can be used to trace carbon flow through food webs (Manlick and Newsome 2022), that the coupling of green and brown food webs regulates trophic position in wild mammals (Manlick et al. 2023), and that climate warming is altering food web linkages (Manlick et al, in revision). In addition, the tools developed through this work were used to assess the functional role of the gut microbiome in mammals (Besser, Manlick, et al. 2023).</p> <div class="accomplishments bottomBorder"><dl class="clearing"><dd> </dd></dl></div> <dd> </dd> <div class="accomplishments bottomBorder"> <div class="tinyMCEContent"> <p>We analyzed small mammal specimens from the University of New Mexico Museum of Southwestern Biology (UNM-MSB), collected additional specimens across New Mexico sky islands, and analyzed food web dynamics through space and time. I also particpiated in multiple stable isotope workshops for K-12 students in the Bosque Ecosystem Monitoring Program (https://bemp.org/) and graduate students enrolled in IsoCamp (https://isocamp.org/).&nbsp;</p> </div> <dl class="clearing"><dd> <div class="tinyMCEContent"> <p>&nbsp;</p> </div> </dd></dl></div><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/03/2023<br>      Modified by: Philip&nbsp;J&nbsp;Manlick</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project uses specimens from New Mexico sky islands to quantify the drivers of food web integration and trophic structure in terrestrial ecosystems. Specifically, the project uses cutting-edge compound-specific stable isotope analysis of individual amino acids (&delta;13C, &delta;15N) from biological collections at the University of New Mexico Museum of Southwestern Biology (UNM-MSB) to quantify the integration of green and brown food webs and the consequences for trophic position and food chain length. The project also focuses on increasing diversity in STEM and promoting collections-based education through the direct mentoring of high school and undergraduate students (e.g., interface with an undergraduate mammalogy course to provide hands-on research experience).  I developed methods to quantify food web coupling using consumer tissues and then applied these approaches to museum collections in New Mexico and Alaska. I found that amino acid isotope analysis can be used to trace carbon flow through food webs (Manlick and Newsome 2022), that the coupling of green and brown food webs regulates trophic position in wild mammals (Manlick et al. 2023), and that climate warming is altering food web linkages (Manlick et al, in revision). In addition, the tools developed through this work were used to assess the functional role of the gut microbiome in mammals (Besser, Manlick, et al. 2023).        We analyzed small mammal specimens from the University of New Mexico Museum of Southwestern Biology (UNM-MSB), collected additional specimens across New Mexico sky islands, and analyzed food web dynamics through space and time. I also particpiated in multiple stable isotope workshops for K-12 students in the Bosque Ecosystem Monitoring Program (https://bemp.org/) and graduate students enrolled in IsoCamp (https://isocamp.org/).                Last Modified: 10/03/2023       Submitted by: Philip J Manlick]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
