<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Bridging Science Teaching and Learning in Title 1 Schools]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>449981.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>449981</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DRL</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Asli Sezen-Barrie</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>asezenba@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924676</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This project addresses a long-standing challenge in science education centered on a national commitment to and interest in advancing the prosperity and welfare of young learners who have been historically underrepresented in science. It addresses challenges with broadening participation in science by providing equity and access to quality science instruction at Title 1 elementary schools in metro Atlanta, Georgia. Title 1 schools are schools with large concentrations of low-income students that receive supplemental funds to assist in meeting educational goals and educational needs of students living near poverty levels. Opportunities to learn science in elementary school are particularly limited; especially in those schools that serve racially and ethnically diverse children and children suffering from poverty. Interventions aimed at broadening participation have been limited in both impact and scope. This project is addressing this challenge through the development, implementation, and evaluation of a professional development model that will prepare teachers to effectively utilize science education practices grounded in culturally responsive pedagogy. It provides a new science instruction model that intersects the best practices in science education with the theoretical principles of culturally relevant/responsive pedagogy found to influence students from low economic, diverse communities. By focusing on both in-service and preservice teachers, the project will make a valuable contribution to the understanding of teacher education across the trajectory of  educators’ careers and deepen an understanding of how to prepare teachers to adopt and effectively utilize effective practices in their everyday classrooms, particularly in relation to science teaching and learning.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will involve 30 preservice and 20 in-service teachers participating in a summer academy and workshops introducing them to instructional features of the model that will later be used during instruction with the students. Instruction provided by the teachers will impact approximately 1,420 students. The goal of the project is to design and test an innovative science instruction model that intersects the best practices in science education with the principles of culturally responsive pedagogy. The two-year design and development project incorporate mixed methods to examine the three components of the model hypothesized as critical for improvements in teacher practice: culturally responsive classroom management, discourse, and anchoring. Use of qualitative and quantitative methods and measures during exploration provides critical information on how to support instruction in Title 1 STEM schools in ways that are feasible, yet effective. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Discovery Research K-12 program (DRK-12) seeks to significantly enhance the learning and teaching of science, technology, engineering, and mathematics (STEM) by preK-12 students and teachers, through research and development of innovative resources, models and tools. Projects in the DRK-12 program build on fundamental research in STEM education and prior research and development efforts that provide theoretical and empirical justification for proposed projects.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/15/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/15/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2010361</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nancy</FirstName>
<LastName>Schafer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nancy J Schafer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[njs@gsu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000544965</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/15/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Brian</FirstName>
<LastName>Williams</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Brian A Williams</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[bawillia@fiu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000544968</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/15/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Diane</FirstName>
<LastName>Truscott</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Diane M Truscott</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[dmt@gsu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000815088</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/15/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Georgia State University Research Foundation, Inc.</Name>
<CityName>ATLANTA</CityName>
<ZipCode>303032921</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4044133570</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>58 EDGEWOOD AVE NE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[FL 3]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>MNS7B9CVKDN7</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GEORGIA STATE UNIVERSITY RESEARCH FOUNDATION INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Georgia State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>303033219</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[30 Pryor Street SW]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7645</Code>
<Text>Discovery Research K-12</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0420</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~449981</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p id="docs-internal-guid-4a4af4e9-7fff-1cdf-0228-4637119f0780" style="line-height: 1.38; margin-top: 0pt; margin-bottom: 0pt;" dir="ltr"><span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">Bridging Science Teaching and Learning in Title 1 Schools: SCI-Bridge was an early-stage design and development project to create a new model integrating best practices in preK-5 science education with culturally relevant pedagogy (CRP) for Title 1 elementary schools (Project # #2010361; 2020-2022).&nbsp; The SCI-Bridge project sought to address racial and socioeconomic related disparities in science learning at the elementary school level through the development, implementation, and evaluation of a professional development model preparing teachers to effectively utilize science education practices grounded in culturally relevant pedagogy (CRP). Specifically, the SCI-Bridge model prepared teachers to use three instructional tools thought to support their development as culturally relevant educators (facilitated discourse, contextual anchoring, and culturally responsive classroom management) in addition to inquiry-based approaches to science teaching. As a result of their participation in the model, teachers, both inservice and preservice, were better prepared to bridge school-based science content with the culture, prior knowledge and lived experiences of students in their classrooms. The project and its findings advance the field&rsquo;s understanding of effective teacher preparation and professional development as they related to elementary science education and efforts to address racial and socio-economic disparities in science education (e.g., participation, literacy, performance).</span></p> <p style="line-height: 1.38; margin-top: 0pt; margin-bottom: 0pt;" dir="ltr"><span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;"><br /></span></p> <p style="line-height: 1.38; margin-top: 0pt; margin-bottom: 0pt;" dir="ltr"><span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">During the grant period, the SCI-Bridge project provided professional development to both inservice and preservice teachers committed to and/or teaching in Title 1 urban schools.&nbsp;</span></p> <p style="line-height: 1.38; margin-top: 0pt; margin-bottom: 0pt;" dir="ltr"><span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">As a result of their participation in the project, educators, emerging and veteran, demonstrated greater confidence and efficacy with the three SCI-Bridge instructional tools; contextual anchoring, facilitated discourse, and culturally responsive classroom management. Participating teachers were better prepared to make connections between what students were learning and the experiences they brought to the classroom. During inquiry-based science lessons, teachers and their students engaged in a more collaborative, fluid discourse about science content. Finally, teachers&rsquo; use of culturally responsive classroom management strategies preserved the importance of routines, procedures and high expectations for learners while demonstrating care, respect, and community building in the classroom.&nbsp;</span></p> <p style="line-height: 1.38; margin-top: 0pt; margin-bottom: 0pt;" dir="ltr"><span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;"><br /></span></p> <p style="line-height: 1.38; margin-top: 0pt; margin-bottom: 0pt;" dir="ltr"><span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">Findings from the study found that inquiry-based education facilitated culturally relevant pedagogy in important ways. First, intentionality appears to be an important outcome of the SCI-Bridge model. When done well, hands-on/minds-on learning and collaborative discourse occur organically during inquiry-based instruction. Furthermore, the intentional learning structures teachers put in place influence the teaching and learning that occurs in the classroom. Taken together, these purposeful pedagogical moves (e.g. facilitated discourse and contextual anchoring) in well-managed and responsive classrooms offer dispositional benefits for teachers and students that extend across the curriculum. Given the marginalization of science in the elementary classroom, these findings offer a promising strategy for integrating science across the elementary curriculum and thereby broadening participation in science education at the elementary school level, particularly for urban communities.</span></p> <p style="line-height: 1.38; margin-top: 0pt; margin-bottom: 0pt;" dir="ltr"><span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">&nbsp;</span></p> <p style="line-height: 1.38; margin-top: 0pt; margin-bottom: 0pt;" dir="ltr"><span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">The SCI-Bridge model also influenced the ways that teachers thought about science literacy, the children in their classrooms, and their roles as elementary science educators. Once teachers developed an awareness of culturally relevant pedagogy through modeling such as that provided in the SCI-Bridge program, they could not &ldquo;unsee&rdquo; it.&nbsp; Inquiry-based instruction provides a natural conduit for its application. Integrated, inquiry-based science instruction takes as normative practice student questioning, meaning-making, and action-taking. It redefines urban communities as places of potential as opposed to spaces of deficiency. The SCI-Bridge project remains committed to elevating the presence of science in the urban elementary classroom through integrated inquiry and culturally relevant pedagogy. The model has the means to help schools find ways to bring science into the elementary classroom daily.&nbsp;The power of the integration and inquiry in the model offers promise for STEM schools and programs where content does not stand alone, nor is it limited in the instructional milieu.&nbsp; The SCI-Bridge model can also serve as a bridge for integrating instruction across the STEM disciplines. Further development of the SCI-Bridge model will advance the conversation about broadening the participation of economically, racially, and linguistically diverse student populations in science using integrated inquiry. </span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/01/2023<br>      Modified by: Brian&nbsp;Williams</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[Bridging Science Teaching and Learning in Title 1 Schools: SCI-Bridge was an early-stage design and development project to create a new model integrating best practices in preK-5 science education with culturally relevant pedagogy (CRP) for Title 1 elementary schools (Project # #2010361; 2020-2022).  The SCI-Bridge project sought to address racial and socioeconomic related disparities in science learning at the elementary school level through the development, implementation, and evaluation of a professional development model preparing teachers to effectively utilize science education practices grounded in culturally relevant pedagogy (CRP). Specifically, the SCI-Bridge model prepared teachers to use three instructional tools thought to support their development as culturally relevant educators (facilitated discourse, contextual anchoring, and culturally responsive classroom management) in addition to inquiry-based approaches to science teaching. As a result of their participation in the model, teachers, both inservice and preservice, were better prepared to bridge school-based science content with the culture, prior knowledge and lived experiences of students in their classrooms. The project and its findings advance the field’s understanding of effective teacher preparation and professional development as they related to elementary science education and efforts to address racial and socio-economic disparities in science education (e.g., participation, literacy, performance).   During the grant period, the SCI-Bridge project provided professional development to both inservice and preservice teachers committed to and/or teaching in Title 1 urban schools.  As a result of their participation in the project, educators, emerging and veteran, demonstrated greater confidence and efficacy with the three SCI-Bridge instructional tools; contextual anchoring, facilitated discourse, and culturally responsive classroom management. Participating teachers were better prepared to make connections between what students were learning and the experiences they brought to the classroom. During inquiry-based science lessons, teachers and their students engaged in a more collaborative, fluid discourse about science content. Finally, teachers’ use of culturally responsive classroom management strategies preserved the importance of routines, procedures and high expectations for learners while demonstrating care, respect, and community building in the classroom.    Findings from the study found that inquiry-based education facilitated culturally relevant pedagogy in important ways. First, intentionality appears to be an important outcome of the SCI-Bridge model. When done well, hands-on/minds-on learning and collaborative discourse occur organically during inquiry-based instruction. Furthermore, the intentional learning structures teachers put in place influence the teaching and learning that occurs in the classroom. Taken together, these purposeful pedagogical moves (e.g. facilitated discourse and contextual anchoring) in well-managed and responsive classrooms offer dispositional benefits for teachers and students that extend across the curriculum. Given the marginalization of science in the elementary classroom, these findings offer a promising strategy for integrating science across the elementary curriculum and thereby broadening participation in science education at the elementary school level, particularly for urban communities.   The SCI-Bridge model also influenced the ways that teachers thought about science literacy, the children in their classrooms, and their roles as elementary science educators. Once teachers developed an awareness of culturally relevant pedagogy through modeling such as that provided in the SCI-Bridge program, they could not "unsee" it.  Inquiry-based instruction provides a natural conduit for its application. Integrated, inquiry-based science instruction takes as normative practice student questioning, meaning-making, and action-taking. It redefines urban communities as places of potential as opposed to spaces of deficiency. The SCI-Bridge project remains committed to elevating the presence of science in the urban elementary classroom through integrated inquiry and culturally relevant pedagogy. The model has the means to help schools find ways to bring science into the elementary classroom daily. The power of the integration and inquiry in the model offers promise for STEM schools and programs where content does not stand alone, nor is it limited in the instructional milieu.  The SCI-Bridge model can also serve as a bridge for integrating instruction across the STEM disciplines. Further development of the SCI-Bridge model will advance the conversation about broadening the participation of economically, racially, and linguistically diverse student populations in science using integrated inquiry.        Last Modified: 05/01/2023       Submitted by: Brian Williams]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
