<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[2020 International Conference on Resource Sustainability (icRS 2020); Dublin, Ireland; June 30 - July 2, 2020]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>30000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>30000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Bruce Hamilton</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bhamilto@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032920000</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This travel award will support 20 U.S.-based early-career researchers to attend the 2020 International Conference on Resource Sustainability (icRS 2020) to be held in Dublin, Ireland from June 30th to July 2nd, 2020. The icRS 2020 conference serves as a platform for researchers and practitioners around the world to advance the critical role of resources in the circular economy from the diverse perspectives of underdeveloped, developing and developed economies. The conference will discuss how to achieve urban sustainability through wise resources management policy and practices. Attending the conference will allow the U.S.-based early-career researchers to showcase their research and to develop networks with their peers around the world.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;At the conference, it is expected that a diverse group of 400-500 participants will share their work through both paper and poster presentations, as well as formal and informal discussions. Researchers from groups underrepresented in STEM fields will be given priority in participant selection. High-quality papers from the conference will be recommended to special issues in journals that support the conference. An Editor Panel will be organized at the conference to allow direct interactions between conference attendees and editors of relevant journals on academic publishing. Early-career researchers will benefit from formal interactions with editors at the Editor Panel as well as informal interactions during the conference.  This networking will help their academic careers through a better understanding of editorial criteria in evaluating manuscript submissions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/20/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/20/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2010398</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ming</FirstName>
<LastName>Xu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ming Xu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mingxu@umich.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000573355</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/20/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dongyang</FirstName>
<LastName>Deng</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Dongyang Deng</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ddeng@ncat.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000757012</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/20/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>North Carolina Agricultural &amp; Technical State University</Name>
<CityName>GREENSBORO</CityName>
<ZipCode>274110002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3363347995</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1601 E MARKET ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>SKH5GMBR9GL3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORTH CAROLINA AGRICULTURAL AND TECHNICAL STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[North Carolina A&T State University]]></Name>
<CityName>GREENSBORO</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>274110001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1601 E Market St]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7643</Code>
<Text>EnvS-Environmtl Sustainability</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~30000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><h2>Key Project Objectives</h2> <p>Outline the primary objectives of the project, including supporting early-career researchers' participation in icRS 2021, fostering knowledge exchange, enhancing professional development, and promoting the advancement of resources sustainability and circular economy research.</p> <h2>Achievements and Impacts</h2> <h3>Human Resource Development</h3> <ul> <li><span>Enhanced Skills:</span> Early-career researchers improved their research presentation, communication, and networking skills through participation.</li> <li><span>Professional Growth:</span> Attendees gained confidence, exposure, and networking opportunities, contributing to their growth as emerging experts.</li> </ul> <h3>Knowledge Dissemination</h3> <ul> <li><span>Cutting-edge Insights:</span> Researchers shared the latest research findings and practices related to resources sustainability and circular economy.</li> <li><span>Global Reach:</span> Virtual format allowed for broader accessibility and dissemination of research outcomes to a diverse audience.</li> </ul> <h3>Collaboration and Networking</h3> <ul> <li><span>Interdisciplinary Connections:</span> Attendees networked with peers, experts, and practitioners from various disciplines and backgrounds.</li> <li><span>Potential Collaborations:</span> Opportunities for future collaborative research projects and partnerships were explored.</li> </ul> <h3>Educational Enrichment</h3> <ul> <li><span>Curriculum Enhancement:</span> Early-career researchers integrated fresh insights and case studies into educational programs, enriching student learning experiences.</li> <li><span>Real-world Examples:</span> The conference materials provided concrete real-world examples that educators can incorporate into their teaching materials.</li> </ul> <h3>Enhanced Professional Landscape</h3> <ul> <li><span>Global Visibility:</span> Researchers and institutions gained visibility within the global academic and professional community.</li> <li><span>Innovation and Best Practices:</span> Attendees were exposed to innovative research and best practices, inspiring future research directions.</li> </ul> <h2><span style="color: #f58526; font-size: 12px; font-weight: normal;">Awareness and Advocacy</span></h2> <ul> <li><span>Public Awareness:</span> The conference raised awareness about environmental challenges and sustainable solutions among the general public.</li> <li><span>Policy Influence:</span> Research findings informed policy discussions and advocacy efforts, promoting sustainable resource management.</li> </ul> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/14/2023<br>      Modified by: Dongyang&nbsp;Deng</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[Key Project Objectives  Outline the primary objectives of the project, including supporting early-career researchers' participation in icRS 2021, fostering knowledge exchange, enhancing professional development, and promoting the advancement of resources sustainability and circular economy research. Achievements and Impacts Human Resource Development  Enhanced Skills: Early-career researchers improved their research presentation, communication, and networking skills through participation. Professional Growth: Attendees gained confidence, exposure, and networking opportunities, contributing to their growth as emerging experts.  Knowledge Dissemination  Cutting-edge Insights: Researchers shared the latest research findings and practices related to resources sustainability and circular economy. Global Reach: Virtual format allowed for broader accessibility and dissemination of research outcomes to a diverse audience.  Collaboration and Networking  Interdisciplinary Connections: Attendees networked with peers, experts, and practitioners from various disciplines and backgrounds. Potential Collaborations: Opportunities for future collaborative research projects and partnerships were explored.  Educational Enrichment  Curriculum Enhancement: Early-career researchers integrated fresh insights and case studies into educational programs, enriching student learning experiences. Real-world Examples: The conference materials provided concrete real-world examples that educators can incorporate into their teaching materials.  Enhanced Professional Landscape  Global Visibility: Researchers and institutions gained visibility within the global academic and professional community. Innovation and Best Practices: Attendees were exposed to innovative research and best practices, inspiring future research directions.  Awareness and Advocacy  Public Awareness: The conference raised awareness about environmental challenges and sustainable solutions among the general public. Policy Influence: Research findings informed policy discussions and advocacy efforts, promoting sustainable resource management.           Last Modified: 08/14/2023       Submitted by: Dongyang Deng]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
