<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[NSF Postdoctoral Fellowship in Biology FY 2018]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>138000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>138000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DBI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>John Barthell</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jbarthel@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922618</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This action funds an NSF Postdoctoral Research Fellowship in Biology for FY 2020, Research Using Biological Collections. The fellowship supports research and training of the Fellow that will utilize biological collections in innovative ways. One way to understand species and build evolutionary trees is through DNA analysis, but this method is can be expensive and laborious to scale to hundreds of geographically diverse specimens. Spectral signatures are inexpensive datasets that reveal a tremendous amount of biological information by recording the interactions of visual and infrared light with leaf tissues. Just like DNA sequence analysis, spectral signatures can inform leaf physiology, species boundaries, and evolutionary relationships. This project will provide a novel approach and primary case study of the application of spectral signatures to museum collections. It will teach undergraduate students from diverse backgrounds (especially first-generation academics) in the Chicago area to scan leaves in the Field Museum herbarium and then the Fellow will use the scans for species identification, taxonomy, and evolutionary analysis. The results will help speed up our understanding of biological diversity by coupling a powerful new technology with the wealth of biological specimens sitting in museum collections.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Specifically, this project will generate new genomic data and spectral signatures (400-2,500 nm) from herbarium and archaeological collections to refine hypotheses of the origins and domestication of coca (Erythroxylum spp.), a culturally significant South American crop and the natural source of cocaine. The Fellow’s previous phylogeographic research has shown that the four modern coca varieties originated from at least two independent domestication events from the wild progenitor E. gracilipes. This project will add 198 more samples representing key geographic areas to the exon-capture DNA dataset and conduct statistical phylogeographic analyses. It will also incorporate spectral signatures made from ~1000 herbarium specimens plus 40 archaeological leaf remains up to 8,000 years old for high-resolution phenotypic analyses of modern and ancient coca leaves. The project will also analyze spectral signatures from the other ~260 wild species in the Coca family and compare these to existing phylogenomic hypotheses to research the general utility of spectral signatures for species identification and phylogenetic inference. Thus, the PI will receive training in remote sensing as well as in population genetics; undergraduate students underrepresented in STEM disciplines will, in turn, gain herbarium and laboratory experience in these same areas of inquiry, refining our understanding of the systematics of the Coca family in the Neotropics and stimulating collections-based research using spectral signatures.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/29/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/29/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2010821</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dawson</FirstName>
<LastName>White</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Dawson M White</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<NSF_ID>000808664</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/29/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>White, Dawson M</Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<ZipCode>606052496</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT/>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG/>
<ORG_UEI_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[White, Dawson M]]></Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>606052827</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF/>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1127</Code>
<Text>Evolutionary Processes</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~138000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project generated novel and substantial genomic resources for the coca crops and wild relatives, created new and critical herbarium vouchers and tissues for genomic analysis, and produced novel results on the utility of species spectral signatures from biological collections.</p> <p>To complete research objectives on the origin and evolution of the coca crops, the PI first acquired additional funding, sequenced, assembled, and published the first genomes for the Coca family of plants, comprising the two species of coca crops (Erythroxylum coca and E. novogranatense) plus an additional 56 wild species. All these genomes are now available to the public via GenBank. Next, the PI filled significant geographic sampling gaps via two field work campaigns in South America. Work in Ecuador in 2021 produced a new wild species of Erythroxylum, the first scientific record of indigenous use of the wild ancestor of coca (E. gracilipes), and collections of traditional landraces of both coca species as well as new hybrid varieties from illicit farms. This also facilitated collaborations with three Ecuadorian universities, curation of specimens in five Ecuadorian herbaria, and the samples were used for two Ecuadorian undergraduate thesis projects where the PI has also gained experience as co-advisor. In Colombia in 2022, the PI collected several coca landraces across a geographic and elevational range in the Sierra Nevada de Santa Marta and presented his research on coca domestication and biogeography at a symposium at the Universidad Nacional de Colombia.</p> <p>The field collections were combined with samples from US and international herbaria to complete the genome sequencing objective for the project: DNA was extracted from a curated set of 155 samples representing the coca crop taxa and wild ancestor, E. gracilipes, and 2.8 Tb of whole-genome DNA sequence data have been generated. This comprehensive dataset samples incorporates several undocumented lineages from Colombia, Ecuador, Peru, and Venezuela that are essential and exciting components for understanding coca domestication and evolution. The PI is now combining the sequence data with the published genomes to complete the proposed analyses on the origins and evolution of the coca crops in his next position as Postdoctoral Fellow of the Harvard University Herbaria. Thus, the fellowship project produced large genomic datasets and resources, created many international networks and collaborations, and demonstrated the importance of biological collections for evolutionary biology and biodiversity research. The PI gained experience conducting international field and herbarium work, serving as an advisor on undergraduate theses, and disseminating his research to scientific audiences and university students at the Field Museum, Harvard University, and the Universidad Nacional de Colombia.</p> <p>The project is now conducting the analyses to tell the next chapter of the evolutionary story of coca, a potent symbol of the clash of traditional culture and globalization. Given the dynamic relationship of this plant and humans, from its ancient, complex, and beneficial role among indigenous cultures compared to the destructive role of cocaine and its global market, it is paramount to disseminate the story of coca as a medicine, mild stimulant, and ritualistic device for its equitable valuation.</p> <p>The spectral objectives of the project have produced the first analyses of species spectral signatures from authentic herbarium specimens. The leaves from 412 herbarium specimens of the coca crops and wild relatives can be classified to their appropriate taxon with 60-66% accuracy. Most misclassifications occur among varieties within the same species, revealing a possible limit on the method, but larger sample sizes should improve classification accuracy. Contrary to expectation, leaves mounted on herbarium paper performed better than loose leaves whose spectrum was not contaminated by glue and paper. Taxonomic classification of archaeological coca leaves was &lt;40% accurate across three different coca taxa, showing that degradation and contamination of these tissues is far more severe than in herbarium material and that spectral-based taxonomic classification is not appropriate for archaeological leaves 500-800 years old.</p> <p>These analyses were presented in seminars at the Field Museum, Harvard University, and the ASCEND Winter Symposium 2022, an NSF Biology Integration Institute focused on spectral applications in biodiversity (spectralbiology.org), where the PI is now a member. Results are currently being integrated with other datasets in an article focused the effects of glue and paper, age, and methods for rejuvenating spectra from degraded tissues to provide a utilitarian perspective and standard protocols on spectral analysis of herbarium collections.</p> <p>The PI gained experience in spectral data collection and analysis, and is now heading a Collections Spectrometry Working Group aimed at dissemination of current results and the establishment of standardized protocols and experiments that will define the role of herbarium spectroscopy for high-throughput inventories and monitoring projects of global biodiversity; thus improving our understanding of ecosystem processes in this era of global change.<strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/25/2023<br>      Modified by: Dawson&nbsp;M&nbsp;White</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project generated novel and substantial genomic resources for the coca crops and wild relatives, created new and critical herbarium vouchers and tissues for genomic analysis, and produced novel results on the utility of species spectral signatures from biological collections.  To complete research objectives on the origin and evolution of the coca crops, the PI first acquired additional funding, sequenced, assembled, and published the first genomes for the Coca family of plants, comprising the two species of coca crops (Erythroxylum coca and E. novogranatense) plus an additional 56 wild species. All these genomes are now available to the public via GenBank. Next, the PI filled significant geographic sampling gaps via two field work campaigns in South America. Work in Ecuador in 2021 produced a new wild species of Erythroxylum, the first scientific record of indigenous use of the wild ancestor of coca (E. gracilipes), and collections of traditional landraces of both coca species as well as new hybrid varieties from illicit farms. This also facilitated collaborations with three Ecuadorian universities, curation of specimens in five Ecuadorian herbaria, and the samples were used for two Ecuadorian undergraduate thesis projects where the PI has also gained experience as co-advisor. In Colombia in 2022, the PI collected several coca landraces across a geographic and elevational range in the Sierra Nevada de Santa Marta and presented his research on coca domestication and biogeography at a symposium at the Universidad Nacional de Colombia.  The field collections were combined with samples from US and international herbaria to complete the genome sequencing objective for the project: DNA was extracted from a curated set of 155 samples representing the coca crop taxa and wild ancestor, E. gracilipes, and 2.8 Tb of whole-genome DNA sequence data have been generated. This comprehensive dataset samples incorporates several undocumented lineages from Colombia, Ecuador, Peru, and Venezuela that are essential and exciting components for understanding coca domestication and evolution. The PI is now combining the sequence data with the published genomes to complete the proposed analyses on the origins and evolution of the coca crops in his next position as Postdoctoral Fellow of the Harvard University Herbaria. Thus, the fellowship project produced large genomic datasets and resources, created many international networks and collaborations, and demonstrated the importance of biological collections for evolutionary biology and biodiversity research. The PI gained experience conducting international field and herbarium work, serving as an advisor on undergraduate theses, and disseminating his research to scientific audiences and university students at the Field Museum, Harvard University, and the Universidad Nacional de Colombia.  The project is now conducting the analyses to tell the next chapter of the evolutionary story of coca, a potent symbol of the clash of traditional culture and globalization. Given the dynamic relationship of this plant and humans, from its ancient, complex, and beneficial role among indigenous cultures compared to the destructive role of cocaine and its global market, it is paramount to disseminate the story of coca as a medicine, mild stimulant, and ritualistic device for its equitable valuation.  The spectral objectives of the project have produced the first analyses of species spectral signatures from authentic herbarium specimens. The leaves from 412 herbarium specimens of the coca crops and wild relatives can be classified to their appropriate taxon with 60-66% accuracy. Most misclassifications occur among varieties within the same species, revealing a possible limit on the method, but larger sample sizes should improve classification accuracy. Contrary to expectation, leaves mounted on herbarium paper performed better than loose leaves whose spectrum was not contaminated by glue and paper. Taxonomic classification of archaeological coca leaves was &lt;40% accurate across three different coca taxa, showing that degradation and contamination of these tissues is far more severe than in herbarium material and that spectral-based taxonomic classification is not appropriate for archaeological leaves 500-800 years old.  These analyses were presented in seminars at the Field Museum, Harvard University, and the ASCEND Winter Symposium 2022, an NSF Biology Integration Institute focused on spectral applications in biodiversity (spectralbiology.org), where the PI is now a member. Results are currently being integrated with other datasets in an article focused the effects of glue and paper, age, and methods for rejuvenating spectra from degraded tissues to provide a utilitarian perspective and standard protocols on spectral analysis of herbarium collections.  The PI gained experience in spectral data collection and analysis, and is now heading a Collections Spectrometry Working Group aimed at dissemination of current results and the establishment of standardized protocols and experiments that will define the role of herbarium spectroscopy for high-throughput inventories and monitoring projects of global biodiversity; thus improving our understanding of ecosystem processes in this era of global change.           Last Modified: 04/25/2023       Submitted by: Dawson M White]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
