<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[I-Corps: A novel vaginal dynamometer for evaluating pelvic floor health in  women]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ruth Shuman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rshuman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922160</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this I-Corps project is the development of a new device to take accurate measures of pelvic floor strength to provide with physicians with a reliable and repeatable assessment of pelvic floor health. One in every four women in the US will experience a pelvic floor disorder in their lifetime. Physicians still rely on digital palpation, a finger-squeeze test, to assess the pelvic floor, which has marginal clinical reliability. This device can detect small changes in pelvic floor strength and help physicians diagnose a pelvic floor disorder before symptoms arise.  This project will not only focus on the development of this diagnostic device, but also begin assessing the need and commercial opportunity for other products focused on pelvic floor care and rehabilitation. Pelvic health is a largely underserved market and has only recently gained attention through the commercialization of several mobile health training aids.   &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project is to explore the development of a vaginal dynamometer, based on a reusable speculum coupled with a removable sensor to assess pelvic floor strength. The results from this device showed that a removable sensor design provides accurate results while reducing the cost-per-use to an acceptable level for routine use. The major limiting factor of current pelvic floor assessment technologies is the cost of use. Perineometers, ultrasound, and MRI are prohibitively costly for routine use in regular gynecologic checkups. The removable sensor design allows the patient-contacting portion of the device to undergo standard reprocessing protocols, such as autoclave, while the fragile sensor and electronics are removed and reused. We believe that such a design would become accessible for routine gynecologic use and could become a vital sign of pelvic health, much like blood pressure is for cardiovascular health.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/22/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/22/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2010176</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
<LastName>Hitchcock</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Robert Hitchcock</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[r.hitchcock@utah.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000504434</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/22/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Utah</Name>
<CityName>SALT LAKE CITY</CityName>
<ZipCode>841129049</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8015816903</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>201 PRESIDENTS CIR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Utah</StateName>
<StateCode>UT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>UT01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>LL8GLEVH6MG3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF UTAH</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Utah]]></Name>
<CityName>Salt Lake City</CityName>
<StateCode>UT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>841125001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[36 South Wasatch Dr.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Utah</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>UT01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The major goal of this project was to evaluate the commercial viability of an intra-vaginal dynamometer for use in assessing pelvic floor strength in women. Commercial viability were evaluated by testing business model assumptions through customer discovery interviews.&nbsp;Interview responses indicated that stationary measurement of pelvic floor strength would not significantly alter clinical practice, which led to a pivot in the device design and intended market.&nbsp;<span class="A5"><span lang="EN-US">A different potential device design and target market was identified through customer discovery interviews. The new product is a wearable dual-sensor intra-vaginal device designed to support pelvic rehabilitation in physical therapy clinics.&nbsp;<span lang="EN-US">Measurement of the pelvic floor during activities, such as running, allows physical therapists to evaluate patients when their pelvic symptoms are most bothersome, a capability they currently do not have. Through this dynamic evaluation, Physical therapists can reduce their time diagnosis patients and focus on treatment and reinforcement of proper pelvic contraction techniques.&nbsp;</span></span></span>Assessment of pelvic muscles during activities could also aid pelvic floor researchers in determining pathophysiologic pathways of pelvic organ prolapse or stress urinary incontinence. Results and finding from other studies could then be rapidly translated into clinical practice, as the same device used in research studies would be available for patients and their clinicians.&nbsp;The new device design and intended market business model were partially validated.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/20/2022<br>      Modified by: Robert&nbsp;Hitchcock</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The major goal of this project was to evaluate the commercial viability of an intra-vaginal dynamometer for use in assessing pelvic floor strength in women. Commercial viability were evaluated by testing business model assumptions through customer discovery interviews. Interview responses indicated that stationary measurement of pelvic floor strength would not significantly alter clinical practice, which led to a pivot in the device design and intended market. A different potential device design and target market was identified through customer discovery interviews. The new product is a wearable dual-sensor intra-vaginal device designed to support pelvic rehabilitation in physical therapy clinics. Measurement of the pelvic floor during activities, such as running, allows physical therapists to evaluate patients when their pelvic symptoms are most bothersome, a capability they currently do not have. Through this dynamic evaluation, Physical therapists can reduce their time diagnosis patients and focus on treatment and reinforcement of proper pelvic contraction techniques. Assessment of pelvic muscles during activities could also aid pelvic floor researchers in determining pathophysiologic pathways of pelvic organ prolapse or stress urinary incontinence. Results and finding from other studies could then be rapidly translated into clinical practice, as the same device used in research studies would be available for patients and their clinicians. The new device design and intended market business model were partially validated.          Last Modified: 04/20/2022       Submitted by: Robert Hitchcock]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
