<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[NSF Postdoctoral Fellowship in Biology FY 2020: Biotic drivers of local adaptation:  Integrating the evolutionary consequences of plant-soil feedbacks into sagebrush]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>138000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>138000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DBI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Daniel Marenda</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dmarenda@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922157</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This action funds an NSF Postdoctoral Research Fellowship in Biology for FY 2020, Integrative Research Investigating the Rules of Life Governing Interactions Between Genomes, Environment and Phenotypes. The fellowship supports research and training of the fellow that will contribute to the area of Rules of Life in innovative ways. When a population is better suited to its native environment than populations from other areas are, this is called local adaptation. Changes such as climate and interaction with other species can change local adaptation and affect species survival. This research will investigate the extent to which species interactions shape local adaptation, focusing on big sagebrush (Artemisia tridentata) populations and the microbial communities that live in the soil where the shrub grows. Big sagebrush is threatened, and replanting efforts are being made across a large region of the western US. However, these restoration efforts often fail. This project will be important for understanding sagebrush ecology and promoting conservation efforts. Results will be communicated with stakeholders through partnerships with the US Geological Survey, as well as through a graphic novel developed by the fellow. This work will engage diverse undergraduate researchers in a training program at Boise State University, while furthering the training of the fellow in mathematical modeling and microbial ecology.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Species interactions can generate selection, and inclusion of biotic selective agents may alter conclusions about a population’s vulnerability drawn from examining local adaptation based on climate alone. To quantify the extent to which sagebrush-soil microbe interactions shape local adaptation, the fellow will construct a common garden experiment that translocates plant populations and soil across a climatic gradient, sequence microbial communities, and develop an integral projection model that leverages short- and long-term data to assess the influence of biotic interactions on population growth. This research will assess the following hypotheses: 1) Biotic interactions contribute to local adaptation in sagebrush populations, but fitness impacts vary with environment, population origin, and demographic stage; 2) Inclusion of biotic interactions alters predictions of populations’ growth and sensitivity to translocation, compared to those based on abiotic factors alone. This work has the potential to improve the understanding of higher-order patterns of phenotypic plasticity and population persistence in rapidly changing environments. To broaden the impact of the work, the fellow will engage undergraduates in the research.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/30/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/30/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2010868</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Allison</FirstName>
<LastName>Simler-Williamson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Allison B Simler-Williamson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<NSF_ID>000705969</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/30/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Allison Simler-Williamson</Name>
<CityName>Boise</CityName>
<ZipCode>837127320</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Idaho</StateName>
<StateCode>ID</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>ID02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Boise State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Boise</CityName>
<StateCode>ID</StateCode>
<ZipCode>837251135</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Idaho</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>ID02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1127</Code>
<Text>Evolutionary Processes</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7275</Code>
<Text>Cross-BIO Activities</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>068Z</Code>
<Text>URoL-Understanding Rules of Life</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~138000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Intellectual Merit</span></strong></p> <p>Local adaptation describes the process by which populations evolve to become better suited to their "home" conditions, compared to other populations from more distant environments. Patterns of local adaptation are fundamental to predicting where populations will disappear from ecosystems as climate change rapidly shifts the environmental conditions that organisms evolved with, as well how we select the seeds and seedlings to use in conservation and restoration activities. However, most of the study of local adaptation focuses on climate-related factors, even though species interactions, such as between organisms and their pathogens, their predators, and their competitors, can also create pressures that are unique to a particular population?s home region, resulting in "biotic" adaptation.</p> <p>Rapidly declining big sagebrush (<em>Artemisia tridentata) </em>populations are threatened by climate change, altered wildfires, and invasions by nonnative grasses, which has prompted the widespread movement of sagebrush seeds into sites requiring restoration. Though seeds are often selected based on climate-related adaptation, seeding success remains difficult to predict from climatic conditions alone. &nbsp;In this research, we developed a combination of field, greenhouse, and lab experiments to examine whether this declining, widely translocated plant exhibits patterns of local adaptation associated with its interactions with soil bacteria and fungi. Then, we assessed how the inclusion of interactions with soil bacteria and fungi impacted predictions of whether big sagebrush populations were likely to establish during restoration actions, compared to models that solely relied on climate and soil characteristics. We additionally examined whether the density of sagebrush populations influenced the strength of the impacts of bacteria and fungi (as an example of an "ecological-evolutionary feedback").</p> <p><br />We found that the impacts of soil fungi and bacteria on sagebrush seedlings depended upon how dissimilar the planting environment was to a given seed's home environment.&nbsp; "Local" sagebrush populations experienced reduced impacts from soil pathogens on the survival of seeds and the youngest seedlings, and more positive impacts from microbes as the seedlings, compared to populations planted with the most "environmentally distant" fungi and bacteria. Population models predicted that the number of seedlings surviving to the end of the first year increased when seedlings that were planted into their local soil microbes relative to more foreign microbial communities, indicating possible local adaptation to these species interactions. Further, population establishment was most sensitive to microbial impacts on seeds and young seedlings, shortly after germination. By quantifying the contributions of microbial communities to the establishment of translocated plant populations, this work advances our understanding of how species interactions shape not only population persistence but also the outcomes of restoration actions necessitated by global change.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Broader Impacts</span></strong></p> <p>We found that soil bacteria and fungi have population-specific impacts on seeds and seedlings of this ecologically important species, which has significant implications for the selection of seeds in sagebrush restoration and conservation efforts, especially considering the variability observed in past management outcomes. We have communicated the results of this work through collaborations with the U.S. Geological Survey and through groups dedicated to the management and restoration of drylands and rangelands in the western United States. We also developed a series of digital illustrations inspired by the results of this research, which merges artistic and scientific communication approaches to appeal to broad audiences in Idaho.</p> <p>This work supported the mentorship of five early career women in science, including undergraduates, graduate students, and postdoctoral researchers. This project provided hands-on research opportunities for undergraduate researchers via "Vertically Integrated" projects, which allow for students to collaborate with diverse teams of researchers across career stages.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/09/2023<br>      Modified by: Allison&nbsp;B&nbsp;Simler-Williamson</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2010868/2010868_10681727_1683679702188_bioticadaptation--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2010868/2010868_10681727_1683679702188_bioticadaptation--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Local adaptation observed in big sagebrush, associated with soil fungi and bacteria"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2010868/2010868_10681727_1683679702188_bioticadaptation--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Local adaptation observed in big sagebrush, associated with soil fungi and bacteria"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">This illustration was created by postdoctoral fellow Allison Simler-Williamson as part of a series of artworks to creatively communicate the results of this research to broad audiences.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Allison Simler-Williamson</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Allison&nbsp;B&nbsp;Simler-Williamson</div> <div class="imageTitle">Local adaptation observed in big sagebrush, associated with soil fungi and bacteria</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Intellectual Merit  Local adaptation describes the process by which populations evolve to become better suited to their "home" conditions, compared to other populations from more distant environments. Patterns of local adaptation are fundamental to predicting where populations will disappear from ecosystems as climate change rapidly shifts the environmental conditions that organisms evolved with, as well how we select the seeds and seedlings to use in conservation and restoration activities. However, most of the study of local adaptation focuses on climate-related factors, even though species interactions, such as between organisms and their pathogens, their predators, and their competitors, can also create pressures that are unique to a particular population?s home region, resulting in "biotic" adaptation.  Rapidly declining big sagebrush (Artemisia tridentata) populations are threatened by climate change, altered wildfires, and invasions by nonnative grasses, which has prompted the widespread movement of sagebrush seeds into sites requiring restoration. Though seeds are often selected based on climate-related adaptation, seeding success remains difficult to predict from climatic conditions alone.  In this research, we developed a combination of field, greenhouse, and lab experiments to examine whether this declining, widely translocated plant exhibits patterns of local adaptation associated with its interactions with soil bacteria and fungi. Then, we assessed how the inclusion of interactions with soil bacteria and fungi impacted predictions of whether big sagebrush populations were likely to establish during restoration actions, compared to models that solely relied on climate and soil characteristics. We additionally examined whether the density of sagebrush populations influenced the strength of the impacts of bacteria and fungi (as an example of an "ecological-evolutionary feedback").   We found that the impacts of soil fungi and bacteria on sagebrush seedlings depended upon how dissimilar the planting environment was to a given seed's home environment.  "Local" sagebrush populations experienced reduced impacts from soil pathogens on the survival of seeds and the youngest seedlings, and more positive impacts from microbes as the seedlings, compared to populations planted with the most "environmentally distant" fungi and bacteria. Population models predicted that the number of seedlings surviving to the end of the first year increased when seedlings that were planted into their local soil microbes relative to more foreign microbial communities, indicating possible local adaptation to these species interactions. Further, population establishment was most sensitive to microbial impacts on seeds and young seedlings, shortly after germination. By quantifying the contributions of microbial communities to the establishment of translocated plant populations, this work advances our understanding of how species interactions shape not only population persistence but also the outcomes of restoration actions necessitated by global change.     Broader Impacts  We found that soil bacteria and fungi have population-specific impacts on seeds and seedlings of this ecologically important species, which has significant implications for the selection of seeds in sagebrush restoration and conservation efforts, especially considering the variability observed in past management outcomes. We have communicated the results of this work through collaborations with the U.S. Geological Survey and through groups dedicated to the management and restoration of drylands and rangelands in the western United States. We also developed a series of digital illustrations inspired by the results of this research, which merges artistic and scientific communication approaches to appeal to broad audiences in Idaho.  This work supported the mentorship of five early career women in science, including undergraduates, graduate students, and postdoctoral researchers. This project provided hands-on research opportunities for undergraduate researchers via "Vertically Integrated" projects, which allow for students to collaborate with diverse teams of researchers across career stages.             Last Modified: 05/09/2023       Submitted by: Allison B Simler-Williamson]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
