<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[NSF Postdoctoral Fellowship in Biology FY 2020]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>138000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>207000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DBI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>John Barthell</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jbarthel@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922618</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This action funds an NSF Postdoctoral Research Fellowship in Biology for FY 2020, Integrative Research Investigating the Rules of Life Governing Interactions Between Genomes, Environment and Phenotypes. The fellowship supports research and training of the Fellow that will contribute to the area of Rules of Life in innovative ways. Animals perceive the world through dedicated sensory systems such as vision, hearing, taste, and smell. In many animals, these systems have become specialized to detect and filter the most ecologically relevant signals from the environment. Animals that are sensory specialists provide excellent research models for understanding the core molecular and cellular processes underlying sensory stimulus detection, transduction, and processing by the nervous system, as sensory receptors and downstream cellular pathways are often enhanced to facilitate an organism’s unique lifestyle and ecological niche. Furthermore, because sensory systems transduce similar environmental stimuli such as light, chemicals, and mechanical force into cellular signals, comparative investigations across diverse animals can provide key insight into the basic principles by which molecular and cellular processes facilitate sensory transduction and adaptation.&lt;br/&gt;   &lt;br/&gt;The studies proposed here will leverage the unique sensory biology of marine molluscs, including cephalopods (octopus, squid, cuttlefish) and sacoglossan sea slugs, to identify cellular mechanisms underlying sensory stimulus detection and transduction. Specifically, comparative transcriptomics and ribosomal profiling will be used to identify gene expression profiles from morphologically- and physiologically-distinct sensory cells in the specialized arms and sucker cups of the octopus, as well as from various other molluscan species. This multi-species approach will facilitate the identification of conserved and divergent features underlying sensory transduction both within molluscs and among animals more broadly. Functional properties of putative sensory receptor proteins will be characterized using single-cell electrophysiological recordings in both acutely dissociated native cells and heterologous expression systems including Xenopus oocytes and HEK293 cells. Finally, immunohistochemical staining, ex vivo nerve recordings, and quantitative behavioral analyses will be employed to understand how sensory information is integrated by the nervous system to generate appropriate behavioral responses. This research will provide a crucial training opportunity for the Fellow to develop experimental skills in gene expression, cell physiology, and behavioral analyses. Additionally, the charismatic nature of the study organisms will attract public interest for educational outreach activities and will facilitate research and mentorship opportunities for undergraduate and graduate students of diverse and underrepresented groups. Outreach activities will occur at Boston-based institutions like the New England Aquarium and Harvard Museum of Natural History.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/26/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/30/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2010971</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Patric</FirstName>
<LastName>Vaelli</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Patric Vaelli</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<NSF_ID>000815587</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/26/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Vaelli, Patric</Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<ZipCode>02138</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Harvard University]]></Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021382020</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7275</Code>
<Text>Cross-BIO Activities</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8049</Code>
<Text>Biology Postdoctoral Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>068Z</Code>
<Text>URoL-Understanding Rules of Life</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>097Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Impacts on Existing Activities</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>102Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-Disproportionate Impcts Inst-Indiv</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>1V21</Code>
<Name>R&amp;RA ARP Act DEFC V</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>010V2122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[R&RA ARP Act DEFC V]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~138000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~69000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>In the proposed research, the PI aimed to describe the molecular, cellular, and physiological processes underlying chemical sensation in the arms of the California two-spot octopus (<em>Octopus bimaculoides</em>). The objective of this research was to identify the properties underlying a poorly described sensory system: the chemical-sensitive taste cells present in octopus sucker cups. To this end, the PI first generated gene transcription data from the sucker cups of octopus, as well as three other cephalopod species (bobtail squid, longfin squid, cuttlefish). This comparative genetic approach across cephalopods that possess or lack taste cells facilitated the identification of an octopus-specific family of cys-loop receptor genes, whose nearest human ancestor is the nicotinic acetylcholine receptor. The cys-loop receptor family broadly contains many familiar receptors, including serotonin, GABA, glycine, and acetylcholine receptors, and the odorant binding cys-loop receptors in octopus may represent a new founding member of the gene family. This work has been further advanced to understand the structural features of the octopus? receptor and how it compares to its human relative, allowing further insight into the structural properties of our own human receptors.</p> <p>Further, the PI investigated the chemical sensitivity of octopus receptor genes by electrophysiological analysis of individual octopus receptors expressed in cell culture. This method allowed screening of dozens of chemicals on octopus receptors without sacrificing animals or using animal tissues; we simply express the octopus receptor gene in a controlled cell culture system for chemical screening. Our initial surveys identified an octopus receptor tuned for sticky, hydrophobic terpene molecules, and another receptor that responded to hydrophilic bitter molecules. In the final experiments, we found that individual chemicals identified in our screen could elicit responses in the animal nervous system, as determined through electrophysiological recordings in the octopus arm nerve. We also found that the animals discriminate between some of these molecules behaviorally, choosing to avoid regions of their aquarium that had been laced with experimental chemicals. Taken together, these results provide a foundation for exploring the unique chemical taste sensation of aquatic animals such as the octopus, who, separate from terrestrial animals in the air, live in a suspended aqueous medium surrounded by chemical information. Furthermore, comparative biology with anciently diverged animals such as the octopus provide significant insight into the unique and conserved features of the molecular and physiological processes underlying taste and other sensations in humans.</p> <p>The results of this work will be disseminated as two publications (<em>in preparation</em>), from which scholars can access our transcriptomic data, receptor sequences, and methodologies. Because of the broad laboratory training accomplished during the fellowship period, the PI has received and accepted a new position as Research Scientist III in the Harvard Medical School working on mammalian pain sensation and the development of new non-opioid drugs for chronic pain.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/29/2022<br>      Modified by: Patric&nbsp;Vaelli</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ In the proposed research, the PI aimed to describe the molecular, cellular, and physiological processes underlying chemical sensation in the arms of the California two-spot octopus (Octopus bimaculoides). The objective of this research was to identify the properties underlying a poorly described sensory system: the chemical-sensitive taste cells present in octopus sucker cups. To this end, the PI first generated gene transcription data from the sucker cups of octopus, as well as three other cephalopod species (bobtail squid, longfin squid, cuttlefish). This comparative genetic approach across cephalopods that possess or lack taste cells facilitated the identification of an octopus-specific family of cys-loop receptor genes, whose nearest human ancestor is the nicotinic acetylcholine receptor. The cys-loop receptor family broadly contains many familiar receptors, including serotonin, GABA, glycine, and acetylcholine receptors, and the odorant binding cys-loop receptors in octopus may represent a new founding member of the gene family. This work has been further advanced to understand the structural features of the octopus? receptor and how it compares to its human relative, allowing further insight into the structural properties of our own human receptors.  Further, the PI investigated the chemical sensitivity of octopus receptor genes by electrophysiological analysis of individual octopus receptors expressed in cell culture. This method allowed screening of dozens of chemicals on octopus receptors without sacrificing animals or using animal tissues; we simply express the octopus receptor gene in a controlled cell culture system for chemical screening. Our initial surveys identified an octopus receptor tuned for sticky, hydrophobic terpene molecules, and another receptor that responded to hydrophilic bitter molecules. In the final experiments, we found that individual chemicals identified in our screen could elicit responses in the animal nervous system, as determined through electrophysiological recordings in the octopus arm nerve. We also found that the animals discriminate between some of these molecules behaviorally, choosing to avoid regions of their aquarium that had been laced with experimental chemicals. Taken together, these results provide a foundation for exploring the unique chemical taste sensation of aquatic animals such as the octopus, who, separate from terrestrial animals in the air, live in a suspended aqueous medium surrounded by chemical information. Furthermore, comparative biology with anciently diverged animals such as the octopus provide significant insight into the unique and conserved features of the molecular and physiological processes underlying taste and other sensations in humans.  The results of this work will be disseminated as two publications (in preparation), from which scholars can access our transcriptomic data, receptor sequences, and methodologies. Because of the broad laboratory training accomplished during the fellowship period, the PI has received and accepted a new position as Research Scientist III in the Harvard Medical School working on mammalian pain sensation and the development of new non-opioid drugs for chronic pain.       Last Modified: 08/29/2022       Submitted by: Patric Vaelli]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
