<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Workshop on The State of High School Cybersecurity Education for Preparing a Cybersecurity Workforce]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>100000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>100000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DRL</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Wu He</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>wuhe@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032920000</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The cybersecurity workforce shortage is a critical, immediate, and growing problem in the United States. Increasing the number of youth pursuing cybersecurity degrees and careers will require a multilayered strategy.  Some of the steps needed to achieve this goal include:  making cybersecurity teaching and learning in secondary schools rigorous, engaging and relevant; providing opportunities for youth to learn about cybersecurity as a field of study and career options, and smoothing the transition to postsecondary success by including additional studies or workforce placement.  Some states have begun integrating cybersecurity content into their K-12 computer science and/or Career Technical Education (CTE) standards and are offering curriculum in cybersecurity; however, the breadth, depth, and implementation varies from one state to another. In many states, integrating cybersecurity into the K-12 curriculum still emphasizes students’ online safety, e.g. secure passwords, cyberbullying and identity protection. This project will implement a workshop to analyze the current state of cybersecurity education in high schools. The results will advance knowledge and understanding about the state of K-12 cybersecurity education in the United States at a crucial time. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project aims to implement a workshop to analyze the state of the art of cybersecurity education in the U.S. high schools.  Approximately 30 participants (educators, policymakers, and industry leaders) from six states — which have made good progress in implementing cybersecurity education standards and creating career pathways in high schools — will attend the workshop and produce a report on the state of high school cybersecurity education for preparing a cybersecurity workforce. The goals of the workshop are to: 1) understand the prospective effectiveness of these standards, and their consequent curricula and pathways, for generating meaningful cybersecurity learning and meeting workforce demands; 2) identify factors that enable or thwart the implementation of cybersecurity standards across school districts with a specific focus on factors involving different socioeconomic and racial/ethnic profiles; 3) Understand the developmental support needed to effectively teach cybersecurity in high schools; and 4) summarize challenges and provide recommendations for advancing cybersecurity in high school education in the context of addressing the cybersecurity workforce shortage. The workshop will produce timely and useful information about the efficacy of various educational standards to fill the cybersecurity workforce gap and provide a blueprint for states that are looking for creating their own cybersecurity strands and pathways.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is partially supported by NSF's Discovery Research PreK-12 (DRK-12) program, in the Directorate for Education &amp; Human Resources. DRK-12 seeks to significantly enhance the learning and teaching of science, technology, engineering and mathematics (STEM) by preK-12 students and teachers through research and development of innovative resources, models and tools. Projects in the DRK-12 program build on fundamental research in STEM education and prior research and development efforts that provide theoretical and empirical justification for proposed projects.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/27/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/27/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2010614</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gaby</FirstName>
<LastName>Dagher</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gaby Dagher</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[gabydagher@boisestate.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000719406</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/27/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jidong</FirstName>
<LastName>Xiao</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jidong Xiao</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jidongxiao@boisestate.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000720233</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/27/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Boise State University</Name>
<CityName>BOISE</CityName>
<ZipCode>837250001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2084261574</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1910 UNIVERSITY DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Idaho</StateName>
<StateCode>ID</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>ID02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>HYWTVM5HNFM3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>BOISE STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>HYWTVM5HNFM3</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Boise State University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>ID</StateCode>
<ZipCode>837251135</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Idaho</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>ID02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>152Y</Code>
<Text>Accelerating Discovery in Ed</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7645</Code>
<Text>Discovery Research K-12</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0420</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~100000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The State of High School Cybersecurity Education for Preparing a Cybersecurity Workforce Workshop brought together representatives &ndash; educators, practitioners, and policymakers &ndash; from six states (Colorado, Florida, New York, Maryland, Texas, Virginia) to solicit information from different perspectives about their experience in designing and implementing their strands and pathways.</p> <p>Given that the workshop took place during the global COVID-19 pandemic, we could not meet face-to-face. We carefully designed the workshop to allow for maximum voice from all participants, allow for all participants to hear diverse ideas, and also allow for whole group discussions in a productive virtual format. We carefully structured and scaffolded small group discussions to ensure that norms around sharing talk time were easily facilitated and that discussions were efficient and productive.</p> <p>Prior to the workshop, each of the six states were provided with the same set of questions to answer in a report format. PI, Co-PIs, and one organizing committee (OC) representative from each state met at least weekly for about four months prior to the workshop. OCs recruited and facilitated state working groups that collaborated to co-write the state report. Each state shared an overall report in our spring 2021 virtual workshop and then worked in multi-state, multi-role small groups to share findings on specific sections of the report. State reports, workshop slideshows, and all small group discussion notes were collected. All state reports were analyzed and then shared with the PI and OC teams for feedback.</p> <p>The collected information was then analyzed and described in a nationwide final report. The findings are presented as state-by-state findings to ensure a rich description of the status of cybersecurity education for each state. Findings from each state describe cybersecurity education standards and pathways, responses to workforce needs, teacher professional development opportunities and needs, and cybersecurity education resources. In addition, we share a feature story that describes a unique element of cybersecurity education from each state.</p> <p>The nationwide report serves as a blueprint for states with different levels of advancements in cybersecurity interested in creating their own cybersecurity strands and pathways. The workshop utilized the National Cybersecurity Workforce Framework, as well as the list of competencies of expertise for cybersecurity jobs, both of which are provided by the National Institute for Cybersecurity Careers and Studies (NICCS), to evaluate the effectiveness of existing standards and pathways. The workshop advances knowledge about the state of K-12 cybersecurity education in the United States at a crucial time.&nbsp; Given the dire labor shortages in cybersecurity, this workshop produced timely and useful information about the efficacy of various educational standards to fill the cybersecurity workforce gap.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/01/2022<br>      Modified by: Gaby&nbsp;Dagher</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2010614/2010614_10689791_1641082925612_2022_01_01_17_17_38_Cybersecurity_Workshop_GroupShot--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2010614/2010614_10689791_1641082925612_2022_01_01_17_17_38_Cybersecurity_Workshop_GroupShot--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Workshop Group Shot"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2010614/2010614_10689791_1641082925612_2022_01_01_17_17_38_Cybersecurity_Workshop_GroupShot--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Workshop Group Shot"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">-</div> <div class="imageCredit">-</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Gaby&nbsp;Dagher</div> <div class="imageTitle">Workshop Group Shot</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The State of High School Cybersecurity Education for Preparing a Cybersecurity Workforce Workshop brought together representatives &ndash; educators, practitioners, and policymakers &ndash; from six states (Colorado, Florida, New York, Maryland, Texas, Virginia) to solicit information from different perspectives about their experience in designing and implementing their strands and pathways.  Given that the workshop took place during the global COVID-19 pandemic, we could not meet face-to-face. We carefully designed the workshop to allow for maximum voice from all participants, allow for all participants to hear diverse ideas, and also allow for whole group discussions in a productive virtual format. We carefully structured and scaffolded small group discussions to ensure that norms around sharing talk time were easily facilitated and that discussions were efficient and productive.  Prior to the workshop, each of the six states were provided with the same set of questions to answer in a report format. PI, Co-PIs, and one organizing committee (OC) representative from each state met at least weekly for about four months prior to the workshop. OCs recruited and facilitated state working groups that collaborated to co-write the state report. Each state shared an overall report in our spring 2021 virtual workshop and then worked in multi-state, multi-role small groups to share findings on specific sections of the report. State reports, workshop slideshows, and all small group discussion notes were collected. All state reports were analyzed and then shared with the PI and OC teams for feedback.  The collected information was then analyzed and described in a nationwide final report. The findings are presented as state-by-state findings to ensure a rich description of the status of cybersecurity education for each state. Findings from each state describe cybersecurity education standards and pathways, responses to workforce needs, teacher professional development opportunities and needs, and cybersecurity education resources. In addition, we share a feature story that describes a unique element of cybersecurity education from each state.  The nationwide report serves as a blueprint for states with different levels of advancements in cybersecurity interested in creating their own cybersecurity strands and pathways. The workshop utilized the National Cybersecurity Workforce Framework, as well as the list of competencies of expertise for cybersecurity jobs, both of which are provided by the National Institute for Cybersecurity Careers and Studies (NICCS), to evaluate the effectiveness of existing standards and pathways. The workshop advances knowledge about the state of K-12 cybersecurity education in the United States at a crucial time.  Given the dire labor shortages in cybersecurity, this workshop produced timely and useful information about the efficacy of various educational standards to fill the cybersecurity workforce gap.          Last Modified: 01/01/2022       Submitted by: Gaby Dagher]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
