<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[6th International Conference of Quantitative Genetics (ICQG6)]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>47280.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>47280</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08090300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IOS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Theodore Morgan</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tmorgan@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927868</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The Sixth International Conference of Quantitative Genetics (ICQG6) will be held in Brisbane, Australia, June 2021. Quantitative genetics is concerned with traits for which variation between individuals is controlled in part by DNA differences between individuals. These traits include those that are affected by environmental factors and change during evolution and that affect human health or economic traits in domesticated plants and animals. The hereditary component for these traits is often complex and requires sophisticated mathematical and statistical analyses to relate observed trait values to genetic profiles. Quantitative geneticists are now addressing very large genetic datasets made possible by advances in molecular biology, with human genetic studies now capable of revealing information for a billion separate genetic elements, and the scale of data is also large for plants and animals. The ICQG6 will bring over 500 scientists and students together to survey the current state of the field and to consider future activities.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Sixth International Conference of Quantitative Genetics (ICQG6) to be held in Brisbane, Australia, June 2021. Important health problems will are addressed in this application by an emphasis on the genetic determinants of human disease. Studies of disease rest heavily on sound statistical methodology. Many new statistical techniques that address complex traits and the integration of genotype, gene expression and clinical trait data will be covered in the Conference. Advances in human health often follow the studies made on model organisms to be described at the ICQG6. Use of model organisms requires an understanding of the shared evolutionary history of man and other organisms, and some speakers will address the evolution of quantitative traits. Quantitative genetic methodology, especially techniques for mapping quantitative trait loci (QTL), is often developed for plant and animal populations where controlled crosses can be made. Advances in plant and animal breeding also lead to improved human health by increasing the quality and quantity of food. The technological advances of the last decade have meant that quantitative genetic studies are being conducted at an unprecedented scale. Moreover, there are also studies on the quantitative genetics of omics traits, including at the single-cell level. Many conference attendees develop new methods that are applicable across a range of species and traits. In particular, progress in human genetics has been made with methodology developed in livestock genetics. Dialog between methodologists across species has been found to provide new ideas, new directions and new ways of thinking.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/21/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/21/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2010561</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Bruce</FirstName>
<LastName>Weir</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Bruce S Weir</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[bsweir@u.washington.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000251405</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/21/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Washington</Name>
<CityName>SEATTLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>981951016</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2065434043</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4333 BROOKLYN AVE NE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>HD1WMN6945W6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF WASHINGTON</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Washington]]></Name>
<CityName>Seattle</CityName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>981951617</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Biostatistics, 3980 15th Ave NE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1112</Code>
<Text>Genetic Mechanisms</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1127</Code>
<Text>Evolutionary Processes</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7657</Code>
<Text>Integrtv Ecological Physiology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7465</Code>
<Text>NANOSCALE BIO CORE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~47280</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The International Conferences on Quantitative Genetics (ICQG) bring together researchers from diverse fields of application - humans, crops, livestock, cells and &lsquo;omics - to discuss the latest research on the genetics of quantitative traits. Quantitative genetics is concerned with traits for which variation between individuals is controlled in part by DNA differences between individuals. While classically applied to continuously distributed traits, the models and methods also apply to the many complex traits that are binary (e.g., disease). Those working in the field of quantitative genetics employ sophisticated statistical methods to address real-world problems. While quantitative genetics methods date back to the classic papers of 100 years ago, the new genomic technologies of the last decade have generated data on an unprecedented scale, both in terms of numbers of phenotypes and sample sizes. For example, quantitative genetics methods are now applied to phenotypes measured at the level of individual cell types. These new data have allowed old questions to be addressed and have generated a plethora of new methods.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>ICQG6 was scheduled to be held in Brisbane, Australia in June 2020. Due to the COVID pandemic, the meeting was re-configured as a virtual conference and held in the first two weeks of November, 2020. There were 1101 registrants, with 380 being from the United States. NSF award IOS-2010561provided registration costs for 122 US students.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Participants&rsquo; interests, as indicated by those who submitted abstracts for conference presentations or posters, in decreasing numbers were: Livestock Genetics, Statistical Methodology, Human Genetics, Genotype by Environment Interaction, Plant Genetics, Evolutionary Genetics, &nbsp;and Cell and &lsquo;Omic biology.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Video recordings of the conference are available at</p> <p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLtctn4M0PiqyIAIbEDnx1lhXY1VOfsZn6">https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLtctn4M0PiqyIAIbEDnx1lhXY1VOfsZn6</a></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/05/2022<br>      Modified by: Bruce&nbsp;S&nbsp;Weir</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The International Conferences on Quantitative Genetics (ICQG) bring together researchers from diverse fields of application - humans, crops, livestock, cells and ‘omics - to discuss the latest research on the genetics of quantitative traits. Quantitative genetics is concerned with traits for which variation between individuals is controlled in part by DNA differences between individuals. While classically applied to continuously distributed traits, the models and methods also apply to the many complex traits that are binary (e.g., disease). Those working in the field of quantitative genetics employ sophisticated statistical methods to address real-world problems. While quantitative genetics methods date back to the classic papers of 100 years ago, the new genomic technologies of the last decade have generated data on an unprecedented scale, both in terms of numbers of phenotypes and sample sizes. For example, quantitative genetics methods are now applied to phenotypes measured at the level of individual cell types. These new data have allowed old questions to be addressed and have generated a plethora of new methods.        ICQG6 was scheduled to be held in Brisbane, Australia in June 2020. Due to the COVID pandemic, the meeting was re-configured as a virtual conference and held in the first two weeks of November, 2020. There were 1101 registrants, with 380 being from the United States. NSF award IOS-2010561provided registration costs for 122 US students.     Participants’ interests, as indicated by those who submitted abstracts for conference presentations or posters, in decreasing numbers were: Livestock Genetics, Statistical Methodology, Human Genetics, Genotype by Environment Interaction, Plant Genetics, Evolutionary Genetics,  and Cell and ‘Omic biology.     Video recordings of the conference are available at  https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLtctn4M0PiqyIAIbEDnx1lhXY1VOfsZn6             Last Modified: 01/05/2022       Submitted by: Bruce S Weir]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
