<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Public Support for Disaster Risk Reduction Policies in the Bahamas after Hurricane Dorian]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>39228.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>39228</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Daan Liang</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dliang@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922441</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This Rapid Response Research (RAPID) project creates new knowledge that is crucial for developing more resilient communities.  It improves understanding of how experiencing a disaster affects people’s attitudes towards, and support for, disaster risk and disaster risk reduction (DRR) policies, particularly building standards and construction regulations.  Project researchers collect and analyze waves of public opinion data from the Bahamas, parts of which were devastated by the Category 5 Hurricane Dorian in early September 2019.   The project will advance scientific understanding of post-disaster public opinion dynamics and help support strategic efforts to strengthen policies and programs to reduce human and economic losses from disasters.  It will also serve U.S. humanitarian and security interests, since losses from hazard events in the Caribbean region affect U.S. foreign assistance, immigration flows and patterns, and, ultimately, national security.  Finally, this project will increase public engagement with and appreciation of science and technology, as researchers will disseminate public-facing reports on key findings about hazard event experiences, public support for risk reduction, and “windows of opportunity” for achieving enhanced building survivability and safety. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The data for this project will be collected over a 12 month period in multiple waves of telephone surveys in the Bahamas, and then analyzed by researchers at Florida International University’s Extreme Events Institute.  Findings will reveal whether and how “focusing events” like disasters cause event-driven shifts in public awareness and opinion—a question for which existing research has offered mixed or at best inconclusive results.  Concretely, the project seeks to understand a) whether—and how—disasters increase perceptions of risk and public demand for risk reduction policies, and b) the extent and duration of any such changes in public opinion (e.g., whether these changes in attitudes are long-term or short-term, whether attitudes tend to return to baseline pre-event levels or settle at a new equilibrium).  The project will contribute to the accumulation of knowledge not only in disaster research but also in public policy and administration, the psychology of risk, and political culture.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/23/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/24/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2011872</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
<LastName>Olson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Richard S Olson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[olsonr@fiu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000450011</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/23/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Barry</FirstName>
<LastName>Levitt</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Barry S Levitt</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[levittb@fiu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000571805</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/23/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Florida International University</Name>
<CityName>MIAMI</CityName>
<ZipCode>331992516</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3053482494</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>11200 SW 8TH ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>26</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL26</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>Q3KCVK5S9CP1</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>FLORIDA INTERNATIONAL UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>D4GCCCMXR1H3</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Florida International University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>331990001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>26</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL26</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1638</Code>
<Text>HDBE-Humans, Disasters, and th</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>036E</Code>
<Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>041E</Code>
<Text>HAZARD AND DISASTER REDUCTION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>042E</Code>
<Text>HAZARD AND DISASTER RESPONSE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1576</Code>
<Text>NATIONL EARTHQK HZRD REDCT PRG</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~39228</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project assessed the impact of a country experiencing a disaster on its people's attitudes towards disaster risk and, especially, disaster risk reduction (DRR) practices and policies. &nbsp;Researchers collected and analyzed public opinion data from the Bahamas, parts of which were devastated by the Category 5 Hurricane Dorian in early September 2019.&nbsp;</p> <p>The project sought to determine whether and how disasters serve as "focusing events" that, among other effects, shift public awareness and opinion and, potentially, open "windows of opportunity" for changing the design or implementation of relevant policies -- in this instance, building codes and construction regulations. Do disasters indeed affect people's attitudes towards future disaster risk and risk reduction?&nbsp; Are these changes enduring or ephemeral? If shifts in public opinion are short-lived, how quickly do they begin to revert back to baseline values?&nbsp; (And if so, does public sentiment fully revert to pre-event levels or, instead, stabilize at some other level?)&nbsp;</p> <p>Working with a locally-based survey research firm, the project collected three waves of survey data --&nbsp; in June 2020, December 2020, and July-August 2021 -- with sample sizes each n=1000.&nbsp; The resulting dataset was merged with two waves of survey data collected in the Bahamas prior to the start of the project (in October and December 2019), as well as baseline measurements from a 2014 cross-national survey.</p> <p>Tracking change over time in aggregate public opinion, project researchers found that Bahamians' support for safer construction practices increased after the 2019 hurricane, then declined.&nbsp; As of August 2021, nearly two years after Hurricane Dorian, Bahamians' collective support for DRR practices was lower than its post-event high -- but had, in fact, stabilized at a higher level than was measured prior to the hurricane (see Fig. 1).</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Similarly, average levels of support for increased government enforcement of DRR policies was high -- 75% (a percentage adapted from a seven-point Likert scale) -- a month after the 2019 hurricane, then declined to 66% at the three month mark (though support increased again in 2020-2021, coinciding with the COVID-19 pandemic; see below).</p> <p>Regression-style analysis of individual level data confirmed that, controlling for demographic traits and relevant attitudinal variables, the passage of time since the hurricane did significantly erode support both for DRR practices and for enforcement of DRR policies and regulations.&nbsp; Multivariate analysis also revealed that:</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <ul> <li>Higher perception of future risk from a disaster significantly increases one's support for DRR policies relevant to that specific type of disaster.</li> </ul> <p>&nbsp;</p> <ul> <li>Higher perception of future risk from one kind of disaster is associated with a higher perception of future risk from <em>other</em> kinds of disasters. &nbsp;(Here, the COVID-19 pandemic may have indirectly contributed to Bahamians' renewed support for DRR policies -- not only for public health programs but for building codes and construction regulations as well.)</li> </ul> <p>&nbsp;</p> <ul> <li>Belief in the efficacy of DRR -- believing that better building code enforcement would have prevented harm from the hurricane -- strongly predicts support for DRR policies and practices (and this perception of efficacy, too, declined over time).</li> </ul> <p>&nbsp;</p> <ul> <li>How severely one was affected by a disaster does <span style="text-decoration: underline;">not</span> significantly shape subsequent support for relevant DRR policies and practices. </li> </ul> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The dynamics of public support for DRR have immense theoretical and practical implications.&nbsp; Project findings are contributing to the accumulation of knowledge in such fields as public policy, the psychology of risk, and public opinion / political culture, as well as the growing multidisciplinary field of disaster studies.&nbsp; Most impactfully, the project provided a rare opportunity to study changing support for public policies in a timely manner and to test hypotheses about disasters as <em>potential</em>&nbsp;"focusing events," before it was known whether this particular disaster would or would not shift the politics of policy.&nbsp; The study thus overcame a methodological problem (selection bias) that previously hampered much of the existing research on this topic.</p> <p>The project also provides a framework for governments at all levels (local to national) and other stakeholders (NGOs, interest groups, international aid agencies) to better understand the timing of opportunities to strengthen and improve the implementation of DRR policies and practices -- and to build public support for those efforts. Finally, by creating new tools and generating new knowledge that might reduce injuries and deaths, material losses, and social instability in the wake of future hazard events, this project serves to improve the well-being of individuals in society; strengthen U.S. humanitarian and security interests; and increase public engagement with science and technology, among other socially-relevant outcomes.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/30/2021<br>      Modified by: Barry&nbsp;S&nbsp;Levitt</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2011872/2011872_10665766_1640897881694_Fig1Supportforsaferconstruction--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2011872/2011872_10665766_1640897881694_Fig1Supportforsaferconstruction--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Fig 1 - Support for Safer Construction Practices in the Bahamas"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2011872/2011872_10665766_1640897881694_Fig1Supportforsaferconstruction--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Fig 1 - Support for Safer Construction Practices in the Bahamas"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Change Over Time in Support for Safer Construction Practices in the Bahamas after Hurricane Dorian</div> <div class="imageCredit">BARRY LEVITT</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Barry&nbsp;S&nbsp;Levitt</div> <div class="imageTitle">Fig 1 - Support for Safer Construction Practices in the Bahamas</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project assessed the impact of a country experiencing a disaster on its people's attitudes towards disaster risk and, especially, disaster risk reduction (DRR) practices and policies.  Researchers collected and analyzed public opinion data from the Bahamas, parts of which were devastated by the Category 5 Hurricane Dorian in early September 2019.   The project sought to determine whether and how disasters serve as "focusing events" that, among other effects, shift public awareness and opinion and, potentially, open "windows of opportunity" for changing the design or implementation of relevant policies -- in this instance, building codes and construction regulations. Do disasters indeed affect people's attitudes towards future disaster risk and risk reduction?  Are these changes enduring or ephemeral? If shifts in public opinion are short-lived, how quickly do they begin to revert back to baseline values?  (And if so, does public sentiment fully revert to pre-event levels or, instead, stabilize at some other level?)   Working with a locally-based survey research firm, the project collected three waves of survey data --  in June 2020, December 2020, and July-August 2021 -- with sample sizes each n=1000.  The resulting dataset was merged with two waves of survey data collected in the Bahamas prior to the start of the project (in October and December 2019), as well as baseline measurements from a 2014 cross-national survey.  Tracking change over time in aggregate public opinion, project researchers found that Bahamians' support for safer construction practices increased after the 2019 hurricane, then declined.  As of August 2021, nearly two years after Hurricane Dorian, Bahamians' collective support for DRR practices was lower than its post-event high -- but had, in fact, stabilized at a higher level than was measured prior to the hurricane (see Fig. 1).     Similarly, average levels of support for increased government enforcement of DRR policies was high -- 75% (a percentage adapted from a seven-point Likert scale) -- a month after the 2019 hurricane, then declined to 66% at the three month mark (though support increased again in 2020-2021, coinciding with the COVID-19 pandemic; see below).  Regression-style analysis of individual level data confirmed that, controlling for demographic traits and relevant attitudinal variables, the passage of time since the hurricane did significantly erode support both for DRR practices and for enforcement of DRR policies and regulations.  Multivariate analysis also revealed that:     Higher perception of future risk from a disaster significantly increases one's support for DRR policies relevant to that specific type of disaster.      Higher perception of future risk from one kind of disaster is associated with a higher perception of future risk from other kinds of disasters.  (Here, the COVID-19 pandemic may have indirectly contributed to Bahamians' renewed support for DRR policies -- not only for public health programs but for building codes and construction regulations as well.)      Belief in the efficacy of DRR -- believing that better building code enforcement would have prevented harm from the hurricane -- strongly predicts support for DRR policies and practices (and this perception of efficacy, too, declined over time).      How severely one was affected by a disaster does not significantly shape subsequent support for relevant DRR policies and practices.       The dynamics of public support for DRR have immense theoretical and practical implications.  Project findings are contributing to the accumulation of knowledge in such fields as public policy, the psychology of risk, and public opinion / political culture, as well as the growing multidisciplinary field of disaster studies.  Most impactfully, the project provided a rare opportunity to study changing support for public policies in a timely manner and to test hypotheses about disasters as potential "focusing events," before it was known whether this particular disaster would or would not shift the politics of policy.  The study thus overcame a methodological problem (selection bias) that previously hampered much of the existing research on this topic.  The project also provides a framework for governments at all levels (local to national) and other stakeholders (NGOs, interest groups, international aid agencies) to better understand the timing of opportunities to strengthen and improve the implementation of DRR policies and practices -- and to build public support for those efforts. Finally, by creating new tools and generating new knowledge that might reduce injuries and deaths, material losses, and social instability in the wake of future hazard events, this project serves to improve the well-being of individuals in society; strengthen U.S. humanitarian and security interests; and increase public engagement with science and technology, among other socially-relevant outcomes.           Last Modified: 12/30/2021       Submitted by: Barry S Levitt]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
