<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[GLOBE Earth System Science Partner Collaborative Planning Workshop; Boulder, CO; Spring 2020]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>99549.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>99549</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>RISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div of Res, Innovation, Synergies, &amp; Edu</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Brandon Jones</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mbjones@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924713</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Part 1&lt;br/&gt;The University Corporation of Atmospheric Research (UCAR) GLOBE Implementation Office (GIO) and the UCAR Center for Science Education propose to host a two and a half-day conference and three follow-up web meetings to share ideas, lessons learned and to create and implement a plan for developing and sustaining statewide GLOBE Earth System Science (ESS) Partner Collaboratives in each of the six GLOBE regions of the United States. The conference will provide GLOBE Partners with an adaptive model to work collaboratively and leverage existing resources to increase impact on STEM Earth System Science. The conference will be facilitated by members of the Colorado ESS GLOBE Collaborative, the US GLOBE Country Coordinator, GLOBE Regional Representatives and GLOBE partner leaders chosen from one or more states in each GLOBE region.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Part 2&lt;br/&gt;The University Corporation of Atmospheric Research (UCAR) GLOBE Implementation Office (GIO) and the UCAR Center for Science Education propose a planning workshop that will use the Collective Impact Framework to provide GLOBE Partners with an adaptive model to work collaboratively and leverage existing resources to increase impact on STEM Earth System Science with direct connections to the GLOBE Program strategic plan. This proposed work directly aligns with the GLOBE Program Strategic Plan Community Goal 2 CG2): “Increase interactions and collaborations among local, regional and international GLOBE communities through events and activities.” In the implementation plan, three of the related CG2 strategies that could be addressed includes: 1)Community members encourage and enable each other to support GLOBE activities and events. 2)Support GLOBE-community events: i.e. short-term thematic data collection 3)Increase GLOBE community’s awareness of collaboration opportunities.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/31/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/31/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2011518</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Anthony</FirstName>
<LastName>Murphy</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Anthony P Murphy</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[tmurphy@ucar.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000284189</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/31/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University Corporation For Atmospheric Res</Name>
<CityName>BOULDER</CityName>
<ZipCode>803012252</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3034971000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3090 CENTER GREEN DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>YEZEE8W5JKA3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY CORPORATION FOR ATMOSPHERIC RESEARCH</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[UCAR]]></Name>
<CityName>Boulder</CityName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>803012252</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3090 Center Green Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7699</Code>
<Text>Integrat &amp; Collab Ed &amp; Rsearch</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~99549</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Global Learning and Observations to Benefit the Environment (GLOBE) Program was founded onEarth Day, 1994. GLOBE provides students and the public around the world with ways to contribute toour understanding of the Earth?s environment. GLOBE is an international science and education programthat provides future scientists with the tools needed to understand Earth's biggest mysteries. TheGLOBE Implementation Office (GIO) provides high-quality support GLOBE community worldwide. Wework with scientists, teachers, and an extensive network of partners to increase the public participationin The GLOBE Program. The GIO is funded by NASA through an agreement with the UniversityCorporation for Atmospheric Science (UCAR).</p> <p>GLOBE works with science education organizations in the United States to accomplish its mission. TheGLOBE Program recruits schools to implement GLOBE by training GLOBE teachers and their students inusing GLOBE's protocols and data. For this project, GIO partnered with the UCAR Center for ScienceEducation to develop seven Earth System Science (ESS) Collaborative Teams. The teams were made upof former, existing, and potential GLOBE partners. The project began in March 2020 with remotelearning opportunities over two-years culminating in a workshop in July 2022. The purpose of thisproject was to study how the ESS collaborative model could be adapted across GLOBE regions in theUnited States.</p> <p>At first, it was important to communicate the vision of the project amongst existing US GLOBE Partnerswho were interested in working with other ESS organizations in their area. After review of theapplications of organizations interested in the project, seven collaborative teams were accepted. The following teams participated in the project:</p> <ul> <li>California Strong</li> <li>Colorado Earth System Science Collaborative</li> <li>GLOBE Historically Black College and University (HBCU)/Cross Regional</li> <li> Just Science/Cross Regional</li> <li>Midwest</li> <li>New England</li> <li>New York</li> </ul> <p>The Project Leads spoke with team leaders in late 2021 to determine their priorities for an in-personworkshop in the summer of 2022. Project Leads worked with an internal evaluator to develop questionsto assess the priorities from the teams for the workshop. The priorities were then used to develop theworkshop agenda. The project also developed survey questions to assess the extent to which theprojects goals were met. Many workshop participants voiced interest in reconvening as a larger, allteams group in the future.</p> <p>Based on the results of this project, Project Leads learned that the collaborative teams approach haspotential to support ESS and GLOBE education and outreach in the United States.</p> <p>For any questions or comments on the ESS Collaborative project, please contact:<br />John Ristvey, Director</p> <p>UCAR Center for Science Education</p> <p>University Corporation for Atmospheric Research</p> <p>jristvey@ucar.edu</p> <p>303-497-25913090</p> <p>Center Green Drive</p> <p>Boulder, Colorado, 80301, USA</p> <p>This report is based on the work supported by the National Science Foundation (NSF) under Grant #2011518. Any opinions, findings, or conclusions expressed in this material are those of the authors anddo not necessarily reflect the views of the National Science Foundation.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/02/2023<br>      Modified by: Anthony&nbsp;P&nbsp;Murphy</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2011518/2011518_10652208_1676582989535_PXL_20220709_175925645--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2011518/2011518_10652208_1676582989535_PXL_20220709_175925645--rgov-800width.jpg" title="ESS Collaborative Group photo"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2011518/2011518_10652208_1676582989535_PXL_20220709_175925645--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="ESS Collaborative Group photo"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">GIO staff and ESS Collaborative participants pose at the in-person workshop in July 2022 in Estes Park, Co.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Diane Ristvey</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Anthony&nbsp;P&nbsp;Murphy</div> <div class="imageTitle">ESS Collaborative Group photo</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2011518/2011518_10652208_1676583169741_collaboration--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2011518/2011518_10652208_1676583169741_collaboration--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Cross Region Team 2 Collaboration"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2011518/2011518_10652208_1676583169741_collaboration--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Cross Region Team 2 Collaboration"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Cross Region Team 2 participates in a collaborative discussion.</div> <div class="imageCredit">John Ristvey</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Anthony&nbsp;P&nbsp;Murphy</div> <div class="imageTitle">Cross Region Team 2 Collaboration</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2011518/2011518_10652208_1676583666444_presentation3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2011518/2011518_10652208_1676583666444_presentation3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Virtual Engagement"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2011518/2011518_10652208_1676583666444_presentation3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Virtual Engagement"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Participants at the in-person meeting in Estes Park, CO incorporate virtual presentations to include participants who were unable to attend.</div> <div class="imageCredit">John Ristvey</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Anthony&nbsp;P&nbsp;Murphy</div> <div class="imageTitle">Virtual Engagement</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2011518/2011518_10652208_1676584177913_smiling--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2011518/2011518_10652208_1676584177913_smiling--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Soil Collection"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2011518/2011518_10652208_1676584177913_smiling--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Soil Collection"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Two participants gather soil for an activity at the in-person meeting in July 2022 in Estes Park Co.</div> <div class="imageCredit">John Ristvey</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Anthony&nbsp;P&nbsp;Murphy</div> <div class="imageTitle">Soil Collection</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2011518/2011518_10652208_1676584284169_soilsample2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2011518/2011518_10652208_1676584284169_soilsample2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Soil Collection Activity"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2011518/2011518_10652208_1676584284169_soilsample2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Soil Collection Activity"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">More participants take soil samples during an activity at the in person meeting in July 2022 in Estes Park Co.</div> <div class="imageCredit">John Ristvey</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Anthony&nbsp;P&nbsp;Murphy</div> <div class="imageTitle">Soil Collection Activity</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2011518/2011518_10652208_1676584371659_reading--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2011518/2011518_10652208_1676584371659_reading--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Soil Collection Analysis"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2011518/2011518_10652208_1676584371659_reading--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Soil Collection Analysis"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Two participants analyze the soil samples taken in the field at the in person meeting in Estes Park, CO in July 2022.</div> <div class="imageCredit">John Ristvey</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Anthony&nbsp;P&nbsp;Murphy</div> <div class="imageTitle">Soil Collection Analysis</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Global Learning and Observations to Benefit the Environment (GLOBE) Program was founded onEarth Day, 1994. GLOBE provides students and the public around the world with ways to contribute toour understanding of the Earth?s environment. GLOBE is an international science and education programthat provides future scientists with the tools needed to understand Earth's biggest mysteries. TheGLOBE Implementation Office (GIO) provides high-quality support GLOBE community worldwide. Wework with scientists, teachers, and an extensive network of partners to increase the public participationin The GLOBE Program. The GIO is funded by NASA through an agreement with the UniversityCorporation for Atmospheric Science (UCAR).  GLOBE works with science education organizations in the United States to accomplish its mission. TheGLOBE Program recruits schools to implement GLOBE by training GLOBE teachers and their students inusing GLOBE's protocols and data. For this project, GIO partnered with the UCAR Center for ScienceEducation to develop seven Earth System Science (ESS) Collaborative Teams. The teams were made upof former, existing, and potential GLOBE partners. The project began in March 2020 with remotelearning opportunities over two-years culminating in a workshop in July 2022. The purpose of thisproject was to study how the ESS collaborative model could be adapted across GLOBE regions in theUnited States.  At first, it was important to communicate the vision of the project amongst existing US GLOBE Partnerswho were interested in working with other ESS organizations in their area. After review of theapplications of organizations interested in the project, seven collaborative teams were accepted. The following teams participated in the project:  California Strong Colorado Earth System Science Collaborative GLOBE Historically Black College and University (HBCU)/Cross Regional  Just Science/Cross Regional Midwest New England New York   The Project Leads spoke with team leaders in late 2021 to determine their priorities for an in-personworkshop in the summer of 2022. Project Leads worked with an internal evaluator to develop questionsto assess the priorities from the teams for the workshop. The priorities were then used to develop theworkshop agenda. The project also developed survey questions to assess the extent to which theprojects goals were met. Many workshop participants voiced interest in reconvening as a larger, allteams group in the future.  Based on the results of this project, Project Leads learned that the collaborative teams approach haspotential to support ESS and GLOBE education and outreach in the United States.  For any questions or comments on the ESS Collaborative project, please contact: John Ristvey, Director  UCAR Center for Science Education  University Corporation for Atmospheric Research  jristvey@ucar.edu  303-497-25913090  Center Green Drive  Boulder, Colorado, 80301, USA  This report is based on the work supported by the National Science Foundation (NSF) under Grant #2011518. Any opinions, findings, or conclusions expressed in this material are those of the authors anddo not necessarily reflect the views of the National Science Foundation.       Last Modified: 03/02/2023       Submitted by: Anthony P Murphy]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
