<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[The influence of Comb Jellies (Mnemiopsis leidyi) on Harmful algal blooms, and Vibrio spp. in the Maryland Coastal Bays.]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>199980.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>199980</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div. of Equity for Excellence in STEM</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Regina Sievert</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rsievert@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922808</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The Centers of Research Excellence in Science and Technology-Postdoctoral Research Fellowship (CREST-PRF) track within the CREST program supports beginning CREST Center investigators with significant potential and provides them with training and research experiences that will broaden perspectives, facilitate interdisciplinary interactions and establish them in positions of leadership within the scientific community. This CREST-PRF project is aligned with the research focus of the CREST Center for the Integrated Study of Coastal Ecosystem Processes and Dynamics (CISCEP) at the University of Maryland Eastern Shore. The goal of this research is to understand the relationship between comb jelly, Harmful Algae Blooms (HAB), pathogenic bacteria, and environmental factors in Maryland Coastal Bays.  The recipient of this fellowship will participate in American Association for the Advancement of Science workshops and learn how to communicate this research to the public. The recipient will also broaden their knowledge of predictive modeling by attending the Chesapeake Community Research and Modeling Symposium.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Maryland Coastal Bays (MCBs) are one of the most diverse estuaries on the east coast providing habitat for juvenile fish, osprey, and terrapins. Understanding the relationship between M. leidyi, HABs, Vibrio spp. and environmental factors can be useful for environmental managers. The proposed project will be analyzing the effects of M. leidyi on Vibrio spp. and HABs abundance in the MCBs. This data will be used to develop empirical predictive models on HABs and Vibrio spp. abundance in the MCBs. Through the collaboration with the Maryland-Department of Natural Resources, National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, and the CREST program at University of Maryland Eastern Shore, the proposed work will be able to combine knowledge and data to further understand and predict the relationship between HABs and Vibrio spp. The work will inform the public and local government on the overall health of the Maryland Coastal Bays, regarding HABs, pathogenic Vibrio spp. and can be used to design management strategies.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/25/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/03/2023</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2011481</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Salina</FirstName>
<LastName>Parveen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Salina Parveen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<NSF_ID>000484200</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/25/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate>11/22/2021</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Detbra</FirstName>
<LastName>Rosales</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Detbra Rosales</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<NSF_ID>000792401</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/25/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Jacobs</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John M Jacobs</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<NSF_ID>000793933</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/25/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate>11/22/2021</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Rosales, Detbra</Name>
<CityName>salisbury</CityName>
<ZipCode>21801</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MD01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Maryland Easternshore]]></Name>
<CityName>Princess Anne</CityName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>218531299</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MD01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9131</Code>
<Text>Centers for Rsch Excell in S&amp;T</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9131</Code>
<Text>CENTERS FOR RSCH EXCELL IN S&amp;T</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0421</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~199980</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The relationship between bacteria, harmful algal species and Ctenophores are poorly understood. Especially the relationship between the ctenophore <em>M. leidyi</em>, harmful algal species and <em>Vibrio</em>s. An objective of this study was to determine the relationship between <em>Vibrios</em> and harmful algal species. A second objective was to determine the relationship with <em>Vibrios</em> and <em>M. leidyi</em>. The last objective is to define the relationship with <em>M. leidyi</em> and bacterial communities found in the Maryland Coastal Bays (MCBs). To examine these relationships in the MCBs I sampled water and <em>M. leidyi</em> in 2021-2022 from April-October at seven sites found in Assawoman Bay, Isle of wight bay, Sinepuxtent bay, Newport Bay and Chincoteague Bay. Environmental data such as temperature, salinity, dissolved oxygen, and nutrients were collected to determine the association between these abiotic and biotic variables. Bacterial and harmful algal composition was identified in environmental samples. Microbial communities were also identified in <em>M. leidyi</em>.</p> <p><em>M. leidyi</em> was present in both years and at all sites. There was a significant difference in <em>M. leidyi</em> abundance within sites. <em>M. leidyi</em> was most abundant in areas with high turbidity such Assawoman Bay. However, there was no strong association between turbidity and <em>M. leidyi</em> abundance in this study. Previous studies found associations between temperature, available zooplankton and phytoplankton, salinity, and <em>M. leidyi</em> concentration. However, this study revealed no association between <em>M. leidyi</em> spatial distribution and any environmental parameters in the MCBs. This could be due to small sample size and or the influence of other factors on <em>M. leidyi</em> concentrations.</p> <p>&nbsp;<em>Vibrios </em>were detected in <em>M. leidyi</em> and water samples. There was no strong relationship between <em>M. leidyi</em> and <em>Vibrio</em> abundance. Which is surprising because <em>Vibrios</em> can attach to complex polymers as found on <em>M. leidyi</em>. The lack of association between <em>M. leidyi</em> and <em>Vibrio</em> abundance could be due to small sample size or that other factors are playing a role on their abundance in the environment. In this study, nutrients varied within sites and higher concentrations of NH<sub>4</sub><sup>+</sup>, NO<sub>3</sub>:NO<sub>2</sub><sup>-</sup> and TDN were found in Assawoman bay. A generalized linear model revealed that temperature was the best at detecting total (<em>Vvha+) V. vulnificus</em> in <em>M. leidyi </em>and TDN was the best at detecting total (<em>Trh</em>+) <em>V. parahaemolyticus</em> in water<em>.</em> &nbsp;</p> <p>Harmful algal composition varied between sites. <em>&nbsp;K. veneficum </em>was the most abundant HAB species in Assawoman bay and this has been observed in other studies. Assawoman bay is known to be influenced by agricultural runoff as well as treated effluents from ocean pines wastewater treatment plant. Nutrients from these different sources may have played a role in <em>K. veneficum</em> abundance in Assawoman bay. <em>C. toxicum</em> was the most abundant HAB species in Newport Bay and has been previously detected in this area. Newport Bay is influenced by agricultural runoff, it is a poorly flushed system with a long residence time. Combination of nutrients and poorly flushed system may have played a role in the abundance of <em>C. toxicum</em> in Newport Bay<em>. </em>Sites near Ocean city inlet had a diverse HAB community, which could be due to the exchange of ocean and fresh water transporting HABs from different areas. There was a positive association with <em>V .parahaemolyticus</em>, picocyanobacterial and raphidophyte biomass.</p> <p>Microbial communities in <em>M. leidyi </em>and water differed between sites. Water samples collected from Assawoman Bay had an abundance of Flavobacteriales a bacterial group that plays a role in degrading organic matter and can impact the biogeochemical cycles. Water samples collected from Chincoteague Bay had an abundance of Rickettsiales a group that can be an endosymbiont to protist and aquatic invertebrates in marine environments. <em>M. leidyi</em> collected from Assawoman Bay had an abundance of Enterobacterialeas a group that is known to be found in nutrient rich areas. <em>M. leidyi</em> samples collected from Chincoteague Bay had an abundance of Rhizobiales a group that are known to be nitrogen fixing and found in salt marshes.</p> <p>Even though there was not a significant association between <em>M. leidyi</em> abundance and <em>Vibrios</em>. This study provided new knowledge on the ecology of <em>Vibrios </em>and <em>M. leidyi. </em>Temperature was a major factor influencing <em>M. leidyi</em> abundance in the MCBs. Sea surface temperatures are increasing globally this may lead to an increase in <em>M. leidyi </em>abundance in estuaries. Additionally, <em>M. leidyi</em> can alter microbial dynamics and alter the food web. This study provided novel information on the influence of <em>M. leidyi</em> on microbial dynamics in the MCBs. Data from this study can be used for future ecological models on harmful algal bloom and <em>Vibrio</em> dynamics in estuarine systems. Through the collaboration with MD-DNR, NOAA, and the CREST program at University of Maryland Eastern Shore results from this project were presented at the Joint aquatic science meeting, American society for microbiology and NOAA science seminar.</p> <p><em>&nbsp;</em></p> <p><em><br /></em></p> <p><em>&nbsp;</em></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/05/2023<br>      Modified by: Detbra&nbsp;Rosales</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The relationship between bacteria, harmful algal species and Ctenophores are poorly understood. Especially the relationship between the ctenophore M. leidyi, harmful algal species and Vibrios. An objective of this study was to determine the relationship between Vibrios and harmful algal species. A second objective was to determine the relationship with Vibrios and M. leidyi. The last objective is to define the relationship with M. leidyi and bacterial communities found in the Maryland Coastal Bays (MCBs). To examine these relationships in the MCBs I sampled water and M. leidyi in 2021-2022 from April-October at seven sites found in Assawoman Bay, Isle of wight bay, Sinepuxtent bay, Newport Bay and Chincoteague Bay. Environmental data such as temperature, salinity, dissolved oxygen, and nutrients were collected to determine the association between these abiotic and biotic variables. Bacterial and harmful algal composition was identified in environmental samples. Microbial communities were also identified in M. leidyi.  M. leidyi was present in both years and at all sites. There was a significant difference in M. leidyi abundance within sites. M. leidyi was most abundant in areas with high turbidity such Assawoman Bay. However, there was no strong association between turbidity and M. leidyi abundance in this study. Previous studies found associations between temperature, available zooplankton and phytoplankton, salinity, and M. leidyi concentration. However, this study revealed no association between M. leidyi spatial distribution and any environmental parameters in the MCBs. This could be due to small sample size and or the influence of other factors on M. leidyi concentrations.   Vibrios were detected in M. leidyi and water samples. There was no strong relationship between M. leidyi and Vibrio abundance. Which is surprising because Vibrios can attach to complex polymers as found on M. leidyi. The lack of association between M. leidyi and Vibrio abundance could be due to small sample size or that other factors are playing a role on their abundance in the environment. In this study, nutrients varied within sites and higher concentrations of NH4+, NO3:NO2- and TDN were found in Assawoman bay. A generalized linear model revealed that temperature was the best at detecting total (Vvha+) V. vulnificus in M. leidyi and TDN was the best at detecting total (Trh+) V. parahaemolyticus in water.    Harmful algal composition varied between sites.  K. veneficum was the most abundant HAB species in Assawoman bay and this has been observed in other studies. Assawoman bay is known to be influenced by agricultural runoff as well as treated effluents from ocean pines wastewater treatment plant. Nutrients from these different sources may have played a role in K. veneficum abundance in Assawoman bay. C. toxicum was the most abundant HAB species in Newport Bay and has been previously detected in this area. Newport Bay is influenced by agricultural runoff, it is a poorly flushed system with a long residence time. Combination of nutrients and poorly flushed system may have played a role in the abundance of C. toxicum in Newport Bay. Sites near Ocean city inlet had a diverse HAB community, which could be due to the exchange of ocean and fresh water transporting HABs from different areas. There was a positive association with V .parahaemolyticus, picocyanobacterial and raphidophyte biomass.  Microbial communities in M. leidyi and water differed between sites. Water samples collected from Assawoman Bay had an abundance of Flavobacteriales a bacterial group that plays a role in degrading organic matter and can impact the biogeochemical cycles. Water samples collected from Chincoteague Bay had an abundance of Rickettsiales a group that can be an endosymbiont to protist and aquatic invertebrates in marine environments. M. leidyi collected from Assawoman Bay had an abundance of Enterobacterialeas a group that is known to be found in nutrient rich areas. M. leidyi samples collected from Chincoteague Bay had an abundance of Rhizobiales a group that are known to be nitrogen fixing and found in salt marshes.  Even though there was not a significant association between M. leidyi abundance and Vibrios. This study provided new knowledge on the ecology of Vibrios and M. leidyi. Temperature was a major factor influencing M. leidyi abundance in the MCBs. Sea surface temperatures are increasing globally this may lead to an increase in M. leidyi abundance in estuaries. Additionally, M. leidyi can alter microbial dynamics and alter the food web. This study provided novel information on the influence of M. leidyi on microbial dynamics in the MCBs. Data from this study can be used for future ecological models on harmful algal bloom and Vibrio dynamics in estuarine systems. Through the collaboration with MD-DNR, NOAA, and the CREST program at University of Maryland Eastern Shore results from this project were presented at the Joint aquatic science meeting, American society for microbiology and NOAA science seminar.                Last Modified: 06/05/2023       Submitted by: Detbra Rosales]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
