<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[WOU-MMA: Improved Data Access for GW Astronomy]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>390000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>390000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Pedro Marronetti</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>pmarrone@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927372</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This award supports research in relativity and relativistic astrophysics and it addresses the priority areas of NSF's "Windows on the Universe" Big Idea. Gravitational-wave astronomy is one of the most rapidly evolving fields in astrophysics.  Over the past few years, the interferometer gravitational-wave observatories LIGO and Virgo have begun to record compact object mergers of black holes and neutron stars for the first time.  These discoveries are having a tremendous impact on our ability to study the population of black holes in our universe, learn about fundamental particle physics through study of the dense interiors of neutron stars, test general relativity as never before, and investigate a range of other topics.  Data from these cutting edge instruments are made available to the scientific community and the public  through the Gravitational Wave Open Science Center (GWOSC) at gw-openscience.org.  As LIGO and Virgo become more sensitive, the rate of discoveries is quickly accelerating.  Starting in 2015, the number of observed compact object mergers has grown from 1, to 10, to 50.  During the last observing run, LIGO and Virgo were observing mergers of black holes or neutron stars about once per week, and future upgrades are expected to make this rate grow.  As we begin to record hundreds or thousands of these astrophysical events, the scientific community will need a new set of tools to access and analyze the information associated with these discoveries.  This project will fund the construction of a new “event portal”, which will allow scientists, teachers, students,  and enthusiasts around the world to browse catalogs of compact object mergers, study measurements of black hole properties, view graphics and plots, and listen to data converted to audio files, as well as download and analyze the associated interferometer data.  The award also includes funding to host an Open Data Workshop to train students and scientists who wish to contribute to this new field of astronomy.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Large collections of gravitational-wave events will invite a wide set of scientific investigations, but only if researchers with diverse interests are able to access and explore the associated data. Current structures on the GWOSC website provide only minimal support for derived data products (e.g., source parameters), and will not scale to hundreds of events. Going forward, the set of researchers interested in gravitational-wave science will likely broaden substantially to include more people interested in stellar populations, general relativity, nuclear astrophysics, and other fields. Many of these same people will be highly interested in derived data products, in addition to the gravitational-wave strain data GWOSC already hosts. Developing the event portal will enable these researchers to find and understand the data they need, and empower them to carry through their investigations.  In addition, both the event portal and the Open Data Workshop will make gravitational-wave science more accessible to a wider array of researchers. Because less expertise will be needed to engage with this science, the event portal will “lower-the-bar” for entry into the field, and empower a more diverse group of scientists and students to benefit from GW observations.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/09/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/09/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2011966</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jonah</FirstName>
<LastName>Kanner</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jonah B Kanner</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jkanner@caltech.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000814924</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/09/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>California Institute of Technology</Name>
<CityName>PASADENA</CityName>
<ZipCode>911250001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6263956219</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1200 E CALIFORNIA BLVD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>28</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA28</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>U2JMKHNS5TG4</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CALIFORNIA INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[California Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>PASADENA</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>911250600</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1200 E California Blvd]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>28</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA28</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>107Y</Code>
<Text>WoU-Windows on the Universe: T</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7569</Code>
<Text>CYBERINFRASTRUCTURE/SCIENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~390000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>LIGO and Virgo are now observing mergers of binary black holes and binary neutron stars, known collectively as compact object mergers. &nbsp;During the period of this grant, the number of observed compact object mergers published by the LIGO/Virgo/KAGRA collaboration increased ninefold, from 10 to 93. &nbsp;This awarded provided support for two activities to improve public access to data associated with these discoveries.</p> <p>1) We developed and populated the Event Portal, a new database for tracking published gravitational-wave observations. &nbsp;The Event Portal now includes all compact object mergers published by the LIGO/Virgo/KAGRA collaboration, and is available via the GWOSC website at gwosc.org. &nbsp;</p> <p>The Event Portal includes both HTML and REST API interfaces. &nbsp;Users can browse lists of events or query for objects based on their physical parameters. &nbsp;Through the portal, researchers and students can find the masses, spins, and distances to each compact object merger, browse spectrograms, and download associated data. &nbsp;For each event, linked data include instrument strain data, segment lists indicating times of good quality data, posterior sample files from parameter estimation, and skymaps showing estimated source locations. &nbsp;</p> <p>2) We helped organize three Gravitational Wave Open Data Workshops. &nbsp;These workshops combine lectures from data analysis experts introducing popular techniques in the field, with hands-on programming tutorials that invite participants to work with real gravitational-wave data downloaded from the GWOSC website. &nbsp;The workshops include a data challenge at the end, so that participants can use their new skills to find simulated signals hidden in real instrument data. &nbsp;During this grant period, we explored an innovative, hybrid format for the workshop. &nbsp;After an online workshop with 100 people in 2021, we transitioned to a hybrid format using 15-20 Study Hub locations around the world, paired with an online course that includes video lectures, software tutorials, quiz questions, and the data challenge. &nbsp;This scalable format allowed hundreds of people to participate in-person at Study Hubs, and thousands to enroll in the online course. &nbsp;All materials from the course are available for free, and students can enroll at anytime by visiting gwosc.org/workshops. &nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/27/2023<br>      Modified by: Jonah&nbsp;B&nbsp;Kanner</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2011966/2011966_10683989_1698360975333_single-event--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2011966/2011966_10683989_1698360975333_single-event--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Event Portal"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2011966/2011966_10683989_1698360975333_single-event--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Event Portal"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">An example single event view in the Event Portal.  Visible are basic information about a binary black hole merger, along with links to download instrument strain data.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jonah Kanner</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jonah&nbsp;B&nbsp;Kanner</div> <div class="imageTitle">Event Portal</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2011966/2011966_10683989_1698360861529_gwosc-home--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2011966/2011966_10683989_1698360861529_gwosc-home--rgov-800width.jpg" title="GWOSC Home"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2011966/2011966_10683989_1698360861529_gwosc-home--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="GWOSC Home"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">GWOSC Home Page</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jonah Kanner</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jonah&nbsp;B&nbsp;Kanner</div> <div class="imageTitle">GWOSC Home</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2011966/2011966_10683989_1698361083981_quickview--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2011966/2011966_10683989_1698361083981_quickview--rgov-800width.jpg" title="GW Quickview"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2011966/2011966_10683989_1698361083981_quickview--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="GW Quickview"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The GW Quickview App makes use of the Event Portal API, allowing users to create customized plots of data in an interactive environment.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jonah Kanner</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jonah&nbsp;B&nbsp;Kanner</div> <div class="imageTitle">GW Quickview</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2011966/2011966_10683989_1698361380058_workshops--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2011966/2011966_10683989_1698361380058_workshops--rgov-800width.jpg" title="GW Open Data Workshops"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2011966/2011966_10683989_1698361380058_workshops--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="GW Open Data Workshops"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">All materials from recent GW Open Data Workshops are available as a free, online course.  Enroll at any time!</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jonah Kanner</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jonah&nbsp;B&nbsp;Kanner</div> <div class="imageTitle">GW Open Data Workshops</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ LIGO and Virgo are now observing mergers of binary black holes and binary neutron stars, known collectively as compact object mergers.  During the period of this grant, the number of observed compact object mergers published by the LIGO/Virgo/KAGRA collaboration increased ninefold, from 10 to 93.  This awarded provided support for two activities to improve public access to data associated with these discoveries.  1) We developed and populated the Event Portal, a new database for tracking published gravitational-wave observations.  The Event Portal now includes all compact object mergers published by the LIGO/Virgo/KAGRA collaboration, and is available via the GWOSC website at gwosc.org.    The Event Portal includes both HTML and REST API interfaces.  Users can browse lists of events or query for objects based on their physical parameters.  Through the portal, researchers and students can find the masses, spins, and distances to each compact object merger, browse spectrograms, and download associated data.  For each event, linked data include instrument strain data, segment lists indicating times of good quality data, posterior sample files from parameter estimation, and skymaps showing estimated source locations.    2) We helped organize three Gravitational Wave Open Data Workshops.  These workshops combine lectures from data analysis experts introducing popular techniques in the field, with hands-on programming tutorials that invite participants to work with real gravitational-wave data downloaded from the GWOSC website.  The workshops include a data challenge at the end, so that participants can use their new skills to find simulated signals hidden in real instrument data.  During this grant period, we explored an innovative, hybrid format for the workshop.  After an online workshop with 100 people in 2021, we transitioned to a hybrid format using 15-20 Study Hub locations around the world, paired with an online course that includes video lectures, software tutorials, quiz questions, and the data challenge.  This scalable format allowed hundreds of people to participate in-person at Study Hubs, and thousands to enroll in the online course.  All materials from the course are available for free, and students can enroll at anytime by visiting gwosc.org/workshops.            Last Modified: 10/27/2023       Submitted by: Jonah B Kanner]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
