<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Student Travel Grant for 2020 Society for Industrial and Applied Mathematics International Conference on Data Mining (SDM)]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>25000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>25000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sylvia Spengler</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sspengle@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927347</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The 2020 Society for Industrial and Applied Mathematics (SIAM) International Conference on Data Mining (SDM 2020) is being organized by SIAM in cooperation with the American Statistical Association.  SDM 2020 will be held in Cincinnati, Ohio from May 7 to May 9, 2020. Funds will provide travel support for approximately 16 students from institutions in the United States to participate in a student consortium that is to be held as part of SDM 2020.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award will provide support for student participation in a new consortium, the SIAM Student Consortium.  It will provide the students with an opportunity to learn new data skills (Python) and to participate with peers and leading researchers.  Conference leadership will provide mentors to the participants.   This is one of the first meetings to make an effort to engage undergraduates, including from underrepresented groups, and is a complement to the range of graduate doctoral consortia.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/03/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/03/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2011666</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Joyce</FirstName>
<LastName>Ho</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Joyce C Ho</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[joyce.c.ho@emory.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000723482</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/03/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Emory University</Name>
<CityName>ATLANTA</CityName>
<ZipCode>303221061</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4047272503</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>201 DOWMAN DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>S352L5PJLMP8</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>EMORY UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Emory University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>303224250</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7364</Code>
<Text>Info Integration &amp; Informatics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7364</Code>
<Text>INFO INTEGRATION &amp; INFORMATICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~25000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The SIAM (Society for Industrial and Applied Mathematics) International Conference on Data Mining (SDM) is a top-tier conference in the field of data mining. It provides a venue for researchers who are addressing problems in data mining to present their work in a peer-reviewed forum.&nbsp;</p> <p>SDM 2020 was canceled due to the COVID-19 pandemic and all the activity in 2020 was merged into SDM 2021.</p> <p>This project funded 91 students to attend the SDM 2021 conference virtually (due to the COVID-19 pandemic). Special efforts were made to support students from disenfranchised groups and/or had limited prior experience attending a computer science conference. As such, 57 students were from the disenfranchised group and 62 students attended their first computer science conference. Participants had access to all the SDM 2021 sessions including the tutorials on various subjects. The students were invited to participate in the doctoral forum panel where panelists from both industry and academia gave advice about graduate school, research, and industry trends. Students also had the opportunity to ask questions in the chat. A condensed video of the panel was posted publicly on SIAM's YouTube channel. The students were also invited to activities in Gather.Town to interact with the doctoral forum panelists, the doctorly symposium poster judges, and the graduate students.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/02/2022<br>      Modified by: Joyce&nbsp;C&nbsp;Ho</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The SIAM (Society for Industrial and Applied Mathematics) International Conference on Data Mining (SDM) is a top-tier conference in the field of data mining. It provides a venue for researchers who are addressing problems in data mining to present their work in a peer-reviewed forum.   SDM 2020 was canceled due to the COVID-19 pandemic and all the activity in 2020 was merged into SDM 2021.  This project funded 91 students to attend the SDM 2021 conference virtually (due to the COVID-19 pandemic). Special efforts were made to support students from disenfranchised groups and/or had limited prior experience attending a computer science conference. As such, 57 students were from the disenfranchised group and 62 students attended their first computer science conference. Participants had access to all the SDM 2021 sessions including the tutorials on various subjects. The students were invited to participate in the doctoral forum panel where panelists from both industry and academia gave advice about graduate school, research, and industry trends. Students also had the opportunity to ask questions in the chat. A condensed video of the panel was posted publicly on SIAM's YouTube channel. The students were also invited to activities in Gather.Town to interact with the doctoral forum panelists, the doctorly symposium poster judges, and the graduate students.       Last Modified: 05/02/2022       Submitted by: Joyce C Ho]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
