<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Broadening Participation Research: Investigating the Effects of a Linked, Interdisciplinary Learning Community Model on Achievement and Persistence of Black Males]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>349614.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>349614</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div. of Equity for Excellence in STEM</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tori Rhoulac Smith</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tosmith@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922315</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This study is investigating the extent to which results from the College Student Inventory (CSI) cognitive and non-cognitive measures are predictive of persistence from the first to the third year of college.  Researchers demonstrate the effectiveness of theory-based teaching and learning concepts in STEM  by using a proactive means of identifying STEM students who may be at-risk for academic difficulty and applying an intervention based upon concepts and practices for establishing learning communities. The intervention inputs include linked interdisciplinary regular courses such as biology and oral communication that integrate content and application coursework; theme-based interdisciplinary seminars, early immersion into research, and receipt of mentoring. The study links research and education and advances understanding of factors associated with improving achievement and retention of Black male undergraduates in STEM. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The study is grounded in Tinto’s Departure Theory and situated cognition theory. Researchers will investigate (1) to what extent was participation in the linked courses associated with higher cumulative GPAs, continuous enrollment, and higher completion rates?, (2) What motivational factors measured by the College Student Inventory predict academic success and persistence of STEM students who might be at-risk for academic difficulty? (3) In what ways has the interdisciplinary learning community experience changed students’ approaches to understanding STEM course materials? And (4) In what ways did students, instructors, and the institution benefit from the interdisciplinary learning community? The study sample will include all incoming freshmen who will be placed in one of two comparison conditions – those not enrolled into an interdisciplinary learning community and non-STEM students whose predicted academic difficulty scores range from 1-9. A comparative regression discontinuity design will be used to analyze the quantitative and qualitative measures of the effects of the intervention. The research results are expected to inform the design of interventions for at-risk undergraduate students. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This study is supported by the Historically Black Colleges and Universities Undergraduate Program, broadening participation in STEM education research track.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/26/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/26/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2011889</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Haynes</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>K</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John K Haynes</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[john.haynes@morehouse.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000260254</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/26/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Terry</FirstName>
<LastName>Mills</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Terry L Mills</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[terrymills226@gmail.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000815791</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/26/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Morehouse College</Name>
<CityName>ATLANTA</CityName>
<ZipCode>303143773</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4706390633</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>830 WESTVIEW DR SW</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>KTE2MFWTKAE5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MOREHOUSE COLLEGE INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>KTE2MFWTKAE5</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Morehouse College]]></Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>303143773</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[830 Westview Drive SW]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1594</Code>
<Text>Hist Black Colleges and Univ</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8212</Code>
<Text>Broaden Particip STEM Resrch</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0420</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~349614</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Hopps Scholars Program at Morehouse College aimed to promote the growth and success of STEM students, particularly those from underrepresented groups. This report provides an overview of the project outcomes, methodologies, student benefits, and recommendations for program enhancements. Additionally, it highlights the challenges faced when the COVID-19 pandemic unexpectedly impacted every aspect of the academic endeavor and describes how the program adapted to engage with the scholars during uncertain times.</p> <p><strong>Methodology</strong></p> <p>The selection process for participants in the Hopps Scholars Program utilized the College Student Inventory survey (CSI). The CSI is a tool that assesses students' interests, skills, and academic motivations. By administering the CSI to entering first-year STEM students, the program identified individuals who demonstrated potential and interest in STEM fields; and who could benefit from participation in the project. The survey results helped tailor academic advising and mentoring support based on students' individual needs and aspirations.</p> <p><strong>The Hopps Scholars Project outcomes</strong></p> <ul> <li><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Development of Linked Interdisciplinary Courses</span>: The program attempted to develop two sets of linked interdisciplinary courses. One was successfully implemented, and the other was not. The first set of courses integrated general chemistry with social problems, providing students with a comprehensive understanding of the scientific principles and societal implications of chemical research. The second set of linked courses was not implemented due to curriculum committee review timelines. However, the curriculum combines Algebra 1 with Music and Culture, connecting mathematical concepts, such as geometric sequences to music. The goal of these linked courses was to enhance students' critical thinking, problem-solving skills, and interdisciplinary perspectives.&nbsp;</li> <li><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Enhanced Academic Advising and Mentoring</span>: The Hopps Scholars received tailored academic advising and mentoring support throughout the project. This personalized guidance helped students navigate their STEM coursework, explore research opportunities, and make informed decisions about their academic and career paths.The integration of the College Student Inventory (CSI) with the StarFish advising system showed great possibilities for further enhancing academic advising.</li> <li><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Exposure to Research Opportunities</span>: The program provided students with research opportunities, including a detailed virtual tour of Oakridge National Research Labs. These experiences exposed the scholars to cutting-edge scientific research, fostering their interest and engagement in scientific exploration.</li> </ul> <ol> </ol> <p>The COVID-19 pandemic posed significant challenges to the program's operations. The unexpected and widespread impact of the pandemic disrupted academic activities, including in-person classes, research projects, and on-campus engagements.&nbsp;</p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Adaptation and Engagement</span>: Despite the challenges, the Hopps Scholars Program found innovative ways to engage with the scholars and adapt to the uncertainties. Virtual platforms were utilized to conduct remote advising and mentoring sessions, maintain communication, and facilitate academic support. The program also facilitated virtual networking opportunities and guest lectures to ensure scholars remained connected to the STEM community.</p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Findings:</span>&nbsp;&nbsp;Findings from analysis conducted on the CSI database comprised of 164 students enrolled in STEM majors at Morehouse College provided additional evidence for the utility of the CSI. There was a strong, negative correlation between overall GPA scores and Perceived Academic Difficulty (PAD), r= -.52, n=164, p &lt; .001. In other words, higher PAD scores are associated with, and predictive of lower GPAs. This negative correlation suggests that the CSI could provide useful information regarding STEM students enrolled at Morehouse College. The PAD scores could be used to identify those students who are most likely to struggle academically.Other information provided by the CSI could be used to help identify the type of guidance that should be provided and which students will need to be worked with more closely to better ensure that they are receptive and responsive to support efforts.</p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Recommendations</span>: The proactive identification and selection of STEM undergraduates who might benefit from such a program provides an opportunity for timely intervention and guidance, rather than a triage approach to get students back on track. As a research project, students voluntarily participated in the project activities. However, a more effective approach might be to establish the linked interdisciplinary courses and enhanced early advising model as a formal pathway for first and second-year STEM students who might benefit from such support.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/04/2023<br>      Modified by: Terry&nbsp;L&nbsp;Mills</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Hopps Scholars Program at Morehouse College aimed to promote the growth and success of STEM students, particularly those from underrepresented groups. This report provides an overview of the project outcomes, methodologies, student benefits, and recommendations for program enhancements. Additionally, it highlights the challenges faced when the COVID-19 pandemic unexpectedly impacted every aspect of the academic endeavor and describes how the program adapted to engage with the scholars during uncertain times.  Methodology  The selection process for participants in the Hopps Scholars Program utilized the College Student Inventory survey (CSI). The CSI is a tool that assesses students' interests, skills, and academic motivations. By administering the CSI to entering first-year STEM students, the program identified individuals who demonstrated potential and interest in STEM fields; and who could benefit from participation in the project. The survey results helped tailor academic advising and mentoring support based on students' individual needs and aspirations.  The Hopps Scholars Project outcomes  Development of Linked Interdisciplinary Courses: The program attempted to develop two sets of linked interdisciplinary courses. One was successfully implemented, and the other was not. The first set of courses integrated general chemistry with social problems, providing students with a comprehensive understanding of the scientific principles and societal implications of chemical research. The second set of linked courses was not implemented due to curriculum committee review timelines. However, the curriculum combines Algebra 1 with Music and Culture, connecting mathematical concepts, such as geometric sequences to music. The goal of these linked courses was to enhance students' critical thinking, problem-solving skills, and interdisciplinary perspectives.  Enhanced Academic Advising and Mentoring: The Hopps Scholars received tailored academic advising and mentoring support throughout the project. This personalized guidance helped students navigate their STEM coursework, explore research opportunities, and make informed decisions about their academic and career paths.The integration of the College Student Inventory (CSI) with the StarFish advising system showed great possibilities for further enhancing academic advising. Exposure to Research Opportunities: The program provided students with research opportunities, including a detailed virtual tour of Oakridge National Research Labs. These experiences exposed the scholars to cutting-edge scientific research, fostering their interest and engagement in scientific exploration.     The COVID-19 pandemic posed significant challenges to the program's operations. The unexpected and widespread impact of the pandemic disrupted academic activities, including in-person classes, research projects, and on-campus engagements.   Adaptation and Engagement: Despite the challenges, the Hopps Scholars Program found innovative ways to engage with the scholars and adapt to the uncertainties. Virtual platforms were utilized to conduct remote advising and mentoring sessions, maintain communication, and facilitate academic support. The program also facilitated virtual networking opportunities and guest lectures to ensure scholars remained connected to the STEM community.  Findings:  Findings from analysis conducted on the CSI database comprised of 164 students enrolled in STEM majors at Morehouse College provided additional evidence for the utility of the CSI. There was a strong, negative correlation between overall GPA scores and Perceived Academic Difficulty (PAD), r= -.52, n=164, p &lt; .001. In other words, higher PAD scores are associated with, and predictive of lower GPAs. This negative correlation suggests that the CSI could provide useful information regarding STEM students enrolled at Morehouse College. The PAD scores could be used to identify those students who are most likely to struggle academically.Other information provided by the CSI could be used to help identify the type of guidance that should be provided and which students will need to be worked with more closely to better ensure that they are receptive and responsive to support efforts.  Recommendations: The proactive identification and selection of STEM undergraduates who might benefit from such a program provides an opportunity for timely intervention and guidance, rather than a triage approach to get students back on track. As a research project, students voluntarily participated in the project activities. However, a more effective approach might be to establish the linked interdisciplinary courses and enhanced early advising model as a formal pathway for first and second-year STEM students who might benefit from such support.       Last Modified: 09/04/2023       Submitted by: Terry L Mills]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
