<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[The Eighth International Symposium on Data Assimilation (ISDA); Fort Collins, Colorado;  June 8-12, 2020]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>15581.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>15581</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06020105</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AGS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Nicholas Anderson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>nanderso@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924715</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The 8th International Symposium on Data Assimilation will take place during the week of June 8th, 2020 in Ft. Collins, CO on the campus of Colorado State University.  An international group of scientists and students will come together to discuss ideas that are at the forefront of data assimilation research.  This award provides travel support for up to 7 students to attend the Symposium, present their research, and interact with researchers from various domestic and foreign institutions.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The main topics that will be discussed at the Symposium include:  1) Method Development and Mathematics of Data Assimilation, 2) Satellite Data Assimilation, 3) Error Covariance Estimation in Observations, State and Model, 4) Coupled Data Assimilation Developments, 5) Convective Scale Data Assimilation, 6) Atmospheric Chemistry and Aerosol Data Assimilation, 7) Emerging Applications of Data Assimilation, and 8) Machine Learning for Data Assimilation.  The presentations and posters will be hosted publicly, with permission, and there will be a summary article submitted to the Bulletin of the American Meteorological Society.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/12/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/12/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2011670</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Steven</FirstName>
<LastName>Fletcher</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Steven J Fletcher</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[fletcher@cira.colostate.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000493753</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/12/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Colorado State University</Name>
<CityName>FORT COLLINS</CityName>
<ZipCode>805212807</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9704916355</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>601 S HOWES ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>LT9CXX8L19G1</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>COLORADO STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>Q7VRM266G891</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Colorado State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Fort Collins</CityName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>805231375</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1375 Campus Delivery]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1525</Code>
<Text>Physical &amp; Dynamic Meteorology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~15581</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This award supported the air and local travel, per diem, and hotel expenses for four Ph.D. Students to attend the 8th International Symposium for Data Assimilation (ISDA) at the Canvas Stadium on Colorado State University's main campus in Fort Collins, Colorado, USA, between June 6th to June 10th 2022.</p> <p>By issuing these awards the four students were able to attend one of the world's leading data assimilation meetings, with scientists, professors, and students from all around the world attending.&nbsp; The meeting has previous been in Germany, the United Kingdom, and Japan and a rotational basis, and this was the first time it has been held in the United States.</p> <p>The symposium was held in a less formal setting, with lunch being provided each day to allow for discussions to continue from the different presentations, but also to allow students to sit with the world's leading data assimilation scientists and have constructive conversations with them.</p> <p>The original intention of this award was to provide support to both some international students and some domestic students to attend the symposium at the same location and at about the same time, in 2020 but due to COVID19 we were not able to host the meeting then.&nbsp; In 2021 there the every four years World Meteorological Organisation (WMO)'s data assimilation meeting took place, and the ISDA does not take place in the same year as this meeting.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/19/2022<br>      Modified by: Steven&nbsp;J&nbsp;Fletcher</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This award supported the air and local travel, per diem, and hotel expenses for four Ph.D. Students to attend the 8th International Symposium for Data Assimilation (ISDA) at the Canvas Stadium on Colorado State University's main campus in Fort Collins, Colorado, USA, between June 6th to June 10th 2022.  By issuing these awards the four students were able to attend one of the world's leading data assimilation meetings, with scientists, professors, and students from all around the world attending.  The meeting has previous been in Germany, the United Kingdom, and Japan and a rotational basis, and this was the first time it has been held in the United States.  The symposium was held in a less formal setting, with lunch being provided each day to allow for discussions to continue from the different presentations, but also to allow students to sit with the world's leading data assimilation scientists and have constructive conversations with them.  The original intention of this award was to provide support to both some international students and some domestic students to attend the symposium at the same location and at about the same time, in 2020 but due to COVID19 we were not able to host the meeting then.  In 2021 there the every four years World Meteorological Organisation (WMO)'s data assimilation meeting took place, and the ISDA does not take place in the same year as this meeting.       Last Modified: 10/19/2022       Submitted by: Steven J Fletcher]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
