<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Partial Support of the Board on Physics and Astronomy]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>171385.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>171385</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kathleen McCloud</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kmccloud@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928236</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This award provides partial core support to the Board on Physics and Astronomy (BPA). The physics and astronomy communities cover a broad and diverse set of research efforts. As a part of the National Academies, the BPA monitors developments and assesses the health of the fields that make up this area of research. Its membership is drawn from universities, industry, and national laboratories, and its members' areas of expertise span much of the breadth of physics and astronomy. The experts involved are broadly representative of the community, and they provide their informed perspectives on issues that affect the progress and vitality of physics and astronomy research. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The principal work to be supported by this award will be to support the board's semi-annual meetings as well as non-sponsored activities associated with the board's carrying out its responsibilities to support the physics and astronomy research communities. Another action will be the work on the next round of physics and astronomy/astrophysics decadal surveys. This award is co-funded by the Divisions of Physics, Astronomical Sciences, and Materials Research, within the Directorate for Mathematical and Physical Sciences.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/26/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/08/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2011625</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Lancaster</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>James C Lancaster</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jlancaster@nas.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000073938</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/26/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate>03/08/2022</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Colleen</FirstName>
<LastName>Hartman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>N</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Colleen N Hartman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[chartman@nas.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000830349</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/08/2022</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>National Academy of Sciences</Name>
<CityName>WASHINGTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>204180007</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2023342254</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2101 CONSTITUTION AVE NW</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>PKFJZHG2MLG9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NATIONAL ACADEMY OF SCIENCES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>PKFJZHG2MLG9</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[National Academies of Sciences, Engineering and Medicine]]></Name>
<CityName>Washingon,</CityName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>200012721</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[500 Fifth St., N.W.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1712</Code>
<Text>DMR SHORT TERM SUPPORT</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1798</Code>
<Text/>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9134</Code>
<Text>Integrative Activities in Phys</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~171385</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Since the dawn of human inquiry, scientists have been driven by a relentless pursuit of understanding the universe at both the smallest and largest scales. This quest for knowledge has been one of humanity's most ambitious and challenging endeavors, demanding substantial resources and talent from the United States and the global scientific community. In this context, it is essential for the scientific community and the institutions that provide and manage resources for scientific pursuits to receive prudent, science-based advice. The Board on Physics and Astronomy (BPA) fulfills this crucial role by offering critical and independent advice.</p> <p>To accomplish its objectives, the Board collaborates closely with various stakeholders, including the physics and astronomy communities in academia, national laboratories, and industry, as well as federal agencies and their advisory committees. It also engages with relevant scientific and technical societies and other boards and committees within the National Academies. The specific functions of the BPA encompass the following:</p> <ol> <li><strong>Monitoring the Health of Physics and Astronomy:</strong> BPA      continuously assesses the status of the physics and astronomy disciplines      to identify trends in research and track new developments at the      scientific forefront.</li> <li><strong>Assisting in Strategic Program Planning:</strong> BPA      actively seeks ways to support federal agencies in their strategic program      planning efforts, ensuring that scientific endeavors align with national      priorities.</li> <li><strong>Fostering Interdisciplinary Interactions:</strong> Recognizing the interconnectedness of various scientific fields, BPA      encourages interactions and cooperation among academic disciplines to      foster holistic and innovative research.</li> <li><strong>Strengthening Connections to Technology:</strong> BPA      emphasizes the importance of integrating advancements in technology with      physics and astronomy research, propelling the boundaries of scientific      discovery.</li> <li><strong>Enhancing Public Understanding of Science:</strong> Recognizing the significance of public support, BPA endeavors to improve      public understanding of scientific advancements and their impact on      society.</li> <li><strong>Overseeing Standing and Discipline Committees:</strong> BPA      supervises several standing and discipline committees responsible for      assessing the progress of various subfields and responding to federal      agency requests or needs.</li> <li><strong>Promoting Collaboration Among Research Entities:</strong> BPA      actively encourages collaboration among federal agencies, government      laboratories, and universities involved in physics and astronomy research,      fostering a robust research ecosystem.</li> </ol> <p>The Board on Physics and Astronomy plays a vital role in shaping the trajectory of scientific progress in the United States. By providing informed advice and fostering collaboration among stakeholders, BPA ensures that the nation remains at the forefront of scientific innovation, tackling the most pressing questions about the universe and its mysteries.</p> <p>Since&nbsp; 2019, BPA has published high-impact studies, including:</p> <ul> <li>Fundamental Research in High Energy Density Science, 2023</li> <li>Analysis of Potential Interference Issues Related to FCC Order 20-48, 2023</li> <li>Views of the U.S. National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine on Agenda Items at Issue at the World Radiocommunication Conference 2023</li> <li>Physics of Life, 2022</li> <li>Frontiers in Synthetic Moir? Quantum Matter, Condensed Matter and Materials Research Committee (CMMRC), 2022</li> <li>Pathways to Discovery in Astronomy and Astrophysics for the 2020s (?Astro 2020?), 2021</li> <li>Bringing Fusion to the U.S. Grid, 2021</li> <li>Plasma Science: Enabling Technology, Sustainability, Security, and Exploration, 2021</li> <li>Manipulating Quantum Systems: An Assessment of Atomic, Molecular, and Optical Physics in the United States, 2020</li> <li>Frontiers in Memristive Material for Neuromorphic Processing Applications, 2020</li> <li>Frontiers of Materials Research: A Decadal Survey, 2019</li> <li>Frontiers in Thermal Transport and Energy Conversion: Proceedings of a Workshop, 2019</li> <li>Burning Plasma Research, 2019</li> </ul> <p>BPA standing committees published the following short reports or filings:</p> <ul> <li>Committee on Radio Frequencies (CORF) FCC Filings in 2023 alone:         <ul> <li>In the Matter of Single Network Future: Supplemental Coverage from Space Innovation, filed with the FCC May 2023</li> <li>In the Matter of Amendment of Part 90 of the Commission?s Rules, filed with the FCC in April 2023</li> <li>In the Matter of Spectrum Rules and Policies for the Operation of WT Docket No. 22-323 Unmanned Aircraft Systems Petition of AIA for Rulemaking to Adopt Service RM-11798 (terminated) Rules for Unmanned Aircraft Systems Command) and Control in the 5030-5091MHz Band, filed with the FCC, March 2023</li> <li>In the Matter of Expediting Initial Processing of Satellite Space Innovation, filed with the FCC, March 2023.</li> </ul> </li> </ul> <p>All CORF filings may be found at: <a href="https://app.smartsheet.com/b/publish?EQBCT=834bd6edb47748fabed372eead9eeea2">https://app.smartsheet.com/b/publish?EQBCT=834bd6edb47748fabed372eead9eeea2</a></p> <ul> <li>Roman Space Telescope Observing Time Allocation Principles, Committee on Astronomy and Astrophysics (CAA), 2022</li> </ul> <p>As BPA looks ahead to the future, it is driven by a profound sense of purpose and a deep commitment to enhancing the landscape of physics and astronomy research. With an exciting suite of upcoming initiatives and a dynamic team ready to tackle challenges, BPA is poised to trailblaze new paths of discovery, leaving an indelible mark on the scientific landscape. By continuing to forge new vistas and embrace opportunities, BPA is steadfast in its resolve to push the boundaries of knowledge, unravel the mysteries of the cosmos, and pave the way for a brighter and more enlightened future.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/31/2023<br>      Modified by: Colleen&nbsp;N&nbsp;Hartman</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Since the dawn of human inquiry, scientists have been driven by a relentless pursuit of understanding the universe at both the smallest and largest scales. This quest for knowledge has been one of humanity's most ambitious and challenging endeavors, demanding substantial resources and talent from the United States and the global scientific community. In this context, it is essential for the scientific community and the institutions that provide and manage resources for scientific pursuits to receive prudent, science-based advice. The Board on Physics and Astronomy (BPA) fulfills this crucial role by offering critical and independent advice.  To accomplish its objectives, the Board collaborates closely with various stakeholders, including the physics and astronomy communities in academia, national laboratories, and industry, as well as federal agencies and their advisory committees. It also engages with relevant scientific and technical societies and other boards and committees within the National Academies. The specific functions of the BPA encompass the following:  Monitoring the Health of Physics and Astronomy: BPA      continuously assesses the status of the physics and astronomy disciplines      to identify trends in research and track new developments at the      scientific forefront. Assisting in Strategic Program Planning: BPA      actively seeks ways to support federal agencies in their strategic program      planning efforts, ensuring that scientific endeavors align with national      priorities. Fostering Interdisciplinary Interactions: Recognizing the interconnectedness of various scientific fields, BPA      encourages interactions and cooperation among academic disciplines to      foster holistic and innovative research. Strengthening Connections to Technology: BPA      emphasizes the importance of integrating advancements in technology with      physics and astronomy research, propelling the boundaries of scientific      discovery. Enhancing Public Understanding of Science: Recognizing the significance of public support, BPA endeavors to improve      public understanding of scientific advancements and their impact on      society. Overseeing Standing and Discipline Committees: BPA      supervises several standing and discipline committees responsible for      assessing the progress of various subfields and responding to federal      agency requests or needs. Promoting Collaboration Among Research Entities: BPA      actively encourages collaboration among federal agencies, government      laboratories, and universities involved in physics and astronomy research,      fostering a robust research ecosystem.   The Board on Physics and Astronomy plays a vital role in shaping the trajectory of scientific progress in the United States. By providing informed advice and fostering collaboration among stakeholders, BPA ensures that the nation remains at the forefront of scientific innovation, tackling the most pressing questions about the universe and its mysteries.  Since  2019, BPA has published high-impact studies, including:  Fundamental Research in High Energy Density Science, 2023 Analysis of Potential Interference Issues Related to FCC Order 20-48, 2023 Views of the U.S. National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine on Agenda Items at Issue at the World Radiocommunication Conference 2023 Physics of Life, 2022 Frontiers in Synthetic Moir? Quantum Matter, Condensed Matter and Materials Research Committee (CMMRC), 2022 Pathways to Discovery in Astronomy and Astrophysics for the 2020s (?Astro 2020?), 2021 Bringing Fusion to the U.S. Grid, 2021 Plasma Science: Enabling Technology, Sustainability, Security, and Exploration, 2021 Manipulating Quantum Systems: An Assessment of Atomic, Molecular, and Optical Physics in the United States, 2020 Frontiers in Memristive Material for Neuromorphic Processing Applications, 2020 Frontiers of Materials Research: A Decadal Survey, 2019 Frontiers in Thermal Transport and Energy Conversion: Proceedings of a Workshop, 2019 Burning Plasma Research, 2019   BPA standing committees published the following short reports or filings:  Committee on Radio Frequencies (CORF) FCC Filings in 2023 alone:          In the Matter of Single Network Future: Supplemental Coverage from Space Innovation, filed with the FCC May 2023 In the Matter of Amendment of Part 90 of the Commission?s Rules, filed with the FCC in April 2023 In the Matter of Spectrum Rules and Policies for the Operation of WT Docket No. 22-323 Unmanned Aircraft Systems Petition of AIA for Rulemaking to Adopt Service RM-11798 (terminated) Rules for Unmanned Aircraft Systems Command) and Control in the 5030-5091MHz Band, filed with the FCC, March 2023 In the Matter of Expediting Initial Processing of Satellite Space Innovation, filed with the FCC, March 2023.     All CORF filings may be found at: https://app.smartsheet.com/b/publish?EQBCT=834bd6edb47748fabed372eead9eeea2  Roman Space Telescope Observing Time Allocation Principles, Committee on Astronomy and Astrophysics (CAA), 2022   As BPA looks ahead to the future, it is driven by a profound sense of purpose and a deep commitment to enhancing the landscape of physics and astronomy research. With an exciting suite of upcoming initiatives and a dynamic team ready to tackle challenges, BPA is poised to trailblaze new paths of discovery, leaving an indelible mark on the scientific landscape. By continuing to forge new vistas and embrace opportunities, BPA is steadfast in its resolve to push the boundaries of knowledge, unravel the mysteries of the cosmos, and pave the way for a brighter and more enlightened future.       Last Modified: 10/31/2023       Submitted by: Colleen N Hartman]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
