<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Conference: Plant Cell Biology International 2020; June 1-5, 2020, Kolympari, Crete]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>49000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>49000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>MCB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Charles Cunningham</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>chacunni@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922283</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[There is a strong need to develop the knowledge base that will enable rational design of improved crop species. To attain this goal, researchers must learn how plant cells integrate metabolism, cytoskeletal organization, and vesicle trafficking during growth and in response to environmental challenges. The first Plant Cell Biology International (PCBI) meeting capitalizes on the interaction between two well-established plant cell biology communities across the Atlantic, the Midwest Plant Cell Dynamics (PCD) and the European Network for Plant Endomembrane Research (ENPER) groups and provides a framework to meet these goals. The focus of this meeting is unique, and features workshops centered on designing an image acquisition and processing pipeline for multi-scale analysis of cellular systems and international collaborations. Keynote speakers for the 2020 meeting are recognized world experts in organelle dynamics and endomembrane trafficking. All participants will network, have the opportunity to present posters, and many early career scientists will have opportunities for oral presentations. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;There is a growing core of plant cell biologists who seek to better understand the underlying mechanisms of organelle and cell dynamics, and share similar technical challenges to meet their research goals. It’s important to find the most effective ways to employ combinations of quantitative imaging techniques, biochemical techniques, and computational tools to gain a mechanistic understanding of plant cellular systems. Meeting these goals will require data sharing and the development and training of faculty, post-doctoral fellows, graduate and undergraduate students in state-of-the-art quantitative cell biology methods. The first Plant Cell Biology International (PCBI) meeting will 1) advance intellectual exchange and longer term collaborations between US- and Europe-based laboratories, 2) enhance the cultural understanding of next generation of innovators in both continents, 3) provide the opportunity for plant cell biologist to discuss their latest research, develop collaborations, and 4) promote the development of new tools that will accelerate mechanistic analyses of cell dynamics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/06/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/22/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2011965</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
<LastName>Szymanski</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Daniel B Szymanski</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[szymandb@purdue.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000318381</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/06/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Marcela</FirstName>
<LastName>Pierce</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Marcela Pierce</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mrojasp@ncsu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000497250</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/06/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Georgia</FirstName>
<LastName>Drakakaki</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Georgia Drakakaki</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[gdrakakaki@ucdavis.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000561392</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/06/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Davis</Name>
<CityName>DAVIS</CityName>
<ZipCode>956186153</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5307547700</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1850 RESEARCH PARK DR, STE 300</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>TX2DAGQPENZ5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, DAVIS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>NUDGYLBB4S99</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Davis]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>956186153</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1114</Code>
<Text>Cellular Dynamics and Function</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7465</Code>
<Text>NANOSCALE BIO CORE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~49000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The first Plant Cell Biology International (PCBI) meeting capitalized on the interaction between two well-established plant cell biology communities across the Atlantic, the Midwest Plant Cell Dynamics (PCD) and the European Network for Plant Endomembrane Research (ENPER). PCBI&nbsp; provided a framework to better understand the underlying mechanisms of organelle and cell dynamics, and gain a mechanistic understanding of plant cellular systems. The conference successfully took place in person during August 1-5th 2022 at the Orthodox Academy of Crete in Kolympari, Crete, Greece.</p> <p>The conference offered opportunities for undergraduate and graduate students, postdocs and young investigators to present their results and interact across different disciplines. Labs participated from USA, South America, Europe, UK, Israel and Hong-Kong despite being held during recovery of the COVID pandemic. Successfully, there was not a single incident of a&nbsp; positive COVID&nbsp; incident during the meeting. The Orthodox Academy of Crete was an excellent location and venue to hold this joint meeting. The location was in good proximity in many countries both part of EU but also Africa and Middle East, thus being a strategic hub for an international meeting,&nbsp; offering a natural environment for scientific exchange.</p> <p>There was a total of 110 registered&nbsp; participants at the meeting.</p> <p>Travel fellowships enabled the participation of undergraduate, graduate students, postdocs and young investigators with&nbsp; several&nbsp; awardees self-reporting as members of underrepresented groups.</p> <p>Participants engaged in a workshop led by Jesse Aaron (Janelia Research Campus) focused on designing image acquisition, processing and reporting pipelines.</p> <p>Students and postdocs presented their results in oral format or poster sessions while they received feedback from experts in the field, leading to new collaborations. Students and postdocs also led/moderated the conference sessions.</p> <p>Resources for Mental Health and Wellness in Science were introduced by Professor&nbsp; Carolyn Dewa, UC Davis, in order to enhance resilience in the Community of Plant Cell Biologists.</p> <p>The conference provided an open and inclusive forum for oral presentations that allowed all labs to share research results. Over 80 % of conference attendees were students, postdocs and young investigators. Student and post-doc presentations were geared toward the application of existing strategies for plant cell studies, the development of new methodologies, and data interpretation to understand the fundamental mechanisms of plant cellular dynamics.</p> <p>Workshops centered on best practices for image acquisition and processing pipelines in order to improve the quality of acquired data and their publication.</p> <p>Workshops on professional development such as wellbeing and publication practices, by scientific journal editors benefited the participants at large.</p> <p>The presentation by the NSF, on opportunities for international collaborations informed the participants on funding opportunities and avenues that can support international partnerships.</p> <p>Overall, this was the inaugural international joint Plant Cell Biology conference that for the first time officially brought together plant cell biologists. Due to its success, it was rescheduled for 2025 at the OAC in Crete, to continue strengthening the plant cell biology community and exchanging knowledge and expertise across the globe.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/27/2023<br>      Modified by: Georgia&nbsp;Drakakaki</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The first Plant Cell Biology International (PCBI) meeting capitalized on the interaction between two well-established plant cell biology communities across the Atlantic, the Midwest Plant Cell Dynamics (PCD) and the European Network for Plant Endomembrane Research (ENPER). PCBI  provided a framework to better understand the underlying mechanisms of organelle and cell dynamics, and gain a mechanistic understanding of plant cellular systems. The conference successfully took place in person during August 1-5th 2022 at the Orthodox Academy of Crete in Kolympari, Crete, Greece.  The conference offered opportunities for undergraduate and graduate students, postdocs and young investigators to present their results and interact across different disciplines. Labs participated from USA, South America, Europe, UK, Israel and Hong-Kong despite being held during recovery of the COVID pandemic. Successfully, there was not a single incident of a  positive COVID  incident during the meeting. The Orthodox Academy of Crete was an excellent location and venue to hold this joint meeting. The location was in good proximity in many countries both part of EU but also Africa and Middle East, thus being a strategic hub for an international meeting,  offering a natural environment for scientific exchange.  There was a total of 110 registered  participants at the meeting.  Travel fellowships enabled the participation of undergraduate, graduate students, postdocs and young investigators with  several  awardees self-reporting as members of underrepresented groups.  Participants engaged in a workshop led by Jesse Aaron (Janelia Research Campus) focused on designing image acquisition, processing and reporting pipelines.  Students and postdocs presented their results in oral format or poster sessions while they received feedback from experts in the field, leading to new collaborations. Students and postdocs also led/moderated the conference sessions.  Resources for Mental Health and Wellness in Science were introduced by Professor  Carolyn Dewa, UC Davis, in order to enhance resilience in the Community of Plant Cell Biologists.  The conference provided an open and inclusive forum for oral presentations that allowed all labs to share research results. Over 80 % of conference attendees were students, postdocs and young investigators. Student and post-doc presentations were geared toward the application of existing strategies for plant cell studies, the development of new methodologies, and data interpretation to understand the fundamental mechanisms of plant cellular dynamics.  Workshops centered on best practices for image acquisition and processing pipelines in order to improve the quality of acquired data and their publication.  Workshops on professional development such as wellbeing and publication practices, by scientific journal editors benefited the participants at large.  The presentation by the NSF, on opportunities for international collaborations informed the participants on funding opportunities and avenues that can support international partnerships.  Overall, this was the inaugural international joint Plant Cell Biology conference that for the first time officially brought together plant cell biologists. Due to its success, it was rescheduled for 2025 at the OAC in Crete, to continue strengthening the plant cell biology community and exchanging knowledge and expertise across the globe.       Last Modified: 06/27/2023       Submitted by: Georgia Drakakaki]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
