<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research: Adaptive, Multi-Layered Fenestration Elements for Optimum Building Energy Performance and Occupant Comfort]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>11/12/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>174990.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>174494</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Gianluca Cusatis</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>gcusatis@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925026</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[As buildings work towards reducing energy demands, while maintaining a both thermally and visually comfortable environment for occupants, fenestrations (i.e. windows) are a key influential component in this effort. Fenestrations allow for natural daylight and outdoor views, but also represent the least thermally efficient portion of the building envelope, as well as a source of unwanted discomfort glare and direct sunlight. A multi-layered, dynamically-operated fenestration system that can be installed in new buildings or retrofitted for an existing building will address building energy use and occupant comfort needs under a diverse range of climate conditions. The project will explore the theoretical and practical challenges for the building industry to develop a model for the performance of dynamic fenestration designs to enhance building energy sustainability and human health.  To encourage exchanging of ideas internationally, the research team will collaborate with European colleagues through the European Commission Horizon 2020 PLUG-N-HARVEST project. In addition, instructional and interdisciplinary research opportunities will be provided for graduate and undergraduate students of civil, mechanical, and materials engineering to serve a vital need, particularly from existing buildings.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research will lay the theoretical and practical foundations for the intelligent control and operations of smart and energy efficient fenestrations by developing an adaptive, multi-layered solution. This includes: (a) a dual-band, continuous-state electrochromic glazing applied to the window exterior in a matrix pattern to enable localized control, (b) a motorized and dynamically-operated shading device, and (c) a novel, multi-physics model-based adaptive control framework, with the goal of balancing a range of building energy consumption and occupant thermal and visual comfort priorities in real time. The exterior 2-dimensional electrochromic glazing array combined with a second dynamic layer on the fenestration interior provides the ability to address localized occupant visual comfort challenges, and allows for a broader range of capabilities to control solar heat gains, while addressing differences in occupant comfort criteria. The model framework solution will be tested and evaluated using simulations, and a full-scale testbed.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/06/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/20/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2011296</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Zheng</FirstName>
<LastName>O'Neill</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Zheng D O'Neill</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[zoneill@tamu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000643008</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/06/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Texas A&amp;M Engineering Experiment Station</Name>
<CityName>COLLEGE STATION</CityName>
<ZipCode>778433124</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9798626777</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3124 TAMU</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>QD1MX6N5YTN4</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TEXAS A&amp;M ENGINEERING EXPERIMENT STATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>QD1MX6N5YTN4</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Texas A&M Engineering Experiment Station]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>778454645</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>073y</Code>
<Text>ECI-Engineering for Civil Infr</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1637</Code>
<Text>Structural and Architectural E</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1642</Code>
<Text>Special Initiatives</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>036E</Code>
<Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>039E</Code>
<Text>STRUCTURAL SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>052Z</Code>
<Text>ArchEng Architectural Engineering</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>091Z</Code>
<Text>Data Initiatives</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1057</Code>
<Text>CIS BASE RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>CVIS</Code>
<Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01001819DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~139502</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~34992</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>As buildings work towards reducing energy demands while maintaining a both thermally and visually comfortable environment for occupants, a key influential component of buildings that can significantly impact these goals is the fenestrations (i.e., windows). Today, most windows are static elements with constant thermal and optical properties. Yet, depending on occupant preferences, exterior climate conditions, and associated solar angles, the ideal fenestration properties can vary significantly. In this project, we investigated the use of an adaptive, multi-layered solution, which enhances both optical and thermal properties of existing buildings? fenestrations. Such systems include (a) a dual-band, continuous-state electrochromic glazing applied to the window exterior in a matrix pattern to enable localized control, and (b) a motorized and dynamically-operated shading device. The intelligent control and operation of this fenestration system is optimized through a novel, multi-physics model-based adaptive control framework, with the goal of balancing a range of building energy consumption and occupant thermal and visual comfort priorities in real-time. In addition, research results have been disseminated to the community through journal and conference papers. One Ph.D. researcher was trained in this project.</p> <p>This project developed an adaptive control framework for the advanced fenestration system in conjunction with a controllable electric lighting system and Heating, Ventilation, and Air Conditioning (HVAC) system. The studied fenestration systems have an adjustable blind and dynamic electrochromic (EC) glazing element. This control framework aims to reduce building energy demands while maintaining a thermally and visually comfortable environment for occupants. We first generated a workflow of the control-oriented model development. This workflow consists of three phases. In phase one, a co-simulation model using EnergyPlus (a whole-building energy performance simulator) and Radiance (a daylighting simulator) is constructed and used as an online virtual testbed. In phase two, a system dynamics excitation process is performed, which aims to fully excite the systems' reactions to different weather conditions and control inputs. In phase 3, an offline data-driven model training is used to develop forecasting models for thermal performance, lighting performance, and power consumption of the building with the proposed adaptive fenestration systems.</p> <p>We exploited a model-based optimal control approach for the building with the proposed adaptive fenestration systems. The control variables for this system include the supply air temperature setpoint of the variable air volume system, the power input of the artificial lighting, the state of the electrochromic glazing, and the slat angle and position of the blinds. This model-based control works as follows. At each time step, an optimizer is employed to compute the optimal control inputs for the next timestep, which aims to minimize the system cost while maintaining thermal and visual comforts. Then, these control inputs obtained are applied to the virtual testbed, and the operating results using the virtual testbed will then be fed back to the control-oriented models for next-step predictions. This process will continue until the end of the current simulation period. This control method can provide significant benefits to the building: daylight utilization can be optimized, and the operating cost of the building can be saved by reducing the demand for artificial lighting and spacing heating. Compared to the baseline case, approximately more than 20% cost savings can be achieved.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/27/2022<br>      Modified by: Zheng&nbsp;D&nbsp;O'neill</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2011296/2011296_10547551_1666905000628_Figure1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2011296/2011296_10547551_1666905000628_Figure1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 1"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2011296/2011296_10547551_1666905000628_Figure1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 1"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The workflow of the control-oriented model development</div> <div class="imageCredit">Feng Fan, Zheng O'Neill</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Zheng&nbsp;D&nbsp;O'neill</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 1</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2011296/2011296_10547551_1666910655832_Picture_2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2011296/2011296_10547551_1666910655832_Picture_2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 2"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2011296/2011296_10547551_1666910655832_Picture_2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 2"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Control architecture of the building with both fenestration and heating, ventilation and air-conditioning (HVAC) systems (T: temperature, RH: relative humidity, ZMAT: zone mean air temperature, SP: setpoint, EC: electrochromic, BSDF: Bidirectional Scattering Distribution Function from Radiance)</div> <div class="imageCredit">Feng Fan, Zheng O'Neill</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Zheng&nbsp;D&nbsp;O'neill</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 2</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2011296/2011296_10547551_1666910691958_Figure3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2011296/2011296_10547551_1666910691958_Figure3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 3"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2011296/2011296_10547551_1666910691958_Figure3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 3"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Comparisons of performance from the optimal controller and the baseline controller in a building with an adaptive fenestration system (one day)</div> <div class="imageCredit">Feng Fan, Zheng O'Neill</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Zheng&nbsp;D&nbsp;O'neill</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 3</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ As buildings work towards reducing energy demands while maintaining a both thermally and visually comfortable environment for occupants, a key influential component of buildings that can significantly impact these goals is the fenestrations (i.e., windows). Today, most windows are static elements with constant thermal and optical properties. Yet, depending on occupant preferences, exterior climate conditions, and associated solar angles, the ideal fenestration properties can vary significantly. In this project, we investigated the use of an adaptive, multi-layered solution, which enhances both optical and thermal properties of existing buildings? fenestrations. Such systems include (a) a dual-band, continuous-state electrochromic glazing applied to the window exterior in a matrix pattern to enable localized control, and (b) a motorized and dynamically-operated shading device. The intelligent control and operation of this fenestration system is optimized through a novel, multi-physics model-based adaptive control framework, with the goal of balancing a range of building energy consumption and occupant thermal and visual comfort priorities in real-time. In addition, research results have been disseminated to the community through journal and conference papers. One Ph.D. researcher was trained in this project.  This project developed an adaptive control framework for the advanced fenestration system in conjunction with a controllable electric lighting system and Heating, Ventilation, and Air Conditioning (HVAC) system. The studied fenestration systems have an adjustable blind and dynamic electrochromic (EC) glazing element. This control framework aims to reduce building energy demands while maintaining a thermally and visually comfortable environment for occupants. We first generated a workflow of the control-oriented model development. This workflow consists of three phases. In phase one, a co-simulation model using EnergyPlus (a whole-building energy performance simulator) and Radiance (a daylighting simulator) is constructed and used as an online virtual testbed. In phase two, a system dynamics excitation process is performed, which aims to fully excite the systems' reactions to different weather conditions and control inputs. In phase 3, an offline data-driven model training is used to develop forecasting models for thermal performance, lighting performance, and power consumption of the building with the proposed adaptive fenestration systems.  We exploited a model-based optimal control approach for the building with the proposed adaptive fenestration systems. The control variables for this system include the supply air temperature setpoint of the variable air volume system, the power input of the artificial lighting, the state of the electrochromic glazing, and the slat angle and position of the blinds. This model-based control works as follows. At each time step, an optimizer is employed to compute the optimal control inputs for the next timestep, which aims to minimize the system cost while maintaining thermal and visual comforts. Then, these control inputs obtained are applied to the virtual testbed, and the operating results using the virtual testbed will then be fed back to the control-oriented models for next-step predictions. This process will continue until the end of the current simulation period. This control method can provide significant benefits to the building: daylight utilization can be optimized, and the operating cost of the building can be saved by reducing the demand for artificial lighting and spacing heating. Compared to the baseline case, approximately more than 20% cost savings can be achieved.             Last Modified: 10/27/2022       Submitted by: Zheng D O'neill]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
