<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Catalyst Award: Enhancing the Academic Infrastructure in Biology at FVSU by Enriching Course Offerings and Faculty Development]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>199999.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>199999</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div. of Equity for Excellence in STEM</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Carleitta Paige-Anderson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cpaigean@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922816</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Catalyst Projects provide support for Historically Black Colleges and Universities to work towards establishing research capacity of faculty to strengthen science, technology, engineering and mathematics undergraduate education and research. It is expected that the award will further the faculty member's research capability, improve research and teaching at the institution. and involve undergraduate students in research experiences. This project at Fort Valley State will redesign three biology courses. Students at Fort Valley State University will be provided undergraduate research opportunities and learn scientific communication. FVSU faculty will be able to enhance their teaching techniques by participating in training workshops. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Fort Valley State University proposes to enhance the academic infrastructure in biology to meet the increasing demand for minority scientists to pursue careers in clinical and laboratory research. The curricula in three upper-division courses will be revised with an emphasis on integrating modern concepts in biotechnology. This will be accomplished by employing constructivist pedagogy, integration of course-based research experiences (CUREs), and cyber-instruction. The practice of active learning is likely to build student’s core competencies- application of the process of science, quantitative reasoning, effective communication, collaboration, appreciation for the interdisciplinary nature of science, and mastery in scientific communication skills. Through active engagement, students will make meaningful connections, gain multiple perspectives on modern-day-science leading to improved critical learning and problem-solving skills, and thus will be better prepared for the 21st-century skills.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/06/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/06/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2011847</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Seema</FirstName>
<LastName>Dhir</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Seema Dhir</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[Dhirs@fvsu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000252771</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/06/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Celia</FirstName>
<LastName>Dodd</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Celia Dodd</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[doddc@fvsu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000667599</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/06/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kaneatra</FirstName>
<LastName>Simmons</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kaneatra J Simmons</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[kaneatra.simmons@fvsu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000806853</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/06/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Fort Valley State University</Name>
<CityName>FORT VALLEY</CityName>
<ZipCode>310304313</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4788256253</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1005 STATE UNIVERSITY DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>LVDJS9UYPLD4</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>FORT VALLEY STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>LVDJS9UYPLD4</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Fort Valley State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Fort Valley</CityName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>310304313</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1005 State University Dr]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1594</Code>
<Text>Hist Black Colleges and Univ</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0420</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~199999</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The project aim was to implement evidence-based practices in three upper-division biology courses. It was accomplished by redesigning the curricula through the implementation of course-based undergraduate research experiences (CUREs) and by integrating a scientific communication component to promote undergraduate research and enhance students? experiences in professional settings. To further develop students? hands-on research experience, STEM faculty members hosted and attended two three-four days long hands-on training workshops on Gene Editing clustered regularly interspaced short palindromic repeats (CRISPR/Cas9) technology including the Bootcamp. To enhance the competitiveness of our students for graduate school or STEM workforce we offered mentored research opportunities during the academic year and summer, interaction with invited speakers, and travel opportunities to attend scientific conferences. Other activities include a seminar series, professional and career development workshops, GRE preparation classes, and field trips to various labs.</p> <p>The grant supported enhanced educational experiences for over 185 students in classroom and research labs.&nbsp; Student presentations at research conferences such as ERN, ABRCMS, SOT, and Annual Research Day at FVSU were instrumental in bolstering students? confidence and increasing the competitiveness of our graduates in the STEM discipline. Student survey results indicated positive responses to newly developed laboratory exercises. Highlights of students? achievements in the labs and undergraduate research experience were disseminated in nine articles on the FVSU website.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/03/2023<br>      Modified by: Seema&nbsp;Dhir</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The project aim was to implement evidence-based practices in three upper-division biology courses. It was accomplished by redesigning the curricula through the implementation of course-based undergraduate research experiences (CUREs) and by integrating a scientific communication component to promote undergraduate research and enhance students? experiences in professional settings. To further develop students? hands-on research experience, STEM faculty members hosted and attended two three-four days long hands-on training workshops on Gene Editing clustered regularly interspaced short palindromic repeats (CRISPR/Cas9) technology including the Bootcamp. To enhance the competitiveness of our students for graduate school or STEM workforce we offered mentored research opportunities during the academic year and summer, interaction with invited speakers, and travel opportunities to attend scientific conferences. Other activities include a seminar series, professional and career development workshops, GRE preparation classes, and field trips to various labs.  The grant supported enhanced educational experiences for over 185 students in classroom and research labs.  Student presentations at research conferences such as ERN, ABRCMS, SOT, and Annual Research Day at FVSU were instrumental in bolstering students? confidence and increasing the competitiveness of our graduates in the STEM discipline. Student survey results indicated positive responses to newly developed laboratory exercises. Highlights of students? achievements in the labs and undergraduate research experience were disseminated in nine articles on the FVSU website.          Last Modified: 08/03/2023       Submitted by: Seema Dhir]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
