<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RUI: Calculation of Higher Order Corrections to Positronium Energy Levels]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>150000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>150000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Robert Forrey</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rforrey@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925199</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Positronium is the bound system consisting of the electron and its antiparticle, the positron.  As such, it forms an “exotic atom”, similar in many ways to traditional simple atoms such as hydrogen and helium, but different because of its unique composition and because of its tendency to annihilate, transforming into pure electromagnetic energy in the form of high-energy photons.  Many properties of positronium, such as energy levels and lifetimes, are accessible to high-precision experiments.  Positronium properties can also be calculated theoretically to high precision using the methods of bound-state Quantum Electrodynamics (QED) because strong and weak interaction effects are negligible.  Consequently, positronium is an ideal system for testing the limits of QED bound state physics and for exploring the consequences of agreement or disagreement between theory and experiment at this high level of precision.  The activities involved in calculating the positronium energy levels will be of great educational value to the undergraduate students at Franklin &amp; Marshall College involved as collaborators in that work. The students will learn theoretical methods and techniques of calculation more advanced than those usually encountered at the undergraduate level.  They will gain valuable experience by doing the research, by presenting their results at professional meetings, and by publishing their work as co-authors in research journals.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;Positronium energy levels of low-lying states (n=1 and n=2) have been measured with uncertainties of roughly 1 MHz, and experiments are presently being developed and performed to significantly reduce some of these uncertainties.  The 1S-2S transition is of particular interest because it has the smallest natural line-width and thus the greatest potential for improvement.  These transition energies and more will be calculated to a new and higher level of precision.  The calculations will be based on the low-energy effective quantum field theory NRQED (Non-Relativistic QED), which provides a natural and efficient framework for the study of non-relativistic atoms such as positronium.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/12/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/12/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2011762</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gregory</FirstName>
<LastName>Adkins</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gregory S Adkins</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[greg.adkins@fandm.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000470032</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/12/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Franklin and Marshall College</Name>
<CityName>LANCASTER</CityName>
<ZipCode>176032827</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7173584517</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>415 HARRISBURG AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>11</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA11</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>P4NXVGAJNQK3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>FRANKLIN AND MARSHALL COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>P4NXVGAJNQK3</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Franklin and Marshall College]]></Name>
<CityName>Lancaster</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>176043003</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[415 Harrisburg Ave, PO Box 3003]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>11</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA11</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1284</Code>
<Text>AMO Theory/Atomic, Molecular &amp;</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9229</Code>
<Text>RES IN UNDERGRAD INST-RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~150000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Positronium, the electron-positron bound state, is arguably the simplest bound system.&nbsp; Its constituents have no known internal structure.&nbsp; Their low mass means that the eventual annihilation of this matter--antimatter "exotic atom" will be exclusively to photons or, rarely, neutrinos.&nbsp; The relative simplicity of the positronium system makes it attractive for testing our understanding of bound state theory.&nbsp; At the same time, positronium is accessible to high-precision experiments.&nbsp; The detailed comparison between experimental measurements of energy intervals and decay rates with the corresponding results of theoretical calculations provides an important test of the formalism of bound-state quantum field theory and the limits of fundamental theory.</p> <p><br />The specific scientific goal of this grant was to compute corrections to the energy levels of positronium at order alpha^7 in the fine structure constant alpha.&nbsp; Complete results for these corrections will be essential when ongoing and proposed higher-precision experimental measurements of various positronium transition energies are available in order to understand the consequences of the measured results.&nbsp; Comparison between theory and experiment for the 2S-1S transition energy could provide a pure-QED value of the Rydberg constant of comparable precision to the 2018 CODATA value.&nbsp; It would also provide a new best value for the electron-positron mass ratio, which is a test of CPT.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p><br />Some of the methods used for the evaluation of the complicated multi-loop Feynman integrals required for our work were initially developed for high-energy particle physics calculations.&nbsp; It turns out that it can be easier to evaluate corrections for systems with two different masses such as muonium (with an electron and a muon) than for single-mass systems such as positronium.&nbsp; (The positronium results can then be obtained by taking the limit that the masses become equal.)&nbsp; Using these techniques, a new result was obtained for recoil corrections to muonium energies at order alpha^6 that is exact in the particle masses.&nbsp; This result gives an experimentally relevant correction to the muonium ground-state hyperfine interval.&nbsp; The same methods are being applied to the positronium calculations at order alpha^7 in ongoing work.</p> <p>The ideas and methods of this area of research were made available to the wider community through the publication of a monograph "Quantum Electrodynamics: Atoms, Lasers, and Gravity" that I co-authored with Ulrich Jentschura (published in 2022 by World Scientific) and a review article "Precision spectroscopy of positronium: testing bound-state QED theory and the search for physics beyond the Standard Model" that I wrote with David Cassidy and Jesus Perez-Rios (published in 2022 by Physics Reports).</p> <p>The activities involved in calculating positronium energy levels were of great educational value to the undergraduate students involved as collaborators in this work.&nbsp; The students gained valuable experience by doing the research, by presenting results to their peers in campus research fairs, and by publishing their work as co-authors.&nbsp; Five students were involved in the work supported by this grant, some for several years.&nbsp; Those who have graduated already will attend or plan to attend physics graduate school in the future.&nbsp; The specific techniques that the students learned in the course of this work are broadly applicable to research in a number of areas of physics, and the experience of being part of an extensive and challenging research effort will be useful to them in their future work in any area of study.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/29/2023<br>      Modified by: Gregory&nbsp;S&nbsp;Adkins</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Positronium, the electron-positron bound state, is arguably the simplest bound system.  Its constituents have no known internal structure.  Their low mass means that the eventual annihilation of this matter--antimatter "exotic atom" will be exclusively to photons or, rarely, neutrinos.  The relative simplicity of the positronium system makes it attractive for testing our understanding of bound state theory.  At the same time, positronium is accessible to high-precision experiments.  The detailed comparison between experimental measurements of energy intervals and decay rates with the corresponding results of theoretical calculations provides an important test of the formalism of bound-state quantum field theory and the limits of fundamental theory.   The specific scientific goal of this grant was to compute corrections to the energy levels of positronium at order alpha^7 in the fine structure constant alpha.  Complete results for these corrections will be essential when ongoing and proposed higher-precision experimental measurements of various positronium transition energies are available in order to understand the consequences of the measured results.  Comparison between theory and experiment for the 2S-1S transition energy could provide a pure-QED value of the Rydberg constant of comparable precision to the 2018 CODATA value.  It would also provide a new best value for the electron-positron mass ratio, which is a test of CPT.     Some of the methods used for the evaluation of the complicated multi-loop Feynman integrals required for our work were initially developed for high-energy particle physics calculations.  It turns out that it can be easier to evaluate corrections for systems with two different masses such as muonium (with an electron and a muon) than for single-mass systems such as positronium.  (The positronium results can then be obtained by taking the limit that the masses become equal.)  Using these techniques, a new result was obtained for recoil corrections to muonium energies at order alpha^6 that is exact in the particle masses.  This result gives an experimentally relevant correction to the muonium ground-state hyperfine interval.  The same methods are being applied to the positronium calculations at order alpha^7 in ongoing work.  The ideas and methods of this area of research were made available to the wider community through the publication of a monograph "Quantum Electrodynamics: Atoms, Lasers, and Gravity" that I co-authored with Ulrich Jentschura (published in 2022 by World Scientific) and a review article "Precision spectroscopy of positronium: testing bound-state QED theory and the search for physics beyond the Standard Model" that I wrote with David Cassidy and Jesus Perez-Rios (published in 2022 by Physics Reports).  The activities involved in calculating positronium energy levels were of great educational value to the undergraduate students involved as collaborators in this work.  The students gained valuable experience by doing the research, by presenting results to their peers in campus research fairs, and by publishing their work as co-authors.  Five students were involved in the work supported by this grant, some for several years.  Those who have graduated already will attend or plan to attend physics graduate school in the future.  The specific techniques that the students learned in the course of this work are broadly applicable to research in a number of areas of physics, and the experience of being part of an extensive and challenging research effort will be useful to them in their future work in any area of study.       Last Modified: 08/29/2023       Submitted by: Gregory S Adkins]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
