<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Structures, Dynamics, and Thermodynamics of Atomic Boson-Fermion Mixtures]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>178505.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>178505</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Robert Forrey</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rforrey@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925199</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Atomic mixtures are ubiquitous in our daily life. For example, air is a mixture of nitrogen, oxygen, and other ingredients. Cooling down the air leads to liquefaction, showing a typical example of structural transitions in multi-species mixtures. The microscopic world governed by quantum physics contains mixtures of quantum particles that exhibit many exotic phenomena awaiting our exploration. There are two types of atoms in the universe, bosons and fermions. They differ by their peer-interactions: bosons tends to congregate in the quantum regime while fermions stay away from each other. Questions about the physics of a quantum mixture of both bosons and fermions have fascinated scientists for decades. Helium atoms have offered a platform for exploring quantum mixtures, however, the systems are complicated by the complex atomic interactions and challenging experiments. Nevertheless, recent advances in cooling, trapping, and manipulating atoms have successfully produced boson-fermion quantum mixtures and renewed research interest in such systems. The proposed research will investigate the structures, thermodynamics, and dynamics of the novel atomic boson-fermion mixtures. Explicitly, the research will deliver (1) a full theory of the of quantum boson-fermion mixtures, allowing a detailed analysis of the system in and out of equilibrium, (2) a description of how bosons and fermions push each other to form a homogeneous mixture like air or a separation like oil in water, and (3) an exploration and prediction of the dynamics of quantum boson-fermion mixtures driven across the different structures. Moreover, while the quantum mixtures realized by different experimental research groups are confined in different geometries, the proposed research will extract the universal behavior and elucidate the underlying mechanism. The results will reveal the novel structures and dynamics of quantum boson-fermion mixtures and advance our understanding of the many-body physics behind composite quantum systems. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The rapid developments of trapping and manipulating multi-species atomic mixtures have made the investigation of boson-fermion mixtures an important and urgent task, and the research will deliver a timely description of the structures and dynamics of the mixtures. The phase diagrams of atomic mixtures in uniform or harmonic potentials from the framework developed in the research based on quantum field theories will explain the current and future experimental data and guide the investigations of critical phenomena in multi-species quantum systems. The simulations and analysis of the spatial structures of the mixtures will demonstrate the extraction of critical exponents from a phase-separated structure in equilibrium, and the analysis of the quantum dynamics will reveal the influence of the fermions on the vortex formation in the bosonic superfluid. The breakdown of the scaling behavior in boson-fermion mixtures will reflect the first-order structural transition, and a comparison with the conventional analyses across a second-order phase transition will reveal the size of the critical regime. The research will establish collaborations with experimental groups to characterize the structures, thermodynamics, and dynamics of atomic boson-fermion mixtures across structural transitions in different trap geometries. The theoretical framework, simulations, and results will guide and explain experiments of atomic mixtures. To promote the research and advocate public learning, the PI will present public lectures to the local communities that have high populations of under-represented minorities and will recruit minority and women students to participate in the research and increase diversity.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/10/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/22/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2011360</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>CHIH CHUN</FirstName>
<LastName>CHIEN</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>CHIH CHUN CHIEN</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[cchien5@ucmerced.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000675732</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California - Merced</Name>
<CityName>MERCED</CityName>
<ZipCode>953435001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2092012039</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5200 N LAKE RD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>FFM7VPAG8P92</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, MERCED</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California - Merced]]></Name>
<CityName>Merced</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>953435001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5200 North Lake Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1284</Code>
<Text>AMO Theory/Atomic, Molecular &amp;</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002223DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~59572</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~66089</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2022~52844</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Atomic mixtures are ubiquitous. For example, air is a mixture of nitrogen and oxygen and exhibits complex behavior as temperature or pressure changes. Recent progress in cooling and controlling atoms in laboratories makes it an important task to investigate ultracold atomic mixtures in the quantum regime, and this is the goal of the project. The research began with a derivation of a general theoretical framework capable of describing the structures and thermodynamics of atomic mixtures, followed by a development of numerical simulation tools capable of capturing the complex behavior at low temperatures. When the framework is applied to binary mixtures of atoms with opposite statistical behavior, various mixed or separating structures were discovered as a result of a competition between kinetic and interaction energies. The interface separating different species reveals an interesting quantity known as the healing length as the species on both sides are forbidden to enter the opposite side and result in inhomogeneity. The phase diagrams of selected atomic mixtures from the research are shown in Figure 1, which shed light on future experimental investigations. Next, atomic mixtures of two superfluids of different nature are analyzed. Through a unified description developed in the research, different phenomena previously studied in superconductors and magnetic systems can be demonstrated by ultracold atoms acting as a versatile quantum simulator. Selected profiles of atomic superfluids from the research are shown in Figure 2, further showcasing the rich structures of atomix mixtures.</p> <p>By generalizing the theory to exotic geometries, such as the spherical bubble trap for atoms realized in the International Space Station, fundamental properties of atomic superfluids are shown in the research to be smoothly tunable by varying the size of the bubble trap. Moreover, the theoretical framework have been adapted to describe energy currents in quantum systems and electric currents in circuits, as illustrated in Figure 3. The generalization of the research uncovered exotic phenomena, such as local heat flow from cold to hot due to geometric effect and variation of electric current due to remnants of a symmetry. The results thus showcase the physics behind the interplay among strongly interacting quantum systems, atomic physics, computational physics, geometry, and topology.</p> <p>During the support of the award, two PhD students completed their degrees and four undergraudates submitted their senior honor theses based on the research under the supervision of the PI. Among those students, two are women and three are Hispanic, which demonstrates the effort to increase diversity in physics. The research results have been documented in 13 publications in scientific journals and several presentations in professional conferences and seminars. The manuscripts of all publications have been uploaded to the arXiv online depository for free public access. The physics curriculum at University of California, Merced, which is a Hispanic Serving Institute, has been renovated to integrate quantum physics and technology (QST) into undergraduate and graduate courses to cultivate the workforce for the emerging industry and education of QST with the help of the award. The PI also broadcasted the research and QST to local communities in the California Central Valley with a high population of under-represented minorities via events at UC Merced and local schools. Moreover, the PI offered assistance to research groups from China, Poland, and Egypt that requested help to establish research programs in atomic physics based on the project.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/16/2023<br>      Modified by: Chih Chun&nbsp;Chien</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2011360/2011360_10694715_1692134259659_BF_1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2011360/2011360_10694715_1692134259659_BF_1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Phase diagrams of binary atomic mixtures in box potentials"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2011360/2011360_10694715_1692134259659_BF_1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Phase diagrams of binary atomic mixtures in box potentials"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Phase diagrams of selected binary atomic mixtures with opposite statistical properties in one-dimensional box potentials. As the inter-species interaction increases, the mixtures separate into three-chunk or two chunk structures.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Adapted from Physical Review A 107, 023308 (2023) published by the American Physical Society.</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Chih Chun&nbsp;Chien</div> <div class="imageTitle">Phase diagrams of binary atomic mixtures in box potentials</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2011360/2011360_10694715_1692134553602_BF_2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2011360/2011360_10694715_1692134553602_BF_2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Atomic superfluid mixtures with inhomogeneous interactions"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2011360/2011360_10694715_1692134553602_BF_2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Atomic superfluid mixtures with inhomogeneous interactions"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Profiles of selected atomic superfluid mixtures in the presence of inhomogeneous interactions. The penetration of one species into a different region is an analogue of the proximity effect of superconductors and spatial Kibble-Zurek mechanism of magnetic systems.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Adapted from Physical Review A 107, 063314 (2023) published by the American Physical Society.</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Chih Chun&nbsp;Chien</div> <div class="imageTitle">Atomic superfluid mixtures with inhomogeneous interactions</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2011360/2011360_10694715_1692134762129_BF_3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2011360/2011360_10694715_1692134762129_BF_3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Systems benefit from the project"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2011360/2011360_10694715_1692134762129_BF_3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Systems benefit from the project"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The theoretical framework also applies to other systems beyond ultracold atoms. Examples include mechanical systems, thermal transport, and electronic transport in circuits, to name a few.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Adapted from Physical Review E 105, 064111 (2023) and Physical Review Letters 128, 097701 (2022) published by the American Physical Society.</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Chih Chun&nbsp;Chien</div> <div class="imageTitle">Systems benefit from the project</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Atomic mixtures are ubiquitous. For example, air is a mixture of nitrogen and oxygen and exhibits complex behavior as temperature or pressure changes. Recent progress in cooling and controlling atoms in laboratories makes it an important task to investigate ultracold atomic mixtures in the quantum regime, and this is the goal of the project. The research began with a derivation of a general theoretical framework capable of describing the structures and thermodynamics of atomic mixtures, followed by a development of numerical simulation tools capable of capturing the complex behavior at low temperatures. When the framework is applied to binary mixtures of atoms with opposite statistical behavior, various mixed or separating structures were discovered as a result of a competition between kinetic and interaction energies. The interface separating different species reveals an interesting quantity known as the healing length as the species on both sides are forbidden to enter the opposite side and result in inhomogeneity. The phase diagrams of selected atomic mixtures from the research are shown in Figure 1, which shed light on future experimental investigations. Next, atomic mixtures of two superfluids of different nature are analyzed. Through a unified description developed in the research, different phenomena previously studied in superconductors and magnetic systems can be demonstrated by ultracold atoms acting as a versatile quantum simulator. Selected profiles of atomic superfluids from the research are shown in Figure 2, further showcasing the rich structures of atomix mixtures.  By generalizing the theory to exotic geometries, such as the spherical bubble trap for atoms realized in the International Space Station, fundamental properties of atomic superfluids are shown in the research to be smoothly tunable by varying the size of the bubble trap. Moreover, the theoretical framework have been adapted to describe energy currents in quantum systems and electric currents in circuits, as illustrated in Figure 3. The generalization of the research uncovered exotic phenomena, such as local heat flow from cold to hot due to geometric effect and variation of electric current due to remnants of a symmetry. The results thus showcase the physics behind the interplay among strongly interacting quantum systems, atomic physics, computational physics, geometry, and topology.  During the support of the award, two PhD students completed their degrees and four undergraudates submitted their senior honor theses based on the research under the supervision of the PI. Among those students, two are women and three are Hispanic, which demonstrates the effort to increase diversity in physics. The research results have been documented in 13 publications in scientific journals and several presentations in professional conferences and seminars. The manuscripts of all publications have been uploaded to the arXiv online depository for free public access. The physics curriculum at University of California, Merced, which is a Hispanic Serving Institute, has been renovated to integrate quantum physics and technology (QST) into undergraduate and graduate courses to cultivate the workforce for the emerging industry and education of QST with the help of the award. The PI also broadcasted the research and QST to local communities in the California Central Valley with a high population of under-represented minorities via events at UC Merced and local schools. Moreover, the PI offered assistance to research groups from China, Poland, and Egypt that requested help to establish research programs in atomic physics based on the project.        Last Modified: 08/16/2023       Submitted by: Chih Chun Chien]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
