<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[NSF Student Travel Grant for 2020 ACM SIGCOMM Symposium on Software Defined Networking (SDN) Research (SOSR)]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>15000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>15000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ann Von Lehmen</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>avonlehm@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924756</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This award supports travel for up to 15 students to attend the ACM SIGCOMM Symposium on SDN Research (SOSR), March 3rd, 2020, San Jose, CA.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;SOSR is a high impact and top-tier forum for presentations and discussions of SDN network challenges and new networking technologies that will shape the future of SDN. The conference features a high-quality technical program with opportunities for students who might otherwise be unable to attend the conference to interact with senior researchers from both industry and academia in individual and group discussions.  It also enables them to network with their peer group, identify interesting new research topics, and explore different career paths and opportunities.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/24/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/24/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2011914</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rui</FirstName>
<LastName>Zhang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Rui Zhang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ruizhang@udel.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000651467</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/24/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Delaware</Name>
<CityName>NEWARK</CityName>
<ZipCode>197160099</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3028312136</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>220 HULLIHEN HALL</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Delaware</StateName>
<StateCode>DE</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DE00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>T72NHKM259N3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF DELAWARE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Delaware]]></Name>
<CityName>Newark</CityName>
<StateCode>DE</StateCode>
<ZipCode>197160099</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[210 Hullihen Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Delaware</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DE00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7363</Code>
<Text>Networking Technology and Syst</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~15000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The ACM SIGNCOMM Symposium on SDN Research (SOSR) is a leading platform for the presentation and discussion of the challenges and emerging networking technologies that will shape the future of SDN. This award aimed to support 15 US-based students to participate in SOSR 2020, which was initially scheduled for March 3rd, 2020, in San Jose, CA. SOSR 2020 received nine applications for student travel grants from US-based students and approved them all.</p> <p><br />Regrettably, SOSR 2020 was canceled due to the escalating threat of COVID-19. In particular, the World Health Organization had heightened its assessment of the risk of spread and impact of COVID-19 to "very high" at a global level on January 15th, 2020. There were also COVID-19 cases reported in Santa Clara, CA, where the SOSR 2020 conference was to take place. As a consequence, the SOSR 2020 organizing committee announced the conference's cancellation on February 29th, 2020, just three days ahead of the proposed date.</p> <p><br />By this point, some student travel grant recipients had already made their flight and hotel reservations. Accordingly, a portion of the fund amounting to $1968.20 was used to reimburse these students for their non-refundable flight and hotel reservations, and cancellation charges, per the NSF Implementation of OMB Memorandum M-20-17, &ldquo;Administrative Relief for Recipients and Applicants of Federal Financial Assistance Directly Impacted by the Novel Coronavirus (COVID-19) due to Loss of Operations,&rdquo; dated March 19, 2020.</p> <p><br />The first No-Cost Extension request of the award was submitted and approved, permitting the remaining funds to be reallocated to support US-based students attending SOSR 2021. However, SOSR 2021 was held virtually from October 11-12, 2021, hence, no funds were expended during that reporting period. A second No-Cost Extension request was subsequently submitted and approved, allowing for the remaining funds to be repurposed to support students attending SOSR 2022. While SOSR 2022 was initially planned as an in-person event, the organizing committee later opted for a virtual format on October 20th, 2022. As such, no additional funds were disbursed during this reporting period. At the conclusion of this project period, the remaining funds are returned to the NSF.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/02/2023<br>      Modified by: Rui&nbsp;Zhang</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The ACM SIGNCOMM Symposium on SDN Research (SOSR) is a leading platform for the presentation and discussion of the challenges and emerging networking technologies that will shape the future of SDN. This award aimed to support 15 US-based students to participate in SOSR 2020, which was initially scheduled for March 3rd, 2020, in San Jose, CA. SOSR 2020 received nine applications for student travel grants from US-based students and approved them all.   Regrettably, SOSR 2020 was canceled due to the escalating threat of COVID-19. In particular, the World Health Organization had heightened its assessment of the risk of spread and impact of COVID-19 to "very high" at a global level on January 15th, 2020. There were also COVID-19 cases reported in Santa Clara, CA, where the SOSR 2020 conference was to take place. As a consequence, the SOSR 2020 organizing committee announced the conference's cancellation on February 29th, 2020, just three days ahead of the proposed date.   By this point, some student travel grant recipients had already made their flight and hotel reservations. Accordingly, a portion of the fund amounting to $1968.20 was used to reimburse these students for their non-refundable flight and hotel reservations, and cancellation charges, per the NSF Implementation of OMB Memorandum M-20-17, "Administrative Relief for Recipients and Applicants of Federal Financial Assistance Directly Impacted by the Novel Coronavirus (COVID-19) due to Loss of Operations," dated March 19, 2020.   The first No-Cost Extension request of the award was submitted and approved, permitting the remaining funds to be reallocated to support US-based students attending SOSR 2021. However, SOSR 2021 was held virtually from October 11-12, 2021, hence, no funds were expended during that reporting period. A second No-Cost Extension request was subsequently submitted and approved, allowing for the remaining funds to be repurposed to support students attending SOSR 2022. While SOSR 2022 was initially planned as an in-person event, the organizing committee later opted for a virtual format on October 20th, 2022. As such, no additional funds were disbursed during this reporting period. At the conclusion of this project period, the remaining funds are returned to the NSF.       Last Modified: 06/02/2023       Submitted by: Rui Zhang]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
