<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[NSF INCLUDES Planning Grant: Cultivating Research and Equity in Sign-related Technology]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>99999.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>102599</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div. of Equity for Excellence in STEM</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joseph Whitmeyer</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jwhitmey@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927808</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This NSF INCLUDES planning grant is funded by NSF Inclusion across the Nation of Communities of Learners of Underrepresented Discoverers in Engineering and Science (NSF INCLUDES), a comprehensive national initiative to enhance U.S. leadership in discoveries and innovations by focusing on diversity, inclusion and broadening participation in STEM at scale. The goal of this planning grant is to initiate a collaborative network focused on increasing the inclusion of deaf and hard-of-hearing (D/HH) individuals in the development of sign-related technologies.  Many research projects use cutting-edge technologies applied to sign language translation, sign language teaching, or sign recognition. These projects include signing avatars, virtual/augmented reality sign language learning, gesture recognition for sign language, machine learning for sign recognition, wearable sensors for sign translation, and more. While the potential for these technologies is great, more inclusion and resource-sharing is needed.  This project addresses these goals through building and supporting a network of researchers and industry professionals who have interest in sign-related technologies and share a vision for how the network can help build fruitful collaborations.   This work increases the inclusion of D/HH individuals in the field and fosters the development of young D/HH students who wish to work in this area.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In this project, a network called Cultivating Research and Equity in Sign-Related Technologies (CREST) is established, a workshop is hosted to launch the network, and resources are provided for collaboration and communication among network members.  The workshop will develop the shared vision among stakeholders and initiate and strengthen partnerships. Activities of the network will have a two-way benefit: 1) D/HH researchers and students who are working on sign-related technologies are able to gain experience with new technologies and develop STEM skills they may not already possess; 2) Researchers with the technological capacity to develop cutting-edge sign-related technology benefit from expanding their networks to include those who are already experts in sign languages and the unique challenges they present: sign language users and D/HH researchers.  The CREST network increases the chances that sign-related technologies will be developed with D/HH input at all stages, meaning these technologies will be more likely to benefit people who use sign languages as a primary form of communication.  It allows for the growth of a community around a rapidly changing field which has the potential to reap great benefits for deaf individuals and communities of people who use sign language.  Two activities, contribution of videos and of blogs and posts, will deepen the connection between the CREST network and the NSF INCLUDES National Network that exists already, and the CREST network will bring new people to the National Network.  This work will benefit D/HH students, staff, and researchers who are part of the network, as well as the broader communities which may be affected by the technologies in development.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/07/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/26/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2012924</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Melissa</FirstName>
<LastName>Malzkuhn</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Melissa Malzkuhn</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[melissa.malzkuhn@gallaudet.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000719889</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/07/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lorna</FirstName>
<LastName>Quandt</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lorna Quandt</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[lorna.quandt@gallaudet.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000719891</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/07/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Gallaudet University</Name>
<CityName>WASHINGTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>200023600</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2026515497</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>800 FLORIDA AVE NE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>TQCJUED1WEF9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GALLAUDET UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Gallaudet University]]></Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>200023695</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[800 Florida Ave, NE, Kendall Hal]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>032Y</Code>
<Text>Eddie Bernice Johnson INCLUDES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>097Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Impacts on Existing Activities</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0420</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0421</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>04002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~99999</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~2600</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-6e84de5f-7fff-6ce5-b0e9-67a99318489e"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Cultivating Research &amp; Equity in Sign-related Technology (CREST Network) is an NSF-funded collaborative network aiming to foster discussions and collaborations in sign-related technologies, including sign language recognition, signing avatars, sign translation, and signing in mixed reality (e.g., virtual or augmented realities). The CREST Network project has significantly impacted the field of sign language technology by forming a new community in which researchers, students, scholars, and technicians can all come together for the equitable advancement of the technology. The Network has provided a platform for collaboration and knowledge sharing among researchers, students, and professionals, which has helped foster new collaborations and promote sharing of knowledge and resources among researchers, students, and professionals.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The CREST Network established an online presence, including a website, social media accounts, and a community listserv, on which members can post and share opportunities and ideas.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>In the Summer of 2021, CREST Network hosted CREST Fest, in which six distinguished leaders gave pre-recorded talks, which we released with ASL/English interpretation and captions. For each talk, we hosted a live "conversation-style" webinar, in which the presenter was joined by a host to discuss the content of their talk. We also hosted one "Hot Topics" panel in which seven discussants joined for a lively discussion on the state of the signed language technology field. These events engaged hundreds of participants globally, ranging from students, postdocs, and industry scientists to distinguished leaders in private and academic research. Critically, all events were accessible via ASL and English, we provided captioning, and the majority of invited presenters/discussants were deaf themselves.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Following CREST Fest in 2021, we continued to host CREST Talks in 2022, in which 6 additional online talks were held, in which researchers and developers shared the latest updates in sign language recognition, avatar generation, end-to-end automated sign translation, in addition to other topics.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Documentation and archiving are critical to developing a community resource such as CREST. As such, we have recorded all presentations and webinars, hosted them on YouTube and our website, and have them available for future viewing (with interpreting and captions).&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The CREST Network project has made a significant impact in increasing diversity in STEM fields, specifically in the area of sign language technology. Historically, deaf individuals and sign language users have been underrepresented in technology development. However, the CREST Network has helped to break down these barriers by centering deaf voices and perspectives in the conversation. This has led to new opportunities for deaf students and researchers to grow their professional networks and become more involved in the field. The CREST Network has also helped promote more inclusive science and research by providing a platform for collaboration and knowledge sharing among researchers, students, and professionals.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The events hosted by the CREST Network, such as CREST Fest and CREST Talks, have increased the visibility and representation of deaf individuals in the field. The presentations and webinars provided a platform for deaf researchers and developers to share their latest updates and findings, and the live "conversation-style" webinars provided an opportunity for further engagement and discussion.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>In addition to increasing diversity and representation in the field, the CREST Network has also contributed to developing new knowledge and pedagogical methods in sign language technology. The collaborations and knowledge sharing that have emerged as a result of the Network have led to new research and development in sign language recognition, avatar generation, and automated sign translation. These advancements can potentially improve the quality of life for deaf individuals and sign language users and can be used to create more inclusive and accessible technology for all.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Overall, the CREST Network has made a significant impact in the field of sign language technology and increasing diversity in STEM fields. The Network has formed a new community in which researchers, students, scholars, and technicians can all come together for the equitable advancement of the technology, and has provided a platform for collaboration and knowledge sharing. The events hosted by the Network have increased the visibility and representation of deaf individuals in the field, and the Network's contributions to new knowledge and pedagogical methods have the potential to improve the quality of life for deaf individuals and sign language users.</span></p> <div><span><br /></span></div> </span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/27/2023<br>      Modified by: Lorna&nbsp;Quandt</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Cultivating Research &amp; Equity in Sign-related Technology (CREST Network) is an NSF-funded collaborative network aiming to foster discussions and collaborations in sign-related technologies, including sign language recognition, signing avatars, sign translation, and signing in mixed reality (e.g., virtual or augmented realities). The CREST Network project has significantly impacted the field of sign language technology by forming a new community in which researchers, students, scholars, and technicians can all come together for the equitable advancement of the technology. The Network has provided a platform for collaboration and knowledge sharing among researchers, students, and professionals, which has helped foster new collaborations and promote sharing of knowledge and resources among researchers, students, and professionals.  The CREST Network established an online presence, including a website, social media accounts, and a community listserv, on which members can post and share opportunities and ideas.  In the Summer of 2021, CREST Network hosted CREST Fest, in which six distinguished leaders gave pre-recorded talks, which we released with ASL/English interpretation and captions. For each talk, we hosted a live "conversation-style" webinar, in which the presenter was joined by a host to discuss the content of their talk. We also hosted one "Hot Topics" panel in which seven discussants joined for a lively discussion on the state of the signed language technology field. These events engaged hundreds of participants globally, ranging from students, postdocs, and industry scientists to distinguished leaders in private and academic research. Critically, all events were accessible via ASL and English, we provided captioning, and the majority of invited presenters/discussants were deaf themselves.  Following CREST Fest in 2021, we continued to host CREST Talks in 2022, in which 6 additional online talks were held, in which researchers and developers shared the latest updates in sign language recognition, avatar generation, end-to-end automated sign translation, in addition to other topics.  Documentation and archiving are critical to developing a community resource such as CREST. As such, we have recorded all presentations and webinars, hosted them on YouTube and our website, and have them available for future viewing (with interpreting and captions).  The CREST Network project has made a significant impact in increasing diversity in STEM fields, specifically in the area of sign language technology. Historically, deaf individuals and sign language users have been underrepresented in technology development. However, the CREST Network has helped to break down these barriers by centering deaf voices and perspectives in the conversation. This has led to new opportunities for deaf students and researchers to grow their professional networks and become more involved in the field. The CREST Network has also helped promote more inclusive science and research by providing a platform for collaboration and knowledge sharing among researchers, students, and professionals. The events hosted by the CREST Network, such as CREST Fest and CREST Talks, have increased the visibility and representation of deaf individuals in the field. The presentations and webinars provided a platform for deaf researchers and developers to share their latest updates and findings, and the live "conversation-style" webinars provided an opportunity for further engagement and discussion.  In addition to increasing diversity and representation in the field, the CREST Network has also contributed to developing new knowledge and pedagogical methods in sign language technology. The collaborations and knowledge sharing that have emerged as a result of the Network have led to new research and development in sign language recognition, avatar generation, and automated sign translation. These advancements can potentially improve the quality of life for deaf individuals and sign language users and can be used to create more inclusive and accessible technology for all. Overall, the CREST Network has made a significant impact in the field of sign language technology and increasing diversity in STEM fields. The Network has formed a new community in which researchers, students, scholars, and technicians can all come together for the equitable advancement of the technology, and has provided a platform for collaboration and knowledge sharing. The events hosted by the Network have increased the visibility and representation of deaf individuals in the field, and the Network's contributions to new knowledge and pedagogical methods have the potential to improve the quality of life for deaf individuals and sign language users.                   Last Modified: 01/27/2023       Submitted by: Lorna Quandt]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
