<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Experimental Study of Heavy Flavor and CP Violation with the LHCb Experiment at the CERN LHC Collider]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/30/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/29/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1350000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1400723</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kaushik De</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kde@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927480</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[A major focus of experimental particle physics research is on the search for physics beyond the Standard Model.  Flavor physics plays a key role in this endeavor via precision measurements of ﬂavor processes sensitive to quantum loop effects, which complement direct searches at the highest energy accelerators.  The physics reach of the LHCb experiment at the CERN LHC collider includes precision measurements of rare decays and matter-antimatter asymmetry in the charm quark and the bottom quark systems.  At the current level of precision, these measurements impose severe constraints on the energy scale and the structure of new physics models.  However, areas of deviations from the Standard Model are emerging, including signs of lepton non-universality in radiative and semi-leptonic B decays, which are highly sensitive to the presence of new scalar particles. The precision of future measurements in some key areas is expected to reach the required sensitivity to clarify these anomalies or further strengthen the deviations from the Standard Model predictions.  These results could, in conjunction with studies at high energies, point the way to the structure of the physics beyond the Standard Model. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project involves a Maryland experimental particle physics group study of heavy flavor and CP violation with the LHCb experiment. It includes the development and construction of off-detector electronics for the upstream tracker for the LHCb detector upgrade and the installation and commissioning of the tracker, as well as major participation in the physics analysis of recorded and future LHCb data. The physics analysis effort is focused on measurements related to two current anomalies in the decays of B mesons: hints of departure from Lepton Flavor Universality in semileptonic B decays and the longstanding “Kaon pion” puzzle, where the measured CP asymmetries in the family of B to Kaon plus pion decays deviate from expectations. These anomalies, if confirmed, could be due to the imprints of new physics on flavor processes.  Several data analysis techniques will be developed and used, including the use of machine learning. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The ﬁndings of new sources of CP violation beyond the SM will have a profound impact on the understanding of the origin of baryon-antibaryon asymmetry and the ﬁeld of cosmology. The studies of ﬂavor processes will also yield precision information on the decay properties of the bottom and charmed hadrons, serving as a powerful testing ground for the predictions of lattice QCD calculations. The group’s detector upgrade eﬀort provides excellent opportunities for training undergraduate students in experimental and engineering techniques. The group works closely with an outreach program run by the physics and astronomy departments at the University of Maryland, the GRAD-MAP, which is aimed at providing research and training opportunities for undergraduates from underrepresented groups in the Maryland and Washington area community colleges. The group plans to expand this eﬀort to data analysis with the LHCb data by introducing students to advanced data handling and analysis techniques, such as machine learning.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/16/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/01/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2012793</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Abolhassan</FirstName>
<LastName>Jawahery</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Abolhassan Jawahery</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jawahery@physics.umd.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000144076</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/16/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Manuel</FirstName>
<LastName>Franco Sevilla</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Manuel Franco Sevilla</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[manuelf@umd.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000791852</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/16/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Maryland, College Park</Name>
<CityName>College Park</CityName>
<ZipCode>207420001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3014056269</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3112 LEE BLDG 7809 REGENTS DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MD04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NPU8ULVAAS23</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MARYLAND, COLLEGE PARK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>KMGEN62NKEM9</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Maryland College Park]]></Name>
<CityName>College Park</CityName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>207427202</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Physical Sciences Complex]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MD04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>156Y</Code>
<Text>PPP-Precision Particle Physics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>075Z</Code>
<Text>Artificial Intelligence (AI)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7483</Code>
<Text>PHYSICS OF THE UNIVERSE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002223DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~450000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~450000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2022~500723</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Experimental Study of Heavy Flavor and CP Violation with the LHCb</strong></p> <p><strong>Experiment at the CERN LHC Collider</strong></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Understanding the fundamental structure of matter and the origin of the universe is at the core of research in physics, astronomy and cosmology. Our current knowledge of the fundamental constituents of matter and the laws that govern their interactions, obtained from decades of experimental observations and theoretical ideas and efforts, is encapsulated in the so-called Standard Model.&nbsp; However, the Standard Model is believed to be incomplete, as it fails to account for some important findings and questions, such as the apparent imbalance of matter with respect to antimatter in the universe and the strong evidence for dark matter inferred from astronomical observations. A major goal of this research program has been to search for and examine possible evidence for new particles and new laws of nature beyond those described in the Standard Model. The program involves the study of proton-proton collisions at the Large Hadron Collider (LHC) at the CERN laboratory in Switzerland. These collisions are recorded by a particle spectrometer called the LHCb detector. While the results of these studies overwhelmingly conform to the predictions of the Standard Model, evidence for potential deviations has emerged in a few areas.&nbsp; Another key objective of this research program has been to make major contributions to the upgrade of the LHCb detector with the aim of significantly enhancing its sensitivity as well as enabling the operation of the detector at higher intensities of the LHC collider.&nbsp; With the anticipated completion of the installation and commissioning of the upgraded LHCb detector in 2023, extremely precise measurements of the properties of heavy quarks and leptons will be performed, allowing for studies of possible footprints of new physics in these interactions.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Study of the Universality of Lepton Interactions with Gauge Bosons</strong></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>A key feature of the Standard Model is the equality of the strength of interactions between charged leptons- the three electron-like particles amongst the building blocks of matter- and the gauge bosons that mediate the electroweak forces. &nbsp;A major goal of our research program has been a comprehensive study of interactions involving the heaviest charged lepton, the tau lepton, relative those of light leptons, electron and muon.&nbsp; The results of these studies, which show hints of deviation from the Standard Model predictions, are of great interest to the search for physics beyond the Standard Model.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Study of differences in Matter and Antimatter Interactions</strong></p> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p>Another key objective of this program is to perform precise measurements of differences in the behavior of matter particles compared with their antimatter counterparts, the results of which may reveal information on the origin of the observed matter-antimatter imbalance in nature, which is crucial to understanding how the universe evolved to its current state.&nbsp; Studies carried out in this research program led to new measurements of matter-antimatter asymmetries and the development of new algorithms and techniques that improved the capabilities of the LHCb detector in performing such measurements.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Upgrade of the LHCb Detector</strong></p> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p>The LHCb collaboration, the international consortium of institutions that built and now operates the LHCb experiment at CERN, is engaged in a major program to upgrade the detector.&nbsp; The detector upgrade enables the experiment to operate at much higher collision intensities.&nbsp; On this front, our research program has been focused on the design of sophisticated electronics instrumentation for extracting and recording electrical signals from a silicon strip detector system located just upstream of the LHC magnet.&nbsp; This device plays a key role in detecting and recording the trajectories of charged particles produced in the collisions.&nbsp; The new instrument is now being assembled at CERN and will be installed in the LHCb detector during in the 1<sup>st</sup> quarter of 2023.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Training of young scientists and engineers</strong><strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p>In addition to the key physics objectives discussed above, this research program has helped train several young scientists and engineers, including undergraduates, PhD. graduate students, postdoctoral researchers, in sophisticated detector and electronics design and state-of-the-art data analysis and computing techniques.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/04/2023<br>      Modified by: Abolhassan&nbsp;Jawahery</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Experimental Study of Heavy Flavor and CP Violation with the LHCb  Experiment at the CERN LHC Collider     Understanding the fundamental structure of matter and the origin of the universe is at the core of research in physics, astronomy and cosmology. Our current knowledge of the fundamental constituents of matter and the laws that govern their interactions, obtained from decades of experimental observations and theoretical ideas and efforts, is encapsulated in the so-called Standard Model.  However, the Standard Model is believed to be incomplete, as it fails to account for some important findings and questions, such as the apparent imbalance of matter with respect to antimatter in the universe and the strong evidence for dark matter inferred from astronomical observations. A major goal of this research program has been to search for and examine possible evidence for new particles and new laws of nature beyond those described in the Standard Model. The program involves the study of proton-proton collisions at the Large Hadron Collider (LHC) at the CERN laboratory in Switzerland. These collisions are recorded by a particle spectrometer called the LHCb detector. While the results of these studies overwhelmingly conform to the predictions of the Standard Model, evidence for potential deviations has emerged in a few areas.  Another key objective of this research program has been to make major contributions to the upgrade of the LHCb detector with the aim of significantly enhancing its sensitivity as well as enabling the operation of the detector at higher intensities of the LHC collider.  With the anticipated completion of the installation and commissioning of the upgraded LHCb detector in 2023, extremely precise measurements of the properties of heavy quarks and leptons will be performed, allowing for studies of possible footprints of new physics in these interactions.     Study of the Universality of Lepton Interactions with Gauge Bosons     A key feature of the Standard Model is the equality of the strength of interactions between charged leptons- the three electron-like particles amongst the building blocks of matter- and the gauge bosons that mediate the electroweak forces.  A major goal of our research program has been a comprehensive study of interactions involving the heaviest charged lepton, the tau lepton, relative those of light leptons, electron and muon.  The results of these studies, which show hints of deviation from the Standard Model predictions, are of great interest to the search for physics beyond the Standard Model.      Study of differences in Matter and Antimatter Interactions     Another key objective of this program is to perform precise measurements of differences in the behavior of matter particles compared with their antimatter counterparts, the results of which may reveal information on the origin of the observed matter-antimatter imbalance in nature, which is crucial to understanding how the universe evolved to its current state.  Studies carried out in this research program led to new measurements of matter-antimatter asymmetries and the development of new algorithms and techniques that improved the capabilities of the LHCb detector in performing such measurements.      Upgrade of the LHCb Detector     The LHCb collaboration, the international consortium of institutions that built and now operates the LHCb experiment at CERN, is engaged in a major program to upgrade the detector.  The detector upgrade enables the experiment to operate at much higher collision intensities.  On this front, our research program has been focused on the design of sophisticated electronics instrumentation for extracting and recording electrical signals from a silicon strip detector system located just upstream of the LHC magnet.  This device plays a key role in detecting and recording the trajectories of charged particles produced in the collisions.  The new instrument is now being assembled at CERN and will be installed in the LHCb detector during in the 1st quarter of 2023.     Training of young scientists and engineers   In addition to the key physics objectives discussed above, this research program has helped train several young scientists and engineers, including undergraduates, PhD. graduate students, postdoctoral researchers, in sophisticated detector and electronics design and state-of-the-art data analysis and computing techniques.          Last Modified: 09/04/2023       Submitted by: Abolhassan Jawahery]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
