<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research: Integrating Spatial Analysis into Long Term Research]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>45918.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>45918</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>John Yellen</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jyellen@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928759</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The SPatial Archaeometry Research Collaborations (SPARC) Program promotes the use of spatial analysis, 3D modeling, and remote sensing technologies in archaeological research projects. The things archaeologists study—from artifacts to sites to landscapes—almost always have spatial components that are essential to understanding cultural processes. Digital museums allow for morphometric analyses of remote, fragile, and/or priceless artifacts; geophysical investigations help pinpoint subsurface features such as houses that save time and money during excavation; the remote sensing technique LiDAR (Light Detection and Ranging) identifies natural and anthropogenic landscapes such as ancient roads through impediments like vegetation cover. Today, the increasing availability and sophistication of digital technologies is not merely generating new data but is facilitating entirely novel means of engaging with the archaeological record. However, the high costs of instrumentation and software, combined with the expertise they require, create a hurdle for many archaeologists who aim to deploy geospatial technologies in research projects. Through a competitive, peer-reviewed application process, SPARC facilitates collaborations between archaeologists interested in adding a digital component to their research with SPARC institutions, who leverage the technological infrastructure of instrumentation, software, and expertise of faculty and technical staff at the University of Arkansas' Center for Advanced Spatial Technologies, Dartmouth College’s Spatial Archaeometry Lab, and the University of Glasgow. Since 2013, SPARC has supported 35 collaborative projects involving 73 PIs and co-PIs from 46 different institutions for research in over 20 countries. SPARC has a strong track record of supporting women and early-career researchers, providing external funding and publishing opportunities essential to developing competitive careers, and for researchers located at public universities and non-profits. Online seminars and workshops, student training opportunities, leadership in professional organizations, methodological innovations, and new grant awards all stem from SPARC research.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The SPARC Program's goals are to: enhance the research productivity of archaeological projects by making geospatial technologies available to researchers who would not otherwise have access to the tools or skills needed to collect and analyze these data; generate high-value, efficient archaeological data by participating in fieldwork and analytical projects; provide training opportunities for students and professionals seeking to use geospatial techniques; promote the development of new geospatial applications in archaeology and their visibility to the broader community; and support good practice in archiving and publication of digital data. SPARC offers direct support to archaeological projects through awards in three categories—Fieldwork (on-site data collection), Data &amp; Analytics (preparation, processing, and analysis), and Publication (presentation, publication, and archiving)—that utilize a wide-ranging set of methods including high-performance computing, surface reconstruction and morphometric analysis, volumetric 3D imaging, near-surface geophysics, aerial remote sensing and survey (e.g. “drones”), geodetic positioning and topographic survey, and 3D visualization. SPARC strives to build a program that is increasingly visible - attracting top research projects; efficient - as project staff build on their experience; high impact - as pilot projects build skills in research teams around the world; and innovative - with broader collaborations leading to significant methodological advancements.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/24/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/24/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2012600</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jesse</FirstName>
<LastName>Casana</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jesse Casana</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jesse.j.casana@dartmouth.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000241736</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/24/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Dartmouth College</Name>
<CityName>HANOVER</CityName>
<ZipCode>037552170</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6036463007</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>7 LEBANON ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Hampshire</StateName>
<StateCode>NH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NH02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>EB8ASJBCFER9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF DARTMOUTH COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>EB8ASJBCFER9</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Dartmouth College]]></Name>
<CityName>Hanover</CityName>
<StateCode>NH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>037553537</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Silsby Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Hampshire</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NH02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1393</Code>
<Text>ARCHAEOMETRY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1393</Code>
<Text>ARCHAEOMETRY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7298</Code>
<Text>COLLABORATIVE RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~45918</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This grant supported a the Spatial Archaeometry Research Collaborations (SPARC) Program, a multi-institutional initiative that works to expand access to and promote the use of geospatial technologies in archaeological research. A suite of emerging technologies, including aerial and satellite imaging, large-array terrestrial geophysics, multi-sensor drone-based mapping, MicroCT scanning, and 3D documentation and visualization are rapidly transforming how archaeologists discover, document, and interpret the human past. However, the high costs of instrumentation and software combined with the technical expertise these technologies require for successful data collection, processing, and analysis create significant hurdles for researchers, preventing their widespread integration into archaeological investigations, particularly for junior scholars or those at less-well resourced institutions. The SPARC program seeks to bridge these funding and expertise gaps by making the equipment, software, and experienced staff at the University of Arkansas&rsquo; Center for Advanced Spatial Technologies (CAST) and Dartmouth&rsquo;s Spatial Archaeometry Lab (SPARCL) available to archaeological research projects through a competitive, peer-reviewed application process. Proposals to the SPARC program selected for in-kind awards collaborate with SPARC faculty and staff members in planning projects, undertaking field data collection, conducing lab-based data processes analyses, and preparing results for visualization, presentation, publication, and sustainable archiving. In addition, the SPARC program offers an array of online educational and training resources, sponsors in-person workshops and consultations at major conferences, and hosts scholars for residencies that enable intensive collaborative research and skills development. &nbsp;Since 2013, the SPARC program has supported 46 research projects led by 92 PIs and Co-PIs from 63 different institutions, producing dozens of prominent publications, conference presentations, and online tools or data repositories, as well as serving as the basis for $2.2 million in new grant funding.</p> <p>SPARC provides a proven model for both increasing and democratizing access to a variety of specialist skills and technologies that collectively are transforming archaeological research. Results of SPARC-supported research projects produce high-impact results, offering invaluable insights into the human past using technologies that are non-destructive, non-invasive, and replicable. Moreover, the close collaboration of technical experts with archaeologists working in many different world regions and focusing on a wide range of periods helps to facilitate technological and methodological innovation, as we work together to develop creative solutions to challenging problems in data collection and analysis. The frequently transformative results produced through SPARC collaborations, essentially pilot studies in spatial archaeometric research, are often the basis for ongoing investigations that lead to longer-term projects funded by other grant programs.</p> <p>In addition to its mission undertaking collaborative archaeological research projects, the SPARC program plays an important role in supporting educational and outreach initiatives.&nbsp; SPARC produces a wide range of high-quality, online educational programming and instructional tutorials surrounding the use of spatial archaeometric technologies. The program also sponsors in-person workshops on key topics at national conferences, as well as online webinars that will offer open-access opportunities for advanced training. Materials designed for classrooms can be easily integrated into undergraduate education, while the high visibility of our research projects and publications will make results visible to a broad public audience. And finally, the SPARC program plays a critical role in diversity, equity and inclusion initiatives by expanding access to technologies, particularly for historically underrepresented scholars, early career researchers, and scholars at less well-resourced or minority serving institutions.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/04/2023<br>      Modified by: Jesse&nbsp;Casana</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This grant supported a the Spatial Archaeometry Research Collaborations (SPARC) Program, a multi-institutional initiative that works to expand access to and promote the use of geospatial technologies in archaeological research. A suite of emerging technologies, including aerial and satellite imaging, large-array terrestrial geophysics, multi-sensor drone-based mapping, MicroCT scanning, and 3D documentation and visualization are rapidly transforming how archaeologists discover, document, and interpret the human past. However, the high costs of instrumentation and software combined with the technical expertise these technologies require for successful data collection, processing, and analysis create significant hurdles for researchers, preventing their widespread integration into archaeological investigations, particularly for junior scholars or those at less-well resourced institutions. The SPARC program seeks to bridge these funding and expertise gaps by making the equipment, software, and experienced staff at the University of Arkansas’ Center for Advanced Spatial Technologies (CAST) and Dartmouth’s Spatial Archaeometry Lab (SPARCL) available to archaeological research projects through a competitive, peer-reviewed application process. Proposals to the SPARC program selected for in-kind awards collaborate with SPARC faculty and staff members in planning projects, undertaking field data collection, conducing lab-based data processes analyses, and preparing results for visualization, presentation, publication, and sustainable archiving. In addition, the SPARC program offers an array of online educational and training resources, sponsors in-person workshops and consultations at major conferences, and hosts scholars for residencies that enable intensive collaborative research and skills development.  Since 2013, the SPARC program has supported 46 research projects led by 92 PIs and Co-PIs from 63 different institutions, producing dozens of prominent publications, conference presentations, and online tools or data repositories, as well as serving as the basis for $2.2 million in new grant funding.  SPARC provides a proven model for both increasing and democratizing access to a variety of specialist skills and technologies that collectively are transforming archaeological research. Results of SPARC-supported research projects produce high-impact results, offering invaluable insights into the human past using technologies that are non-destructive, non-invasive, and replicable. Moreover, the close collaboration of technical experts with archaeologists working in many different world regions and focusing on a wide range of periods helps to facilitate technological and methodological innovation, as we work together to develop creative solutions to challenging problems in data collection and analysis. The frequently transformative results produced through SPARC collaborations, essentially pilot studies in spatial archaeometric research, are often the basis for ongoing investigations that lead to longer-term projects funded by other grant programs.  In addition to its mission undertaking collaborative archaeological research projects, the SPARC program plays an important role in supporting educational and outreach initiatives.  SPARC produces a wide range of high-quality, online educational programming and instructional tutorials surrounding the use of spatial archaeometric technologies. The program also sponsors in-person workshops on key topics at national conferences, as well as online webinars that will offer open-access opportunities for advanced training. Materials designed for classrooms can be easily integrated into undergraduate education, while the high visibility of our research projects and publications will make results visible to a broad public audience. And finally, the SPARC program plays a critical role in diversity, equity and inclusion initiatives by expanding access to technologies, particularly for historically underrepresented scholars, early career researchers, and scholars at less well-resourced or minority serving institutions.         Last Modified: 01/04/2023       Submitted by: Jesse Casana]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
