<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[NSF INCLUDES Planning Grant: EA3 - Expanding Access to Alabama Agriscience]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>99255.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>99255</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div. of Equity for Excellence in STEM</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Bernard Grant</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bgrant@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928521</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Expanding Access to Alabama Agriscience (EA3)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This NSF INCLUDES planning grant is funded by NSF Inclusion across the Nation of Communities of Learners of Underrepresented Discoverers in Engineering and Science (NSF INCLUDES), a comprehensive national initiative to enhance U.S. leadership in discoveries and innovations by focusing on diversity, inclusion and broadening participation in STEM at scale. The goal of this planning grant is to form a partnership of stakeholders to identify barriers and opportunities to broadening participation in agriscience-related careers across Alabama. The great challenge of modern agriculture is how we continue to feed Earth’s growing population in the face of shrinking farmable land and increasing climate change. One solution is to use genomic tools to identify and incorporate genetic changes that increase yields in the face of decreased inputs and uncertain environments. The demand for the workforce to use these tools is projected to grow faster than the national average, but as in other STEM fields, women and ethnic minorities are currently underrepresented in these agriscience-related careers. Alabama has historically lacked a common vision to expand and weave individual initiatives, resources and expertise into a coordinated network that provides learners with a pathway towards agriscience-related careers. We are program-rich but “coordination-poor”. This proposal seeks to generate a shared awareness of the current landscape, deepen cross-sector relationships and build a common vision for how to broaden agriscience participation from elementary school through the workforce. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The planning proposal has four key objectives: (1) Engage Alabama’s agriscience and educational stakeholders in a collaborative partnership to build cross-sector relationships and identify a common vision to broaden participation across the agriscience workforce (2) Identify the agriscience-related opportunities for student engagement, career exploration and workforce development that are currently available to Alabama learners, (3) Recognize the geographic, academic, financial and cultural barriers that limit student access to these opportunities, (4) Cultivate approaches to overcome these barriers, through modifying/scaling existing initiatives as well as developing new ones. The planning process will utilize collective impact concepts as well as the NSF INCLUDES collaborative infrastructure elements of Shared Vision, Partnership and Goals and Metrics. EA3 partners includes K-12 STEM and Career and Technical Education programs, as well as out-of-school organizations like Future Farmers of America, Alabama 4-H, the Boys and Girls Club and the Educational Outreach team at the HudsonAlpha Institute for Biotechnology. Research and teaching faculty from Alabama A&amp;M, Auburn and Tuskegee universities, together with the plant genomics team from HudsonAlpha, link scientific discovery and workforce development. Lastly, the Alabama Farmers Federation and Alabama Extension offices provide a direct connection to the state’s agriscience industry. Over a 14-month timeframe, this team will assemble for eight videoconferences and five in-person meetings, held across Alabama. The outcomes of these meetings will be woven into a statement of shared vision and an integrated strategic plan for increasing participation in Alabama’s agriscience-related careers. This will have a lasting impact as stakeholders use the knowledge gained through the planning process to develop experiences that effectively boost the participation and retention of underrepresented populations in agriscience-related fields across Alabama.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/22/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/22/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2012972</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Neil</FirstName>
<LastName>Lamb</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Neil E Lamb</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[nlamb@hudsonalpha.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000742933</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/22/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kankshita</FirstName>
<LastName>Swaminathan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kankshita Swaminathan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[kswaminathan@hudsonalpha.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000675687</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/22/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gregory</FirstName>
<LastName>Bernard</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gregory Bernard</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[gbernard@tuskegee.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000606164</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/22/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tyesha</FirstName>
<LastName>Farmer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Tyesha L Farmer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[tyesha.farmer@aamu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000770027</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/22/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alex</FirstName>
<LastName>Harkess</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alex Harkess</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[AHarkess@danforthcenter.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000769816</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/22/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>HudsonAlpha Institute for Biotechnology</Name>
<CityName>Huntsville</CityName>
<ZipCode>358062908</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2563275217</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>601 Genome Way</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Alabama</StateName>
<StateCode>AL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AL05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>M3GAQBN4BWH6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>HUDSONALPHA INSTITUTE FOR BIOTECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[HudsonAlpha Institute for Biotechnology]]></Name>
<CityName>Huntsville</CityName>
<StateCode>AL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>358062908</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[601 Genome Way]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Alabama</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AL05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>032Y</Code>
<Text>Eddie Bernice Johnson INCLUDES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0420</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~99255</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>One of the greatest challenge of modern agriculture is how we continue to feed Earth's growing population in the face of shrinking farmable land and increasing climate change. One solution is to generate the plants that evolution has not, using genomic tools to identify and incorporate those genetic changes that increase yields even with decreased inputs and uncertain environments. <span>The demand for a skilled workforce that develops and implements this and other types of solutions is projected to grow faster than the national average.</span>However, as in other STEM fields, women and ethnic minorities are underrepresented in agriscience-related careers. We sought to identify the factors in Alabama that underlie this broadening participation challenge by forming the <strong>Expanding Access to Alabama Agriscience (EA<sup>3</sup>) partnership</strong>, comprised of stakeholders from formal and informal education, workforce preparation, research and industry.</p> <p>EA<sup>3</sup> brought together experts from diverse racial, geographic, ethnic and STEM backgrounds. Partners included K-12 STEM and Career and Technical Education programs, as well as out-of-school organizations like Future Farmers of America, Alabama 4-H, the Boys and Girls Club and the HudsonAlpha Educational Outreach team. Research and teaching faculty from Alabama A&amp;M, Auburn and Tuskegee universities, together with the plant genomics team from HudsonAlpha, linked scientific discovery and workforce development. Lastly, the Alabama Farmers Federation, and Alabama Extension offices provided a direct connection to the Alabama agriscience industry.</p> <p>Historically, these diverse groups have approached agriscience outreach, education and workforce development from an individual perspective, occasionally working with one or two additional partners. As a result, K-12, university and government sectors have been disconnected from community groups and industry players. This proposal sought to generate a shared awareness of the current landscape, deepen cross-sector relationships and build a common vision for broadening agriscience participation. It leveraged existing content expertise and connectivity to provide a novel system-wide understanding of the resources, challenges and gaps facing Alabama learners considering agriscience careers.</p> <p>The partners met 11 times over the life cycle of the grant. Ten monthly meetings occurred virtually via Zoom, each lasting approximately three hours. The eleventh gathering was in-person and focused on identifying activities to jumpstart broader ag-based participation and next steps.</p> <p>This planning proposal had four key objectives, listed below. A brief summary of the work accomplished by the EA3 team follows each objective.</p> <p><em>(1) Engage Alabama agriscience and educational stakeholders in a collaborative partnership to build cross-sector relationships, and identify a common vision to broaden participation across the agriscience workforce</em></p> <p>The stakeholders crafted the following shared vision and mission</p> <p><strong>Vision: A robust and modern agriscience sector whose workforce reflects the broader social, ethnics and cultural society it serves</strong></p> <p><strong>Mission: Create a network of agriscience-related stakeholders for the purpose of:</strong></p> <ul> <li><strong>expanding access to programs and experiences that cultivate awareness, build talent and diversify the agriscience-related workforce</strong></li> <li><strong>promoting equity and inclusivity for underrepresented populations who have been excluded or marginalized from participation</strong></li> </ul> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><em>(2) Identify the agriscience-related opportunities for student engagement, career exploration and workforce development that are currently available to Alabama learners</em></p> <p>Over the course of the meetings, stakeholders outlined the ag-related student engagement, learner preparation or workforce training opportunities offered by their organization. This allowed us to develop an overview of existing opportunities, as well as identify gaps where programs were lacking.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><em>(3) Recognize the geographic, academic, financial and cultural barriers that limit student access to these opportunities</em></p> <p>The stakeholder team used a root cause analysis process to create an Ishikawa diagram (also called a fishbone or cause-and-effect diagram) to identify the various barriers that currently limit broader participation in agriscience education and workforce pathways across Alabama. These include: lack of awareness, lack of self-identity &amp; confidence, cultural barriers, institutional &amp; societal gaps and accessibility hurdles. Each barrier has multiple underlying causes, which the EA3 team further explored.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><em>(4) Cultivate approaches to overcome these barriers, through modifying/scaling existing initiatives as well as developing new ones.</em></p> <p>From those barriers identified in the Ishikawa diagram, the team prioritized six areas where we felt successful solutions would have the greatest impact on increasing participation. Several possible solutions were identified to address the barrier for each area. The team chose two from each area as initial recommendations. These will be compiled into a roadmap document for expanding participation in agricultural-related careers across Alabama. This work represents an initial, but important step in developing human resources for STEM fields.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/23/2021<br>      Modified by: Neil&nbsp;E&nbsp;Lamb</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ One of the greatest challenge of modern agriculture is how we continue to feed Earth's growing population in the face of shrinking farmable land and increasing climate change. One solution is to generate the plants that evolution has not, using genomic tools to identify and incorporate those genetic changes that increase yields even with decreased inputs and uncertain environments. The demand for a skilled workforce that develops and implements this and other types of solutions is projected to grow faster than the national average.However, as in other STEM fields, women and ethnic minorities are underrepresented in agriscience-related careers. We sought to identify the factors in Alabama that underlie this broadening participation challenge by forming the Expanding Access to Alabama Agriscience (EA3) partnership, comprised of stakeholders from formal and informal education, workforce preparation, research and industry.  EA3 brought together experts from diverse racial, geographic, ethnic and STEM backgrounds. Partners included K-12 STEM and Career and Technical Education programs, as well as out-of-school organizations like Future Farmers of America, Alabama 4-H, the Boys and Girls Club and the HudsonAlpha Educational Outreach team. Research and teaching faculty from Alabama A&amp;M, Auburn and Tuskegee universities, together with the plant genomics team from HudsonAlpha, linked scientific discovery and workforce development. Lastly, the Alabama Farmers Federation, and Alabama Extension offices provided a direct connection to the Alabama agriscience industry.  Historically, these diverse groups have approached agriscience outreach, education and workforce development from an individual perspective, occasionally working with one or two additional partners. As a result, K-12, university and government sectors have been disconnected from community groups and industry players. This proposal sought to generate a shared awareness of the current landscape, deepen cross-sector relationships and build a common vision for broadening agriscience participation. It leveraged existing content expertise and connectivity to provide a novel system-wide understanding of the resources, challenges and gaps facing Alabama learners considering agriscience careers.  The partners met 11 times over the life cycle of the grant. Ten monthly meetings occurred virtually via Zoom, each lasting approximately three hours. The eleventh gathering was in-person and focused on identifying activities to jumpstart broader ag-based participation and next steps.  This planning proposal had four key objectives, listed below. A brief summary of the work accomplished by the EA3 team follows each objective.  (1) Engage Alabama agriscience and educational stakeholders in a collaborative partnership to build cross-sector relationships, and identify a common vision to broaden participation across the agriscience workforce  The stakeholders crafted the following shared vision and mission  Vision: A robust and modern agriscience sector whose workforce reflects the broader social, ethnics and cultural society it serves  Mission: Create a network of agriscience-related stakeholders for the purpose of:  expanding access to programs and experiences that cultivate awareness, build talent and diversify the agriscience-related workforce promoting equity and inclusivity for underrepresented populations who have been excluded or marginalized from participation      (2) Identify the agriscience-related opportunities for student engagement, career exploration and workforce development that are currently available to Alabama learners  Over the course of the meetings, stakeholders outlined the ag-related student engagement, learner preparation or workforce training opportunities offered by their organization. This allowed us to develop an overview of existing opportunities, as well as identify gaps where programs were lacking.     (3) Recognize the geographic, academic, financial and cultural barriers that limit student access to these opportunities  The stakeholder team used a root cause analysis process to create an Ishikawa diagram (also called a fishbone or cause-and-effect diagram) to identify the various barriers that currently limit broader participation in agriscience education and workforce pathways across Alabama. These include: lack of awareness, lack of self-identity &amp; confidence, cultural barriers, institutional &amp; societal gaps and accessibility hurdles. Each barrier has multiple underlying causes, which the EA3 team further explored.     (4) Cultivate approaches to overcome these barriers, through modifying/scaling existing initiatives as well as developing new ones.  From those barriers identified in the Ishikawa diagram, the team prioritized six areas where we felt successful solutions would have the greatest impact on increasing participation. Several possible solutions were identified to address the barrier for each area. The team chose two from each area as initial recommendations. These will be compiled into a roadmap document for expanding participation in agricultural-related careers across Alabama. This work represents an initial, but important step in developing human resources for STEM fields.          Last Modified: 12/23/2021       Submitted by: Neil E Lamb]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
