<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Operation of the Telescope Array, TALE, and the TAx4 Expansion by the University of Utah]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>841026.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>841026</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Darren Grant</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dgrant@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928977</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The Telescope Array (TA) is the largest detector of ultra-high-energy cosmic rays (UHECR) in the northern hemisphere.  TAx4 is an expansion currently under way which will double the number of surface detectors (SD), and since SD deployment can occur along with operations, by 2025 TA will have tripled the existing data set.  This award supports the cosmic ray physics group at Utah for one year of running the Telescope Array (TA) complex, including the Low Energy Extension (TALE) and TAx4.  This covers managerial, engineering and technical staff effort and expenses.  This constitutes a somewhat lower level of support compared to past years, which will reduce the number of nights of collecting data, and provide for a smaller amount of site and equipment maintenance.  The Japanese and Korean partners will concentrate on construction and deployment of the remaining SD units, and maintenance of the new SD wings.  The Utah staff have sole responsibility for facility maintenance, staffing observing shifts and handling data, and maintaining compliance with Bureau of Land Management land use regulations.  TA supports auxiliary and test experiments, recently hosting a lightning mapping array.  The ASPIRE project is the TA’s public education and outreach arm, receiving millions of online visits each year.  Direct outreach also reaches tens of thousands of teachers and students.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Recent exciting results from TA clearly demonstrate the need for more data from an enlarged experiment.  One result is the apparent existence of a “hotspot” with possibly curious properties, such as a different, and apparently position-dependent, cosmic ray (CR) spectrum.  Another is the apparent discrepancy between spectra and CR composition at the highest energies as measured by TA and by the Pierre Auger Observatory, the largest UHECR detector but in the southern hemisphere.  In the longer term, tripling the amount of TA data will help to clarify these comparisons, and continuing TA operations is therefore very important.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/31/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/19/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2012934</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Pierre</FirstName>
<LastName>Sokolsky</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>V</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Pierre V Sokolsky</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ps@physics.utah.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000266742</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/31/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Charles</FirstName>
<LastName>Jui</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Charles C Jui</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jui@cosmic.utah.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000471409</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/31/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Matthews</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>N</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John N Matthews</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jnm@cosmic.utah.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000412025</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/31/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Douglas</FirstName>
<LastName>Bergman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Douglas R Bergman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[bergman@physics.utah.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000544435</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/31/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Utah</Name>
<CityName>SALT LAKE CITY</CityName>
<ZipCode>841129049</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8015816903</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>201 PRESIDENTS CIR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Utah</StateName>
<StateCode>UT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>UT01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>LL8GLEVH6MG3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF UTAH</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Univ of Utah - Millard County Cosmic Ray Center]]></Name>
<CityName>Delta</CityName>
<StateCode>UT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>846248702</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[648 West Main Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Utah</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>UT02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1643</Code>
<Text>Particle Astrophysics/Cosmic P</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~841026</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The major goal of this project is the operation of the Telescope Array Observatory, its low energy extension (TALE), and its new high energy expansion (TAx4).&nbsp; The TAx4 SD expansion remained under construction and commissioning during this project.&nbsp; These three components of the project make measurements on cosmic rays arriving at the Earth with energies between 3x10^15eV and about 10^21eV.&nbsp;</p> <p>The Telescope Array (with TALE and TAx4) consists of an array of 860 scintillator detectors and three telescope stations that observe the sky over these detectors.&nbsp; Each scintillator detector is 3 square meters in area and they are presently sprinkled across about 750 square miles of desert in central Utah. These detectors sample the charge distribution at the Earth?s surface from a shower of particles initiated when a cosmic ray collides with an oxygen or nitrogen molecule in the upper atmosphere.&nbsp; By looking at the charge distribution and the timing information of the detectors hit by the shower, we can determine the arrival direction of the initial cosmic ray and its original energy.&nbsp;</p> <p>We have installed 60 fixed direction telescopes observing the skies over the surface array from three sites on the periphery of the array.&nbsp; &nbsp;These telescopes observe the ultraviolet light generated when the shower of charged particles excites the atmospheric gases they are traversing.&nbsp; The telescopes observe the development of the air shower as it passes through the atmosphere; first seeing the light grow with the number of particles and then decay as the energy per particle drops.&nbsp; From the location and amount of light as well as its timing information, we determine the arrival direction and energy of the incoming particle as well as information indicating its chemical composition.&nbsp;</p> <p>The components of the Telescope Array measure the properties of cosmic rays over five orders of magnitude in energy.&nbsp; At the low energy end, our measurements overlap with those of the IceTop and Kascade-Grande and almost reach down to the direct measurements of cosmic rays by experiments such as ISS-CREAM.&nbsp; &nbsp;At 3x10^15eV the sources of cosmic rays are of galactic origin and the cosmic rays are beginning a rigidity (magnetic confinement) cut-off.&nbsp;&nbsp; First protons and helium are leaking out of the galaxy. As the energy of the particles increases, particles of greater and greater charge begin to escape the magnetic confinement. &nbsp;Eventually, galactic iron is leaking out and extra-galactic protons are leaking into the galaxy.&nbsp; &nbsp;At the highest energies, the cosmic rays interact with the cosmic microwave background photons which limits their propagation distance.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>To understand this picture, one must make measurements of the cosmic ray energy spectrum as well as the chemical composition of cosmic rays as a function of energy.&nbsp; Meanwhile, at the highest energies, the tracks of the particles should experience the smallest magnetic bending.&nbsp;&nbsp; Thus, these particles can be used to search for sources of cosmic rays.</p> <h3>Surface Detector Operations</h3> <p>The TA experiment has been in routine observation mode since the spring of 2008.&nbsp; The TA SD has achieved data-taking efficiency of better than 97%, We operate all SD units, as close to full efficiency as possible.&nbsp; Due to COVID-19, and the inability of our collaborators to travel, the Utah group has had to try to maintain all SDs by itself.&nbsp; With detectors now spread over an area approaching the size Rhode Island, this has led to some loss of efficiency.</p> <h3>Fluorescence Detector Operations</h3> <p>Over the past 12 years, TA telescopes have averaged more than 840 hours of good-weather data<em>. </em>Since COVID, March 2020, our foreign collaborators have been unable to travel to operator/maintain the detectors and the main Black Rock and Long Ridge telescopes have been idled due to their large shutters.&nbsp; However, we have continued to operate the Middle Drum telescopes including the TALE and TAx4 telescopes.&nbsp;&nbsp; We have also operated the Black Rock TAx4 telescopes with their smaller shutters.&nbsp; Where we used to operate with two people at Middle Drum, we currently operate with one person on-site and a second person online via Zoom as part of our COVID safety protocol.&nbsp; The Utah group is also responsible for maintenance and repairs of the 28 telescopes at Middle Drum as well as the 8 TAx4 telescopes at Black Rock.&nbsp;</p> <h3>Facility Management and Maintenance</h3> <p>As the host, the University of Utah group has the primary responsibility for the management of all TA facilities in Utah, including all three FD sites, the SD scintillator array, the Central Laser Facility (CLF), and the Watson Cosmic Ray Center (CRC) in Delta.&nbsp; The CRC serves both as a visitor center as well as the local workshop, storage, and staging area.&nbsp; TA facilities are located in remote areas without paved roads, power lines, or public wideband Internet service.</p> <p>Results and outreach are detailed&nbsp; in the Telescope Array Baseline Report.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/28/2021<br>      Modified by: John&nbsp;N&nbsp;Matthews</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2012934/2012934_10703404_1638125389868_Outcomes-I1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2012934/2012934_10703404_1638125389868_Outcomes-I1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Telescope Array Map"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2012934/2012934_10703404_1638125389868_Outcomes-I1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Telescope Array Map"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Map showing the locations of the Telescope Array scintillator detectors and telescope stations.   The 1800 square km observatory is  currently under expansion and will soon be more than 2900 square km in area.  the observatory is located in central Utah, USA</div> <div class="imageCredit">Stan Thomas - Telescope Array</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">John&nbsp;N&nbsp;Matthews</div> <div class="imageTitle">Telescope Array Map</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2012934/2012934_10703404_1638126899182_Outcomes-I2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2012934/2012934_10703404_1638126899182_Outcomes-I2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="The Telescope Array Detectors"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2012934/2012934_10703404_1638126899182_Outcomes-I2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="The Telescope Array Detectors"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The telescope stations, telescopes, scintillator array, and scintillator detectors of the Telescope Array observatory. The Telescope Array currently samples cosmic ray induced air showers over an area approaching the size of Rhode Island. It is located in central Utah in Millard & Juab Counties.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Charles Jui, Telescope Array</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">John&nbsp;N&nbsp;Matthews</div> <div class="imageTitle">The Telescope Array Detectors</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2012934/2012934_10703404_1638137883373_Outcomes-I3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2012934/2012934_10703404_1638137883373_Outcomes-I3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Highest Energy Event - Event Display"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2012934/2012934_10703404_1638137883373_Outcomes-I3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Highest Energy Event - Event Display"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The highest energy event observed by a surface detector was recently observed by the Telescope Array.  Its energy 2.4x10^20 eV is approaching that of the "Oh-My-God" particle (3.2 x 10^20eV) observed in 1991 by Utah fluorescence telescopes.  Events at these highest energies are quite rare.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Toshihero Fujii - Telescope Array</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">John&nbsp;N&nbsp;Matthews</div> <div class="imageTitle">Highest Energy Event - Event Display</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2012934/2012934_10703404_1638139725867_Outcomes-I4b--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2012934/2012934_10703404_1638139725867_Outcomes-I4b--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Comic Ray Spectrum and Composition"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2012934/2012934_10703404_1638139725867_Outcomes-I4b--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Comic Ray Spectrum and Composition"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Plot of the cosmic ray energy spectrum from 10^15.3 to 10^20.4eV with multiple features.  Cosmic Ray X_max elongation and Composition via X_mas mean and width distributions.  The Telescope Array finds a composition that is light in the energy range 10^18.2 - 10^19 eV.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Tareq AbuZayyad and William Hanlon - Telescope Array</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">John&nbsp;N&nbsp;Matthews</div> <div class="imageTitle">Comic Ray Spectrum and Composition</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2012934/2012934_10703404_1638148077325_Outcomes-I6--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2012934/2012934_10703404_1638148077325_Outcomes-I6--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Excess of Events from Persus Pieces"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2012934/2012934_10703404_1638148077325_Outcomes-I6--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Excess of Events from Persus Pieces"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">An excess of comic rays has been observed coming from the direction of the Perseus-Pieces super cluster.</div> <div class="imageCredit">JiHyun Kim</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">John&nbsp;N&nbsp;Matthews</div> <div class="imageTitle">Excess of Events from Persus Pieces</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The major goal of this project is the operation of the Telescope Array Observatory, its low energy extension (TALE), and its new high energy expansion (TAx4).  The TAx4 SD expansion remained under construction and commissioning during this project.  These three components of the project make measurements on cosmic rays arriving at the Earth with energies between 3x10^15eV and about 10^21eV.   The Telescope Array (with TALE and TAx4) consists of an array of 860 scintillator detectors and three telescope stations that observe the sky over these detectors.  Each scintillator detector is 3 square meters in area and they are presently sprinkled across about 750 square miles of desert in central Utah. These detectors sample the charge distribution at the Earth?s surface from a shower of particles initiated when a cosmic ray collides with an oxygen or nitrogen molecule in the upper atmosphere.  By looking at the charge distribution and the timing information of the detectors hit by the shower, we can determine the arrival direction of the initial cosmic ray and its original energy.   We have installed 60 fixed direction telescopes observing the skies over the surface array from three sites on the periphery of the array.   These telescopes observe the ultraviolet light generated when the shower of charged particles excites the atmospheric gases they are traversing.  The telescopes observe the development of the air shower as it passes through the atmosphere; first seeing the light grow with the number of particles and then decay as the energy per particle drops.  From the location and amount of light as well as its timing information, we determine the arrival direction and energy of the incoming particle as well as information indicating its chemical composition.   The components of the Telescope Array measure the properties of cosmic rays over five orders of magnitude in energy.  At the low energy end, our measurements overlap with those of the IceTop and Kascade-Grande and almost reach down to the direct measurements of cosmic rays by experiments such as ISS-CREAM.   At 3x10^15eV the sources of cosmic rays are of galactic origin and the cosmic rays are beginning a rigidity (magnetic confinement) cut-off.   First protons and helium are leaking out of the galaxy. As the energy of the particles increases, particles of greater and greater charge begin to escape the magnetic confinement.  Eventually, galactic iron is leaking out and extra-galactic protons are leaking into the galaxy.   At the highest energies, the cosmic rays interact with the cosmic microwave background photons which limits their propagation distance.    To understand this picture, one must make measurements of the cosmic ray energy spectrum as well as the chemical composition of cosmic rays as a function of energy.  Meanwhile, at the highest energies, the tracks of the particles should experience the smallest magnetic bending.   Thus, these particles can be used to search for sources of cosmic rays. Surface Detector Operations  The TA experiment has been in routine observation mode since the spring of 2008.  The TA SD has achieved data-taking efficiency of better than 97%, We operate all SD units, as close to full efficiency as possible.  Due to COVID-19, and the inability of our collaborators to travel, the Utah group has had to try to maintain all SDs by itself.  With detectors now spread over an area approaching the size Rhode Island, this has led to some loss of efficiency. Fluorescence Detector Operations  Over the past 12 years, TA telescopes have averaged more than 840 hours of good-weather data. Since COVID, March 2020, our foreign collaborators have been unable to travel to operator/maintain the detectors and the main Black Rock and Long Ridge telescopes have been idled due to their large shutters.  However, we have continued to operate the Middle Drum telescopes including the TALE and TAx4 telescopes.   We have also operated the Black Rock TAx4 telescopes with their smaller shutters.  Where we used to operate with two people at Middle Drum, we currently operate with one person on-site and a second person online via Zoom as part of our COVID safety protocol.  The Utah group is also responsible for maintenance and repairs of the 28 telescopes at Middle Drum as well as the 8 TAx4 telescopes at Black Rock.  Facility Management and Maintenance  As the host, the University of Utah group has the primary responsibility for the management of all TA facilities in Utah, including all three FD sites, the SD scintillator array, the Central Laser Facility (CLF), and the Watson Cosmic Ray Center (CRC) in Delta.  The CRC serves both as a visitor center as well as the local workshop, storage, and staging area.  TA facilities are located in remote areas without paved roads, power lines, or public wideband Internet service.  Results and outreach are detailed  in the Telescope Array Baseline Report.       Last Modified: 11/28/2021       Submitted by: John N Matthews]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
