<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[NSF INCLUDES Planning Grant: Building Cybersecurity Inclusive Pathways towards Higher Education and Research (CIPHER)]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>100000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>100000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div. of Equity for Excellence in STEM</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Michelle Rogers</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mlrogers@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032920000</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This NSF INCLUDES planning grant is funded by NSF Inclusion across the Nation of Communities of Learners of Underrepresented Discoverers in Engineering and Science (NSF INCLUDES), a comprehensive national initiative to enhance U.S. leadership in discoveries and innovations by focusing on diversity, inclusion and broadening participation in STEM at scale. The goal of this planning grant is to address cybersecurity education and training in K-16.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;As cyber threats continue to grow in sophistication, no organization or individual is immune to cyberattacks. On one hand, there is a widening skills gap. Unfilled cybersecurity jobs are expected to reach 1.8 million by 2022, as reported by the Center for Cyber Safety and Education. On the other hand, the cybersecurity education and training institutions in the nation have found it difficult to keep pace with the growing demand for cyber talent. There exists a significant gap between K-12 and college education in cybersecurity. Moreover, it is deeply challenging to achieve diversity and inclusion given the highly technical and interdisciplinary nature of cybersecurity. Lack of partnership and coordination between education institutions further leads to gaps in the nation’s current cybersecurity education landscape. The project aims to pave the way for a national alliance for building Cybersecurity Inclusive Pathways towards Higher Education and Research (CIPHER), that will focus on a researcher-practitioner partnership for the development of fundamental, theoretically-grounded, and systematic approaches to inclusive K-16 cybersecurity education, especially for students with low socioeconomic status (SES). This project will directly benefit at least 10 school districts (with a total of 175,163 students) and a dozen colleges and universities. In the long term, it will provide essential support to inclusive cybersecurity workforce development, mitigating the massive workforce shortage and leading to long-lasting positive impacts on the national economy and social diversity. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project includes a series of planning activities to engage a full spectrum of stakeholders and prepare the groundwork for establishing CIPHER. Scholars from multiple disciplines and practitioners from multiple fields will work together to fully understand the problems and explore the design space. It will lead to fundamental findings about what administrators, educators, counselors, and parents need to know and be able to do to support cybersecurity education. The outcomes include the establishment of a CIPHER researcher-practitioner partnership that engages all stakeholders, deep understanding about the current knowledge and infrastructure gap, and creation of an inclusive model for K-16 cybersecurity education, which can be replicated national-wide for bringing cybersecurity education to all students. The project will develop a range of effective ways including online resources to engage underrepresented or underserved communities. This endeavor will lead to broader and profound impacts, reshaping the landscape of K-16 cybersecurity education in the nation.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/22/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/12/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2012941</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Hongyi</FirstName>
<LastName>Wu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Hongyi Wu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mhwu@arizona.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000184931</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/22/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Chunsheng</FirstName>
<LastName>Xin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Chunsheng Xin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[cxin@odu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000175150</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/22/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Danella</FirstName>
<LastName>Zhao</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Danella Zhao</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[dzhao@odu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000168560</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/22/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate>04/12/2022</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Karen</FirstName>
<LastName>Sanzo</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Karen Sanzo</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ksanzo@odu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000633935</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/22/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Brian</FirstName>
<LastName>Payne</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Brian Payne</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[bpayne@odu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000713084</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/22/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Old Dominion University Research Foundation</Name>
<CityName>NORFOLK</CityName>
<ZipCode>235082561</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7576834293</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4111 MONARCH WAY</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[STE 204]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>VA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>DSLXBD7UWRV6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OLD DOMINION UNIVERSITY RESEARCH FOUNDATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>X6KEFGLHSJX7</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Old Dominion University]]></Name>
<CityName>Norfolk</CityName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>235290001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5115 Hampton Blvd.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>VA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>032Y</Code>
<Text>Eddie Bernice Johnson INCLUDES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0420</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~100000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Through our work we explored the following questions in order to understand how to create a diverse and inclusive K-16 cybersecurity pipeline.</p> <ul> <li>Challenges in implementation: Where to fit cybersecurity into the K-12 curricula? How to ensure time allocation? How to ensure resources and infrastructure in different&nbsp;schools?</li> <li>Challenge&nbsp;in&nbsp;student&nbsp;access:&nbsp;How&nbsp;to&nbsp;ensure&nbsp;students&nbsp;with&nbsp;different&nbsp;socioeconomic&nbsp;status&nbsp;(SES) to have equal access to curricula, teachers, resources and infrastructure needed for cybersecurity education? How to assess students and support student mobility (especially for the areas with high concentration of low SES students and military&nbsp;families)?</li> <li>Challenge&nbsp;in&nbsp;teacher&nbsp;preparation:&nbsp;How&nbsp;to&nbsp;ensure&nbsp;teachers&nbsp;to&nbsp;have&nbsp;access&nbsp;to&nbsp;solid&nbsp;cybersecurity curriculum and learning resources? How to prepare competent teachers to have sufficient knowledge to teach learning modules and increase students' interest in&nbsp;cybersecurity?</li> <li>What are important areas to research related to this topic? What do&nbsp;<em>you</em>&nbsp;want to know about related to diversifying the cybersecurity pipeline?</li> <li>What are barriers to ensuring a diverse cybersecurity pipeline, starting at the K-12 level and bridging to higher education?</li> <li>Who should be involved in CIPHER in school districts?&nbsp;</li> </ul> <p>We also leveraged our project meetings with numerous stakeholders to explore a Networked Improvement Community model with our proposed approach.&nbsp;Through this work we have developed a proposed CIPHER Alliance structure.</p> <p>The proposed CIPHER Alliance structure will use a Networked Improvement Community (NIC) model to work with K-12 teachers and administrators, undergraduate Cybersecurity programs, and community and industry partners to engage in design-based research approaches to understand and develop a robust and diverse cybersecurity educational ecosystem. This will enable us to employ a Researcher-Practitioner Partnership approach which uses a design-based implementation method, to continually monitor the efficacy of the initiative and make real-time changes as needed. CIPHER will employ a multi-state and multi-institutional partnership model to cultivate understandings about how to develop a robust cybersecurity pipeline from the public schools into higher education and the workforce.&nbsp;</p> <p>The Networked Improvement Community (NIC) model leverages continuous improvement methods to allow NIC members to collaboratively engage in problem identification and solution development. Networked Improvement Communities seek to have a deep understanding of the challenges they are addressing, center understanding how the system impacts that issue and developing a theory of action and improvement to aid in addressing the issue.</p> <p>The following identified cross cutting challenges will be initially addressed in the state impact NICs, however through the iterative design model, it is highly probable more challenges will be identified: 1) difficulty in cultivating a diverse and inclusive cybersecurity pipeline; 2) articulation gaps across the K-16 cybersecurity spectrum; 3) a lack of K-12 pedagogical training around cybersecurity; and 4) a lack of an educational cybersecurity ecosystem involving the community of educators and cyber stakeholders. Prior to developing solutions to these challenges, state impact teams will leverage the CS Ready Framework process to further clarify the existing root cause challenges to develop the NIC Aim, as well as identify additional root causes to these challenges. Through the CS Ready Framework process, Impact Teams will design solutions to be tested out and implemented. NICs enable participants to accelerate learning through implementing collective solutions, studying differences in performance, and studying the different implementation conditions. Further, through the INNOVATE Cyber program, teams of undergraduate students in years 2-5 will focus on developing testable prototypes to address the cross-cutting challenges of Diversity and Inclusion, Articulation, Professional Development, and Community Engagement.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/07/2022<br>      Modified by: Karen&nbsp;Sanzo</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Through our work we explored the following questions in order to understand how to create a diverse and inclusive K-16 cybersecurity pipeline.  Challenges in implementation: Where to fit cybersecurity into the K-12 curricula? How to ensure time allocation? How to ensure resources and infrastructure in different schools? Challenge in student access: How to ensure students with different socioeconomic status (SES) to have equal access to curricula, teachers, resources and infrastructure needed for cybersecurity education? How to assess students and support student mobility (especially for the areas with high concentration of low SES students and military families)? Challenge in teacher preparation: How to ensure teachers to have access to solid cybersecurity curriculum and learning resources? How to prepare competent teachers to have sufficient knowledge to teach learning modules and increase students' interest in cybersecurity? What are important areas to research related to this topic? What do you want to know about related to diversifying the cybersecurity pipeline? What are barriers to ensuring a diverse cybersecurity pipeline, starting at the K-12 level and bridging to higher education? Who should be involved in CIPHER in school districts?    We also leveraged our project meetings with numerous stakeholders to explore a Networked Improvement Community model with our proposed approach. Through this work we have developed a proposed CIPHER Alliance structure.  The proposed CIPHER Alliance structure will use a Networked Improvement Community (NIC) model to work with K-12 teachers and administrators, undergraduate Cybersecurity programs, and community and industry partners to engage in design-based research approaches to understand and develop a robust and diverse cybersecurity educational ecosystem. This will enable us to employ a Researcher-Practitioner Partnership approach which uses a design-based implementation method, to continually monitor the efficacy of the initiative and make real-time changes as needed. CIPHER will employ a multi-state and multi-institutional partnership model to cultivate understandings about how to develop a robust cybersecurity pipeline from the public schools into higher education and the workforce.   The Networked Improvement Community (NIC) model leverages continuous improvement methods to allow NIC members to collaboratively engage in problem identification and solution development. Networked Improvement Communities seek to have a deep understanding of the challenges they are addressing, center understanding how the system impacts that issue and developing a theory of action and improvement to aid in addressing the issue.  The following identified cross cutting challenges will be initially addressed in the state impact NICs, however through the iterative design model, it is highly probable more challenges will be identified: 1) difficulty in cultivating a diverse and inclusive cybersecurity pipeline; 2) articulation gaps across the K-16 cybersecurity spectrum; 3) a lack of K-12 pedagogical training around cybersecurity; and 4) a lack of an educational cybersecurity ecosystem involving the community of educators and cyber stakeholders. Prior to developing solutions to these challenges, state impact teams will leverage the CS Ready Framework process to further clarify the existing root cause challenges to develop the NIC Aim, as well as identify additional root causes to these challenges. Through the CS Ready Framework process, Impact Teams will design solutions to be tested out and implemented. NICs enable participants to accelerate learning through implementing collective solutions, studying differences in performance, and studying the different implementation conditions. Further, through the INNOVATE Cyber program, teams of undergraduate students in years 2-5 will focus on developing testable prototypes to address the cross-cutting challenges of Diversity and Inclusion, Articulation, Professional Development, and Community Engagement.          Last Modified: 07/07/2022       Submitted by: Karen Sanzo]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
