<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[A novel approach for conducting transformative science through a professional meeting: the 5th Symposium on Urbanization and Stream Ecology; February 12-15, 2020; Austin, Texas]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>25550.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>25550</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Matthew Kane</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mkane@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927186</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Streams and rivers provide many services to people, including clean drinking water and commercial and recreational fisheries. In urban areas, aquatic ecosystems have been severely degraded, putting ecosystem services at risk. Maintaining these services in cities requires researchers, managers, and local stakeholders to share knowledge. The 5th Symposium on Urbanization and Stream Ecology (SUSE5) will bring together a diverse group of scientists, engineers, practitioners, landscape architects, and planners. They will share fundamental knowledge about stream ecosystems. Together, they will develop effective approaches for rehabilitating streams and rivers in urban landscapes. SUSE5 applies a new format for a professional meeting that uses case studies in Austin, Texas to generate actions with tangible benefits to people. The goal is to advance understanding and management of urban streams and to generate outcomes that benefit human wellbeing.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of SUSE5 is for participants to generate a cross-disciplinary, holistic understanding of urban stream management and rehabilitation while producing actionable draft management plans for the City of Austin. Meeting organizers will advertise broadly to groups not typically associated with aquatic ecology conferences (e.g., civil engineers, social scientists, etc.) and provide financial support to individuals from diverse disciplines and with diverse personal experiences. While plenary speakers will introduce important concepts and two poster sessions will provide opportunities to share contemporary research and management frameworks, four case studies will serve as the foundation for exchanging ideas among attendees. Participants will progress through single-discipline, interdisciplinary, and transdisciplinary groups to generate management plans through a structured process that includes site visits to ground-truth plan concepts. Ancillary activities including a social science experiment examining the benefits of multidisciplinary collaborations for addressing complex environmental problems will increase the intellectual merit of the meeting. Meeting organizers will produce a series of manuscripts and white papers detailing the outcomes of the case-studies and the effectiveness of the novel approach used by SUSE5.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/21/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/21/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2012128</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
<LastName>Smith</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>F</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Robert F Smith</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[smithr@lycoming.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000610068</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/21/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Lycoming College</Name>
<CityName>WILLIAMSPORT</CityName>
<ZipCode>177015778</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5703214101</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1 COLLEGE AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>M2D5B4MCF563</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>LYCOMING COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>N38ZNTLBB2R9</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Lycoming College]]></Name>
<CityName>Williamsport</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>177015157</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[700 College Place]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7381</Code>
<Text>Ecosystem Science</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7643</Code>
<Text>EnvS-Environmtl Sustainability</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7656</Code>
<Text>SYMBIOSIS DEF &amp; SELF RECOG</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~25550</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Streams and rivers are important natural resources that provide valuable goods and services such as drinking water, fisheries, and recreation. These goods and services, however, are imperiled due to global population growth, land development (e.g., urbanization and deforestation), and global climate change. Additionally, the potential disservices caused by streams and rivers (e.g., flooding and erosion) are commonly exacerbated by human activities such as land cover change (e.g., creation of roads and parking lots) and stream channel alterations (e.g., channelization, burial, etc.). Streams and rivers flowing through cities and towns or that drain urban catchments often exhibit a suite of ecological and geomorphic changes resulting from human influences, referred to as the ?urban stream syndrome?, that can diminish goods and services and exacerbate disservices (Walsh et al. 2005). The duality of benefits from services and harm to wellbeing from disservices through physical and social processes create an intimate connection between streams and rivers and human populations governed by complex, potentially interacting, social, political, economic, and ecological factors. Thus, managing and restoring streams in urban landscapes requires interdisciplinary approaches to developing solutions to difficult problems that evolve through time, have contradicting requirements, and are addressed with incomplete information (e.g., a ?wicked? problem).</p> <p>The 5th Symposium on Urbanization and Stream Ecology (SUSE5;<a href="https://www.urbanstreamecology.org/suse5.html"> </a><a href="https://www.urbanstreamecology.org/suse5.html">https://www.urbanstreamecology.org/suse5.html</a>) was a professional meeting (February 12-15, 2020) for students, researchers, academics, government agency personnel, non-profit personnel, citizen scientists, and local stakeholders to share knowledge about effective approaches for managing streams in urban landscapes. Unlike a typical professional meeting dominated by presentations and passive learning, SUSE5 utilized a novel approach centered on four case studies as a foundation for exchanging ideas and to generate actionable outcomes. The symposium?s central goal was to incorporate ideas from historically underrepresented groups, underscoring the need for NSF funding to reduce financial barriers that can limit inclusivity. Diversity of stakeholders and decision-makers promotes the generation of novel solutions to complex problems and equitable outcomes (Moran et al. 2019). NSF funds supported attendance by 28 attendees from underrepresented groups (including 11 stakeholders from local communities) based on their professional background or personal identity (e.g., race, gender identity, sexual preference, etc.) and who had demonstrated financial limitations (including students).</p> <p>The 180 participants worked in groups to develop draft project plans for four real-world sites in Austin, TX. The case-study approach facilitated interdisciplinary collaboration through identifying solutions to ?wicked? urban stream problems. Many of the groups included social, political, financial, and cultural considerations in their solution scoping. The real-world context was supported by the inclusion of City of Austin personnel with direct knowledge of regulatory, planning, and funding factors. Additionally, local stakeholders were involved in grass-roots conservation and community restoration in local Austin neighborhoods near each case-study site. All case-study groups developed and presented draft management plans for their case studies that were collected and reviewed by the City of Austin. This approach resulted actionable outcomes through tangible benefits to the City by 1) informing the preliminary engineering phase of projects; 2) informing new and expanded plans to integrate local stakeholders; 3) identifying unanticipated challenges and associated solutions; 4) encouraging inter- and cross-departmental coordination among City administrative levels; 5) encouraging new and expanded coordination with local stakeholders; and 6) identifying new tools for project design, implementation, and assessment. The City of Austin expanded the list of potential solutions for urban stream restoration and reconceptualized interdisciplinary priorities with expanded community engagement.</p> <p>Ultimately, SUSE5 represented a potentially transformative approach to scientific meetings examining complex socio-ecological problems that generates actionable outcomes. Local stakeholders had unique knowledge of case-study locations, and the overwhelming sentiment at the symposium was that these individuals added substantial learning opportunities for participants and were essential for providing novel perspectives on approaches for management and restoration (Scoggins et al. 2022). Overall, the outcomes from SUSE5 demonstrated how (1) interdisciplinary teams of local stakeholders, government agency personnel, academic researchers, and others can coalesce to create novel solutions to complex socio-ecological problems and (2) how professional meetings with an intentional design with diverse participants can create actionable outcomes that transcend traditional knowledge-sharing formats (Bixler et al., 2022). Twenty-two manuscripts were published in two special issues of professional journals (<a href="https://www.urbanstreamecology.org/resources--publications.html">https://www.urbanstreamecology.org/resources--publications.html</a>) that communicated (1) contemporary research in urban stream ecology and (2) novel approaches to addressing interdisciplinary problems for managing streams and rivers in urban landscapes.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Citations:</span></p> <p>Bixler et al. 2022. Exploring the connection between transdisciplinary co&#8209;production and urban sustainability solutions: a case study at an urban stream management symposium. Urban Ecosystems, 25:1207-1216.</p> <p>Scoggins et al. 2022. Community-powered urban stream restoration: A framework for sustainable and resilient urban ecosystems. Freshwater Science, 41:404-419.</p> <p>Walsh et al. 2005. The urban stream syndrome: current knowledge and the search for a cure. Journal of the North American Benthological Society, 24:706-723.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/30/2023<br>      Modified by: Robert&nbsp;F&nbsp;Smith</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Streams and rivers are important natural resources that provide valuable goods and services such as drinking water, fisheries, and recreation. These goods and services, however, are imperiled due to global population growth, land development (e.g., urbanization and deforestation), and global climate change. Additionally, the potential disservices caused by streams and rivers (e.g., flooding and erosion) are commonly exacerbated by human activities such as land cover change (e.g., creation of roads and parking lots) and stream channel alterations (e.g., channelization, burial, etc.). Streams and rivers flowing through cities and towns or that drain urban catchments often exhibit a suite of ecological and geomorphic changes resulting from human influences, referred to as the ?urban stream syndrome?, that can diminish goods and services and exacerbate disservices (Walsh et al. 2005). The duality of benefits from services and harm to wellbeing from disservices through physical and social processes create an intimate connection between streams and rivers and human populations governed by complex, potentially interacting, social, political, economic, and ecological factors. Thus, managing and restoring streams in urban landscapes requires interdisciplinary approaches to developing solutions to difficult problems that evolve through time, have contradicting requirements, and are addressed with incomplete information (e.g., a ?wicked? problem).  The 5th Symposium on Urbanization and Stream Ecology (SUSE5; https://www.urbanstreamecology.org/suse5.html) was a professional meeting (February 12-15, 2020) for students, researchers, academics, government agency personnel, non-profit personnel, citizen scientists, and local stakeholders to share knowledge about effective approaches for managing streams in urban landscapes. Unlike a typical professional meeting dominated by presentations and passive learning, SUSE5 utilized a novel approach centered on four case studies as a foundation for exchanging ideas and to generate actionable outcomes. The symposium?s central goal was to incorporate ideas from historically underrepresented groups, underscoring the need for NSF funding to reduce financial barriers that can limit inclusivity. Diversity of stakeholders and decision-makers promotes the generation of novel solutions to complex problems and equitable outcomes (Moran et al. 2019). NSF funds supported attendance by 28 attendees from underrepresented groups (including 11 stakeholders from local communities) based on their professional background or personal identity (e.g., race, gender identity, sexual preference, etc.) and who had demonstrated financial limitations (including students).  The 180 participants worked in groups to develop draft project plans for four real-world sites in Austin, TX. The case-study approach facilitated interdisciplinary collaboration through identifying solutions to ?wicked? urban stream problems. Many of the groups included social, political, financial, and cultural considerations in their solution scoping. The real-world context was supported by the inclusion of City of Austin personnel with direct knowledge of regulatory, planning, and funding factors. Additionally, local stakeholders were involved in grass-roots conservation and community restoration in local Austin neighborhoods near each case-study site. All case-study groups developed and presented draft management plans for their case studies that were collected and reviewed by the City of Austin. This approach resulted actionable outcomes through tangible benefits to the City by 1) informing the preliminary engineering phase of projects; 2) informing new and expanded plans to integrate local stakeholders; 3) identifying unanticipated challenges and associated solutions; 4) encouraging inter- and cross-departmental coordination among City administrative levels; 5) encouraging new and expanded coordination with local stakeholders; and 6) identifying new tools for project design, implementation, and assessment. The City of Austin expanded the list of potential solutions for urban stream restoration and reconceptualized interdisciplinary priorities with expanded community engagement.  Ultimately, SUSE5 represented a potentially transformative approach to scientific meetings examining complex socio-ecological problems that generates actionable outcomes. Local stakeholders had unique knowledge of case-study locations, and the overwhelming sentiment at the symposium was that these individuals added substantial learning opportunities for participants and were essential for providing novel perspectives on approaches for management and restoration (Scoggins et al. 2022). Overall, the outcomes from SUSE5 demonstrated how (1) interdisciplinary teams of local stakeholders, government agency personnel, academic researchers, and others can coalesce to create novel solutions to complex socio-ecological problems and (2) how professional meetings with an intentional design with diverse participants can create actionable outcomes that transcend traditional knowledge-sharing formats (Bixler et al., 2022). Twenty-two manuscripts were published in two special issues of professional journals (https://www.urbanstreamecology.org/resources--publications.html) that communicated (1) contemporary research in urban stream ecology and (2) novel approaches to addressing interdisciplinary problems for managing streams and rivers in urban landscapes.     Citations:  Bixler et al. 2022. Exploring the connection between transdisciplinary co&#8209;production and urban sustainability solutions: a case study at an urban stream management symposium. Urban Ecosystems, 25:1207-1216.  Scoggins et al. 2022. Community-powered urban stream restoration: A framework for sustainable and resilient urban ecosystems. Freshwater Science, 41:404-419.  Walsh et al. 2005. The urban stream syndrome: current knowledge and the search for a cure. Journal of the North American Benthological Society, 24:706-723.       Last Modified: 04/30/2023       Submitted by: Robert F Smith]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
