<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[The 6th Midwest Single Molecule Workshop; August, 2020; Omaha Nebraska]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>25250.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>25250</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>MCB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jaroslaw Majewski</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jmajewsk@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927278</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This award provides support for students and post-doctoral associates to attend the 6th Midwest Single Molecule Workshop being held in Omaha, Nebraska, August of 2020. Single molecule biophysics techniques make it possible to observe the transient interactions, multiple structural states, and dynamics of biological molecules and their assemblies.  The applications of single-molecule techniques are rapidly expanding, and a constant exchange of ideas is essential to ensure further developments. Topics to be covered at the workshop include direct visualization of molecular dynamics with high-speed atomic force spectroscopy, single molecule fluorescence, single molecule detection, and optical and magnetic tweezers. The two-day meeting will include invited lectures, poster presentations, short talks, and a keynote address – all organized into thematic sections focused on a specific single-molecule methodology. The meeting will provide an essential professional development opportunity for young scientists and expose undergraduate students to timely research topics. Abstracts of the subjects covered will be compiled for a conference booklet.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/21/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/21/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2012136</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yuri</FirstName>
<LastName>Lyubchenko</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Yuri Lyubchenko</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ylyubchenko@unmc.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000685778</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/21/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alexey</FirstName>
<LastName>Krasnoslobodtsev</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>V</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alexey V Krasnoslobodtsev</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[akrasnos@unomaha.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000706895</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/21/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Nebraska Medical Center</Name>
<CityName>Omaha</CityName>
<ZipCode>681987835</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4025597456</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>987835 Nebraska Medical Center</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Nebraska</StateName>
<StateCode>NE</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NE02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>G15AG3BLLMH4</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>BOARD OF REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF NEBRASKA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>LF77GRM3FWG5</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Nebraska Medical Center]]></Name>
<CityName>Omaha</CityName>
<StateCode>NE</StateCode>
<ZipCode>681987835</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[987835 Nebraska Medical Center]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Nebraska</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NE02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1144</Code>
<Text>Molecular Biophysics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7465</Code>
<Text>NANOSCALE BIO CORE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~25250</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The 6th Midwest Single Molecule Workshop continued the tradition of previous workshops by gathering the leading experts and researchers in single-molecule biophysics from across the Midwest and surrounding areas to share their latest research, discoveries and ideas as well as communicate with peers involved in single molecule studies.<br /><br />The two-day meeting (August 1-2, 2022) featured a wide variety of topics and presenters, including invited lectures, poster presentations, short talks and a keynote address. The program covered all aspects of single molecule biophysics, including experimental and theoretical approaches and the application of these methods to single molecule studies ranging from isolated individual molecules to whole cells.<br /><br />By the tradition, the workshop venue moves between different Midwestern universities. This time, the meeting took place at UNMC, co-organized by Professor Yuri Lyubchenko and Dr. Mohtadin Hashemi. The past five workshops, held at Washington University in St. Louis (2010), University of Michigan at Ann Arbor (2012), University of Illinois at Urbana Champaign (2014), University of Iowa (2016), and Iowa State University (2018) were very popular, and each attracted over 100 participants.</p> <p>The total number&nbsp;attendees&nbsp;of the 6th Midwest Single Molecule Workshop was very similar to the previous meetings. Specifically,&nbsp;excluding the sponsors (13) the total number of participants was 101. Among them:</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Number of students: 46</p> <p>Number of PostDocs: 17</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>With the support of MDPI publisher, awards to students and postdocs were arranged.</p> <p>Number of student awards: 2, Poster and Presentation</p> <p>Number of PostDoc awards: 2, Poster and Presentation</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Number of academic institutes represented: 16</p> <p>Number of companies that sent representatives: 5</p> <p>Number of sponsors excluding academic (3): 6</p> <p>In addition, for this 6th Workshop a&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mdpi.com/journal/ijms/special_issues/single_molecule_studies" target="_blank">Special Issue in the International Journal of Molecular Sciences</a>&nbsp;has been established. A large number of participants including the invited speakers have submitted their findings to the Special Issue. The MDPI publisher provided a substantial discount for submissions to this Special Issue.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/30/2023<br>      Modified by: Yuri&nbsp;Lyubchenko</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The 6th Midwest Single Molecule Workshop continued the tradition of previous workshops by gathering the leading experts and researchers in single-molecule biophysics from across the Midwest and surrounding areas to share their latest research, discoveries and ideas as well as communicate with peers involved in single molecule studies.  The two-day meeting (August 1-2, 2022) featured a wide variety of topics and presenters, including invited lectures, poster presentations, short talks and a keynote address. The program covered all aspects of single molecule biophysics, including experimental and theoretical approaches and the application of these methods to single molecule studies ranging from isolated individual molecules to whole cells.  By the tradition, the workshop venue moves between different Midwestern universities. This time, the meeting took place at UNMC, co-organized by Professor Yuri Lyubchenko and Dr. Mohtadin Hashemi. The past five workshops, held at Washington University in St. Louis (2010), University of Michigan at Ann Arbor (2012), University of Illinois at Urbana Champaign (2014), University of Iowa (2016), and Iowa State University (2018) were very popular, and each attracted over 100 participants.  The total number attendees of the 6th Midwest Single Molecule Workshop was very similar to the previous meetings. Specifically, excluding the sponsors (13) the total number of participants was 101. Among them:     Number of students: 46  Number of PostDocs: 17     With the support of MDPI publisher, awards to students and postdocs were arranged.  Number of student awards: 2, Poster and Presentation  Number of PostDoc awards: 2, Poster and Presentation     Number of academic institutes represented: 16  Number of companies that sent representatives: 5  Number of sponsors excluding academic (3): 6  In addition, for this 6th Workshop a Special Issue in the International Journal of Molecular Sciences has been established. A large number of participants including the invited speakers have submitted their findings to the Special Issue. The MDPI publisher provided a substantial discount for submissions to this Special Issue.          Last Modified: 03/30/2023       Submitted by: Yuri Lyubchenko]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
