<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[NSF INCLUDES Planning Grant: Exploring a Collaborative Model for Broadening Participation in STEM through Digital Fabrication and Making]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>100000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>100000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div. of Equity for Excellence in STEM</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Alicia Santiago Gonzalez</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>asantiag@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924546</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Over the past two decades, thousands of makerspaces, fabrication labs, and digital fabrication spaces have emerged. From libraries and science centers to institutions of higher education, the “Maker Movement” continues to gain momentum and is recognized globally as being at the nexus of technology, innovation, and education.  This mounting interest may be in part due to promising findings from extant research. Prevailing studies show meaningful engagement in making and digital fabrication can result in marked positive outcomes in STEM interest and careers, especially in engineering and manufacturing fields. Some studies have also shown that while outcomes are generally positive, there continues to be a diverse community of learners who appear to be under-engaged and or excluded from participation. This planning grant will address this gap by creating and fostering a diverse coalition of organizations to work together, and with their respective networks of influence, to design for and promote innovative, accessible, inclusive, and equitable high-quality STEM learning environments for all learners through the lens of making and digital fabrication. Through a multi-modal, lived cultural experience framework, the coalition hopes to develop a plan for a strategic, coherent and scalable approach that moves the bar significantly forward in addressing equity in STEM. The effort brings together key stakeholders in the Maker, Fab Lab, Digital Fabrication, and STEM Education movements to create a shared vision and action plan that ignites a broader, more inclusive group of stakeholders in education, both formal and informal. The initial cohort of organizations will include the key national and international organizations Citizen Schools, Digital Promise, Fab Foundation, FabLearn, Maker Ed and Nation of Makers to begin the process of creating a shared vision, and communicating that vision throughout their networks to a broader and more diverse community of stakeholders.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;During the one-year project duration, project partners will leverage existing expertise and networks to work collectively to identify and pioneer effective culturally relevant making practices and policies that increase STEM engagement and success among underrepresented groups. Efforts will be centered on two of the five NSF INCLUDES design elements of collaborative infrastructure: Shared Vision and Leadership and Communication. In tandem with developing a common agenda, the Shared Vision component will include several reinforcing activities: (1) map and analyze relevant current programming, (2) establish a set of agreed upon equity and inclusion specific definitions, (3) identify strategies for recognizing existing funds of knowledge among learners, and (4) develop a strategic plan of action. Reinforcing activities for the Leadership and Communication component will include: (1) the establishment of a collaborative support model and operations protocol, (2) documentation and exchange of practices across organizational programming, and (3) a joint publication/policy white paper on the state of broadening participation in making and digital fabrication contexts. To ground this work, an equity and inclusion workshop will be held for partner organizations to promote shared understanding and collective impact. In addition, intentional connections will be made to the NSF INCLUDES National Network through knowledge, data, and resource sharing, networking, and participation in the online community. If successful, this planning grant has the potential to lay a strong foundation for a future large-scale center, alliance, or network focused on broadening participation in STEM through making and digital fabrication. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This planning grant is funded by NSF Inclusion across the Nation of Communities of Learners of Underrepresented Discoverers in Engineering and Science (NSF INCLUDES), a comprehensive national initiative to enhance U.S. leadership in discoveries and innovations by focusing on diversity, inclusion and broadening participation in STEM at scale.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/22/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/22/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2012790</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sonya</FirstName>
<LastName>Pryor-Jones</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sonya M Pryor-Jones</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[sonya@fabfoundation.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000808314</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/22/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sherry</FirstName>
<LastName>Lassiter</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sherry J Lassiter</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[Sherry.Lassiter@cba.mit.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000612911</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/22/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>The Fab Foundation</Name>
<CityName>BOSTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>021095002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6173314659</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>50 MILK ST 16TH FL</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>KP4KRT4KJ6B5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>FAB FOUNDATION, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[The Fab Foundation]]></Name>
<CityName>Boston</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021095002</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[50 Milk Street, 16th Floor]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>032Y</Code>
<Text>Eddie Bernice Johnson INCLUDES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0420</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~100000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The outcomes of the planning grant, <em>Exploring a Collaborative Model for Broadening Participation in STEM through Digital Fabrication and Making </em>were establishing a shared vision and action agenda amongst six leading maker education organizations to address issues of advocacy, adoption, quality, and sustainability related to broadening participation in STEM, and more specifically digital fabrication and making. These organizations included:&nbsp; Citizen Schools, Digital Promise, FabLearn (Teachers College, Columbia University), &nbsp;Fab Foundation, &nbsp;MakerEd and Nation of Makers, all of which have formed an informal coalition under the name of Field Building Collaborative (FBC).</p> <p>Deliverables and outcomes were driven by the two INCLUDES design elements of collaborative infrastructure: Shared Vision, and Leadership and Communication.</p> <p><strong><em>Shared Vision Outcomes</em></strong></p> <p>The FBC engaged the Anti-Oppression Resource and Training Alliance (AORTA) organization as our Professional Development consultant to help us develop: (1) &nbsp;a shared Theory of Change/Principles of Unity, (2) decision making processes, (3) an equity checklist representing group norms and agreements for working together and (4) a strategic mapping. Through a series of professional development workshops and focus groups we progressed on all 4 goals.&nbsp; We determined our decision making process, created a MOU and Bylaws for a potential future formal collaboration, created a an equity checklist as well as a strategic mapping that identifies the focus areas and assets of the FBC organizations that will help shape strategies to execute and offer to the field of digital fabrication and maker learning for broadening participation for underserved communities.&nbsp;</p> <p><strong><em>Leadership and Communication Outcomes</em></strong></p> <p>The FBC wrote a policy paper, &nbsp;a white paper, engaged the broader STEM and maker community through conference workshops and information sharing,&nbsp; and developed a set of tools for equity based storytelling to raise the awareness around making and digital fabrication in marginalized communities. &nbsp;</p> <p><em>White Paper</em></p> <p>The white paper, entitled <em>Transforming Public Education with Making and Digital Fabrication </em>was written by a subgroup of the FBC. The paper summarizes the history of the maker movement, the current status of maker education and projects a path forward to adoption, quality, and sustainability related to broadening participation in STEM, and more specifically digital fabrication and making. The paper is framed in equity-based story-telling crediting the rich diversity of people and cultures that have contributed to the growth of the maker movement and digital fabrication, yet have not been recognized as part of the innovation and leadership that has built the movement to its status today.&nbsp;</p> <p><em>Policy Paper</em></p> <p>The policy paper,&nbsp;<em>Making Public Schools Places of Innovation in the 21st Century</em>, was written initially for the Day One Project, a project aimed at democratizing the policy making process, by leveraging the &nbsp;voices of experts and activists across the science and technology community to set legislative agendas.</p> <p>The policy paper recommends ?that the new administration implement a multi-pronged approach to bring&nbsp; maker-centered learning environments to K-12 students throughout the United States, that builds on existing infrastructure and focuses on: (1) spearheading and promoting a national campaign on the role of making in our daily lives and the workforce, (2) increasing access to maker and digital fabrication professional development training for K-12 educators, and (3) incentivizing public-private partnerships to expand access to the tools and resources for maker-centered learning curricula and spaces.? [FBC: 2021a]&nbsp;</p> <p><em>Website and Equity Storytelling</em></p> <p>FBC member organizations partnered with Dr. Monica White of Grand Pearl Communications to provide a professional development workshop series focused on equity-based storytelling.&nbsp; &nbsp;Each organization was asked to conduct and document two interviews around equity in maker-centered learning. We documented the interviews in different ways, and provided these interviews as the foundational content for a new website for the FBC.&nbsp; &nbsp;</p> <p>The FBC partnered with a minority-owned website development organization, Emerson Soto Consulting to create a website that provides tools for equity based storytelling:&nbsp;&nbsp;<a href="http://buildfabmake.org/">http://buildfabmake.org</a></p> <p><em>Promoting, listening and learning</em></p> <p>During the year, the FBC promoted the FBC and tapped different related communities to listen and learn, by hosting a few workshops and presentations -- providing opportunities to discuss critical questions around the future of digital fabrication and maker education.</p> <p>The two conferences in which the FBC held workshops and presented the work and learning sessions were the FABxLIve 2020 Conference (the annual Fab Lab Network international conference) and the ASTC Virtual 2020 Conference (the annual Association of Science and Technology Centers conference.) The presentations challenged participants with key questions around maker education and how the community might best move this work forward.<em>&nbsp;</em></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>In conclusion, to create inclusive and equitable and multiple pathways for organizations and communities to participate in the FBC, we have designed strategies for stakeholders to engage with these efforts in ways that accommodate different levels of commitment and acknowledge differences in capacity and resources that stakeholders may have at any given time.&nbsp;&nbsp;Our strategic planning continues, as we add membership and leadership and continue to design our future collaboration.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/03/2022<br>      Modified by: Sherry&nbsp;J&nbsp;Lassiter</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The outcomes of the planning grant, Exploring a Collaborative Model for Broadening Participation in STEM through Digital Fabrication and Making were establishing a shared vision and action agenda amongst six leading maker education organizations to address issues of advocacy, adoption, quality, and sustainability related to broadening participation in STEM, and more specifically digital fabrication and making. These organizations included:  Citizen Schools, Digital Promise, FabLearn (Teachers College, Columbia University),  Fab Foundation,  MakerEd and Nation of Makers, all of which have formed an informal coalition under the name of Field Building Collaborative (FBC).  Deliverables and outcomes were driven by the two INCLUDES design elements of collaborative infrastructure: Shared Vision, and Leadership and Communication.  Shared Vision Outcomes  The FBC engaged the Anti-Oppression Resource and Training Alliance (AORTA) organization as our Professional Development consultant to help us develop: (1)  a shared Theory of Change/Principles of Unity, (2) decision making processes, (3) an equity checklist representing group norms and agreements for working together and (4) a strategic mapping. Through a series of professional development workshops and focus groups we progressed on all 4 goals.  We determined our decision making process, created a MOU and Bylaws for a potential future formal collaboration, created a an equity checklist as well as a strategic mapping that identifies the focus areas and assets of the FBC organizations that will help shape strategies to execute and offer to the field of digital fabrication and maker learning for broadening participation for underserved communities.   Leadership and Communication Outcomes  The FBC wrote a policy paper,  a white paper, engaged the broader STEM and maker community through conference workshops and information sharing,  and developed a set of tools for equity based storytelling to raise the awareness around making and digital fabrication in marginalized communities.    White Paper  The white paper, entitled Transforming Public Education with Making and Digital Fabrication was written by a subgroup of the FBC. The paper summarizes the history of the maker movement, the current status of maker education and projects a path forward to adoption, quality, and sustainability related to broadening participation in STEM, and more specifically digital fabrication and making. The paper is framed in equity-based story-telling crediting the rich diversity of people and cultures that have contributed to the growth of the maker movement and digital fabrication, yet have not been recognized as part of the innovation and leadership that has built the movement to its status today.   Policy Paper  The policy paper, Making Public Schools Places of Innovation in the 21st Century, was written initially for the Day One Project, a project aimed at democratizing the policy making process, by leveraging the  voices of experts and activists across the science and technology community to set legislative agendas.  The policy paper recommends ?that the new administration implement a multi-pronged approach to bring  maker-centered learning environments to K-12 students throughout the United States, that builds on existing infrastructure and focuses on: (1) spearheading and promoting a national campaign on the role of making in our daily lives and the workforce, (2) increasing access to maker and digital fabrication professional development training for K-12 educators, and (3) incentivizing public-private partnerships to expand access to the tools and resources for maker-centered learning curricula and spaces.? [FBC: 2021a]   Website and Equity Storytelling  FBC member organizations partnered with Dr. Monica White of Grand Pearl Communications to provide a professional development workshop series focused on equity-based storytelling.   Each organization was asked to conduct and document two interviews around equity in maker-centered learning. We documented the interviews in different ways, and provided these interviews as the foundational content for a new website for the FBC.     The FBC partnered with a minority-owned website development organization, Emerson Soto Consulting to create a website that provides tools for equity based storytelling:  http://buildfabmake.org  Promoting, listening and learning  During the year, the FBC promoted the FBC and tapped different related communities to listen and learn, by hosting a few workshops and presentations -- providing opportunities to discuss critical questions around the future of digital fabrication and maker education.  The two conferences in which the FBC held workshops and presented the work and learning sessions were the FABxLIve 2020 Conference (the annual Fab Lab Network international conference) and the ASTC Virtual 2020 Conference (the annual Association of Science and Technology Centers conference.) The presentations challenged participants with key questions around maker education and how the community might best move this work forward.      In conclusion, to create inclusive and equitable and multiple pathways for organizations and communities to participate in the FBC, we have designed strategies for stakeholders to engage with these efforts in ways that accommodate different levels of commitment and acknowledge differences in capacity and resources that stakeholders may have at any given time.  Our strategic planning continues, as we add membership and leadership and continue to design our future collaboration.          Last Modified: 01/03/2022       Submitted by: Sherry J Lassiter]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
