<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Doctoral Dissertation Improvement Award: Factors Which Underlie Long Term Cultural Change]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>25142.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>25142</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>John Yellen</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jyellen@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928759</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Under the supervision of Dr. Daniel Adler, Jayson Gill will study variability in stone tool (lithic) technology to test behavioral and geographic hypotheses related to the appearance of novel technologies and the the evolution of both Homo sapiens and Neanderthals. This project will test the competing hypotheses of population expansion (migration) and independent innovation for the appearance of new technologies as proposed by prior research. The researchers will apply a quantitative approach to studying the degree to which changes in technology can be attributed to cultural continuity or cultural replacement. Lithic artifact morphology reflects both cultural preferences and functional considerations, thus they represent a ubiquitous, vast, and durable record of past behaviors that can be utilized to investigate how changes occur. Clarifying how and why technology changes is essential to addressing the role that behavior plays in the complex narrative of human evolution. This project will support the doctoral training of the Co-PI (Jayson Gill) and training in quantitative techniques for students. Data produced in this study will be made freely available online as reference material and results will be widely disseminated through conference presentations, journal articles, and public engagement.  &lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;This research utilizes cultural evolutionary theory, optimality modeling, and insights from experimental assemblages to address chronological patterns in past technologies in an attempt to disentangle the effects of social transmission, functional considerations, and raw material choice on the shape of lithics. Archaeological assemblages in two regions document the appearance of novel behaviors and variability both proceeding and following this appearance. Five lithic assemblages from two regions will be subjected to three-dimensional scanning and multivariate statistical methods as a means to identify the morphological relationships between different lithic technologies through time. The results will be evaluated against the morphological expectations in competing migration and innovation hypotheses. Further, results of shape-based statistics will be assessed against expectations derived from experimental work and will identify the relationship between changes in technology and changes in the functional proficiency of tool kits against a backdrop of broad chronological changes in the environment. Morphological relationships, or the lack thereof, between technologies can serve as a proxy for the degree of regional continuity in lithic production behaviors. Establishing continuity or abrupt change, as well as identifying the factors promoting the adoption of new technologies is vital to expanding the current understanding of the role that migration, behavioral adaptation, and innovation have on group variation during this significant period in human evolution.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/05/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/05/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2012112</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
<LastName>Adler</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Daniel Adler</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[daniel.adler@uconn.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000590720</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/05/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jayson</FirstName>
<LastName>Gill</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jayson P Gill</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jayson.gill@uconn.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000814908</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/05/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Connecticut</Name>
<CityName>STORRS</CityName>
<ZipCode>062691133</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8604863622</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>438 WHITNEY RD EXTENSION UNIT 11</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CT02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>WNTPS995QBM7</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CONNECTICUT</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>D9SNFDRCW3W7</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Connecticut]]></Name>
<CityName>Storrs</CityName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>062691176</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[354 Mansfield Rd]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CT02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7606</Code>
<Text>Archaeology DDRI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1391</Code>
<Text>ARCHAEOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~25142</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Middle Pleistocene (~781&ndash;126 thousand years ago) witnesses broad changes in stone tool technologies along with the evolution of both our species <em>Homo sapiens </em>and Neanderthals.<em> </em>One of the most notable changes to stone tool technology during this period is the replacement of the large cutting tools (handaxes) of the Acheulian with the products of prepared core technology (Levallois) characteristic of the Middle Palaeolithic techno-period. This change also coincides with human expansion into diverse environments and changes to other behaviors such as hunting strategies and landuse patterns.</p> <p>Explanations for this technological change in Afro-Eurasia fall into two categories. The first set of explanations favor a single origin of prepared core technology and its spread through the migration of archaic human populations. This suggests that technology can be used to identify groups or species of human. The second set of explanations favor multiple periods of innovation of prepared core technology in different regions as an outcome of adaptations to local circumstances. This suggests that technological types do not reflect specific human groups or species. Ongoing work on this question increasingly supports the latter set of explanations. Regardless of the origin of this technology, the process of its innovation and early adaptive nature are poorly understood.</p> <p>This project combines archaeological data and experimental approaches to explore the origins, innovation, and adaptative qualities of prepared cores during marine isotope stage 9 (337&ndash;300 thousand years ago) in two regions of Eurasia, the Armenian Highlands and Britain. This project utilizes 3D scanning of artifacts in conjunction with statistical analyses to investigate the behaviors underpinning this technological shift.</p> <p>The experimental component of the project was aimed at creating a new approach to quantifying the adaptive properties of the products (flakes) of different technologies using 3D scans of the cores used to produce them. This method circumvents issues with identifying production techniques from the flakes. The method was tested using experimentally created stone tools. Results of the experimental component revealed that measurements taken on scans of cores are excellent proxies for the flake removed from them. The method was applied to archaeological assemblages from the Lower Palaeolithic site of Nor Geghi-1 in Armenia to test if the earliest iterations of Levallois prepared core technology in this region was optimal in the same way as later Middle Palaeolithic Levallois technology. The study reveals the following:</p> <p>-&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Early Levallois prepared cores at the site do not produce products with more cutting edge than other production techniques present.</p> <p>-&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Early Levallois prepared cores at the site do not produce more standardized products in terms of size or shape than other production techniques present.</p> <p>There is a disparity between these results and what has been argued for later prepared core technology in the Middle Palaeolithic. Generally, this suggests that factors driving the use of prepared core technology may have changed over time or rather that innovation and later widespread use of prepared core technology involved different adaptive considerations.</p> <p>The project&rsquo;s main component tested hypotheses about the origin and innovative process behind early prepared core technology in the Armenian Highlands and Britain. Three archaeological localities in Armenia (Hatis-1, Nor Geghi-1 south, Nor Geghi-1 north) and five in Britain (Elveden, Hoxne, Purfleet, Ebbsfleet, Creffield Road) were used in this part of the study. Both areas contain assemblages that have been used to support the local innovation of Levallois prepared cores. Statistical shape analysis of 3D scan data from the two regions was used to test for patterns of technological change to ask:</p> <p>-&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Are there patterns of change that support a local origin of prepared core technology?</p> <p>-&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; What is the process of technological evolution that leads to early prepared cores in these regions?</p> <p>The results of this part of the study are the following:</p> <p>-&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Early prepared core technology in Armenia is invented locally resulting from the evolution of both large cutting tools (handaxes) and simple cores in the underlying Acheulian technology found in the region.</p> <p>-&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Early prepared core technology in Britain is not likely to have been invented locally and may have been introduced with populations migrating into the region.</p> <p>These results broadly support the growing consensus that there are multiple origins of prepared cores. Further, this suggests that technologies during the Pleistocene make poor proxies for populations or species as their appearance can be due to convergent processes of innovation or population movement.</p> <p>As a whole, this project contributes to our understanding of behavioral evolution during the Pleistocene across regions and highlights the utility of 3D scanning for asking questions about the archaeological record while providing a new way of analyzing 3D data. Further, this research contributed to the successful completion of the co-PI&rsquo;s doctoral dissertation, along with providing training in digital methods to undergraduate students.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/26/2023<br>      Modified by: Jayson&nbsp;P&nbsp;Gill</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2012112/2012112_10656270_1689704429947_NGItech--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2012112/2012112_10656270_1689704429947_NGItech--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Armenian Artifacts"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2012112/2012112_10656270_1689704429947_NGItech--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Armenian Artifacts"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Examples of the artifact types from Armenian sites used in this study. a. Hatis-1 LCT. b. Nor Geghi-1 south LCT. c. Nor Geghi-1 north LCT. d. Nor Geghi-1 Levallois. Nor Geghi-1 SPC. Nor Geghi-1 platform core.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jayson P. Gill</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jayson&nbsp;P&nbsp;Gill</div> <div class="imageTitle">Armenian Artifacts</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2012112/2012112_10656270_1689704344062_BRITTECH--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2012112/2012112_10656270_1689704344062_BRITTECH--rgov-800width.jpg" title="British Artifacts"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2012112/2012112_10656270_1689704344062_BRITTECH--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="British Artifacts"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Examples of the artifact types from British sites used in this study. a. Elveden LCT. b. Hoxne LCT. c. Purfleet LCT. d. Purfleet Levallois core. E. Purfleet SPC. F. Purfleet platform core. g. discoid core. h. Ebbsfleet Levallois core. i. Creffield Road Levallois core.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jayson P. Gill</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jayson&nbsp;P&nbsp;Gill</div> <div class="imageTitle">British Artifacts</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2012112/2012112_10656270_1689704548892_CORESEXP--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2012112/2012112_10656270_1689704548892_CORESEXP--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Experimental Artifacts"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2012112/2012112_10656270_1689704548892_CORESEXP--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Experimental Artifacts"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">. Examples of the six core types with refitting flakes used in the experimental study: a. discoid, b. core-on-flake, c. multi-platform, d. LCT, e. hierarchical, f. prismatic blade. Core-scars used from each core are highlighted in red with refitting flakes outlined in red.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jayson P. Gill</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jayson&nbsp;P&nbsp;Gill</div> <div class="imageTitle">Experimental Artifacts</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2012112/2012112_10656270_1689704099203_Map1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2012112/2012112_10656270_1689704099203_Map1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Study Areas"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2012112/2012112_10656270_1689704099203_Map1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Study Areas"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Location of study areas in Eurasia.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jayson P. Gill</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jayson&nbsp;P&nbsp;Gill</div> <div class="imageTitle">Study Areas</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2012112/2012112_10656270_1689704180239_Map--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2012112/2012112_10656270_1689704180239_Map--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Study Areas 2"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2012112/2012112_10656270_1689704180239_Map--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Study Areas 2"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">a. British site locations. b. Armenian site locations.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jayson P. Gill</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jayson&nbsp;P&nbsp;Gill</div> <div class="imageTitle">Study Areas 2</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Middle Pleistocene (~781&ndash;126 thousand years ago) witnesses broad changes in stone tool technologies along with the evolution of both our species Homo sapiens and Neanderthals. One of the most notable changes to stone tool technology during this period is the replacement of the large cutting tools (handaxes) of the Acheulian with the products of prepared core technology (Levallois) characteristic of the Middle Palaeolithic techno-period. This change also coincides with human expansion into diverse environments and changes to other behaviors such as hunting strategies and landuse patterns.  Explanations for this technological change in Afro-Eurasia fall into two categories. The first set of explanations favor a single origin of prepared core technology and its spread through the migration of archaic human populations. This suggests that technology can be used to identify groups or species of human. The second set of explanations favor multiple periods of innovation of prepared core technology in different regions as an outcome of adaptations to local circumstances. This suggests that technological types do not reflect specific human groups or species. Ongoing work on this question increasingly supports the latter set of explanations. Regardless of the origin of this technology, the process of its innovation and early adaptive nature are poorly understood.  This project combines archaeological data and experimental approaches to explore the origins, innovation, and adaptative qualities of prepared cores during marine isotope stage 9 (337&ndash;300 thousand years ago) in two regions of Eurasia, the Armenian Highlands and Britain. This project utilizes 3D scanning of artifacts in conjunction with statistical analyses to investigate the behaviors underpinning this technological shift.  The experimental component of the project was aimed at creating a new approach to quantifying the adaptive properties of the products (flakes) of different technologies using 3D scans of the cores used to produce them. This method circumvents issues with identifying production techniques from the flakes. The method was tested using experimentally created stone tools. Results of the experimental component revealed that measurements taken on scans of cores are excellent proxies for the flake removed from them. The method was applied to archaeological assemblages from the Lower Palaeolithic site of Nor Geghi-1 in Armenia to test if the earliest iterations of Levallois prepared core technology in this region was optimal in the same way as later Middle Palaeolithic Levallois technology. The study reveals the following:  -       Early Levallois prepared cores at the site do not produce products with more cutting edge than other production techniques present.  -       Early Levallois prepared cores at the site do not produce more standardized products in terms of size or shape than other production techniques present.  There is a disparity between these results and what has been argued for later prepared core technology in the Middle Palaeolithic. Generally, this suggests that factors driving the use of prepared core technology may have changed over time or rather that innovation and later widespread use of prepared core technology involved different adaptive considerations.  The project’s main component tested hypotheses about the origin and innovative process behind early prepared core technology in the Armenian Highlands and Britain. Three archaeological localities in Armenia (Hatis-1, Nor Geghi-1 south, Nor Geghi-1 north) and five in Britain (Elveden, Hoxne, Purfleet, Ebbsfleet, Creffield Road) were used in this part of the study. Both areas contain assemblages that have been used to support the local innovation of Levallois prepared cores. Statistical shape analysis of 3D scan data from the two regions was used to test for patterns of technological change to ask:  -       Are there patterns of change that support a local origin of prepared core technology?  -       What is the process of technological evolution that leads to early prepared cores in these regions?  The results of this part of the study are the following:  -       Early prepared core technology in Armenia is invented locally resulting from the evolution of both large cutting tools (handaxes) and simple cores in the underlying Acheulian technology found in the region.  -       Early prepared core technology in Britain is not likely to have been invented locally and may have been introduced with populations migrating into the region.  These results broadly support the growing consensus that there are multiple origins of prepared cores. Further, this suggests that technologies during the Pleistocene make poor proxies for populations or species as their appearance can be due to convergent processes of innovation or population movement.  As a whole, this project contributes to our understanding of behavioral evolution during the Pleistocene across regions and highlights the utility of 3D scanning for asking questions about the archaeological record while providing a new way of analyzing 3D data. Further, this research contributed to the successful completion of the co-PI’s doctoral dissertation, along with providing training in digital methods to undergraduate students.       Last Modified: 07/26/2023       Submitted by: Jayson P Gill]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
