<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[STTR Phase I:  Novel Acellular Grafts Containing Rifampin and Minocycline for Single-Stage Reconstruction of Stage II-III Pressure Ulcers]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>251208.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>251208</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Erik Pierstorff</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>epiersto@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922165</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact /commercial potential of this Small Business Technology Transfer (STTR) Phase I project is to develop a wound care product to heal bed sores or pressure ulcers (PUs). Over 2.5 million Americans, usually older adults, suffer from PUs annually. PUs can be deep wounds, take many months to heal, cause significant pain; if infected, they can lead to sepsis and death. The annual U.S. cost for treatment of all PUs is estimated to be greater than $11 billion. Current treatment options involve surgical reconstruction with skin or skin substitute grafts, which can fail to heal the pressure ulcer because of infection or because the graft was not strong enough. To address these issues, the proposed project will develop a novel skin substitute that is pro-regenerative, stronger, and releases infection-fighting drugs at the surgical site to allow healing. This could benefit physicians and hospitals treating patients with stage II-III PUs (58% of all PUs); the 3-year market potential is over $150 million. The underlying technology of the proposed solution can be used to make novel grafts for treatment of numerous wound types, improving healing and patient quality of life.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Technology Transfer (STTR) Phase I project focuses on demonstrating the feasibility of this drug-loaded, polymer-impregnated acellular biologic graft (ABG) platform technology. Currently, PUs are surgically reconstructed using skin or skin substitute grafts, like ABGs, which often fail due to infection or lack of mechanical strength. By embedding a polymer hydrogel within an ABG, it can be mechanically strengthened. Furthermore, mixing the polymer with drugs (drug+polyABG) enables a drug delivery system that provides sustained, local release of therapeutic agents such as anti-infectives over a 14-day period. This novel approach simultaneously provides an allogeneic scaffold for patient-mediated tissue regeneration and counters onset of common complications during wound healing. This biocompatible polymer impregnation of ABGs for therapeutic applications has not been performed previously. This Phase I project will demonstrate feasibility drug+polyABG by (1) characterizing drug release and bioactivity in vitro and (2) assessing efficacy in an in vivo mouse model of single-stage reconstruction of stage II-III PUs challenged with topical MRSA.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/10/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/28/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041, 47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2012920</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nicholas</FirstName>
<LastName>Pashos</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nicholas Pashos</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[npashos@bio-aesthetics.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000736249</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>BIOAESTHETICS CORPORATION</Name>
<CityName>DURHAM</CityName>
<ZipCode>277012102</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8336224723</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>323 FOSTER ST STE 300</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>CB6YT355CQK5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>BIOAESTHETICS CORPORATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[BioAesthetics Corporation]]></Name>
<CityName>RESEARCH TRIANGLE PARK</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>277090003</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[6 DAVIS DRIVE, SUITE 828]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1505</Code>
<Text>STTR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>008E</Code>
<Text>Gene and Drug Delivery</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>6883</Code>
<Text>CHEMISTRY OF LIFE PROCESSES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~251208</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Phase I Project Outcomes Report</p> <p>BioAesthetics is developing a transformative acellular biologic graft (ABG) containing both a polymer and anti-infective drugs (drug+polyABG) for treating stage II-III pressure ulcers (PUs) that provides both a human-derived collagen scaffold for tissue regeneration and a hydrogel drug delivery system (DDS) for sustained, local release of therapeutic agents (e.g., antibiotics, pain medications, and/or anti-inflammatories) at the PU site to enhance wound healing and reduce patient mortality. PUs are a large, growing medical burden in the U.S. with over 2.5 million people affected annually. Approximately 70% of all PUs occur in the geriatric population and about 25% of nursing home residents are impacted by PUs. PUs are one of the most frequent causes of death in older adults, with up to 60,000 patients dying each year in the U.S. from PU-related complications.&nbsp;</p> <p>In the Phase I project, drug+polyABGs were generated using decellularized human skin from deceased donors, silk fibroin for the polymer hydrogel, and the antibiotics rifampin and minocycline as the drugs creating R/M+silkABGs. Rifampin and minocycline were chosen as the drugs due to their ability to kill methicillin-resistant&nbsp;<em>Staphylococcus aureus</em>&nbsp;(MRSA), which is one of the most common microbes found in PUs and contributes to PU depth and duration. First, the R/M+silkABGs were assessed&nbsp;<em>in vitro</em>&nbsp;for how the drug was released from the grafts, whether the released drug was able to kill MRSA, and whether the grafts supported the growth of human cells. Then, the best R/M+silkABGs, based on their ability to release R/M for 14 days at levels lethal to MRSA and support human cell growth, were tested&nbsp;<em>in vivo</em>&nbsp;in a mouse model of PUs to evaluate wound healing over 21 days in infected and non-infected wounds.&nbsp;</p> <p>BioAesthetics successfully generated R/M+silkABGs that release R/M for at least 14 days at concentrations lethal to MRSA and support human cell growth. It was observed that higher concentrations of polymer provided longer sustained drug release. Results of the mouse study showed that R/M+silkABGs inhibited bacterial growth and reduced bacterial burden to that of levels seen in uninfected mice by day 5. R/M+silkABGs had significantly decreased bacterial loads in the wound after 21 days as compared to a commercial control and silkABGs both not containing drugs. In addition, after 21 days, cells and new blood vessels could be observed in R/M+silkABGs at levels similar to controls indicating they are viable for wound healing. These results demonstrate proof-of-concept that R/M+silkABGs are viable for treating PUs and should be investigated further in a Phase II project.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/24/2023<br>      Modified by: Nicholas&nbsp;Pashos</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Phase I Project Outcomes Report  BioAesthetics is developing a transformative acellular biologic graft (ABG) containing both a polymer and anti-infective drugs (drug+polyABG) for treating stage II-III pressure ulcers (PUs) that provides both a human-derived collagen scaffold for tissue regeneration and a hydrogel drug delivery system (DDS) for sustained, local release of therapeutic agents (e.g., antibiotics, pain medications, and/or anti-inflammatories) at the PU site to enhance wound healing and reduce patient mortality. PUs are a large, growing medical burden in the U.S. with over 2.5 million people affected annually. Approximately 70% of all PUs occur in the geriatric population and about 25% of nursing home residents are impacted by PUs. PUs are one of the most frequent causes of death in older adults, with up to 60,000 patients dying each year in the U.S. from PU-related complications.   In the Phase I project, drug+polyABGs were generated using decellularized human skin from deceased donors, silk fibroin for the polymer hydrogel, and the antibiotics rifampin and minocycline as the drugs creating R/M+silkABGs. Rifampin and minocycline were chosen as the drugs due to their ability to kill methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus (MRSA), which is one of the most common microbes found in PUs and contributes to PU depth and duration. First, the R/M+silkABGs were assessed in vitro for how the drug was released from the grafts, whether the released drug was able to kill MRSA, and whether the grafts supported the growth of human cells. Then, the best R/M+silkABGs, based on their ability to release R/M for 14 days at levels lethal to MRSA and support human cell growth, were tested in vivo in a mouse model of PUs to evaluate wound healing over 21 days in infected and non-infected wounds.   BioAesthetics successfully generated R/M+silkABGs that release R/M for at least 14 days at concentrations lethal to MRSA and support human cell growth. It was observed that higher concentrations of polymer provided longer sustained drug release. Results of the mouse study showed that R/M+silkABGs inhibited bacterial growth and reduced bacterial burden to that of levels seen in uninfected mice by day 5. R/M+silkABGs had significantly decreased bacterial loads in the wound after 21 days as compared to a commercial control and silkABGs both not containing drugs. In addition, after 21 days, cells and new blood vessels could be observed in R/M+silkABGs at levels similar to controls indicating they are viable for wound healing. These results demonstrate proof-of-concept that R/M+silkABGs are viable for treating PUs and should be investigated further in a Phase II project.          Last Modified: 01/24/2023       Submitted by: Nicholas Pashos]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
