<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[NSF INCLUDES Planning Grant: Creating the Networks That Can Build and Sustain Inclusive, Workforce-relevant STEM Courses for Underrepresented Students]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>100000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>100000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div. of Equity for Excellence in STEM</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Deena Khalil</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dkhalil@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928141</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Disparities in access to and availability of workforce-relevant STEM courses continue to persist. The inequities are particularly profound for high school students of color and students from rural and low-income backgrounds. As a consequence, these students are less likely to succeed in STEM courses and pursue STEM majors and careers. When workforce-relevant STEM courses are available, underrepresented and underserved students are also more likely to be taught by teachers who are ill-prepared to teach such courses. This further exacerbates the problems and failures of inequity in the education system. This planning grant will begin to address these challenges through a large-scale social-change-driven coordinated effort. The American Institutes for Research (AIR), in collaboration with 100Kin10, will create this large-scale change by preparing for, launching, and supporting three place-based networks to improve the quality of and equitable access to workforce-relevant STEM courses. These networks will develop plans that, when implemented, will enable more underrepresented students to access and succeed in workforce-relevant STEM courses, as well as determine the extent to which the collaborative infrastructure and its use contribute to those systemic improvements. Each of the place-based networks, made up of districts, teacher preparation programs, business communities, and other relevant organizations in a geographic region, will test, adapt, and refine strategies for driving STEM improvements at the local level.  If successful, this foundational work will not only inform the approach for expanding and scaling the model, but it will also contribute to NSF’s commitment to improving quality and inclusion within the K–12 education system by focusing on broadening participation challenges at the high school level.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Over the 12-month project duration, the guiding framework for the work will be centered on two of the five NSF INCLUDES design elements of collaborative infrastructure; (a) leadership and communication and (b) expansion, sustainability and scale. Using this framework, the work will begin with a literature scan conducted by AIR to identify evidence-based practices and measures aligned to leadership, communication, expansion, sustainability, and scale in PK–12 education systems. AIR and 100Kin10 will then work collaboratively with the place-based networks to co-design plans that use evidence-based practices for collaboration among members and promote evidence-based strategies for reducing systemic STEM inequities to support the design and delivery of workforce-relevant high school STEM courses, especially in low-income, rural, and majority-minority high schools. Specifically, the co-designed plans will work to: (1) improve educators’ capacity to develop and teach workforce-relevant STEM courses; (2) increase the number of high school students enrolling in and completing workforce-relevant STEM courses; and (3) expand, sustain, and scale evidence-based practices for supporting underrepresented student populations in STEM. The place-based network plans will include goals and metrics for tracking the progress in overcoming the inequities and determining the extent to which specific collaborative mechanisms spur progress toward the place-based networks’ aim.  After identifying and selecting the goals and metrics, the project team will work with the place-based networks to understand the local, root causes of inequity in student access to workforce-relevant STEM; support the creation of strong local place-based networks; and draft plans with goals and metrics for progress in overcoming the inequities and collaborative mechanisms that may spur that progress. The support of these efforts will be led by the backbone organization, 100Kin10. The role of the backbone organization will be to support the launch the three place-based networks, support their partnerships through workshops and convenings, and connect them to its extensive national networks of representatives from more than 30 organizations nationwide with expertise in the central levers of systemic STEM change and focused on improving access to workforce-relevant STEM courses. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This planning grant is funded by NSF Inclusion across the Nation of Communities of Learners of Underrepresented Discoverers in Engineering and Science (NSF INCLUDES), a comprehensive national initiative to enhance U.S. leadership in discoveries and innovations by focusing on diversity, inclusion, and broadening participation in STEM at scale.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/17/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/17/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2012896</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Talia</FirstName>
<LastName>Milgrom-Elcott</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Talia Milgrom-Elcott</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[tme@100Kin10.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000816564</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/17/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Julie</FirstName>
<LastName>Kochanek</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Julie Kochanek</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jkochanek@air.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000699237</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/17/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>American Institutes for Research in the Behavioral Sciences</Name>
<CityName>ARLINGTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>222023289</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2024035000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1400 CRYSTAL DR FL 10</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>VA08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>MCN6J5L6M3T4</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>AMERICAN INSTITUTES FOR RESEARCH IN THE BEHAVIORAL SCIENCES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[American Institutes for Research]]></Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>200073835</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1000 Thomas Jefferson Street, NW]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>032Y</Code>
<Text>Eddie Bernice Johnson INCLUDES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0420</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~100000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><em>Collaborative infrastructure building and strengthening &nbsp;</em></p> <ul> <li>The AIR team completed a literature scan that focused on the characteristics of successful place-based networks and how to measure conditions of equity in STEM education. The literature scan provides an overview of how to achieve equity in STEM teaching and learning in kindergarten through 12th grade and the challenges involved; it also summarizes the characteristics of successful place-based networks with a focus on the collective impact model, explores instruments used for measuring the impact of a place-based network, and examines the nascent research on sustaining, scaling up, and communicating the work of a place-based network.&nbsp; </li> <li>In partnership with AIR during the grant, 100kin10 released an actionable research report focused on how to increase the range and quality of high school STEM courses, particularly for students of color. The report is based on a review of existing research and in-depth interviews with more than 20 experts from across the field.&nbsp;</li> <li>The AIR team adapted the Collective Impact model to meet the needs of the project's structure. Through the planning grant, AIR has taken on the role of a backbone organization in developing the plans for the ARISE Alliance. The ARISE Alliance developed materials that will support the creation of a guiding vision and strategy, aligned activities by the eventual alliance members, developed plans to establish shared measurement practices, and provided a network lead to each place-based network who would serve as their local backbone. The ARISE Alliance cultivated engagement and ownership among the alliance members to begin working toward creating a sustainable network. The ARISE Alliance also convened the planning grant advisory board to reflect on the progress we have made during the planning grant period and to consider next steps for strengthening the partnerships and supporting their work.</li> <li>Using the literature scan and the adapted systems change framework to develop selection criteria, the ARISE Alliance identified and selected four partners among interested potential place-based networks and worked with them to understand the root causes of inequity in student access to workforce-relevant STEM specific to their local context. The place-based networks were selected through a set of criteria identified through a literature review as essential to the success of a place-based network. These criteria served as a starting point, and the selected place-based networks showed a commitment to each one.&nbsp;&nbsp; </li> </ul> <ol> <li>Involvement and understanding of the local community. </li> <li>Common purpose and clear agenda.</li> <li>Backbone organization and/or strong leadership. </li> <li>Coordination of efforts commitment.</li> <li>Clear measures of success and ability to collect data. </li> <li>Communication structures.</li> <li>Emphasis on equity. </li> <li>Sustainability model for growth.&nbsp; </li> </ol>  <ul> <li>The ARISE Alliance partnered with place-based networks to develop plans for an Alliance focused on addressing access, design, and social capital barriers to the delivery of workforce-relevant high school STEM courses, especially students of color. Each place-based network convened three times. Out of those conversations, ARISE Alliance proposed a plan for selecting and developing measures to monitor the collaborative infrastructure of an alliance and the progress of the place-based networks as well as a proposal for iterative learning and monitoring progress toward expansion, sustainability and scale, and leadership and communication to enable continuous improvement and will continue to work with alliance members to select and develop measures that monitor the collaborative infrastructure of the place-based networks. Input from the place-based networks informed the development and submission of the ARISE Alliance proposal submitted by AIR in January 2021. </li> </ul> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><em>Collaboration with the NSF INCLUDES Coordination Hub to build critical knowledge that shows measurable progress toward long-term goals </em></p> <ul> <li>Under the ARISE Alliance, the AIR team joined the following NSF INCLUDES affinity groups and attended meetings: Models of Collaboration and Partnerships, Evaluation, Exploring STEM Pathways, and Shared Measures.&nbsp;</li> <li>The ARISE Alliance coordinated and facilitated a coffee and conversation event with the support of NSF INCLUDES to discuss developing and sustaining work-based learning opportunities with industry partners.&nbsp; Discussion centered around the differences in ways that school districts, universities, and industry partners come to the work of diversifying STEM, and about the ways to communicate the benefits of diversifying STEM to industry partners.&nbsp; The conversation was attended by 14 members of the NSF INCLUDES Network. </li> </ul> <p><em>Work to build on-ramps for other organizations and broadening participation stakeholders to join in and expand the National Network</em></p> <ul> <li>Throughout the planning grant, the ARISE Alliance      encouraged members of the place-based networks to sign up for the National      Network's affinity groups.&nbsp;</li> <li>The ARISE Alliance also shared resources from the National Network with their place-based networks on topics around building collaborative infrastructure, the role of a backbone, successful collaborations and partnerships, and specific interventions related to the shared vision and goals of the Alliance.&nbsp;&nbsp;</li> </ul> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/26/2021<br>      Modified by: Julie&nbsp;Kochanek</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Collaborative infrastructure building and strengthening    The AIR team completed a literature scan that focused on the characteristics of successful place-based networks and how to measure conditions of equity in STEM education. The literature scan provides an overview of how to achieve equity in STEM teaching and learning in kindergarten through 12th grade and the challenges involved; it also summarizes the characteristics of successful place-based networks with a focus on the collective impact model, explores instruments used for measuring the impact of a place-based network, and examines the nascent research on sustaining, scaling up, and communicating the work of a place-based network.   In partnership with AIR during the grant, 100kin10 released an actionable research report focused on how to increase the range and quality of high school STEM courses, particularly for students of color. The report is based on a review of existing research and in-depth interviews with more than 20 experts from across the field.  The AIR team adapted the Collective Impact model to meet the needs of the project's structure. Through the planning grant, AIR has taken on the role of a backbone organization in developing the plans for the ARISE Alliance. The ARISE Alliance developed materials that will support the creation of a guiding vision and strategy, aligned activities by the eventual alliance members, developed plans to establish shared measurement practices, and provided a network lead to each place-based network who would serve as their local backbone. The ARISE Alliance cultivated engagement and ownership among the alliance members to begin working toward creating a sustainable network. The ARISE Alliance also convened the planning grant advisory board to reflect on the progress we have made during the planning grant period and to consider next steps for strengthening the partnerships and supporting their work. Using the literature scan and the adapted systems change framework to develop selection criteria, the ARISE Alliance identified and selected four partners among interested potential place-based networks and worked with them to understand the root causes of inequity in student access to workforce-relevant STEM specific to their local context. The place-based networks were selected through a set of criteria identified through a literature review as essential to the success of a place-based network. These criteria served as a starting point, and the selected place-based networks showed a commitment to each one.      Involvement and understanding of the local community.  Common purpose and clear agenda. Backbone organization and/or strong leadership.  Coordination of efforts commitment. Clear measures of success and ability to collect data.  Communication structures. Emphasis on equity.  Sustainability model for growth.      The ARISE Alliance partnered with place-based networks to develop plans for an Alliance focused on addressing access, design, and social capital barriers to the delivery of workforce-relevant high school STEM courses, especially students of color. Each place-based network convened three times. Out of those conversations, ARISE Alliance proposed a plan for selecting and developing measures to monitor the collaborative infrastructure of an alliance and the progress of the place-based networks as well as a proposal for iterative learning and monitoring progress toward expansion, sustainability and scale, and leadership and communication to enable continuous improvement and will continue to work with alliance members to select and develop measures that monitor the collaborative infrastructure of the place-based networks. Input from the place-based networks informed the development and submission of the ARISE Alliance proposal submitted by AIR in January 2021.       Collaboration with the NSF INCLUDES Coordination Hub to build critical knowledge that shows measurable progress toward long-term goals   Under the ARISE Alliance, the AIR team joined the following NSF INCLUDES affinity groups and attended meetings: Models of Collaboration and Partnerships, Evaluation, Exploring STEM Pathways, and Shared Measures.  The ARISE Alliance coordinated and facilitated a coffee and conversation event with the support of NSF INCLUDES to discuss developing and sustaining work-based learning opportunities with industry partners.  Discussion centered around the differences in ways that school districts, universities, and industry partners come to the work of diversifying STEM, and about the ways to communicate the benefits of diversifying STEM to industry partners.  The conversation was attended by 14 members of the NSF INCLUDES Network.    Work to build on-ramps for other organizations and broadening participation stakeholders to join in and expand the National Network  Throughout the planning grant, the ARISE Alliance      encouraged members of the place-based networks to sign up for the National      Network's affinity groups.  The ARISE Alliance also shared resources from the National Network with their place-based networks on topics around building collaborative infrastructure, the role of a backbone, successful collaborations and partnerships, and specific interventions related to the shared vision and goals of the Alliance.             Last Modified: 08/26/2021       Submitted by: Julie Kochanek]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
