<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[TCUP SGR: Salish Kootenai College Life Sciences Hg(II) Methylating Microbiota and Methyl-Hg(II) Concentrations in Flathead Lake]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>199942.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>199942</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div. of Equity for Excellence in STEM</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jody Chase</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lchase@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925173</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[A goal of the Tribal Colleges and Universities Program (TCUP) is to increase the science, technology, engineering and mathematics (STEM) instructional and research capacities of specific institutions of higher education that serve the Nation's indigenous students. Expanding the research capacity at these institutions expands the opportunities for students to pursue challenging, rewarding careers in STEM fields, provides for research studies in areas that may be locally relevant, and encourages a faculty community to look beyond the traditional classroom for intellectual and professional growth. This project aligns directly with that goal, and moreover may prove to be a model for similar engagement at other small community colleges.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project aims to identify microbiota and methyl-Hg(II) concentrations in Flathead Lake to map the environmental impacts climate change may be incurring on the Flathead reservation and in the wider Flathead valley in Montana.  Elemental mercury (Hg) is deposited into the atmosphere primarily from sources including coal-burning and forest fires. Atmospheric Hg(II) accumulates in large water bodies, such as Flathead Lake on the Flathead reservation. Hg(II) in the lakebed soil sediments is subject to methylation by methylating microbiota, such as the methanogens sp. Once methylated, Hg(II) bioaccumulates/biomagnifies in the environment increasing with the size and phylum of animals reaching, often, toxic levels in apex predators and humans.   Preliminary work by undergraduate students at the Salish Kootenai College has identified methanogen sp. in the soil-bed samples from two locations in the lower Flathead Lake and methyl-Hg(II) in the water.  Salish Kootenai College will sample Flathead Lake for Hg(II)-methylating microbiota in the lakebed soil and for concentrations of methyl-Hg(II) in the water.  Experimental procedures will include RNA isolation and sequencing to identify the local microbe population and to measure the concentration of methyl-Hg(II) in the water at those microbe sites.  Further sampling will aim to provide a solid statistical basis for climate change reference as it will impact the Flathead valley where climate change will result in higher Hg(II) deposition in the lake and promote microbial growth for Hg(II) methylation.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/17/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/17/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2013863</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Christina</FirstName>
<LastName>Rush</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Christina Rush</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[christina_rush@skc.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000626570</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/17/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Salish Kootenai College</Name>
<CityName>PABLO</CityName>
<ZipCode>598557700</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4062754800</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>58138 US HIGHWAY 93</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Montana</StateName>
<StateCode>MT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MT01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>Q1G9U7V3Q8C7</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SALISH KOOTENAI COLLEGE, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>Q1G9U7V3Q8C7</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Salish Kootenai College]]></Name>
<CityName>pablo</CityName>
<StateCode>MT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>598550070</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[P O BOX 70]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Montana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MT01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1744</Code>
<Text>Tribal College &amp; Univers Prog</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0420</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~199942</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Project Outcomes Report: NSF Award number 2013863</p> <p>Project Title: TCUP SGR: Salish Kootenai College Life Sciences Hg(II) Methylating Microbiota and Methyl-Hg(II) Concentrations in Flathead Lake</p> <p>Recipient Organization: Salish Kootenai College</p> <p>Project/Grant Period: 7/15/2020 - 6/30/2022</p> <p>PI: Christina L. Rush</p> <p>This grant supported research on the microbiota of Flathead Lake on the Confederated Salish and Kootenai Tribes Reservation. The work was carried out in the Cellular and Molecular Biology lab at Salish Kootenai College by undergraduate research students.&nbsp;</p> <p>Salish Kootenai College (SKC) is located in Pablo, Montana and currently serves 59% enrolled Native Tribal members and 15% descendant Native Tribal members. The Life Sciences Department houses Life Sciences and General Sciences students representing 13% of the total full time student population at SKC. Research is an integral part of the degree programs offered and allows undergraduates the experience to learn laboratory techniques useful for future careers. Training Native researchers is a central goal in parallel with research themes that directly interest and impact the Native population on the reservation.&nbsp;</p> <p>The awarded NSF TCUP SGR grant supported students in their efforts to understand the populations of microbes in the lake-bed soil of Flathead Lake. Of particular interest to this award, the percentage of mercury-methylating bacteria was emphasized as these populations directly impact the Native food sources from the lake.&nbsp;</p> <p>Over the course of the award, over a hundred soil samples were collected from Flathead Lake for processing. Despite the COVID pandemic, nearly all of the samples have been analyzed.</p> <p>Data shows that Flathead Lake houses a diverse population of microbes from those that are normally found in extreme environments to microbiota from animal ruminant&nbsp;stomachs. Alongside these varied populations, mercury methylators are in abundance of approximately 25% of many samples.&nbsp;</p> <p>Intellectual merit of this research was to define the microbiology of Flathead Lake, where no data of this kind has been done before. Broader impacts are to the Native community and the world-wide community in adding to the base of knowledge about microbes in glacier fed lakes. Moreover, the levels of these populations may guide scientific exploration of how microbes change as their environment changes.&nbsp;</p> <p>Finally, the direct impact of the research to undergraduate Native students has led to successful matriculation for the next generation of Native scientists.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/12/2022<br>      Modified by: Christina&nbsp;Rush</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Project Outcomes Report: NSF Award number 2013863  Project Title: TCUP SGR: Salish Kootenai College Life Sciences Hg(II) Methylating Microbiota and Methyl-Hg(II) Concentrations in Flathead Lake  Recipient Organization: Salish Kootenai College  Project/Grant Period: 7/15/2020 - 6/30/2022  PI: Christina L. Rush  This grant supported research on the microbiota of Flathead Lake on the Confederated Salish and Kootenai Tribes Reservation. The work was carried out in the Cellular and Molecular Biology lab at Salish Kootenai College by undergraduate research students.   Salish Kootenai College (SKC) is located in Pablo, Montana and currently serves 59% enrolled Native Tribal members and 15% descendant Native Tribal members. The Life Sciences Department houses Life Sciences and General Sciences students representing 13% of the total full time student population at SKC. Research is an integral part of the degree programs offered and allows undergraduates the experience to learn laboratory techniques useful for future careers. Training Native researchers is a central goal in parallel with research themes that directly interest and impact the Native population on the reservation.   The awarded NSF TCUP SGR grant supported students in their efforts to understand the populations of microbes in the lake-bed soil of Flathead Lake. Of particular interest to this award, the percentage of mercury-methylating bacteria was emphasized as these populations directly impact the Native food sources from the lake.   Over the course of the award, over a hundred soil samples were collected from Flathead Lake for processing. Despite the COVID pandemic, nearly all of the samples have been analyzed.  Data shows that Flathead Lake houses a diverse population of microbes from those that are normally found in extreme environments to microbiota from animal ruminant stomachs. Alongside these varied populations, mercury methylators are in abundance of approximately 25% of many samples.   Intellectual merit of this research was to define the microbiology of Flathead Lake, where no data of this kind has been done before. Broader impacts are to the Native community and the world-wide community in adding to the base of knowledge about microbes in glacier fed lakes. Moreover, the levels of these populations may guide scientific exploration of how microbes change as their environment changes.   Finally, the direct impact of the research to undergraduate Native students has led to successful matriculation for the next generation of Native scientists.       Last Modified: 07/12/2022       Submitted by: Christina Rush]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
