<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Safety in Ocean and Field Sciences:  Developing best practices for harassment prevention and response]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>11/08/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>81665.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>81665</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Leslie J. Rissler</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lrissler@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924628</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This award will fund a workshop (place and dates to be determined) to develop policies and best practices to deal with sexual harrassment associated with field research. While many institutions and organizations are revisiting their policies and practices regarding sexual harassment, there remains a gap in attention to policies and best practices specifically tailored to the remote and isolated nature of the field environment. Institutions lack policy on response to the acute safety issues caused by harassment in remote settings, as well as guidance on jurisdiction for potential responses,This workshop will: (1) open a dialogue between sexual harassment experts and the field research community to develop best practices and recommendations; (2) build coordination and encouraging consistency in policy setting and enforcement across field stations and oceanographic platforms; (3) develop processes to monitor the reporting of sexual harassment instances occurring at remote field locations; and (4) promote a safe culture for scientists conducting research at remote field stations and on oceanographic vessels. Participants will include sexual harassment experts, leadership from academic research institutions, research stations, and ship operators, field researchers, technical/crew managers, and representation from member associations. The recommendations will be broadly distributed at appropriate scientific meetings and associations.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/11/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/04/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2013711</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Terry</FirstName>
<LastName>McGlynn</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Terry McGlynn</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[tmcglynn@csudh.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000463214</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/04/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Anne</FirstName>
<LastName>Kelly</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Anne Kelly</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[anne.kelly@tnc.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000754803</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/04/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Anne</FirstName>
<LastName>Kelly</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Anne Kelly</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[anne.kelly@tnc.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000754803</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/11/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate>11/04/2021</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>CSU Fullerton Auxiliary Services Corporation</Name>
<CityName>FULLERTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>928313014</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6572782106</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1121 N STATE COLLEGE BLVD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>45</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA45</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>VQ5WK498QDC6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CSU FULLERTON AUXILIARY SERVICES CORPORATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[California State University Fullerton]]></Name>
<CityName>Fullerton</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>928313599</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[800 N. State College Boulevard]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>45</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA45</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1127</Code>
<Text>Evolutionary Processes</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1690</Code>
<Text>EDUCATION/HUMAN RESOURCES,OCE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01001920DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~81665</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Outcomes</strong></p> <p>The primary outcome of this project was the "Report of the Workshop to Promote Safety in Field Sciences" (https://zenodo.org/record/5604956). This report was the result of a three-day workshop with nearly 70 national leading experts in field science and ocean research management, the harassment problem in field sciences, harassment prevention, and institutional policy and law around harassment.&nbsp; This report details 52 recommendations for meaningful institutional changes to prevent and respond to harassment in field research. Recommendations are aimed at universities, professional societies, field research teams, field stations, ocean research platforms, and funding agencies.</p> <p>A journal article summarizing the workshop process and findings was published in 2023: Yarincik, K., A. Kelly, T. McGlynn, and R.M. Verble. 2023. Best practices to promote field science safety. Integrative and Comparative Biology, in press. DOI: 10.1093/icb/icad014</p> <p>In addition, the findings of this report have been presented at several professional conferences since 2021.</p> <p><strong>Broader impacts</strong></p> <p>The workshop report, as of June 2023, has been downloaded over 5,000 times. The impacts to the broader community are difficult to track, as there is no formal tracking process for any groups, institutions, or agencies adopting the recommendations. However, the report authors have been contacted by many diverse interest groups looking to adopt some set of the report recommendations. These groups include:</p> <ul> <li>The AdvanceGEO team (NSF-funded)</li> <li>Professional scientific society leadership</li> <li>Major research and defense contractors (e.g., Fluor and Battelle)</li> <li>University leadership</li> <li>Funding agency leadership</li> <li>US House Committee on Science and Technology Policy</li> </ul> <p>The House Committee on Science and Technology Policy incorporated some of these recommendations into HR 4346, the CHIPS and Science Act of 2022. These recommendations include requirements for federal funding related to harassment prevention and response. Dr. Kelly continues to work with this committee on crafting more effective legislation on funding requirements.</p> <p>The House Committee on Science and Technology Policy also invited the report authors to testify at the hearings on harassment in the Antarctic research program, held December 6, 2022. Dr. Kelly testified on institutional best practices based on the findings of the workshop report.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/12/2023<br>      Modified by: Anne&nbsp;Kelly</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Outcomes  The primary outcome of this project was the "Report of the Workshop to Promote Safety in Field Sciences" (https://zenodo.org/record/5604956). This report was the result of a three-day workshop with nearly 70 national leading experts in field science and ocean research management, the harassment problem in field sciences, harassment prevention, and institutional policy and law around harassment.  This report details 52 recommendations for meaningful institutional changes to prevent and respond to harassment in field research. Recommendations are aimed at universities, professional societies, field research teams, field stations, ocean research platforms, and funding agencies.  A journal article summarizing the workshop process and findings was published in 2023: Yarincik, K., A. Kelly, T. McGlynn, and R.M. Verble. 2023. Best practices to promote field science safety. Integrative and Comparative Biology, in press. DOI: 10.1093/icb/icad014  In addition, the findings of this report have been presented at several professional conferences since 2021.  Broader impacts  The workshop report, as of June 2023, has been downloaded over 5,000 times. The impacts to the broader community are difficult to track, as there is no formal tracking process for any groups, institutions, or agencies adopting the recommendations. However, the report authors have been contacted by many diverse interest groups looking to adopt some set of the report recommendations. These groups include:  The AdvanceGEO team (NSF-funded) Professional scientific society leadership Major research and defense contractors (e.g., Fluor and Battelle) University leadership Funding agency leadership US House Committee on Science and Technology Policy   The House Committee on Science and Technology Policy incorporated some of these recommendations into HR 4346, the CHIPS and Science Act of 2022. These recommendations include requirements for federal funding related to harassment prevention and response. Dr. Kelly continues to work with this committee on crafting more effective legislation on funding requirements.  The House Committee on Science and Technology Policy also invited the report authors to testify at the hearings on harassment in the Antarctic research program, held December 6, 2022. Dr. Kelly testified on institutional best practices based on the findings of the workshop report.       Last Modified: 06/12/2023       Submitted by: Anne Kelly]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
