<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Doctoral Dissertation: Indigenous Land Defense: Emerging Networks of Survival]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>37280.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>37280</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06090100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OPP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Polar Programs (OPP)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Erica Hill</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>erhill@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032920000</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Indigenous peoples are developing novel social mechanisms to deal with rapid change and emerging conflicts, including land resettlement, language revitalization and traditional skill-building. However, we know little about the processes and contexts from which these strategies arise.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will use a case study from the Northwest Coast of North America to evaluate how Indigenous communities socially and culturally adapt to conflicts over sovereignty, land use and access. This research aims to document the new social networks that emerge in these contexts and how they contribute to Indigenous resiliency. To understand the opportunities and consequences of emerging networks, this project will (1) document the socio-cultural norms that emerge amidst Indigenous resettlement of traditional territories; (2) identify types of social networks that develop; (3) evaluate connections between these new networks and gender, race, and economic factors.  The ultimate objective is to trace community networks and evaluate their impacts on Indigenous resilience, an issue with broad implications for Arctic Indigenous communities.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/25/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/25/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.078</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2013436</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dana-Ain</FirstName>
<LastName>Davis</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Dana-Ain Davis</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[danaaindavis@yahoo.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000649746</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/25/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Anne</FirstName>
<LastName>Spice</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Anne Spice</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[aspice@gradcenter.cuny.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000766686</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/25/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>CUNY Graduate School University Center</Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<ZipCode>100164309</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2128177526</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>365 5TH AVE STE 8113</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>QVW9TFAZJFE7</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH FOUNDATION OF THE CITY UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[CUNY Graduate School University Center]]></Name>
<CityName>New York</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>100164309</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[365 Fifth Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5221</Code>
<Text>ASSP-Arctic Social Science</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1079</Code>
<Text>ARCTIC RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5221</Code>
<Text>ARCTIC SOCIAL SCIENCES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>02XX</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>0100XXXXDB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~37280</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>For this project, the researcher used the methodology of auto-ethnography to document their experience of an Indigenous land-defense encampment. Through active participant observation, historical research, and examination of media products during the course of the project, the research describes the historical and political context of current Wet'suwet'en land disputes, including the effects of environmental change, Canadian legal and political structures, and resource extraction on access to and use of Indigenous lands. The project juxtaposes the operational frameworks of resource extraction companies with Wet'suwet'en understandings of seasonality, land use, and Indigenous sovereignty. By analyzing how space is defined and understood by different actors in the dispute over pipeline construction, the research illuminates points of tension between Indigenous and corporate ways of knowing the environment and our place within it.&nbsp;</p> <p>This research methodology contributes to an Indigenous feminist approach by working from the experience and perspective of the researcher. Auto-ethnography is an important method within anthropology and related fields, and the narrative style of the completed dissertation provides a model for social science inquiry firmly embedded in Indigenous worldviews and protocols. The analysis shows how resource extraction constrains the use of land for Wet'suwet'en people, and has broad applicability in human geography, Indigenous studies, and anthropology. Additionally, the research utilizes the framework of Indigenous environmental justice to demonstrate how colonial histories and contexts continue to affect the current experience of land-based politics, climate change, cultural practices, and relationships to the environment for Indigenous peoples. As such, it is also applicable to environmental policy and management, Indigenous governance and Canadian legal mechanisms, and organizations working in environmental justice and Indigenous rights.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/08/2022<br>      Modified by: Anne&nbsp;Spice</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ For this project, the researcher used the methodology of auto-ethnography to document their experience of an Indigenous land-defense encampment. Through active participant observation, historical research, and examination of media products during the course of the project, the research describes the historical and political context of current Wet'suwet'en land disputes, including the effects of environmental change, Canadian legal and political structures, and resource extraction on access to and use of Indigenous lands. The project juxtaposes the operational frameworks of resource extraction companies with Wet'suwet'en understandings of seasonality, land use, and Indigenous sovereignty. By analyzing how space is defined and understood by different actors in the dispute over pipeline construction, the research illuminates points of tension between Indigenous and corporate ways of knowing the environment and our place within it.   This research methodology contributes to an Indigenous feminist approach by working from the experience and perspective of the researcher. Auto-ethnography is an important method within anthropology and related fields, and the narrative style of the completed dissertation provides a model for social science inquiry firmly embedded in Indigenous worldviews and protocols. The analysis shows how resource extraction constrains the use of land for Wet'suwet'en people, and has broad applicability in human geography, Indigenous studies, and anthropology. Additionally, the research utilizes the framework of Indigenous environmental justice to demonstrate how colonial histories and contexts continue to affect the current experience of land-based politics, climate change, cultural practices, and relationships to the environment for Indigenous peoples. As such, it is also applicable to environmental policy and management, Indigenous governance and Canadian legal mechanisms, and organizations working in environmental justice and Indigenous rights.           Last Modified: 07/08/2022       Submitted by: Anne Spice]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
