<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative research:  Physiological signatures of variable weaning strategies in wild primates]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>63156.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>63156</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rebecca Ferrell</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rferrell@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927850</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Premature weaning can result in poor infant developmental outcomes and increased infant mortality; however, the social conditions that lead to premature weaning and its consequences are still poorly understood. The central goal of this project is to examine how stressful social conditions linked to the immigration of new adult males and/or poor maternal condition influence the likelihood of premature weaning, and, in turn how premature weaning then influences infant growth, gut microbial colonization, and the development of the immune system in a nonhuman primate model. Given the importance of early weaning as a hallmark of human evolution, developing comprehensive longitudinal models of this early life transition are valuable. In addition, the findings may serve as an animal model for understanding the costs and benefits of truncated or extended breastfeeding in modern humans. The project will provide rigorous scientific training to at least one post-doctoral fellow and several graduate and undergraduate students. The PIs will also engage in public outreach at local and international levels, contributing to scientific education and conservation efforts both domestically and abroad.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project examines the links between social factors, variable weaning strategies, and infant growth and immune system development in geladas. It draws on both cross-sectional and longitudinal data collected from infants aged 0-2.5 years to address the following goals: (1) Determine how social factors related to stressful demographic changes and/or maternal condition influence the timing of nursing cessation; (2) Identify how earlier weaning relative to infant size is related to stunted postnatal growth, altered gut microbial diversity and composition, and the concentration of urinary neopterin, a biomarker for cellular inflammation. Geladas are ideal for this research because their social system is characterized by frequent and stressful social upheavals that disrupt infant development and can even lead to infant mortality. Further, gelada females form strong dominance hierarchies that determine access to food, thus allowing researchers to address how social factors linked to poor maternal nutrition are associated with variable weaning strategies. Together, these attributes make geladas an excellent model system in which to study premature weaning. This study will be one of the first to integrate innovative methods in isotopic/elemental chemistry, genomics, endocrinology, and digital photogrammetry to examine the causes and consequences of premature weaning in wild primate infants, thus identifying some of the key mechanisms bridging early life social adversity to long-term developmental and health. Student trainees will have the opportunity to learn methods in behavioral data collection as well as various wet lab methods to characterize the composition of the gut microbiome and define weaning by the amount of milk vs. plant-origin carbon and nitrogen found in noninvasively collected fecal samples.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/16/2019</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/16/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2013888</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Noah</FirstName>
<LastName>Snyder-Mackler</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Noah Snyder-Mackler</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[nsnyderm@asu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000538381</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/16/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Arizona State University</Name>
<CityName>TEMPE</CityName>
<ZipCode>852813670</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4809655479</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>660 S MILL AVENUE STE 204</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AZ04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NTLHJXM55KZ6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ARIZONA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Arizona State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Tempe</CityName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>852816011</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[660 South Mill Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AZ04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1392</Code>
<Text>Biological Anthropology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1392</Code>
<Text>Biological Anthropology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01001819DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~63156</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-03bcb8c5-7fff-5542-ad56-09b2735172ee"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Intellectual Merit: <br /></span><span><span>Premature weaning can result in poor infant developmental outcomes and increased infant mortality; however, the conditions that lead to premature weaning and its consequences are still poorly understood. The goal of this project was to examine what environmental factors impact infant development and adult health and survival, with a focus on infant growth, gut microbial colonization, and the development of the immune system in a nonhuman primate model, the gelada. Given the importance of early weaning as a hallmark of human evolution, developing comprehensive longitudinal models of this early life transition are valuable.&nbsp;</span></span></p> <p dir="ltr">This project first characterized the gut microbiome of adult geladas and found that climatological variables, like rainfall, dramatically altered the composition of the gut microbiome, which likely reflects a gut microbiome adaptation to seasonal changes in food availability. Infants also exhibit stark developmental shifts in their gut microbiome at the level of overall diversity, which increases with age, as well as in the types of microbes present. In early life, the most abundant microbes are related to oligosaccharide degradation and fermentation, and help infants to digest milk. Later in life, cellulolytic and fibrolytic bacterial taxa become abundant and are likely linked to the introduction of solid food in the diet. These developmental changes were corroborated by changes in elemental ratios of carbon to nitrogen (CN), which showed that C/N ratios decline with increasing infant age, reflecting a shift from consumption of high-nitrogen milk to low-nitrogen plants. Together, these changes demonstrate that noninvasive measurements can accurately capture nutritional weaning, which occurs at ~15 mos of age in geladas. Finally, this proejct showed that variation in the maternal environment can influence the gut microbiome as well as inflammation as masured by noninvasive immune markers.&nbsp;<span>Together, this study integrated innovative methods in isotopic/elemental chemistry, genomics, endocrinology, and digital photogrammetry to identify the causes and consequences of premature weaning in a wild primate, thus identifying some of the key mechanisms bridging early life environments to long-term developmental and health.</span></p> <p><br /><span>Broader Impacts:</span><span> <br />This project has provided training opportunities in behavior, genomics, and physiology for two postdoctoral associates and several graduate students and undergraduates. It also provided valuable training and employment for three Ethiopian field assistants. The project members also shared the results from this project to a both an academic audience at conferences and in invited talks, as well as to the broader public both in the US and in Ethiopia where the data were collected. Finally, this project has provided novel information on the health and development of the endemic gelada, which will have important conservation implications for this unique species.&nbsp;</span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/29/2021<br>      Modified by: Noah&nbsp;Snyder-Mackler</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   Intellectual Merit:  Premature weaning can result in poor infant developmental outcomes and increased infant mortality; however, the conditions that lead to premature weaning and its consequences are still poorly understood. The goal of this project was to examine what environmental factors impact infant development and adult health and survival, with a focus on infant growth, gut microbial colonization, and the development of the immune system in a nonhuman primate model, the gelada. Given the importance of early weaning as a hallmark of human evolution, developing comprehensive longitudinal models of this early life transition are valuable.  This project first characterized the gut microbiome of adult geladas and found that climatological variables, like rainfall, dramatically altered the composition of the gut microbiome, which likely reflects a gut microbiome adaptation to seasonal changes in food availability. Infants also exhibit stark developmental shifts in their gut microbiome at the level of overall diversity, which increases with age, as well as in the types of microbes present. In early life, the most abundant microbes are related to oligosaccharide degradation and fermentation, and help infants to digest milk. Later in life, cellulolytic and fibrolytic bacterial taxa become abundant and are likely linked to the introduction of solid food in the diet. These developmental changes were corroborated by changes in elemental ratios of carbon to nitrogen (CN), which showed that C/N ratios decline with increasing infant age, reflecting a shift from consumption of high-nitrogen milk to low-nitrogen plants. Together, these changes demonstrate that noninvasive measurements can accurately capture nutritional weaning, which occurs at ~15 mos of age in geladas. Finally, this proejct showed that variation in the maternal environment can influence the gut microbiome as well as inflammation as masured by noninvasive immune markers. Together, this study integrated innovative methods in isotopic/elemental chemistry, genomics, endocrinology, and digital photogrammetry to identify the causes and consequences of premature weaning in a wild primate, thus identifying some of the key mechanisms bridging early life environments to long-term developmental and health.   Broader Impacts:  This project has provided training opportunities in behavior, genomics, and physiology for two postdoctoral associates and several graduate students and undergraduates. It also provided valuable training and employment for three Ethiopian field assistants. The project members also shared the results from this project to a both an academic audience at conferences and in invited talks, as well as to the broader public both in the US and in Ethiopia where the data were collected. Finally, this project has provided novel information on the health and development of the endemic gelada, which will have important conservation implications for this unique species.        Last Modified: 11/29/2021       Submitted by: Noah Snyder-Mackler]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
