<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Center for Vision Science Symposium: Active Vision; Rochester, NY; June 2020]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>48500.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>48500</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Betty Tuller</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>btuller@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927238</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This award will support  travel and attendance costs for students, postdoctoral fellows, and faculty speakers at the 31st Center for Vision Science (CVS) Symposium on Active Vision. The Symposium will be held at the University of Rochester June 11-14, 2020. Active vision, the study of vision in the context of natural motor behavior, has grown and expanded greatly in recent years, in part due to advances in computational power, display technology, and ability to track body movements. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A rapidly growing body of evidence indicates that motor activity plays a critical role in the computational strategies used for establishing neural representations and achieving task demands. By bringing together a diverse array of viewpoints and creative methodological approaches to the study of the visual system in action, this symposium aims to uncover common principles of visuomotor computation, identify promising new research directions, disseminate knowledge of recent advances in the field, and attract and help form a new generation of researchers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/20/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/20/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2013317</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Martina</FirstName>
<LastName>Poletti</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Martina Poletti</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[martina.poletti@gmail.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000689933</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/20/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michele</FirstName>
<LastName>Rucci</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michele Rucci</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mrucci@ur.rochester.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000486601</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/20/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jude</FirstName>
<LastName>Mitchell</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jude Mitchell</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jmitch27@ur.rochester.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000702239</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/20/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Rochester</Name>
<CityName>ROCHESTER</CityName>
<ZipCode>146113847</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5852754031</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>910 GENESEE ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[STE 200]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>25</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY25</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>F27KDXZMF9Y8</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ROCHESTER</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University or Rochester]]></Name>
<CityName>Rochester</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>146270140</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[518 Hylan Bldg. Box 270140]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>25</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY25</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7252</Code>
<Text>Perception, Action &amp; Cognition</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7252</Code>
<Text>Perception, Action and Cognition</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~48500</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This grant contributed supporting a scientific symposium on motor behavior and sensory perception, which took place on May 19-22, 2022. This symposium was designed to accomplish three specific objectives: (1) advance understanding of the interactions between perception and behavior; (2) help creating a community of researchers; and (3) contribute forming a new generation of scholars.&nbsp;</p> <p>We organized the symposium in five talk sessions and two poster sessions distributed over the course of four days. The talks included presentations and panel discussions from 24 invited speakers.&nbsp; Approximately 150 participants attended the conference, including 57 graduate students and 21 postdoctoral researchers.&nbsp; Attendance was broadly international, with over one third of participants from outside the US, including participants from Canada, Europe, and Australia.</p> <p><strong>Intellectual Merit:</strong> This symposium was designed to provide a different perspective to the study of sensory perception.&nbsp; Under natural conditions, visual processes unfold in the incessant presence of motor behavior, as visually-guided actions contribute shaping the input signals to the retina.&nbsp; However, primarily because of technical limitations, laboratory studies of visual functions have traditionally minimized motor behavior and passively presented stimuli.&nbsp;</p> <p>Active vision, the study of vision in the context of natural motor behavior, has grown and expanded greatly in recent years, in part due to advances in computational power, display technology, and tracking of body movements. A vast and rapidly growing body of evidence indicates that motor activity plays a critical role in the computational strategies used for establishing neural representation and achieving task demands.&nbsp;</p> <p>By bringing together a diverse array of viewpoints and creative methodological approaches to the study of the visual system in action, this symposium focused on common principles of visuomotor computation.&nbsp; In terms of intellectual merit, the major goals of the symposium were to contribute establishing the behavioral foundations of visual perception and identify promising research directions. To this end, we invited a diverse group of 24 speakers from within and outside the US, who have distinguished themselves for innovative and creative research in areas pertinent to active vision. We purposely aimed for scholars who followed different approaches and focus on distinct questions, yet united by the common thread of studying sensory processing in close conjunction with motor behavior.&nbsp; The speakers intermingled with the other participants, many of whom presented relevant results in a poster format, thanks to a highly interactive meeting format that allocated ample room for in-depth discussions and facilitated cross-fertilization of ideas.</p> <p><strong>Broader Impact</strong>: There are many ways in which better understanding of how the visual system operates would benefit society, from the potential clinical repercussions to the development of innovative technology for visual displays, visual aids, and machine vision systems.&nbsp; Furthermore, the symposium served an important educational mission by contribute forming a new generation of scholars. It aimed to attract new students to the field by informing them about recent advances on the pervasive coupling between perception and action. As planned, we had a strong student participation from both the University of Rochester and other institutions. &nbsp; Students benefitted from the format of the meeting, which was specifically designed to facilitate interactions.&nbsp; We took several specific actions to encourage student involvement, including organizing two student-oriented poster sessions, and providing travel awards for students from distant locations.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/16/2023<br>      Modified by: Michele&nbsp;Rucci</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This grant contributed supporting a scientific symposium on motor behavior and sensory perception, which took place on May 19-22, 2022. This symposium was designed to accomplish three specific objectives: (1) advance understanding of the interactions between perception and behavior; (2) help creating a community of researchers; and (3) contribute forming a new generation of scholars.   We organized the symposium in five talk sessions and two poster sessions distributed over the course of four days. The talks included presentations and panel discussions from 24 invited speakers.  Approximately 150 participants attended the conference, including 57 graduate students and 21 postdoctoral researchers.  Attendance was broadly international, with over one third of participants from outside the US, including participants from Canada, Europe, and Australia.  Intellectual Merit: This symposium was designed to provide a different perspective to the study of sensory perception.  Under natural conditions, visual processes unfold in the incessant presence of motor behavior, as visually-guided actions contribute shaping the input signals to the retina.  However, primarily because of technical limitations, laboratory studies of visual functions have traditionally minimized motor behavior and passively presented stimuli.   Active vision, the study of vision in the context of natural motor behavior, has grown and expanded greatly in recent years, in part due to advances in computational power, display technology, and tracking of body movements. A vast and rapidly growing body of evidence indicates that motor activity plays a critical role in the computational strategies used for establishing neural representation and achieving task demands.   By bringing together a diverse array of viewpoints and creative methodological approaches to the study of the visual system in action, this symposium focused on common principles of visuomotor computation.  In terms of intellectual merit, the major goals of the symposium were to contribute establishing the behavioral foundations of visual perception and identify promising research directions. To this end, we invited a diverse group of 24 speakers from within and outside the US, who have distinguished themselves for innovative and creative research in areas pertinent to active vision. We purposely aimed for scholars who followed different approaches and focus on distinct questions, yet united by the common thread of studying sensory processing in close conjunction with motor behavior.  The speakers intermingled with the other participants, many of whom presented relevant results in a poster format, thanks to a highly interactive meeting format that allocated ample room for in-depth discussions and facilitated cross-fertilization of ideas.  Broader Impact: There are many ways in which better understanding of how the visual system operates would benefit society, from the potential clinical repercussions to the development of innovative technology for visual displays, visual aids, and machine vision systems.  Furthermore, the symposium served an important educational mission by contribute forming a new generation of scholars. It aimed to attract new students to the field by informing them about recent advances on the pervasive coupling between perception and action. As planned, we had a strong student participation from both the University of Rochester and other institutions.   Students benefitted from the format of the meeting, which was specifically designed to facilitate interactions.  We took several specific actions to encourage student involvement, including organizing two student-oriented poster sessions, and providing travel awards for students from distant locations.          Last Modified: 08/16/2023       Submitted by: Michele Rucci]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
