<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Phenomenology of Electroweak Symmetry Breaking, Supersymmetry, and the Frontiers of the Standard Model]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>180000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>180000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Keith Dienes</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kdienes@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925314</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This award funds the research activities of Professor Stephen P. Martin at Northern Illinois University.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will advance our knowledge of the basic building blocks of matter and the forces of interaction between them.  Among the fundamental subatomic particles is the Higgs boson, which was discovered in 2012 and is now the subject of intense studies at the Large Hadron Collider.  Professor Martin will pursue an enhanced understanding of the Higgs boson and other subatomic particles.  He will also study theories that extend the known particles and forces, including a possibility known as supersymmetry.  The central prediction of this theory is that for each of the known types of fundamental particles, there must be another type with very similar properties but which are much heavier.  Professor Martin will work on strategies for discovering such new particles at the Large Hadron Collider and proposed future collider experiments.  He will also do the same for theories that provide alternatives to supersymmetry.  These activities advance the national interest by promoting our understanding of how nature works at the most fundamental level.  This project will also have broader impacts.  Professor Martin will mentor and train students at both the graduate and undergraduate levels on relevant methods of research.  He will also interact directly with pre-college students and other interested members of the public through exhibitions and judging at local and regional science fairs.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;More technically, Martin will compute multi-loop corrections to the effective potential that governs the scalar field associated with the Higgs boson.  He will extend existing results for the effective potential in general non-supersymmetric theories to include supersymmetric models, using regularization methods that respect supersymmetric invariance.  He will also develop methods for evaluating three-loop contributions to particle masses, including the Higgs boson and the W and Z bosons of the Standard Model of particle physics.  He will study non-minimal theories of supersymmetry, exploring possibilities that address a puzzle called the little hierarchy problem.  He will study the production and decay of supersymmetric particles at proposed future proton-proton and electron-positron colliders, to understand the reach of those experiments for making new discoveries.  He also plans to continue studies of new particles in non-supersymmetric theories, including, for example, new vector-like leptons.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/21/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/19/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2013340</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Stephen</FirstName>
<LastName>Martin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Stephen P Martin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[spmartin@niu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000457042</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/21/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Northern Illinois University</Name>
<CityName>DEKALB</CityName>
<ZipCode>601152828</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8157531581</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1425 W LINCOLN HWY</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>14</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL14</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>M2EEE68GGCY9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORTHERN ILLINOIS UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Northern Illinois University]]></Name>
<CityName>DeKalb</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>601152828</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[301 Lowden Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>14</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL14</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1286</Code>
<Text>Elem. Particle Physics/Theory</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~180000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project produced several studies of the prospects for discovering new fundamental particles at the present Large Hadron Collider and proposed future colliders. One class of new particles is similar to the electron, but is much heavier and short-lived and interacts in slightly different ways than an electron would. It was found that although these new particles would be very difficult to discover at the Large Hadron Collider, they would be straightforward to find at proposed facilities that would collider electrons and positrons, provided that the beam energies of those colliders will be high enough.</p> <p>The project also studied and classified certain theoretical frameworks that could naturally explain dark matter as a type of very light and very weakly interacting particle called an axion. These theoretical frameworks include supersymmetry, a general proposal that for each known type of fundamental particle, there is a "partner" type of particle that interacts in the same way but has a much larger mass. It was found that theories of this type that avoid possible conflicts with data from astrophysics also predict that the axion should be discoverable at experiments that should be possible with present technology.</p> <p>The project also worked out several new calculation techniques in high-energy particle physics that will enable more efficient and precise evaluations of particle masses and interactions. Particle physicists currently use a theory called the Standard Model, which contains about 20 input numbers, to predict the results of their experiments. The project produced relatively simple formulas that relate these theoretical input parameters to measured quantities including the masses of particles like the top quark, the Higgs boson, and the Z and W particles that are responsible for the weak nuclear force.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/14/2023<br>      Modified by: Stephen&nbsp;P&nbsp;Martin</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project produced several studies of the prospects for discovering new fundamental particles at the present Large Hadron Collider and proposed future colliders. One class of new particles is similar to the electron, but is much heavier and short-lived and interacts in slightly different ways than an electron would. It was found that although these new particles would be very difficult to discover at the Large Hadron Collider, they would be straightforward to find at proposed facilities that would collider electrons and positrons, provided that the beam energies of those colliders will be high enough.  The project also studied and classified certain theoretical frameworks that could naturally explain dark matter as a type of very light and very weakly interacting particle called an axion. These theoretical frameworks include supersymmetry, a general proposal that for each known type of fundamental particle, there is a "partner" type of particle that interacts in the same way but has a much larger mass. It was found that theories of this type that avoid possible conflicts with data from astrophysics also predict that the axion should be discoverable at experiments that should be possible with present technology.  The project also worked out several new calculation techniques in high-energy particle physics that will enable more efficient and precise evaluations of particle masses and interactions. Particle physicists currently use a theory called the Standard Model, which contains about 20 input numbers, to predict the results of their experiments. The project produced relatively simple formulas that relate these theoretical input parameters to measured quantities including the masses of particles like the top quark, the Higgs boson, and the Z and W particles that are responsible for the weak nuclear force.                Last Modified: 09/14/2023       Submitted by: Stephen P Martin]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
