<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Low-Threshold Modular Detectors for Coherent Elastic Neutrino-Nucleus Scattering]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>248975.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>248975</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>William Wester</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>wwester@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924677</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The goal of this R&amp;D award is to develop Transition-Edge Sensor (TES) detectors optimized for measurements of Coherent Elastic Neutrino-Nucleus Scattering (CEvNS) with  low-energy thresholds two orders of magnitude lower than the CsI detectors used for the initial CEvNS measurement. These detectors will open a new window at low-recoil energies to study this relatively new channel in neutrino physics that has yet to be fully explored. By measuring the neutrino spectrum from a reactor, and comparing it to the standard model predictions, we gain sensitivity to physics beyond the Standard Model in scenarios including 1) an anomalous neutrino magnetic moment, 2) Non-Standard Interactions (NSI) of neutrinos, and 3) neutrinos coupling to new particles beyond the Standard Model. At the same time, they will enable a study of the low energy end of the reactor antineutrino flux that is inaccessible to inverse-beta-decay detectors and a search for possible sterile neutrinos, which have been postulated to exist but have never been seen.  In pursuit of this goal, there are four objectives: (1) perform a detailed study to model and optimize a low-threshold TES-based CEvNS experiment focusing on detector performance, backgrounds, and science reach, (2) fabricate several prototype detectors based on the outcome of (1), (3) test these detectors and compare their performance to the models, and (4) train a new generation of neutrino experimental physicists. The work has a broad impact that extends beyond neutrino physics. TES detectors have applications in cosmology, astronomy, industry, and defense. This activity will contribute to the training of undergraduate and graduate students and postdoctoral researchers, continuing the group’s commitment to mentoring undergraduates from underrepresented groups by participating in the Summer Research Opportunities Program (SROP) at Northwestern.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The group will evaluate TES designs for optimizing the science output of a CEvNS experiment at a nuclear reactor. Given a neutrino flux at the detector, they will consider the TES device physics, target materials and mass per detector, readout multiplexing architectures and achievable mass with these parameters, detector packaging and installation in a cryogenic system, backgrounds, shielding, and calibration. They will fabricate several TES sensors on standard silicon wafers based on the outcomes of the optimization study. The Northwestern EXperimental Underground Site (NEXUS) at Fermilab will be used to test these prototype detectors and compare their performance to their models. Calibrations will be performed with optical and X-ray sources and a dedicated neutron beam and backing detector array to accurately report the response to low-energy nuclear recoils.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/09/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/29/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2013203</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Enectali</FirstName>
<LastName>Figueroa-Feliciano</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Enectali Figueroa-Feliciano</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[enectali@northwestern.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000484720</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/09/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Northwestern University</Name>
<CityName>EVANSTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>602080001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3125037955</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>633 CLARK STREET</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>EXZVPWZBLUE8</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORTHWESTERN UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Northwestern University]]></Name>
<CityName>Evanston</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>602080834</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2145 Sheridan Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1232</Code>
<Text>Nuclear &amp; Hadron Quantum Chrom</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7235</Code>
<Text>Particle Astrophysics/Undergro</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7483</Code>
<Text>PHYSICS OF THE UNIVERSE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~132148</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~116827</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Neutrinos are one of the most enigmatic of fundamental particles and the only ones we can produce that clearly show physics beyond the standard model. The relatively new CEvNS neutral current channel, detected for the first time in 2017, provides a new way to study neutrino properties, understand nuclear form factors, and search for deviations from standard model predictions.</p> <p>This proposal had four objectives:</p> <p>(1) perform a detailed study to model and optimize a low-threshold TES-based CEvNS experiment focusing on detector performance and science reach</p> <p>(2) fabricate several prototype &nbsp;CEvNS detectors based on the outcome of (1)</p> <p>(3) test these detectors and compare their performance to our models, and</p> <p>(4) train a new generation of neutrino experimental physicists.</p> <p><em>Modeling and Optimization</em>: We used our decades-long experience in the modeling of TES devices to evaluate designs for optimizing the science output of a CEvNS experiment at a nuclear reactor. We developed a detailed thermal model of the detector architecture and designed prototype detectors, and developed the mechanical detector housing and electronics readout to study these devices.</p> <p><em>Fabrication</em>: We fabricated a wafer of more than 500 individual TES sensors based on the outcomes of the optimization study at the Argonne National Laboratory with a 22mK transition temperature (see Figure "TES Wafer")</p> <p><em>Testing and Validation</em>: We used silicon and zinc as our target materials in our testing. Detector testing was carried out at our collaborator institutions. UMass Amherst performed all the Silicon detector testing and MIT performed the Zinc target tests (see Figure "Prototype Ricochet Device"). Our group, in collaboration with the University of Toronto, set up a Python processing software based on an open-source version of the SuperCDMS-developed detector analysis software called pyCRP. This software package uses python scripts and Jupyter notebooks for the data analysis. Northwestern also led the modeling effort, and took complex impedance data at Argonne National Lab on individual test chips. Finally, a tower of 5 detectors was designed and put together over the summer of 2022, and installed in the NEXUS facility in the fall. This payload includes a 36 g Ge target, a 40 g Zn target, and a 21 g LMO target for neutrinoless double beta decay R&amp;D for the CUPID experiment, all read out by the modular TES chips designed through this grant. Results of these will be part of the next grant.</p> <p><em>Training and Outreach</em><span>: The activities in this proposal provided fertile ground for training of Valentina Novati, a postdoctoral researcher, and several graduate students at Northwestern, UMass, and MIT. The outcomes of this work have been presented by our students and PI at several national and international conferences.</span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/09/2022<br>      Modified by: Enectali&nbsp;Figueroa-Feliciano</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2013203/2013203_10694621_1670612239084_TES_wafer--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2013203/2013203_10694621_1670612239084_TES_wafer--rgov-800width.jpg" title="TES Wafer"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2013203/2013203_10694621_1670612239084_TES_wafer--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="TES Wafer"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Prototype standard silicon 4-in wafer with 600 devices. A similar design on a 6 in wafer would yield more than 1000 TES devices per wafer.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Argonne National Lab and Northwestern University</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Enectali&nbsp;Figueroa-Feliciano</div> <div class="imageTitle">TES Wafer</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2013203/2013203_10694621_1670612650368_Prototype_Device--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2013203/2013203_10694621_1670612650368_Prototype_Device--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Prototype Ricochet Device"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2013203/2013203_10694621_1670612650368_Prototype_Device--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Prototype Ricochet Device"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">A Zinc target is held in a copper R&D holder. A triangular-shaped gold film has been deposited on its surface, and a TES chip is mounted on the holder in preparation to being connected to the target via a gold wire bond.</div> <div class="imageCredit">MIT, Northwestern</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Enectali&nbsp;Figueroa-Feliciano</div> <div class="imageTitle">Prototype Ricochet Device</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Neutrinos are one of the most enigmatic of fundamental particles and the only ones we can produce that clearly show physics beyond the standard model. The relatively new CEvNS neutral current channel, detected for the first time in 2017, provides a new way to study neutrino properties, understand nuclear form factors, and search for deviations from standard model predictions.  This proposal had four objectives:  (1) perform a detailed study to model and optimize a low-threshold TES-based CEvNS experiment focusing on detector performance and science reach  (2) fabricate several prototype  CEvNS detectors based on the outcome of (1)  (3) test these detectors and compare their performance to our models, and  (4) train a new generation of neutrino experimental physicists.  Modeling and Optimization: We used our decades-long experience in the modeling of TES devices to evaluate designs for optimizing the science output of a CEvNS experiment at a nuclear reactor. We developed a detailed thermal model of the detector architecture and designed prototype detectors, and developed the mechanical detector housing and electronics readout to study these devices.  Fabrication: We fabricated a wafer of more than 500 individual TES sensors based on the outcomes of the optimization study at the Argonne National Laboratory with a 22mK transition temperature (see Figure "TES Wafer")  Testing and Validation: We used silicon and zinc as our target materials in our testing. Detector testing was carried out at our collaborator institutions. UMass Amherst performed all the Silicon detector testing and MIT performed the Zinc target tests (see Figure "Prototype Ricochet Device"). Our group, in collaboration with the University of Toronto, set up a Python processing software based on an open-source version of the SuperCDMS-developed detector analysis software called pyCRP. This software package uses python scripts and Jupyter notebooks for the data analysis. Northwestern also led the modeling effort, and took complex impedance data at Argonne National Lab on individual test chips. Finally, a tower of 5 detectors was designed and put together over the summer of 2022, and installed in the NEXUS facility in the fall. This payload includes a 36 g Ge target, a 40 g Zn target, and a 21 g LMO target for neutrinoless double beta decay R&amp;D for the CUPID experiment, all read out by the modular TES chips designed through this grant. Results of these will be part of the next grant.  Training and Outreach: The activities in this proposal provided fertile ground for training of Valentina Novati, a postdoctoral researcher, and several graduate students at Northwestern, UMass, and MIT. The outcomes of this work have been presented by our students and PI at several national and international conferences.       Last Modified: 12/09/2022       Submitted by: Enectali Figueroa-Feliciano]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
