<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Shape Memory Alloy Thermal Energy Harvesting System]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>225000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>225000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Muralidharan Nair</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mnair@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927059</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project will address challenges with enduring low operating margins and plant inefficiencies across many application areas. Recovering low-grade waste heat is often a technically impractical and cost-prohibitive process. The proposed technology is designed to offset operating costs and increase overall plant efficiency. Target users for the thermal energy-harvesting system are owners/operators of combined heat and power (CHP) installations, metal manufacturers, chemical processors, industrial boilers, and other industrial facilities currently unable to recover the substantial amounts of low-grade waste heat that their facilities generate. The technology would potentially offer these applications reduced operating costs, reduced energy demands, and improved sustainability.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project will advance the translation of porous Shape Memory Alloy (SMA) materials as actuators. The innovation will be an SMA actuator comprised of a novel, porous SMA material operating in a compact rotary form. The porous material's small feature size will allow for fast heat transfer and phase transformation, compared to solid SMA actuators. This novel actuator is expected to result in the recovery of substantially more power from the same mass of SMA material. The proposed Phase I proof-of-concept work will produce validated models of the overall SMA behavior and its coupled behavior in a system, including heat transfer, thermo-mechanical behavior, and localized stresses. In addition to the improved models, the proposed work will focus on reliability for translation of porous SMA materials.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/15/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/15/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2013838</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kelly</FirstName>
<LastName>Rowles</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kelly J Rowles</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[kelly.rowles@legovsystemsgroup.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000792023</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/15/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>LEGOV SYSTEMS GROUP LLC</Name>
<CityName>BOISE</CityName>
<ZipCode>837135146</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2088691122</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1805 WILDWOOD ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Idaho</StateName>
<StateCode>ID</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>ID02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NV9BGVJESF56</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>LEGOV SYSTEMS GROUP LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>RMMFNHCS8BD3</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Legov Systems Group]]></Name>
<CityName>Boise</CityName>
<StateCode>ID</StateCode>
<ZipCode>837094571</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[10941 W. Mohawk Pl]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Idaho</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>ID01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>123E</Code>
<Text>CENTERS: ADVANCED MATERIALS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~225000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-b6aacd74-7fff-3204-c1a4-abdcec42ffe6"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The overall project goal was to demonstrate the technical feasibility of generating electricity from low-grade waste heat using our innovative shape memory alloy (SMA) actuator made from nickel-titanium (NiTi) tubes operating with rotary motion. In order to accomplish this overall goal, the team focused on achieving three main objectives: develop performance models of SMA actuators, evaluate the reliability of NiTi SMA porous tubes for low-grade heat recovery, and demonstrate the technical feasibility of our thermal energy harvesting system by building and characterizing a system that operates with cold and hot water. Our target was to operate a full thermal cycle in 7 seconds and produce 50 Watts of power.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The original plan was to use tubes made from porous NiTi materials as actuators because of their small feature size and anticipated fast reaction time. However, these articles proved to be unreliable and were subject to premature failure with one article operating for 1300 cycles and all others failing upon initial loading. In order to demonstrate feasibility, the team switched to thin-walled, solid NiTi tubes. While solid actuators had slower response than the porous tubes, they were robust and enabled us to demonstrate feasibility. A demonstration system was built using solid NiTi tubes trained to actuate with rotary motion. Hot and cold water were used to cause rotary actuation. A</span><span> full heating and cooling cycle of the solid tube actuator was completed in </span><span>7.5 seconds</span><span>, which is much slower than the </span><span>target 1 second</span><span> </span><span>as expected for porous tubes. The solid tube demonstration system exhibited a peak mechanical power of </span><span>24.8W</span><span> which compares favorably with our </span><span>target 50W</span><span> system given the slower cycle time of solid tubes. </span><span>Models for heat transfer and SMA actuation showed good agreement with experimental data and will provide good tools for future SMA actuator development.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>During this Phase I project, feasibility of thermal energy harvesting using Nitinol was demonstrated with small-scale hardware. Models of the thermal, SMA actuation, and the generator were developed and weakly coupled together to provide a rough estimate of system behavior. Porous tube actuators were found to underperform and prone to failure, thus preventing them from being used in the demonstration system. Solid tube rotary actuators were used to demonstrate the technology and achieved peak mechanical power of 24.8W and average power of 3.1W. Power output was limited by cycle time which could be improved using different flow rates and fluid temperatures. The work completed demonstrated the overall feasibility of thermal energy harvesting with Nitinol rotary actuators, however, much work remains to further develop and commercialize the technology. Future work will focus on decreasing cycle time, increasing mechanical power, matching electrical generators with the system, and scaling up to provide continuous rotary motion using multiple actuators.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/29/2022<br>      Modified by: Kelly&nbsp;J&nbsp;Rowles</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   The overall project goal was to demonstrate the technical feasibility of generating electricity from low-grade waste heat using our innovative shape memory alloy (SMA) actuator made from nickel-titanium (NiTi) tubes operating with rotary motion. In order to accomplish this overall goal, the team focused on achieving three main objectives: develop performance models of SMA actuators, evaluate the reliability of NiTi SMA porous tubes for low-grade heat recovery, and demonstrate the technical feasibility of our thermal energy harvesting system by building and characterizing a system that operates with cold and hot water. Our target was to operate a full thermal cycle in 7 seconds and produce 50 Watts of power. The original plan was to use tubes made from porous NiTi materials as actuators because of their small feature size and anticipated fast reaction time. However, these articles proved to be unreliable and were subject to premature failure with one article operating for 1300 cycles and all others failing upon initial loading. In order to demonstrate feasibility, the team switched to thin-walled, solid NiTi tubes. While solid actuators had slower response than the porous tubes, they were robust and enabled us to demonstrate feasibility. A demonstration system was built using solid NiTi tubes trained to actuate with rotary motion. Hot and cold water were used to cause rotary actuation. A full heating and cooling cycle of the solid tube actuator was completed in 7.5 seconds, which is much slower than the target 1 second as expected for porous tubes. The solid tube demonstration system exhibited a peak mechanical power of 24.8W which compares favorably with our target 50W system given the slower cycle time of solid tubes. Models for heat transfer and SMA actuation showed good agreement with experimental data and will provide good tools for future SMA actuator development.  During this Phase I project, feasibility of thermal energy harvesting using Nitinol was demonstrated with small-scale hardware. Models of the thermal, SMA actuation, and the generator were developed and weakly coupled together to provide a rough estimate of system behavior. Porous tube actuators were found to underperform and prone to failure, thus preventing them from being used in the demonstration system. Solid tube rotary actuators were used to demonstrate the technology and achieved peak mechanical power of 24.8W and average power of 3.1W. Power output was limited by cycle time which could be improved using different flow rates and fluid temperatures. The work completed demonstrated the overall feasibility of thermal energy harvesting with Nitinol rotary actuators, however, much work remains to further develop and commercialize the technology. Future work will focus on decreasing cycle time, increasing mechanical power, matching electrical generators with the system, and scaling up to provide continuous rotary motion using multiple actuators.          Last Modified: 04/29/2022       Submitted by: Kelly J Rowles]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
