<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Workshop - Understanding accelerators as organizations that influence diversity and inclusion in entrepreneurship through practices; University Park, PA; Summer 2020]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>38950.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>38950</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tara Behrend</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tsbehren@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928053</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Despite the widespread availability of accelerators and other context for entrepreneurship education, the high-tech, high-growth (HTHG) entrepreneurial ecosystem remains mostly white and male. Accelerators are organizations with specific practices and processes that inform their culture and structure. Research that is devoted to the organizational science of accelerators and their practical role in matters of diversity and inclusion in HTHG entrepreneurship is needed. To prime the development of such a literature, this workshop – Understanding Accelerators as Organizations that Influence Diversity and Inclusion in Entrepreneurship – will convene faculty researchers and graduate students in organization science and entrepreneurship as well as practitioners who facilitate accelerators. Once assembled, participants will set forth an agenda for future research that will advance theories of organization about accelerators while attending to issues of relevance in practice. The output from the gathering will be shared widely to stimulate awareness about the need for greater diversity and inclusion in the entrepreneurial ecosystem and the means by which scholars and practitioners can collaborate on rigorous and relevant research. Moreover, the workshop aims to be the beginning of an ongoing community of shared interest that can continue to move forward scholarship on entrepreneurship and diversity over time.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In recent decades, studies of science education have shifted the expectations for diversity and inclusion contexts for learning about Science, Technology, Engineering, and Math (STEM). Despite the overlap between STEM and HTHG entrepreneurship, only limited insights have transferred from informal STEM learning contexts to accelerators. Starting with these gaps, this workshop will highlight what is known (and what needs to be known) about accelerators as organizations and their impact on matters of diversity and inclusion in HTHG entrepreneurship. The developed research agenda will encourage interdisciplinary scholarship on matters of diversity and inclusion in contexts for entrepreneurship education. New insights stand to be fostered in organizational science regarding how to support greater diversity and inclusion in accelerators as well as in adjacent activity settings such as universities with formal entrepreneurship programs and businesses in the entrepreneurial ecosystem. These insights will advance scientific knowledge on the role that the processes and practices of accelerators have on the initial involvement and career trajectories of entrepreneurs from non-dominant population groups (including women, people of color, people from working class backgrounds, and people from rural communities), thereby promoting greater equity in the innovation economy.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/07/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/07/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2013661</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Betsy</FirstName>
<LastName>Campbell</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Betsy Campbell</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[bjc28@psu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000807383</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/07/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Pennsylvania State Univ University Park</Name>
<CityName>UNIVERSITY PARK</CityName>
<ZipCode>168021503</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8148651372</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>201 OLD MAIN</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>15</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA15</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NPM2J7MSCF61</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>THE PENNSYLVANIA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Pennsylvania State Univ University Park]]></Name>
<CityName>University Park</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>168023206</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[201 Chambers Building]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT/>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA"</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8031</Code>
<Text>SoO-Science Of Organizations</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~38950</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Innovative entrepreneurship lacks diversity. Women, people of color, people from rural communities, and people with differently abled bodies are under-represented. Despite the widespread availability of accelerators, the demographics of entrepreneurship remain unchanged. It seems that accelerators have been successful at providing more people in general with entrepreneurial learning opportunities, but this has not translated into <em>more minoritized people</em> founding innovative ventures.</p> <p>This workshop (NSF Award Abstract # 2013661) convened scholars and accelerator leaders to explore how diversity, inclusion, and belonging are understood, how accelerator leaders are addressing the persistent lack of diversity in entrepreneurship, and how scholars and practitioners might collaborate to build better theory and make social change.</p> <p>The workshop originally was designed as an in-person one-day gathering on the University Park campus of Penn State University. However, the restrictions of the pandemic required a shift to a virtual setting. The workshop was transformed into a series of 60-90-minute online sessions over the span of five weeks. Each session had a theme:</p> <p>Session 1 - Perspectives from the field: Hearing from accelerator leaders</p> <p>Session 2 - Turning to the literature</p> <p>Session 3 - Possible projects: Exploring and evolving ideas</p> <p>Session 4 - Prospective project exchange: Developing projects and recommendations</p> <p>Session 5 - Considering future ways to develop the work collaboratively</p> <p>Members of the workshop were invited to two additional virtual events &ndash; one public and one only for members of the workshop &ndash; focused on emerging work related to diversity in accelerators. These events were part of the 2021 virtual Babson College Entrepreneurship Research Conference (BCERC). Participants also had access to the workshop website, a suite of online shared documents, and an online discussion forum.</p> <p>Fifty scholars, doctoral students, and accelerator leaders were invited to participate in the workshop. Invited faculty members contribute to the entrepreneurship-as-practice literature or do research addressing matters of diversity in entrepreneurship. Many also explore the rigor-relevance debate in the management literature or the research-practice divide in the entrepreneurship literature. The invited accelerator leaders facilitate some of the largest informal entrepreneurship education and support programs in the US. They also write or speak about the importance of diversity, inclusion, and belonging in contexts for entrepreneurial learning.</p> <p>In order to connect research to the real concerns of practice, the workshop encouraged accelerator leaders to share insights and issues from the field. Chief among the topics raised was the lack of representation of women and people of color in leadership roles within accelerators (e.g., personnel, mentors, funders). A second concern was the impact of accelerator expectations related to matters of performance and scaling on minoritized founders. And a third was the role of cultural influences beyond the accelerator and even in childhood on prospective founders; the ways that the lack of diversity in entrepreneurship starts long before someone applies to participate in an accelerator cohort.</p> <p>These insights from accelerator leaders prompted conversations about research projects that could advance both theory and practice on matters of diversity. Studies probing matters of representation in accelerators could investigate the practices related to mentoring, staffing, partnering, and funding. Studies focused on pressures related to performance could investigate the practices related to cohort selection, sociomateriality within the accelerator, and even the role of time, including historical perspectives and the moment-by-moment co-creation of identities and contexts. And studies exploring the ways that young people come to see themselves in innovative entrepreneurial work could investigate the interactions that youth -- especially girls, children of color, and other minoritized children -- have with entrepreneurial narratives and other forms of discovery about entrepreneurship.</p> <p>Intellectual Merit: A main goal of this workshop was to identify research questions and approaches that could investigate diversity in accelerators in ways that would advance theory and practice. The workshop has produced a research agenda entitled, <em>Diversity in innovative entrepreneurship: Developing a practice-informed research agenda</em>. The workshop also has sparked several collaborations between scholars and practitioners and an ongoing community of shared interest.</p> <p>Broader Impact: The workshop and the deliverables from the workshop are already helping to foster closer collaborations between scholars and practitioners in accelerators. As theory becomes better connected to the actual challenges of practice, accelerators will be positioned to help make the entrepreneurial ecosystem more diverse. Moreover, additional research anchored in practice-theories may influence the ways that organizations across the entire entrepreneurial ecosystem come to understand diversity and endeavor to address matters of diversity, inclusion, and belonging.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/31/2022<br>      Modified by: Betsy&nbsp;Campbell</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Innovative entrepreneurship lacks diversity. Women, people of color, people from rural communities, and people with differently abled bodies are under-represented. Despite the widespread availability of accelerators, the demographics of entrepreneurship remain unchanged. It seems that accelerators have been successful at providing more people in general with entrepreneurial learning opportunities, but this has not translated into more minoritized people founding innovative ventures.  This workshop (NSF Award Abstract # 2013661) convened scholars and accelerator leaders to explore how diversity, inclusion, and belonging are understood, how accelerator leaders are addressing the persistent lack of diversity in entrepreneurship, and how scholars and practitioners might collaborate to build better theory and make social change.  The workshop originally was designed as an in-person one-day gathering on the University Park campus of Penn State University. However, the restrictions of the pandemic required a shift to a virtual setting. The workshop was transformed into a series of 60-90-minute online sessions over the span of five weeks. Each session had a theme:  Session 1 - Perspectives from the field: Hearing from accelerator leaders  Session 2 - Turning to the literature  Session 3 - Possible projects: Exploring and evolving ideas  Session 4 - Prospective project exchange: Developing projects and recommendations  Session 5 - Considering future ways to develop the work collaboratively  Members of the workshop were invited to two additional virtual events &ndash; one public and one only for members of the workshop &ndash; focused on emerging work related to diversity in accelerators. These events were part of the 2021 virtual Babson College Entrepreneurship Research Conference (BCERC). Participants also had access to the workshop website, a suite of online shared documents, and an online discussion forum.  Fifty scholars, doctoral students, and accelerator leaders were invited to participate in the workshop. Invited faculty members contribute to the entrepreneurship-as-practice literature or do research addressing matters of diversity in entrepreneurship. Many also explore the rigor-relevance debate in the management literature or the research-practice divide in the entrepreneurship literature. The invited accelerator leaders facilitate some of the largest informal entrepreneurship education and support programs in the US. They also write or speak about the importance of diversity, inclusion, and belonging in contexts for entrepreneurial learning.  In order to connect research to the real concerns of practice, the workshop encouraged accelerator leaders to share insights and issues from the field. Chief among the topics raised was the lack of representation of women and people of color in leadership roles within accelerators (e.g., personnel, mentors, funders). A second concern was the impact of accelerator expectations related to matters of performance and scaling on minoritized founders. And a third was the role of cultural influences beyond the accelerator and even in childhood on prospective founders; the ways that the lack of diversity in entrepreneurship starts long before someone applies to participate in an accelerator cohort.  These insights from accelerator leaders prompted conversations about research projects that could advance both theory and practice on matters of diversity. Studies probing matters of representation in accelerators could investigate the practices related to mentoring, staffing, partnering, and funding. Studies focused on pressures related to performance could investigate the practices related to cohort selection, sociomateriality within the accelerator, and even the role of time, including historical perspectives and the moment-by-moment co-creation of identities and contexts. And studies exploring the ways that young people come to see themselves in innovative entrepreneurial work could investigate the interactions that youth -- especially girls, children of color, and other minoritized children -- have with entrepreneurial narratives and other forms of discovery about entrepreneurship.  Intellectual Merit: A main goal of this workshop was to identify research questions and approaches that could investigate diversity in accelerators in ways that would advance theory and practice. The workshop has produced a research agenda entitled, Diversity in innovative entrepreneurship: Developing a practice-informed research agenda. The workshop also has sparked several collaborations between scholars and practitioners and an ongoing community of shared interest.  Broader Impact: The workshop and the deliverables from the workshop are already helping to foster closer collaborations between scholars and practitioners in accelerators. As theory becomes better connected to the actual challenges of practice, accelerators will be positioned to help make the entrepreneurial ecosystem more diverse. Moreover, additional research anchored in practice-theories may influence the ways that organizations across the entire entrepreneurial ecosystem come to understand diversity and endeavor to address matters of diversity, inclusion, and belonging.       Last Modified: 05/31/2022       Submitted by: Betsy Campbell]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
