<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Data-Based System Reliability Design for Wind]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>464750.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>464750</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joy Pauschke</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jpauschk@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927024</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Wind loads used in current design standards do not account for various sources of uncertainties, such as wind tunnel records, climatological data, and surface roughness length. This simplified characterization may yield inaccurate wind effects and, as a result, unsatisfactory estimates of the performance of buildings subjected to wind loads. This award will overcome limitations of current standards by developing a practical computational framework for wind design, based on climatological data, wind tunnel records, and rigorous probabilistic/statistical concepts. The framework will quantify the uncertainties in wind loads by probabilistic models, propagate these uncertainties into wind effects by efficient computational methods, and develop design conditions which view buildings as systems rather than collections of independent components. The research will be complemented by an educational program involving course development, graduate and undergraduate researchers, and presentations at national and international conferences. The computational framework will be shared with the NSF-supported Natural Hazards Engineering Research Infrastructure, Computational Modeling and Simulation Center, as a module for wind design.  This research will contribute to NSF's role in the National Windstorm Impact Reduction Program. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will develop a computational framework that constitutes a new paradigm in wind engineering. The framework will map climatological and wind tunnel data into system reliability estimates for buildings subjected to wind loads by accounting for the mechanical and aerodynamic characteristics of these buildings. The system reliability methodology for wind design will be based on: (1) novel probabilistic models for wind loads whose samples and realizations, rather than just their mean and correlation functions, will be statistically consistent with wind tunnel time histories, (2) new efficient methods for calculating wind effect samples from wind load samples in linear/nonlinear structures subjected to stationary/nonstationary, Gaussian/non-Gaussian wind loads, and (3) system reliability estimates of structural performance that, unlike current approaches that check ultimate/serviceability limit states member-by-member, will consider these limit states simultaneously at all structural members. The format of the ultimate/serviceability criteria will be similar to that of current standards.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/17/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/17/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2013697</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mircea</FirstName>
<LastName>Grigoriu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mircea D Grigoriu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mdg12@cornell.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000107763</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/17/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Cornell University</Name>
<CityName>ITHACA</CityName>
<ZipCode>148502820</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6072555014</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>341 PINE TREE RD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>19</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY19</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>G56PUALJ3KT5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CORNELL UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Cornell University]]></Name>
<CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>148533501</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[527 College Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>19</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY19</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>073Y</Code>
<Text>ECI-Engineering for Civil Infr</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>036E</Code>
<Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>039E</Code>
<Text>STRUCTURAL SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>040E</Code>
<Text>Haz mitigation of structural sys</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1057</Code>
<Text>CIS BASE RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7231</Code>
<Text>CYBERINFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>CVIS</Code>
<Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~464750</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Accurate estimates of extreme wind responses are required for the design of safe and economical structural systems subjected to wind loads.&nbsp; The accuracy of these estimates is affected by the inherent uncertainty in wind loads and the inability of current methods for wind analysis to predict extremes of wind responses even for linear structures.&nbsp; The project addresses these two aspects of Wind Engineering.&nbsp; It (1) constructs probabilistic models capable of characterizing wind loads, which constitute Gaussian and/or non-Gaussian random functions of time, and fits these models to pressure time series provided by the boundary layer wind tunnel facility at the University of Florda and (2) develops practical methods for calculating responses of linear/nonlinear structural systems subjected to Gaussian/non-Gausian wind loads and estimating extremes of these responses which can be used directly for wind design.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The developments in the project are based on finite dimensional (FD) models , i.e., deterministic functions of time and finite sets of random variables, which are required to satisfy two conditions.&nbsp; First, the FD wind load models must capture the details of the wind load time series such that responses to these models are consistent with actual responses.&nbsp; Second, the number of random variables in the definition of the FD wind load models must be relatively small such that the numerical algorithms employed to estimate extreme wind responses to FD models are efficient.&nbsp; The performance of the FD wind loads models and of the methods for estimating extreme wind responses has been validated successfully against wind tunnel and synthetic data.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/29/2023<br>      Modified by: Mircea&nbsp;D&nbsp;Grigoriu</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Accurate estimates of extreme wind responses are required for the design of safe and economical structural systems subjected to wind loads.  The accuracy of these estimates is affected by the inherent uncertainty in wind loads and the inability of current methods for wind analysis to predict extremes of wind responses even for linear structures.  The project addresses these two aspects of Wind Engineering.  It (1) constructs probabilistic models capable of characterizing wind loads, which constitute Gaussian and/or non-Gaussian random functions of time, and fits these models to pressure time series provided by the boundary layer wind tunnel facility at the University of Florda and (2) develops practical methods for calculating responses of linear/nonlinear structural systems subjected to Gaussian/non-Gausian wind loads and estimating extremes of these responses which can be used directly for wind design.     The developments in the project are based on finite dimensional (FD) models , i.e., deterministic functions of time and finite sets of random variables, which are required to satisfy two conditions.  First, the FD wind load models must capture the details of the wind load time series such that responses to these models are consistent with actual responses.  Second, the number of random variables in the definition of the FD wind load models must be relatively small such that the numerical algorithms employed to estimate extreme wind responses to FD models are efficient.  The performance of the FD wind loads models and of the methods for estimating extreme wind responses has been validated successfully against wind tunnel and synthetic data.          Last Modified: 09/29/2023       Submitted by: Mircea D Grigoriu]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
