<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Using Virtual Reality Mathematics and Science Simulations to Prepare Elementary Teachers to Create Successful Learning Experiences for Students in High-Need Urban Schools]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>586111.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>586111</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kathleen Bergin</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kbergin@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925171</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This project aims to serve the national interest of improving teaching and learning of mathematics and science.  Specifically, it will investigate the use of mixed reality classroom simulations in the preparation of K-8 teachers in urban schools.  Mixed-reality virtual simulations combine real people and physical environments with virtual people and places. Pilots spend long hours using virtual simulators before flying a plane carrying real passengers.  It is now possible to provide K-8 pre-service teachers with  opportunities to virtually practice teaching strategies that can enhance learning before serving students in real classrooms. California State Los Angeles University Charter College of Education faculty will modify scenario scripts and develop new ones specifically focused on science and mathematics concepts in the context of high-poverty, urban schools with large ethnically diverse student populations. The project, in partnership with elementary and middle schools in the Los Angeles Unified School District in East Los Angeles and other smaller area districts, intends to investigate three research questions associated with the impact of mixed-reality virtual classroom simulations in K-8 teacher preparation.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will modify and develop scripts using Mursion-TeachLivE software, based on work originally developed at the University of Central Florida. The project’s modified curriculum using mixed reality classroom simulation experiences integrated into several courses uses scenarios directed by faculty-developed scripts for teaching science and mathematics concepts to avatars that simulate elementary and middle school students. Through these simulations, pre-service teachers can present science and mathematics content, review content, practice behavior management skills, practice specific instructional techniques such as scaffolding, or perform many other daily tasks that a teacher would experience in an in-person classroom. The overarching intent of this project is to improve pre-service teachers’ ability to teach mathematics and science in urban schools. This goal will be achieved by studying the implementation by pre-service teachers of a virtual simulated classroom. The project’s research study intends to use participants from two cohorts of elementary pre-service teachers in a credentialing program. It aims to follow each cohort through three semesters in three courses and their student teaching, a fourth course. Data to be collected consists of: 1) course assignments, including science and mathematics lesson plans and a COVID classroom management plan, completed by pre-service teachers in experimental and control groups; 2) video recordings of the experimental group enrolled in courses using the virtual classroom simulations to practice lesson delivery and classroom management; 3) midterm and final assessments of pre-service teachers teaching by faculty supervisors; 4) focus groups of both the experimental and control group pre-service teachers; 5) virtual simulated classroom scripts prepared by the College faculty; and 6) a faculty focus group. Quantitative (statistical) and qualitative (content and discourse analyses) methods will be employed for data analysis. Project success has the potential to better prepare hundreds of future K-8 teachers to provide their elementary students with learning success in mathematics and science by meeting the challenges and opportunities they will find in ethnically diverse, high-poverty, urban classrooms.  The dissemination of project findings, as well as sustaining and institutionalizing the project through continued collaboration with school partners has the potential for significant and measurable future broader impacts for the targeted K-8 students, for their families, and for their communities. The NSF IUSE: EHR Program supports research and development projects to improve the effectiveness of STEM education for all students.  Through the Engaged Student Learning track, the program supports the creation, exploration, and implementation of promising practices and tools.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/21/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/09/2023</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2013230</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Cheryl</FirstName>
<LastName>Ney</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Cheryl L Ney</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[cney@cslanet.calstatela.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000779299</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/21/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate>02/09/2023</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kimberly</FirstName>
<LastName>Persiani</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kimberly Persiani</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[kpersia@calstatela.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000806801</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/09/2023</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kimberly</FirstName>
<LastName>Persiani</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kimberly Persiani</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[kpersia@calstatela.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000806801</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/21/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate>02/09/2023</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>California State L A University Auxiliary Services Inc.</Name>
<CityName>LOS ANGELES</CityName>
<ZipCode>900324226</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3233433648</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5151 STATE UNIVERSITY DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>34</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA34</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>C1ABLRAQTB48</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CAL STATE LA UNIVERSITY AUXILIARY SERVICES INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[California State University, Los Angeles]]></Name>
<CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>900324221</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5151 State University Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>34</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA34</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1795</Code>
<Text>Robert Noyce Scholarship Pgm</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1998</Code>
<Text>IUSE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8209</Code>
<Text>Improv Undergrad STEM Ed(IUSE)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0420</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~586111</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
