<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[WOWCLAN People: Workshop on Water, Culture, Language, and Native People in the Arctic]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>26757.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>26757</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06090100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OPP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Polar Programs (OPP)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Erica Hill</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>erhill@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032920000</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The Workshop on Water, Culture, Language, and Native People (WOWCLAN) will be a three-day workshop attended by Indigenous representatives from Siberia, Alaska, and the Pacific Northwest. The workshop is designed to discuss the collection of reliable water quality data in these respective regions, as well as discuss data management and archival techniques for Indigenous data sources. The workshop explores the boundaries and connections between Indigenous Knowledge and western science and will create an ongoing dialogue between Indigenous Peoples and the science community on the issue of water quality and data collection and sharing. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Workshop organizers will train participants in data collection and testing, as well as cultural preservation and documentation. In addition to learning scientific techniques and the use of various monitoring and recording devices, Indigenous participants will have the opportunity to build relationships and exchange views and ideas. Western scientists will gain an understanding of Indigenous needs and perspectives with regard to human health and the environment, as well as a new understanding of water quality in several remote regions that have seen little data collection on this topic. This project will contribute to broader impacts by improving understanding of spatially distinct cultures, advancing cultural understanding, advancing understanding of water quality and, by extension, environmental quality. The effect of blending Indigenous Knowledge with science will lead to greater understanding of human and environmental well-being, with a goal to increased diversity and Indigenous representation in various scientific enterprises. Outcomes of this workshop will include extensive training opportunities for conference participants and a final workshop report that will be made publicly available.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/25/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/27/2023</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.078</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2013929</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Anderson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John W Anderson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jwa@uidaho.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000632963</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/27/2023</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jonathan</FirstName>
<LastName>Waterhouse</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jonathan Waterhouse</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[waterhouse@uidaho.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000692929</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/25/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate>02/27/2023</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Regents of the University of Idaho</Name>
<CityName>MOSCOW</CityName>
<ZipCode>838449803</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2088856651</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>875 PERIMETER DR MS 3020</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Idaho</StateName>
<StateCode>ID</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>ID01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>QWYKRJH5NNJ3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF IDAHO</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Idaho]]></Name>
<CityName>Moscow</CityName>
<StateCode>ID</StateCode>
<ZipCode>838443020</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Idaho</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>ID00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5221</Code>
<Text>ASSP-Arctic Social Science</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1079</Code>
<Text>ARCTIC RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5221</Code>
<Text>ARCTIC SOCIAL SCIENCES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>02XX</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>0100XXXXDB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~26757</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Workshop on Water, Culture, Language, and Native People (WOWCLAN)</strong></p> <p>The Arctic is facing unprecedented environmental challenges due to climate change that are impacting water quality and threatening the natural environment and traditional activities of Indigenous Peoples. These rapid changes to the Arctic ecosystem, such as persistent hoarfrost, melting ice, and thawing permafrost directly affect water quality and pose significant risks to traditional practices making the active participation in water quality monitoring even more vital for preserving the delicate balance of the region. The Workshop on Water, Culture, Language, and Native People (WOWCLAN) project was created to address these challenges by hosting and allowing for the open exchange of thought in a series of workshop environments that facilitate interactions between water culture, language, and contemporary science. WOWCLAN presented recommendations from the Arctic Horizons 2017 report and had an overarching goal to build better understandings between Indigenous cultures and western scientific research.</p> <p>WOWCLAN was attended by Indigenous representatives from the Pacific Northwest, Alaska and Canada (Coeur d?Alene-Schitsu'umsh, Chilkat-Klukwan/Tlingit, Samish Tribes, and Teslin/Tetlit First Nations). The workshops aimed to address the pressing concern of environmental challenges in the Arctic region, particularly the impact of climate change on water quality, and its direct effect on the livelihoods and cultural practices of Indigenous Peoples.</p> <p>To better understand these unique challenges from remote and diverse populations, and due to global COVID-19 travel restrictions, WOWCLAN provided virtual reality headsets for all participants, and hosted trainings and workshops that harnessed the potential of extended reality (XR) technology. Coupling XR with mobile smart device applications made it possible to bring these communities together in cultural exchange and provide training and professional development opportunities.</p> <p>The integration of XR technology with water quality data collection offered the participants transformative insights on how their communities could enable themselves to preserve and transmit cultural knowledge, language, traditions, and history to future generations. The XR workshops have resulted in several key co-evolved initiatives and recommendations with far-reaching implications in the future:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Foster Indigenous Knowledge and Language via XR Storytelling:</strong> Harness the immersive power of XR technology to revitalize Indigenous storytelling by preserving water culture and language in a dynamic and interactive manner. Conduct personal interviews with respected elders and knowledge holders, capturing their profound wisdom and experiences related to water. By incorporating XR elements into storytelling, we can create compelling narratives that support cultural heritage and language, ensuring its preservation for generations to come.</li> <li><strong>Introduce XR Platforms for Sharing Water Culture:</strong> Leverage XR platforms to showcase the beauty and significance of water culture and its interconnection with the natural environment. Through XR experiences, people can immerse themselves in ancestral stories, rituals, and practices, fostering a deeper appreciation for the sacred relationship between water cultural identity. Integrating Indigenous language amplifies the essence of cultural heritage, further strengthening emotional connections to water and its preservation.</li> <li><strong>Evaluate Water Quality Technologies with Cultural Consideration:</strong> Conduct comprehensive evaluations of water quality monitoring technologies, considering their compatibility with Indigenous cultural practices and language. Collaborate with community members to assess the applicability, efficacy, and relevance of these technologies in the context of water culture. Respectful evaluations ensure that water quality research respects cultural norms, reinforcing the bond between science and Indigenous heritage.</li> <li><strong>Support Water Quality and XR Education Programs in Indigenous Languages:</strong> Facilitate water quality and XR education programs conducted in Indigenous languages. These programs empower community members to actively engage in water quality data collection efforts using XR technology, while preserving and revitalizing native languages. </li> </ul> <p>By respectfully engaging in water quality data collection through XR technology and mobile applications, Indigenous communities are active participants in shaping scientific research, storytelling, and land management. This active involvement not only strengthens connections to the land but also fosters interest in science, technology, engineering, and mathematics (STEM) disciplines. These initiatives present an opportunity for capacity building by providing training and educational resources to community members, equipping them with essential skills for sustainable water resource management.&nbsp; WOWCLAN provided significant training and professional development opportunities for Indigenous communities. Participants received training in XR technology, data interpretation, environmental monitoring, and collaborative research practices.</p> <p>Results from WOWCLAN workshops have wide-ranging implications for Indigenous education, language revitalization, and climate change monitoring and adaptation efforts. By empowering Indigenous communities and fostering long-term partnerships, efforts like this will continue to bridge the gap between scientific research and Indigenous Knowledge. The results of the WOWCLAN People project have been disseminated to communities of interest through presentations and panel discussions at the Augmented World Expo (AWE) and the Native Youth Climate and Adaptation Leadership Congress (NYCALC). The dissemination of project outcomes to native youth ensures the sustainability and continuation of these efforts in the future.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/27/2023<br>      Modified by: John&nbsp;W&nbsp;Anderson</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2013929/2013929_10660440_1690477352818_WOWCLAN--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2013929/2013929_10660440_1690477352818_WOWCLAN--rgov-800width.jpg" title="XR-WOWCLAN"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2013929/2013929_10660440_1690477352818_WOWCLAN--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="XR-WOWCLAN"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">This image depicts one of the XR WOWCLAN workshop spaces.  Ground LIDAR scanning, 360 imagery, and water quality data taken at the source are depicted.  In the center is a portal that returns participants to the common XR-campfire meeting room.</div> <div class="imageCredit">John W Anderson</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">John&nbsp;W&nbsp;Anderson</div> <div class="imageTitle">XR-WOWCLAN</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Workshop on Water, Culture, Language, and Native People (WOWCLAN)  The Arctic is facing unprecedented environmental challenges due to climate change that are impacting water quality and threatening the natural environment and traditional activities of Indigenous Peoples. These rapid changes to the Arctic ecosystem, such as persistent hoarfrost, melting ice, and thawing permafrost directly affect water quality and pose significant risks to traditional practices making the active participation in water quality monitoring even more vital for preserving the delicate balance of the region. The Workshop on Water, Culture, Language, and Native People (WOWCLAN) project was created to address these challenges by hosting and allowing for the open exchange of thought in a series of workshop environments that facilitate interactions between water culture, language, and contemporary science. WOWCLAN presented recommendations from the Arctic Horizons 2017 report and had an overarching goal to build better understandings between Indigenous cultures and western scientific research.  WOWCLAN was attended by Indigenous representatives from the Pacific Northwest, Alaska and Canada (Coeur d?Alene-Schitsu'umsh, Chilkat-Klukwan/Tlingit, Samish Tribes, and Teslin/Tetlit First Nations). The workshops aimed to address the pressing concern of environmental challenges in the Arctic region, particularly the impact of climate change on water quality, and its direct effect on the livelihoods and cultural practices of Indigenous Peoples.  To better understand these unique challenges from remote and diverse populations, and due to global COVID-19 travel restrictions, WOWCLAN provided virtual reality headsets for all participants, and hosted trainings and workshops that harnessed the potential of extended reality (XR) technology. Coupling XR with mobile smart device applications made it possible to bring these communities together in cultural exchange and provide training and professional development opportunities.  The integration of XR technology with water quality data collection offered the participants transformative insights on how their communities could enable themselves to preserve and transmit cultural knowledge, language, traditions, and history to future generations. The XR workshops have resulted in several key co-evolved initiatives and recommendations with far-reaching implications in the future:  Foster Indigenous Knowledge and Language via XR Storytelling: Harness the immersive power of XR technology to revitalize Indigenous storytelling by preserving water culture and language in a dynamic and interactive manner. Conduct personal interviews with respected elders and knowledge holders, capturing their profound wisdom and experiences related to water. By incorporating XR elements into storytelling, we can create compelling narratives that support cultural heritage and language, ensuring its preservation for generations to come. Introduce XR Platforms for Sharing Water Culture: Leverage XR platforms to showcase the beauty and significance of water culture and its interconnection with the natural environment. Through XR experiences, people can immerse themselves in ancestral stories, rituals, and practices, fostering a deeper appreciation for the sacred relationship between water cultural identity. Integrating Indigenous language amplifies the essence of cultural heritage, further strengthening emotional connections to water and its preservation. Evaluate Water Quality Technologies with Cultural Consideration: Conduct comprehensive evaluations of water quality monitoring technologies, considering their compatibility with Indigenous cultural practices and language. Collaborate with community members to assess the applicability, efficacy, and relevance of these technologies in the context of water culture. Respectful evaluations ensure that water quality research respects cultural norms, reinforcing the bond between science and Indigenous heritage. Support Water Quality and XR Education Programs in Indigenous Languages: Facilitate water quality and XR education programs conducted in Indigenous languages. These programs empower community members to actively engage in water quality data collection efforts using XR technology, while preserving and revitalizing native languages.    By respectfully engaging in water quality data collection through XR technology and mobile applications, Indigenous communities are active participants in shaping scientific research, storytelling, and land management. This active involvement not only strengthens connections to the land but also fosters interest in science, technology, engineering, and mathematics (STEM) disciplines. These initiatives present an opportunity for capacity building by providing training and educational resources to community members, equipping them with essential skills for sustainable water resource management.  WOWCLAN provided significant training and professional development opportunities for Indigenous communities. Participants received training in XR technology, data interpretation, environmental monitoring, and collaborative research practices.  Results from WOWCLAN workshops have wide-ranging implications for Indigenous education, language revitalization, and climate change monitoring and adaptation efforts. By empowering Indigenous communities and fostering long-term partnerships, efforts like this will continue to bridge the gap between scientific research and Indigenous Knowledge. The results of the WOWCLAN People project have been disseminated to communities of interest through presentations and panel discussions at the Augmented World Expo (AWE) and the Native Youth Climate and Adaptation Leadership Congress (NYCALC). The dissemination of project outcomes to native youth ensures the sustainability and continuation of these efforts in the future.          Last Modified: 07/27/2023       Submitted by: John W Anderson]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
