<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[NSF INCLUDES Planning Grant: Project Radial]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>99957.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>99957</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div. of Equity for Excellence in STEM</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Subrata Acharya</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>acharyas@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922451</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This project will establish a collective impact initiative that will use radio astronomy research to advance the development of a diverse US STEM workforce. The National Radio Astronomy Observatory (NRAO) requires extensive high-throughput computing infrastructure and a skilled workforce, to develop innovative approaches in computing and data science, to manage and exploit the large and complex datasets produced by its radio telescopes. In-depth academic research has investigated the causes of the persistent under-representation of minorities in the US STEM sector. The needs of the NRAO, and the findings of the research, inspired initial meetings between the NRAO and minority-serving institutions (MSIs). At these meetings, it was agreed that both astronomy and diversity could benefit from a network of multi-institutional, cross-disciplinary partners, to commit complementary expertise and resources. The Radial Alliance, consisting of ten MSIs and NRAO, will seek to provide these ten MSIs with high-throughput computing processing infrastructure and support; data sets from the NRAO’s Very Large Array Sky Survey; and an open access, interactive undergraduate and graduate curriculum, to train under-represented minority students in astronomy, computing and data science. This innovative approach will be supported by a “cradle to career” development program, including an interactive K-12 curriculum for schools surrounding the MSIs; undergraduate research experiences and a mentorship program for students; a professional development program for students, educators and faculty; affirmative spaces on the MSI campuses; and an outreach program targeted at students’ families and communities. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of this planning grant is to complete initiation and planning phases for the Radial Alliance. The initiation phase will finalize a clear business case, shared vision, mission and goals for the Radial Alliance and will consist of a front-end evaluation, including a literature review, direct needs assessments, and resources audit. This will inform a development lab during which Radial partner MSIs, other partners, beneficiaries and invited subject experts will meet in-person to finalize these elements and co-design the objectives, key activities, and metrics of the Radial Alliance. The planning phase will build organizational structure and a three-year plan for the Radial Alliance, including shared vision and goals, and plans for communication, evaluation, and sustainability.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This planning grant is funded by NSF Inclusion across the Nation of Communities of Learners of Underrepresented Discoverers in Engineering and Science (NSF INCLUDES), a comprehensive national initiative to enhance U.S. leadership in discoveries and innovations by focusing on diversity, inclusion and broadening participation in STEM at scale.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/16/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/30/2023</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2013080</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Angela</FirstName>
<LastName>Speck</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>K</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Angela K Speck</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[angela.speck@utsa.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000300094</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/16/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Morris</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David Morris</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[dmorris@uvi.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000701770</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/16/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lyndele</FirstName>
<LastName>von Schill</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lyndele von Schill</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[lvonschi@nrao.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000721882</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/16/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Eddie</FirstName>
<LastName>Red</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Eddie Red</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[eddie.red@morehouse.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000797453</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/16/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Anja</FirstName>
<LastName>Fourie</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Anja Fourie</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[afourie@nrao.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000803915</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/16/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Associated Universities, Inc.</Name>
<CityName>WASHINGTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>200362252</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2024621676</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1400 16TH ST NW</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[STE 730]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NZBMKZMW68N3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ASSOCIATED UNIVERSITIES INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[AUI/National Radio Astronomy Observatory]]></Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>200366225</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1400 16TH ST NW STE 730]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>032Y</Code>
<Text>Eddie Bernice Johnson INCLUDES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0420</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~99957</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Radio Astronomy Data Imaging and Analysis Lab (RADIAL) is a collective impact initiative consisting of a network of diverse partners that use radio astronomy high-throughput computing (HTC) challenges to recruit, train and accelerate the progress and success of historically marginalized students in fields required by the radio astronomy sector and other scientific disciplines that utilize HTC and data science.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The RADIAL Alliance consists of 14 minority-serving institutions (MSIs), namely Agnes Scott College, Florida A&amp;M University, Morehouse College, Morgan State University, New Mexico Tech, Norfolk State University (NSU), South Carolina State University, Spelman College, Texas Tech University (TTU), University of California Santa Cruz (UCSC), University of Texas San Antonio (UTSA), University of Puerto Rico Mayagu&#776;ez (UPRM), University of the Virgin Islands, and University of the West Indies, with project support provided by the National Radio Astronomy Observatory (NRAO).</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>This NSF INCLUDES Planning Grant enabled the appointment of a full-time Project Director for one year, who established a Project Office at NRAO, facilitated the formal establishment of the Alliance, and coordinated the co-design and development of collaborative infrastructure.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The following collaborative infrastructure was co-designed and developed in the first year: a shared vision for broadening participation of target population(s) in HTC and data science; multi-stakeholder partnerships and infrastructure to achieve progress on common goals and objectives of the Alliance; relevant metrics to evaluate the quality, performance and effectiveness of Alliance activities; an Alliance Board, Steering Committee and Working Groups and relevant internal and external communication plans and processes; and a Sustainability Plan to expand, sustain and scale the Alliance, its activities and impact.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>This grant also enabled RADIAL to host a RADIAL Development Lab in Miami, FL&nbsp;from 22-23 September 2022 in order to provide partners with an annual progress report and continue the co-design and planning of Alliance work.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Finally, the grant supported&nbsp;six historically marginalized students attending RADIAL MSIs, one historically marginalized RADIAL summer research program alumna,&nbsp;and one RADIAL MSI faculty member to participate in the 241st Meeting of the American Astronomical Society (AAS), Seattle, WA, 8-12 January 2023 to share their research and promising practices.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The outcomes listed below are highlights of several achieved through this collective impact initiative:</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <ul> <li>Hosted three annual RADIAL Development Labs (see above);</li> <li>Collaborated with UPRM to secure funding for the first RADIAL HTC worker node to be hosted at the NSF Center for&nbsp;Advanced Radio Sciences and Engineering (CARSE) at UPRM (under construction June 2023);</li> <li>Collaborated with UPRM to secure funding from the NSF and establish a RADIAL&nbsp;Summer Research Exchange Program for six students per year for three years with NSU, UPRM and UTSA through NSF CARSE (launched June 2023);</li> <li>Collaborated with UCSC to secure funding from the Alfred P. Sloan Foundation and establish a RADIAL&nbsp;Summer Research Program for two students per year for three years at the University of Wisconsin-Madison (UW); as well as a graduate tuition scholarship for two qualifying students per year for two years at UW (launched May 2022);</li> <li>Hosted a Summer Research Experience for one graduate student who conducted research into identifying best practices that foster inclusive learning environments for students and faculty in each of the RADIAL MSI partner institutions;</li> <li>Established quarterly meetings between RADIAL&nbsp;partners and VLASS Science Working Groups to workshop ideas to increase RADIAL&nbsp;student access to VLASS data (2021);</li> <li>Collaborated with TTU&nbsp;to establish a VLASS Work Study Pilot Program in collaboration with RADIAL partners&nbsp;and NRAO scientists in order to increase RADIAL student access to VLASS data (to launch October 2023);</li> <li>Disseminated educational and outreach material in collaboration with partners using NRAO&rsquo;s online open-access learning platform (launched May 2022);</li> <li>Created&nbsp;a&nbsp;series&nbsp;of&nbsp;recorded&nbsp;interviews&nbsp;with&nbsp;STEM&nbsp;professionals&nbsp;who&nbsp;are&nbsp;either&nbsp;a&nbsp;member&nbsp;of&nbsp;a historically marginalized group (HMG) or an active ally of STEM professionals and students from a HMG. These&nbsp;podcast&nbsp;recordings&nbsp;will&nbsp;be&nbsp;made&nbsp;available&nbsp;to RADIAL students via the NRAO&rsquo;s online open-access learning platform (launched May 2022);</li> <li>Collaborated&nbsp;with&nbsp;SpectrumX&nbsp;on&nbsp;a&nbsp;successful&nbsp;proposal&nbsp;for&nbsp;the&nbsp;implementation&nbsp;of&nbsp;a&nbsp;Broadband Mapping&nbsp;Using&nbsp;Smartphones Project that will see RADIAL students collect and analyze wireless coverage data in geographic areas close to&nbsp;their&nbsp;home&nbsp;institutions,&nbsp;in&nbsp;order&nbsp;to monitor the health of the broadband network, and report these findings to the FCC (launched January 2023); and</li> <li>One of the students supported to present their research at the 241st Meeting of the AAS, Doni&nbsp;Anderson of the University of Michigan, received the Chambliss medal for her research poster titled &ldquo;Three-dimensional mapping of the Gum Nebula&rdquo; (January 2023).</li> </ul> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Knowledge co-created and promising practices co-developed by the Project Director, partner institution leads and MSI students were shared with stakeholders at the 2021 and 2022 National Society for Black Physicists&nbsp;Conference,&nbsp;Society for the Advancement of Chicanos/Hispanics and Native Americans in Science (SACNAS) Conference, and AAS Summer and Winter Meetings.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/18/2023<br>      Modified by: Anja&nbsp;Fourie</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Radio Astronomy Data Imaging and Analysis Lab (RADIAL) is a collective impact initiative consisting of a network of diverse partners that use radio astronomy high-throughput computing (HTC) challenges to recruit, train and accelerate the progress and success of historically marginalized students in fields required by the radio astronomy sector and other scientific disciplines that utilize HTC and data science.     The RADIAL Alliance consists of 14 minority-serving institutions (MSIs), namely Agnes Scott College, Florida A&amp;M University, Morehouse College, Morgan State University, New Mexico Tech, Norfolk State University (NSU), South Carolina State University, Spelman College, Texas Tech University (TTU), University of California Santa Cruz (UCSC), University of Texas San Antonio (UTSA), University of Puerto Rico Mayagu&#776;ez (UPRM), University of the Virgin Islands, and University of the West Indies, with project support provided by the National Radio Astronomy Observatory (NRAO).     This NSF INCLUDES Planning Grant enabled the appointment of a full-time Project Director for one year, who established a Project Office at NRAO, facilitated the formal establishment of the Alliance, and coordinated the co-design and development of collaborative infrastructure.     The following collaborative infrastructure was co-designed and developed in the first year: a shared vision for broadening participation of target population(s) in HTC and data science; multi-stakeholder partnerships and infrastructure to achieve progress on common goals and objectives of the Alliance; relevant metrics to evaluate the quality, performance and effectiveness of Alliance activities; an Alliance Board, Steering Committee and Working Groups and relevant internal and external communication plans and processes; and a Sustainability Plan to expand, sustain and scale the Alliance, its activities and impact.     This grant also enabled RADIAL to host a RADIAL Development Lab in Miami, FL from 22-23 September 2022 in order to provide partners with an annual progress report and continue the co-design and planning of Alliance work.     Finally, the grant supported six historically marginalized students attending RADIAL MSIs, one historically marginalized RADIAL summer research program alumna, and one RADIAL MSI faculty member to participate in the 241st Meeting of the American Astronomical Society (AAS), Seattle, WA, 8-12 January 2023 to share their research and promising practices.     The outcomes listed below are highlights of several achieved through this collective impact initiative:     Hosted three annual RADIAL Development Labs (see above); Collaborated with UPRM to secure funding for the first RADIAL HTC worker node to be hosted at the NSF Center for Advanced Radio Sciences and Engineering (CARSE) at UPRM (under construction June 2023); Collaborated with UPRM to secure funding from the NSF and establish a RADIAL Summer Research Exchange Program for six students per year for three years with NSU, UPRM and UTSA through NSF CARSE (launched June 2023); Collaborated with UCSC to secure funding from the Alfred P. Sloan Foundation and establish a RADIAL Summer Research Program for two students per year for three years at the University of Wisconsin-Madison (UW); as well as a graduate tuition scholarship for two qualifying students per year for two years at UW (launched May 2022); Hosted a Summer Research Experience for one graduate student who conducted research into identifying best practices that foster inclusive learning environments for students and faculty in each of the RADIAL MSI partner institutions; Established quarterly meetings between RADIAL partners and VLASS Science Working Groups to workshop ideas to increase RADIAL student access to VLASS data (2021); Collaborated with TTU to establish a VLASS Work Study Pilot Program in collaboration with RADIAL partners and NRAO scientists in order to increase RADIAL student access to VLASS data (to launch October 2023); Disseminated educational and outreach material in collaboration with partners using NRAO’s online open-access learning platform (launched May 2022); Created a series of recorded interviews with STEM professionals who are either a member of a historically marginalized group (HMG) or an active ally of STEM professionals and students from a HMG. These podcast recordings will be made available to RADIAL students via the NRAO’s online open-access learning platform (launched May 2022); Collaborated with SpectrumX on a successful proposal for the implementation of a Broadband Mapping Using Smartphones Project that will see RADIAL students collect and analyze wireless coverage data in geographic areas close to their home institutions, in order to monitor the health of the broadband network, and report these findings to the FCC (launched January 2023); and One of the students supported to present their research at the 241st Meeting of the AAS, Doni Anderson of the University of Michigan, received the Chambliss medal for her research poster titled "Three-dimensional mapping of the Gum Nebula" (January 2023).      Knowledge co-created and promising practices co-developed by the Project Director, partner institution leads and MSI students were shared with stakeholders at the 2021 and 2022 National Society for Black Physicists Conference, Society for the Advancement of Chicanos/Hispanics and Native Americans in Science (SACNAS) Conference, and AAS Summer and Winter Meetings.             Last Modified: 07/18/2023       Submitted by: Anja Fourie]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
