<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Fast and scalable printing of high-resolution microfluidic devices using HLP technology.]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>224606.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>224606</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rajesh Mehta</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rmehta@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922174</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broadder impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is to advance the development of microfluidic devices for life sciences research. Currently, devices with high-resolution microchannels are typically manufactured using sophisticated cleanroom microfabrication facilities, requiring technical expertise, high costs, and long turnaround times; these factors inhibit their use. This project will enable rapid manufacturing of customized microfluidics devices with substantially lower costs and turnaround times. This technology will impact research in applications including fundamental cell biology, drug screening, cellular therapy, toxicity testing, and tissue engineering.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This SBIR Phase I project will advance the translation of hybrid laser printing (HLP), combining the quick and large-scale printing capability of Continuous Liquid Interface Production (CLIP) with precision processing of additive multiphoton polymerization (MPP) and subtractive multiphoton ablation (MPA) into a single versatile machine. Technical challenges in material discovery and scalability will be addressed in this work: 1) Discover new materials not only compatible with HLP process but also showing the necessary durability, transparency, biocompatibility, and impermeability to fluids; and characterize key HLP parameters, such as ablation z-range used in MPA mode and dead-zone thickness used in CLIP mode; and 2) Scale the maximum printable size of HLP process using a novel multiscale CLIP strategy combined with a step-stitch projection printing method. The project will develop a prototype for life sciences applications.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/15/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/17/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2013942</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Zheng</FirstName>
<LastName>Xiong</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Zheng Xiong</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[zhxiongoptics@gmail.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000816270</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/15/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>3D MICROFLUIDICS LLC</Name>
<CityName>CHITTENANGO</CityName>
<ZipCode>130374002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6193985924</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5900 STRAWMOUNT TRL</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>22</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY22</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>E3L7ATDTRXL5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>3D MICROFLUIDICS LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[3D MICROFLUIDICS LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>liverpool</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>130904045</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[36 Grampian road, Apt 4]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>22</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY22</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8029</Code>
<Text>Manufacturing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~224606</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>&lsquo;Precision micropart&rsquo; is an umbrella term which includes microfluidic devices, molds, and parts several inches in size with some features at micrometer or even sub-micrometer resolutions. Such parts are needed by start-ups, medium and large sized companies, academic researchers, and national laboratories for many applications in the life sciences market. Despite substantial need, users are reluctant to use precision microparts due to the lack of a cost- and time-effective manufacturing solution. At present, photolithography remains the gold standard, and possibly the only option, to make precision microparts. This typically requires the use of expensive and exclusive cleanroom-micro-/nano-fabrication facilities and involves multiple labor-intensive steps. 3D Microfluidics LLC (3DM) aims to provide precision microparts at low-cost <em>($100-500 per device/part)</em> with rapid turnaround times <em>(2 days)</em> even if volumes are low <em>(1-100)</em> or if designs are complex. This is possible due to 3DM&rsquo;s patented hybrid (additive-subtractive) printing (HLP) technology which is capable of seamlessly integrating three distinct modes of manufacturing namely projection stereolithography (PS), two-photon polymerization (TPP) and two-photon ablation (TPA) into a single versatile machine. However, for commercialization, many technical challenges were identified. 3DM was awarded SBIR Phase I grant to solve two key challenges related to &lsquo;Material Discovery&rsquo; and &lsquo;Scalability&rsquo;. 3DM was successful in accomplishing both challenges: (1) a material formulation that works well with HLP and exhibits desirable properties was discovered, and (2) a new additive multiscale projection stereolithography (MPS) printer capable of rapidly printing 30mm x 60mm sized microfluidic devices and structures with ~10&micro;m resolution was designed and built. These results set up the foundation to provide the first ever rapid prototyping service for &lsquo;precision microparts&rsquo; at low-costs; this service will be independent of part volumes, design complexities or high-resolution requirements, and will not rely on expensive and exclusive microfabrication facilities. This will lead to widespread adoption of microfabricated parts by the life science community for target applications such as fundamental cell biology, drug screening, cellular therapy, toxicity testing, and tissue engineering to name a few.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/30/2021<br>      Modified by: Zheng&nbsp;Xiong</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ ‘Precision micropart’ is an umbrella term which includes microfluidic devices, molds, and parts several inches in size with some features at micrometer or even sub-micrometer resolutions. Such parts are needed by start-ups, medium and large sized companies, academic researchers, and national laboratories for many applications in the life sciences market. Despite substantial need, users are reluctant to use precision microparts due to the lack of a cost- and time-effective manufacturing solution. At present, photolithography remains the gold standard, and possibly the only option, to make precision microparts. This typically requires the use of expensive and exclusive cleanroom-micro-/nano-fabrication facilities and involves multiple labor-intensive steps. 3D Microfluidics LLC (3DM) aims to provide precision microparts at low-cost ($100-500 per device/part) with rapid turnaround times (2 days) even if volumes are low (1-100) or if designs are complex. This is possible due to 3DM’s patented hybrid (additive-subtractive) printing (HLP) technology which is capable of seamlessly integrating three distinct modes of manufacturing namely projection stereolithography (PS), two-photon polymerization (TPP) and two-photon ablation (TPA) into a single versatile machine. However, for commercialization, many technical challenges were identified. 3DM was awarded SBIR Phase I grant to solve two key challenges related to ‘Material Discovery’ and ‘Scalability’. 3DM was successful in accomplishing both challenges: (1) a material formulation that works well with HLP and exhibits desirable properties was discovered, and (2) a new additive multiscale projection stereolithography (MPS) printer capable of rapidly printing 30mm x 60mm sized microfluidic devices and structures with ~10&micro;m resolution was designed and built. These results set up the foundation to provide the first ever rapid prototyping service for ‘precision microparts’ at low-costs; this service will be independent of part volumes, design complexities or high-resolution requirements, and will not rely on expensive and exclusive microfabrication facilities. This will lead to widespread adoption of microfabricated parts by the life science community for target applications such as fundamental cell biology, drug screening, cellular therapy, toxicity testing, and tissue engineering to name a few.          Last Modified: 08/30/2021       Submitted by: Zheng Xiong]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
