<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  A thermogel-based drug delivery platform for the upper gastrointestinal bleeding treatment]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>224999.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>244999</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Henry Ahn</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>hahn@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927069</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is to develop an innovative method to treat upper gastrointestinal bleeding (UGIB). UGIB results in more than 550,000 hospitalizations per year in the US alone with a mortality rate of up to 20%. The gastrointestinal (GI) bleeding market is projected to be nearly USD 1 billion by 2026, with the overall hemostatic agents market reaching over USD 5 billion. Current solutions require endoscopy performed by a specialist or hospital admission. The proposed approach is a drinkable formulation to stop bleeding after ingestion, eliminating the need for endoscopic intervention or hospitalization. The technology developed in this project could then be applied to other bleeding scenarios, including field/combat medicine or rapid treatment of hemorrhage during surgical complications. The gel can also be used as a drug delivery vehicle for a variety of disorders of the upper GI tract.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project will demonstrate a new approach to achieve hemostasis in patients with upper gastrointestinal bleeding (UGIB), based on a novel thermosensitive gel (thermogel) formulation. The drinkable formulation is liquid at ambient temperature and becomes a mucoadhesive gel when warmed to body temperature, thereby treating hemorrhage in the upper GI tract without the need for endoscopic intervention. Its action is based on two synergistic effects: (1) The in situ gelation of the mucoadhesive thermogel provides a mechanical barrier against blood flow, and (2) the slow release of drugs from the thermogel at the hemorrhage site enables more rapid healing. Initial efforts will be dedicated to formulation development wherein compatibility of the thermogel with different drug candidates will be evaluated, and optimization of the gelation temperature will be performed. The best formulations will then be tested in vitro for stability, drug release kinetics, and mucoadhesion. Finally, the effectiveness of the proposed approach will be assessed in preclinical models of bleeding, demonstrating its superior ability to reach hemostasis. This is expected to apply to disorders including gastroesophageal reflux disease, eosinophilic esophagitis, and oral mucositis.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/24/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/24/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041, 47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2014730</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Navdeep</FirstName>
<LastName>Kaur</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Navdeep Kaur</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[sbirpi@intacttherapeutics.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000816438</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/24/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate>07/16/2021</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>JEFFREY</FirstName>
<LastName>LINHARDT</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>JEFFREY LINHARDT</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[sbirpi2@intacttherapeutics.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000858812</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/16/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>INTACT THERAPEUTICS</Name>
<CityName>PALO ALTO</CityName>
<ZipCode>943041118</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6508883616</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2627 HANOVER ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>16</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA16</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>ZYZ1FU7HBU73</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>INTACT THERAPEUTICS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[INTACT THERAPEUTICS]]></Name>
<CityName>Hayward</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>945453716</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3944 Trust Way]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>14</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA14</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8091</Code>
<Text>SBIR Outreach &amp; Tech. Assist</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7573</Code>
<Text>BIO-RELATED MATERIALS RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8038</Code>
<Text>Biotechnology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8042</Code>
<Text>Health and Safety</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~224999</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~20000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Upper gastrointestinal bleeding (UGIB) represents 75% of all GI bleeding cases worldwide and it is one of the leading causes of emergency hospital admission for gastrointestinal problems in the US. The mainstay treatment for patients with acute UGIB is endoscopy. Endoscopic hemostatic therapy is recommended by current international guidelines within 24 hours after the admission of a patient with UGIB in an Emergency Department, and it yields even lower mortality rates if performed within the first six hours. Endoscopy is associated with complications in patients who are actively bleeding and can be life-threatening in unstable patients with medical comorbidities. Patients must be optimally resuscitated to minimize their risk of complications and the procedure should not be undertaken until cardiovascular stability is achieved. The prehospital management of UGIB is pivotal to safeguard the conditions of patients prior to an effective endoscopic treatment, which can reduce mortality from 20% to 1.6%, in severe cases. However, differently from other critical hemorrhages, emergency medical services don&rsquo;t have the tools to control acute UGIB due to the technical challenges in delivering an initial blockade to the hemorrhage in the upper GI tract. Intact Therapeutics is developing INT-201, the first non-endoscopic product based on a proprietary thermal hydrogel formulation for the delivery of hemostatic drugs, which combines mechanical and clotting-promoting actions to rapidly stop bleeding in the upper GI tract and stabilize the affected patients waiting to receive an endoscopic treatment. The extensive coating of the mucosal wall of the GI tract will allow improved bioavailability and better local drug absorption while reducing systemic exposure and potential side effects.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Intact Therapeutics tested the ability of the thermal hydrogel prototype to mechanically stop the bleeding in a rat model. The thermal hydrogel stops the flow of blood, quickly achieving hemostasis. &nbsp;From the preliminary results, thermal hydrogel also demonstrated the potential to be tuned as a drug carrier in order to topically deliver clotting promoter drugs to improve coagulation and quickly stop bleeding. To treat UGIB, a lead thermal hydrogel formulation based on a drug was developed. The lead formulation was tested for gelation temperature, drug release effectiveness, and physicochemical stability and the results confirmed the INT-201&rsquo;s ability to deliver different types of drugs topically at the site of bleeding. With in-vivo tests for clotting efficacy, it was validated that the identified lead formulation swiftly stops the bleeding in the rat model. The intended application for INT-201 is to treat UGIB in both acute and chronic settings. In order to bring the development of INT-201 to the clinical trial-ready stage, the safety, pharmacokinetics, and treatment efficacy of INT-201 will be validated in a large animal model.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>INT-201 thermal hydrogel can rapidly stop bleeding due to its faster gelation time, and ability to deliver clot-promoting drugs topically at the site of bleeding, all without the need for endoscopy. This will reduce the need for blood transfusions and stabilize patients when endoscopy is unavailable, thereby ultimately reducing the need for hospitalization, as well as morbidity and mortality. The administration of INT-201 is straightforward and can be self-administered by patients with chronic bleeding or performed by a nurse or paramedic in emergency settings. INT-201 will improve the quality of life and clinical outcome of the ~300,000 US citizens who present at the emergency department with UGIB every year and will help save up to $2.5 B spent annually by hospitals for UGIB management. The current lack of a pre-endoscopic treatment for the stabilization of UGIB patients will ensure the broad adoption of INT-201 in emergency departments, intensive care units, and rural and military settings and substantially reduce casualties. Additionally, the range of drugs that could be delivered via thermal hydrogels is wide: it has been shown that the loading and release of proteins, DNA, and antibiotics are all compatible with thermal hydrogels. Intact Therapeutics will enable potential applications for the treatment of other medical conditions like surgical hemorrhage, gastroesophageal reflux disease, eosinophilic esophagitis, oral mucositis, diabetic retinopathy, hepatocellular carcinoma, vascular surgery, and wound management.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/13/2022<br>      Modified by: Jeffrey&nbsp;Linhardt</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Upper gastrointestinal bleeding (UGIB) represents 75% of all GI bleeding cases worldwide and it is one of the leading causes of emergency hospital admission for gastrointestinal problems in the US. The mainstay treatment for patients with acute UGIB is endoscopy. Endoscopic hemostatic therapy is recommended by current international guidelines within 24 hours after the admission of a patient with UGIB in an Emergency Department, and it yields even lower mortality rates if performed within the first six hours. Endoscopy is associated with complications in patients who are actively bleeding and can be life-threatening in unstable patients with medical comorbidities. Patients must be optimally resuscitated to minimize their risk of complications and the procedure should not be undertaken until cardiovascular stability is achieved. The prehospital management of UGIB is pivotal to safeguard the conditions of patients prior to an effective endoscopic treatment, which can reduce mortality from 20% to 1.6%, in severe cases. However, differently from other critical hemorrhages, emergency medical services don’t have the tools to control acute UGIB due to the technical challenges in delivering an initial blockade to the hemorrhage in the upper GI tract. Intact Therapeutics is developing INT-201, the first non-endoscopic product based on a proprietary thermal hydrogel formulation for the delivery of hemostatic drugs, which combines mechanical and clotting-promoting actions to rapidly stop bleeding in the upper GI tract and stabilize the affected patients waiting to receive an endoscopic treatment. The extensive coating of the mucosal wall of the GI tract will allow improved bioavailability and better local drug absorption while reducing systemic exposure and potential side effects.     Intact Therapeutics tested the ability of the thermal hydrogel prototype to mechanically stop the bleeding in a rat model. The thermal hydrogel stops the flow of blood, quickly achieving hemostasis.  From the preliminary results, thermal hydrogel also demonstrated the potential to be tuned as a drug carrier in order to topically deliver clotting promoter drugs to improve coagulation and quickly stop bleeding. To treat UGIB, a lead thermal hydrogel formulation based on a drug was developed. The lead formulation was tested for gelation temperature, drug release effectiveness, and physicochemical stability and the results confirmed the INT-201’s ability to deliver different types of drugs topically at the site of bleeding. With in-vivo tests for clotting efficacy, it was validated that the identified lead formulation swiftly stops the bleeding in the rat model. The intended application for INT-201 is to treat UGIB in both acute and chronic settings. In order to bring the development of INT-201 to the clinical trial-ready stage, the safety, pharmacokinetics, and treatment efficacy of INT-201 will be validated in a large animal model.     INT-201 thermal hydrogel can rapidly stop bleeding due to its faster gelation time, and ability to deliver clot-promoting drugs topically at the site of bleeding, all without the need for endoscopy. This will reduce the need for blood transfusions and stabilize patients when endoscopy is unavailable, thereby ultimately reducing the need for hospitalization, as well as morbidity and mortality. The administration of INT-201 is straightforward and can be self-administered by patients with chronic bleeding or performed by a nurse or paramedic in emergency settings. INT-201 will improve the quality of life and clinical outcome of the ~300,000 US citizens who present at the emergency department with UGIB every year and will help save up to $2.5 B spent annually by hospitals for UGIB management. The current lack of a pre-endoscopic treatment for the stabilization of UGIB patients will ensure the broad adoption of INT-201 in emergency departments, intensive care units, and rural and military settings and substantially reduce casualties. Additionally, the range of drugs that could be delivered via thermal hydrogels is wide: it has been shown that the loading and release of proteins, DNA, and antibiotics are all compatible with thermal hydrogels. Intact Therapeutics will enable potential applications for the treatment of other medical conditions like surgical hemorrhage, gastroesophageal reflux disease, eosinophilic esophagitis, oral mucositis, diabetic retinopathy, hepatocellular carcinoma, vascular surgery, and wound management.       Last Modified: 12/13/2022       Submitted by: Jeffrey Linhardt]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
