<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Visuotactile tests of mental domains]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>225000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>225000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Alastair Monk</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>amonk@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924392</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I is better outcomes and lower costs for people with major neurological or psychiatric conditions.  The proposed technology will offer a set of tests for assessment of cognitive function.  Millions of Americans suffer persistent emotional, cognitive, or sensorimotor dysfunction after experiencing traumatic brain injury.  The proposed system will operate on standard mobile devices to facilitate easy diagnosis and treatment. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project will establish the feasibility of developing a battery of visuotactile tests to assess mental domains. The proposed study will yield stimulus-response data (psychometric functions) based on novel visuotactile measures and compare them to analogous functions based on gold-standard measures that are much less accessible. Personalized testing will maximize interpretability by customizing stimulus parameters for each individual and testing session, thus minimizing the likelihood of floor and ceiling effects. The feasibility aims will be achieved if psychometric trends for the proposed measures match those found for analogous gold-standard measures.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/10/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/20/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041, 47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2014693</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ran</FirstName>
<LastName>Carmi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ran Carmi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[carmi@eye-predict.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000517922</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Eye-Predict</Name>
<CityName>LOS ANGELES</CityName>
<ZipCode>900272955</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6263764804</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3400 BEN LOMOND PL</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[APT 301]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>30</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA30</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>EMT6N5RHL8C5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>EYE-PREDICT LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Eye-Predict]]></Name>
<CityName>LOS ANGELES</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>900272955</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3400 BEN LOMOND PL STE 301]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>30</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA30</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>090E</Code>
<Text>Chem/Bio and Physical Diagnostics</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8018</Code>
<Text>Smart and Connected Health</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8032</Code>
<Text>Software Services and Applications</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8033</Code>
<Text>Hardware Software Integration</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8089</Code>
<Text>Understanding the Brain/Cognitive Scienc</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~225000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><span>Overview</span></span><span>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span>This project resulted in a novel test battery that leverages touchscreens and finger gestures to assess mental function. This battery is designed to offer a superior combination of validity and accessibility compared to alternatives. Testing reports could inform intervention decisions for post-injury patients, leading to improved outcomes and lower costs if better decisions are made.&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><span>Intellectual Merit</span></span></p> <p><span>This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project established the feasibility of developing and using visuotactile tests to emulate less accessible eyegaze tests of mental function by demonstrating equivalent stimulus-response functions for clinically relevant measures. This finding justifies the larger investment that would be needed to demonstrate clinically meaningful accuracy, precision, and reliability.</span></p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><span>Broader Impacts</span></span></p> <p><span>This SBIR project established the feasibility of using a novel test battery based on accessible visuotactile measures to meet assessment needs in health, educational, and professional settings. The initial target application is to inform intervention decisions for the millions of individuals who suffer from persistent dysfunction and symptoms following traumatic injuries. Rapid test deployment to diverse settings will be facilitated by a software-as-a-service framework and free trial periods. Successful commercialization will result in a large-scale testing database and enable synergistic applications, such as visuotactile training to improve mental function.</span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/05/2022<br>      Modified by: Ran&nbsp;Carmi</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Overview         This project resulted in a novel test battery that leverages touchscreens and finger gestures to assess mental function. This battery is designed to offer a superior combination of validity and accessibility compared to alternatives. Testing reports could inform intervention decisions for post-injury patients, leading to improved outcomes and lower costs if better decisions are made.   Intellectual Merit  This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project established the feasibility of developing and using visuotactile tests to emulate less accessible eyegaze tests of mental function by demonstrating equivalent stimulus-response functions for clinically relevant measures. This finding justifies the larger investment that would be needed to demonstrate clinically meaningful accuracy, precision, and reliability.  Broader Impacts  This SBIR project established the feasibility of using a novel test battery based on accessible visuotactile measures to meet assessment needs in health, educational, and professional settings. The initial target application is to inform intervention decisions for the millions of individuals who suffer from persistent dysfunction and symptoms following traumatic injuries. Rapid test deployment to diverse settings will be facilitated by a software-as-a-service framework and free trial periods. Successful commercialization will result in a large-scale testing database and enable synergistic applications, such as visuotactile training to improve mental function.       Last Modified: 08/05/2022       Submitted by: Ran Carmi]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
