<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research: Segmentation of Time Series via Self-Normalization]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>99999.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>99999</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Yong Zeng</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>yzeng@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927299</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This project aims to develop new statistical methodology and theory for change-point analysis of time series data. Change-point models have wide applications in many scientific areas, including modeling the daily volatility of the U.S. financial market, and the weekly growth rate of an infectious disease such as coronavirus, among others. Compared with existing methodologies, this research will provide inference for a flexible range of change point models, which will remain valid under complex dependence relationships exhibited by real datasets. The methodologies ensuing from the project will be disseminated to the relevant scientific communities via publications, conference and seminar presentations, and the development of open-source software. The Principal Investigators (PIs) will jointly mentor a Ph.D. student and involve undergraduate students in the research, and offer advanced topic courses to introduce the state-of-the-art techniques in time series analysis.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Time series segmentation, also known as change-point estimation, is one of the fundamental problems in statistics, where a time series is partitioned into piecewise homogeneous segments such that each piece shares the same behavior. There is a vast body of literature devoted to change-point estimation in independent observations; however, robust methodology and rigorous theory that can accommodate temporal dependence is still scarce. Motivated by the recent success of the self-normalization (SN) method, which was developed by one of the PIs for structural break testing and other inference problems in time series, the PIs will advance the self-normalization technique to time series segmentation. Specifically, the PIs will develop a systematic and unified SN-based change-point estimation methodology and the associated theory for (i) segmenting a piecewise stationary time series into homogeneous pieces so within each piece a finite dimensional parameter is constant; (ii) segmenting a linear trend model with stationary and weakly dependent errors into periods with constant slope. The segmentation algorithms to be developed are broadly applicable to fixed-dimensional time series data and can be further extended to cover high-dimensional and locally stationary time series with proper modification of the self-normalized test statistics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/16/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/27/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2014053</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Zifeng</FirstName>
<LastName>Zhao</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Zifeng Zhao</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[zzhao2@nd.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000815781</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/16/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Notre Dame</Name>
<CityName>NOTRE DAME</CityName>
<ZipCode>465565708</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5746317432</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>940 Grace Hall</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IN02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>FPU6XGFXMBE9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF NOTRE DAME DU LAC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>KKBMKNFZ5PJ4</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Notre Dame]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>465565646</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IN02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1269</Code>
<Text>STATISTICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0122</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002223DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~32358</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~33319</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2022~34322</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>In this project, we study the problem of time series segmentation, also known as change-point estimation. It is one of the fundamental problems in statistics and has broad applications in many scientific areas including bioinformatics, climate science, economics, finance, genetics, medical science, epidemiology and signal processing.</p> <p><br />An important issue for time series segmentation is how to rigorously handle the unknown temporal dependence, where observations across time are inter-dependent with each other. Based on the self-normalization (SN) principle, we have designed novel time series segmentation algorithms that can implement effective multiple change-point estimation universally for scalar/vector/functional/regression time series with sound theoretical guarantees. Compared to existing literature, our method is robust to temporal dependence and is furthermore tuning-free, which makes it an easy-to-use time series segmentation algorithm for researchers and practitioners. We have developed a computationally efficient R package, SNSeg, which implements the proposed algorithms in R.</p> <p><br />As an important application of our proposed algorithm, we have analyzed the trajectories of the COVID-19 pandemic in the U.S. and 30 other major countries in the world. In particular, we have applied the proposed segmentation algorithm to the time series of daily new cases(i.e. the infection curve) of COVID-19 and found that the growth of the pandemic can be partitioned into several distinct phases. Based on our analysis, we show that public health intervention policies such as lockdown are effective in early phases of the pandemic. In addition, we have designed a two-step forecasting algorithm that can generate both point prediction and interval prediction for the daily new cases in the near future. It is shown to perform better than the algorithm used by the CDC in backtesting.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/05/2023<br>      Modified by: Zifeng&nbsp;Zhao</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ In this project, we study the problem of time series segmentation, also known as change-point estimation. It is one of the fundamental problems in statistics and has broad applications in many scientific areas including bioinformatics, climate science, economics, finance, genetics, medical science, epidemiology and signal processing.   An important issue for time series segmentation is how to rigorously handle the unknown temporal dependence, where observations across time are inter-dependent with each other. Based on the self-normalization (SN) principle, we have designed novel time series segmentation algorithms that can implement effective multiple change-point estimation universally for scalar/vector/functional/regression time series with sound theoretical guarantees. Compared to existing literature, our method is robust to temporal dependence and is furthermore tuning-free, which makes it an easy-to-use time series segmentation algorithm for researchers and practitioners. We have developed a computationally efficient R package, SNSeg, which implements the proposed algorithms in R.   As an important application of our proposed algorithm, we have analyzed the trajectories of the COVID-19 pandemic in the U.S. and 30 other major countries in the world. In particular, we have applied the proposed segmentation algorithm to the time series of daily new cases(i.e. the infection curve) of COVID-19 and found that the growth of the pandemic can be partitioned into several distinct phases. Based on our analysis, we show that public health intervention policies such as lockdown are effective in early phases of the pandemic. In addition, we have designed a two-step forecasting algorithm that can generate both point prediction and interval prediction for the daily new cases in the near future. It is shown to perform better than the algorithm used by the CDC in backtesting.       Last Modified: 10/05/2023       Submitted by: Zifeng Zhao]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
