<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I:  Directed protein evolution: Creating high affinity protein ligands for controlling economically detrimental plant pathogens and pests</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>224594.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>249594</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Erik Pierstorff</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>epiersto@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922165</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is to create next generation crop products. Crop loss due to pathogens has been estimated to be approximately 20-40% of total possible yield.  The proposed technology is an environmentally-friendly way to combat pests, even if they evolve to be resistant to conventional methods. This technology can be used for other life sciences applications, including special cancer treatments. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed project is to generate new and durable resistant crops by producing ligands that can bind to virulence factors of plant pathogens to make them malfunction. The novel protein evolution technology is a rapid and automated platform for developing high-affinity protein ligands. It comprises a self-sustaining, iterative bacterial culture system that drives the emergence of new protein and peptide sequences expressed by the M13 bacteriophage. Once pathogens or pest develop resistance for the ligands we generate, new and stronger binding ligands could be quickly evolved to control them.  The technology is broadly applicable to developing optimized protein sequences for virtually any affinity interaction.  Other applications include protein purification, antibody optimization as well as engineering novel receptors for cancer immunotherapy.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/07/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/20/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2014621</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jiarui</FirstName>
<LastName>Li</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jiarui Li</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ljrluck@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7853177639</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000816777</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/07/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>INNATRIX, INC.</Name>
<CityName>CHAPEL HILL</CityName>
<ZipCode>275990001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9193708434</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>250 BELL TOWER DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>MC72EA9LJ9A5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>INNATRIX INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Innatrix]]></Name>
<CityName>Durham</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>277090003</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[104 TW Alexander Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8091</Code>
<Text>SBIR Outreach &amp; Tech. Assist</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>144E</Code>
<Text>Synthetic biology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8038</Code>
<Text>Biotechnology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~249594</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>To address the unmet need for alternative crop protection strategies, Innatrix, Inc. initiated an NSF Phase I SBIR program in June of 2020.&nbsp; We have accomplished project technical objectives and their respective subtasks and goals.&nbsp; The project outcomes are summarized here:</p> <ul> <li>Confirmed bacterial cultures are viable more than 2 weeks;</li> <li>Explored different spaces to have optimal expression of trxA and Hibit genes;</li> <li>Performed Evostat runs for ligands for more than 2 weeks;</li> <li>Identified 9 different protein ligands to bind to the target IPI-O4, confirmed by ELISA assays. The preliminary lab efficacy showed 4 protein ligands displayed good control of late blight;</li> <li>Received the issuance of a U.S. patent (U.S. patent No.&nbsp;<span>10,858,648)</span>, a foundational component of the company as we move toward commercialization.</li> </ul> <p>In addition, the project success has led to several business accomplishments:</p> <ul> <li><span>Found beachhead market after attending NSF I-Corp program;</span></li> <li><span>Granted a U.S. patent for our protein evolution technology;</span></li> <li><span>Innatrix team was invited to participate Bayer CropScience&rsquo;s Grants4 Ag Program, with $10K initial investment;</span></li> <li><span>Secured research and business partners: Bayer CropScience, Orion Integrated Biosciences, Global Agricultural Development Corporation;</span></li> <li><span>Raised $250K funds from NC Biotech Center;</span></li> <li><span>Innatrix team has been selected into Aglaunch365 program.</span></li> </ul> <p>Thank you for your great help and support!!</p> <p><span>&nbsp;</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/01/2021<br>      Modified by: Jiarui&nbsp;Li</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ To address the unmet need for alternative crop protection strategies, Innatrix, Inc. initiated an NSF Phase I SBIR program in June of 2020.  We have accomplished project technical objectives and their respective subtasks and goals.  The project outcomes are summarized here:  Confirmed bacterial cultures are viable more than 2 weeks; Explored different spaces to have optimal expression of trxA and Hibit genes; Performed Evostat runs for ligands for more than 2 weeks; Identified 9 different protein ligands to bind to the target IPI-O4, confirmed by ELISA assays. The preliminary lab efficacy showed 4 protein ligands displayed good control of late blight; Received the issuance of a U.S. patent (U.S. patent No. 10,858,648), a foundational component of the company as we move toward commercialization.   In addition, the project success has led to several business accomplishments:  Found beachhead market after attending NSF I-Corp program; Granted a U.S. patent for our protein evolution technology; Innatrix team was invited to participate Bayer CropScience’s Grants4 Ag Program, with $10K initial investment; Secured research and business partners: Bayer CropScience, Orion Integrated Biosciences, Global Agricultural Development Corporation; Raised $250K funds from NC Biotech Center; Innatrix team has been selected into Aglaunch365 program.   Thank you for your great help and support!!                Last Modified: 12/01/2021       Submitted by: Jiarui Li]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
