<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Efficient Estimation of Treatment Effects via Nonparametric Machine Learning]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>154390.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>154390</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Yong Zeng</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>yzeng@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927299</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Advances in technology have created numerous large-scale datasets in observational studies, which bring unprecedented opportunities for evaluating the effectiveness of various treatments. The complex nature of large-scale observational data, such as its massive volume and high dimensions in confounders, pose great challenges to the existing conventional methods for causal analysis. The corresponding statistical implication is that even a small amount of bias can easily lead to erroneous conclusions. Thanks to the rapid development of scalable computing techniques, nonparametric machine learning methods have a strong potential for bias reduction via employing data-driven strategies for dimensionality reduction. However, careful consideration must be given in order to realize the potential for studying the underlying causal mechanisms. This project aims to develop cutting-edge statistical methods with theoretical insights for causality analysis using deep neural networks. The new statistical tools meet the immediate needs from various scientific areas for exploring causal relationships from large-scale observational data. The research will facilitate the causality analysis of modern complex data with important applications. This project will integrate research and education through course development, open-source software development, and undergraduate and graduate student training. &lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;The PI will develop a new unified approach with thorough theoretical justifications for efficient estimation of causal effects using deep neural networks. The method will then be applied to large-scale datasets with binary, multi-valued, or continuous-valued treatment variables. Three interconnected topics will be pursued. Specifically, the PI will offer a new perspective on learning treatment effects through a generalized optimization estimation. As a result, two convenient and efficient estimators of treatment effects will be developed, respectively, in the second and third topics. The estimators involve one nuisance model that will be approximated by deep neural networks, which will be investigated in the first topic. The general optimization framework includes the average, quantile and asymmetric least squares treatment effects as special cases. The methods take full advantage of the large sample size of large-scale data and provide effective protection against model mis-specification bias. The project involves devising new machine learning methods and algorithms for causal studies, establishing the theoretical validity, and developing valid inference procedures. It will promote machine learning methods for causality analysis, and will break new ground in drawing causal inference from large-scale observational datasets.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/19/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/19/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2014221</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Shujie</FirstName>
<LastName>Ma</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Shujie Ma</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[shujie.ma@ucr.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000604712</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/19/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Riverside</Name>
<CityName>RIVERSIDE</CityName>
<ZipCode>925210001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9518275535</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>200 UNIVERSTY OFC BUILDING</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>39</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA39</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>MR5QC5FCAVH5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA AT RIVERSIDE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California, Riverside]]></Name>
<CityName>Riverside</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>925210001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[900 University Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>39</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA39</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1269</Code>
<Text>STATISTICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>079Z</Code>
<Text>Machine Learning Theory</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~154390</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The project has developed cutting-edge statistical methods with theoretical insights for treatment effects estimation and causal inference using powerful and flexible machine learning algorithms. The PI has developed new machine learning tools adapted to the causal framework, established their theoretical validity, and developed valid inference procedures. The developed statistical tools meet the immediate needs from various scientific areas for studying causal relationships from large-scale observational data. &nbsp;</p> <p>Under the support of this award, the PI has completed a number of peer-reviewed journal articles with her students, and some of them have appeared in statistics, machine learning, and econometrics journals. The PI has trained several PhD students with their dissertation topics on the proposed research. The PI and her students have developed computational algorithms and software packages for the proposed methods, and have applied the methods to different biomedical and econometrics data applications. &nbsp;The research provides an effective statistical toolbox that can facilitate the causality analysis of modern complex data with important applications. The developed methods have attracted and promoted collaborations with researchers from Public Health, Medicine, Economics, and Social Sciences. &nbsp;The project has also integrated research and education through course development, outreach programs, and undergraduate and graduate student training. The PI has offered special topic courses to their graduate students, and has included the proposed research topics in both her undergraduate and graduate classes. The PI has given a number of seminar talks in different departments including her own department to disseminate the research results of this project, and has also presented the results in international and local conferences and workshops.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/19/2023<br>      Modified by: Shujie&nbsp;Ma</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The project has developed cutting-edge statistical methods with theoretical insights for treatment effects estimation and causal inference using powerful and flexible machine learning algorithms. The PI has developed new machine learning tools adapted to the causal framework, established their theoretical validity, and developed valid inference procedures. The developed statistical tools meet the immediate needs from various scientific areas for studying causal relationships from large-scale observational data.    Under the support of this award, the PI has completed a number of peer-reviewed journal articles with her students, and some of them have appeared in statistics, machine learning, and econometrics journals. The PI has trained several PhD students with their dissertation topics on the proposed research. The PI and her students have developed computational algorithms and software packages for the proposed methods, and have applied the methods to different biomedical and econometrics data applications.  The research provides an effective statistical toolbox that can facilitate the causality analysis of modern complex data with important applications. The developed methods have attracted and promoted collaborations with researchers from Public Health, Medicine, Economics, and Social Sciences.  The project has also integrated research and education through course development, outreach programs, and undergraduate and graduate student training. The PI has offered special topic courses to their graduate students, and has included the proposed research topics in both her undergraduate and graduate classes. The PI has given a number of seminar talks in different departments including her own department to disseminate the research results of this project, and has also presented the results in international and local conferences and workshops.           Last Modified: 09/19/2023       Submitted by: Shujie Ma]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
