<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Development of a Novel, Cost-Effective Gait Training Device Utilized at Home for the Neurological Patient Population]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>223370.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>223370</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Alastair Monk</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>amonk@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924392</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation (SBIR) Phase I project would be the development of a neurorehabilitation technology with a total addressable market of $54B and the opportunity to increase access to advanced care for the 5.2 million people in the US living with paralysis and the 1.3 million people each year that experience an extreme neurological injury or diagnosis that can lead to severe gait impairment. This technology will encourage a proactive approach to care, eliminate the need for a clinician to be physically present in the rehabilitation experience, and introduce software solutions to increase motivation and connectivity. Clinically, if successful, this technology could dramatically decrease secondary complications, help people regain the ability to walk, and ultimately reduce costs associated with neurological diagnoses.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I is to develop an at-home gait trainer for rehabilitation and physical therapy of individuals with neurological injuries or neurological conditions using a patient-centered approach. This project integrates at-home advanced medical technology with telemedicine physical therapy.  This will enable continued rehabilitation and physical therapy without clinical oversight via training videos.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/24/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/20/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2014635</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ben</FirstName>
<LastName>Taylor</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ben Taylor</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ben.taylor@healinginnovations.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000816929</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/24/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>HEALING INNOVATIONS INC</Name>
<CityName>NASHVILLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>372281709</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6159655020</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>240 GREAT CIRCLE RD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[STE 350]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>Z87CCATFZJH3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>HEALING INNOVATIONS, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[HEALING INNOVATIONS INC]]></Name>
<CityName>Nashville</CityName>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>372102125</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[41 Peabody St.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>010E</Code>
<Text>DISABILITY RES &amp; HOMECARE TECH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8018</Code>
<Text>Smart and Connected Health</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8032</Code>
<Text>Software Services and Applications</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~223370</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>In the United States, approximately 5.2 million people, nearly 1 in 50 individuals, are living with paralysis. In addition, 1.3 million people each year experience an extreme neurological injury or diagnosis that can lead to severe gait impairment. In the US healthcare system, acute care facilities are incentivized to decrease the average length of stay, so more complex patients are discharged to secondary care settings and eventually the home earlier than before. This leaves many individuals searching for methods to continue their rehabilitation journey. COVID-19 further magnified this gap in care as a large percentage of this patient population were immunocompromised and were forced to stop their rehabilitation and exercise routine.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><strong>Project Outcomes</strong></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>In the Phase I project, Healing Innovations performed extensive customer discovery to better understand the needs of this population and other stakeholders involved. From those findings, Healing Innovations established a comprehensive set of design criteria that detailed functional, safety, and user experience requirements for a gait therapy device.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>These requirements guided the development process of mechanical, electrical, and software systems. Complex mechanical systems were designed to provide accurate gait biomechanics and clinically valuable features, ensure user safety, and create a seamless user workflow. A software platform was created to provide valuable metrics to the user and motivate them to continue their rehabilitation journey. Electrical control systems were created to work with the mechanical system and provide input into the software system.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Healing Innovations successfully created a functional design in the Rise&amp;Walk InHome. It is a novel, patent-pending device designed to provide gait training in a residential setting; it provides a similar function to clinical gait training devices while significantly simpler and less expensive. The work in Phase I positions Healing Innovations well to prototype and refine the device design, perform necessary regulatory testing, and prepare for commercial launch.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span><br /></span></p> <p dir="ltr"><strong>Intellectual Merit</strong></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The design process for the Rise&amp;Walk InHome required significant mechanical, software, and electrical engineering effort. The design required creating rigorous safety features, complex mechanical and electrical functions for clinical relevance and user benefit, and cost optimization to improve access to the technology. The integration of the electromechanical system with a user-friendly software ecosystem was also a significant technical undertaking.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span><br /></span></p> <p dir="ltr"><strong>Broader Impact</strong></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The Rise&amp;Walk InHome has the potential to increase access to gait therapy, encourage a proactive approach to care, eliminate the need for a clinician to be physically present in the rehabilitation experience, and increase motivation in the neurological patient population.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Clinically, this technology could dramatically decrease secondary complications, help restore motor abilities, promote independence, and ultimately reduce the astronomical costs associated with neurological diagnoses. Finally, large-scale data collection and analysis of long-term gait training will enable the scientific community to better identify common themes associated with the restoration of function. </span><span>The InHome has the potential to positively change the lives of thousands of individuals living with paralysis.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/30/2021<br>      Modified by: Ben&nbsp;Taylor</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ In the United States, approximately 5.2 million people, nearly 1 in 50 individuals, are living with paralysis. In addition, 1.3 million people each year experience an extreme neurological injury or diagnosis that can lead to severe gait impairment. In the US healthcare system, acute care facilities are incentivized to decrease the average length of stay, so more complex patients are discharged to secondary care settings and eventually the home earlier than before. This leaves many individuals searching for methods to continue their rehabilitation journey. COVID-19 further magnified this gap in care as a large percentage of this patient population were immunocompromised and were forced to stop their rehabilitation and exercise routine.    Project Outcomes In the Phase I project, Healing Innovations performed extensive customer discovery to better understand the needs of this population and other stakeholders involved. From those findings, Healing Innovations established a comprehensive set of design criteria that detailed functional, safety, and user experience requirements for a gait therapy device.  These requirements guided the development process of mechanical, electrical, and software systems. Complex mechanical systems were designed to provide accurate gait biomechanics and clinically valuable features, ensure user safety, and create a seamless user workflow. A software platform was created to provide valuable metrics to the user and motivate them to continue their rehabilitation journey. Electrical control systems were created to work with the mechanical system and provide input into the software system. Healing Innovations successfully created a functional design in the Rise&amp;Walk InHome. It is a novel, patent-pending device designed to provide gait training in a residential setting; it provides a similar function to clinical gait training devices while significantly simpler and less expensive. The work in Phase I positions Healing Innovations well to prototype and refine the device design, perform necessary regulatory testing, and prepare for commercial launch.   Intellectual Merit The design process for the Rise&amp;Walk InHome required significant mechanical, software, and electrical engineering effort. The design required creating rigorous safety features, complex mechanical and electrical functions for clinical relevance and user benefit, and cost optimization to improve access to the technology. The integration of the electromechanical system with a user-friendly software ecosystem was also a significant technical undertaking.    Broader Impact The Rise&amp;Walk InHome has the potential to increase access to gait therapy, encourage a proactive approach to care, eliminate the need for a clinician to be physically present in the rehabilitation experience, and increase motivation in the neurological patient population.  Clinically, this technology could dramatically decrease secondary complications, help restore motor abilities, promote independence, and ultimately reduce the astronomical costs associated with neurological diagnoses. Finally, large-scale data collection and analysis of long-term gait training will enable the scientific community to better identify common themes associated with the restoration of function. The InHome has the potential to positively change the lives of thousands of individuals living with paralysis.          Last Modified: 09/30/2021       Submitted by: Ben Taylor]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
