<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[STTR Phase I:  Optimization of a device for peripheral nerve recordings to diagnose neuropathy]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>225000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>245000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Henry Ahn</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>hahn@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927069</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Technology Transfer Research (STTR) Phase I project is to optimize and validate a novel medical device for early detection and diagnosis of peripheral neuropathy (PN). PN is damage of nerve fibers, typically starting in the skin and distal limbs and migrating to deeper tissue layers as the disease progresses, and affecting an estimated 30 million people. Currently no diagnostic tool nor cure exists, but early detection affords the possibility of slowing disease progression. The goal of this project is to advance the development of a small, cost-effective, portable microneedle device measuring nerve conductance, the only method to directly determine nerve function and determine the most accurate assessment of peripheral nerve health. This device addresses the need for a non-invasive, painless, early onset neuropathy diagnostic device for use in a clinical setting. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed STTR Phase I project will develop a novel medical device using an array of modified microneedle electrodes to measure nerve conductance in small nerve fibers of skin and underlying tissues. The project goals include: 1) reproducibly recording nerve conductance across an entire needle array and averaging signals using mathematical algorithms to interpret nerve signals for an assessment of neuropathic state; 2) determining the necessity of electrical stimulation for detecting nerve conductance; 3) optimizing signal amplification for an appropriate signal-to-noise ratio; 4) determining optimal needle specifications; and 5) developing wireless communication of the recorded signal and software for signal processing and transmission. Optimization of signal:noise ratio, signal amplification, needle specification and determination of the need for electrical stimulation will be done utilizing healthy animal models. Utilizing validated animal models of peripheral neuropathy, device measurements will be compared to nerve conductance velocity (to diagnose advanced PN) and standard (indirect) assessments of PN, including quantitative assessment of tactile allodynia (Von Frey test), behavioral assays (acetone spray test, hot/cold plate assay), and tissue biopsies.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/17/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/09/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2014779</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kristy</FirstName>
<LastName>Townsend</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kristy Townsend</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[kristy.townsend@osumc.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000727273</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/17/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Magdalena</FirstName>
<LastName>Blaszkiewicz</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Magdalena Blaszkiewicz</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[neuright@gmail.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000791690</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/17/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>NEURIGHT, INC.</Name>
<CityName>ORONO</CityName>
<ZipCode>044733610</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6177843459</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>20 GODFREY DR STE 201</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maine</StateName>
<StateCode>ME</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>ME02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>FG21BZ9M96B7</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NEURIGHT, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Maine]]></Name>
<CityName>Orono</CityName>
<StateCode>ME</StateCode>
<ZipCode>044733610</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[168 College Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maine</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>ME02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1505</Code>
<Text>STTR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8091</Code>
<Text>SBIR Outreach &amp; Tech. Assist</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8038</Code>
<Text>Biotechnology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~225000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~20000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Neuright, Inc.</p> <p>Project Outcomes Report</p> <p>STTR Phase I: Optimization of a device for peripheral nerve recordings to diagnose neuropathy</p> <p>An estimated 30 million people in the U.S. suffer from peripheral neuropathy, a debilitating disease of nerve dieback. However, peripheral neuropathy diagnosis is often delayed due to a lack of reliable, non-invasive, easy to employ tools in disease assessment, especially for small fiber neuropathy or conditions in which small fiber neuropathy precedes large fiber neuropathy.&nbsp; Our Phase I STTR project was aimed at addressing this gap in peripheral neuropathy diagnosis, and focused on addressing technical hurdles related to the diagnostic capabilities of our Detecting Early Neuropathy (DEN) microneedle medical device. Our primary objective was to optimize and test the device for the sensitive detection of diabetic peripheral neuropathy (DPN) in a pre-clinical (mouse) model. This included determining the optimal needle material and coating/insulation, needle depth, number of needles in the array and their amplification, noise-reduction and signal processing, and finally whether or not electrical stimulation was necessary in order to record nerve electrical activity in the skin and subdermal tissues.&nbsp; Our secondary objective was to develop software and wireless communication in a HIPAA and FDA compliant manner and begin developing algorithms to interpret nerve recording data for diagnostic criteria.</p> <p>During the Phase I award period we completed prototype development and validation and confirmed we could measure small fiber nerve electrical activity in skin and subdermal tissues of the mouse, we finalized the optimization of the mouse recording prototype device and utilized it for a complete pre-clinical study using a mouse model of diabetic small fiber neuropathy, we finalized our device designs after R&amp;D testing and submitted a full patent, and aspects of this research were presented at local and regional research symposia and are now being prepared in a series of research manuscripts that will be submitted to peer-reviewed journals. Significant progress was also made on our custom wireless electronics designs and prototypes, data analyses, and software development. Most Importantly, at the conclusion of the Phase I period, we were able to finalize a human prototype of the device and tested it in two separate human subjects (people in our R&amp;D team) to validate that we were able to record numerous electrical signatures including small fiber nerve action potentials. This device will be used in future R&amp;D work to conduct a First in Human (FIH) testing study with collaborating neurologists at The Ohio State University?s Wexner Medical Center. We have an expert collaborative team in place for this next phase of growth in order to ensure the continued success of this R&amp;D endeavor, with the goal of moving into clinical trials and FDA pre-submission within the next several years.</p> <p>Work undertaken under this project has also resulted in training and professional development of numerous undergraduate students, including 3 undergraduate engineering/bioengineering students and 4 biology students.&nbsp; These students will also be co-authors on subsequent research manuscripts that are currently under preparation.&nbsp;</p> <p>The summation of the work under this project has resulted in pursuance of federal (NSF Phase II STTR to optimize the DEN for human use) and private funding in order continue with the momentum achieved under the Phase I period and move the DEN further along its commercialization process. Considering that there is currently no functional diagnostic tool on the market for assessing small fiber peripheral neuropathy commercialization of the DEN could benefit the millions of patients suffering from peripheral neuropathy by providing a diagnosis at a time when intervention may deter disease progression.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/17/2022<br>      Modified by: Magdalena&nbsp;Blaszkiewicz</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Neuright, Inc.  Project Outcomes Report  STTR Phase I: Optimization of a device for peripheral nerve recordings to diagnose neuropathy  An estimated 30 million people in the U.S. suffer from peripheral neuropathy, a debilitating disease of nerve dieback. However, peripheral neuropathy diagnosis is often delayed due to a lack of reliable, non-invasive, easy to employ tools in disease assessment, especially for small fiber neuropathy or conditions in which small fiber neuropathy precedes large fiber neuropathy.  Our Phase I STTR project was aimed at addressing this gap in peripheral neuropathy diagnosis, and focused on addressing technical hurdles related to the diagnostic capabilities of our Detecting Early Neuropathy (DEN) microneedle medical device. Our primary objective was to optimize and test the device for the sensitive detection of diabetic peripheral neuropathy (DPN) in a pre-clinical (mouse) model. This included determining the optimal needle material and coating/insulation, needle depth, number of needles in the array and their amplification, noise-reduction and signal processing, and finally whether or not electrical stimulation was necessary in order to record nerve electrical activity in the skin and subdermal tissues.  Our secondary objective was to develop software and wireless communication in a HIPAA and FDA compliant manner and begin developing algorithms to interpret nerve recording data for diagnostic criteria.  During the Phase I award period we completed prototype development and validation and confirmed we could measure small fiber nerve electrical activity in skin and subdermal tissues of the mouse, we finalized the optimization of the mouse recording prototype device and utilized it for a complete pre-clinical study using a mouse model of diabetic small fiber neuropathy, we finalized our device designs after R&amp;D testing and submitted a full patent, and aspects of this research were presented at local and regional research symposia and are now being prepared in a series of research manuscripts that will be submitted to peer-reviewed journals. Significant progress was also made on our custom wireless electronics designs and prototypes, data analyses, and software development. Most Importantly, at the conclusion of the Phase I period, we were able to finalize a human prototype of the device and tested it in two separate human subjects (people in our R&amp;D team) to validate that we were able to record numerous electrical signatures including small fiber nerve action potentials. This device will be used in future R&amp;D work to conduct a First in Human (FIH) testing study with collaborating neurologists at The Ohio State University?s Wexner Medical Center. We have an expert collaborative team in place for this next phase of growth in order to ensure the continued success of this R&amp;D endeavor, with the goal of moving into clinical trials and FDA pre-submission within the next several years.  Work undertaken under this project has also resulted in training and professional development of numerous undergraduate students, including 3 undergraduate engineering/bioengineering students and 4 biology students.  These students will also be co-authors on subsequent research manuscripts that are currently under preparation.   The summation of the work under this project has resulted in pursuance of federal (NSF Phase II STTR to optimize the DEN for human use) and private funding in order continue with the momentum achieved under the Phase I period and move the DEN further along its commercialization process. Considering that there is currently no functional diagnostic tool on the market for assessing small fiber peripheral neuropathy commercialization of the DEN could benefit the millions of patients suffering from peripheral neuropathy by providing a diagnosis at a time when intervention may deter disease progression.          Last Modified: 01/17/2022       Submitted by: Magdalena Blaszkiewicz]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
