<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Novel drug delivery system using engineered exosomes]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>225000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>225000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Henry Ahn</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>hahn@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927069</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[he broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase 1 project entails developing an novel drug delivery platform to deliver drug into poorly accessible druggable targets. Drugs targeting inflammation are encapsulated in an new way for treatment of chronic inflammatory diseases such as psoriasis, lupus, rheumatoid arthritis. Biological therapies remain the standard for autoimmune diseases, but patients can have immune system problems due to the production of autoantibodies. This project addresses this challenge with a novel encapsulation technology that delivers biological therapies to hard-to-reach inflammation sites. This technology could be advantageous because it reduces immunosuppression and anti-drug antibodies production. This project will improve patient treatment outcomes and reduce treatment reduce cost. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase 1 project will test a proof-of-concept that entails demonstrating that an exosome-based delivery vehicle for biologics will potentially inhibit inappropriate TLR-driven inflammation. Induction of autoimmune diseases including psoriasis, rheumatoid arthritis and lupus strongly correlate with chronic inflammation driven by inflammatory signaling pathways mediated by endosomal TLRs. Our goal is to develop an exosome-based therapy that can inhibit poorly accessible endosomal TLR7-driven inflammation. To test this concept, our plan involves genetically modifying human cell lines to produce engineered exosomes that contain anti-TLR7 antibody to inhibit endosomal TLR7-driven inflammation. We will develop a drug encapsulation platform in which engineered exosomes bear an anti-TLR7 antibody fused with an exosome transmembrane protein called tetraspanin. This complex delivers an antibody payload to TLR7 targets located in on endosomal membrane inner surface. This anti-TLR7 antibody will bind to dimer-interfaces of TLR7 monomer and thereby block TLR7 receptor dimerization, which in turn blocks proinflammatory signaling. This work is important because blocking TLR7 receptor activation, which is situated upstream in the signaling cascade, will presumably diminish immunosuppression and lead to a better outcome that current anti-TNF therapies that are more broad spectrum because their site of action is downstream in a signaling pathway axis.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/03/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/03/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2014266</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Souvenir</FirstName>
<LastName>Tachado</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Souvenir D Tachado</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[stachado@souviebiodelivery.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000801171</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/03/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>SOUVIE BIODELIVERY LLC</Name>
<CityName>ORO VALLEY</CityName>
<ZipCode>857551963</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7744637261</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1800 E INNOVATION PARK DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AZ06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>H21KZV4VYUB3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SOUVIE BIODELIVERY LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[SOUVIE BIODELIVERY LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>Tucson</CityName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>857479192</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[9040 S Rita Rd]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AZ06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>008E</Code>
<Text>Gene and Drug Delivery</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>6883</Code>
<Text>CHEMISTRY OF LIFE PROCESSES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~225000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>SBIR Phase1 Project Outcomes Report: Novel drug delivery system using engineered exosomes</strong></p> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p><strong>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </strong>Souvenir D Tachado, Principal Investigator</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Founder/President, Souvie Biodelivery</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Proposal number: 2014266</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Start Date: 02/15/2021&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; End Date:01/31/2022</p> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong>Drug side effects, technically known as adverse drug reactions (ADR), are unwanted drug effects that have considerable economic as well as clinical costs as they often lead to hospital admission, prolongation of hospital stay and emergency room visits. ADRs account for 4.2-30% of hospital admissions in the USA and Canada. The impact and the management of ADRs is complex and may cost up to 30.1 billion dollars annually. ADRs are a source of additional burden on patients, their caregivers, and the healthcare systems that treat them. Drugs can often bind different protein targets and it remains unclear which of these targets cause adverse side effects in the human body. This adverse drug reactions happens when a single drug often interacts with multiple cell types (healthy and diseased) in the body not always limited to the intended targets.&nbsp;</p> <p>For example, inflammatory autoimmune disorders such as psoriasis, systemic lupus erythematosus are treated with corticosteroids, immunosuppressive drugs, and biologics such as anti-tumor necrosis factor alpha (TNF&#61537;) antibodies like Humira. However, a lot of patients do not respond fully to therapies. While the efficacy of these drugs decreases over time, the risks of infections and cancer associated with their use are increasing. This is because the drug delivery system used to deliver these drugs are not optimal. This consequence can lead to medication nonadherence, which is mostly intentional with patients making a rational decision not to take their medication based on their knowledge, experience and beliefs which can be costly for the patients and the society in general.<em></em></p> <p>Exosomes are extracellular vesicles, or small bubbles, released from cells that act as shuttles for genetic information, proteins, and messenger RNA to other cells. Exosomes are involved in major pathophysiological processes, including cellular homeostasis, infection propagation, cancer development and cardiovascular diseases. They are also explored for delivery of therapeutic payloads to specific cells and tissues, harnessing their intrinsic tissue-homing capabilities, opening new frontiers for modern drug delivery. From a drug delivery perspective, exosomes are comparable to liposomes used in mRNA vaccines against COVID-19 given that both are phospholipid based. The use of exosomes as therapeutic agents is rapidly evolving, showing enormous potential in various research fields such as inflammation, infectious diseases, regenerative medicine, oncology, and autoimmune diseases. Souvie BioDelivery LLC developed an exosome-based drug delivery system to inhibit the source(s) of inflammation that is responsible for causing disease in chronic auto-immune diseases such as psoriasis, systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE), and rheumatoid arthritis (RA). Drugs were encapsulated, in this case antibodies, in engineered exosomes displaying the natural repertoire of surface markers that targets delivery and prevents an immune response to the cargo and vehicle. The core innovation is to use an exosome membrane scaffold as the targeting molecule, which thereby provides for an intrinsic membrane localization signal that can traffic exosomes inside the cells. This exosome-based delivery platform will protect the drug from unintended degradation, eliminate side effects, lowers expression of substances that affects the efficacy of the drug, and increase drug&rsquo;s effectiveness by delivery to tissues with high penetration. The properties of exosomes such as biocompatibility, preferred tumor homing, adjustable targeting efficiency, low immunogenicity, and stability make them striking and excellent drug delivery vehicles for use in various disease applications.&nbsp;</p> <p>The broader impact of our project is that successful demonstration of the engineering of exosomes loaded with antibody-based drugs could lead to a new class of lipid-based formulations of antibodies. In addition, there is societal need to develop a novel targeted anti-inflammatory drug delivery system to treat chronic autoimmune diseases like lupus erythematosus, psoriasis, and rheumatoid arthritis and even cancer and heart disease. This is in line with NSF mission to promote the progress of science; to advance the national health, prosperity, and welfare; and to secure the national defense; and for other purposes. The technology offers the capability to improve the ability of the body to fight infections that are induced by drug delivery vehicles and biologics currently on the market. The improved specificity provided by the engineered exosomes as drug carriers provide opportunities to develop treatments for other inflammation-driven diseases including cancer, sepsis, metabolic syndrome, as well as for other indication such as solid tumors where current drug delivery technology falls short. Improved outcomes and improved patient experience due to reduction or elimination of unwanted side effects will translate into lower cost of treatment.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/11/2022<br>      Modified by: Souvenir&nbsp;D&nbsp;Tachado</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ SBIR Phase1 Project Outcomes Report: Novel drug delivery system using engineered exosomes                                                 Souvenir D Tachado, Principal Investigator                                                 Founder/President, Souvie Biodelivery                                                            Proposal number: 2014266                                        Start Date: 02/15/2021        End Date:01/31/2022      Drug side effects, technically known as adverse drug reactions (ADR), are unwanted drug effects that have considerable economic as well as clinical costs as they often lead to hospital admission, prolongation of hospital stay and emergency room visits. ADRs account for 4.2-30% of hospital admissions in the USA and Canada. The impact and the management of ADRs is complex and may cost up to 30.1 billion dollars annually. ADRs are a source of additional burden on patients, their caregivers, and the healthcare systems that treat them. Drugs can often bind different protein targets and it remains unclear which of these targets cause adverse side effects in the human body. This adverse drug reactions happens when a single drug often interacts with multiple cell types (healthy and diseased) in the body not always limited to the intended targets.   For example, inflammatory autoimmune disorders such as psoriasis, systemic lupus erythematosus are treated with corticosteroids, immunosuppressive drugs, and biologics such as anti-tumor necrosis factor alpha (TNF&#61537;) antibodies like Humira. However, a lot of patients do not respond fully to therapies. While the efficacy of these drugs decreases over time, the risks of infections and cancer associated with their use are increasing. This is because the drug delivery system used to deliver these drugs are not optimal. This consequence can lead to medication nonadherence, which is mostly intentional with patients making a rational decision not to take their medication based on their knowledge, experience and beliefs which can be costly for the patients and the society in general.  Exosomes are extracellular vesicles, or small bubbles, released from cells that act as shuttles for genetic information, proteins, and messenger RNA to other cells. Exosomes are involved in major pathophysiological processes, including cellular homeostasis, infection propagation, cancer development and cardiovascular diseases. They are also explored for delivery of therapeutic payloads to specific cells and tissues, harnessing their intrinsic tissue-homing capabilities, opening new frontiers for modern drug delivery. From a drug delivery perspective, exosomes are comparable to liposomes used in mRNA vaccines against COVID-19 given that both are phospholipid based. The use of exosomes as therapeutic agents is rapidly evolving, showing enormous potential in various research fields such as inflammation, infectious diseases, regenerative medicine, oncology, and autoimmune diseases. Souvie BioDelivery LLC developed an exosome-based drug delivery system to inhibit the source(s) of inflammation that is responsible for causing disease in chronic auto-immune diseases such as psoriasis, systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE), and rheumatoid arthritis (RA). Drugs were encapsulated, in this case antibodies, in engineered exosomes displaying the natural repertoire of surface markers that targets delivery and prevents an immune response to the cargo and vehicle. The core innovation is to use an exosome membrane scaffold as the targeting molecule, which thereby provides for an intrinsic membrane localization signal that can traffic exosomes inside the cells. This exosome-based delivery platform will protect the drug from unintended degradation, eliminate side effects, lowers expression of substances that affects the efficacy of the drug, and increase drug’s effectiveness by delivery to tissues with high penetration. The properties of exosomes such as biocompatibility, preferred tumor homing, adjustable targeting efficiency, low immunogenicity, and stability make them striking and excellent drug delivery vehicles for use in various disease applications.   The broader impact of our project is that successful demonstration of the engineering of exosomes loaded with antibody-based drugs could lead to a new class of lipid-based formulations of antibodies. In addition, there is societal need to develop a novel targeted anti-inflammatory drug delivery system to treat chronic autoimmune diseases like lupus erythematosus, psoriasis, and rheumatoid arthritis and even cancer and heart disease. This is in line with NSF mission to promote the progress of science; to advance the national health, prosperity, and welfare; and to secure the national defense; and for other purposes. The technology offers the capability to improve the ability of the body to fight infections that are induced by drug delivery vehicles and biologics currently on the market. The improved specificity provided by the engineered exosomes as drug carriers provide opportunities to develop treatments for other inflammation-driven diseases including cancer, sepsis, metabolic syndrome, as well as for other indication such as solid tumors where current drug delivery technology falls short. Improved outcomes and improved patient experience due to reduction or elimination of unwanted side effects will translate into lower cost of treatment.          Last Modified: 07/11/2022       Submitted by: Souvenir D Tachado]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
