<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[STTR Phase I:  A novel dual paraboloid mirror device for enhanced light collection in confocal and fluorescence microscopy]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>225000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>225000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Erik Pierstorff</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>epiersto@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922165</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project will be to improve research in the life sciences. This research often uses confocal and fluorescence imaging technologies to capture high-resolution, high-contrast images of biological samples. However, these methods traditionally require high levels of illuminating light, resulting in damage to tissues, disruption of normal processes like cell division, and competing with the light being measured in the experiment.  The proposed solution will improve the collection of light in these microscopes.  This will allow researchers to minimize damage to samples, thus removing current experimental constraints and enabling the development of new and far-ranging applications on an already powerful research platform. The proposed technology will be useful for disease and pharmaceutical research.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed project will involve the development of a simple, add-on, mirrored sample chamber unit capable of enhancing confocal microscopy capabilities by substantially increasing microscope fluorescence collection efficiency limits. This will require overcoming design challenges because the use of mirrors to collect and refocus emitted light has rarely been attempted in confocal microscopy. The proposed R&amp;D work includes: 1) sample chamber and mirror design and prototyping, 2) design of mounting hardware and integration with an existing confocal system, and 3) exploration of compatible modalities, including Total Internal Reflection Fluorescence microscopy and Stochastic Optical Reconstruction Microscopy. Completion of the proposed objectives will lead to the development of a device that increases the light collection efficiency beyond the current 40% limit, is compatible with any detection objective, and does not require a separate optical path to the detector.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/19/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/20/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2014972</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Joel</FirstName>
<LastName>Smith</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Joel Smith</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jsmith@mizarimaging.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000815457</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/19/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
<LastName>Maddox</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Paul Maddox</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[pmaddox@unc.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000664212</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/19/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>MIZAR IMAGING LLC</Name>
<CityName>CHAPEL HILL</CityName>
<ZipCode>275144600</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5089397500</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2 GOOSENECK RD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>KXVMAEJ8C419</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MIZAR IMAGING LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[MIZAR IMAGING LLC]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>275144600</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1505</Code>
<Text>STTR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8038</Code>
<Text>Biotechnology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8616</Code>
<Text>Instr Rsrch,Metro&amp;Std NanTech</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~225000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The purpose of this project was to increase the light collection of a research fluorescence microscope system.&nbsp; Any point of light, whether a light bulb or a small cell labeled with a fluorescent dye, will emit light in all directions.&nbsp; However, our detection devices, such as your eye or a camera or a research microscope only collect the light directed towards it.&nbsp; The light emitted away from the eye/camera/microscope is lost.&nbsp; In this project, we designed an mirror-based system to collect more of the light that is emitted from a sample on a fluorescence microscope.&nbsp; Simply a parabolic mirror would be placed behind the sample.&nbsp; This mirror would be designed in such a way to reflect the light going away from the microscope back into the microscope, thus increasing the amount of light collected.</p> <p>It turned out that the optics that were designed were harder to manufacture than we anticipated with costs and lead-times beyond the scope of a Phase 1 proposal&nbsp; As a result, we were forced to try and work with sub-optimal off-the-shelf optics for this project.&nbsp; These optics proved to be insufficient for this application and prevented us from completing this project as anticipated.&nbsp; However, we now have a much better grasp on the optical design needed and believe we have a path forward to redesign these parabolic mirrors in a way that will make them more efficient and easier to manufacture.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/02/2023<br>      Modified by: Joel&nbsp;Smith</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The purpose of this project was to increase the light collection of a research fluorescence microscope system.  Any point of light, whether a light bulb or a small cell labeled with a fluorescent dye, will emit light in all directions.  However, our detection devices, such as your eye or a camera or a research microscope only collect the light directed towards it.  The light emitted away from the eye/camera/microscope is lost.  In this project, we designed an mirror-based system to collect more of the light that is emitted from a sample on a fluorescence microscope.  Simply a parabolic mirror would be placed behind the sample.  This mirror would be designed in such a way to reflect the light going away from the microscope back into the microscope, thus increasing the amount of light collected.  It turned out that the optics that were designed were harder to manufacture than we anticipated with costs and lead-times beyond the scope of a Phase 1 proposal  As a result, we were forced to try and work with sub-optimal off-the-shelf optics for this project.  These optics proved to be insufficient for this application and prevented us from completing this project as anticipated.  However, we now have a much better grasp on the optical design needed and believe we have a path forward to redesign these parabolic mirrors in a way that will make them more efficient and easier to manufacture.          Last Modified: 02/02/2023       Submitted by: Joel Smith]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
