<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[STTR Phase I: Development and Commercialization of the SafeLight Family of Antimicrobial Materials for Combatting the COVID-19 Pandemic and Hospital Acquired Infections]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>225000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>225000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Erik Pierstorff</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>epiersto@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922165</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact of this Small Business Technology Transfer (STTR) Phase I project is the development of new antimicrobial materials to reduce the spread of harmful bacteria and viruses in a variety of settings, particularly for self-disinfecting personal protection equipment against SARS-CoV-2 to combat the COVID-19 pandemic. While primarily intended for use in hospitals, these antimicrobial materials can also impact bio-defense; military facilities; food processing, packaging, and service industries; wastewater treatment facilities; daycare and long-term care facilities; and even personal households. Beyond the current pandemic, this technology can address hospital-acquired infections, which add an estimated $30-45 billion to health care costs every year; and the food service industry, where norovirus foodborne infections alone account for an economic loss of about $5.8 B annually in the United States.  The proposed technology offers significant benefit for the current COVID-19 challenge and beyond. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed project will develop light-activated surface-disinfecting materials based on photodynamic inactivation that generates singlet oxygen – a highly reactive yet environmentally benign species – to cause non-specific damage to microbes, rendering them inactive. The technical challenges are: 1) the development of chemical species capable of producing singlet oxygen upon exposure to light, but stable at the high temperatures of manufacturing processes, for which we will start with a known class of compounds; 2) the development of a method for the production and embedding of the newly-developed photoreactive compounds within relevant materials, particularly for the manufacture of personal protection equipment; and 3) evaluation of process efficacy for virucidal (against coronaviruses), antibacterial, antimycotic and sporicidal use.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/29/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/12/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2014753</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
<LastName>Sheehan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Robert J Sheehan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[rsheehan300@gmail.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000830522</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/12/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Reza</FirstName>
<LastName>Ghiladi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Reza A Ghiladi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[reza_ghiladi@ncsu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000497047</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/29/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mahmut</FirstName>
<LastName>Dirican</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mahmut Dirican</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mdirican34@gmail.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000793312</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/29/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate>06/12/2020</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>PHOTOCIDE PROTECTION, INC.</Name>
<CityName>RALEIGH</CityName>
<ZipCode>276950001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9196241744</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4512 THOMAS HALL</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>CV3RHJ1J52E4</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PHOTOCIDE PROTECTION INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[North Carolina State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Raleigh</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>276957615</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2620 Yarbrough Dr]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1505</Code>
<Text>STTR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8038</Code>
<Text>Biotechnology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~225000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Both the COVID-19 pandemic and the chronic problem of hospital-acquired infections (HAIs) together illustrate that the transmission of pathogens is a major threat to global healthcare, especially for elderly, injured, and immune-compromised patients. Accordingly, effective preventative measures that include both surface sterilization methods and the increased production of PPE must be identified and put into place. To this latter point, however, the pandemic has repeatedly highlighted critical gaps in our healthcare and manufacturing infrastructures, especially with regard to PPE availability: with supply chains impacted by a combination of worker illness, as well as shortfalls in common raw material sources (e.g., polypropylene) due to dramatically heightened demand, medical personnel and the general population have faced critical shortages of PPE, including masks, so much so that they often resort to reusing disposable PPE.Thus, there is a critical need for self-disinfecting materials that are capable of broadly (bacteria, viruses, and fungi) protecting patients, medical personnel, and the general public, for prolonged periods of time, that are cost effective, easy to manufacture, and which are available in a variety of form factors (masks, gowns, and surface coverings - including bed rails, tray tables, monitoring equipment, and door handles).&nbsp;</p> <p class="DCMaintext">The goal of this STTR Phase I project was to de-risk the development of novel visible light-activated materials with anti-infective properties to combat the escalating threat posed by harmful pathogens responsible for hospital acquired infections (HAIs), but also covering SARS-CoV-2. To date, there are no visible-light photoactive coatings in use in hospitals and related healthcare settings. This is primarily due to a number of misconceptions related to scalability/cost, the incorrect belief that UV light is needed, but also due to manufacturing and production knowledge gaps. To address these issues, we examined the antimicrobial efficacy of a simple bicomponent spray coating composed of the commercially-available UV-photocrosslinkable polymer <em>N</em>-methyl-4(4&rsquo;-formyl-styryl)pyridinium methosulfate acetal poly(vinyl alcohol) (SbQ-PVA) and one of three aPDI photosensitizers (PSs): zinc-tetra(4-<em>N</em>-methylpyridyl)porphine (ZnTMPyP<sup>4+</sup>), methylene blue (MB), and Rose Bengal (RB). We applied these photodynamic coatings, collectively termed SbQ-PVA/PS, to a variety of commercially available materials. Scanning electron microscopy (SEM) and time-of-flight secondary ion mass spectrometry (ToF-SIMS) confirmed the successful application of the coatings, while inductively coupled plasma-optical emission spectroscopy (ICP-OES) revealed a photosensitizer loading of 0.09-0.78 nmol PS/mg material. The antimicrobial efficacy of the coated materials was evaluated against methicillin-susceptible <em>Staphylococcus aureus</em> ATCC-29213 and human coronavirus strain HCoV-229E. Upon illumination with visible light (60 min, 400-700 nm, 65&plusmn;5 mW/cm<sup>2</sup>), the coated materials inactivated <em>S. aureus</em> by 97-99.999% and HCoV-229E by 92-99.999%, depending on the material and PS employed. Photobleaching studies employing HCoV-229E demonstrated detection limit inactivation (99.999%) even after exposure for four weeks to indoor ambient room lighting.</p> <p class="DCMaintext">Taken together, the results here further confirm that photodynamic spray coatings afford a largely unexplored route to accelerated, effective and comprehensive antimicrobial materials, particularly for their application in reusable self-disinfecting PPE. To-date, and despite their highly potent antimicrobial activity, the adoption of such photoactive materials to reduce infection transmission in hospitals and related healthcare facilities has been hampered by the lack of a scalable and cost-effective means to manufacture them, and high-production methods for producing aPDI-based materials are needed. Here, we have demonstrated that a simple bicomponent spray coating comprised of a photocrosslinkable polymer and a photosensitizer can be applied to a range of commercially available materials used in the public sector. Not only is the spray coating method facile, inexpensive and scalable through the use of off-the-shelf components, it is well suited for expedient integration into existing manufacturing lines that already employ similar UV-curable inks. While further studies examining the launderability and durability of such coatings are needed (as are studies on a wider scope of materials, e.g., polypropylene, more commonly used in PPE), these and other studies suggest that photodynamic spray coatings may be a simple but effective tool for reducing the transmission of pathogens in healthcare settings, thereby adding to the infection-prevention toolbox available to healthcare workers and the general public.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/14/2022<br>      Modified by: Reza&nbsp;A&nbsp;Ghiladi</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Both the COVID-19 pandemic and the chronic problem of hospital-acquired infections (HAIs) together illustrate that the transmission of pathogens is a major threat to global healthcare, especially for elderly, injured, and immune-compromised patients. Accordingly, effective preventative measures that include both surface sterilization methods and the increased production of PPE must be identified and put into place. To this latter point, however, the pandemic has repeatedly highlighted critical gaps in our healthcare and manufacturing infrastructures, especially with regard to PPE availability: with supply chains impacted by a combination of worker illness, as well as shortfalls in common raw material sources (e.g., polypropylene) due to dramatically heightened demand, medical personnel and the general population have faced critical shortages of PPE, including masks, so much so that they often resort to reusing disposable PPE.Thus, there is a critical need for self-disinfecting materials that are capable of broadly (bacteria, viruses, and fungi) protecting patients, medical personnel, and the general public, for prolonged periods of time, that are cost effective, easy to manufacture, and which are available in a variety of form factors (masks, gowns, and surface coverings - including bed rails, tray tables, monitoring equipment, and door handles).  The goal of this STTR Phase I project was to de-risk the development of novel visible light-activated materials with anti-infective properties to combat the escalating threat posed by harmful pathogens responsible for hospital acquired infections (HAIs), but also covering SARS-CoV-2. To date, there are no visible-light photoactive coatings in use in hospitals and related healthcare settings. This is primarily due to a number of misconceptions related to scalability/cost, the incorrect belief that UV light is needed, but also due to manufacturing and production knowledge gaps. To address these issues, we examined the antimicrobial efficacy of a simple bicomponent spray coating composed of the commercially-available UV-photocrosslinkable polymer N-methyl-4(4’-formyl-styryl)pyridinium methosulfate acetal poly(vinyl alcohol) (SbQ-PVA) and one of three aPDI photosensitizers (PSs): zinc-tetra(4-N-methylpyridyl)porphine (ZnTMPyP4+), methylene blue (MB), and Rose Bengal (RB). We applied these photodynamic coatings, collectively termed SbQ-PVA/PS, to a variety of commercially available materials. Scanning electron microscopy (SEM) and time-of-flight secondary ion mass spectrometry (ToF-SIMS) confirmed the successful application of the coatings, while inductively coupled plasma-optical emission spectroscopy (ICP-OES) revealed a photosensitizer loading of 0.09-0.78 nmol PS/mg material. The antimicrobial efficacy of the coated materials was evaluated against methicillin-susceptible Staphylococcus aureus ATCC-29213 and human coronavirus strain HCoV-229E. Upon illumination with visible light (60 min, 400-700 nm, 65&plusmn;5 mW/cm2), the coated materials inactivated S. aureus by 97-99.999% and HCoV-229E by 92-99.999%, depending on the material and PS employed. Photobleaching studies employing HCoV-229E demonstrated detection limit inactivation (99.999%) even after exposure for four weeks to indoor ambient room lighting. Taken together, the results here further confirm that photodynamic spray coatings afford a largely unexplored route to accelerated, effective and comprehensive antimicrobial materials, particularly for their application in reusable self-disinfecting PPE. To-date, and despite their highly potent antimicrobial activity, the adoption of such photoactive materials to reduce infection transmission in hospitals and related healthcare facilities has been hampered by the lack of a scalable and cost-effective means to manufacture them, and high-production methods for producing aPDI-based materials are needed. Here, we have demonstrated that a simple bicomponent spray coating comprised of a photocrosslinkable polymer and a photosensitizer can be applied to a range of commercially available materials used in the public sector. Not only is the spray coating method facile, inexpensive and scalable through the use of off-the-shelf components, it is well suited for expedient integration into existing manufacturing lines that already employ similar UV-curable inks. While further studies examining the launderability and durability of such coatings are needed (as are studies on a wider scope of materials, e.g., polypropylene, more commonly used in PPE), these and other studies suggest that photodynamic spray coatings may be a simple but effective tool for reducing the transmission of pathogens in healthcare settings, thereby adding to the infection-prevention toolbox available to healthcare workers and the general public.       Last Modified: 02/14/2022       Submitted by: Reza A Ghiladi]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
