<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[STTR Phase I:  Nuclear Magnetic Resonance Spectroscopy at Low Magnetic Fields]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>225000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>225000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Benaiah Schrag</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bschrag@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928323</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This Small Business Technology Transfer (STTR) Phase I project will develop a novel method for chemical analysis using nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) spectroscopy at moderate and low magnetic field strengths. A major cost and physical limitation of NMR spectroscopy is the high-field magnet typically required. Although high-field instruments face competition from smaller benchtop-sized instruments, now a $120 million segment of the $1.25 billion NMR market, these moderate-field devices have lower performance, high cost, and lack portability. This project will address these challenges by exploring a new method designed to work in weaker, different magnetic fields produced with cheap, light, portable magnets. This will bring down the cost and expand the NMR market in a broader range of applications in petroleum exploration, refining, and chemical manufacturing; and potentially smaller educational institutions such as high schools. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The intellectual merit of this project is the development of the physical theory behind a new form of NMR spectroscopy and its testing in moderate-field benchtop spectrometers, as well as in low-field regimes where spectroscopic information is currently impossible to acquire. This is made possible by a recently discovered phenomenon called "spin-lock induced crossing" (SLIC), which measures how the system responds to a small rotating magnetic field rather than a strong static field. One goal will be to expand the theoretical understanding of SLIC in order to predict and analyze the unconventional spectra it produces. Other experimental tasks will include exploring the physical specifications necessary for spectrometers to use the technique, evaluating the method's performance compared to conventional NMR spectroscopy, creating a dictionary of low-field spectra for common chemicals, and developing methods for automatic analysis and interpretation of the spectra. The results will be used to develop software for implementing the method on current benchtop instruments and will also provide a basis for the design and translation of low-field spectrometers based solely on these methods.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/16/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/13/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041, 47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2014924</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Matthew</FirstName>
<LastName>Rosen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Matthew Rosen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[msrosen@mgh.harvard.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000631104</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/16/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Stephen</FirstName>
<LastName>DeVience</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Stephen J DeVience</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[sjdevience@gmail.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000814933</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/16/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>SCALAR MAGNETICS, LLC</Name>
<CityName>ELLICOTT CITY</CityName>
<ZipCode>210431925</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3054395955</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>8925 OLD FREDERICK RD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MD03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>QHCRF2D3P7Q1</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SCALAR MAGNETICS LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Athinoula A. Martinos Center for Biomedical Imaging]]></Name>
<CityName>Charlestown</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021292020</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[149 Thirteenth Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1505</Code>
<Text>STTR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>090E</Code>
<Text>Chem/Bio and Physical Diagnostics</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~225000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Scalar Magnetics LLC completed a Phase I STTR project in partnership with Massachusetts General Hospital. A novel form of low-field nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) spectroscopy was investigated in support of the ultimate goal of creating portable, low-cost NMR spectrometers. Technical requirements for the spectrometer, such as magnetic field homogeneity and stability, were determined to be feasible and were within the specifications of the spectrometer available for testing. Signal strength, experiment time, the ability to resolve and identify spectra, and the ability to quantify components of a mixture were all characterized via simulations as well as measurements of chemical samples, and they were found to be acceptable. Spectra were acquired in a few hours with sufficient signal to successfully identify the majority of the chemical samples from a spectral dictionary. In a mixture of three chemicals, their quantities were determined to within 10% of the true value. Further work to improve these results then led to the invention of a new pulse sequence with about 100-fold better sensitivity and less stringent technical requirements.</p> <p>Our low-field method was found to work as well or better than high-field NMR for certain applications. Long-range interactions between spins were more easily detected and measured at low field. Measurements of chemical exchange between alcohol and water, which allows the fraction of water to be measured, was also more easily performed at low field.</p> <p>The project also provided educational opportunities for both a visiting graduate student and an undergraduate summer researcher.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/22/2022<br>      Modified by: Stephen&nbsp;J&nbsp;Devience</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Scalar Magnetics LLC completed a Phase I STTR project in partnership with Massachusetts General Hospital. A novel form of low-field nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) spectroscopy was investigated in support of the ultimate goal of creating portable, low-cost NMR spectrometers. Technical requirements for the spectrometer, such as magnetic field homogeneity and stability, were determined to be feasible and were within the specifications of the spectrometer available for testing. Signal strength, experiment time, the ability to resolve and identify spectra, and the ability to quantify components of a mixture were all characterized via simulations as well as measurements of chemical samples, and they were found to be acceptable. Spectra were acquired in a few hours with sufficient signal to successfully identify the majority of the chemical samples from a spectral dictionary. In a mixture of three chemicals, their quantities were determined to within 10% of the true value. Further work to improve these results then led to the invention of a new pulse sequence with about 100-fold better sensitivity and less stringent technical requirements.  Our low-field method was found to work as well or better than high-field NMR for certain applications. Long-range interactions between spins were more easily detected and measured at low field. Measurements of chemical exchange between alcohol and water, which allows the fraction of water to be measured, was also more easily performed at low field.  The project also provided educational opportunities for both a visiting graduate student and an undergraduate summer researcher.       Last Modified: 09/22/2022       Submitted by: Stephen J Devience]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
