<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Engineering probiotic yeast to treat hyperuricemia and gout]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>224840.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>244840</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Erik Pierstorff</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>epiersto@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922165</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project will be the development of an engineered probiotic as an treatment for hyperuricemia and gout. Acute gout episodes cause debilitating pain and hypersensitivity, seriously impairing mobility. Over time, joint damage and deformity, chronic usage-related pain, and disfigurement follow. Although gout can be treated by drugs that lower uric acid levels, these drugs have significant drawbacks for many patients: they have limited effectiveness, are associated with serious side effects, and may be expensive. Gout patients experience an estimated increase of 5 absence days annually with an incremental cost of $3,000 per patient. The 9.2 million gout patients in the USA spend more than $1.3 billion per year on gout drugs. Moreover, roughly half take additional supplements. The proposed project will develop a novel probiotic strain to address hyperuricemia.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project will advance hyperuricemia treatment using an engineered probiotic. The proposed treatment is based on the observation that enzymatically degrading uric acid in the intestine reduces serum uric acid levels, unlike conventional treatments targeting the circulatory system, the urinary tract, or function systemically. This project will use genetic screening to identify a probiotic strain to break down uric acid, engineering it to prevent gene mobility across species and avoid transfer of antibiotic resistance to the intestinal microbiome. Finally, we will confirm safety and efficacy in a mouse model of hyperuricemia.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/06/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/26/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041, 47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2014679</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Christoph</FirstName>
<LastName>Geisler</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Christoph Geisler</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[christoph@unlocked-labs.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000817075</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/06/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>UNLOCKED LABS INC.</Name>
<CityName>LARAMIE</CityName>
<ZipCode>820723037</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3073401616</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1938 EAST HARNEY STREET, SUITE 2</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wyoming</StateName>
<StateCode>WY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WY00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>HE5AH1LKAUA3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNLOCKED LABS INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[THERANEUTRICS LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>Laramie</CityName>
<StateCode>WY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>820723037</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1938 Harney Street STE 247]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wyoming</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WY00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8091</Code>
<Text>SBIR Outreach &amp; Tech. Assist</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>144E</Code>
<Text>Synthetic biology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8038</Code>
<Text>Biotechnology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~224840</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~20000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Background:&nbsp;</strong>Uric acid is the end product of purine catabolism in humans. Purines include adenine and guanine, which can be found in DNA, RNA, ATP, and many other biological molecules. In mammals other than great apes, the poorly soluble uric acid is further processed into highly soluble allantoin. Humans cannot convert uric acid into allantoin because of the evolutionary loss of the enzymes involved in this pathway. As a result, humans have much higher urate levels than other animals. As uric acid is poorly soluble, it forms needle-sharp crystals when levels exceed the solubility threshold ? thus causing gout. In humans, about two-thirds of uric acid is excreted through the urine, and about a third is biodegraded by bacteria in the GI tract.</p> <p><strong>Outcome of the research project:&nbsp;</strong>Phase I focused on developing probiotic microbes with an enhanced ability to biodegrade uric acid, in order to reduce serum uric acid levels by removing uric acid through the GI tract. Specifically, the goals of the Phase I project - all of which were met or exceeded - were (1) to optimize a probiotic yeast strain engineered to break down uric acid, and (2) to obtain a preliminary assessment of <em>in vivo</em> efficacy in a hyperuricemic mouse model. Building on Phase I success, the ultimate SBIR project goal is to develop, validate, and commercialize such probiotics for human use.</p> <p><strong>Intellectual merits:&nbsp;</strong>The intestine has an underused potential for uric acid elimination. Our novel and innovative approach to treating hyperuricemia is designed to take advantage of this potential by using hardy probiotics engineered to break down uric acid in the intestine. Use of the intestine as a biological compartment for uric acid degradation sets our approach apart from conventional treatments, which target the circulatory system, the urinary tract, or function systemically. Importantly, the emerging concept of using engineered microbes to biodegrade small molecules in the intestine as a viable therapeutic approach has recently been gaining traction.</p> <p><strong>Broader impacts:&nbsp;</strong>Unlocked Labs? probiotic strains offer the potential for broader societal and economic benefit by advancing the health and welfare of the American public. Specifically, there are 9.2 million gout patients in the US alone, and a total of 45 million US Americans with hyperuricemia, who are at risk of gout and urate kidney stones. These patients will directly benefit from our innovative approach towards using probiotics for serum urate levels reduction.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/17/2022<br>      Modified by: Christoph&nbsp;Geisler</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Background: Uric acid is the end product of purine catabolism in humans. Purines include adenine and guanine, which can be found in DNA, RNA, ATP, and many other biological molecules. In mammals other than great apes, the poorly soluble uric acid is further processed into highly soluble allantoin. Humans cannot convert uric acid into allantoin because of the evolutionary loss of the enzymes involved in this pathway. As a result, humans have much higher urate levels than other animals. As uric acid is poorly soluble, it forms needle-sharp crystals when levels exceed the solubility threshold ? thus causing gout. In humans, about two-thirds of uric acid is excreted through the urine, and about a third is biodegraded by bacteria in the GI tract.  Outcome of the research project: Phase I focused on developing probiotic microbes with an enhanced ability to biodegrade uric acid, in order to reduce serum uric acid levels by removing uric acid through the GI tract. Specifically, the goals of the Phase I project - all of which were met or exceeded - were (1) to optimize a probiotic yeast strain engineered to break down uric acid, and (2) to obtain a preliminary assessment of in vivo efficacy in a hyperuricemic mouse model. Building on Phase I success, the ultimate SBIR project goal is to develop, validate, and commercialize such probiotics for human use.  Intellectual merits: The intestine has an underused potential for uric acid elimination. Our novel and innovative approach to treating hyperuricemia is designed to take advantage of this potential by using hardy probiotics engineered to break down uric acid in the intestine. Use of the intestine as a biological compartment for uric acid degradation sets our approach apart from conventional treatments, which target the circulatory system, the urinary tract, or function systemically. Importantly, the emerging concept of using engineered microbes to biodegrade small molecules in the intestine as a viable therapeutic approach has recently been gaining traction.  Broader impacts: Unlocked Labs? probiotic strains offer the potential for broader societal and economic benefit by advancing the health and welfare of the American public. Specifically, there are 9.2 million gout patients in the US alone, and a total of 45 million US Americans with hyperuricemia, who are at risk of gout and urate kidney stones. These patients will directly benefit from our innovative approach towards using probiotics for serum urate levels reduction.       Last Modified: 10/17/2022       Submitted by: Christoph Geisler]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
