<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Model Independent Interpretations of Precision Measurement and Data Utility Preservation with SMEFT]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>45000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>45000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Keith Dienes</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kdienes@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925314</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This award funds the research activities of Professor William Shepherd at Sam Houston State University.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Large Hadron Collider (LHC) is the highest-energy experiment in fundamental physics ever built, and it is producing copious amounts of data and highly precise measurements of the properties of the known elementary particles.  A significant international investment has already been made in its planning and construction, and it is now important that we ensure that we learn as much as we can from the data taken there.  In his research, Professor Shepherd aims to develop tools and techniques to interpret LHC and other fundamental physics measurements within as broad a scope as possible, without needing to refer to one specific model.  As such, these tools will make such measurements easier to interpret in new models which have yet to be invented, thereby preserving and enhancing the utility of this data for the future.  Research in this area advances the national interest by maximizing our understanding of fundamental physical law.  This research also has significant broader impacts, most importantly in the mentoring and involvement of undergraduate students in the process of frontier scientific research.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;More technically, Professor Shepherd will study the Standard Model Effective Field Theory (SMEFT), which encodes in a new perturbation series in inverse new-particle masses all of the possible effects of new physics which are too heavy to probe directly. The SMEFT gives a valuable dictionary for discussing what deviations can be expected from the Standard Model (SM) predictions in such cases, and importantly is valid at all lower energies as well, thereby allowing the complete integration of lower-energy, high-precision measurements such as flavor-changing processes, SM-forbidden processes, and precise measurements of, e.g., parity-violating scattering at low energies.  This work importantly includes theoretical uncertainties inherent in the SMEFT treatment, which enables the bounds derived to be straightforwardly applied to new physics models without the caveats often needed for previous EFT approaches to new physics. This project will build out the number of observables which have been consistently calculated including these errors, design searches which are more sensitive to SMEFT effects and more robust against the theoretical errors, and ultimately contribute significantly to global fits of the full SMEFT parameter space, which have the potential to serve as a successor to the precision Electroweak data encoded into usable pseudo-observables by the LEP ElectroWeak Working Group.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/24/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/20/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2014103</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>William</FirstName>
<LastName>Shepherd</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>William Shepherd</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[shepherd@shsu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000813452</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/24/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Sam Houston State University</Name>
<CityName>HUNTSVILLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>773410001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9362943621</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1806 AVE J</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>DJPXLZAE9931</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SAM HOUSTON STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Sam Houston State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Huntsville</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>773412448</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[P O Box 2448]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1286</Code>
<Text>Elem. Particle Physics/Theory</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~45000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The major research goals of this project are to develop and promote model-independent understandings of LHC searches using the Standard Model Effective Field Theory (SMEFT) and to explore tools for collider searches utilizing more subtle signatures at the LHC. In particular, SMEFT studies are intended to explore the impact of higher-order-in-EFT uncertainties on the appropriate interpretation of these searches for new physics.</p> <p>Broader impact goals of this project are dominated by student research opportunity provisioning. Research articles which have sufficiently narrow and well-defined tasks for undergraduate students to contribute to are to be chosen to include student researchers, providing training in the true nature of research, career development and grad school applications boosts as well as the opportunity to partially fund their undergraduate education through education-related work activities rather than needing to have a 'side hustle' to pay their tuition and rent.</p> <p>I produced two research articles while funded by this grant, including one which was coauthored by three current or former SHSU undergraduate students. Significant student involvement was achieved in the SMEFT research of this project, and a software and student training pipeline was established to maintain those important contributions going forward.</p> <p>Students were also enabled to present their research at the annual Pheno conference, providing them with contact with world-leading researchers in the field and developing their profiles and self-confidence in their abilities and research contributions.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/16/2021<br>      Modified by: William&nbsp;Shepherd</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The major research goals of this project are to develop and promote model-independent understandings of LHC searches using the Standard Model Effective Field Theory (SMEFT) and to explore tools for collider searches utilizing more subtle signatures at the LHC. In particular, SMEFT studies are intended to explore the impact of higher-order-in-EFT uncertainties on the appropriate interpretation of these searches for new physics.  Broader impact goals of this project are dominated by student research opportunity provisioning. Research articles which have sufficiently narrow and well-defined tasks for undergraduate students to contribute to are to be chosen to include student researchers, providing training in the true nature of research, career development and grad school applications boosts as well as the opportunity to partially fund their undergraduate education through education-related work activities rather than needing to have a 'side hustle' to pay their tuition and rent.  I produced two research articles while funded by this grant, including one which was coauthored by three current or former SHSU undergraduate students. Significant student involvement was achieved in the SMEFT research of this project, and a software and student training pipeline was established to maintain those important contributions going forward.  Students were also enabled to present their research at the annual Pheno conference, providing them with contact with world-leading researchers in the field and developing their profiles and self-confidence in their abilities and research contributions.       Last Modified: 09/16/2021       Submitted by: William Shepherd]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
