<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Non-mechanical harvesting of wind energy]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>225000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>225000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rajesh Mehta</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rmehta@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922174</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is to advance a technology for converting wind energy into electrical power.  Wind turbines need massive support structures, generate noise, require ongoing maintenance, and negatively impact some wildlife. This project will advance a method to harvest the wind’s energy using novel transformers requiring no moving components. Current estimates indicate that this approach to electrical power generation would require less maintenance, lower costs, and have lower environmental impact.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This SBIR Phase I project will advance electrostatic generation of wind power. The proposed design of the power generator creates negative air ions by coronal emission.   As the wind carries negative ions away from the power generator, the latter is left with net positive charge and a large positive voltage relative to the ground.  The proposed project will explore the trade space of wind-to-electricity transformers at scale.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/21/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/21/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2014674</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
<LastName>Epstein</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Richard Epstein</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[richard.epstein@gmail.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000549786</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/21/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>ThermoDynamic Films</Name>
<CityName>SANTA FE</CityName>
<ZipCode>875054639</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5053101224</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1313 MADRID RD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Mexico</StateName>
<StateCode>NM</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NM03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>J4DFFD9J7AU6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>THERMODYNAMIC FILMS LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[ThermoDynamic Films]]></Name>
<CityName>Santa Fe</CityName>
<StateCode>NM</StateCode>
<ZipCode>875054639</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1313 Madrid Rd]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Mexico</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NM03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8035</Code>
<Text>Hardware Devices</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~225000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This Phase I NSF SBIR support has helped ThermoDynamic Films, LLC (TDF) develop Solid-State Wind Energy to Electricity Transformers (SSWEETs), which produce electrical power with no moving parts or fluids, other than the wind. Engineering and cost estimates indicate that when SSWEET-based power generation is scaled up to commercial powers, it will be much more economical than traditional wind-turbine energy generation and have less negative environmental impact. Since SSWEETs have no moving components, they would require little maintenance and would not generate noise. They have less visual impact than wind turbines and do not endanger birds and other wildlife.</p> <p>A SSWEET installation creates negative air ions by coronal emission. The wind carries the ions away from SSWEET thereby generating currents and large voltages.&nbsp; The charged ions eventually settle to ground, and the SSWEET harvests the wind-induced power as the charges return to the SSWEET from the ground to complete the circuit.</p> <p>TDF built a scalable SSWEET wind farm &nbsp;to address the important question of how the power scales with the size of the system. This issue must be addressed experimentally because of the complexity of the SSWEET power generation in the real-world. For example, the negative ions produced in one part of the wind farm may be captured by the attractors elsewhere in the setup.</p> <p>The work carried out in this Phase I program developed the groundwork for understanding the power scaling and economics of Solid-State Wind Energy to Electricity Transformers. TDF will use its own funds to complete this exploratory work. If the conclusions of the research are promising, TDF will seek investor support to further advance this technology.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/22/2021<br>      Modified by: Richard&nbsp;Epstein</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This Phase I NSF SBIR support has helped ThermoDynamic Films, LLC (TDF) develop Solid-State Wind Energy to Electricity Transformers (SSWEETs), which produce electrical power with no moving parts or fluids, other than the wind. Engineering and cost estimates indicate that when SSWEET-based power generation is scaled up to commercial powers, it will be much more economical than traditional wind-turbine energy generation and have less negative environmental impact. Since SSWEETs have no moving components, they would require little maintenance and would not generate noise. They have less visual impact than wind turbines and do not endanger birds and other wildlife.  A SSWEET installation creates negative air ions by coronal emission. The wind carries the ions away from SSWEET thereby generating currents and large voltages.  The charged ions eventually settle to ground, and the SSWEET harvests the wind-induced power as the charges return to the SSWEET from the ground to complete the circuit.  TDF built a scalable SSWEET wind farm  to address the important question of how the power scales with the size of the system. This issue must be addressed experimentally because of the complexity of the SSWEET power generation in the real-world. For example, the negative ions produced in one part of the wind farm may be captured by the attractors elsewhere in the setup.  The work carried out in this Phase I program developed the groundwork for understanding the power scaling and economics of Solid-State Wind Energy to Electricity Transformers. TDF will use its own funds to complete this exploratory work. If the conclusions of the research are promising, TDF will seek investor support to further advance this technology.          Last Modified: 12/22/2021       Submitted by: Richard Epstein]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
