<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[STTR Phase I:  Continuous Manufacturing of Mechanically-Robust, Superinsulating Aerogel Monoliths and Thin Films via a New Ambient-Pressure Freeze Drying Technology]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>224557.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>224557</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rajesh Mehta</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rmehta@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922174</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Technology Transfer (STTR) Phase I project is to enable affordable manufacturing process for aerogel, an ultralight structural material that can reduce the fuel consumption and emissions of cars, planes, and rockets.  Aerogels are a class of ultralight materials exhibiting unparalleled thermal insulation, soundproofing, and energy-absorbing properties.  New structurally-durable aerogels can serve as ultralight alternatives to plastics with potential applications in vehicle lightweighting, energy-efficient buildings, and ultralight armor. The proposed work facilitates transitioning these materials to applications and reducing operating costs, reliance on typical fuels, and emissions in the transportation and construction sectors. It will also benefit artificial tissue scaffolds, apparel, bulletproof vests, and energy storage.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This STTR Phase I project will advance the translation of aerogels.  Manufacturing monolithic aerogels is currently challenging and expensive because of high-pressure batch processing. The proposed work will develop a first-of-its-kind, potentially continuous, accelerated atmospheric-pressure freeze drying technology to enable cost-efficient manufacturing of monolithic polymer-based aerogels of unlimited dimensions.  This will require a multidisciplinary approach integrating freeze drying, fluid physics, and nanoporous media in which jet impingement arrays will be used to achieve drying rates approaching a vacuum-based process without requiring a vacuum or pressure chamber. The research will focus on mass transfer phenomena related to removal of solvent from sol-gel-derived nanoporous gel media without damaging the gel's delicate skeletal framework. The research plan includes fluid flow modeling and experiments to demonstrate process feasibility for large-scale translation.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/16/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/26/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041, 47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2014881</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Stephen</FirstName>
<LastName>Steiner</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME>III</PI_SUFX_NAME>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Stephen Steiner</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ssteiner@aerogeltechnologies.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000646378</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/16/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Aerogel Technologies, LLC</Name>
<CityName>MILWAUKEE</CityName>
<ZipCode>532174118</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4149440019</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1001 W BRENTWOOD LN</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WI04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>J2R9F74X27G6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>AEROGEL TECHNOLOGIES LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Aerogel Technologies, LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>Boston</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021362196</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1 WESTINGHOUSE PLAZA, D157]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1505</Code>
<Text>STTR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8029</Code>
<Text>Manufacturing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~224557</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The objective of this STTR Phase I project was to enable an affordable manufacturing process for aerogel, an ultralight insulating material. Specifically, structurally-durable aerogels produced by Aerogel Technologies, which can reduce the fuel consumption and emissions of vehicles, and enable emerging technologies and novel designs in cars, planes, and rockets. Aerogels are a class of ultralight materials exhibiting unparalleled thermal insulation, soundproofing, and energy-absorbing properties. New structurally-durable aerogels can serve as ultralight alternatives to plastics with potential applications in vehicle lightweighting, energy-efficient buildings, and ultralight armor. Manufacturing of monolithic aerogels has historically been challenging and expensive because of the high-pressure batch processing required.&nbsp; Prior to this grant, Aerogel Technologies discovered an alternative method for manufacturing polymer aerogels via a new ambient-pressure freeze-drying process.&nbsp; In this STTR between Aerogel Technologies and Tufts University, we sought to advance this new ambient-pressure freeze-drying technology in support of improving the scalability and enabling continuous roll-to-roll manufacturing of superinsulating aerogel materials as well as nanoporous materials of all sorts.</p> <p>In our STTR Phase I grant, Aerogel Technologies and Tufts University achieved four objectives towards this goal.&nbsp; 1) We constructed, commissioned, and utilized a drying system to demonstrate a ~75% reduction of the time required to produce aerogels by ambient-pressure freeze drying. 2) We completed the development of an apparatus at Tufts and used it to measure the permeability of aerogels, an essential parameter necessary to model the freeze-drying process. 3) We developed a preliminary model of the freeze-drying process. 4) We designed, constructed, and a tested a pilot-scale manufacturing module capable of producing 2' x 4' aerogel panels using accelerated ambient-pressure freeze drying.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/29/2022<br>      Modified by: Stephen&nbsp;Steiner</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The objective of this STTR Phase I project was to enable an affordable manufacturing process for aerogel, an ultralight insulating material. Specifically, structurally-durable aerogels produced by Aerogel Technologies, which can reduce the fuel consumption and emissions of vehicles, and enable emerging technologies and novel designs in cars, planes, and rockets. Aerogels are a class of ultralight materials exhibiting unparalleled thermal insulation, soundproofing, and energy-absorbing properties. New structurally-durable aerogels can serve as ultralight alternatives to plastics with potential applications in vehicle lightweighting, energy-efficient buildings, and ultralight armor. Manufacturing of monolithic aerogels has historically been challenging and expensive because of the high-pressure batch processing required.  Prior to this grant, Aerogel Technologies discovered an alternative method for manufacturing polymer aerogels via a new ambient-pressure freeze-drying process.  In this STTR between Aerogel Technologies and Tufts University, we sought to advance this new ambient-pressure freeze-drying technology in support of improving the scalability and enabling continuous roll-to-roll manufacturing of superinsulating aerogel materials as well as nanoporous materials of all sorts.  In our STTR Phase I grant, Aerogel Technologies and Tufts University achieved four objectives towards this goal.  1) We constructed, commissioned, and utilized a drying system to demonstrate a ~75% reduction of the time required to produce aerogels by ambient-pressure freeze drying. 2) We completed the development of an apparatus at Tufts and used it to measure the permeability of aerogels, an essential parameter necessary to model the freeze-drying process. 3) We developed a preliminary model of the freeze-drying process. 4) We designed, constructed, and a tested a pilot-scale manufacturing module capable of producing 2' x 4' aerogel panels using accelerated ambient-pressure freeze drying.       Last Modified: 08/29/2022       Submitted by: Stephen Steiner]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
