<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[STTR Phase I:  SynchronyGamma – A Music-Based Intervention for Alzheimer’s and MCI]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>224846.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>224846</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Alastair Monk</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>amonk@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924392</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader/commercial impact of this Small Business Technology Transfer (STTR) Phase I project is to address age-related cognitive impairments. Neurodegenerative disorders are a rapidly growing public-health concern, with Alzheimer’s disease alone projected to affect 13.8 million Americans by 2050. Alzheimer’s disease patients undergo gradual cognitive decline and during this progression, patients experience multiple pain points, including memory loss, executive function deficits, and depression. Early intervention in the mild impairment stage may assist in delaying cognitive decline. While pharmacological interventions for Alzheimer’s disease have primarily targeted biological markers such as amyloid-Beta plaques, these strategies have shown limited success in improving outcomes. The proposed device consists of a novel therapy for cognitive impairment conditions through a device that stimulates the brain via music and lights.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Technology Transfer (STTR) Phase I project will result in a digital-health device that non-invasively drives Gamma-frequency neural activity in the brain to improve memory and cognition in aging individuals suffering from Mild Cognitive Impairment and Alzheimer’s disease. The digital-health device is based on neural network technology that models the dynamics of rhythmic brain activity. In clinical populations who have disruptions in brain rhythms, i.e., patients with Alzheimer’s disease or Mild Cognitive Impairment, we hypothesize that these technologies can help restore normal brain activity important for memory and cognition. This project will: 1) optimize the technology by integrating multiple Gamma-frequency parameters into a flexible neural network model for musical beat detection, and 2) determine how the device impacts neural activity and cognitive abilities in aging adults with Mild Cognitive Impairment and Alzheimer’s disease.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/29/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/29/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2014870</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ji Chul</FirstName>
<LastName>Kim</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ji Chul Kim</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jichul.kim@oscilloscape.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000816987</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/29/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Psyche</FirstName>
<LastName>Loui</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Psyche Loui</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[p.loui@northeastern.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000803144</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/29/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>OSCILLOSCAPE, LLC</Name>
<CityName>FARMINGTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>060321913</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5617060863</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>400 FARMINGTON AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CT05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>CPDCLG55B5Z3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OSCILLOSCAPE LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>WJEDSPWV7CN7</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[OSCILLOSCAPE, LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>Farmington</CityName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>060321913</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[400 Farmington Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CT05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1505</Code>
<Text>STTR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8033</Code>
<Text>Hardware Software Integration</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~224846</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Neurodegenerative disorders are a rapidly growing public-health concern, with Alzheimer's disease (AD) alone projected to affect 13.8 million Americans by 2050. AD patients undergo gradual cognitive decline, with mild cognitive impairment (MCI) being an early stage of the disorder. During this progression, patients experience multiple symptoms, including memory loss, executive function deficits, and depression. While there is no known cure for AD, several invasive drug-based treatments are available. These treatments do not stop, but can slow AD from progressing and improve the conditions of patients and their caregivers. However, drug-based interventions have yielded limited success: for instance, a recent pharmacological intervention that targeted amyloid-Beta (A&beta;) plaques in the brain, a biomarker of AD, failed to improve cognitive outcomes in AD patients. Moreover, drug-based interventions can have deleterious effects, such as diarrhea, nausea, loss of appetite, and sleep disturbances. Thus, there is an urgent need to develop effective non-invasive therapies, those without undesirable side-effects, to treat AD and related disorders. Early intervention in the MCI stage may reduce or even reverse cognitive decline.</p> <p>Neuroscience research has shown that rhythmic brain activity enables communication within and between brain areas. Healthy brain rhythms enable perception, attention, memory, and cognition; they develop over the lifespan and are reduced in aging, especially in dementia. The ability to causally control brain rhythms--through a process called neural entrainment--may have crucial implications for healthy neurocognitive aging. Importantly, rhythms in the theta and gamma frequency ranges underlie memory and cognition. Recent findings have shown that gamma-frequency neural entrainment may improve memory and cognition and reduce amyloid-Beta (A&beta;) plaques in the brain. Recent research has also shown that musical rhythms are a powerful stimulus for neural entrainment. Such findings offer an exciting avenue towards non-invasive sensory interventions.</p> <p>In this Small Business Technology Transfer (STTR) Phase I project we took the first critical steps toward developing a scientifically validated, music-based therapeutic to address Alzheimer's disease and related dementias. First, using patented neural network technology to model the dynamics of rhythmic brain activity, we designed a device to non-invasively drive theta- and gamma-frequency neural activity with a combination of music and synchronized light. Our approach individualizes rhythmic brain stimulation, by tuning a rhythmic visual stimulus to patient-selected music. Next, we ran preclinical proof-of-concept / microdosing studies in cognitively normal younger and older adults. Our studies successfully demonstrated the ability to entrain cortical theta and gamma oscillations with the combination of music and synchronized light. We showed that increased gamma synchrony persists after one 30-minute session. We also found evidence that music listening with <em>SynchronyGamma</em> may improve working performance memory in older adults. Phase II will focus on improving our ability to entrain brain activity and improve memory and cognition in individuals suffering from Mild Cognitive Impairment (MCI) and Alzheimer's disease (AD). For clinical populations who have disruptions in brain rhythms, i.e. patients with AD or MCI, we hypothesize that regular use of this therapy will restore the normal rhythmic brain activity important for memory and cognition.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/29/2021<br>      Modified by: Ji Chul&nbsp;Kim</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Neurodegenerative disorders are a rapidly growing public-health concern, with Alzheimer's disease (AD) alone projected to affect 13.8 million Americans by 2050. AD patients undergo gradual cognitive decline, with mild cognitive impairment (MCI) being an early stage of the disorder. During this progression, patients experience multiple symptoms, including memory loss, executive function deficits, and depression. While there is no known cure for AD, several invasive drug-based treatments are available. These treatments do not stop, but can slow AD from progressing and improve the conditions of patients and their caregivers. However, drug-based interventions have yielded limited success: for instance, a recent pharmacological intervention that targeted amyloid-Beta (A&beta;) plaques in the brain, a biomarker of AD, failed to improve cognitive outcomes in AD patients. Moreover, drug-based interventions can have deleterious effects, such as diarrhea, nausea, loss of appetite, and sleep disturbances. Thus, there is an urgent need to develop effective non-invasive therapies, those without undesirable side-effects, to treat AD and related disorders. Early intervention in the MCI stage may reduce or even reverse cognitive decline.  Neuroscience research has shown that rhythmic brain activity enables communication within and between brain areas. Healthy brain rhythms enable perception, attention, memory, and cognition; they develop over the lifespan and are reduced in aging, especially in dementia. The ability to causally control brain rhythms--through a process called neural entrainment--may have crucial implications for healthy neurocognitive aging. Importantly, rhythms in the theta and gamma frequency ranges underlie memory and cognition. Recent findings have shown that gamma-frequency neural entrainment may improve memory and cognition and reduce amyloid-Beta (A&beta;) plaques in the brain. Recent research has also shown that musical rhythms are a powerful stimulus for neural entrainment. Such findings offer an exciting avenue towards non-invasive sensory interventions.  In this Small Business Technology Transfer (STTR) Phase I project we took the first critical steps toward developing a scientifically validated, music-based therapeutic to address Alzheimer's disease and related dementias. First, using patented neural network technology to model the dynamics of rhythmic brain activity, we designed a device to non-invasively drive theta- and gamma-frequency neural activity with a combination of music and synchronized light. Our approach individualizes rhythmic brain stimulation, by tuning a rhythmic visual stimulus to patient-selected music. Next, we ran preclinical proof-of-concept / microdosing studies in cognitively normal younger and older adults. Our studies successfully demonstrated the ability to entrain cortical theta and gamma oscillations with the combination of music and synchronized light. We showed that increased gamma synchrony persists after one 30-minute session. We also found evidence that music listening with SynchronyGamma may improve working performance memory in older adults. Phase II will focus on improving our ability to entrain brain activity and improve memory and cognition in individuals suffering from Mild Cognitive Impairment (MCI) and Alzheimer's disease (AD). For clinical populations who have disruptions in brain rhythms, i.e. patients with AD or MCI, we hypothesize that regular use of this therapy will restore the normal rhythmic brain activity important for memory and cognition.       Last Modified: 12/29/2021       Submitted by: Ji Chul Kim]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
