<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Imprints of New Physics on Cosmological Observations]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>240000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>240000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Keith Dienes</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kdienes@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925314</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This award funds the research activities of Professor Savvas M. Koushiappas at Brown University. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Most of the matter in the universe takes the form of a mysterious "dark matter" which is unlike the familiar matter we deal with in our everyday lives.  In the last few years, cosmological observations and laboratory constraints have shown that the nature of this dark matter remains elusive.  Likewise, there have been many challenges to our understanding of the basic characteristics of the universe itself.  As part of his research, Professor Koushiappas will attempt to understand the nature of dark matter and dark energy, explore new possible interactions between dark matter and regular matter, and attempt to study the cosmological and gravitational effects of dark-matter properties.  As a result, research in this area advances the national interest by promoting the progress of science in one of its most fundamental questions: the discovery and understanding of physical laws. This project is also envisioned to have significant broader impacts. Professor Koushiappas will involve graduate students and advanced undergraduate students in this research, thereby providing critical training for junior physicists beginning research in this field. He will also give public lectures on his research results. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;More technically, Professor Koushiappas will establish a research program to unite theoretical studies of the physics of dark matter with current and future cosmological observations. Bridging the gap between cosmology, astrophysics, and particle physics, Professor Koushiappas will use observations of the cosmic microwave background, the growth of structure and high-energy photons and other energetic particles to tackle fundamental questions about the nature of dark matter, the origin of the discrepancy in the accelerated expansion rate of the universe, the astrophysical effects of cosmology, and most importantly the interplay and connections between these different lines of inquiry. These goals will be achieved through sophisticated theoretical modeling and through the use of new and existing statistical and analysis tools.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/17/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/20/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2014052</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Savvas</FirstName>
<LastName>Koushiappas</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Savvas M Koushiappas</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[Savvas_Koushiappas@brown.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000512205</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/17/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Brown University</Name>
<CityName>PROVIDENCE</CityName>
<ZipCode>029129127</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4018632777</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1 PROSPECT ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>RI01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>E3FDXZ6TBHW3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>BROWN UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>E3FDXZ6TBHW3</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Brown University]]></Name>
<CityName>Providence</CityName>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>029129002</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[BOX 1929]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>RI01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1288</Code>
<Text>Particle Astrophysics &amp; Cosmol</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7483</Code>
<Text>PHYSICS OF THE UNIVERSE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~240000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
