<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Nanocomposite Ionomers and Proton Exchange Membranes]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>225000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>225000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rajesh Mehta</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rmehta@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922174</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact of this SBIR Phase I project advances the translation of hydrogen technologies in heavy duty and ultra-duty applications. The hydrogen economy could generate an estimated $2.5 T in economic value in the manufacturing, transportation, energy storage, and building energy, sectors.  Current membranes that require high humidity levels and low temperatures for operation complicates fuel cell thermal and water management components in heavy duty fuel cell systems. The proposed solution advances the development of a new membrane serving as a drop-in replacement to enable low humidity and elevated operating temperatures.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This SBIR Phase I project will use porous polymer supports to translate a nanocomposite material that exhibits both low humidity and elevated temperature proton conductivity into a standardized solution for a proton exchange membranes. Furthermore, the composite materials will be added at high volume fractions to confer additional benefits in mechanical stability and lower gas permeability. The project activities include material translation into supported membranes, membrane composite formulation optimization, measurements of key membrane properties, and demonstration in a fuel cell stack. If successful, the project would yield new proton exchange membranes that enable operation under low humidity – elevated temperature conditions to simplify fuel cell systems while extending system durability.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/15/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/28/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2014453</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gary</FirstName>
<LastName>Ong</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>K</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gary K Ong</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[garyong@celadynetech.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000792976</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/15/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>CELADYNE TECHNOLOGIES, INC.</Name>
<CityName>WILLOWBROOK</CityName>
<ZipCode>605273918</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5126451634</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>162 MACARTHUR DR APT 5313</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>MJHMMMLMFGN9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CELADYNE TECHNOLOGIES, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Argonne National Laboratory]]></Name>
<CityName>Lemont</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>604394801</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[9700 S Cass Ave.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8029</Code>
<Text>Manufacturing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~225000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Intellectual Merit</span></strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">:</span> This Small Business Innovation Research Phase 1 project developed nanocomposite ionomers and proton exchange membranes that can unlock simplified and more efficient fuel cells. In this work, Celadyne developed nanocomposite ceramic &ndash; polymer composites that exhibit proton conductivity at low humidity &ndash; elevated temperature conditions. Celadyne showed that this approach can be used to achieve conductivities that are comparable to the state of the art conductivity of 0.1 S/cm or higher that persist at elevated temperatures and low humidity. The high loading of ceramics in the material also reduces hydrogen crossover in the material significantly. As part of this work, the membrane was also integrated with conventional gas diffusion layers to show preliminary performance of the membrane in a fuel cell configuration.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Broader/Commercial Impact:</span></strong> This work directly enables the hydrogen economy, which the Hydrogen Council estimates will generate 2.5 trillion in economic value and 30 million new jobs. When used in the combined sectors of manufacturing, transportation, energy storage, and building energy, hydrogen can serve as a multi-purpose fuel to negate 6 Gt of global CO<sub>2</sub> emissions. Fuel cells are necessary to convert hydrogen into usable energy in transportation, and stationary power applications. Specific to the former, performance improvements in efficiency and durability along with a reduction in size can allow product diversification of fuel cells to decrease price and encourage the adoption of hydrogen as fuel. Realizing new nanocomposite membrane concepts will also spur applied and basic research on ion transport in heterogeneous systems.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/29/2022<br>      Modified by: Gary&nbsp;K&nbsp;Ong</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Intellectual Merit: This Small Business Innovation Research Phase 1 project developed nanocomposite ionomers and proton exchange membranes that can unlock simplified and more efficient fuel cells. In this work, Celadyne developed nanocomposite ceramic &ndash; polymer composites that exhibit proton conductivity at low humidity &ndash; elevated temperature conditions. Celadyne showed that this approach can be used to achieve conductivities that are comparable to the state of the art conductivity of 0.1 S/cm or higher that persist at elevated temperatures and low humidity. The high loading of ceramics in the material also reduces hydrogen crossover in the material significantly. As part of this work, the membrane was also integrated with conventional gas diffusion layers to show preliminary performance of the membrane in a fuel cell configuration.     Broader/Commercial Impact: This work directly enables the hydrogen economy, which the Hydrogen Council estimates will generate 2.5 trillion in economic value and 30 million new jobs. When used in the combined sectors of manufacturing, transportation, energy storage, and building energy, hydrogen can serve as a multi-purpose fuel to negate 6 Gt of global CO2 emissions. Fuel cells are necessary to convert hydrogen into usable energy in transportation, and stationary power applications. Specific to the former, performance improvements in efficiency and durability along with a reduction in size can allow product diversification of fuel cells to decrease price and encourage the adoption of hydrogen as fuel. Realizing new nanocomposite membrane concepts will also spur applied and basic research on ion transport in heterogeneous systems.       Last Modified: 08/29/2022       Submitted by: Gary K Ong]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
