<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[STTR Phase I: Active Transport of Caffeine through a Blood-Brain Barrier Model]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>225000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>225000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Erik Pierstorff</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>epiersto@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922165</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact of this Small Business Technology Transfer (STTR) Phase I project is to create a drug-discovery platform that will screen quickly and early in the process for candidate therapeutics that can enter the central nervous system (CNS). The goal is to minimize the lengthy and expensive clinical trials that ultimately fail because of their failure to enter the BBB by providing a high assurance that the drug can pass the blood/brain barrier (BBB). The project will facilitate discovering next-generation interventional treatments for serious brain-related diseases and will greatly benefit patients and families fighting debilitating diseases that are difficult or impossible to treat with current methods.  The ability to screen for BBB penetration early is needed. An estimated 2% of small drug molecules and no large molecules are able to pass into CNS to treat neurodegenerative diseases, multiple sclerosis and strokes, accounting for 12% of total global deaths. Each of these diseases represents a major healthcare cost and caregiver burden.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed project focuses on mimicking the BBB. This work will utilize cylindrical hydrogels to provide three distinct regions for the growth of multiple types of cells related to the BBB, thereby providing an environment that is similar to the native system. This will provide a highly relevant model to visualize the active transport of bioactive molecules across the BBB to create effective, next-generation therapeutics for use in the CNS. One goal is to show cell survival throughout ten-day-long trials. Additionally, the genetic response of the cells within the system will be analyzed to better understand their behavior, and the system’s inherent conductivity will show real-time cell-to-cell communication. Once a model is created, the transport of caffeine across the model barrier will be studied and compared with known values of how the molecule acts within the body to begin validating the system.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/02/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/03/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041, 47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2014346</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Andrew</FirstName>
<LastName>Makowski</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Andrew J Makowski</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[makowski.drew@gmail.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000863723</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/20/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Neda</FirstName>
<LastName>Sanatkaran</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Neda Sanatkaran</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[sanatkaran@gmail.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000839072</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>10/16/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate>09/20/2021</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Reza</FirstName>
<LastName>Montazami</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Reza Montazami</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[reza@iastate.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000083013</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>10/21/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nicole</FirstName>
<LastName>Hashemi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>N</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nicole N Hashemi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[nastaran@iastate.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000247469</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/02/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate>10/21/2020</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Farrokh</FirstName>
<LastName>Sharifi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Farrokh Sharifi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[farrokh.sharifi.64@gmail.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000816766</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/02/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate>10/16/2020</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>NISTRON, L.L.C.</Name>
<CityName>AMES</CityName>
<ZipCode>500148069</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2025777117</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3021 RED FOX RD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Iowa</StateName>
<StateCode>IA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>JYPFQ892W7Q5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NISTRON, L. L. C.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Iowa State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Ames</CityName>
<StateCode>IA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>500112030</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2529 Union Dr]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Iowa</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1505</Code>
<Text>STTR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>066E</Code>
<Text>INSTRUMENTATION &amp; DIAGNOSTICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8038</Code>
<Text>Biotechnology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~225000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Nistron's STTR Phase I work investigates the pharmacokinetics of the blood-brain barrier (BBB), building on the extensive research and studies that have been done in the Hashemi lab at Iowa State University.&nbsp; Along with the fabrication of hollow microfibers, the mimicking of BBB is divided into three significant steps, which include: 1- Seeding of human brain endothelial cells on the inner surface of hollow micro-fibers, 2- Encapsulation of pericyte cells in the wall of the microfibers, and 3- Seeding of astrocyte cells on the outer surface of microfibers.&nbsp; This accomplished model could mimic the BBB and simulate and study the transfer of different drugs and molecules across the BBB.</p> <p>Microfluidic in-vitro devices are powerful tools for various biomedical engineering applications, and they are unmatched for creating continuous, biocompatible hydrogel microfibers with highly controlled sizes and cross-sectional shapes.&nbsp; Microfluidic fiber fabrication utilizes cell-safe gelation conditions, thereby enabling cell encapsulation, in direct contradiction to previous techniques like electrospinning.&nbsp; Wet spinning, or extrusion, uses the same cell-safe gelation processes as microfluidics, but this system lacks the innovative internal geometries and hydrodynamic focusing that allow for the creation of fibers with a wide degree of sizes and cross-sectional shapes.&nbsp; The strength of this method enables the creation of bioinspired hydrogel microfibers for a variety of tissue targets, but the immediate cellular and genetic implications of microfluidic microfiber manufacturing remain understudied.</p> <p>To date, Nistron and STTR phase 1 partner have accomplished seeding cells on the outer surface of microfibers previous to phase 1, and during phase 1, cells have been encapsulated in the wall of the hollow microfibers and on the inner surface of the hollow microfiber; qPCR gene studies were conducted during the phase 1 project to evaluate the behavior of cells in this environment, in addition to conductivity profiling.</p> <p>Altogether, we have developed a tunable alginate/graphene hollow microfiber-based microfluidic platform for long-term support for the in-vitro culture of encapsulated cells.&nbsp; By introducing BSA-graphene into alginate hollow microfibers, their conductivities could be significantly enhanced to deliver and receive electrical signals to cells by a factor of 2.&nbsp; The present findings displayed the first description of porous conductive alginate hollow microfibers to enhance the essential nutrition and metabolic waste transferring between the internal and the external environment of cells.&nbsp; Further development of the microfluidic platform and further optimization of cell numbers on the inner and outer surfaces of alginate/graphene hollow microfibers could facilitate other applications of this technology to applications such as cellular therapies and drug- and gene-delivery strategies.</p> <p>During Phase I, one of the main challenges was tight cell junctions of endothelial cells on the inside wall.&nbsp; Due to the presence of cells in the core solution, since the core solution rate is higher than the pre-polymer solution, not all the cells could be seeded on the inner surface of the hollow microfiber, but adding different extracellular matrix (ECM) proteins, like collagen I, help cell attachment once the appropriate grade/supplier was found.&nbsp; Also, increasing the cell density in the core solution showed that more cells could be seeded on the inner surface of hollow microfiber.&nbsp; Once this step was optimized, the three cell lines (endothelial, pericytes, astrocytes) could be seeded and encapsulated on the inner and outer surface and in the wall of the hollow microfiber while manufacturing, respectively.&nbsp; Co-cultured cells have been tested recently, and proof of concept with different cell lines has been completed, as shown below in conclusion. &nbsp;Further prolonged studies will need to be conducted to monitor cell proliferation and possible gene expression, but an initial co-cultured environment has been achieved</p> <p>Three technical steps have been developed to mimic the BBB.&nbsp; In the first step, Nistron and ISU have created solid microfibers using a microfluidic chip capable of manufacturing polyethylene glycol diacrylate (PEGDA) microfibers with neural cells.&nbsp; In the second step, Nistron developed a novel microfluidic chip with five inlets capable of fabricating hollow microfibers.&nbsp; Also, it has been stated that alginate hydrogels showed better cell viability, which ended in using alginate and alginate/graphene hydrogels instead of PEGDA to fabricate microfibers.&nbsp; In this study, cells were encapsulated in the hollow microfiber wall during manufacturing, adding to the novelty.&nbsp; In the third step, the cell suspension was used in the core solution, which resulted in the seeding of the cells on the inner surface of the hollow microfiber, and different ECM proteins were used to assess the cell adhesion to the inner surface.&nbsp; Cells could be seeded or encapsulated by adding either to the core or pre-polymer solutions.</p> <p>In conclusion, Nistron's next-generation microfiber with alginate/graphene composition was incorporated with the previous findings to demonstrate proof of concept for a viable cell-encapsulated microfiber with superior conductivity and physical interactions.&nbsp; These findings pave the way to complete research showing the feasibility of the active transport of caffeine.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/27/2022<br>      Modified by: Andrew&nbsp;J&nbsp;Makowski</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Nistron's STTR Phase I work investigates the pharmacokinetics of the blood-brain barrier (BBB), building on the extensive research and studies that have been done in the Hashemi lab at Iowa State University.  Along with the fabrication of hollow microfibers, the mimicking of BBB is divided into three significant steps, which include: 1- Seeding of human brain endothelial cells on the inner surface of hollow micro-fibers, 2- Encapsulation of pericyte cells in the wall of the microfibers, and 3- Seeding of astrocyte cells on the outer surface of microfibers.  This accomplished model could mimic the BBB and simulate and study the transfer of different drugs and molecules across the BBB.  Microfluidic in-vitro devices are powerful tools for various biomedical engineering applications, and they are unmatched for creating continuous, biocompatible hydrogel microfibers with highly controlled sizes and cross-sectional shapes.  Microfluidic fiber fabrication utilizes cell-safe gelation conditions, thereby enabling cell encapsulation, in direct contradiction to previous techniques like electrospinning.  Wet spinning, or extrusion, uses the same cell-safe gelation processes as microfluidics, but this system lacks the innovative internal geometries and hydrodynamic focusing that allow for the creation of fibers with a wide degree of sizes and cross-sectional shapes.  The strength of this method enables the creation of bioinspired hydrogel microfibers for a variety of tissue targets, but the immediate cellular and genetic implications of microfluidic microfiber manufacturing remain understudied.  To date, Nistron and STTR phase 1 partner have accomplished seeding cells on the outer surface of microfibers previous to phase 1, and during phase 1, cells have been encapsulated in the wall of the hollow microfibers and on the inner surface of the hollow microfiber; qPCR gene studies were conducted during the phase 1 project to evaluate the behavior of cells in this environment, in addition to conductivity profiling.  Altogether, we have developed a tunable alginate/graphene hollow microfiber-based microfluidic platform for long-term support for the in-vitro culture of encapsulated cells.  By introducing BSA-graphene into alginate hollow microfibers, their conductivities could be significantly enhanced to deliver and receive electrical signals to cells by a factor of 2.  The present findings displayed the first description of porous conductive alginate hollow microfibers to enhance the essential nutrition and metabolic waste transferring between the internal and the external environment of cells.  Further development of the microfluidic platform and further optimization of cell numbers on the inner and outer surfaces of alginate/graphene hollow microfibers could facilitate other applications of this technology to applications such as cellular therapies and drug- and gene-delivery strategies.  During Phase I, one of the main challenges was tight cell junctions of endothelial cells on the inside wall.  Due to the presence of cells in the core solution, since the core solution rate is higher than the pre-polymer solution, not all the cells could be seeded on the inner surface of the hollow microfiber, but adding different extracellular matrix (ECM) proteins, like collagen I, help cell attachment once the appropriate grade/supplier was found.  Also, increasing the cell density in the core solution showed that more cells could be seeded on the inner surface of hollow microfiber.  Once this step was optimized, the three cell lines (endothelial, pericytes, astrocytes) could be seeded and encapsulated on the inner and outer surface and in the wall of the hollow microfiber while manufacturing, respectively.  Co-cultured cells have been tested recently, and proof of concept with different cell lines has been completed, as shown below in conclusion.  Further prolonged studies will need to be conducted to monitor cell proliferation and possible gene expression, but an initial co-cultured environment has been achieved  Three technical steps have been developed to mimic the BBB.  In the first step, Nistron and ISU have created solid microfibers using a microfluidic chip capable of manufacturing polyethylene glycol diacrylate (PEGDA) microfibers with neural cells.  In the second step, Nistron developed a novel microfluidic chip with five inlets capable of fabricating hollow microfibers.  Also, it has been stated that alginate hydrogels showed better cell viability, which ended in using alginate and alginate/graphene hydrogels instead of PEGDA to fabricate microfibers.  In this study, cells were encapsulated in the hollow microfiber wall during manufacturing, adding to the novelty.  In the third step, the cell suspension was used in the core solution, which resulted in the seeding of the cells on the inner surface of the hollow microfiber, and different ECM proteins were used to assess the cell adhesion to the inner surface.  Cells could be seeded or encapsulated by adding either to the core or pre-polymer solutions.  In conclusion, Nistron's next-generation microfiber with alginate/graphene composition was incorporated with the previous findings to demonstrate proof of concept for a viable cell-encapsulated microfiber with superior conductivity and physical interactions.  These findings pave the way to complete research showing the feasibility of the active transport of caffeine.       Last Modified: 12/27/2022       Submitted by: Andrew J Makowski]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
