<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Development of High-Purity NaI(T1) Crystals for the SABRE Dark Matter Experiment]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>240000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>240000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>William Wester</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>wwester@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924677</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Astrophysical observations and cosmological data give strong evidence that nearly a quarter of the Universe consists of dark matter. Weakly interacting massive particles (WIMPs) and axions have been proposed as theoretically favored candidates for dark matter. Despite the strong evidence for the existence of dark matter, neither WIMPs nor axions have been conclusively detected. The DAMA/LIBRA experiment claims for more than a decade to have detected dark matter with an array of low background NaI(Tl) crystal scintillators. However, other experiments with different detectors have not seen evidence for dark matter, even though they have very high sensitivity. Because the sensitivity to dark matter may depend on details of the detector material, a new search for evidence of dark matter with NaI(Tl) detectors with much lower background than DAMA/LIBRA achieved is needed. This award will fund the SABRE (Sodium-iodide with Active Background REjection) experiment which has been focused on the development of new crystals with lower background than DAMA/LIBRA.  The development of high purity crystals can affect many fields of research, perhaps even semiconductors which presently have trace levels of radioactivity that affect their reliability. The effort also involves many fields and attracts students with a wide range of backgrounds. SABRE also promotes strong relationships with industrial partners, who then brought new products and services to all customers. Collaboration with RMD, Sigma Aldrich, Seastar Chemicals, and Sandfire has brought high purity products and sensitive assay services to the market. Collaboration with the Mellen Company has led to an invention that can be used to purify materials with higher efficiency.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research funded by this award will support the development and testing of a low-background NaI(Tl) crystal detector exploiting the new zone-refining technique developed by Princeton in collaboration with Mellen Company in order to improve the present record established with NaI-33; and the development of a crystal growth facility underground at the Canfranc Laboratory, Spain. SABRE will have two phases: phase 1 consists of one detector at the Gran Sasso Laboratory (LNGS), in Italy, which works as a proof-of-principle (PoP) for testing the radio-purity of crystals; in phase 2, twin detectors will be built in the northern and southern hemispheres. The SABRE-south is planned to be installed in the SUPL (Stawell Underground Physics Laboratory), a new underground laboratory in Australia under construction. The two detectors will enhance the potentiality to differentiate a dark matter signal from seasonal and local effects.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/26/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/05/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2014198</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Frank</FirstName>
<LastName>Calaprice</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Frank P Calaprice</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[calaprice@princeton.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000460659</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/26/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate>07/05/2022</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jay</FirstName>
<LastName>Benziger</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jay B Benziger</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[benziger@princeton.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000170844</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/07/2022</StartDate>
<EndDate>07/05/2022</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jay</FirstName>
<LastName>Benziger</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jay B Benziger</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[benziger@princeton.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000170844</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/05/2022</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Princeton University</Name>
<CityName>PRINCETON</CityName>
<ZipCode>085442001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6092583090</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1 NASSAU HALL</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NJ12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NJ1YPQXQG7U5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>THE TRUSTEES OF PRINCETON UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Princeton University]]></Name>
<CityName>Princeton</CityName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>085442020</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Washington Road, Jadwin Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NJ12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7235</Code>
<Text>Particle Astrophysics/Undergro</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7483</Code>
<Text>PHYSICS OF THE UNIVERSE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8037</Code>
<Text>Advanced Manufacturing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~120000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~120000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>Deciphering the nature of dark matter represents one of the most significant scientific inquiries of our time. The DAMA/LIBRA experiment, located at the deep-underground Gran Sasso National Laboratory (LNGS) in Italy, has reported an annual modulation signal consistent with the presence of dark matter particles in the Milky Way. However, their findings appear to be in conflict with results from other experiments that have yielded null results in the search for dark matter. Only an experiment employing the same target material as DAMA/LIBRA, namely&nbsp;low background NaI(Tl) detectors,&nbsp;can perform a model-independent test of their claim. The SABRE (Sodium-iodide with Active Background REjection) project aims to develop ultra-low background sodium iodide scintillation crystals for a highly sensitive dark matter search, providing insights into this long-standing debate.</span></p> <p><span><span>The SABRE R&amp;D effort, funded by this award, has provided a proof-of-principle for such a detector by developing NaI(Tl) crystal scintillators with background levels comparable to those of DAMA/LIBRA. Significant progress has been made in producing highly radiopure NaI powder, exhibiting impurity levels similar to, or even lower than, the final crystals used in DAMA. Furthermore, the potential for further purification has been demonstrated through the application of the zone refining method. Crystals grown using the zone refining process on NaI powder can achieve background levels two to three times lower than those of DAMA/LIBRA crystals.</span></span></p> <p>A potential second phase of research would involve deploying an array of such detectors in a low background environment, enabling a model-independent search for the annual modulation signature of the dark matter interaction rate with lower background and increased sensitivity compared to the DAMA/LIBRA experiment. The ultimate goal of SABRE is to deploy two independent NaI(Tl) crystal arrays in the northern (SABRE North) and southern (SABRE South) hemispheres, facilitating the identification of potential contributions to the modulation from seasonal or site-related effects. This unique and extremely powerful feature distinguishes the SABRE project.</p> <p>Broader impacts: Understanding the nature of dark matter would have implications for numerous scientific fields, ranging from thelargest scale of astronomy to the smallest scale of elementary particle physics. Moreover, the technology developed in this project, with its stringent demands for ultra-pure materials, would benefit other fields reliant on such materials, including semiconductors and nanotechnology devices. The SABRE project fosters strong collaborations between industry and academia, allowing for the development of new technologies, products, and measurement techniques that will be made available to the research and industrial market at large.</p> <p><span><span><br /></span></span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/17/2023<br>      Modified by: Jay&nbsp;B&nbsp;Benziger</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2014198/2014198_10680774_1689608892148_NaICrystal--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2014198/2014198_10680774_1689608892148_NaICrystal--rgov-800width.jpg" title="NaI Crystals"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2014198/2014198_10680774_1689608892148_NaICrystal--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="NaI Crystals"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">NaI(Tl) crystals grown from Astro grade powder</div> <div class="imageCredit">Princeton University Physics</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jay&nbsp;B&nbsp;Benziger</div> <div class="imageTitle">NaI Crystals</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2014198/2014198_10680774_1689609065497_ZonrRefiner--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2014198/2014198_10680774_1689609065497_ZonrRefiner--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Zone Refiner"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2014198/2014198_10680774_1689609065497_ZonrRefiner--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Zone Refiner"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Multipass Zone Refiner for growth and purification of NaI crystals from Astrograde powder</div> <div class="imageCredit">Princeton University Physics</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jay&nbsp;B&nbsp;Benziger</div> <div class="imageTitle">Zone Refiner</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Deciphering the nature of dark matter represents one of the most significant scientific inquiries of our time. The DAMA/LIBRA experiment, located at the deep-underground Gran Sasso National Laboratory (LNGS) in Italy, has reported an annual modulation signal consistent with the presence of dark matter particles in the Milky Way. However, their findings appear to be in conflict with results from other experiments that have yielded null results in the search for dark matter. Only an experiment employing the same target material as DAMA/LIBRA, namely low background NaI(Tl) detectors, can perform a model-independent test of their claim. The SABRE (Sodium-iodide with Active Background REjection) project aims to develop ultra-low background sodium iodide scintillation crystals for a highly sensitive dark matter search, providing insights into this long-standing debate.  The SABRE R&amp;D effort, funded by this award, has provided a proof-of-principle for such a detector by developing NaI(Tl) crystal scintillators with background levels comparable to those of DAMA/LIBRA. Significant progress has been made in producing highly radiopure NaI powder, exhibiting impurity levels similar to, or even lower than, the final crystals used in DAMA. Furthermore, the potential for further purification has been demonstrated through the application of the zone refining method. Crystals grown using the zone refining process on NaI powder can achieve background levels two to three times lower than those of DAMA/LIBRA crystals.  A potential second phase of research would involve deploying an array of such detectors in a low background environment, enabling a model-independent search for the annual modulation signature of the dark matter interaction rate with lower background and increased sensitivity compared to the DAMA/LIBRA experiment. The ultimate goal of SABRE is to deploy two independent NaI(Tl) crystal arrays in the northern (SABRE North) and southern (SABRE South) hemispheres, facilitating the identification of potential contributions to the modulation from seasonal or site-related effects. This unique and extremely powerful feature distinguishes the SABRE project.  Broader impacts: Understanding the nature of dark matter would have implications for numerous scientific fields, ranging from thelargest scale of astronomy to the smallest scale of elementary particle physics. Moreover, the technology developed in this project, with its stringent demands for ultra-pure materials, would benefit other fields reliant on such materials, including semiconductors and nanotechnology devices. The SABRE project fosters strong collaborations between industry and academia, allowing for the development of new technologies, products, and measurement techniques that will be made available to the research and industrial market at large.          Last Modified: 07/17/2023       Submitted by: Jay B Benziger]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
