<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>FSML: A culture facility for small marine organisms at Shannon Point Marine Center</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>182413.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>182413</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DBI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Peter McCartney</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>pmccartn@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928470</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Shannon Point Marine Center (SPMC; https://www.wwu.edu/spmc/) has historically relied on culture methods to study how small marine organisms grow, feed, and respond to environmental pressures such as ocean acidification. Single-celled algae and non-photosynthetic protists are also used as foods for other marine organisms that are the focus of research at SPMC, including larger zooplankton, endangered pinto abalone, and threatened Pacific herring. This award supports the acquisition of equipment used for culturing small marine organisms, particularly single-celled planktonic (free-floating) algae and their direct consumers. The new culture facility will be used by students at a variety of levels in both classroom and independent research settings, and will involve new faculty from the main campus in research at the marine laboratory. The facility will also support increased collaboration with area resource management. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The new instrumentation will enable isolation and identification of small marine organisms (stereomicroscope), maintenance of these organisms in culture (environmental chambers, laminar flow hood, autoclave) and characterization of their abundance and condition (flow cytometer). Research areas at SPMC that are dependent on the ability to isolate and culture small marine organisms include protist chemical signaling and defense ecology, ocean acidification effects on regional zooplankton and larval fish biology, invertebrate developmental biology and ecology, chemical defense studies, and symbiosis research. New research areas that will require the requested isolation and culturing facilities include culture of endangered pinto abalone and expansion of ocean acidification studies to threatened stocks of Pacific herring. Student involvement with the culture facility will occur through multiple avenues, including a summer REU program (pending), our graduate Marine and Estuarine Science program, and the capstone projects envisioned for the new undergraduate major in Marine and Coastal Sciences. Several of the projects that will use the culture facility have regional conservation impacts, including testing larval herring diet-development relationships, and developing methods for culture of endangered pinto abalone. Through these and other avenues, the culture facility will form or strengthen existing partnerships with area agencies and stakeholders who have interest in aquaculture pilot projects (e.g. Puget Sound Restoration Fund, Washington Department of Ecology) or environmental impact research (e.g. WA Ocean Acidification Center). Finally, the culture facility will improve our ability to provide cultures of heterotrophic dinoflagellates and ciliates to researchers worldwide, a service that has led to numerous significant publications in plankton ecology, biogeochemistry, and phylogenetics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/12/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/12/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2014617</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Suzanne</FirstName>
<LastName>Strom</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Suzanne L Strom</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Suzanne.Strom@wwu.edu</EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000111740</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/12/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Western Washington University</Name>
<CityName>Bellingham</CityName>
<ZipCode>982259038</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3606502884</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>516 High Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>079253134</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WESTERN WASHINGTON UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>079253134</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Shannon Point Marine Center]]></Name>
<CityName>Anacortes</CityName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>982214042</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1900 Shannon Point Rd]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7593</Code>
<Text>FIELD STATIONS AND MARINE LABS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~182413</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This grant supported the acquisition of equipment for the culture and study of small marine organisms at Western Washington University&rsquo;s Shannon Point Marine Center (SPMC). Researchers at SPMC have long studied the invertebrate larvae and protists that inhabit the Salish Sea and adjacent North Pacific waters, and the marine lab has housed a culture collection of protist isolates since the mid 1990s. The new equipment has brought the culture facility at SPMC into the 21<sup>st</sup> century and added new capacities. This includes two controlled environment chambers, one of which is larger and with higher illumination than the 40-year-old unit being replaced. New equipment for culturing marine organisms includes an autoclave and a biological safety cabinet/laminar flow hood for preparation of growth media and sterile transfer of organisms. A new research-grade stereomicroscope allows for identification, isolation, and manipulation of protists and small metazoans. A next-generation flow cytometer allows the quantification and characterization (e.g. size, pigment content) of single-celled organisms including bacteria and algae. Despite covid-related delays in equipment availability and laboratory access, the newly upgraded culture facility is already in active use by researchers, including faculty and students. The new equipment was described to the user community in a &lsquo;virtual open house&rsquo; in summer 2021, and protocols for use of the flow cytometer have been developed and shared widely. Undergraduates in a Marine and Coastal Sciences research internship course are using all of the new equipment to study the ecology and physiology of harmful algal bloom-forming species isolated from the Salish Sea. Graduate student research using the flow cytometer includes study of phytoplankton communities in the Gulf of Alaska, as well as investigation of snow algae from Washington&rsquo;s North Cascades mountain range. Other research supported by the new equipment includes culture of ciliates for ultrastructure studies, and investigations of mixotrophic nutrition by phytoplankton. The flow cytometer and stereomicroscope will be taken to sea in 2022 on expeditions investigating the planktonic ecosystem of the northern Gulf of Alaska, in conjunction with NSF&rsquo;s Long-Term Ecosystem Research program.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/26/2021<br>      Modified by: Suzanne&nbsp;L&nbsp;Strom</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This grant supported the acquisition of equipment for the culture and study of small marine organisms at Western Washington University’s Shannon Point Marine Center (SPMC). Researchers at SPMC have long studied the invertebrate larvae and protists that inhabit the Salish Sea and adjacent North Pacific waters, and the marine lab has housed a culture collection of protist isolates since the mid 1990s. The new equipment has brought the culture facility at SPMC into the 21st century and added new capacities. This includes two controlled environment chambers, one of which is larger and with higher illumination than the 40-year-old unit being replaced. New equipment for culturing marine organisms includes an autoclave and a biological safety cabinet/laminar flow hood for preparation of growth media and sterile transfer of organisms. A new research-grade stereomicroscope allows for identification, isolation, and manipulation of protists and small metazoans. A next-generation flow cytometer allows the quantification and characterization (e.g. size, pigment content) of single-celled organisms including bacteria and algae. Despite covid-related delays in equipment availability and laboratory access, the newly upgraded culture facility is already in active use by researchers, including faculty and students. The new equipment was described to the user community in a ‘virtual open house’ in summer 2021, and protocols for use of the flow cytometer have been developed and shared widely. Undergraduates in a Marine and Coastal Sciences research internship course are using all of the new equipment to study the ecology and physiology of harmful algal bloom-forming species isolated from the Salish Sea. Graduate student research using the flow cytometer includes study of phytoplankton communities in the Gulf of Alaska, as well as investigation of snow algae from Washington’s North Cascades mountain range. Other research supported by the new equipment includes culture of ciliates for ultrastructure studies, and investigations of mixotrophic nutrition by phytoplankton. The flow cytometer and stereomicroscope will be taken to sea in 2022 on expeditions investigating the planktonic ecosystem of the northern Gulf of Alaska, in conjunction with NSF’s Long-Term Ecosystem Research program.          Last Modified: 10/26/2021       Submitted by: Suzanne L Strom]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
