<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Pacifichem 2020 Symposia #337, #396, #106, and #109; Honolulu, HI - Dec. 2020]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>10000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>10000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Nora Savage</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>nosavage@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927949</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[A large body of literature has resulted from research on interactions between nanomaterials and biological and ecological systems. As a consequence of these research activities, current regulations are being examined for adequacy. The overall goal of these symposia is to promote collaboration and discussion across multiple disciplines related to nanotechnology. These symposia will help bring together chemists, biologists, engineers, and legislators to discuss the necessary approaches and to discuss cost-effective measures to prevent unintentional environmental and health degradation as a result of the widespread use of nanomaterials. Support for these symposia will provide outstanding graduate students and participants with travel funds to attend the 2020 International Chemical Congress of Pacific Basin Societies, to be held in Honolulu, Hawaii, December 15-20, 2020. The awarded graduate students and participants will be selected by a scientific committee based on the intellectual merit and the broader impacts of their research. To promote diversity, equity and inclusion, students and participants from traditionally underrepresented groups will be given high priority. The awarded students and participants will have the opportunity to expose to be a variety of scientific topics, including but not limited to nano-bio interactions, nanotoxicology, nanomedicine, colloid and surface science, particulate matter, smart surfaces, self-assembly, 3D printed organs, and bionanotechnology. Particular focus will be on understanding and designing safe nano-bio interfaces for materials, medicine, and the environment. These symposia will provide students and participants with an excellent opportunity to communicate research and education activities in the area of nanotechnology.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The PI will seek participation from distinguished researchers and students in four symposia within the 2020 International Chemical Congress of Pacific Basin Societies (Pacifichem), which will be held in Honolulu, Hawaii, December 15-20, 2020. These four symposia are (1) Understanding and Designing Safe Nano‐Bio Interfaces for Materials, Medicine, and the Environment, (2) Interfacial Phenomena for Bubbles, Droplets, Films and Soft Matter, (3) Peptide Self‐Assembly: Chemistry and Nanotechnology, and (4) 3D Printing in Chemistry, Biology and Materials. All four symposia are highly interdisciplinary and have far-reaching impacts on multiple scientific disciplines. This support will provide students and participants with a unique opportunity to attend the Pacifichem 2020, and to learn the state-of-the-art knowledge of nanotechnology and nanosafety. The PI will disseminate knowledge to the academic community and the industry through the publication of review and commentary articles that will highlight the state-of-the-art of nano-bio interactions, colloid and surface sciences, self-assembled peptides and nanomedicine, additive manufacturing, and other major topics discussed in these symposia.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/19/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/19/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2014822</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yi</FirstName>
<LastName>Zuo</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Yi Zuo</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[yzuo@hawaii.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000520893</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/19/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Hawaii</Name>
<CityName>HONOLULU</CityName>
<ZipCode>968222247</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8089567800</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2425 CAMPUS RD SINCLAIR RM 1</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Hawaii</StateName>
<StateCode>HI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>HI01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NSCKLFSSABF2</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF HAWAII</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Hawaii at Manoa]]></Name>
<CityName>Honolulu</CityName>
<StateCode>HI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>968222382</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2540 Dole St, Holmes Hall 302]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Hawaii</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>HI01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1179</Code>
<Text>Nanoscale Interactions Program</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1415</Code>
<Text>PMP-Particul&amp;MultiphaseProcess</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~10000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>A large body of literature has demonstrated nanosafety issues at all levels of nano-bio interfaces, from biomolecules, cells, organs, organisms, to local ecosystems. As a consequence of these research activities, more comprehensive regulations are enforced to oversee research and commercial applications of nanotechnology. One&nbsp;goal of this project is to organize a symposium to bring together chemists, biologists, engineers, and legislators to discuss necessary precautionary approaches of nanotechnology and to stimulate cost-effective measures to prevent environmental and health degradation. The particular focus is on safety and sustainability of nanotechnology.</p> <p>Colloidal and interfacial phenomena play a central role in a variety of physical chemistry and biophysical areas, such as smart surfaces, self-assembly and bionanotechnology. Drops, bubbles, films and particles form the fundamental element of many of the soft matter systems and applications. Another goal of this project is to organize a symposium that focuses on interfacial phenomena in these multiphase systems.</p> <p>Peptides are appealing building blocks for supramolecular chemistry due to their simple structures, flexibility in sequence manipulation, relatively high stability along with good biodegradability, high biocompatibility, and ease of production on a large scale. With the advances of synthetic methods for peptides, in the past decade a lot of peptides have been designed, synthesized, and applied toward supramolecular self-assembly. The third goal of this project is to organize a symposium that focuses on chemistry, materials and nanotechnology of peptide self-assembly, their properties and applications.</p> <p>We successfully organized three symposia: "Understanding and Designing Safe Nano&#8208;Bio Interfaces for Materials, Medicine, and the Environment", "Interfacial Phenomena for Bubbles, Droplets, Films and Soft Matter", and "Peptide Self&#8208;Assembly: Chemistry and Nanotechnology" in the Pacifichem held virtually on December 16-21, 2021. These three symposia hosted a total of 78 oral presentations and 19 posters. Scientists and students who presented in these three symposia came from countries all over the world. We have awarded three presentation awards to outstanding graduate students.</p> <p>These three symposia promoted interdisciplinary collaborations among chemists, biologists, engineers, and legislators to discuss necessary precautionary approaches of nanotechnology and to stimulate cost-effective measures to prevent environmental and health degradation. The outcome of this project has both scientific and educational impacts on nanotechnology and colloid and surface sciences.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/18/2023<br>      Modified by: Yi&nbsp;Zuo</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ A large body of literature has demonstrated nanosafety issues at all levels of nano-bio interfaces, from biomolecules, cells, organs, organisms, to local ecosystems. As a consequence of these research activities, more comprehensive regulations are enforced to oversee research and commercial applications of nanotechnology. One goal of this project is to organize a symposium to bring together chemists, biologists, engineers, and legislators to discuss necessary precautionary approaches of nanotechnology and to stimulate cost-effective measures to prevent environmental and health degradation. The particular focus is on safety and sustainability of nanotechnology.  Colloidal and interfacial phenomena play a central role in a variety of physical chemistry and biophysical areas, such as smart surfaces, self-assembly and bionanotechnology. Drops, bubbles, films and particles form the fundamental element of many of the soft matter systems and applications. Another goal of this project is to organize a symposium that focuses on interfacial phenomena in these multiphase systems.  Peptides are appealing building blocks for supramolecular chemistry due to their simple structures, flexibility in sequence manipulation, relatively high stability along with good biodegradability, high biocompatibility, and ease of production on a large scale. With the advances of synthetic methods for peptides, in the past decade a lot of peptides have been designed, synthesized, and applied toward supramolecular self-assembly. The third goal of this project is to organize a symposium that focuses on chemistry, materials and nanotechnology of peptide self-assembly, their properties and applications.  We successfully organized three symposia: "Understanding and Designing Safe Nano&#8208;Bio Interfaces for Materials, Medicine, and the Environment", "Interfacial Phenomena for Bubbles, Droplets, Films and Soft Matter", and "Peptide Self&#8208;Assembly: Chemistry and Nanotechnology" in the Pacifichem held virtually on December 16-21, 2021. These three symposia hosted a total of 78 oral presentations and 19 posters. Scientists and students who presented in these three symposia came from countries all over the world. We have awarded three presentation awards to outstanding graduate students.  These three symposia promoted interdisciplinary collaborations among chemists, biologists, engineers, and legislators to discuss necessary precautionary approaches of nanotechnology and to stimulate cost-effective measures to prevent environmental and health degradation. The outcome of this project has both scientific and educational impacts on nanotechnology and colloid and surface sciences.       Last Modified: 09/18/2023       Submitted by: Yi Zuo]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
