<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Low-cost Transparent Conductive Oxide Manufacturing for Smart Windows]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>225000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>225000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Steven Konsek</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project will advance the development of energy-efficient windows. Electrochromic windows may be used to reduce energy costs related to climate control and lighting, eliminate glare, and improve visual comfort in commercial buildings. Electrochromic window manufacturers cite reduction in overall energy loads by an average of 20% and peak energy demand by up to 26%. Growth of the electrochromic window market has lagged because of high manufacturing costs. This project will enable low-cost manufacturing of films employed widely in energy conversion and conservation applications to enable widespread use of electrochromic energy-efficient windows.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project will explore the translation of solution-processed transparent conductors used in large area devices. Transparent conductive oxide (TCO) films are typically produced by vacuum-based techniques or chemical vapor deposition. These coatings often suffer from high expense, poor uniformity, and optical haze.  The proposed research is aimed to eliminate the common drawbacks of conventional TCO films. The technical objectives of this Phase I research project support development of low-cost, large area, solution deposited TCOs meeting industrial performance requirements.  This research project will establish correlations between precursor formulation and film processing to control film composition, morphology, and electrical properties and reliably meet industrial specifications.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/14/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/14/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2015042</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Cory</FirstName>
<LastName>Perkins</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Cory Perkins</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[corykperkins@gmail.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000792819</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/14/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>NEXTC CORPORATION</Name>
<CityName>CORVALLIS</CityName>
<ZipCode>973304254</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5039316088</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1110 NE CIRCLE BLVD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OR04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>ZKGZD6HXL3C4</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NEXTC CORP</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[NEXTC CORPORATION]]></Name>
<CityName>Corvallis, OR</CityName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<ZipCode>973318673</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Gilbert Hall, 2100 Monroe Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OR04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>123E</Code>
<Text>CENTERS: ADVANCED MATERIALS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~225000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Energy conversion and conservation technologies are at&nbsp;the&nbsp;forefront of material&nbsp;science&nbsp;challenges to improve efficiencies, increase&nbsp;device&nbsp;yields, and reduce costs. New materials and&nbsp;processes are required to meet market needs and catalyze&nbsp;market&nbsp;growth.&nbsp;For example, glass&nbsp;coated with transparent conductive oxide&nbsp;(TCO)&nbsp;films are required to manufacture&nbsp;transparent&nbsp;electronics including solar modules and electrochromic windows,&nbsp;among others. These electronic device&nbsp;manufacturers are held captive to the pricing and&nbsp;performance&nbsp;terms&nbsp;defined by glass&nbsp;manufactures. There is currently no&nbsp;platform that&nbsp;enables&nbsp;high-performance and low-cost&nbsp;manufacturing.</p> <p>nexTC&nbsp;is developing transformative chemistries for solution-processed transparent conductive&nbsp;oxides that enable&nbsp;low-cost module manufacturing and meet manufacturer's needs.&nbsp;During this&nbsp;project,&nbsp;key&nbsp;breakthroughs in chemistries and processing led to demonstration of&nbsp;feasibility&nbsp;to&nbsp;create market competitive TCO films via slot-die coating.&nbsp;Our chemistries offer a completely&nbsp;new approach that yields films with ultra-smooth surfaces and high transmission, without&nbsp;sacrificing conductivity which is common with solution processed TCO films.&nbsp;The demonstrated performance within the Phase I project meets key market requirements for conductivity and improves on the current standard for transmission and haze. The technical&nbsp;advances&nbsp;catalyzed by this SBIR project have enabled nexTC to generate&nbsp;interest from industry&nbsp;leaders&nbsp;within electrochromic window and TCO-coated glass markets.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/09/2021<br>      Modified by: Cory&nbsp;Perkins</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Energy conversion and conservation technologies are at the forefront of material science challenges to improve efficiencies, increase device yields, and reduce costs. New materials and processes are required to meet market needs and catalyze market growth. For example, glass coated with transparent conductive oxide (TCO) films are required to manufacture transparent electronics including solar modules and electrochromic windows, among others. These electronic device manufacturers are held captive to the pricing and performance terms defined by glass manufactures. There is currently no platform that enables high-performance and low-cost manufacturing.  nexTC is developing transformative chemistries for solution-processed transparent conductive oxides that enable low-cost module manufacturing and meet manufacturer's needs. During this project, key breakthroughs in chemistries and processing led to demonstration of feasibility to create market competitive TCO films via slot-die coating. Our chemistries offer a completely new approach that yields films with ultra-smooth surfaces and high transmission, without sacrificing conductivity which is common with solution processed TCO films. The demonstrated performance within the Phase I project meets key market requirements for conductivity and improves on the current standard for transmission and haze. The technical advances catalyzed by this SBIR project have enabled nexTC to generate interest from industry leaders within electrochromic window and TCO-coated glass markets.          Last Modified: 09/09/2021       Submitted by: Cory Perkins]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
