<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research:  Development and empirical tests of a mechanistic multi-host, multi-pathogen theory]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>161960.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>161960</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010208</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kari Segraves</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ksegrave@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928935</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Most plants and animals can be infected by very small organisms that can make them sick.  The infected plant or animal is called a "host" and the infecting organism is called a "pathogen".  The interaction between hosts and pathogens is important to understand because it often determines one's health. Scientists are now becoming aware that the host-pathogen interaction is more complicated because one host can be infected by many pathogens, all of whom interact with each other as well as with the host.  Likewise, one type of pathogen can infect several types of hosts, and how one host responds can influence whether another host becomes infected.  Figuring out how all this plays out in Nature requires carefully designed experiments and mathematical models and this project provides both.  Developing a deeper understanding of hosts and pathogens is critical because humans are dramatically altering the biological world, introducing new types of hosts and pathogens in some areas and removing them from others. Understanding how such gains and losses of organisms influences the spread of disease is important to the fields of conservation science and public health. This research program will train undergraduate, graduate, and high school students in the fields of disease ecology and mathematical biology, and will engage the public through a variety of outreach activities. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Humans are impacting biodiversity patterns globally and these changes can influence the risk and prevalence of infectious diseases. The goal of this project is to develop a mechanistic multi-host multi-pathogen epidemiological theory that explains how between-host and between-pathogen competition jointly shape disease dynamics.  To determine how competition alters the amplification or dilution of diseases, mathematical models will be developed and tested using planktonic species and their associated pathogens via laboratory based mesocosm and field experiments. This work will both extend current theory on multi-host and multi-pathogen communities as well as unify theory developed independently for diseases with different transmission modes.  The theory-data pairing approach of this study is likely to generate important advances in epidemiological theory and disease ecology. This work will also yield insight into how future alterations to diversity will affect disease outbreaks in humans and wildlife.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/24/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/24/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2015280</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Cortez</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael H Cortez</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[cortez@bio.fsu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000604402</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/24/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Florida State University</Name>
<CityName>TALLAHASSEE</CityName>
<ZipCode>323060001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8506445260</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>874 TRADITIONS WAY</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>JF2BLNN4PJC3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>FLORIDA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>D4GCCCMXR1H3</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Florida State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Tallahasee</CityName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>323064166</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[874 Traditions Way]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1182</Code>
<Text>POP &amp; COMMUNITY ECOL PROG</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01001819DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~161960</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><br />Outbreaks of diseases in animals and plants are caused by small organisms that make them sick.&nbsp; Infected animals or plants are called "hosts" and the infecting organisms are called "pathogens". In many parts of the world, areas are occupied by many host species and many pathogen species, which means that animals of different species can be infected by the same pathogen and that a single animal can be infected by more than one pathogen at the same time. As a result, the size of an outbreak of a particular disease is affected by how many host species and how many pathogen species are present in that area. &nbsp;<br /><br />This project developed mathematical models to explain how the presence or absence of host and pathogen species affect the sizes of disease outbreaks.&nbsp; The results from this project explain how the number of host species in an area affects outbreak sizes.&nbsp; Specifically, this research shows how the size of an outbreak depends on (i) whether the host species are good or poor at spreading the pathogen, (ii) whether the host species are competing for food, water, and other resources, and (iii) whether the pathogen is transmitted through direct contact (individuals touching) or through the environment (contaminating an area).&nbsp; That in turn explains why prior models and experiments saw larger outbreaks in some cases and smaller outbreaks in other cases. Thus, this work unified and extended our understanding of how the presence/absence of host species affect disease outbreaks.&nbsp;&nbsp; The results from this project also explain how the size of an outbreak of one pathogen is affected by the the presence of a second pathogen in the same area.&nbsp; Specifically, this research shows how the size of the outbreak depends on (i) if a single organism can be infected by more than one pathogen at the same time and (ii) if being infected by more than one pathogen is better or worse than being infected by a single pathogen (which is determined by how the pathogens interact with each other).&nbsp; Combined, this work greatly extends our understanding of how the gains and losses of host species and the gains and losses of pathogen species affect outbreak sizes in animal and plant populations. This will help us better predict how future alterations to diversity (that is, gains and losses of host and pathogen species) will affect disease outbreaks in humans and wildlife.&nbsp; In addition to advancing knowledge in science, this research program trained an undergraduate student, a graduate student, and a postdoctoral researcher in the fields of disease ecology and mathematical biology.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/26/2022<br>      Modified by: Michael&nbsp;H&nbsp;Cortez</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Outbreaks of diseases in animals and plants are caused by small organisms that make them sick.  Infected animals or plants are called "hosts" and the infecting organisms are called "pathogens". In many parts of the world, areas are occupied by many host species and many pathogen species, which means that animals of different species can be infected by the same pathogen and that a single animal can be infected by more than one pathogen at the same time. As a result, the size of an outbreak of a particular disease is affected by how many host species and how many pathogen species are present in that area.    This project developed mathematical models to explain how the presence or absence of host and pathogen species affect the sizes of disease outbreaks.  The results from this project explain how the number of host species in an area affects outbreak sizes.  Specifically, this research shows how the size of an outbreak depends on (i) whether the host species are good or poor at spreading the pathogen, (ii) whether the host species are competing for food, water, and other resources, and (iii) whether the pathogen is transmitted through direct contact (individuals touching) or through the environment (contaminating an area).  That in turn explains why prior models and experiments saw larger outbreaks in some cases and smaller outbreaks in other cases. Thus, this work unified and extended our understanding of how the presence/absence of host species affect disease outbreaks.   The results from this project also explain how the size of an outbreak of one pathogen is affected by the the presence of a second pathogen in the same area.  Specifically, this research shows how the size of the outbreak depends on (i) if a single organism can be infected by more than one pathogen at the same time and (ii) if being infected by more than one pathogen is better or worse than being infected by a single pathogen (which is determined by how the pathogens interact with each other).  Combined, this work greatly extends our understanding of how the gains and losses of host species and the gains and losses of pathogen species affect outbreak sizes in animal and plant populations. This will help us better predict how future alterations to diversity (that is, gains and losses of host and pathogen species) will affect disease outbreaks in humans and wildlife.  In addition to advancing knowledge in science, this research program trained an undergraduate student, a graduate student, and a postdoctoral researcher in the fields of disease ecology and mathematical biology.        Last Modified: 08/26/2022       Submitted by: Michael H Cortez]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
