<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Formulation parameters for delivery of fatty acids to repel biting insects]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>224668.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>224668</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anna Brady</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>abrady@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927077</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) project is to improve personal-use insect repellents, impacting transmission of diseases such as Lyme and Zika, and positively affecting public health.  The proposed innovation will formulate a natural insect repellent within a skincare formulation that is all-natural and safe for use directly on skin, by using a novel chemistry that is both effective and attractive to use. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This SBIR Phase I project proposes to use novel, natural ingredients classified as safe for cosmetics and offering superior insect repellency, compared to both the standard synthetic DEET and currently marketed natural actives, incorporating fatty acids for a sustained delivery mechanism. This project will demonstrate feasibility of a new hybrid solution by demonstrating: 1) Efficacy for insect repellency; 2) Safety skin care profile; and 3) Consumer consumption properties.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/28/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/28/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2015350</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kim</FirstName>
<LastName>Benz</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kim D Benz</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[onederings@yahoo.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000814210</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/28/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>ONE-DERINGS LLC</Name>
<CityName>CLARKSVILLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>451139310</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9377250830</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2305 S CLARKSVILLE RD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>15</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OH15</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>FUZVLBZERRL4</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ONE-DERINGS LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[ONEDERINGS LAVENDER FARM]]></Name>
<CityName>Clarksville</CityName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>451139310</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2195 S Clarksville Rd]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>15</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OH15</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8030</Code>
<Text>Chemical Technology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~224668</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The first insect repellent product in the US was launched 65 years ago<sup> </sup>yet insect-borne diseases remain a public health concern in the US and globally. The CDC reports disease epidemics from viruses spread by mosquitoes are happening more often. For most viruses spread by mosquitoes, no vaccines or specific medicines are available<em>.</em><sup> </sup><span>Globally, the health challenge posed by mosquitoes is severe. The WHO reports that in 2020, there were an estimated 241 million cases of malaria worldwide&nbsp; Tick borne&nbsp;diseases increasingly threaten the health of people in the United States. The CDC reports that each year, approximately 30,000 cases of Lyme disease are reported to CDC. &nbsp;While recent estimates based on insurance records suggest that approximately 476,000 people are treated for Lyme disease each year in the United States.</span></p> <p><span><span>DEET</span> (N,N-<span>Diethyl</span>-meta-<span>toluamide</span>) is considered the gold-standard active for broad spectrum efficacy and safety. However, products with <span>DEET</span> have a very unpleasant odor and skin feel, melt plastic, and are perceived by some consumers as containing an unsafe chemical.&nbsp;&nbsp; Products with other synthetic actives can be somewhat more pleasant to use than <span>DEET</span> products and do not harm plastic, but do not meet <span>DEET'</span>s effectiveness. Additionally, because they are synthetic, each may still be perceived with suspicion by consumers (who believe they may be putting poison on their skin). There are several natural essential oil actives that are pleasant to use, perceived as safe but have very limited effectiveness or relatively short effective time</span><sup>. </sup><span>Some natural products attempt to match <span>DEET'</span>s effectiveness by increasing concentration of essential oils to high levels and thus become polarizing in their smell and feel (pungent and unpleasant).&nbsp; Furthermore, two of the EPA approved natural actives limit claims to mosquitoes or have no time claims on the label. The search continues for the perfect insect repellent active.</span></p> <p><span>This NSF project tested fatty acid actives derived from coconut or palm oil.&nbsp; Although fatty acids have seen widespread human use in cosmetic applications and as dietary supplements, no one has used them for a skin-applied, broad-spectrum insect repellent.&nbsp; This project saw the opportunity of finally achieving the widespread, effective skin-applied insect repellent to support public health and prevent insect-borne disease. A novel-for-human-use insect repellent was designed to achieve a high insect <span>repellency</span>, over an extended time via a delivery system that is created from a skin care product chassis. As such, it has pleasant scent and skin feel aesthetics. Additionally, it contains recognizable ingredients that are viewed as safe to apply to skin (e.g., per <span>EWG</span>) and are economical, even for developing geographies. This will encourage consumers to be proactive in protecting themselves against insect bites and thus the likelihood of contacting insect borne disease.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/27/2022<br>      Modified by: Kim&nbsp;D&nbsp;Benz</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The first insect repellent product in the US was launched 65 years ago yet insect-borne diseases remain a public health concern in the US and globally. The CDC reports disease epidemics from viruses spread by mosquitoes are happening more often. For most viruses spread by mosquitoes, no vaccines or specific medicines are available. Globally, the health challenge posed by mosquitoes is severe. The WHO reports that in 2020, there were an estimated 241 million cases of malaria worldwide  Tick borne diseases increasingly threaten the health of people in the United States. The CDC reports that each year, approximately 30,000 cases of Lyme disease are reported to CDC.  While recent estimates based on insurance records suggest that approximately 476,000 people are treated for Lyme disease each year in the United States.  DEET (N,N-Diethyl-meta-toluamide) is considered the gold-standard active for broad spectrum efficacy and safety. However, products with DEET have a very unpleasant odor and skin feel, melt plastic, and are perceived by some consumers as containing an unsafe chemical.   Products with other synthetic actives can be somewhat more pleasant to use than DEET products and do not harm plastic, but do not meet DEET's effectiveness. Additionally, because they are synthetic, each may still be perceived with suspicion by consumers (who believe they may be putting poison on their skin). There are several natural essential oil actives that are pleasant to use, perceived as safe but have very limited effectiveness or relatively short effective time. Some natural products attempt to match DEET's effectiveness by increasing concentration of essential oils to high levels and thus become polarizing in their smell and feel (pungent and unpleasant).  Furthermore, two of the EPA approved natural actives limit claims to mosquitoes or have no time claims on the label. The search continues for the perfect insect repellent active.  This NSF project tested fatty acid actives derived from coconut or palm oil.  Although fatty acids have seen widespread human use in cosmetic applications and as dietary supplements, no one has used them for a skin-applied, broad-spectrum insect repellent.  This project saw the opportunity of finally achieving the widespread, effective skin-applied insect repellent to support public health and prevent insect-borne disease. A novel-for-human-use insect repellent was designed to achieve a high insect repellency, over an extended time via a delivery system that is created from a skin care product chassis. As such, it has pleasant scent and skin feel aesthetics. Additionally, it contains recognizable ingredients that are viewed as safe to apply to skin (e.g., per EWG) and are economical, even for developing geographies. This will encourage consumers to be proactive in protecting themselves against insect bites and thus the likelihood of contacting insect borne disease.          Last Modified: 07/27/2022       Submitted by: Kim D Benz]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
