<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[UNS: Interfacial Properties of Nanoconfined Ionic Liquid]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>167168.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>167168</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Nora Savage</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>nosavage@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927949</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[#1511626&lt;br/&gt;Min, Younjin&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Ionic liquids (ILs) are a relatively new class of liquids that consist only of cations and anions. Some of the useful properties of typical ILs are their negligibly low vapor pressure, fire resistance, excellent chemical and thermal stability, wide liquid temperature ranges, and wide electrochemical windows. Given these excellent properties, ILs have been used or considered for use in organic synthesis, catalysis, chemical separation, and fuel and solar cells, and their applications continue to expand. Despite a plethora of emerging processes involving ILs, however, an understanding of the interfacial properties of ILs under confinement, such as rheological properties and glass transition temperatures, remain very limited compared with that of other confined material classes, such as polymers, electrolyte solutions, and liquid crystals. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The objective of the proposed work is twofold: (i) to obtain relationships describing how the structure, viscosity, and glass transition temperature of ILs depend on degree of confinement (separation) and (ii) to obtain a fundamental understanding of how the molecular parameters of confined ILs, such as the relative sizes and shapes of cations and anions and the surface properties of confining surfaces, such as surface potential and degree of hydrophobicity, affect the abovementioned properties under nanoconfinement. Our main hypothesis is that when the dimension of confinement becomes comparable to the Debye screening length of ILs, the confined glass transition temperature deviates from the bulk glass transition temperature. This hypothesis will primarily be tested with the surface forces apparatus technique, which is a unique technique that can link molecular studies to meso-scale studies and also to bulk-scale studies. This work will be first of its kind to directly measure the viscosity and glass transition temperature of ILs under dynamically controlled nanoconfined environments. From a fundamental science perspective, the proposed work represents an important step in understanding the structure/property relationships of ILs under confinement. Such an understanding may ultimately lead to new fundamental insights into a systematic method to select an ion pair(s) for the rational design of ILs operating under nanoconfined environments and with the desired physical properties. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will first provide pivotal guidelines to select desirable types of ILs on demand on the basis of their important interfacial properties under nanoconfinement. Such knowledge will be useful to optimize and design applications involving confined ILs, such as batteries, solar cells, and lubricants. The educational plan consists of three main components that will focus on the research supervision of students, teaching, mentoring, and outreach to interface with the research components of the project. These components include the (i) development of a new graduate course on the interfacial phenomena of soft matter to be taught by the PI, (ii) mentoring of underrepresented undergraduate students in research, and (iii) dissemination of the project outcomes to the general public in the Akron area, where the minority constitutes 25% of the total population, by reliance on the connections established with local high school teachers through an educational electronic device development grant funded by NSF.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/08/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/08/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2015653</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Younjin</FirstName>
<LastName>Min</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Younjin Min</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[younjinm@ucr.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000644483</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/08/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Riverside</Name>
<CityName>RIVERSIDE</CityName>
<ZipCode>925210001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9518275535</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>200 UNIVERSTY OFC BUILDING</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>41</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA41</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>MR5QC5FCAVH5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA AT RIVERSIDE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Riverside]]></Name>
<CityName>Riverside</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>925210001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[245 University Office Building]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>41</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA41</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1414</Code>
<Text>INTERFAC PROCESSES &amp; THERMODYN</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>057E</Code>
<Text>Thermodynamics</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01001516DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~167168</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Ionic liquids, having melting points less than 100 &deg;C, are organic salts consisting entirely of ions. Negligibly low vapor pressure, fire resistance, excellent chemical and thermal stability, wide liquid temperature ranges, and wide electrochemical windows are examples of the useful properties of typical ionic liquids (ILs). Because of these excellent properties, ILs have been used or considered for use in catalysis, chemical separation, hazardous chemical storage and transportation, lubrication, batteries and polymer gel electrolytes, fuel and solar cells, and their applications continue to expand. In spite of a plethora of emerging processes involving ionic liquids, the understanding of structure, dynamics, and physicochemical properties of ILs under confinement is still very limited compared to that of other material classes such as polymers, electrolyte solutions, and liquid crystals. This project has filled several knowledge gaps regarding the dynamics, molecular organization, flow behavior, and thermal characteristics of ionic liquids under nanoconfinement.</p> <p>In particular, the role of surface chemistry on the intermolecular interactions and force-distance profiles of ionic liquids has been established. The forces between ionic liquids across hydrophilic surfaces have been found to show stronger order and larger magnitudes compared to that across hydrophobic surfaces. In addition, we have determined how the surface chemistry influences the viscosity of nanoconfined ionic liquids. The bulk viscosity does not demonstrate any significant change with respect to the surface chemistry. On the other hand, below length scales of 20-25 nm, nonlinear viscosity trends can emerge depending on the relatively size of ionic liquid molecular, structural anisotropy of ionic liquid, and the nature of interactions between the confining surface and ionic liquid adsorbates. One of the key outcomes of the project is the establishment of friction phase diagram of ionic liquids under nanoconfinement, which describes the effects of time scales on frictional dissipation. Another outcome of the project is the revelation of the fact that while bulk ionic liquid display Newtonian behavior, nanoconfined ILs display shear-thinning behavior (i.e., non-Newtonian). Shear-thinning behavior had become more intense as the degree of nanoconfinement increased (i.e., the separation decreased). As number of ion layers increases in the gap (confined zone), shear thinning phenomenon, as well as magnitude of force responses gradually diminish, giving rise to decrease of absolute value of viscosity.</p> <p class="NSFText">This project has involved four components of integrating research and education. The first component has achieved an increased participation of minority students in academic research; the second component has contributed to curriculum development; and the third component has facilitated the training of graduate students who are capable of functioning successfully as independent investigators in academic, governmental, or industrial research positions. The work has been broadly disseminated through presentations by the PIs and students at informal public science talks, conferences, and departmental seminars.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/30/2021<br>      Modified by: Younjin&nbsp;Min</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2015653/2015653_10366682_1630376183870_Ionicliquid--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2015653/2015653_10366682_1630376183870_Ionicliquid--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Some Ionic Liquids"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2015653/2015653_10366682_1630376183870_Ionicliquid--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Some Ionic Liquids"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Molecular structures of some of the ionic liquids utilized in this project</div> <div class="imageCredit">Younjin Min</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Younjin&nbsp;Min</div> <div class="imageTitle">Some Ionic Liquids</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Ionic liquids, having melting points less than 100 &deg;C, are organic salts consisting entirely of ions. Negligibly low vapor pressure, fire resistance, excellent chemical and thermal stability, wide liquid temperature ranges, and wide electrochemical windows are examples of the useful properties of typical ionic liquids (ILs). Because of these excellent properties, ILs have been used or considered for use in catalysis, chemical separation, hazardous chemical storage and transportation, lubrication, batteries and polymer gel electrolytes, fuel and solar cells, and their applications continue to expand. In spite of a plethora of emerging processes involving ionic liquids, the understanding of structure, dynamics, and physicochemical properties of ILs under confinement is still very limited compared to that of other material classes such as polymers, electrolyte solutions, and liquid crystals. This project has filled several knowledge gaps regarding the dynamics, molecular organization, flow behavior, and thermal characteristics of ionic liquids under nanoconfinement.  In particular, the role of surface chemistry on the intermolecular interactions and force-distance profiles of ionic liquids has been established. The forces between ionic liquids across hydrophilic surfaces have been found to show stronger order and larger magnitudes compared to that across hydrophobic surfaces. In addition, we have determined how the surface chemistry influences the viscosity of nanoconfined ionic liquids. The bulk viscosity does not demonstrate any significant change with respect to the surface chemistry. On the other hand, below length scales of 20-25 nm, nonlinear viscosity trends can emerge depending on the relatively size of ionic liquid molecular, structural anisotropy of ionic liquid, and the nature of interactions between the confining surface and ionic liquid adsorbates. One of the key outcomes of the project is the establishment of friction phase diagram of ionic liquids under nanoconfinement, which describes the effects of time scales on frictional dissipation. Another outcome of the project is the revelation of the fact that while bulk ionic liquid display Newtonian behavior, nanoconfined ILs display shear-thinning behavior (i.e., non-Newtonian). Shear-thinning behavior had become more intense as the degree of nanoconfinement increased (i.e., the separation decreased). As number of ion layers increases in the gap (confined zone), shear thinning phenomenon, as well as magnitude of force responses gradually diminish, giving rise to decrease of absolute value of viscosity. This project has involved four components of integrating research and education. The first component has achieved an increased participation of minority students in academic research; the second component has contributed to curriculum development; and the third component has facilitated the training of graduate students who are capable of functioning successfully as independent investigators in academic, governmental, or industrial research positions. The work has been broadly disseminated through presentations by the PIs and students at informal public science talks, conferences, and departmental seminars.       Last Modified: 08/30/2021       Submitted by: Younjin Min]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
