<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Correlated Graphical Models for High-Dimensional Heterogeneous Data: Theory, Optimization, and Applications]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>100000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>100000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Yong Zeng</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>yzeng@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927299</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This project is motivated by the pressing need for analyzing modern high-dimensional heterogeneous data from multiple sources. Driven by high-throughput biotechnologies, it is increasingly common to have multiple types of measurements on the same set of subjects. Integration of heterogeneous data types is the key to gaining fundamental knowledge on biological processes. Complex characteristics of modern biological data also result in challenges for data analysis and statistical modeling. This project will contribute to theoretical and methodological development through novel graphical models suitable for fusing correlated and mixed data from static and dynamic conditions. These approaches have great potential to translate rich data into meaningful knowledge. The new statistical methods and theories will also advance modern statistical science. The resulting products of this project will provide valuable software tools to scientific communities. This research will promote curriculum development, student training, and educational outreach.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Multimodal data from different experimental platforms have different properties and characteristics. In many systems, including biological processes, regulation is modularized and temporally dynamic in nature. Common regulatory principles exist in certain related biological conditions. This project will focus on the development of new data integration methods and theories through novel correlated graphical models from a frequentist inference perspective. The methods will be based on exponential Markov random fields beyond the traditional Gaussian assumption. The new methods will allow for network discovery for high-dimensional heterogeneous data from multiple static and dynamic conditions. This project also involves the development of efficient algorithms for complex optimization problems incorporating the structure-inducing regularization mechanism.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/28/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/28/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2015481</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yuping</FirstName>
<LastName>Zhang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Yuping Zhang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[yuping.zhang@uconn.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000671033</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/28/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Connecticut</Name>
<CityName>STORRS</CityName>
<ZipCode>062691133</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8604863622</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>438 WHITNEY RD EXTENSION UNIT 11</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CT02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>WNTPS995QBM7</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CONNECTICUT</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>D9SNFDRCW3W7</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Connecticut]]></Name>
<CityName>Storrs</CityName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>062694098</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[215 Glenbrook Road, Unit 4098]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CT02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1269</Code>
<Text>STATISTICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~100000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>High-dimensional heterogeneous data from multiple sources are commonly observed in many fields. This project made contributions to theoretical and methodological development on novel graphical models suitable for fusing correlated and mixed data from static and dynamic conditions. Specifically, we developed a statistical learning framework for multiple mixed graphical models via a penalized approximate likelihood estimation. We also developed a fast algorithm for variational maximum likelihood inference approach, which takes advantage of the log-determinant relaxation. We exploited the block diagonal structure of the solution and identified a simple necessary and sufficient condition to identify the connected components in the solution to determine the block diagonal structure. We then employed a divide-and-conquer approach to the joint structural inference problem for multiple related large sparse networks. Moreover, we developed a joint learning framework for mixed pairwise exponential graphical models conditionally specified by heterogeneous multi-parameter exponential families based on pseudo-likelihood regularized by a hierarchical group lasso penalty. We made comparisons of these methods both numerically and theoretically. Furthermore, we developed a new statistical framework for joint structural estimation of time&#8208;varying mixed graphical models based on multivariate data over a series of time points. We applied our newly developed methods to cancer biology and neuroscience network research.&nbsp;</p> <p>In addition, we developed publicly available software tools for the newly developed methods.&nbsp;</p> <p>This project also contributed to curriculum development, student training, and educational outreach.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/02/2023<br>      Modified by: Yuping&nbsp;Zhang</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ High-dimensional heterogeneous data from multiple sources are commonly observed in many fields. This project made contributions to theoretical and methodological development on novel graphical models suitable for fusing correlated and mixed data from static and dynamic conditions. Specifically, we developed a statistical learning framework for multiple mixed graphical models via a penalized approximate likelihood estimation. We also developed a fast algorithm for variational maximum likelihood inference approach, which takes advantage of the log-determinant relaxation. We exploited the block diagonal structure of the solution and identified a simple necessary and sufficient condition to identify the connected components in the solution to determine the block diagonal structure. We then employed a divide-and-conquer approach to the joint structural inference problem for multiple related large sparse networks. Moreover, we developed a joint learning framework for mixed pairwise exponential graphical models conditionally specified by heterogeneous multi-parameter exponential families based on pseudo-likelihood regularized by a hierarchical group lasso penalty. We made comparisons of these methods both numerically and theoretically. Furthermore, we developed a new statistical framework for joint structural estimation of time&#8208;varying mixed graphical models based on multivariate data over a series of time points. We applied our newly developed methods to cancer biology and neuroscience network research.   In addition, we developed publicly available software tools for the newly developed methods.   This project also contributed to curriculum development, student training, and educational outreach.       Last Modified: 10/02/2023       Submitted by: Yuping Zhang]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
