<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  High Precision Coaxial Magnetic Gear]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>225000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>225000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ela Mirowski</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>emirowsk@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922936</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is to investigate applications of a new high-performance mechanical gearbox. Electric motors account for approximately 23 percent of electricity consumed in the United States and roughly 63 percent of manufacturing sector electricity.  An improvement in geared motor technology can help realize energy savings.  A magnetic gear creates speed change without any physical contact, requires no gear lubrication, has inherent overload protection, has low acoustic emissions and low starting torque. Due to its contact-free torque production, a magnetic gear has the potential for a long lifetime while operating at high efficiency.  This project will advance the development of a magnetic gearbox, with many potential applications.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project explores the trade space of magnetic gearboxes with regard to efficiency, thermal stability, and torque density and the potential trade-offs with respect to cost.  Multiphysics-based numerical and analytic modeling co-design techniques will be utilized to explore the thermal and mechanical sizing trade-offs impacting the efficiency of the magnetic gears while mitigating magnet demagnetization. The proposed designs will utilize a unique laminated magnet array combined with the laminated slotted modulator.  The project will explore the design trade-offs with respect to stack length and mechanical deflection in the context of the magnetic and thermal design.  The project will demonstrate the efficiency and performance capabilities of a magnetic gearbox compared with an equivalently sized mechanically geared motor.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/15/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/15/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2015163</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Bertrand</FirstName>
<LastName>DeChant</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Bertrand W DeChant</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[bdech@fluxmagic.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000811792</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/15/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>FLUXMAGIC, INC.</Name>
<CityName>PORTLAND</CityName>
<ZipCode>972014811</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7044211864</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2828 S CORBETT AVE STE 113</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OR01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>M2KCJ9MANNA9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>FLUXMAGIC, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[FluxMagic, Inc.]]></Name>
<CityName>Portland</CityName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<ZipCode>972014815</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2828 SW Corbett Ave, Suite 214C]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OR01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8034</Code>
<Text>Hardware Components</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~225000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project investigated the performance potential of coaxial magnetic gears. A coaxial magnetic gear<strong> </strong>uses magnetic field space-modulation to create torque and speed change without physical contact. The magnetic gears non-contact operation eliminates mechanical gear contact loss which can yield increased conversion efficiency. The non-contact operation also significantly increases the gear service life and eliminates the need for regular lubrication. A magnetic gear also provides inherent overload protection, since if the magnetic gear is over-torqued, the poles will simply slip past one another. In contrast, a mechanical gearbox would catastrophically fail due to broken gear teeth or structure.</p> <p>This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project involved testing two new types of coaxial magnetic gears. The project focused on designing, building, and testing of a new type of contra-rotating magnetic gear water thruster as well as a new type of hermetically sealed magnetically geared water thruster. The project explored the trade space of magnetic gearboxes regarding efficiency, thermal stability, and torque density and the trade-offs between these and cost. A multiphysics-based numerical co-design analysis technique was used to explore the thermal and mechanical sizing trade-offs impacting the efficiency of the magnetic gears while mitigating failure such as thermal magnet demagnetization. The magnetic gear designs used a unique modulation and magnet arrangement that improved their manufacturability and lowered cost. This project also explored the torque density design trade-offs with respect to axial stack length and radial mechanical deflection in the context of the magnetic and thermal design limits.</p> <p>The project focused on the use of magnetic gearing for water thruster applications. Magnetic gearing could enable novel designs to greatly increase water thruster performance while also improving the reliability of water thruster technology. The commercial development of a magnetic gear thruster for electric watercraft may also improve the ride performance of electric boats by enabling new configurations and operating conditions. This is expected to also result in a more efficient and reliable alternative to conventional water propulsion technology.</p> <p>More generally, the use of magnetic gearing could benefit society by increasing the energy conversion efficiency of drive train technology. Mechanical gearboxes are extensively utilized throughout the economy for increasing speed and decreasing the torque requirements for motors thereby decreasing the drives size and cost.&nbsp; Therefore, the clear end-user demonstration of high-torque density magnetic gears that this project investigated has the potential to transform a broad range of energy conversion technologies and provide a significant positive impact to the economy.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/19/2022<br>      Modified by: Bertrand&nbsp;W&nbsp;Dechant</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project investigated the performance potential of coaxial magnetic gears. A coaxial magnetic gear uses magnetic field space-modulation to create torque and speed change without physical contact. The magnetic gears non-contact operation eliminates mechanical gear contact loss which can yield increased conversion efficiency. The non-contact operation also significantly increases the gear service life and eliminates the need for regular lubrication. A magnetic gear also provides inherent overload protection, since if the magnetic gear is over-torqued, the poles will simply slip past one another. In contrast, a mechanical gearbox would catastrophically fail due to broken gear teeth or structure.  This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project involved testing two new types of coaxial magnetic gears. The project focused on designing, building, and testing of a new type of contra-rotating magnetic gear water thruster as well as a new type of hermetically sealed magnetically geared water thruster. The project explored the trade space of magnetic gearboxes regarding efficiency, thermal stability, and torque density and the trade-offs between these and cost. A multiphysics-based numerical co-design analysis technique was used to explore the thermal and mechanical sizing trade-offs impacting the efficiency of the magnetic gears while mitigating failure such as thermal magnet demagnetization. The magnetic gear designs used a unique modulation and magnet arrangement that improved their manufacturability and lowered cost. This project also explored the torque density design trade-offs with respect to axial stack length and radial mechanical deflection in the context of the magnetic and thermal design limits.  The project focused on the use of magnetic gearing for water thruster applications. Magnetic gearing could enable novel designs to greatly increase water thruster performance while also improving the reliability of water thruster technology. The commercial development of a magnetic gear thruster for electric watercraft may also improve the ride performance of electric boats by enabling new configurations and operating conditions. This is expected to also result in a more efficient and reliable alternative to conventional water propulsion technology.  More generally, the use of magnetic gearing could benefit society by increasing the energy conversion efficiency of drive train technology. Mechanical gearboxes are extensively utilized throughout the economy for increasing speed and decreasing the torque requirements for motors thereby decreasing the drives size and cost.  Therefore, the clear end-user demonstration of high-torque density magnetic gears that this project investigated has the potential to transform a broad range of energy conversion technologies and provide a significant positive impact to the economy.          Last Modified: 02/19/2022       Submitted by: Bertrand W Dechant]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
