<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Scalable Production of Platform Chemicals from Inedible Biomass and CO2]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>225000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>225000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anna Brady</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>abrady@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927077</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is enable the production of sustainably-sourced plastics offering superior performance at lower cost than conventional petroleum-sourced plastics. The technology in this project produces materials from CO2 and inedible biomass. It dramatically lowers the manufacturing cost by eliminating more than half the steps required by traditional methods. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This SBIR Phase I project proposes to develop process chemistry conditions for the continuous oxidation of furfural to furoic acid using air as the oxidant. Furfural is a feedstock chemical produced industrially from diverse inedible (lignocellulosic) biomass sources. Furfural oxidation is a key step in the process for producing FDCA. The proposed project will advance the translation by demonstrating that oxidation can take place under continuous flow at high rates and conversions using operating conditions (flow rate, concentration, pressure, etc.) amenable to high-volume production. This project will evaluate a suite of reaction parameters and a collection of catalysts under continuous liquid and air flow to find optimal conditions. A preliminary assessment of catalyst stability under high-performance conditions will also be performed.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/07/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/08/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041, 47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2015157</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Aanindeeta</FirstName>
<LastName>Banerjee</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Aanindeeta Banerjee</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[banerjee.guddie@gmail.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000816035</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/07/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>RESOURCE CHEMICAL CORP.</Name>
<CityName>PALO ALTO</CityName>
<ZipCode>943041135</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6174618271</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1450 COLUMBIA CT</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>QN9FQ2DMNRJ5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESOURCE CHEMICAL CORP</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[RESOURCE CHEMICAL CORP.]]></Name>
<CityName>Palo Alto</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>943041135</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1450 Columbia Ct]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8030</Code>
<Text>Chemical Technology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~225000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>ReSource Chemical Corp. aims to replace chemicals made from petroleum with sustainably sourced chemicals that offer superior performance at a competitive cost. For our first product, we are commercializing a process to manufacture furan-2,5-dicarboxylic acid (FDCA) from CO<sub>2</sub> and furfural, a commodity feedstock made exclusively from inedible biomass (lignocellulose). FDCA is used to make polyesters such as polyethylene furanoate (PEF) that have superior performance compared to PET, the world?s 2<sup>nd</sup> largest commodity polymer. FDCA technologies developed in industry over the past 20 years require edible fructose feedstocks and are limited by high process complexity and high costs. ReSource has proprietary chemistry and chemical process technology to produce FDCA using ~1/3 the process steps as the state-of-the-art fructose-based technology, which would make it possible to produce FDCA-based polyesters that are cost-competitive with PET. Because it uses truly sustainable feedstocks, the ReSource process also makes it possible to produce FDCA that is carbon negative (cradle-to-gate).</p> <p>The focus of the SBIR Phase I project was an oxidation step, in which furfural is oxidized over a catalyst using air as the oxidant to produce 2-furoic acid, the intermediate in our process for FDCA production. The goals of the project were to gain greater insight into the reaction pathways that are operative under conditions that are desirable for high-volume production and to evaluate a reactor design for continuous operation. The experimental results provided a key insight into the furfural oxidation pathway and revealed the operating conditions that result in high yields of furoic acid when the reaction is performed at high concentration, which is critical for minimizing the overall energy demand of the process. The findings from the Phase I project support two reactor design options for performing the furfural oxidation step continuously in an integrated process for FDCA production. These options will be compared directly in the next development phase. In addition to advancing the ReSource technology, the fundamental chemical knowledge gained by the project is relevant to improving the performance of other oxidation reactions of interest for production of fine and commodity chemicals.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/29/2022<br>      Modified by: Aanindeeta&nbsp;Banerjee</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ ReSource Chemical Corp. aims to replace chemicals made from petroleum with sustainably sourced chemicals that offer superior performance at a competitive cost. For our first product, we are commercializing a process to manufacture furan-2,5-dicarboxylic acid (FDCA) from CO2 and furfural, a commodity feedstock made exclusively from inedible biomass (lignocellulose). FDCA is used to make polyesters such as polyethylene furanoate (PEF) that have superior performance compared to PET, the world?s 2nd largest commodity polymer. FDCA technologies developed in industry over the past 20 years require edible fructose feedstocks and are limited by high process complexity and high costs. ReSource has proprietary chemistry and chemical process technology to produce FDCA using ~1/3 the process steps as the state-of-the-art fructose-based technology, which would make it possible to produce FDCA-based polyesters that are cost-competitive with PET. Because it uses truly sustainable feedstocks, the ReSource process also makes it possible to produce FDCA that is carbon negative (cradle-to-gate).  The focus of the SBIR Phase I project was an oxidation step, in which furfural is oxidized over a catalyst using air as the oxidant to produce 2-furoic acid, the intermediate in our process for FDCA production. The goals of the project were to gain greater insight into the reaction pathways that are operative under conditions that are desirable for high-volume production and to evaluate a reactor design for continuous operation. The experimental results provided a key insight into the furfural oxidation pathway and revealed the operating conditions that result in high yields of furoic acid when the reaction is performed at high concentration, which is critical for minimizing the overall energy demand of the process. The findings from the Phase I project support two reactor design options for performing the furfural oxidation step continuously in an integrated process for FDCA production. These options will be compared directly in the next development phase. In addition to advancing the ReSource technology, the fundamental chemical knowledge gained by the project is relevant to improving the performance of other oxidation reactions of interest for production of fine and commodity chemicals.          Last Modified: 09/29/2022       Submitted by: Aanindeeta Banerjee]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
