<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  The role of gravity in advanced materials manufacturing for the era of digital transformation]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>225000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>245000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Muralidharan Nair</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mnair@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927059</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is the development, design, and optimization of new materials in the absence of gravity.  The current approach to in-space manufacturing is primarily trial-and-error.  The proposed technology will advance a systematic approach to in-space manufacturing, enabling the development of new materials with better properties and cost-competitive associated infrastructure. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project will advance the translation of material development in zero-G environments. Chemical formulations of known materials may be unstable under the effect of body forces, but the mechanisms through which these forces impact the phase diagram remain unknown. This project will integrate experimental, computational, and machine learning techniques to identify material formulations amenable to zero-G manufacturing.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/04/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/05/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041, 47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2015155</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ioana</FirstName>
<LastName>Cozmuta</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ioana Cozmuta</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ioana@zerogspace.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000805700</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/04/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>G-SPACE, INC</Name>
<CityName>SUNNYVALE</CityName>
<ZipCode>940871559</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5106711789</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1266 PARKINGTON AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>L4RAYANJN337</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>G-SPACE INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[G-Space, Inc]]></Name>
<CityName>Sunnyvale</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>940871559</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1266 Parkington Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8091</Code>
<Text>SBIR Outreach &amp; Tech. Assist</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>024E</Code>
<Text>MATERIALS DESIGN</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1218</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED TECHNOLOGIES &amp; INSTRM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>4080</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED COMP RESEARCH PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~225000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~20000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-960e1866-7fff-c844-0766-18462fc4b45e"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Heavy Metal Fluoride Glasses (HMFG) is the generic term used to refer to hundreds of new fluoride glass forming systems in which ZrF</span><span><span>4</span></span><span> or InF</span><span><span>3</span></span><span> is the glass former which have an optical transparency window spanning from the UV to the mid-IR. HMFGs were discovered around 1974 by the Poulain brothers and their co-workers at the University of Rennes in France. The Poulain brothers later founded Le Verre Fluor?, the French company partnering with G-SPACE on ZBLAN related matters. Amongst all HMFG, ZBLAN with a base formulation of 53%ZrF</span><span><span>4</span></span><span>-20%BaF</span><span><span>2</span></span><span>-4%LaF</span><span><span>3</span></span><span>-3%AlF</span><span><span>3</span></span><span>-20%NaF, is the most stable and utilized material and has the potential to deliver a solution several orders of magnitude better than current state of the art fiber optics. HMFG are very unstable to devitrification during both bulk glass synthesis and fiber drawing, an instability that requires extremely precise process control. This instability is rarely acknowledged or understood by the current players attempting to manufacture superior ZBLAN through in-space manufacturing.</span><span> </span><span>Leveraging on the microgravity environment, in-space manufacturing (ISM) has the potential to expand the region of stability in which HMFG glasses can be processed. Quantifying thermophysical property changes during microgravity processing is quintessential in establishing microgravity process control and requires a systematic approach to understand the structural and morphological changes responsible for the devitrification of ZBLAN to minimize crystallization in conjunction with the absence of gravity. Since experimentation in space is not feasible to the extent required here, during the NSF SBIR Phases I award, G-SPACE established feasibility for a combination of terrestrial levitation, physics modeling and atomistic simulations to downselect promising formulations for eventual ISM demonstration embedded under the ATOM? software platform.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Under this Phase I G-SPACE has developed and demonstrated for the first time a terrestrial levitation procedure to rapidly determine formulations and corresponding parameters for optimal in-space processing together with the ATOM? software analytics capabilities for automatic processing of levitation data and extraction of the impact of the gravitational force on thermophysical properties of interest.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The G-SPACE team has successfully developed, built, and populated the ATOM</span><span><span>TM</span></span><span> software architecture with meaningful initial data such as a formulation database, microgravity thermophysical properties, physics models for mechanism elucidation, and heat transfer and fiber optics performance design for ISM process improvement that allowed the company to expand its user base into other applications and use cases.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>In addition, G-SPACE developed a conceptual design of a modern levitation facility (GEMS* - patent pending) to be built in Phase II which is optimized to overcome inherent limitations of existing terrestrial levitation facilities</span><span> that will also consider versatility in the type of samples that it can process (materials, biological, etc.). The GEMS facility will also represent a key US national asset.</span></p> <div><span><br /></span></div> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/15/2022<br>      Modified by: Ioana&nbsp;Cozmuta</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2015155/2015155_10692655_1660592099979_Image_NSF_Support_NoCapt--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2015155/2015155_10692655_1660592099979_Image_NSF_Support_NoCapt--rgov-800width.jpg" title="G-SPACE Final Outcome Image"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2015155/2015155_10692655_1660592099979_Image_NSF_Support_NoCapt--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="G-SPACE Final Outcome Image"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Snapshots of ZBLAN showing various states of the glass during terrestrial levitation and corresponding ATOM(TM) analytics</div> <div class="imageCredit">G-SPACE, Inc</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Ioana&nbsp;Cozmuta</div> <div class="imageTitle">G-SPACE Final Outcome Image</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   Heavy Metal Fluoride Glasses (HMFG) is the generic term used to refer to hundreds of new fluoride glass forming systems in which ZrF4 or InF3 is the glass former which have an optical transparency window spanning from the UV to the mid-IR. HMFGs were discovered around 1974 by the Poulain brothers and their co-workers at the University of Rennes in France. The Poulain brothers later founded Le Verre Fluor?, the French company partnering with G-SPACE on ZBLAN related matters. Amongst all HMFG, ZBLAN with a base formulation of 53%ZrF4-20%BaF2-4%LaF3-3%AlF3-20%NaF, is the most stable and utilized material and has the potential to deliver a solution several orders of magnitude better than current state of the art fiber optics. HMFG are very unstable to devitrification during both bulk glass synthesis and fiber drawing, an instability that requires extremely precise process control. This instability is rarely acknowledged or understood by the current players attempting to manufacture superior ZBLAN through in-space manufacturing. Leveraging on the microgravity environment, in-space manufacturing (ISM) has the potential to expand the region of stability in which HMFG glasses can be processed. Quantifying thermophysical property changes during microgravity processing is quintessential in establishing microgravity process control and requires a systematic approach to understand the structural and morphological changes responsible for the devitrification of ZBLAN to minimize crystallization in conjunction with the absence of gravity. Since experimentation in space is not feasible to the extent required here, during the NSF SBIR Phases I award, G-SPACE established feasibility for a combination of terrestrial levitation, physics modeling and atomistic simulations to downselect promising formulations for eventual ISM demonstration embedded under the ATOM? software platform. Under this Phase I G-SPACE has developed and demonstrated for the first time a terrestrial levitation procedure to rapidly determine formulations and corresponding parameters for optimal in-space processing together with the ATOM? software analytics capabilities for automatic processing of levitation data and extraction of the impact of the gravitational force on thermophysical properties of interest.  The G-SPACE team has successfully developed, built, and populated the ATOMTM software architecture with meaningful initial data such as a formulation database, microgravity thermophysical properties, physics models for mechanism elucidation, and heat transfer and fiber optics performance design for ISM process improvement that allowed the company to expand its user base into other applications and use cases. In addition, G-SPACE developed a conceptual design of a modern levitation facility (GEMS* - patent pending) to be built in Phase II which is optimized to overcome inherent limitations of existing terrestrial levitation facilities that will also consider versatility in the type of samples that it can process (materials, biological, etc.). The GEMS facility will also represent a key US national asset.               Last Modified: 08/15/2022       Submitted by: Ioana Cozmuta]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
