<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution/UNOLS Fleet: The future of marine gravimetry for geophysical research by the UNOLS academic research vessel fleet]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>348146.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>348146</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06040100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OCE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>James Holik</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jholik@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927711</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The Potential Field Pool Equipment (PFPE) operated out of Wood Hole Oceanographic Institution (WHOI) provides marine gravimeter expertise, instrumentation and support to the United States oceanographic community, specifically the Academic Research Fleet (ARF). They propose to acquire a new DgS high-resolution advance technology (AT) marine gravimeter and integrate this new gravity acquisition system into the fleet of BGM-3 marine gravimeters currently in use. PFPE is funded by the US National Science Foundation (NSF) and has been operating for several decades in support of academic potential fields measurements on research ships. Current BGM-3 gravimeter systems used in the ARF are between 30-40 years old. While these gravimeters produce excellent data, they contain electromechanical sensors that require extensive maintenance and care in handling/shipping, and they are ITAR (International Traffic in Arms Regulations) classified. New-generation gravimeters will provide significant advantage in operations and maintenance over time and are not subject to ITAR controls. One meter is proposed here:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;DgS AT gravimeter $348,146 &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts&lt;br/&gt;The principal impact of the present proposal is under Merit Review Criterion 2 of the Proposal Guidelines (NSF 19-602). It provides infrastructure support for scientists to use the vessel and its shared-use instrumentation in support of their NSF-funded oceanographic research projects (which individually undergo separate review by the relevant research program of NSF).  The acquisition, maintenance and operation of shared-use instrumentation allows NSF-funded researchers from any US university or lab access to working, calibrated instruments for their research, reducing the cost of that research, and expanding the base of potential researchers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/13/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/13/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2015229</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Masako</FirstName>
<LastName>Tominaga</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Masako Tominaga</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mtominaga@whoi.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000559263</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/13/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
<LastName>Fornari</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Daniel J Fornari</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[dfornari@whoi.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000123842</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/13/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution</Name>
<CityName>WOODS HOLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>025431535</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5082893542</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>266 WOODS HOLE RD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>GFKFBWG2TV98</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WOODS HOLE OCEANOGRAPHIC INSTITUTION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution]]></Name>
<CityName>Woods Hole</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>025431535</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[360 Woods Hole Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5413</Code>
<Text>OCEANOGRAPHIC INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~348146</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="p1">Having new-generation gravimeters that can be easily installed on research vessels in UNOLS (University-National Oceanographic Laboratory System) vessels, as well as ships of opportunity that will be operating in remote regions of the global ocean, without constraints imposed by ITAR (International Traffic in Arms Regulations) restrictions, is an important future goal for both marine geophysics and the strategic needs of the United States. Current BGM3 gravimeter systems used in the US academic research fleet are ~30-40 years old. While these gravimeters produce excellent data, they contain electromechanical sensors that require extensive maintenance and care in handling/shipping, and they are ITAR classified. The periodic calibration procedure for the BGM3 sensor is also ITAR classified. The Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution?s (WHOI) Shipboard Scientific Services Group (SSSG) maintains a facility --the Potential Fields Pool Equipment (PFPE) ? that helps UNOLS shipboard technical groups in the operation and maintenance of the fleet of 9-10 BGM3 gravimeters provided by PFPE that are installed onboard US oceanographic academic research vessels.</p> <p class="p1">High-resolution gravimeters with precision mechanical sensors that are not ITAR classed are now available. These new systems are commercially available from companies in the USA and would provide equivalent resolution marine gravity data (compared to the BGM3 systems), and hence would result in a vast improvement on the flexibility of transport and installation of a marine gravity system on a greater number of available research ships and in more remote regions of the global ocean. These remote areas are where sea surface gravity data are of high value to calibrate gravity models based on satellite gravity and to provide resolution unavailable by satellite gravity models.&nbsp;</p> <p>The Dynamic Gravity Systems (DgS) Advanced Technology (AT) marine gravity system represents the latest advancements in dynamic gravity survey meters. AT gravimeters feature completely redesigned electronics for both data acquisition and control of the system. The Advanced Technology meter follows the long line of reliability and performance established by Lacoste and Romberg (L-R) with their first stable platform, model S, marine gravity meter in the early 1960s. The heart of the DgS Advanced Technology meter features instantaneous, full force feedback beam control that keeps the beam locked at the reading line of the sensor. Errors, normally induced when the beam is not at the reading line in non-feedback systems, are virtually eliminated. There is no requirement for a counter screw and spring tension motor to drive the beam back to the reading line position. As a result, the mechanical errors and faults associated with both counter screw and spring tension are vastly reduced. The state of the art digital control system requires minimal operator input and virtually no calibration once the system has left the factory.</p> <p>A summary of our accomplishments for this project are:</p> <p>Procurement and testing of the WHOI-PFPE DgS AT1 marine gravimeter (sn017).</p> <p>Side-by-side comparison between a BGM3 gravimeter, and the new DgS gravimeter meter, both on land and at sea.</p> <p>Four (4) research cruises have been conducted with the PFPE DgS gravimeter over the past 2 years (in conjunction with simultaneous BGM3 gravity data collection) and the system is currently installed on RV T. Thompson (U. Washington) and will remain installed through CY2022.</p> <p>Conducted quality assessment of DgS gravity data with respect to well-known characteristics of BGM3 gravity data collected concurrently with DgS gravity acquisition in a variety of seafloor and tectonic environments in a variety of marine weather conditions.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/22/2022<br>      Modified by: Daniel&nbsp;J&nbsp;Fornari</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2015229/2015229_10664109_1650619501288_AR49-figures-small_Page_2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2015229/2015229_10664109_1650619501288_AR49-figures-small_Page_2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="figures for Final Report of new marine gravimeter project"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2015229/2015229_10664109_1650619501288_AR49-figures-small_Page_2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="figures for Final Report of new marine gravimeter project"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">caption included in figure file</div> <div class="imageCredit">Daniel Fornari</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Daniel&nbsp;J&nbsp;Fornari</div> <div class="imageTitle">figures for Final Report of new marine gravimeter project</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2015229/2015229_10664109_1650619417215_AR49-figures-small_Page_1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2015229/2015229_10664109_1650619417215_AR49-figures-small_Page_1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="figures for Final Report of new marine gravimeter project"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2015229/2015229_10664109_1650619417215_AR49-figures-small_Page_1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="figures for Final Report of new marine gravimeter project"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">captions included in each figure</div> <div class="imageCredit">Daniel Fornari</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Daniel&nbsp;J&nbsp;Fornari</div> <div class="imageTitle">figures for Final Report of new marine gravimeter project</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2015229/2015229_10664109_1650619553399_AR49-figures-small_Page_3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2015229/2015229_10664109_1650619553399_AR49-figures-small_Page_3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="figures for Final Report of new marine gravimeter project"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2015229/2015229_10664109_1650619553399_AR49-figures-small_Page_3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="figures for Final Report of new marine gravimeter project"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">caption included in figure file</div> <div class="imageCredit">Daniel Fornari</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Daniel&nbsp;J&nbsp;Fornari</div> <div class="imageTitle">figures for Final Report of new marine gravimeter project</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[Having new-generation gravimeters that can be easily installed on research vessels in UNOLS (University-National Oceanographic Laboratory System) vessels, as well as ships of opportunity that will be operating in remote regions of the global ocean, without constraints imposed by ITAR (International Traffic in Arms Regulations) restrictions, is an important future goal for both marine geophysics and the strategic needs of the United States. Current BGM3 gravimeter systems used in the US academic research fleet are ~30-40 years old. While these gravimeters produce excellent data, they contain electromechanical sensors that require extensive maintenance and care in handling/shipping, and they are ITAR classified. The periodic calibration procedure for the BGM3 sensor is also ITAR classified. The Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution?s (WHOI) Shipboard Scientific Services Group (SSSG) maintains a facility --the Potential Fields Pool Equipment (PFPE) ? that helps UNOLS shipboard technical groups in the operation and maintenance of the fleet of 9-10 BGM3 gravimeters provided by PFPE that are installed onboard US oceanographic academic research vessels. High-resolution gravimeters with precision mechanical sensors that are not ITAR classed are now available. These new systems are commercially available from companies in the USA and would provide equivalent resolution marine gravity data (compared to the BGM3 systems), and hence would result in a vast improvement on the flexibility of transport and installation of a marine gravity system on a greater number of available research ships and in more remote regions of the global ocean. These remote areas are where sea surface gravity data are of high value to calibrate gravity models based on satellite gravity and to provide resolution unavailable by satellite gravity models.   The Dynamic Gravity Systems (DgS) Advanced Technology (AT) marine gravity system represents the latest advancements in dynamic gravity survey meters. AT gravimeters feature completely redesigned electronics for both data acquisition and control of the system. The Advanced Technology meter follows the long line of reliability and performance established by Lacoste and Romberg (L-R) with their first stable platform, model S, marine gravity meter in the early 1960s. The heart of the DgS Advanced Technology meter features instantaneous, full force feedback beam control that keeps the beam locked at the reading line of the sensor. Errors, normally induced when the beam is not at the reading line in non-feedback systems, are virtually eliminated. There is no requirement for a counter screw and spring tension motor to drive the beam back to the reading line position. As a result, the mechanical errors and faults associated with both counter screw and spring tension are vastly reduced. The state of the art digital control system requires minimal operator input and virtually no calibration once the system has left the factory.  A summary of our accomplishments for this project are:  Procurement and testing of the WHOI-PFPE DgS AT1 marine gravimeter (sn017).  Side-by-side comparison between a BGM3 gravimeter, and the new DgS gravimeter meter, both on land and at sea.  Four (4) research cruises have been conducted with the PFPE DgS gravimeter over the past 2 years (in conjunction with simultaneous BGM3 gravity data collection) and the system is currently installed on RV T. Thompson (U. Washington) and will remain installed through CY2022.  Conducted quality assessment of DgS gravity data with respect to well-known characteristics of BGM3 gravity data collected concurrently with DgS gravity acquisition in a variety of seafloor and tectonic environments in a variety of marine weather conditions.          Last Modified: 04/22/2022       Submitted by: Daniel J Fornari]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
