<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Rapid-scanning Ultrafast Imaging Microscope for Material Inspection]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>225000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>225000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Benaiah Schrag</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bschrag@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928323</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader/commercial impact of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project will develop and demonstrate a novel imaging microscopy technique for next-generation semiconductor defect inspection and material characterization. The technique is based on ultrafast spectroscopy and is uniquely able to measure functional material parameters over a rapidly raster-scanned image. The semiconductor industry relies on process control to maintain high yield and to prevent the propagation of faults through the manufacturing process.  Semiconductor inspection represents a market of nearly $5 B in size and generates an estimated 15% of spending in the semiconductor industry. As the materials used in semiconductor devices evolve, so too must the inspection techniques. Many next-generation materials for various applications, such as solar energy and displays, are not pristine single crystals, and their inspection requires new technologies.  The proposed project will advance the development of the next-generation materials.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The intellectual merit of this project is to investigate translation of real-time imaging via ultrafast spectroscopy. The primary challenge of this project is that ultrafast spectroscopy scans at a single point typically take seconds to minutes, and a useful imaging system must raster a point excitation over a wide area containing thousands of pixels. This Phase I effort will develop a method and metrics for this technique, using images with substantially fewer samples. The project will explore methods to measure trapped states and defects that degrade semiconductor functionality. Performance goals include accelerating the speed of single-point spectroscopy by two orders of magnitude. Longer-term goals include integration of ultrafast spectroscopy with microscopy for materials analysis.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/14/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/14/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2015068</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Eric</FirstName>
<LastName>Martin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Eric Martin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[emartin@monstrsense.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000793713</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/14/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>MONSTR SENSE TECHNOLOGIES, LLC</Name>
<CityName>ANN ARBOR</CityName>
<ZipCode>481082053</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4233212076</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3830 PACKARD ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[STE. 150]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>WF7ZJCQ4CL35</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MONSTR SENSE TECHNOLOGIES, LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[MONSTR SENSE TECHNOLOGIES, LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>481034728</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1108 W MADISON ST]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>090E</Code>
<Text>Chem/Bio and Physical Diagnostics</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~225000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-d4859d23-7fff-973f-b7e2-426d9667a8b7"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><strong>Motivation</strong></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Most defects in silicon are identified by shining white light on the wafer surface and using machine learning algorithms to find imperfections. These tools have high computing power and imaging speed, but the image metric (intensity of reflected or scattered light) provides little to no information about the defect. For next-generation semiconductors, these standard inspection tools are not sufficient. Compound semiconductors such as gallium nitride (GaN) and silicon carbide (SiC) contain millions times more defects than silicon, and white light inspection tools cannot distinguish the killer defects in these materials. The situation has become a focus of the semiconductor industry as the use of compound semiconductors has spiked due to massive consumer demand for electric vehicles, 5G technology, and full-spectrum LEDs.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Advanced imaging tools, such as photoluminescence imaging, are beginning to find their way into semiconductor fabs out of necessity. However, photoluminescence imaging is fundamentally too slow to measure full wafers with high resolution. A likely candidate for redefining semiconductor inspection is nonlinear imaging with ultrafast lasers. Ultrafast spectroscopies are already becoming an essential tool for material science engineers to measure trapped states and defects that degrade semiconductor functionalities. The tools also do not have the fundamental speed limits of photoluminescence imaging.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><strong>Project Overview</strong></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Ultrafast spectroscopic scans are prohibitively slow to be measured over a substantial number of pixels, but in this NSF SBIR Phase I project, we demonstrate a way to acquire useful information from ultrafast measurements in a fraction of the time. The result is that we are able to measure large, high-resolution images that we use to identify defects and map energy loss in real time.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The goals of the project were to demonstrate that ultrafast imaging could be implemented with a fast image acquisition rate and to apply the imaging tool to a few semiconductor samples of interest. Through customer discovery we identified a few prime targets for the application demonstrations. First, we confirmed that our beachhead market is convinced by ultrafast applications in 2D materials, a class of materials that has exhibited tremendous growth in research labs. Second, we found large industry interest in defect inspection in compound semiconductors. In the Phase I effort we show promising and marketable results in both of these application areas.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><strong>Key R&amp;D Outcomes</strong></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>We developed a novel approach to ultrafast lifetime imaging. Through an innovative procedural design that focuses on image acquisition, we are now able to acquire ultrafast lifetime images in seconds that previously required hours.</span></p> <p dir="ltr">The technical development effort involved two parts: First, we developed and demonstrated a laser-scanning microscope called <a href="https://monstrsense.com/products/nessie/" target="_blank">NESSIE</a> that is optimized for semiconductor research applications, many of which require that the sample is mounted in a cryostat. Second, we integrated the microscope with BIGFOOT, an ultrafast spectrometer that MONSTR Sense developed independently. The full integration for rapid imaging required us to make substantial advancements in the hardware, electronics, and software designs. We also developed a version of the microscope that can access blue wavelengths down to 380 nm for measuring GaN-based materials and SiC.</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Our Phase I technical development efforts resulted in a new MONSTR Sense product, a provisional patent, and a publication accepted in Optics Letters.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Beyond the technical development work we also began validating ultrafast imaging for defect inspection in next-generation semiconductors. We tested the capability of ultrafast imaging to reveal semiconductor defects in compound semiconductors. Our test results showed that the technique provides a rapid alternative to the current state-of-the-art advanced imaging tools that the semiconductor industry has been trying to implement.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>We also demonstrated ultrafast imaging for measuring next-generation semiconductors that have not left the lab yet, specifically 2D materials. Because ultrafast techniques are well suited for measuring energy transfer, the research community that develops heterostructures of 2D materials commonly uses ultrafast techniques. Because the samples are small and inhomogeneous, we were able to show in the SBIR project that ultrafast imaging is the clear next step for characterizing 2D materials and heterostructures in these labs.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><strong>Broader Impact</strong></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The NSF SBIR Phase I project has had a profound impact on the commercial focus of MONSTR Sense and, as a result, the potential of ultrafast technology. This grant funding enabled the research and customer discovery time required for the founders to find commercial opportunities outside of fundamental research. Starting as an ultrafast spectroscopy company that develops tools for scientists, we have distilled the most commercially useful aspects of our technology and merged it with imaging. The resulting imaging technology is now positioned to solve large process control problems in the semiconductor industry. Ultimately, this project will benefit a broader community as it has helped successfully bridge the gap between fundamental research and viable technology.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/23/2021<br>      Modified by: Eric&nbsp;Martin</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2015068/2015068_10670872_1632430540636_NESSIEsmall--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2015068/2015068_10670872_1632430540636_NESSIEsmall--rgov-800width.jpg" title="NESSIE prototype"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2015068/2015068_10670872_1632430540636_NESSIEsmall--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="NESSIE prototype"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Laser-scanning microscope designed for imaging with ultrafast laser-based techniques.</div> <div class="imageCredit">MONSTR Sense Technologies, LLC</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Eric&nbsp;Martin</div> <div class="imageTitle">NESSIE prototype</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2015068/2015068_10670872_1632430747066_Fig3_MoSe2_LIcomp--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2015068/2015068_10670872_1632430747066_Fig3_MoSe2_LIcomp--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Novel detection scheme developed"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2015068/2015068_10670872_1632430747066_Fig3_MoSe2_LIcomp--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Novel detection scheme developed"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Conventional detection schemes either do not suppress spurious modulations (I), or they introduce blurring between pixels (II). The Box lock-in provides the least correlation between pixels, most suppression of spurious signals, and best signal-to-noise ratio (SNR).</div> <div class="imageCredit">MONSTR Sense Technologies, LLC</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Eric&nbsp;Martin</div> <div class="imageTitle">Novel detection scheme developed</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2015068/2015068_10670872_1632430858944_Fig1_Patent--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2015068/2015068_10670872_1632430858944_Fig1_Patent--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Ultrafast imaging of 2D material semiconductor heterostructure"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2015068/2015068_10670872_1632430858944_Fig1_Patent--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Ultrafast imaging of 2D material semiconductor heterostructure"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Images of the overlapping 2D material heterostructure region are measured as a function of a pulse delay to reveal the ultrafast decay time in the each pixel of the false-color image.</div> <div class="imageCredit">MONSTR Sense Technologies, LLC</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Eric&nbsp;Martin</div> <div class="imageTitle">Ultrafast imaging of 2D material semiconductor heterostructure</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2015068/2015068_10670872_1632431525845_GaAs_FWM_imaging--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2015068/2015068_10670872_1632431525845_GaAs_FWM_imaging--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Defects measured in compound semiconductor"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2015068/2015068_10670872_1632431525845_GaAs_FWM_imaging--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Defects measured in compound semiconductor"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Compound semiconductor gallium arsenide is measured with three imaging modalities of the NESSIE prototype. (a) Standard white light imaging reveal surface defects. Laser-scanned (b) resonant linear and (c) four-wave mixing (FWM) reveal the heightened sensitivity of these modalities over white light.</div> <div class="imageCredit">MONSTR Sense Technologies, LLC</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Eric&nbsp;Martin</div> <div class="imageTitle">Defects measured in compound semiconductor</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   Motivation Most defects in silicon are identified by shining white light on the wafer surface and using machine learning algorithms to find imperfections. These tools have high computing power and imaging speed, but the image metric (intensity of reflected or scattered light) provides little to no information about the defect. For next-generation semiconductors, these standard inspection tools are not sufficient. Compound semiconductors such as gallium nitride (GaN) and silicon carbide (SiC) contain millions times more defects than silicon, and white light inspection tools cannot distinguish the killer defects in these materials. The situation has become a focus of the semiconductor industry as the use of compound semiconductors has spiked due to massive consumer demand for electric vehicles, 5G technology, and full-spectrum LEDs. Advanced imaging tools, such as photoluminescence imaging, are beginning to find their way into semiconductor fabs out of necessity. However, photoluminescence imaging is fundamentally too slow to measure full wafers with high resolution. A likely candidate for redefining semiconductor inspection is nonlinear imaging with ultrafast lasers. Ultrafast spectroscopies are already becoming an essential tool for material science engineers to measure trapped states and defects that degrade semiconductor functionalities. The tools also do not have the fundamental speed limits of photoluminescence imaging. Project Overview Ultrafast spectroscopic scans are prohibitively slow to be measured over a substantial number of pixels, but in this NSF SBIR Phase I project, we demonstrate a way to acquire useful information from ultrafast measurements in a fraction of the time. The result is that we are able to measure large, high-resolution images that we use to identify defects and map energy loss in real time. The goals of the project were to demonstrate that ultrafast imaging could be implemented with a fast image acquisition rate and to apply the imaging tool to a few semiconductor samples of interest. Through customer discovery we identified a few prime targets for the application demonstrations. First, we confirmed that our beachhead market is convinced by ultrafast applications in 2D materials, a class of materials that has exhibited tremendous growth in research labs. Second, we found large industry interest in defect inspection in compound semiconductors. In the Phase I effort we show promising and marketable results in both of these application areas. Key R&amp;D Outcomes We developed a novel approach to ultrafast lifetime imaging. Through an innovative procedural design that focuses on image acquisition, we are now able to acquire ultrafast lifetime images in seconds that previously required hours. The technical development effort involved two parts: First, we developed and demonstrated a laser-scanning microscope called NESSIE that is optimized for semiconductor research applications, many of which require that the sample is mounted in a cryostat. Second, we integrated the microscope with BIGFOOT, an ultrafast spectrometer that MONSTR Sense developed independently. The full integration for rapid imaging required us to make substantial advancements in the hardware, electronics, and software designs. We also developed a version of the microscope that can access blue wavelengths down to 380 nm for measuring GaN-based materials and SiC. Our Phase I technical development efforts resulted in a new MONSTR Sense product, a provisional patent, and a publication accepted in Optics Letters. Beyond the technical development work we also began validating ultrafast imaging for defect inspection in next-generation semiconductors. We tested the capability of ultrafast imaging to reveal semiconductor defects in compound semiconductors. Our test results showed that the technique provides a rapid alternative to the current state-of-the-art advanced imaging tools that the semiconductor industry has been trying to implement. We also demonstrated ultrafast imaging for measuring next-generation semiconductors that have not left the lab yet, specifically 2D materials. Because ultrafast techniques are well suited for measuring energy transfer, the research community that develops heterostructures of 2D materials commonly uses ultrafast techniques. Because the samples are small and inhomogeneous, we were able to show in the SBIR project that ultrafast imaging is the clear next step for characterizing 2D materials and heterostructures in these labs. Broader Impact The NSF SBIR Phase I project has had a profound impact on the commercial focus of MONSTR Sense and, as a result, the potential of ultrafast technology. This grant funding enabled the research and customer discovery time required for the founders to find commercial opportunities outside of fundamental research. Starting as an ultrafast spectroscopy company that develops tools for scientists, we have distilled the most commercially useful aspects of our technology and merged it with imaging. The resulting imaging technology is now positioned to solve large process control problems in the semiconductor industry. Ultimately, this project will benefit a broader community as it has helped successfully bridge the gap between fundamental research and viable technology.          Last Modified: 09/23/2021       Submitted by: Eric Martin]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
