<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Groundwater resilience to hydrologic extremes and climate variability: The case of Hurricane Dorian]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>49104.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>49104</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Laura Lautz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>llautz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927775</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The impact of Hurricane Dorian (September 2019) was catastrophic, especially in Grand Bahama, where the hurricane generated a storm surge that drove extensive flooding and saltwater contamination of the groundwater resources of the island. Groundwater, in the form of freshwater lenses (FWLs), is the sole source of drinking water on the island. It is unclear how quickly FWLs recover from saltwater contamination, and how that recovery is driven by the intensity, duration, and frequency of precipitation during the wet season and the characteristics of groundwater aquifers. The overarching goal of this study is to understand how the rate of recovery of FWLs that have been impacted by storm-induced salinization is connected to climatological characteristics (intensity, duration and frequency of precipitation) and how future FWL recovery will be affected by elevated sea level and extended periods of drought induced by climate change, as well as the human response to these events, such as excessive pumping activity. The study will provide opportunities for training and international research experiences for undergraduate and graduate students, as well as engagement with stakeholders in the region impacted by saltwater intrusion.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;It is hypothesized that the rate of recovery of freshwater lenses (FWLs) impacted by storm-induced saltwater intrusion is primarily driven by climatic variability and climate change. This study will enable the collection of time-sensitive, perishable groundwater data pertaining to storm-induced saltwater intrusion on the island of Grand Bahama following Hurricane Dorian. These datasets will later be used to build a robust three-dimensional, density dependent model to simulate the saltwater intrusion process in the FWL system and accurately predict the seawater intrusion extent, its temporal dynamics and the flushing process, as well as the combined effect of climate stressors such as sea level rise and change in recharge. The ultimate goal is to develop a framework that combines seasonal forecasts of precipitation with state-of-the art numerical models to assess the impact of climatic variability and climate change on the rate of recovery of the FWLs. This project will provide training opportunities and international research experiences to students at Sacramento State, which is a Hispanic Serving Institution and an Asian American and Native American Pacific Islander Serving Institution, and at Florida Institute of Technology. The citizen science data collection initiative will provide opportunities to local high school students and students from University of the Bahamas to interact and participate in the generation of scientific knowledge. Local water management authorities will benefit from the generation of new data. Subsequent development of models based on these data will be available to the local authorities and will assist them in decision making and planning procedures.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/07/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/07/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2015311</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Zoi</FirstName>
<LastName>Dokou</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Zoi Dokou</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[zoi.dokou@csus.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000786748</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/07/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Efthymios</FirstName>
<LastName>Nikolopoulos</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Efthymios Nikolopoulos</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[efthymios.nikolopoulos@rutgers.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000795294</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/07/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University Enterprises, Incorporated</Name>
<CityName>SACRAMENTO</CityName>
<ZipCode>958192605</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9162786402</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>6000 J ST STE 3700</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[BOOKSTORE BLDG]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>N58JMBDDUGU7</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY ENTERPRISES, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[California State University, Sacramento]]></Name>
<CityName>Sacramento</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>958192605</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[6000 J Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1579</Code>
<Text>Hydrologic Sciences</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~49104</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>In September 2019, hurricane Dorian hit the northernmost islands of the Bahamas as a Category 5 storm. Its impact was catastrophic in Grand Bahama, where it generated a storm surge that resulted in extensive flooding and salinization of the groundwater resources of the island, which is the sole source of water for the local communities in the form of freshwater lens (FWL). The aim of this RAPID award was to collect time-sensitive, perishable data on groundwater and soil salinity that will help us understand how the groundwater recovery rate after this disturbance is affected by climatic variability and anthropogenic activities.&nbsp;</p> <p>The key outcomes of the project are the following:&nbsp; a) the compilation of a unique database of transient data of soil and groundwater salinity and groundwater levels post hurricane Dorian b) a MS thesis on the development of groundwater model that simulates lateral and storm-induced salinization on the island, c) two conference presentations, at the American Geophysical Union Fall Meeting 2020 and at the Sustainable Grand Bahama conference in 2022 d) a manuscript to be submitted to the International Journal of Bahamian Studies in collaboration with faculty from the University of the Bahamas, as an effort to disseminate our results to the local community (in preparation). e) a Data in Brief article describing the dataset (in preparation). The database created as part of this project was published, per NSF guidelines, in a permanent data repository and can be found at 10.5281/zenodo.6509571.</p> <p><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Intellectual Merit</span></strong></p> <p>The main contribution of this project was the compilation of a time sensitive, unique data of soil and groundwater salinity and levels collected post hurricane that provide important insight on the resilience of water resources in small tropical islands. Based on the results and the persistence of highly elevated salinity levels, well above drinking standards, it is estimated that FWL recovery to pre-hurricane state will require many years, thus posing significant risk on socioeconomic activities and the environment of the island. This unique dataset was used to build a robust three-dimensional, density dependent model to simulate the saltwater intrusion process in the FWL system and accurately predict the seawater intrusion extent, its temporal dynamics and the flushing process. This model will also be used to study the combined effect of climate stressors such as sea level rise and change in recharge with anthropogenic impacts such as overdraft. The ultimate goal is to develop a framework that combines climate forecasts with state-of-the art numerical models to assess the impact of climatic variability and climate change on the rate of recovery of the FWL.&nbsp;</p> <p><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Broader Impacts</span></strong></p> <p>This project provided training opportunities and international research experiences to undergraduate and graduate students at California State University, Sacramento, which is a Hispanic Serving Institution and an Asian American and Native American Pacific Islander Serving Institution, and at Florida Institute of Technology. Three students were trained as part of this project in data collection and analysis. One student from California State University, Sacramento was trained in groundwater modeling with emphasis on density-dependent processes, as part of her MS thesis research. The results of this project were used and will continue to be used by the PI and co-PI as part of their courses, to expose students to real world, current challenges in environmental engineering. Faculty and students from University of the Bahamas also participated in the data collection and generation of scientific knowledge, as part of the project. Local water management authorities can use this new dataset and the subsequent development of a modeling framework this dataset will support, as they develop a sustainable water resources plan to strengthen the resilience of the island.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/20/2022<br>      Modified by: Zoi&nbsp;Dokou</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2015311/2015311_10649067_1653079423505_PineforestHurricaneDorian--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2015311/2015311_10649067_1653079423505_PineforestHurricaneDorian--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Pine Forest in Grand Bahama"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2015311/2015311_10649067_1653079423505_PineforestHurricaneDorian--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Pine Forest in Grand Bahama"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Grand Bahama?s pine forest was severely damaged by hurricane Dorian. Many pine trees were destroyed by the high winds but also many died due to saltwater toxicity.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Nivea Mazzoni</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Zoi&nbsp;Dokou</div> <div class="imageTitle">Pine Forest in Grand Bahama</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2015311/2015311_10649067_1653080038573_GB_SEAWAT_Model_Results--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2015311/2015311_10649067_1653080038573_GB_SEAWAT_Model_Results--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Grand Bahama SEAWAT Model"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2015311/2015311_10649067_1653080038573_GB_SEAWAT_Model_Results--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Grand Bahama SEAWAT Model"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Map of simulated groundwater levels and TDS on Grand Bahama Island post-hurricane Dorian.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Layla Al Baghdadi, Zoi Dokou</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Zoi&nbsp;Dokou</div> <div class="imageTitle">Grand Bahama SEAWAT Model</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ In September 2019, hurricane Dorian hit the northernmost islands of the Bahamas as a Category 5 storm. Its impact was catastrophic in Grand Bahama, where it generated a storm surge that resulted in extensive flooding and salinization of the groundwater resources of the island, which is the sole source of water for the local communities in the form of freshwater lens (FWL). The aim of this RAPID award was to collect time-sensitive, perishable data on groundwater and soil salinity that will help us understand how the groundwater recovery rate after this disturbance is affected by climatic variability and anthropogenic activities.   The key outcomes of the project are the following:  a) the compilation of a unique database of transient data of soil and groundwater salinity and groundwater levels post hurricane Dorian b) a MS thesis on the development of groundwater model that simulates lateral and storm-induced salinization on the island, c) two conference presentations, at the American Geophysical Union Fall Meeting 2020 and at the Sustainable Grand Bahama conference in 2022 d) a manuscript to be submitted to the International Journal of Bahamian Studies in collaboration with faculty from the University of the Bahamas, as an effort to disseminate our results to the local community (in preparation). e) a Data in Brief article describing the dataset (in preparation). The database created as part of this project was published, per NSF guidelines, in a permanent data repository and can be found at 10.5281/zenodo.6509571.  Intellectual Merit  The main contribution of this project was the compilation of a time sensitive, unique data of soil and groundwater salinity and levels collected post hurricane that provide important insight on the resilience of water resources in small tropical islands. Based on the results and the persistence of highly elevated salinity levels, well above drinking standards, it is estimated that FWL recovery to pre-hurricane state will require many years, thus posing significant risk on socioeconomic activities and the environment of the island. This unique dataset was used to build a robust three-dimensional, density dependent model to simulate the saltwater intrusion process in the FWL system and accurately predict the seawater intrusion extent, its temporal dynamics and the flushing process. This model will also be used to study the combined effect of climate stressors such as sea level rise and change in recharge with anthropogenic impacts such as overdraft. The ultimate goal is to develop a framework that combines climate forecasts with state-of-the art numerical models to assess the impact of climatic variability and climate change on the rate of recovery of the FWL.   Broader Impacts  This project provided training opportunities and international research experiences to undergraduate and graduate students at California State University, Sacramento, which is a Hispanic Serving Institution and an Asian American and Native American Pacific Islander Serving Institution, and at Florida Institute of Technology. Three students were trained as part of this project in data collection and analysis. One student from California State University, Sacramento was trained in groundwater modeling with emphasis on density-dependent processes, as part of her MS thesis research. The results of this project were used and will continue to be used by the PI and co-PI as part of their courses, to expose students to real world, current challenges in environmental engineering. Faculty and students from University of the Bahamas also participated in the data collection and generation of scientific knowledge, as part of the project. Local water management authorities can use this new dataset and the subsequent development of a modeling framework this dataset will support, as they develop a sustainable water resources plan to strengthen the resilience of the island.           Last Modified: 05/20/2022       Submitted by: Zoi Dokou]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
