<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[STTR Phase I:  Use of Hydroxycinnamic Acids and Their Oligomers as Substitutes for Synthetic Growth Promoting Supplements in Livestock Feeds]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>225000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>225000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anna Brady</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>abrady@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927077</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Technology Transfer (STTR) project is to enhance the health of livestock without addition of synthetic antibiotic and antioxidant compounds. The proposed technologies are corn kernel fiber byproducts of ethanol production from corn. The need for such compounds has grown as livestock is now more often raised in concentrated animal feeding operations that confine animals and result in abnormal oxidative stress. The program is based on extracting these naturally occurring compounds from agricultural residues.  These extracts can be used in place of antibiotics and synthetic supplements currently in livestock feeds.  The process proposed will enable production at a cost competitive with synthetic supplements.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This STTR project proposes to assess the biological activity of hydroxy cinnamic acids and their oligomers (HCAs) as beneficial supplements in livestock feed. They are ester-linked to a hemicellulose known to occur in seed crop brans. The linkage is hydrolyzed during pretreatment of corn bran fiber to prepare it for conversion to ethanol and the HCAs dissolve in the pretreatment solution. As free acids they recover their character, which includes antimicrobial, anti-inflammatory and antioxidant properties. The project will provide kilogram quantities of HCAs for use in feeding trials with young swine, wherein they will be compared with naturally sourced feed supplements currently in use in Europe, as well as un-supplemented feed. Components of the extract will be identified and comprehensive biochemical analyses performed, including study of the gastrointestinal physiology and intestinal permeability. Studies will also be performed of gut microbiomes and how the processes involved are influenced by substitution of HCAs as the primary feed supplement. Successful completion of these studies will provide a basis for more comprehensive studies of the use of HCAs as supplements in the diet of other livestock.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/28/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/23/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041, 47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2015010</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rajai</FirstName>
<LastName>Atalla</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Rajai H Atalla</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[rhatalla@celscint.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000552999</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/28/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gerald</FirstName>
<LastName>Shurson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gerald C Shurson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[shurs001@umn.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000746974</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/28/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Cellulose Sciences International</Name>
<CityName>MADISON</CityName>
<ZipCode>537191293</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6087721123</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>510 CHARMANY DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[STE 259]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>WKJ9YR3HUFZ8</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CELLULOSE SCIENCES INTERNATIONAL, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Cellulose Sciences International]]></Name>
<CityName>Madison</CityName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>537191266</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[510 Charmany Drive, Suite 259]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1505</Code>
<Text>STTR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8030</Code>
<Text>Chemical Technology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~225000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>There is a need for natural animal feed supplements to replace synthetic feed supplements currently used in meat protein production in most parts of the world.</p> <p>The reason is that the synthetics or their metabolites can be carcinogenic for the animal, but more importantly to the people who eventually eat the meat.</p> <p>It was found that corn kernel skin, referred to as pericarp, contains suitable natural compounds, usually identified as phytochemicals,&nbsp; but they are not bioavailable and hence not bioactive. The work carried out under this grant demonstrated that. Furthermore, it has shown that when added to animal feed at the appropriate time and under appropriate conditions, these corn kernel pericarp phytochemicals (CKPP) can outperform the synthetic supplements.</p> <p>The work also revealed that these CKPPs have to be added at the right time in the life cycles of the animals. They were tried on tilapia fish and showed significant effects on growth of the fish, indicating that some of the negative stress that can be associated with growth conditions can be overcome so that the fish can grow more rapidly.</p> <p>The CKPP were also added to the feed of piglets weaned at 3 weeks. In that case there was not much effect, as the stress of early weaning seemed to overwhelm the oxidative stress.</p> <p>Other researchers have studied the effects of similar compounds in swine production by adding them to the feed of the sow about three weeks before she has her litter and continue for four weeks of nursing after she has the litter. They observe significant growth promotion.</p> <p>Other preliminary tests with chickens, also suggest positive effects. In future work we will shift our focus to poultry because they represent the largest source of meat protein available to the public.&nbsp;</p> <p>Collaborators in this work were faculty at the Departent of Animal Science at the Univeersity of Minnesota, and faculty in the Department of Animal and Dairy Science at the University of Wisconsin.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/07/2022<br>      Modified by: Rajai&nbsp;H&nbsp;Atalla</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ There is a need for natural animal feed supplements to replace synthetic feed supplements currently used in meat protein production in most parts of the world.  The reason is that the synthetics or their metabolites can be carcinogenic for the animal, but more importantly to the people who eventually eat the meat.  It was found that corn kernel skin, referred to as pericarp, contains suitable natural compounds, usually identified as phytochemicals,  but they are not bioavailable and hence not bioactive. The work carried out under this grant demonstrated that. Furthermore, it has shown that when added to animal feed at the appropriate time and under appropriate conditions, these corn kernel pericarp phytochemicals (CKPP) can outperform the synthetic supplements.  The work also revealed that these CKPPs have to be added at the right time in the life cycles of the animals. They were tried on tilapia fish and showed significant effects on growth of the fish, indicating that some of the negative stress that can be associated with growth conditions can be overcome so that the fish can grow more rapidly.  The CKPP were also added to the feed of piglets weaned at 3 weeks. In that case there was not much effect, as the stress of early weaning seemed to overwhelm the oxidative stress.  Other researchers have studied the effects of similar compounds in swine production by adding them to the feed of the sow about three weeks before she has her litter and continue for four weeks of nursing after she has the litter. They observe significant growth promotion.  Other preliminary tests with chickens, also suggest positive effects. In future work we will shift our focus to poultry because they represent the largest source of meat protein available to the public.   Collaborators in this work were faculty at the Departent of Animal Science at the Univeersity of Minnesota, and faculty in the Department of Animal and Dairy Science at the University of Wisconsin.          Last Modified: 12/07/2022       Submitted by: Rajai H Atalla]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
