<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Doctoral Dissertation Research: Early Urbanism and Long-Term Technological Change in Material Culture]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>25200.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>25200</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rebecca Ferrell</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rferrell@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927850</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This doctoral dissertation project will utilize geoarchaeological data to advance our knowledge of past people’s relationship with the environment and its natural resources, particularly during periods of significant sociopolitical transformations. In addition to generating new comparative data of ancient ceramics to advance archaeological knowledge of long-term sociopolitical change in prehistory, this project will offer robust datasets to better understand the  social impacts of raw material procurement and use in modern and prehistoric communities. The project will foster collaborative relationships between scholars and students of various academic disciplines, such as geology and materials science, and provide advanced research and training for archaeology students and an underrepresented female minority scholar in STEM. The researchers will also promote interest in local cultural heritage through public outreach and collaborations with modern communities.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project builds upon recent literature on early urban societies by scholars who call for more nuanced understandings of urbanism and its effects on daily life. Urbanization in prehistory involved many changes to people’s everyday lives that enabled them to live in dense, socially differentiated settlements. This project aims to better understand changes to raw material procurement and use in ancient crafting traditions during the transition to an urban society. It is centered on long-term technological changes in pottery production at two sites. The researchers will perform two complementary forms of compositional analysis – Instrumental Neutron Activation Analysis (INAA) and petrography (optical mineralogy) – on ceramic collections from these sites. The compositional data will offer insight into how significant sociopolitical change in the region impacted people’s access to and use of raw materials for craft production. These fine-grained analyses will ultimately offer new geochemical and mineralogical data of pottery from both sites to examine the relationship between early urbanism and long-term technological change in ancient crafting traditions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/21/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/21/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2015823</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jeffrey</FirstName>
<LastName>Blomster</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jeffrey Blomster</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[blomster@gwu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000583922</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/21/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Karleen</FirstName>
<LastName>Ronsairo</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Karleen C Ronsairo</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[kronsairo@gwmail.gwu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000795398</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/21/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>George Washington University</Name>
<CityName>WASHINGTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>200520042</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2029940728</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1918 F ST NW</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>ECR5E2LU5BL6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GEORGE WASHINGTON UNIVERSITY (THE)</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[INAH Oaxaca]]></Name>
<CityName>Oaxaca de Juarez</CityName>
<StateCode/>
<ZipCode>68000</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Pino Suárez 715]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>MX</CountryCode>
<CountryName>Mexico</CountryName>
<StateName>RI REQUIRED</StateName>
<CountryFlag>0</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT/>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>""</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7606</Code>
<Text>Archaeology DDRI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1391</Code>
<Text>ARCHAEOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~25200</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Mixteca Alta Clay Survey &amp; Ceramic Study offers new data to investigate the impact of shifting sociopolitical relations in early urban societies on everyday life. The study examines long-term technological change in pottery production in the Nochixtlan Valley of the Mixteca Alta during the transition to urban ways of life in Middle to Late Formative Oaxaca (500-100 BCE). The main research objective is to gain a better understanding of how early Mixtec urbanization impacted pottery production at two early urban centers, Yucuita and Etlatongo, in the Nochixtlan Valley (Figure 1).</p> <p>Neutron activation analysis (NAA) and ceramic petrography were performed on 200 pottery samples and 48 raw clay samples from the Nochixtlan Valley (Figure 2) to generate new geochemical and mineralogical data of paste recipes from two different time periods in the valley: the Yucuita phase (500-300 BCE) and the Early Ramos phase (300-100 BCE) (Figure 3). The compositional data were used to assess long-term technological changes in potters' paste recipes during the urban transition of Middle to Late Formative Oaxaca.</p> <p>The study offers new avenues for future comparative research of early urban societies throughout the world by providing a more nuanced understanding of the relationship between long-term sociopolitical change and everyday technical practices like craft production. It is innovative in combining geoarchaeological data with archaeological inquiries of early urbanism and long-term technological change to offer new perspectives on past peoples' relationship with the environment and its natural resources, particularly during times of significant sociopolitical transformations in prehistory.</p> <p>This research has fostered collaborative relationships and advanced training and research experience for an underrepresented female minority scholar in STEM. The project has also strengthened collaborative relationships between foreign archaeologists and Mexican archaeologists and community members in Oaxaca (Figure 4), and between archaeologists and professionals of other academic disciplines, such as geology and materials science. The project was a crucial step towards efforts to develop a multiregional database of ceramic compositional data in Oaxaca, thus facilitating future research that will address broader theoretical questions of long-term sociopolitical change in ancient Oaxaca.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/31/2022<br>      Modified by: Karleen&nbsp;C&nbsp;Ronsairo</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2015823/2015823_10665434_1643686197650_MACS2020ClaySampleLocations--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2015823/2015823_10665434_1643686197650_MACS2020ClaySampleLocations--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 2"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2015823/2015823_10665434_1643686197650_MACS2020ClaySampleLocations--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 2"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Geological map of the Nochixtlan Valley, Oaxaca, Mexico showing major bedrock units and archaeological sitse. the black squares represent the clay sampling locations of Mixteca Alta Clay Survey in 2020.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Map by Karleen Ronsairo; modified from INEGI 1984, 1:250,000).</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Karleen&nbsp;C&nbsp;Ronsairo</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 2</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2015823/2015823_10665434_1643685777390_Figure1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2015823/2015823_10665434_1643685777390_Figure1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 1"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2015823/2015823_10665434_1643685777390_Figure1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 1"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Map of archaeological sites and geographical regions of Oaxaca with sampled sites, Yucuita and Etlatongo, in bold.</div> <div class="imageCredit">modfied from Joyce 2013: Figure 1.1</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Karleen&nbsp;C&nbsp;Ronsairo</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 1</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2015823/2015823_10665434_1643686312014_Figure2withredoutline--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2015823/2015823_10665434_1643686312014_Figure2withredoutline--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 3"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2015823/2015823_10665434_1643686312014_Figure2withredoutline--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 3"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Ceramic chronology of Oaxaca, Mexico with the Yucuita and Early Ramos ceramic phases highlighted in red.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Modified from Joyce 2010: Figure 1.6.</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Karleen&nbsp;C&nbsp;Ronsairo</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 3</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2015823/2015823_10665434_1643686903571_unnamed--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2015823/2015823_10665434_1643686903571_unnamed--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 4"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2015823/2015823_10665434_1643686903571_unnamed--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 4"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The Co-PI with Mexican archaeologist and community members from San Juan Yucuita.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Karleen Ronsairo</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Karleen&nbsp;C&nbsp;Ronsairo</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 4</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Mixteca Alta Clay Survey &amp; Ceramic Study offers new data to investigate the impact of shifting sociopolitical relations in early urban societies on everyday life. The study examines long-term technological change in pottery production in the Nochixtlan Valley of the Mixteca Alta during the transition to urban ways of life in Middle to Late Formative Oaxaca (500-100 BCE). The main research objective is to gain a better understanding of how early Mixtec urbanization impacted pottery production at two early urban centers, Yucuita and Etlatongo, in the Nochixtlan Valley (Figure 1).  Neutron activation analysis (NAA) and ceramic petrography were performed on 200 pottery samples and 48 raw clay samples from the Nochixtlan Valley (Figure 2) to generate new geochemical and mineralogical data of paste recipes from two different time periods in the valley: the Yucuita phase (500-300 BCE) and the Early Ramos phase (300-100 BCE) (Figure 3). The compositional data were used to assess long-term technological changes in potters' paste recipes during the urban transition of Middle to Late Formative Oaxaca.  The study offers new avenues for future comparative research of early urban societies throughout the world by providing a more nuanced understanding of the relationship between long-term sociopolitical change and everyday technical practices like craft production. It is innovative in combining geoarchaeological data with archaeological inquiries of early urbanism and long-term technological change to offer new perspectives on past peoples' relationship with the environment and its natural resources, particularly during times of significant sociopolitical transformations in prehistory.  This research has fostered collaborative relationships and advanced training and research experience for an underrepresented female minority scholar in STEM. The project has also strengthened collaborative relationships between foreign archaeologists and Mexican archaeologists and community members in Oaxaca (Figure 4), and between archaeologists and professionals of other academic disciplines, such as geology and materials science. The project was a crucial step towards efforts to develop a multiregional database of ceramic compositional data in Oaxaca, thus facilitating future research that will address broader theoretical questions of long-term sociopolitical change in ancient Oaxaca.       Last Modified: 01/31/2022       Submitted by: Karleen C Ronsairo]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
