<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Field of Dreams: Growing a Diverse Mathematics Community]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>149270.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>149270</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Swatee Naik</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>snaik@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924876</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This award will partially support the November 2020 and November 2021 Field of Dreams Conferences, to be held on the University of Minnesota campus. The Field of Dreams Conference is organized by the Math Alliance, an organization whose goal is to increase the number of students from backgrounds underrepresented in the mathematical sciences who earn doctorates in those fields, and the Institute for Mathematics and its Applications. Approximately 200 undergraduate and terminal MS students will attend the conference, and about 80% of those will be underrepresented minorities. All funds from this award will be used to pay the cost of attendance for some of these students. The conference coordinates with the Math Alliance's Facilitated Graduate Admissions Process (F-GAP), which has helped place an average of about 80 Math Alliance Scholars per year in graduate programs the last six years with very good retention to this point. The conference is an essential part of a program to produce a more diverse professional mathematical workforce. In addition, there are events at the conference which assist faculty in mentoring practices and help academic departments transform their cultures to be more inclusive and supportive of student success.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Field of Dreams conference has several purposes, including: providing information about all aspects of the mathematical sciences professions to students wishing to pursue doctoral studies; providing information about summer research programs and opportunities at the NSF-funded Mathematical Sciences Institutes; facilitating appropriate placement of Math Alliance students in graduate programs; providing professional development in mentoring and cultural competence for our Math Alliance faculty; and serving as a clearinghouse for employment opportunities for new (and recent) Math Alliance doctoral recipients. More information about the Math Alliance is available at www.mathalliance.org. Material from previous years' conferences, are available at https://mathalliance.org/field-of-dreams-conference/, and the page for the 2020 conference is https://mathalliance.org/2020-field-of-dreams-conference/.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/17/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/20/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2015550</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Goldberg</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David Goldberg</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[goldberg@math.purdue.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000094296</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/17/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
<LastName>Spirn</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Daniel P Spirn</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[spirn@math.umn.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000394628</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/17/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Benjamin</FirstName>
<LastName>Brubaker</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Benjamin B Brubaker</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[brubaker@math.umn.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000285157</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/17/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jasmine</FirstName>
<LastName>Foo</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>Y</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jasmine Y Foo</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jyfoo@umn.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000599834</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/17/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Minnesota-Twin Cities</Name>
<CityName>MINNEAPOLIS</CityName>
<ZipCode>554552009</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6126245599</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>200 OAK ST SE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>KABJZBBJ4B54</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MINNESOTA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Minnesota-Twin Cities]]></Name>
<CityName>Minneapolis</CityName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>554550101</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[207 Church St. SE, Lind 400]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1260</Code>
<Text>INFRASTRUCTURE PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~149270</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This grant provided support for the Field of Dreams Conferences held between 2020-2022.&nbsp; The Field of Dreams is the primary activity of the Math Alliance. The&nbsp;Math Alliance is a&nbsp;community of math sciences faculty and students aimed at</p> <ul> <li>increasing the number of doctoral degrees in the mathematical sciences among groups that have been traditionally underrepresented in those fields,</li> <li>improving placement of students from these groups in doctoral programs in disciplines that recruit undergraduate mathematics majors,</li> <li>increasing the number of Ph.D.s from these groups who enter the professoriate in the mathematical sciences as well as other appropriate professions,</li> <li>increasing funded research collaborations among faculty members at the universities with mathematical sciences doctoral programs and faculty members at colleges and universities focused on undergraduate students, and</li> <li>fostering the growth of a community of mathematical scientists that promotes a diverse workforce.</li> </ul> <p>Math Alliance Scholars, who are potential graduate students in the mathematical sciences, participate in programs that have been developed to achieve the above goals.&nbsp;</p> <p>Each fall Math Alliance Scholars, together with their Math Alliance Mentors, meet for the Field of Dreams Conference, which typically hosts between 300-500 participants. During the conference, potential graduate students meet with graduate programs in the mathematical sciences as well as professional opportunities in these fields. Scholars spend time with faculty mentors from the Math Alliance schools, get advice on graduate school applications, and attend seminars on graduate school preparation and expectations as well as career seminars.&nbsp;</p> <p>This grant provided support during two COVID-impacted years and one in-person conference.&nbsp; During the two COVID-impacted years, the Field of Dreams was held in a virtual format.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/29/2023<br>      Modified by: Daniel&nbsp;P&nbsp;Spirn</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This grant provided support for the Field of Dreams Conferences held between 2020-2022.  The Field of Dreams is the primary activity of the Math Alliance. The Math Alliance is a community of math sciences faculty and students aimed at  increasing the number of doctoral degrees in the mathematical sciences among groups that have been traditionally underrepresented in those fields, improving placement of students from these groups in doctoral programs in disciplines that recruit undergraduate mathematics majors, increasing the number of Ph.D.s from these groups who enter the professoriate in the mathematical sciences as well as other appropriate professions, increasing funded research collaborations among faculty members at the universities with mathematical sciences doctoral programs and faculty members at colleges and universities focused on undergraduate students, and fostering the growth of a community of mathematical scientists that promotes a diverse workforce.   Math Alliance Scholars, who are potential graduate students in the mathematical sciences, participate in programs that have been developed to achieve the above goals.   Each fall Math Alliance Scholars, together with their Math Alliance Mentors, meet for the Field of Dreams Conference, which typically hosts between 300-500 participants. During the conference, potential graduate students meet with graduate programs in the mathematical sciences as well as professional opportunities in these fields. Scholars spend time with faculty mentors from the Math Alliance schools, get advice on graduate school applications, and attend seminars on graduate school preparation and expectations as well as career seminars.   This grant provided support during two COVID-impacted years and one in-person conference.  During the two COVID-impacted years, the Field of Dreams was held in a virtual format.         Last Modified: 10/29/2023       Submitted by: Daniel P Spirn]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
