<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Composite Resampling Inference for Dependent Data]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>149961.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>149961</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Yong Zeng</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>yzeng@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927299</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Current statistical methodology for dependent data analysis often relies on specifying an adequate model, which can be difficult in practice.  A potential consequence is that conclusions drawn from an inappropriate or mistaken model may be unreliable or misleading.  The project seeks to develop efficient and accurate statistical methods that are "model-free" or apply without restrictive assumptions about the dependence in data.  A direct benefit of this research will be to provide alternative tools for statistical inference that are not susceptible to model choice or model misspecification.  Therefore, the research will benefit data-based inference in scientific areas such as environmetrics, economics, geology, and astronomy, which encounter different forms of dependent data and where model-free methods can play an important role in data analysis.  The project will also support the professional development of students through graduate student mentoring as well as outreach activities with undergraduate students at local colleges and universities for promoting recruitment and education in statistics and data science.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project particularly aims to produce composite, or hybrid-type, resampling methods that combine strategies for re-using dependent data.  By merging philosophically different resampling techniques (subsampling and bootstrap), the PI will investigate convolved subsampling for nonparametric inference. This new resampling method has wide applicability and favorable performance under mild conditions. For important types of strongly or long-range dependent time series, statistical inference depends heavily on an unknown process index. The PI will study resampling under long-memory and develop a first-ever estimator of this index via a composition of resampling ideas.  Additionally, the PI will develop new empirical likelihood methods for time series and spatial data by combining different resampling devices (data transformations and data blocking) for inference over a variety of dependence structures.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/03/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/03/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2015390</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
<LastName>Nordman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Daniel J Nordman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[dnordman@iastate.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000384157</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/03/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Iowa State University</Name>
<CityName>AMES</CityName>
<ZipCode>500112103</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5152945225</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1350 BEARDSHEAR HALL</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[515 MORRILL ROAD]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Iowa</StateName>
<StateCode>IA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>DQDBM7FGJPC5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>IOWA STATE UNIVERSITY OF SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Iowa State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Ames</CityName>
<StateCode>IA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>500112103</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[505 Morrill Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Iowa</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1269</Code>
<Text>STATISTICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~149961</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The proposed research project addressed the development of new statistical ``data-engineering" methods for dependent or correlated data.&nbsp; For handling such data, current statistical methodology often relies on selecting probability models to accurately represent the data.&nbsp; Because modeling often requires some understanding of the data structure, such models can be difficult to select in practice, especially if data are correlated.&nbsp; Additionally, any conclusions and inference drawn from a mistaken model can be misleading.&nbsp; Hence, it is important to develop alternative methods that allow for valid statistical inference without requiring data models or even strong assumptions about the nature of dependence in data.&nbsp; This research project considered new data-engineering strategies for inference, specfically in the form of hybrid data resampling approaches.&nbsp; The general idea is to create statistics from data and then resample from the same data (i.e., re-use the data) to understand how statistics may change across different data configurations; this is important for making statistical tests and decisions.&nbsp; The investigation focused on new computer-intensive resampling methods that have application for data analysis in many scientific fields which encounter correlated data (e.g., Geophysics, Economics, Environmental/Atmospheric Sciences).&nbsp; Novel and improved statistical methods were developed for varying types of complex data arising in practice, such as network data and graphs, spatial data, functional data, time series data, data from educational experiments, and data related to reliability events and counts.&nbsp; This project also helped to advance professional development and training for several students.&nbsp; At least, six students completed Ph.D. degrees in statistics based on dissertation material related to project research.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/28/2023<br>      Modified by: Daniel&nbsp;J&nbsp;Nordman</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The proposed research project addressed the development of new statistical ``data-engineering" methods for dependent or correlated data.  For handling such data, current statistical methodology often relies on selecting probability models to accurately represent the data.  Because modeling often requires some understanding of the data structure, such models can be difficult to select in practice, especially if data are correlated.  Additionally, any conclusions and inference drawn from a mistaken model can be misleading.  Hence, it is important to develop alternative methods that allow for valid statistical inference without requiring data models or even strong assumptions about the nature of dependence in data.  This research project considered new data-engineering strategies for inference, specfically in the form of hybrid data resampling approaches.  The general idea is to create statistics from data and then resample from the same data (i.e., re-use the data) to understand how statistics may change across different data configurations; this is important for making statistical tests and decisions.  The investigation focused on new computer-intensive resampling methods that have application for data analysis in many scientific fields which encounter correlated data (e.g., Geophysics, Economics, Environmental/Atmospheric Sciences).  Novel and improved statistical methods were developed for varying types of complex data arising in practice, such as network data and graphs, spatial data, functional data, time series data, data from educational experiments, and data related to reliability events and counts.  This project also helped to advance professional development and training for several students.  At least, six students completed Ph.D. degrees in statistics based on dissertation material related to project research.           Last Modified: 09/28/2023       Submitted by: Daniel J Nordman]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
