<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Composite Coatings for Improving Energy Efficiency of Building Envelope Systems]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>224996.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>249996</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Steven Konsek</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is the development of energy efficient building coatings that have the potential to significantly reduce greenhouse gas emissions. The market for energy efficient coatings is experiencing accelerated growth due to government and rapid rise in demand for Leadership in Energy and Environmental Design certified structures. With these recent developments, building developers are actively seeking solutions which are technologically robust and cost-effective for meeting energy mandates. These novel architectural coatings not only provide the aesthetics and textured finish as traditional architectural coatings, but also provide the added benefit of decreasing heating and cooling related costs for the building owner.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is focused on developing an optimized blend of phase change materials for incorporation in architectural building envelope coatings such as paint, plaster and stucco, to provide them with insulative properties. The optimized blend will consist of phase change materials (PCMs) with different phase transition temperatures in specific volume proportions to maximize energy savings in a specific climate zone in terms of heating and cooling costs. Preliminary lab work has shown promise that PCMs can be utilized in coatings to reduce temperature swings and shift the peak load to off-peak hours, which can lead to significant cost savings.  This project will develop protocols to maximize incorporation of PCMs in these coatings without compromising their aesthetics. Energy modeling and experimental work including micro- and macro- scale material characterization will be carried out to verify the laboratory and small field-scale performance of these coatings.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/26/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/20/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2015128</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Aashay</FirstName>
<LastName>Arora</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Aashay Arora</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[aashay@enkoat.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000809774</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/26/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>ENKOAT LLC</Name>
<CityName>PHOENIX</CityName>
<ZipCode>850341700</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4805168729</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>275 N GATEWAY DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[STE 131]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AZ03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>CD9JNRNX3EL8</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ENKOAT LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[EnKoat LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>Phoenix</CityName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>850341700</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[275 N. GateWay Drive, Box 6]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AZ03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8091</Code>
<Text>SBIR Outreach &amp; Tech. Assist</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>123E</Code>
<Text>CENTERS: ADVANCED MATERIALS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8021</Code>
<Text>Materials Engineering</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8022</Code>
<Text>Sustainable Infrastructure Materials</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~249996</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>One of the most critical challenges of the 21<sup>st</sup> century is managing the increasing energy consumption of our nation&rsquo;s building stock. This continuous demand for energy is directly related to carbon emissions, leading to global warming and climate change. In the US, the built environment accounts for over 51% of the overall energy consumption, out of which 39% is related to building operations. A significant amount of energy, ~70% of all building operations, is spent on heating and cooling. These statistics suggest that considerable energy savings can be realized if HVAC loads, which are a major component of building (operations) energy use, can be reduced and optimized.</p> <p>In this Phase I SBIR Project, the team at EnKoat investigated and developed novel building envelope coating formulations to reduce energy consumption in the form of heating and cooling. These coatings are formulated using EnKoat&rsquo;s Active Insulation&trade; technology which utilizes phase change materials (PCMs) to regulate heat transfer through a given system. EnKoat&rsquo;s formulations during this study included three different types of architectural coatings &ndash; waterborne paint, cement-based stucco and gypsum-based plaster. To develop these formulations, the project investigated several different types of PCMs to determine the optimum energy savings. The team developed a computer simulation model for a DOE standard residential building and conducted an elaborate parametric study to determine the effect of climate zone, PCM loading, phase change temperature, coating layer thickness, and layer location within the building on the annual heating and cooling costs. The parametric study helped in developing the optimum formulations of paint, plaster and stucco to obtain the maximum savings in different climate zones, which ranged between 15% and 30%.</p> <p>The optimum formulations were applied to substrates (e.g., concrete, metal, asphalt etc.) typically found in residential and commercial buildings and experimentally tested under controlled temperature and humidity conditions by subjecting them to thermal profiles representative of different climate zones. Results showed peak temperature reductions of 5&deg;C to 10&deg;C as compared to a control, translating into significant energy savings and carbon emissions reduction. Laboratory results were further validated using small scale field testing using a hot-box to measure heat transfer and temperature reduction. The results from this project have been extremely promising and demonstrate the potential for these coatings to be an easy to apply retrofit solution for existing buildings, causing them to become more energy efficient and thermally resilient. Moving forward, the performance of these coatings will be validated at pilot scale on larger structures with a focus towards commercialization.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/13/2021<br>      Modified by: Aashay&nbsp;Arora</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ One of the most critical challenges of the 21st century is managing the increasing energy consumption of our nation’s building stock. This continuous demand for energy is directly related to carbon emissions, leading to global warming and climate change. In the US, the built environment accounts for over 51% of the overall energy consumption, out of which 39% is related to building operations. A significant amount of energy, ~70% of all building operations, is spent on heating and cooling. These statistics suggest that considerable energy savings can be realized if HVAC loads, which are a major component of building (operations) energy use, can be reduced and optimized.  In this Phase I SBIR Project, the team at EnKoat investigated and developed novel building envelope coating formulations to reduce energy consumption in the form of heating and cooling. These coatings are formulated using EnKoat’s Active Insulation&trade; technology which utilizes phase change materials (PCMs) to regulate heat transfer through a given system. EnKoat’s formulations during this study included three different types of architectural coatings &ndash; waterborne paint, cement-based stucco and gypsum-based plaster. To develop these formulations, the project investigated several different types of PCMs to determine the optimum energy savings. The team developed a computer simulation model for a DOE standard residential building and conducted an elaborate parametric study to determine the effect of climate zone, PCM loading, phase change temperature, coating layer thickness, and layer location within the building on the annual heating and cooling costs. The parametric study helped in developing the optimum formulations of paint, plaster and stucco to obtain the maximum savings in different climate zones, which ranged between 15% and 30%.  The optimum formulations were applied to substrates (e.g., concrete, metal, asphalt etc.) typically found in residential and commercial buildings and experimentally tested under controlled temperature and humidity conditions by subjecting them to thermal profiles representative of different climate zones. Results showed peak temperature reductions of 5&deg;C to 10&deg;C as compared to a control, translating into significant energy savings and carbon emissions reduction. Laboratory results were further validated using small scale field testing using a hot-box to measure heat transfer and temperature reduction. The results from this project have been extremely promising and demonstrate the potential for these coatings to be an easy to apply retrofit solution for existing buildings, causing them to become more energy efficient and thermally resilient. Moving forward, the performance of these coatings will be validated at pilot scale on larger structures with a focus towards commercialization.          Last Modified: 09/13/2021       Submitted by: Aashay Arora]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
