<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Creating a Master Transformation Recipient Line for Chloroplast Engineering of Maize]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>225000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>225000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Erik Pierstorff</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>epiersto@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922165</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is to develop environmentally sustainable, higher yielding, pest-resistant biotech crops. Crops of the future need dozens of traits to achieve higher yields and protect themselves against insects, pests, diseases and changing environmental conditions.  The proposed technology will enable efficient production of crops engineered with multiple trait genes, higher efficacy of the desired traits, and faster breeding and seed production to accelerate distribution. Unlike current solutions, the proposed technology ensures that traits will not be transferred to weeds or native plant species via pollen. The initial application is corn, the most valuable commercial crop in the US, with insights expected to enhance other crops. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed project aims to create a chloroplast (plastid) transformation platform for engineering corn. Although chloroplast engineering (transplastomic) technology has been developed successfully in a number of dicot crop species (i.e., tobacco, potato), a reproducible technology has not been developed for any monocot crop (i.e., corn, sorghum). The available evidence indicates that the rate-limiting step is the need for a strong selection system to enable the identification and amplification of rare transformed plastids in the embryogenic tissue culture systems typical for monocots. This project will create a Master Transformation Recipient Line (MTRL) of corn for use in a chloroplast engineering platform. The MTRL will contain a targeted genome deletion in a chloroplast-encoded photosynthetic gene, allowing for development of a new selection system that can lead to successful chloroplast engineering of monocot crops.  Ultimately, the corresponding wild-type chloroplast photosynthetic gene will be delivered to the MTRL with other desired traits, facilitating an elegant selection of transformed plastids with the deleted photosynthetic gene restored and as well as carrying the new traits of interest.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/15/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/15/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2015099</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jeffrey</FirstName>
<LastName>Staub</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jeffrey M Staub</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jeff@plastomics.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000822368</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/15/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>PLASTOMICS INC.</Name>
<CityName>SAINT LOUIS</CityName>
<ZipCode>63132</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3149227117</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1100 CORPORATE SQUARE DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MO01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>KT9NNEYHPH57</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PLASTOMICS INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[PLASTOMICS INC.]]></Name>
<CityName>Saint Louis</CityName>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>631322918</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[975 N. Warson Rd]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MO01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8038</Code>
<Text>Biotechnology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~225000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Chloroplast transgenic (transplastomic) plants were first reported in tobacco almost 30 years ago. The technology has multiple advantages for biotechnology crops, including the ability to introduce multiple beneficial traits at the same time into the chloroplast genome, and maternal inheritance of chloroplasts prevents escape of transgenes into the environment. However, no reproducible chloroplast transformation technology exists for any commercial monocot crop, such as maize. The SBIR funded Phase I project aimed to create a Master Transformation Recipient Line (MTRL) of maize to be used for chloroplast transformation. The MTRL is an non-green line of maize created by inactivating a chloroplast-encoded photosynthetic gene, rendering the MTRL plant incapable of photosynthesis. The MTRL plant is created using targeted transcription activator-like effector (TALE)-based genome editing tools that recognize a specific photosynthetic gene in the chloroplast genome and create deletions or single nucleotide mutations that inactivates the target gene. The non-green MTRL lines that are created then enable chloroplast transformation in a second step using the wild-type unmutated photosynthetic genes to restore the green color of cells in tissue culture while also introducing beneficial trait genes of interest ito the chloroplast genome.</p> <p>Multiple TALE-genome editing tool constructs were created that are delivered to chloroplasts (tered, chloroTALEs) to target inactivation of specific chloroplast-encoded photosynthetic genes. Genome editing tools used included well-known TALENs carrying a FokI nuclease and a more recently characterized genome ?base editor?, TALE-cytosine deaminase. Multiple target sites were chosen within the maize chloroplast genome to create non-photosynthetic mutants. The chloroTALE-editing tools were introduced into the maize nuclear genome via standard methods and numerous independently transformed maize lines were recovered. Maize lines were grown in sterile tissue culture and subsequently transferred to the greenhouse to set seeds.</p> <p>Multiple independent nuclear-transformed maize plants were identified that carried large albino sectors on leaves (Figure), suggesting that the chloroTALE editing enzymes catalyzed inactivation of the targeted chloroplast-encoded photosynthetic genes. Albino leaf sectors were dissected and chloroplast genome sequences were analyzed by PCR and sequencing technologies to confirm that mutations were observed in the targeted chloroplast genes. Plants with albino leaf sectors were grown to maturity in the greenhouse and allowed to set seed. Seeds were germinated and again albino leaf sections were also observed in the seed progeny. These data show that the MTRL approach works and forms the basis for additional experiments to purify MTRL mutant lines.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/24/2022<br>      Modified by: Jeffrey&nbsp;M&nbsp;Staub</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2015099/2015099_10670981_1645722425201_Picture1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2015099/2015099_10670981_1645722425201_Picture1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Mutated maize lines"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2015099/2015099_10670981_1645722425201_Picture1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Mutated maize lines"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Independent maize plants with large albino leaf sectors growing in the greenhouse. Albino sectors carry mutations in a chloroplast-encoded photosynthetic gene, whose inactivation causes the albino phenotype</div> <div class="imageCredit">Plastomics Inc</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jeffrey&nbsp;M&nbsp;Staub</div> <div class="imageTitle">Mutated maize lines</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Chloroplast transgenic (transplastomic) plants were first reported in tobacco almost 30 years ago. The technology has multiple advantages for biotechnology crops, including the ability to introduce multiple beneficial traits at the same time into the chloroplast genome, and maternal inheritance of chloroplasts prevents escape of transgenes into the environment. However, no reproducible chloroplast transformation technology exists for any commercial monocot crop, such as maize. The SBIR funded Phase I project aimed to create a Master Transformation Recipient Line (MTRL) of maize to be used for chloroplast transformation. The MTRL is an non-green line of maize created by inactivating a chloroplast-encoded photosynthetic gene, rendering the MTRL plant incapable of photosynthesis. The MTRL plant is created using targeted transcription activator-like effector (TALE)-based genome editing tools that recognize a specific photosynthetic gene in the chloroplast genome and create deletions or single nucleotide mutations that inactivates the target gene. The non-green MTRL lines that are created then enable chloroplast transformation in a second step using the wild-type unmutated photosynthetic genes to restore the green color of cells in tissue culture while also introducing beneficial trait genes of interest ito the chloroplast genome.  Multiple TALE-genome editing tool constructs were created that are delivered to chloroplasts (tered, chloroTALEs) to target inactivation of specific chloroplast-encoded photosynthetic genes. Genome editing tools used included well-known TALENs carrying a FokI nuclease and a more recently characterized genome ?base editor?, TALE-cytosine deaminase. Multiple target sites were chosen within the maize chloroplast genome to create non-photosynthetic mutants. The chloroTALE-editing tools were introduced into the maize nuclear genome via standard methods and numerous independently transformed maize lines were recovered. Maize lines were grown in sterile tissue culture and subsequently transferred to the greenhouse to set seeds.  Multiple independent nuclear-transformed maize plants were identified that carried large albino sectors on leaves (Figure), suggesting that the chloroTALE editing enzymes catalyzed inactivation of the targeted chloroplast-encoded photosynthetic genes. Albino leaf sectors were dissected and chloroplast genome sequences were analyzed by PCR and sequencing technologies to confirm that mutations were observed in the targeted chloroplast genes. Plants with albino leaf sectors were grown to maturity in the greenhouse and allowed to set seed. Seeds were germinated and again albino leaf sections were also observed in the seed progeny. These data show that the MTRL approach works and forms the basis for additional experiments to purify MTRL mutant lines.           Last Modified: 02/24/2022       Submitted by: Jeffrey M Staub]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
