<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Absolute protein quantitation in in vitro diagnostics for gut inflammation]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>224758.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>224758</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Erik Pierstorff</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>epiersto@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922165</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is the determination of the most accurate method of measuring protein abundance in patient samples. The answers obtained will address a fatal neonatal gut disease, necrotizing enterocolitis, that disproportionately affects African-American preterm infants and lacks disease-modifying treatments. The proposed technology will serve as a clinically-deployable diagnostic for hospitals, reference labs, and drug companies, particularly high-acuity neonatal intensive care units.   The proposed project will advance the development of a diagnostic for an underserved population.  In addition, the development team will include underrepresented innovators. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed project will optimize the choice of reference standard and detection method for protein abundance.  Absolute quantification is a prerequisite for data interpretation and validation between experiments, laboratories, and testing platforms.  Current clinical practice exploits only a single type of mutation that gives rise to disease; rarely do they address a target protein with extensive polymorphic variation that is age- and race-dependent. The goal of this proposal is to develop reference clinically robust standards to enable use of a new candidate biomarker in hospital pathology settings. Research objectives include:  (1) identification of optimal reference standard composition for two common methods to quantify biomolecules in clinical settings and (2) understanding usage limitations of these reference standards in the background of high sequence variation in the human population.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/15/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/09/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041, 47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2015077</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sunyoung</FirstName>
<LastName>Kim</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sunyoung Kim</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[sunny@chosendiagnostics.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000521162</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/15/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>CHOSEN DIAGNOSTICS INC</Name>
<CityName>NEW ORLEANS</CityName>
<ZipCode>701122714</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5042644314</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1441 CANAL ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[STE 321]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
<StateCode>LA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>LA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>C67UDPUEB6D3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CHOSEN DIAGNOSTICS INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>GDTNTEC6W745</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[CHOSEN DIAGNOSTICS INC]]></Name>
<CityName>New Orleans</CityName>
<StateCode>LA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>701122714</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1441 Canal Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>LA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8038</Code>
<Text>Biotechnology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~224758</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Gut inflammatory diseases affect all age groups in the human population: elderly, adults, children, and even the smallest of infants.&nbsp;&nbsp;In these medical conditions, our immune response is triggered by bacteria disequilibrium, and then our own body turns against us resulting in organ damage.&nbsp;&nbsp;Diagnosis is an odyssey for the patient and for the physician.&nbsp;&nbsp;Current methods only detect disease when gut inflammation is in advanced and the most severe stages.&nbsp;&nbsp;They also are inaccurate.&nbsp;&nbsp;For necrotizing enterocolitis (NEC), gut inflammation in very premature infants, the current gold standard for diagnosis only positively identifies 44% patients with disease and median time to death after diagnosis is 1 day.&nbsp;&nbsp;Diagnosis of NEC remains an intractable problem and new tools are required to address the annual $3.2B US healthcare spend on NEC.&nbsp;&nbsp;Our proposed solution is NECDetect, a biomarker for accurate and early detection of necrotizing enterocolitis in hospital neonatal intensive care units.</p> <p>Intellectual merit:&nbsp;&nbsp;The major R&amp;D goal was to optimize the choice of reference standard and detection method for FDA 510(k) application and clinical utility.&nbsp;&nbsp;Research proposed would overcome critical technical hurdles, steps that are a prerequisite for prototype development.&nbsp;&nbsp;Full-length proteins and labeled protein fragments were generated for use in two different types of laboratory tests used in hospital clinics.&nbsp;&nbsp;These reagents that were generated during the award period were then tested for robustness and how well they performed in assays with patient samples.&nbsp;&nbsp;Two significant results during the award period are highlighted.&nbsp;&nbsp;First, the recombinant full-length protein can serve as a reference standard for the immunoassay format of NECDetect.&nbsp;&nbsp;Second, labeled, synthetic protein fragments (or peptides) were reliable and robust standards for use in mass spectrometry measurements.&nbsp;&nbsp;Using these two reference standards, NECDetect biomarker quantitation was shown to be feasible for 107 control patient samples. Immunoassay and mass spectrometry permitted measurement of nanomolar and femtomolar amounts of NECDetect biomarker protein in patient samples, respectively.&nbsp;&nbsp;These major findings show clear feasibility and advantages of our biomarker approach, but require additional product development for commercial use.</p> <p>Broader impacts:&nbsp;&nbsp;Answers obtained will address a fatal gut disease that disproportionately affects African-American preemie babies and lacks disease-modifying treatments.&nbsp;&nbsp;Candidate probiotics and drugs are advancing through therapeutic pipelines, but face barriers to development and adoption without a means to select for infants to enroll in clinical trials.&nbsp;&nbsp;Experiments conducted during this award are a key step in providing solutions that are age- and race-dependent; importantly, they provide proof-of-principle that medical innovation tailored for underserved populations can be profitable. Equally important, the medical and research team mirror the population that it serves. Women, underrepresented, and economically disadvantaged individuals were the core R&amp;D participants in the award and are central to bringing scientific innovation to market.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/05/2023<br>      Modified by: Sunyoung&nbsp;Kim</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Gut inflammatory diseases affect all age groups in the human population: elderly, adults, children, and even the smallest of infants.  In these medical conditions, our immune response is triggered by bacteria disequilibrium, and then our own body turns against us resulting in organ damage.  Diagnosis is an odyssey for the patient and for the physician.  Current methods only detect disease when gut inflammation is in advanced and the most severe stages.  They also are inaccurate.  For necrotizing enterocolitis (NEC), gut inflammation in very premature infants, the current gold standard for diagnosis only positively identifies 44% patients with disease and median time to death after diagnosis is 1 day.  Diagnosis of NEC remains an intractable problem and new tools are required to address the annual $3.2B US healthcare spend on NEC.  Our proposed solution is NECDetect, a biomarker for accurate and early detection of necrotizing enterocolitis in hospital neonatal intensive care units.  Intellectual merit:  The major R&amp;D goal was to optimize the choice of reference standard and detection method for FDA 510(k) application and clinical utility.  Research proposed would overcome critical technical hurdles, steps that are a prerequisite for prototype development.  Full-length proteins and labeled protein fragments were generated for use in two different types of laboratory tests used in hospital clinics.  These reagents that were generated during the award period were then tested for robustness and how well they performed in assays with patient samples.  Two significant results during the award period are highlighted.  First, the recombinant full-length protein can serve as a reference standard for the immunoassay format of NECDetect.  Second, labeled, synthetic protein fragments (or peptides) were reliable and robust standards for use in mass spectrometry measurements.  Using these two reference standards, NECDetect biomarker quantitation was shown to be feasible for 107 control patient samples. Immunoassay and mass spectrometry permitted measurement of nanomolar and femtomolar amounts of NECDetect biomarker protein in patient samples, respectively.  These major findings show clear feasibility and advantages of our biomarker approach, but require additional product development for commercial use.  Broader impacts:  Answers obtained will address a fatal gut disease that disproportionately affects African-American preemie babies and lacks disease-modifying treatments.  Candidate probiotics and drugs are advancing through therapeutic pipelines, but face barriers to development and adoption without a means to select for infants to enroll in clinical trials.  Experiments conducted during this award are a key step in providing solutions that are age- and race-dependent; importantly, they provide proof-of-principle that medical innovation tailored for underserved populations can be profitable. Equally important, the medical and research team mirror the population that it serves. Women, underrepresented, and economically disadvantaged individuals were the core R&amp;D participants in the award and are central to bringing scientific innovation to market.           Last Modified: 01/05/2023       Submitted by: Sunyoung Kim]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
