<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Genius of Place Database]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>224297.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>224297</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rajesh Mehta</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rmehta@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922174</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is to bring biomimetic ideas to traditional architecture. This project consists of a development of a robust and innovative database to catalyze incorporating scientific concepts into designs for the built environment.  This project will inspire the design of naturally resilient structures. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This SBIR Phase I project proposes to develop an innovative sustainability tool that abstracts the knowledge of biology from scientific literature and makes it available to architects and designers such that the built environment sector can support biomimetic ideas implementable in terms of material availability and structural codes. The project will be organized by building challenge category, biome, and function.  It will filter champion organisms that have already solved the specified function, and provide translated principles and images to explain the solution.  The project will interpret, capture, store, and systematically distribute their translation of natural systems models for diverse application in the built environment.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/18/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/16/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041, 47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2015132</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Cynthia</FirstName>
<LastName>Fishman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Cynthia Fishman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[discover@biomimicrydesignalliance.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000814327</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/18/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>BIOMIMICRY DESIGN ALLIANCE, LLC</Name>
<CityName>DENVER</CityName>
<ZipCode>802202714</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7132695881</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1229 KRAMERIA ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>Q8KVJY9XNBT3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>BIOMIMICRY DESIGN ALLIANCE, LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[BIOMIMICRY DESIGN ALLIANCE, LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>Denver</CityName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>802202714</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1229 Krameria St]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8032</Code>
<Text>Software Services and Applications</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~224297</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The built environment encompasses the buildings we inhabit, the distribution systems that provide us with water and electricity, and the roads, bridges, and transportation systems we utilize to get from place to place. Creating all these spaces and systems requires collaboration across multiple disciplines. One important discipline that is rarely involved in the design of our built environment though, is biology. The research funded by NSF's SBIR Phase I grant will change that status quo and allow anyone interested in using an innovative sustainability tool to have access to the expertise that biologists can provide. The format by which this expertise can be communicated is through the design lens of biomimicry. Biomimicry is the conscious emulation of nature's genius by mimicking forms, processes, or systems from a functional perspective to solve human design challenges.</p> <p>The ENSPRD (Employing Nature's Solutions to Produce Responsible Designs) platform, which was formerly known as the Genius of Place Database or GPD, is the collection of the research carried out in Phase I.&nbsp; <strong>This project's overarching goal was to make biomimicry accessible to the design community.</strong> The platform allows designers to utilize biomimicry without having a background in biology or training in biomimicry. It provides biomimetic data from scientific publications and articles related to the built environment that are not typically accessible to architects or the design community. It then translates the organism's strategies for solving a certain function into the language of design and includes conceptual renderings to act as design inspiration. The goal is to allow designers to create sustainable and innovative concepts to help mitigate the climate crisis and allow architects and designers to offer more ecologically friendly solutions to clients.</p> <p>&nbsp;The objectives of this project were as follows:</p> <ul> <li>Conduct scientific literature review on published architectural biomimicry research and existing architectural biomimetic products</li> <li>Research publications that discuss quantifiable metrics regarding an organism's performance in relation to a specific predetermined function</li> <li>Create and format over 200 entries to build a robust data set </li> <li>Design an easy-to-access, visually appealing platform to organize entries</li> <li>Expose research and science publications to a population that wouldn't typically have access</li> <li>Educate designers on "superpowers" of organisms</li> </ul> <p>Over the course of Phase I's timeline, Biomimicry Design Alliance (BDA) created a total of 210 entries. Each entry included a concept rendering to highlight how the biology can be used in a tangible way as well as performance metrics so that the concept can be easily compared to more traditional methods.</p> <p>Numerous interviews were conducted before research started to make sure BDA's goals aligned with those of potential users. And focus groups were held after the project was completed in order to get specific feedback on the tool. The participants were from all over the United States: Texas, New York, North Carolina, Arizona, Illinois, and Colorado. Their job titles ranged from Directors of Sustainability to Principals of firms and from sustainability consultants to Project Managers at architecture, engineering, and interior design firms. &nbsp;All participants said this tool would be relevant to their jobs and were excited about its potential. Some quotes from the Q&amp;A section of the focus group are:</p> <p>"This collection of so many research articles, products, concepts, and science is incredible!"</p> <p>"It takes a very complex topic and makes it both approachable and useful for direct incorporation into design."</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/29/2022<br>      Modified by: Cynthia&nbsp;Fishman</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2015132/2015132_10671268_1659128095384_Homepage--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2015132/2015132_10671268_1659128095384_Homepage--rgov-800width.jpg" title="ENSPRD Homepage"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2015132/2015132_10671268_1659128095384_Homepage--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="ENSPRD Homepage"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Example of what the homepage for the web-based tool will look like.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Biomimicry Design Alliance, LLC</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Cynthia&nbsp;Fishman</div> <div class="imageTitle">ENSPRD Homepage</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2015132/2015132_10671268_1642100507902_ClassificationBDA_Final--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2015132/2015132_10671268_1642100507902_ClassificationBDA_Final--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Organism Classification"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2015132/2015132_10671268_1642100507902_ClassificationBDA_Final--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Organism Classification"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Breakdown of Inspirational Organisms</div> <div class="imageCredit">Biomimicry Design Alliance, LLC</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Cynthia&nbsp;Fishman</div> <div class="imageTitle">Organism Classification</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The built environment encompasses the buildings we inhabit, the distribution systems that provide us with water and electricity, and the roads, bridges, and transportation systems we utilize to get from place to place. Creating all these spaces and systems requires collaboration across multiple disciplines. One important discipline that is rarely involved in the design of our built environment though, is biology. The research funded by NSF's SBIR Phase I grant will change that status quo and allow anyone interested in using an innovative sustainability tool to have access to the expertise that biologists can provide. The format by which this expertise can be communicated is through the design lens of biomimicry. Biomimicry is the conscious emulation of nature's genius by mimicking forms, processes, or systems from a functional perspective to solve human design challenges.  The ENSPRD (Employing Nature's Solutions to Produce Responsible Designs) platform, which was formerly known as the Genius of Place Database or GPD, is the collection of the research carried out in Phase I.  This project's overarching goal was to make biomimicry accessible to the design community. The platform allows designers to utilize biomimicry without having a background in biology or training in biomimicry. It provides biomimetic data from scientific publications and articles related to the built environment that are not typically accessible to architects or the design community. It then translates the organism's strategies for solving a certain function into the language of design and includes conceptual renderings to act as design inspiration. The goal is to allow designers to create sustainable and innovative concepts to help mitigate the climate crisis and allow architects and designers to offer more ecologically friendly solutions to clients.   The objectives of this project were as follows:  Conduct scientific literature review on published architectural biomimicry research and existing architectural biomimetic products Research publications that discuss quantifiable metrics regarding an organism's performance in relation to a specific predetermined function Create and format over 200 entries to build a robust data set  Design an easy-to-access, visually appealing platform to organize entries Expose research and science publications to a population that wouldn't typically have access Educate designers on "superpowers" of organisms   Over the course of Phase I's timeline, Biomimicry Design Alliance (BDA) created a total of 210 entries. Each entry included a concept rendering to highlight how the biology can be used in a tangible way as well as performance metrics so that the concept can be easily compared to more traditional methods.  Numerous interviews were conducted before research started to make sure BDA's goals aligned with those of potential users. And focus groups were held after the project was completed in order to get specific feedback on the tool. The participants were from all over the United States: Texas, New York, North Carolina, Arizona, Illinois, and Colorado. Their job titles ranged from Directors of Sustainability to Principals of firms and from sustainability consultants to Project Managers at architecture, engineering, and interior design firms.  All participants said this tool would be relevant to their jobs and were excited about its potential. Some quotes from the Q&amp;A section of the focus group are:  "This collection of so many research articles, products, concepts, and science is incredible!"  "It takes a very complex topic and makes it both approachable and useful for direct incorporation into design."       Last Modified: 07/29/2022       Submitted by: Cynthia Fishman]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
