<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Incorporating High Dielectric Constant Materials into clinical imaging: A Novel Approach for Accelerating 1.5T MRI]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>224966.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>249966</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Henry Ahn</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>hahn@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927069</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase 1 project will target clinical Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI) scanners where there is limited MRI access to a larger patient population.  Enhanced spatial resolution and reduced scan time are in urgent demand for investigating a comprehensive range of biological systems from single cells to humans.  Long scan times reduce the efficiency of radiology department processes and increase the overall cost to clinics and patients. In the research community, high-resolution MRI is a powerful tool for understanding metabolic activity.  This project will pioneer an entirely different solution to the fundamental problem of long scan times by introducing special materials into the clinical MRI scanners most commonly used to address the challenge of signal strength versus patient safety, which ultimately limits the throughput for research studies and clinical tests.   The proposed materials developed under this SBIR program will have an immediate impact on animal and human health studies where neuroscientists are using MRI techniques to monitor brain activity and cognition.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed SBIR Phase 1 project will advance the development of a new approach to MRI, an indispensable clinical imaging modality for radiology and one of the most powerful research instruments for life science. However, it has an inherently low signal-to-noise ratio, limiting both imaging resolution and scan speed.  Development efforts will focus on incorporation of high permittivity dielectric materials into MRI scanners to increase the signal-to-noise ratio by over 40%, thereby cutting the scan time by half.  The dielectric materials would be placed near the patient to increase the MRI signal through stronger electromagnetic coupling.  Materials with dielectric constant values between 4,000 and 6,000 will be synthesized and incorporated into clinical 1.5 Tesla MRI scanners.   Oxide materials with the optimized dielectric properties will be synthesized and characterized before fabricating the final device.   The project will pursue an integrated systems approach including electromagnetic simulation, ceramic processing and testing.  The magnetic field strengths will be optimized by simulating a range of dielectric materials in the MRI scanner and ultimately tested in clinical scanners with a phantom.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/15/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/24/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041, 47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2015016</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sebastian</FirstName>
<LastName>Rupprecht</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sebastian Rupprecht</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[srupprecht@hyqrs.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000813213</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/15/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>HYQ RESEARCH SOLUTIONS, LLC</Name>
<CityName>COLLEGE STATION</CityName>
<ZipCode>778405241</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7015162061</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2151 HARVEY MITCHELL PKWY S</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[STE 208]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NG9UJAMBCRE4</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>HYQ RESEARCH SOLUTIONS, LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[HYQ RESEARCH SOLUTIONS, LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>College Station</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>778405241</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2151 Harvey Mitchell Pkwy S S208]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8091</Code>
<Text>SBIR Outreach &amp; Tech. Assist</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>066E</Code>
<Text>INSTRUMENTATION &amp; DIAGNOSTICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8038</Code>
<Text>Biotechnology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~249966</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Our goal for this project is to accelerate clinical 1.5T MRI to at least twice its current speed while maintaining comparable image quality. Our novel, high permittivity composite material (patent pending) enhances the electromagnetic fields in an MRI RF coil. An optimized material configuration can currently increase the Signal-to-Noise ratio (SNR) 40-60%, which is enough to almost double MRI throughput.</p> <p>Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI) is an indispensable radiological imaging modality, serving as an important, non-invasive diagnostic tool for countless medical conditions and a powerful research instrument for the life sciences. One inherent limitation of in MRI is its inherently low SNR. This limits both the scan speed (limiting throughput) and imaging resolution (limiting applications). These challenges present barriers for both clinical and research applications of MRI and highlight a critical need for new technologies that enhance SNR for MRI.</p> <p>Our simple drop-in upgrade ceramic liner, can overcome this limitation and accelerate any existing and installed MRI coil. Our hand sized proof-of-concept device as generated during this Phase I project achieved this 2x acceleration with comparable or better image quality. We successfully tested strategies to thin the materials and reduce manufacturing costs. In the next steps will be to optimize electromagnetic fields and interaction between RF coil and our device for a whole head device. The material will be further improved to be even thinner. A drop-in in upgrade device will be manufactured in close collaboration with our industry partners.</p> <p>A combination of technologies can ultimately make MRI as fast or faster than Computed Tomography (CT or CAT scans).&nbsp; This will allow to improve standard of care in emergency and interventional medicine. It would also dramatically improve access to this capital intensive technology in general to a broad population.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/29/2022<br>      Modified by: Sebastian&nbsp;Rupprecht</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2015016/2015016_10671129_1661290817927_Project--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2015016/2015016_10671129_1661290817927_Project--rgov-800width.jpg" title="MRI RF head coil with HyQ e-shell"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2015016/2015016_10671129_1661290817927_Project--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="MRI RF head coil with HyQ e-shell"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">HyQ e-shell high permittivity ceramic insert for MRI RF coils to cut MRI scan time in half</div> <div class="imageCredit">Sebastian Rupprecht</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Sebastian&nbsp;Rupprecht</div> <div class="imageTitle">MRI RF head coil with HyQ e-shell</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2015016/2015016_10671129_1661291147703_Preliminarydata--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2015016/2015016_10671129_1661291147703_Preliminarydata--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Proof of concept data - MRI twice as fast"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2015016/2015016_10671129_1661291147703_Preliminarydata--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Proof of concept data - MRI twice as fast"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Comparable MRI images acquired with our proof-of-concept device in a standard clinical MRI head coil at 1.5T shows MRI twice as fast with our material is feasible</div> <div class="imageCredit">Sebastian Rupprecht</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Sebastian&nbsp;Rupprecht</div> <div class="imageTitle">Proof of concept data - MRI twice as fast</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Our goal for this project is to accelerate clinical 1.5T MRI to at least twice its current speed while maintaining comparable image quality. Our novel, high permittivity composite material (patent pending) enhances the electromagnetic fields in an MRI RF coil. An optimized material configuration can currently increase the Signal-to-Noise ratio (SNR) 40-60%, which is enough to almost double MRI throughput.  Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI) is an indispensable radiological imaging modality, serving as an important, non-invasive diagnostic tool for countless medical conditions and a powerful research instrument for the life sciences. One inherent limitation of in MRI is its inherently low SNR. This limits both the scan speed (limiting throughput) and imaging resolution (limiting applications). These challenges present barriers for both clinical and research applications of MRI and highlight a critical need for new technologies that enhance SNR for MRI.  Our simple drop-in upgrade ceramic liner, can overcome this limitation and accelerate any existing and installed MRI coil. Our hand sized proof-of-concept device as generated during this Phase I project achieved this 2x acceleration with comparable or better image quality. We successfully tested strategies to thin the materials and reduce manufacturing costs. In the next steps will be to optimize electromagnetic fields and interaction between RF coil and our device for a whole head device. The material will be further improved to be even thinner. A drop-in in upgrade device will be manufactured in close collaboration with our industry partners.  A combination of technologies can ultimately make MRI as fast or faster than Computed Tomography (CT or CAT scans).  This will allow to improve standard of care in emergency and interventional medicine. It would also dramatically improve access to this capital intensive technology in general to a broad population.          Last Modified: 08/29/2022       Submitted by: Sebastian Rupprecht]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
