<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[2020 Chromatin Structure and Function: Micro to Macro Chromatin Structure in Epigenetics and Disease GRS]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>12985.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>12985</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>MCB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Manju Hingorani</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mhingora@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927323</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The award will provide support for graduate students and post-doctoral researchers to attend the 2020 Gordon Research Seminar (GRS) on Chromatin Structure and Function (May 30-31, 2020 in Castelldelfels, Spain) to be held just prior to the associated Gordon Research Conference (GRC; May 31-June 5, 2020). These conferences bring together young and established scientists from multiple disciplines, from genetics and epigenetics to computational biology, who are investigating mechanisms governing the higher order structure and function of the genome. The GRS serves as a forum for a diverse group of early career scientists to discuss research through seminars and poster sessions, exchange new ideas, technologies and resources informally, and develop their professional network. The program also includes a panel discussion on mentoring and career development with scientists in different professions, such as academia, industry and publishing. The GRS is organized and co-chaired by a graduate student and a post-doctoral fellow, providing them with a significant career development experience. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;New technologies, including genome visualization tools, have accelerated discoveries in chromatin biology in recent years, while increasing the need for multi-disciplinary training and collaborative research. The GRS and GRC serve as a vital link for investigators around the world to share their latest, often unpublished, discoveries, discuss pioneering ideas and launch new collaborations. Topics at the forefront of the field will be covered, including the organization of the genome at various scales, chromatin remodeling mechanisms and their regulation, the effects on cellular development and fate, among others. The GRS in particular will facilitate training and professional development of the next generation of scientists, including underrepresented minorities, in the field of chromatin biology.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/18/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/18/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2015735</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
<LastName>Porter</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Robert S Porter</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[rsporter@umich.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000816303</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/18/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Gordon Research Conferences</Name>
<CityName>EAST GREENWICH</CityName>
<ZipCode>028183454</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4017834011</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5586 POST RD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[UNIT 2]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>RI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>XL5ANMKWN557</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GORDON RESEARCH CONFERENCES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Gordon Research Conferences]]></Name>
<CityName>West Kingston</CityName>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>028921502</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[512 Liberty Lane]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>RI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1112</Code>
<Text>Genetic Mechanisms</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7465</Code>
<Text>NANOSCALE BIO CORE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~12985</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The main objective of the 2022 GRS on Chromatin Structure and Function was to create an environment for young chromatin biologists to share their work and identify and harness opportunities for career development. The intimate nature of the GRS, which directly precedes the GRC, also offered an opportunity for young scientists to exchange ideas and form bonds and life-time colleagues prior to the assembly of the GRC community. 62 early career scientists attended the GRS (90% were graduate students or postdocs, and 66% of the attendees were women). This GRS offered attendees a chance to collaborate before the GRC which had a total of 191 attendees. Our originally scheduled meeting in 2020 was delayed until 2022 due to the COVID-19 pandemic.</p> <p>This meeting, &ldquo;Micro to Macro Chromatin Structure in Epigenetics and Disease<em>&rdquo;</em>, covered a range of topics at the cutting-edge of the chromatin field. Our selection of abstracts, oral presentations, and discussion leaders emphasized the importance of valuing a diverse community of scientists. We selected a diverse set of attendees with respect to background and scientific disciplines. We organized our oral presentations into two sessions, titled &ldquo;Peering into the 3D Architecture of DNA in the Nucleus&rdquo; and &ldquo;Nucleosome Dynamics in Epigenetics States and Disease.&rdquo; For each session, we chose discussion leaders from a list of enthusiastic applicants with an interest in leading the discussion. We additionally had two poster sessions, and altogether attendees were able to get crucial feedback on unpublished work.</p> <p>We recruited an inspiring keynote speaker, Dr. Marc Marti-Renom (Centre for Genomic Regulation, Barcelona), who set the tone for the meeting in discussing his contributions in elucidating higher-order chromatin structure and in creating freely available software to probe chromatin states. We also organized a career panel where we discussed how to navigate various scientific careers. This panel included an academic associate professor, Dr. Melike Lakadamyali, a chief editor of the journal Nature Structural and Molecular Biology, Dr. Carolina Perdigoto, and an industry scientist with Recursion Pharma, Dr. Carl Ebeling. The final schedule of oral presentations, including our keynote speaker and career panel, is publicly available at: <a href="https://www.grc.org/chromatin-structure-and-function-grs-conference/2022/">https://www.grc.org/chromatin-structure-and-function-grs-conference/2022/</a>.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/12/2022<br>      Modified by: Robert&nbsp;S&nbsp;Porter</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The main objective of the 2022 GRS on Chromatin Structure and Function was to create an environment for young chromatin biologists to share their work and identify and harness opportunities for career development. The intimate nature of the GRS, which directly precedes the GRC, also offered an opportunity for young scientists to exchange ideas and form bonds and life-time colleagues prior to the assembly of the GRC community. 62 early career scientists attended the GRS (90% were graduate students or postdocs, and 66% of the attendees were women). This GRS offered attendees a chance to collaborate before the GRC which had a total of 191 attendees. Our originally scheduled meeting in 2020 was delayed until 2022 due to the COVID-19 pandemic.  This meeting, "Micro to Macro Chromatin Structure in Epigenetics and Disease", covered a range of topics at the cutting-edge of the chromatin field. Our selection of abstracts, oral presentations, and discussion leaders emphasized the importance of valuing a diverse community of scientists. We selected a diverse set of attendees with respect to background and scientific disciplines. We organized our oral presentations into two sessions, titled "Peering into the 3D Architecture of DNA in the Nucleus" and "Nucleosome Dynamics in Epigenetics States and Disease." For each session, we chose discussion leaders from a list of enthusiastic applicants with an interest in leading the discussion. We additionally had two poster sessions, and altogether attendees were able to get crucial feedback on unpublished work.  We recruited an inspiring keynote speaker, Dr. Marc Marti-Renom (Centre for Genomic Regulation, Barcelona), who set the tone for the meeting in discussing his contributions in elucidating higher-order chromatin structure and in creating freely available software to probe chromatin states. We also organized a career panel where we discussed how to navigate various scientific careers. This panel included an academic associate professor, Dr. Melike Lakadamyali, a chief editor of the journal Nature Structural and Molecular Biology, Dr. Carolina Perdigoto, and an industry scientist with Recursion Pharma, Dr. Carl Ebeling. The final schedule of oral presentations, including our keynote speaker and career panel, is publicly available at: https://www.grc.org/chromatin-structure-and-function-grs-conference/2022/.          Last Modified: 12/12/2022       Submitted by: Robert S Porter]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
