<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[I-Corps:  Fiber Scaffold Platform For 3D Cell Culture]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ruth Shuman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rshuman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922160</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this I-Corps project is in the translation of scalable three-dimensional cell culture (3DCC) technology.  In 2019 the global and U.S. market sizes for 3DCC technologies were $400M and $150M, respectively, expected to grow at 15% CAGR through 2024. Recent advances in tissue engineering and regenerative medicine, cancer and stem cell research are made possible through the advent of 3DCC techniques, replacing the traditional two-dimensional cell cultures. 3DCC techniques are expected to better mimic natural tissue conditions. The proposed 3D scaffolding technology offers highly customizable scaffolds with specific cell type environments, offering high yield and scalable production of biopharmaceuticals.  This will impact the drug discovery market by improving the reliability of preclinical screening and reduced animal model usage. Further, this 3DCC platform innovation will accelerate the research and commercial activities in tissue engineering, cancer and stem cell markets. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project explores translation of improved three-dimensional cell culture (3DCC) methods. Large-scale production and isolation of cellular metabolites of pharmaceutical value, as well as rapidly growing tissue engineering applications, call for a rapid and high-yield 3DCC technique that supports the right cell phenotype with healthy cell population through a better nutrient and metabolite exchange over an extended period.  Despite significant success of laboratory-scale 3DCC techniques to grow microtissues, they largely misrepresent the natural extracellular (ECM) characteristics, and lack of established high-throughput and rapid screening protocols for drug discovery are hurdles to adopt 3DCC widely in biopharmaceutical industry and research. Therefore, a better scalable 3DCC technique closely mimicking the natural ECM is urgently needed. The proposed 3D scaffolding technology enables biocompatible polymeric fibers as building blocks to recreate the cell-specific scaffold in a bottoms-up approach, mimicking the natural ECMs closely with higher cell yields. Further, these scaffolds can be optimized and scalable to specific applications.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/11/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/02/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041, 47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2016272</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Vladimir</FirstName>
<LastName>Reukov</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Vladimir Reukov</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[reukov@uga.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000813897</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/11/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Georgia Research Foundation Inc</Name>
<CityName>ATHENS</CityName>
<ZipCode>306021589</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7065425939</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>310 E CAMPUS RD RM 409</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NMJHD63STRC5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF GEORGIA RESEARCH FOUNDATION, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Georgia]]></Name>
<CityName>Athens</CityName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>306021589</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[310 East Campus Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Outcomes</strong>. In recent years, advances in cell culture technology have presented us with the possibility of revolutionary developments in biology, medicine, agriculture, and drug development. One of the culprits of scaling up cell-based technologies is the necessity to grow them on two-dimensional surfaces of cell culture flasks, thus increasing costs, waste of plasticware, and potential for contamination. The potential solution to this problem is a technique known as three-dimensional cell culture (3DCC), which allows cells to grow in a manner that more closely mimics their natural environment in the human or animal body. Our team at the University of Georgia developed a unique nanofiber-based 3D scaffolding technology that can serve as the foundation for multiple cell culture-based applications. Over the lifespan of this project, our team has conducted over 200 interviews with potential customers to assess the market potential for this technology.</p> <p><strong>Broader impacts</strong>.Fiber-based three-dimensional cell culture scaffolds are a pivotal advancement for cellular agriculture. Such scaffolds, by simulating a more natural cellular environment, significantly enhance the proliferation of cells. Increased permeability will ensure cell access to nutrients and fast removal of metabolites, ensuring healthier and more robust cell populations. This improvement is crucial for the scalability and viability of cellular agriculture, as it means faster production rates and higher yields, ultimately leading to more ethical and more sustainable sources of proteins.</p> <p>The broader impacts of this project include the introduction of a Special Topics class aimed at undergraduate and graduate students, which provides insights into the entrepreneurial journey, focusing on engaging students in the customer discovery process.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/01/2023<br>      Modified by: Vladimir&nbsp;Reukov</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Outcomes. In recent years, advances in cell culture technology have presented us with the possibility of revolutionary developments in biology, medicine, agriculture, and drug development. One of the culprits of scaling up cell-based technologies is the necessity to grow them on two-dimensional surfaces of cell culture flasks, thus increasing costs, waste of plasticware, and potential for contamination. The potential solution to this problem is a technique known as three-dimensional cell culture (3DCC), which allows cells to grow in a manner that more closely mimics their natural environment in the human or animal body. Our team at the University of Georgia developed a unique nanofiber-based 3D scaffolding technology that can serve as the foundation for multiple cell culture-based applications. Over the lifespan of this project, our team has conducted over 200 interviews with potential customers to assess the market potential for this technology.  Broader impacts.Fiber-based three-dimensional cell culture scaffolds are a pivotal advancement for cellular agriculture. Such scaffolds, by simulating a more natural cellular environment, significantly enhance the proliferation of cells. Increased permeability will ensure cell access to nutrients and fast removal of metabolites, ensuring healthier and more robust cell populations. This improvement is crucial for the scalability and viability of cellular agriculture, as it means faster production rates and higher yields, ultimately leading to more ethical and more sustainable sources of proteins.  The broader impacts of this project include the introduction of a Special Topics class aimed at undergraduate and graduate students, which provides insights into the entrepreneurial journey, focusing on engaging students in the customer discovery process.       Last Modified: 10/01/2023       Submitted by: Vladimir Reukov]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
