<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Doctoral Dissertation Research: Evidentiary Practices for Establishing Psychological Trauma in Asylum Claims]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>25834.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>25834</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jeffrey Mantz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jmantz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927783</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[With establishment of an agreed-upon legal definition of refugee as a person with a “well-founded fear of past and future persecution,” recognizing fear, evaluating its plausibility and verifying its rationality has been at the core of asylum law in the more than 145 countries signatories of the United Nations Convention Relating to the Status of Refugees. Although researchers have been concerned with the interpretation of emotions in immigration law, no particular attention has been placed to the development of policy instruments that aim to differentiate legal fear of persecution from psychological trauma. A better understanding of what makes someone fearful in the eyes of the law can inform U.S. efforts to promulgate sound legal practices that accounts for the complexities of translating experiences into legal and medical evidence. In addition to contributing to the training of a graduate student in the methods of empirical, scientific data collection and analysis, the project would enhance scientific understanding by broadly disseminating its findings to organizations invested in discovering more effective methods for communicating science around legal practice to the public. The project would also broaden the participation of groups historically underrepresented in science. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project explores how medical and psychological science related to trauma is engaged in evidentiary proceedings related to asylum claims. During twelve months of a sociolegal and ethnographic context with a high concentration of refugees (and thus appropriately saturated to constitute a representative study population), the researcher will examine the entirety of asylum process, observing the day-to-day activities of government officials, attorneys, asylum seekers, medical expert witnesses, and organizational staff. She will specifically analyze narrations of fear in asylum interviews, evaluations of fear in medico-legal reports, and evidence of fear in asylum decisions. Data will be collected using archival research, interviews, and participant observation in a range of governmental, legal, and peri-governmental contexts. The findings of this research will help advance the study of legal culture, bureaucratic institutions, and policy practices where law and medicine meet.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/26/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/20/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2016958</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Maria</FirstName>
<LastName>Ramia</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>V</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Maria V Ramia</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[vramia@stanford.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000816892</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/26/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Angela</FirstName>
<LastName>Garcia</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Angela Garcia</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[garcia2@stanford.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000674214</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/26/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Stanford University</Name>
<CityName>STANFORD</CityName>
<ZipCode>943052004</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6507232300</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>450 JANE STANFORD WAY</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>16</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA16</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>HJD6G4D6TJY5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>THE LELAND STANFORD JUNIOR UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Stanford University]]></Name>
<CityName>Stanford</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>943052034</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[450 Jane Stanford Way, Bldg. 50]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>16</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA16</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>128Y</Code>
<Text>Law &amp; Science</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7605</Code>
<Text>Cult Anthro DDRI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1372</Code>
<Text>LAW AND SOCIAL SCIENCES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1390</Code>
<Text>CULTURAL ANTHROPOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~25834</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>With the establishment of the legal definition of refugee as a person with a &ldquo;well-founded fear of past and future persecution,&rdquo; recognizing fear, evaluating its plausibility, and verifying its rationality has been at the core of asylum law in the countries that adhere to the United Nations Convention Relating to the Status of Refugees. Although researchers have been concerned with the interpretation of emotions in immigration law, no particular attention has been placed on the development of policy instruments that aim to differentiate legal fear of persecution from psychological trauma. This project contributes to a better understanding of what makes someone fearful in the eyes of the law. Therefore, it informs U.S. efforts to promulgate sound legal practices that account for the complexity of translating lived experiences into legal and medical evidence. &nbsp;<br /><br />During twelve months of a sociolegal and ethnographic context with a high concentration of asylum seekers (and thus appropriately saturated to constitute a representative study population), the researcher examined the entirety of the asylum petition process, observing the day-to-day activities of government officials, attorneys, asylum seekers, medical expert witnesses, and administrative staff. The investigator has specifically analyzed narrations of fear in asylum interviews, evaluations of fear in medico-legal reports, and evidence of fear in asylum decisions. Data was collected using archival research, interviews, and participant observation in various governmental, legal, and peri-governmental contexts. <br /><br />This project helps advance the study of legal culture, bureaucratic institutions, and policy practices where law and medicine meet. During the past two decades, scholars have examined how the interpretation of emotions is a critical component of decision-making in immigration law. However, there are no studies on how the judgment of fear plays a critical role in determining who is granted legal personhood in asylum law. By investigating the judicialization of fear, or how it is made into a legal object, this project not only contributes to the scholarship focused on asylum and bureaucracy but also aims to expand the role of current research on debates about how law and policy are made when institutions develop instruments to measure emotions. By observing how fear is interpreted in medical terms in the context of immigration law, this project participates in the interdisciplinary analysis of medico-legal reports, therapeutic techniques, and ideas of competency in legal contexts. Therefore, this research offers new perspectives by inquiring into the distinction between legal fear of persecution and psychological diagnoses of post-traumatic stress disorder, trauma, and psychosis. <br /><br />Various disciplines have used ethnographic methods to study fear. However, these &ldquo;ethnographies of fear&rdquo; have mainly touched upon how fear is used to induce social responses. By following how fear is identified, measured, assessed, and evaluated in immigration law, this ethnographic work asks how different ideas of fear contain moral values, political valences, and judgments of who is worthy of rights. By studying cases of immigrants with diagnoses related to trauma, post-traumatic stress disorder, psychosis, and pathological fear, this study contributes to interdisciplinary efforts to understand the experience of people with mental disabilities. <br /><br />This project also contributes to the new conversations on the potential of digital ethnography and digital humanities. The impact of the Covid-19 pandemic on this project resulted in the design of methods that ultimately advance the endeavor to find a meeting point between technology, ethnography, and social scientific analysis. By sharing the researcher&rsquo;s experience in conducting ethnography through digital and hybrid methods&mdash;including court observation and hearing preparation meetings&mdash;this project will contribute to the rising interest in the field of digital ethnography. Additionally, incorporating computational science methodologies into analyzing a large corpus of legal documents has created a synergy between ethnographic methods and computational data analysis that is otherwise undermined or not explored. The researcher has treated computational text analysis as ethnographic material, which has provoked interest in data and text mining experts who are keen on applying ethnographic knowledge to digital humanities. &nbsp;<br /><br />The preliminary results of this research project have been shared at numerous conferences, talks, and panels. The final results will be included in a dissertation format and subsequently as a book for public audiences. In addition to contributing to the training of a graduate student in the methods of empirical, and scientific data collection and analysis, the project enhances scientific understanding by broadly disseminating its findings to organizations invested in discovering more effective methods for communicating science around legal practice. The project will also broaden the participation of groups historically underrepresented in science. The researcher hopes that with the dissemination of this project&rsquo;s results, the public will develop skills to understand the effect of the judicialization of emotions in the lives of immigrants, especially those leaving from Latin American countries.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/02/2023<br>      Modified by: Maria&nbsp;V&nbsp;Ramia</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ With the establishment of the legal definition of refugee as a person with a "well-founded fear of past and future persecution," recognizing fear, evaluating its plausibility, and verifying its rationality has been at the core of asylum law in the countries that adhere to the United Nations Convention Relating to the Status of Refugees. Although researchers have been concerned with the interpretation of emotions in immigration law, no particular attention has been placed on the development of policy instruments that aim to differentiate legal fear of persecution from psychological trauma. This project contributes to a better understanding of what makes someone fearful in the eyes of the law. Therefore, it informs U.S. efforts to promulgate sound legal practices that account for the complexity of translating lived experiences into legal and medical evidence.    During twelve months of a sociolegal and ethnographic context with a high concentration of asylum seekers (and thus appropriately saturated to constitute a representative study population), the researcher examined the entirety of the asylum petition process, observing the day-to-day activities of government officials, attorneys, asylum seekers, medical expert witnesses, and administrative staff. The investigator has specifically analyzed narrations of fear in asylum interviews, evaluations of fear in medico-legal reports, and evidence of fear in asylum decisions. Data was collected using archival research, interviews, and participant observation in various governmental, legal, and peri-governmental contexts.   This project helps advance the study of legal culture, bureaucratic institutions, and policy practices where law and medicine meet. During the past two decades, scholars have examined how the interpretation of emotions is a critical component of decision-making in immigration law. However, there are no studies on how the judgment of fear plays a critical role in determining who is granted legal personhood in asylum law. By investigating the judicialization of fear, or how it is made into a legal object, this project not only contributes to the scholarship focused on asylum and bureaucracy but also aims to expand the role of current research on debates about how law and policy are made when institutions develop instruments to measure emotions. By observing how fear is interpreted in medical terms in the context of immigration law, this project participates in the interdisciplinary analysis of medico-legal reports, therapeutic techniques, and ideas of competency in legal contexts. Therefore, this research offers new perspectives by inquiring into the distinction between legal fear of persecution and psychological diagnoses of post-traumatic stress disorder, trauma, and psychosis.   Various disciplines have used ethnographic methods to study fear. However, these "ethnographies of fear" have mainly touched upon how fear is used to induce social responses. By following how fear is identified, measured, assessed, and evaluated in immigration law, this ethnographic work asks how different ideas of fear contain moral values, political valences, and judgments of who is worthy of rights. By studying cases of immigrants with diagnoses related to trauma, post-traumatic stress disorder, psychosis, and pathological fear, this study contributes to interdisciplinary efforts to understand the experience of people with mental disabilities.   This project also contributes to the new conversations on the potential of digital ethnography and digital humanities. The impact of the Covid-19 pandemic on this project resulted in the design of methods that ultimately advance the endeavor to find a meeting point between technology, ethnography, and social scientific analysis. By sharing the researcher’s experience in conducting ethnography through digital and hybrid methods&mdash;including court observation and hearing preparation meetings&mdash;this project will contribute to the rising interest in the field of digital ethnography. Additionally, incorporating computational science methodologies into analyzing a large corpus of legal documents has created a synergy between ethnographic methods and computational data analysis that is otherwise undermined or not explored. The researcher has treated computational text analysis as ethnographic material, which has provoked interest in data and text mining experts who are keen on applying ethnographic knowledge to digital humanities.    The preliminary results of this research project have been shared at numerous conferences, talks, and panels. The final results will be included in a dissertation format and subsequently as a book for public audiences. In addition to contributing to the training of a graduate student in the methods of empirical, and scientific data collection and analysis, the project enhances scientific understanding by broadly disseminating its findings to organizations invested in discovering more effective methods for communicating science around legal practice. The project will also broaden the participation of groups historically underrepresented in science. The researcher hopes that with the dissemination of this project’s results, the public will develop skills to understand the effect of the judicialization of emotions in the lives of immigrants, especially those leaving from Latin American countries.       Last Modified: 01/02/2023       Submitted by: Maria V Ramia]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
