<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[I-Corps:  Vacuum Stripping and Absorption to Recover Ammonia from Wastewater]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ruth Shuman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rshuman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922160</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact of this I-Corps project is the development of technology that lowers the operating costs for treatment of ammonia-rich wastewater and generates revenues by turning the removed ammonia into a sellable nitrogen fertilizer.  The ever-increasing number of anaerobic digestion systems at municipal wastewater treatment facilities and concentrated animal feeding operations are shifting the paradigm of wastewater treatment from contaminant removal to recovery of bioenergy in the form of biogas, nutrients, and water. The technology may be fabricated in different sizes of modules, providing operational ease and flexibility of scaling. The ammonia extracted from wastewater also has the potential to be used for production of certified organic fertilizers. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project is based on the development of technology termed vacuum stripping and absorption (VaSA) for recovering ammonia in wastewater with high purity. VaSA couples vacuum thermal stripping and acid absorption to pull ammonia out of ammonia-rich wastewater to form ammonium sulfate granules. Moreover, recovering ammonia in wastewater may be a sustainable alternative to the energy-intensive Haber-Bosch process for ammonia synthesis. Using a weak vacuum, the boiling point is reduced from 100 to 65 degrees C for safe, efficient stripping of ammonia without the need for pretreatment. It has been recognized as the most practical method for ammonia recovery and fills the gap for an efficient, versatile, and scalable ammonia recovery technology. When VaSA is incorporated into anaerobic digestion systems, it avoids ammonia inhibition to methane-producing microorganisms, thus enabling stable anaerobic digestion at a higher loading rate. The vacuum-assisted low-temperature thermal treatment in the VaSA process enhances solids solubilization and biodegradability of digestate, further increasing methane production as stripped digestate is returned to the digesters. When employing VaSA to recover ammonia from digester effluent, it improves the ability to separate solids from digester effluent and upgrades the from Class B biosolids to Class A for unrestricted land application.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/11/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/11/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2016333</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Wendong</FirstName>
<LastName>Tao</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Wendong Tao</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[wtao@esf.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000508688</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/11/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>SUNY College of Environmental Science and Forestry</Name>
<CityName>SYRACUSE</CityName>
<ZipCode>132102712</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3154706606</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1 FORESTRY DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>22</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY22</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>LVVEB3CF8MB8</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>THE RESEARCH FOUNDATION FOR THE STATE UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[SUNY College of Environmental Science and Forestry]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>122010009</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This I-Corps Teams project was to test the market fit and develop business models for an innovative technology, vacuum stripping and absorption (VaSA), that strips ammonia out of ammonia-rich wastewater and produce ammonium sulfate with the stripped ammonia as a granular fertilizer. Customer discovery during the project period validated "highly efficient ammonia removal", "reduced operating cost for removal of ammonia from wastewater", "improved digestate dewaterability", and "upgrading biosolids from Class B to more valuable Class A" as critical value propositions of VaSA. It identified three market segments - &nbsp;the anaerobic digestion systems at municipal wastewater treatment facilities and concentrated animal feeding operations, plus landfill leachate.</p> <p>VaSA can be fabricated in modular designs, providing operational ease and flexibility of scaling up. The customer discovery also identified a few desired features of an ammonia recovery technology like VaSA, for example, successful pilot study, diverse operating mode, and alternative heating methods. Based on the customer discovery that VaSA has a tremendous market potential, this I-Corps team has constructed a 125-gallon full-featured prototype and secured fundings to demonstrate VaSA with working prototypes at a water resource recovery facility, a landfill leachate treatment site, and an academic partner's field station. The entrepreneurial lead has successfully defended his doctoral dissertation including technical development and life cycle analysis of the VaSA technology. A startup limited liability company is being registered by the entrepreneurial lead to seek commercialization opportunities.</p> <p>The customer discovery has confirmed that VaSA is one of the very few technologies having a market potential for ammonia recovery. An U.S. patent was issued for the VaSA technology in 2018. VaSA fills the gap of an efficient, versatile, scalable technology to remove and recover ammonia from wastewater. The technical R&amp;D work in this project has provided experimental results for improved design of two components (demister and absorption column) of the working prototypes. The ruggedness and technical feasibility of the modified prototypes have been verified prior to field demonstration.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/13/2022<br>      Modified by: Wendong&nbsp;Tao</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2016333/2016333_10676402_1642091206424_Prototype6--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2016333/2016333_10676402_1642091206424_Prototype6--rgov-800width.jpg" title="The core of a VaSA prototype"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2016333/2016333_10676402_1642091206424_Prototype6--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="The core of a VaSA prototype"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Team visit at an industrial partner to fabricate a prototype</div> <div class="imageCredit">Fred Agyeman</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Wendong&nbsp;Tao</div> <div class="imageTitle">The core of a VaSA prototype</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2016333/2016333_10676402_1642091851734_VaSAatWRRF1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2016333/2016333_10676402_1642091851734_VaSAatWRRF1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Prototype assembled"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2016333/2016333_10676402_1642091851734_VaSAatWRRF1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Prototype assembled"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">A working prototype is assembled at a Water Resource Recovery Facility</div> <div class="imageCredit">Kevin Guerin</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Wendong&nbsp;Tao</div> <div class="imageTitle">Prototype assembled</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This I-Corps Teams project was to test the market fit and develop business models for an innovative technology, vacuum stripping and absorption (VaSA), that strips ammonia out of ammonia-rich wastewater and produce ammonium sulfate with the stripped ammonia as a granular fertilizer. Customer discovery during the project period validated "highly efficient ammonia removal", "reduced operating cost for removal of ammonia from wastewater", "improved digestate dewaterability", and "upgrading biosolids from Class B to more valuable Class A" as critical value propositions of VaSA. It identified three market segments -  the anaerobic digestion systems at municipal wastewater treatment facilities and concentrated animal feeding operations, plus landfill leachate.  VaSA can be fabricated in modular designs, providing operational ease and flexibility of scaling up. The customer discovery also identified a few desired features of an ammonia recovery technology like VaSA, for example, successful pilot study, diverse operating mode, and alternative heating methods. Based on the customer discovery that VaSA has a tremendous market potential, this I-Corps team has constructed a 125-gallon full-featured prototype and secured fundings to demonstrate VaSA with working prototypes at a water resource recovery facility, a landfill leachate treatment site, and an academic partner's field station. The entrepreneurial lead has successfully defended his doctoral dissertation including technical development and life cycle analysis of the VaSA technology. A startup limited liability company is being registered by the entrepreneurial lead to seek commercialization opportunities.  The customer discovery has confirmed that VaSA is one of the very few technologies having a market potential for ammonia recovery. An U.S. patent was issued for the VaSA technology in 2018. VaSA fills the gap of an efficient, versatile, scalable technology to remove and recover ammonia from wastewater. The technical R&amp;D work in this project has provided experimental results for improved design of two components (demister and absorption column) of the working prototypes. The ruggedness and technical feasibility of the modified prototypes have been verified prior to field demonstration.       Last Modified: 01/13/2022       Submitted by: Wendong Tao]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
