<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[I-Corps: Adaptive Robotic Nursing Assistants for Physical Healthcare Delivery]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ruth Shuman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rshuman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922160</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this I-Corps project is the development of robotic technologies to assist healthcare workers deliver better and more efficient services to patients in hospitals and nursing home environments. The Bureau of Labor statistics indicates that there are millions of registered nurses in the United States, which makes them the largest workforce providing healthcare. The proposed technology has the potential to augment the nursing workforce and help offset personnel shortages in hospitals, long-term care facilities, and nursing homes. Adaptive robotic nursing assistants may reduce nurses’ exposure to infectious agents, reduce musculoskeletal injuries, and increase job satisfaction by freeing up time spent on item fetching, repetitive measurements of vital signs, and lifting. A robot that can communicate with the electronic health records to document completed tasks may have greater impact by saving nurses’ time devoted to paperwork. With the predicted shortage in nursing workforce, nurse workloads are expected to increase, and robot nursing assistants have the potential to handle some of the physical and administrative nursing tasks. Patients and hospitals may gain in terms of quality of care, prevention of falls, and faster service through automation.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project is based on the development of adaptive robotic nursing assistants for physical and administrative tasks in hospital environments. The technology consists of a mobile manipulator with an omni-directional base, a 6-degrees of freedom (DOF) robotic arm, and sensors to assist with nursing scenarios such as sitting and walking with patients. The sensors include both non-contact proximity and contact tactile skins to allow the robot to operate safely in busy healthcare environments while interacting physically with nurses and patients. The technology also incorporates human-machine interfaces (HMIs) that allow users to interact with the robot in an intuitive manner that may be tailored to individual preferences. The proposed technology’s neuroadaptive learning control technology may adapt to each user’s behavior during physical human-robot interaction, ensuring both high quality interaction, programmable adaptive HMI behaviors, and robust performance under operational uncertainties. Using this technology, the robot can navigate the environment, fetch objects, and automate mundane nursing tasks while keeping healthcare workers in the decision loop.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/12/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/12/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2016973</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dan</FirstName>
<LastName>Popa</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>O</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Dan O Popa</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[dan.popa@louisville.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000085594</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/12/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Louisville Research Foundation Inc</Name>
<CityName>LOUISVILLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>402081838</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5028523788</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2301 S 3RD ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Kentucky</StateName>
<StateCode>KY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>KY03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>E1KJM4T54MK6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF LOUISVILLE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Univ. of Louisville]]></Name>
<CityName>Louisville</CityName>
<StateCode>KY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>402920001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[WS Speed 200]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Kentucky</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>KY03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>In this project, a team from University of Louisville (UofL) evaluated the commercialization potential of the Adaptive Robotic Nursing Assistant (ARNA) technology developed at the Next Generation Systems Group (NGS). The team interviewed over 120 potential customers for the robot technology, many of them covering the hospital, rather than the nursing home markets. The team spoke to nurses, nurse administrators, doctors, hospital C-Suite administrators, and with robotics suppliers and developed a lean canvass for a future $B commercial opportunity. Interviews were conducted in both urban and rural hospitals, in Kentucky, Oklahoma, Pennsylvania and other health care markets.&nbsp; Although our robot was developed with prior funding from the NSF PFI:BIC program, with consideration of market needs early in the design process, the customer discovery undertaken in this project helped the team narrow a value proposition, and a product market fit centered around ambulation to speed up patient recovery. Finally, the team used the customer discovery findings to seek additional funding for their startup company to further commercialize the patented ARNA technology.&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span>During the project, the team further refined a minimum viable product (MVP) by upgrading the robot's navigation sensor suite, re-designing the handlebar responsible for physical interaction during ambulation, and conducted additional testing of the neuro-adaptive controller embedded in the robot. During 2020 and 2021, the robot was also tested in conjunction with COVID-19 disinfection tasks in our lab's research building, and discussions were conducted with hospital administrators in Louisville interested in seeing the robot in action. The robot was also showcased to numerous health care companies, nurses, and STEM educators over a two year period at UofL's newly established robotics institute (LARRI) and at the School of Nursing.&nbsp;</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/15/2022<br>      Modified by: Dan&nbsp;O&nbsp;Popa</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2016973/2016973_10696376_1668545483120_Picture-ARNASide--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2016973/2016973_10696376_1668545483120_Picture-ARNASide--rgov-800width.jpg" title="ARNA Picture"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2016973/2016973_10696376_1668545483120_Picture-ARNASide--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="ARNA Picture"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The Adaptive Robotic Nursing Assistant (ARNA) will assist nurses with ambulation and sitting tasks to save time, increase productivity and help improve patient outcomes.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Nasser Saadatzi</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Dan&nbsp;O&nbsp;Popa</div> <div class="imageTitle">ARNA Picture</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ In this project, a team from University of Louisville (UofL) evaluated the commercialization potential of the Adaptive Robotic Nursing Assistant (ARNA) technology developed at the Next Generation Systems Group (NGS). The team interviewed over 120 potential customers for the robot technology, many of them covering the hospital, rather than the nursing home markets. The team spoke to nurses, nurse administrators, doctors, hospital C-Suite administrators, and with robotics suppliers and developed a lean canvass for a future $B commercial opportunity. Interviews were conducted in both urban and rural hospitals, in Kentucky, Oklahoma, Pennsylvania and other health care markets.  Although our robot was developed with prior funding from the NSF PFI:BIC program, with consideration of market needs early in the design process, the customer discovery undertaken in this project helped the team narrow a value proposition, and a product market fit centered around ambulation to speed up patient recovery. Finally, the team used the customer discovery findings to seek additional funding for their startup company to further commercialize the patented ARNA technology.   During the project, the team further refined a minimum viable product (MVP) by upgrading the robot's navigation sensor suite, re-designing the handlebar responsible for physical interaction during ambulation, and conducted additional testing of the neuro-adaptive controller embedded in the robot. During 2020 and 2021, the robot was also tested in conjunction with COVID-19 disinfection tasks in our lab's research building, and discussions were conducted with hospital administrators in Louisville interested in seeing the robot in action. The robot was also showcased to numerous health care companies, nurses, and STEM educators over a two year period at UofL's newly established robotics institute (LARRI) and at the School of Nursing.           Last Modified: 11/15/2022       Submitted by: Dan O Popa]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
