<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[NSF Student Travel Grant for 2020  IEEE International Symposium On Field-Programmable Custom Computing Machines (FCCM 2020)]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>15000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>15000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Marilyn McClure</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mmcclure@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925197</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The 2020 IEEE International Symposium On Field-Programmable Custom Computing Machine (FCCM) will be held in Fayetteville AR from May 03 to May 06, 2020.  FCCM is a forum for presenting and discussing new research related to computing that exploits the unique features and capabilities of field-programmable gate arrays (FPGAs) and other reconfigurable hardware, development on architectures, tools, programming models and applications. The conference is organized over multiple technical sessions, workshops, panels and a demo night where companies, research groups and students present the latest development in the field. &lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;Travel grants will make possible the participation of 15 graduate and undergraduate students who will substantially benefit from attending this conference but have limited travel funds. Besides attending technical sessions and learning about latest developments in the field of FPGA, students will benefit from interaction with leading researchers, companies and institutions in the field. This can lead to Internships and full employment opportunities between students and participating companies. Priority will be given to first time attendees, especially those seeking research topics and in the early stages of developing their research agendas. A portion of the award will be devoted to under-represented groups for which substantial recruitment efforts will be undertaken.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/23/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/23/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2016161</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Christophe</FirstName>
<LastName>Bobda</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Christophe Bobda</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[cbobda@ufl.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000583623</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/23/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Florida</Name>
<CityName>GAINESVILLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>326111941</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3523923516</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1523 UNION RD RM 207</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NNFQH1JAPEP3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF FLORIDA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>D4GCCCMXR1H3</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Florida]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>326112002</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7354</Code>
<Text>CSR-Computer Systems Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7354</Code>
<Text>COMPUTER SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~15000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This grant has provided students from various US institutions support to attend the IEEE Symposium on Field-Programmable Custom Computing Machines (FCCM). The grant was awarded in 2019 but because of COVID, the conference took place in person only in 2022.</p> <p>FCCM is the original and premier forum for presenting and discussing new research related to computing that exploits the unique features and capabilities of Field Programmable Gate Arrays (FPGA) and other reconfigurable hardware. Over the past two decades, FCCM has been the place to present leading research and development on architectures, tools, and programming models for field-programmable custom computing machines as well as applications that use such systems.</p> <p>Attending this high-caliber technical event, with multiple technical sessions and workshops, is important for a graduate student&rsquo;s professional development. The students had the opportunity to present their work during a special session to experts and be exposed to state-of-the-art developments in the field. They also used the opportunity to interact with peers from other institutions and companies and met with leading researchers.</p> <p>Overall, 17 students (12 males and 5 females) from the following universities were awarded travel grants, ranging from $400 to $1000. Cornell University, University of Massachusetts Amherst, The University of Texas at Austin, Northeastern University, North Carolina State University, University of Pittsburgh, University of California, Los Angeles, Rice University, University of Southern California, UTRGV, and Yale University.</p> <p>The commercial acceptance of FPGAs as illustrated by numerous products that employ FPGAs has made FPGA devices one of the main computational computing devices in a wide-range of applications. Over the years, FCCM has acquired a solid reputation as one of the most selective conferences in computer architecture, with acceptance rates between 15 and 18%.</p> <p>All participating students have reported that the grant was instrumental for them to attend the conference, getting exposure to the FPGA community and learning about the newest developments in the field.</p> <p><br /> <br /></p> <p>Last Modified: 12/01/2023<br /> Modified by: Christophe&nbsp;Bobda</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/11/2023<br>      Modified by: Christophe&nbsp;Bobda</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This grant has provided students from various US institutions support to attend the IEEE Symposium on Field-Programmable Custom Computing Machines (FCCM). The grant was awarded in 2019 but because of COVID, the conference took place in person only in 2022.  FCCM is the original and premier forum for presenting and discussing new research related to computing that exploits the unique features and capabilities of Field Programmable Gate Arrays (FPGA) and other reconfigurable hardware. Over the past two decades, FCCM has been the place to present leading research and development on architectures, tools, and programming models for field-programmable custom computing machines as well as applications that use such systems.  Attending this high-caliber technical event, with multiple technical sessions and workshops, is important for a graduate student’s professional development. The students had the opportunity to present their work during a special session to experts and be exposed to state-of-the-art developments in the field. They also used the opportunity to interact with peers from other institutions and companies and met with leading researchers.  Overall, 17 students (12 males and 5 females) from the following universities were awarded travel grants, ranging from $400 to $1000. Cornell University, University of Massachusetts Amherst, The University of Texas at Austin, Northeastern University, North Carolina State University, University of Pittsburgh, University of California, Los Angeles, Rice University, University of Southern California, UTRGV, and Yale University.  The commercial acceptance of FPGAs as illustrated by numerous products that employ FPGAs has made FPGA devices one of the main computational computing devices in a wide-range of applications. Over the years, FCCM has acquired a solid reputation as one of the most selective conferences in computer architecture, with acceptance rates between 15 and 18%.  All participating students have reported that the grant was instrumental for them to attend the conference, getting exposure to the FPGA community and learning about the newest developments in the field.       Last Modified: 12/01/2023  Modified by: Christophe Bobda          Last Modified: 01/11/2023       Submitted by: Christophe Bobda]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
