<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[PFI-TT: Mobile device-based detection of toxins in food crops to monitor food safety and improve public health]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>250000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>299998</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Samir M. Iqbal</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>smiqbal@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927529</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Partnerships for Innovation - Technology Translation (PFI-TT) project is enabling food safety testing at most stages in the food-systems value chain by multiple stakeholders, including farmers and consumers at the individual level, the food industry at the points of procurement, storage, and distribution, and by aid agencies to monitor the safety of food aid packages. The initial focus will be to detect two mycotoxins, aflatoxin and fumonisin, both of which are known cancer-causing food contaminants and are found in several food crops including corn. The maximum concentration levels for mycotoxins have been prescribed by many countries; however, these cannot be enforced in most settings because of lack of tools to assess their concentration at the point-of-need. The present work will develop a rapid, low-cost, point-of-need assay for ascertaining food safety with required sensitivity and specificity as recommended by domestic and international food safety agencies. In addition, the team will work with the business partner to optimize the technology for transfer and commercialization to enable it to reach market. It is anticipated that this technology has the potential to significantly reduce unsafe food from the marketplace and improve public health worldwide.&lt;br/&gt;  &lt;br/&gt;The proposed project is focused on developing a technology for point-of-need assessment of food safety by detection of aflatoxin (AF) and fumonisin (FM) in food crops. These mycotoxins can contaminate several food crops including corn, rice, and peanuts.  Consumption of contaminated food can lead to cancer and other adverse health outcomes. The current approach of sending food samples to centralized labs for food safety testing requires expensive equipment, is time-consuming, requires skilled technicians, and is not cost-effective. The proposed technology comprises of a mobile device, a custom-made test strip that accepts food sample extracts and performs the analysis with the help of a smartphone application. The smartphone app operates its imaging system, interprets the test strip results, and displays the results in a few minutes. The analysis results can be transferred to a remote server for monitoring of food safety results. The primary goals of the project include the development of lateral flow assays for AF and FM, optimization of techniques for extracting AF and/or FM from food crops, updating existing smartphone apps to customize them for AF and/or FM detection, and small-scale validation in the lab to determine the performance parameters of the developed sample-in-answer-out assays.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/10/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/11/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2016522</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Erickson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David C Erickson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[de54@cornell.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000486981</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Saurabh</FirstName>
<LastName>Mehta</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Saurabh Mehta</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[smehta@cornell.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000644806</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Timothy</FirstName>
<LastName>Herrman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Timothy J Herrman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[tjh@otsc.tamu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000796259</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Wei</FirstName>
<LastName>Li</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Wei Li</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[wei@otsc.tamu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000819404</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Cornell University</Name>
<CityName>ITHACA</CityName>
<ZipCode>148502820</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6072555014</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>341 PINE TREE RD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>19</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY19</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>G56PUALJ3KT5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CORNELL UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Cornell University]]></Name>
<CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>148502820</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[373 Pine Tree Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>19</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY19</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1662</Code>
<Text>PFI-Partnrships for Innovation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1491</Code>
<Text>BIOTECH, BIOCHEM &amp; BIOMASS ENG</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8038</Code>
<Text>Biotechnology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>CL10</Code>
<Text>CLB-Career Life Balance</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~250000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~49998</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>PFI-TT: Mobile device-based detection of toxins in food crops to monitor food safety and improve public health&nbsp;</strong></p> <p><strong>Plain Language Project Outcomes Report </strong></p> <p>Mycotoxins are naturally occurring toxins produced by certain molds in food and have been shown to cause adverse health effects including poisoning and cancer. Aflatoxins (AF) are among the most commonly found toxins in crops. The World Health Organization recommends that food such as maize (corn) be inspected for evidence of mold before consumption and is committed to protecting the public from mycotoxin exposure through researchand assessment. Our team sought to develop and test a portable, smart phone based system (SAFEphone) that would enable users to easily test the levels of AF and FM mycotoxins in maize at the point of production, storage and distribution in order to detect the presence of food contamination and improve public health.</p> <p>Our team successfully completed the following tasks during the project period 1) developed and validated a new lateral flow assay for aflatoxin B1 (AFB1), 2) configured a new portable test strip reader CubeTM (Chembio Diagnostics GmbH, Germany) to assess its performance and suitability for using the AFB1assay in the field where maize is being produced and distributed (see example of Cube reader and test strips in photos). This smart phone based mobile technology can have global impact by significantly reducingunsafe food from the marketplace thereby improvingpublic health worldwide. This project also allowed our team to participate in the National Science FoundationI-Corps course in the Spring 2022 which enabled us to expand our knowledge and share ideas across a multidisciplinary team. We now have a foundation to transition this new technology to real world industry users.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/23/2022<br>      Modified by: Saurabh&nbsp;Mehta</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2016522/2016522_10706030_1669241239532_Image11-16-22at1.39PM--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2016522/2016522_10706030_1669241239532_Image11-16-22at1.39PM--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Reader and Test Strips"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2016522/2016522_10706030_1669241239532_Image11-16-22at1.39PM--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Reader and Test Strips"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">A photograph of the cube reader and the test strip prototypes</div> <div class="imageCredit">Balaji Srinivasan</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Saurabh&nbsp;Mehta</div> <div class="imageTitle">Reader and Test Strips</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ PFI-TT: Mobile device-based detection of toxins in food crops to monitor food safety and improve public health   Plain Language Project Outcomes Report   Mycotoxins are naturally occurring toxins produced by certain molds in food and have been shown to cause adverse health effects including poisoning and cancer. Aflatoxins (AF) are among the most commonly found toxins in crops. The World Health Organization recommends that food such as maize (corn) be inspected for evidence of mold before consumption and is committed to protecting the public from mycotoxin exposure through researchand assessment. Our team sought to develop and test a portable, smart phone based system (SAFEphone) that would enable users to easily test the levels of AF and FM mycotoxins in maize at the point of production, storage and distribution in order to detect the presence of food contamination and improve public health.  Our team successfully completed the following tasks during the project period 1) developed and validated a new lateral flow assay for aflatoxin B1 (AFB1), 2) configured a new portable test strip reader CubeTM (Chembio Diagnostics GmbH, Germany) to assess its performance and suitability for using the AFB1assay in the field where maize is being produced and distributed (see example of Cube reader and test strips in photos). This smart phone based mobile technology can have global impact by significantly reducingunsafe food from the marketplace thereby improvingpublic health worldwide. This project also allowed our team to participate in the National Science FoundationI-Corps course in the Spring 2022 which enabled us to expand our knowledge and share ideas across a multidisciplinary team. We now have a foundation to transition this new technology to real world industry users.       Last Modified: 11/23/2022       Submitted by: Saurabh Mehta]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
