<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research: Expanding the Reach of Industrial Career Training for Graduate Students]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>8400.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>8400</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Swatee Naik</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>snaik@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924876</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The 16th annual Graduate Student Mathematical Modeling Camp (GSMMC) will be held June 9–12, 2021 at the University of Delaware, followed the week after by the 36th annual Mathematical Problems in Industry (MPI) workshop, June 14–18, 2021 at the University of Vermont.  GSMMC is a mentored, problem-solving workshop, at which small teams of Ph.D. students from across the U.S. are guided through successful mathematical modeling of real-world problems presented by faculty or experienced postdoctoral mentors. Under careful mentoring, student participants build their modeling, teamwork and presentation skills during the week: via the teamwork on modeling and simulating the problems; through the final team presentations made at the end of the week; and in writing the final reports that are produced. Training activities also include numerical simulations and the preparation of a final report outlining their discoveries.  These skills are put to use and consolidated the following week at MPI, where industrial participants present immediate modeling challenges facing their industries, on which academic participants (faculty, postdocs, and the Ph.D. students from GSMMC) work. Significant progress on the industrial problems is usually made, and Ph.D. student participants take the lead in presenting the findings to the industrial participants from industry in final presentations at the week's end. In addition to building their skillsets and resumes, student participants are exposed to valuable networking interactions with a range of industrial participants.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The GSMMC-MPI program is designed to integrate interdisciplinary research and education for graduate students. The GSMMC is focused on graduate student education and training: its chief intellectual merit lies in the development and analysis, by students, of the mathematical models for the problems presented. Problems are highly interdisciplinary, presenting students with a novel intellectual challenge. With the preparatory training provided by the GSMMC, students are ready for the more open-ended, research-level environment of MPI. The questions posed at MPI challenge participants to design new ways of modeling and analyzing industrial mathematics problems in emerging areas of technology. Mathematical modeling, analytical techniques, numerical simulations, and data analysis must all be used effectively. The collaborative approach to problem solving, which brings together mathematicians ranging from graduate students to experienced faculty, is central to the structure of MPI and provides significant additional training to graduate students, while promoting effective scientific communication. Full details for the Camp may be found at https://www.mathsci.udel.edu/events/conferences/gsmmc-2021, and for MPI at https://mpi2021.w3.uvm.edu/.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/20/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/20/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2016099</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Taras</FirstName>
<LastName>Lakoba</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Taras Lakoba</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[tlakoba@uvm.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000164582</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/20/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Bagrow</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>James P Bagrow</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[james.bagrow@uvm.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000610862</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/20/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate>04/20/2021</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Vermont &amp; State Agricultural College</Name>
<CityName>BURLINGTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>054051704</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8026563660</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>85 S PROSPECT STREET</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Vermont</StateName>
<StateCode>VT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>VT00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>Z94KLERAG5V9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF VERMONT &amp; STATE AGRICULTURAL COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Vermont & State Agricultural College]]></Name>
<CityName>Burlington</CityName>
<StateCode>VT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>054050156</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Votey Building]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Vermont</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>VT00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1260</Code>
<Text>INFRASTRUCTURE PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~8400</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The funds were supposed to be used to support graduate student participation&nbsp;in the Mathematical Problems in Industry workshop in 2021, held at the Universityof Vermont (UVM). The funds were not used at UVM since the workshop in 2021 was&nbsp;held remotely, and no travel or lodging expenses were incurred.<br /><br />However, the Graduate Student Camp organizer at the University of Delaware (UD),Prof. David Edwards, did incur extra expenses, because the graduate students whoattended the Camp (June 10 - 13, 2021) as a venue preparing them for the workshop,&nbsp;had to stay at UD during the workshop (June 14 - 18, 2021) and participate remotely&nbsp;from there. Thus, the Camp organizer had to cover the students' meals and housing&nbsp;expenses during the week of the workshop. Since the US Camp was part of this grant'sapplication, all the funds allocated for UVM were paid to the UD Camp organizer.&nbsp;</p> <p>The funds transferred to the graduate student Camp at UD were used to support participation in the workshop of 23 graduate students. These students worked on 3 different projects.Final scientific reports of these projects are found here:</p> <p>https://mpi2021.w3.uvm.edu/program.php</p> <p>One of these project reports was also published here:<br />https://www.cambridge.org/engage/miir/event-details/615b3997fb8619c213ed17f0</p> <p><br />Please contact the Camp organizer, Prof. David Edwards of UD (a co-PI on this grant) for the demographic information of Camp's participants.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/30/2022<br>      Modified by: Taras&nbsp;Lakoba</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The funds were supposed to be used to support graduate student participation in the Mathematical Problems in Industry workshop in 2021, held at the Universityof Vermont (UVM). The funds were not used at UVM since the workshop in 2021 was held remotely, and no travel or lodging expenses were incurred.  However, the Graduate Student Camp organizer at the University of Delaware (UD),Prof. David Edwards, did incur extra expenses, because the graduate students whoattended the Camp (June 10 - 13, 2021) as a venue preparing them for the workshop, had to stay at UD during the workshop (June 14 - 18, 2021) and participate remotely from there. Thus, the Camp organizer had to cover the students' meals and housing expenses during the week of the workshop. Since the US Camp was part of this grant'sapplication, all the funds allocated for UVM were paid to the UD Camp organizer.   The funds transferred to the graduate student Camp at UD were used to support participation in the workshop of 23 graduate students. These students worked on 3 different projects.Final scientific reports of these projects are found here:  https://mpi2021.w3.uvm.edu/program.php  One of these project reports was also published here: https://www.cambridge.org/engage/miir/event-details/615b3997fb8619c213ed17f0   Please contact the Camp organizer, Prof. David Edwards of UD (a co-PI on this grant) for the demographic information of Camp's participants.         Last Modified: 06/30/2022       Submitted by: Taras Lakoba]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
