<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[CAREER: Developing Accurate Crystallography Without Diffraction]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>255406.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>255406</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kelsey Cook</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kcook@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927490</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[With this award, the Chemical Measurements and Imaging Program of the Chemistry Division is funding Dr. James Harper of the University of Central Florida to extend the capability of theoretical methods to accurately predict crystal structures.  Presently, many compounds and even entire classes of compounds are unsuitable for analysis by conventional crystallography methods.  This project combines lattice prediction methods with experimental NMR data to provide new methodology capable of solving structural problems that are now intractable.  This outcome will impact society by improving the ability to characterize a host of new materials.  For example, nearly 60 cephalosporin antibiotics have been described since 1955, yet over 93% in the structures have never been characterized crystallographically. The project focuses on characterizing key cephalosporins as well as other challenging materials.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project focuses on improving the theoretical prediction of crystal structure by including experimental solid-state NMR data in the prediction process.  The NMR data serve to identify a single high-probability conformation before the prediction process.  Because many lattice prediction programs robustly and accurately treat rigid structures but are challenged by flexibility, the NMR data improves prediction by limiting the conformational space searched.  The experimental NMR measurements focus primarily on 13C and 15N chemical shift tensors because such data provide three measurable parameters for each molecular position.  Uncertainties in atomic positions are provided through a molecular dynamics process, to ultimately create structures suitable for deposit into crystallographic databases.  The broader impact of this work includes training students from a primarily undergraduate institution (Washington and Jefferson College) in an annual three week NMR course involving 6-8 students, the creation of a series of Open Courseware lectures describing basic NMR concepts and the more specialized tensor measurement methods, and outreach into the scouting community of central Florida through lab tours and voluntary teaching of merit badge courses.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/10/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/10/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2016185</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Harper</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>K</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>James K Harper</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jkharper@chem.byu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000624615</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Brigham Young University</Name>
<CityName>PROVO</CityName>
<ZipCode>846021128</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8014223360</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>A-153 ASB</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Utah</StateName>
<StateCode>UT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>UT03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>JWSYC7RUMJD1</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>BRIGHAM YOUNG UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Brigham Young University]]></Name>
<CityName>Provo</CityName>
<StateCode>UT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>846025700</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Department of Chemistry and Bioc]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Utah</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>UT03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6880</Code>
<Text>Chemical Measurement &amp; Imaging</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01001516DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01001617DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~14650</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~240756</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Work from this award resulted in 20 publications in peer-reviewed journals.&nbsp; These publications have included 17 graduate students and 8 undergraduates as authors. Two of the students supported by this grant have now graduated with a Ph.D. and a third is expected to graduate in 2022. Broader impacts include teaching of a short course on NMR spectroscopy at two primarily undergraduate institutions and creating a chemistry related workshop for girl scouts.&nbsp; More details on key outcomes are summarized below.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Publications - Intellectual outcomes</strong>. Key publications resulting from this funding are summarized below.</p> <p>1.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; <strong>Title</strong>: Predicting anisotropic thermal displacements for hydrogens from solid-state NMR: a study on hydrogen bonding in polymorphs of palmitic acid</p> <p><strong>Authors</strong>: Wang, L.; Uribe-Romo, F. J.; Mueller, L. J.; Harper, J. K.</p> <p><strong>Journal</strong>: Physical Chemistry Chemical Physics, 2018, Vol. 20, p. 8475.</p> <p><strong>Summary</strong>: An approach is described for predicting the errors in atom positions for crystal structures derived from nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) spectroscopy.&nbsp; The uncertainties predicted by this approach are nearly ten times smaller than those obtained from x-ray diffraction and approximately half the magnitude of the errors from neutron diffraction data.</p> <p>2.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; <strong>Title</strong>: TensorView: A software tool for displaying NMR tensors</p> <p><strong>Authors</strong>: Young, R. P.; Lewis, C. R.; Yang, C.; Wang, L.; Harper, J. K.; Mueller, L.</p> <p><strong>Journal</strong>: Magnetic Resonance in Chemistry, 2018, Vol. 57, p. 211.</p> <p><strong>Summary</strong>: A software program is reported that allows the errors in atom positions to be displayed.&nbsp; These NMR derived ellipsoids can be displayed on the atoms within a microcrystalline structure, even in cases where the crystal structure is unknown or a solid has only weak long range order.&nbsp; An illustration where only the COOH hydrogen in a fatty acid was characterized in shown in Figure 1.</p> <p>3.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; <strong>Title</strong>: Monitoring the refinement of crystal structures with <sup>15</sup>N solid-state NMR shift tensor data.</p> <p><strong>Authors</strong>: Kalakewich, K.; Iuliucci, R.; Mueller, K. T.; Eloranta, H.; Harper, J. K.</p> <p><strong>Journal</strong>: Journal of Chemical Physics, 2015, Vol. 143, article number 194702.</p> <p><strong>Summary</strong>: An improved NMR experiment is described for measuring N-15 chemical shift tensors and shown to be highly accurate.&nbsp; A total of 39 values were measured spanning a range of nearly 400 ppm.&nbsp; These data have become important benchmark data for several theoretical studies.&nbsp; This study also includes work demonstrating one of the first accurate predictions of N-15 shift tensors using theoretical computational methods.</p> <p>4.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; <strong>Title</strong>: Exploiting <sup>13</sup>C/<sup>14</sup>N solid-state distance measurements to assign dihedral angles and locate neighboring molecules.</p> <p><strong>Authors</strong>: Pope, G. M.; Hung, I.; Gan, Z.; Mobarak, H.; Widmalm, G.; Harper, J. K.</p> <p><strong>Journal</strong>: Chemical Communications, 2018, Vol. 54, p. 6376.</p> <p><strong>Summary</strong>: The NMR measurement of Carbon to nitrogen distances for multiple sites within a molecule was demonstrated. This study fulfills a long-standing expectation that C/N distance measurements will become an important tool in structural analysis of solids.&nbsp; This work is the first to demonstrate that such structural information can now be obtained.&nbsp; This study will be a valuable addition to structural studies of materials where the growth of crystals suitable for more conventional crystallography is difficult.</p> <p>5.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; <strong>Title</strong>: refining crystal structures using <sup>13</sup>C NMR chemical shift tensors as a target function.</p> <p><strong>Authors</strong>: Wang, L.; Harper, J. K.</p> <p><strong>Journal</strong>: CrystEngComm, 2021,DOI: 10.1039/d1ce00960e.</p> <p><strong>Summary</strong>: This study demonstrates an NMR based refinement process that adjusts crystal structures from any source to create highly accurate final coordinates.&nbsp; Several non-NMR metrics, examine before and after refinement, indicate that this process does not introduce structural errors. This refinement process appears to provide the most accurate computed <sup>13</sup>C chemical shift data presently available.&nbsp; An illustration of the agreement between computed and experimental shifts is shown in Figure 2.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Broader outcomes</strong>. Some of the important achievements are described below.</p> <p>1.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; A graduate level course on NMR spectroscopy (CHM 5937) was developed and taught at the University of Central Florida.</p> <p>2.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; A short-course was developed to teach basic principles of NMR at primarily undergraduate institutions.&nbsp; Instruction was given at Washington and Jefferson College and Utah Valley University. Approximately 50 students have participated in the program.</p> <p>3.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Community instruction.&nbsp; During the funding period, mosquito borne infections from the Zika virus become a concern in Florida.&nbsp; A workshop was developed aimed at educating girl scouts on the dangers of the Zika virus. This session allowed all participants to make a liter of mosquito repellent based on aloe vera and naturally occurring compounds.&nbsp; This hour-long course has been in great demand over the past several years and over 100 girl scout and their leaders have participated.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/13/2021<br>      Modified by: James&nbsp;K&nbsp;Harper</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2016185/2016185_10373753_1634167764127_Figure1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2016185/2016185_10373753_1634167764127_Figure1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 1"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2016185/2016185_10373753_1634167764127_Figure1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 1"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">An illustration of the uncertainty in H atom position for the COOH hydrogen.</div> <div class="imageCredit">James Harper</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">James&nbsp;K&nbsp;Harper</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 1</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2016185/2016185_10373753_1634167855018_Figure2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2016185/2016185_10373753_1634167855018_Figure2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 2"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2016185/2016185_10373753_1634167855018_Figure2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 2"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">An illustration of the close agreement between computed and experimental 13C shift tensors obtained for the PIs NMR-based refinement process</div> <div class="imageCredit">James Harper</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">James&nbsp;K&nbsp;Harper</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 2</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2016185/2016185_10373753_1634167937580_Figure3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2016185/2016185_10373753_1634167937580_Figure3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 3"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2016185/2016185_10373753_1634167937580_Figure3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 3"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Girl scouts and the PI making a natural product based mosquito repellent to protect against the Zika virus.</div> <div class="imageCredit">James Harper</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">James&nbsp;K&nbsp;Harper</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 3</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Work from this award resulted in 20 publications in peer-reviewed journals.  These publications have included 17 graduate students and 8 undergraduates as authors. Two of the students supported by this grant have now graduated with a Ph.D. and a third is expected to graduate in 2022. Broader impacts include teaching of a short course on NMR spectroscopy at two primarily undergraduate institutions and creating a chemistry related workshop for girl scouts.  More details on key outcomes are summarized below.     Publications - Intellectual outcomes. Key publications resulting from this funding are summarized below.  1.     Title: Predicting anisotropic thermal displacements for hydrogens from solid-state NMR: a study on hydrogen bonding in polymorphs of palmitic acid  Authors: Wang, L.; Uribe-Romo, F. J.; Mueller, L. J.; Harper, J. K.  Journal: Physical Chemistry Chemical Physics, 2018, Vol. 20, p. 8475.  Summary: An approach is described for predicting the errors in atom positions for crystal structures derived from nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) spectroscopy.  The uncertainties predicted by this approach are nearly ten times smaller than those obtained from x-ray diffraction and approximately half the magnitude of the errors from neutron diffraction data.  2.     Title: TensorView: A software tool for displaying NMR tensors  Authors: Young, R. P.; Lewis, C. R.; Yang, C.; Wang, L.; Harper, J. K.; Mueller, L.  Journal: Magnetic Resonance in Chemistry, 2018, Vol. 57, p. 211.  Summary: A software program is reported that allows the errors in atom positions to be displayed.  These NMR derived ellipsoids can be displayed on the atoms within a microcrystalline structure, even in cases where the crystal structure is unknown or a solid has only weak long range order.  An illustration where only the COOH hydrogen in a fatty acid was characterized in shown in Figure 1.  3.     Title: Monitoring the refinement of crystal structures with 15N solid-state NMR shift tensor data.  Authors: Kalakewich, K.; Iuliucci, R.; Mueller, K. T.; Eloranta, H.; Harper, J. K.  Journal: Journal of Chemical Physics, 2015, Vol. 143, article number 194702.  Summary: An improved NMR experiment is described for measuring N-15 chemical shift tensors and shown to be highly accurate.  A total of 39 values were measured spanning a range of nearly 400 ppm.  These data have become important benchmark data for several theoretical studies.  This study also includes work demonstrating one of the first accurate predictions of N-15 shift tensors using theoretical computational methods.  4.     Title: Exploiting 13C/14N solid-state distance measurements to assign dihedral angles and locate neighboring molecules.  Authors: Pope, G. M.; Hung, I.; Gan, Z.; Mobarak, H.; Widmalm, G.; Harper, J. K.  Journal: Chemical Communications, 2018, Vol. 54, p. 6376.  Summary: The NMR measurement of Carbon to nitrogen distances for multiple sites within a molecule was demonstrated. This study fulfills a long-standing expectation that C/N distance measurements will become an important tool in structural analysis of solids.  This work is the first to demonstrate that such structural information can now be obtained.  This study will be a valuable addition to structural studies of materials where the growth of crystals suitable for more conventional crystallography is difficult.  5.     Title: refining crystal structures using 13C NMR chemical shift tensors as a target function.  Authors: Wang, L.; Harper, J. K.  Journal: CrystEngComm, 2021,DOI: 10.1039/d1ce00960e.  Summary: This study demonstrates an NMR based refinement process that adjusts crystal structures from any source to create highly accurate final coordinates.  Several non-NMR metrics, examine before and after refinement, indicate that this process does not introduce structural errors. This refinement process appears to provide the most accurate computed 13C chemical shift data presently available.  An illustration of the agreement between computed and experimental shifts is shown in Figure 2.     Broader outcomes. Some of the important achievements are described below.  1.     A graduate level course on NMR spectroscopy (CHM 5937) was developed and taught at the University of Central Florida.  2.     A short-course was developed to teach basic principles of NMR at primarily undergraduate institutions.  Instruction was given at Washington and Jefferson College and Utah Valley University. Approximately 50 students have participated in the program.  3.     Community instruction.  During the funding period, mosquito borne infections from the Zika virus become a concern in Florida.  A workshop was developed aimed at educating girl scouts on the dangers of the Zika virus. This session allowed all participants to make a liter of mosquito repellent based on aloe vera and naturally occurring compounds.  This hour-long course has been in great demand over the past several years and over 100 girl scout and their leaders have participated.          Last Modified: 10/13/2021       Submitted by: James K Harper]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
