<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[NSF Student Travel Grant for 2020 Conferences on  File and Storage Technologies (FAST) and Networked Design and Implementation (NSDI)]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Erik Brunvand</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ebrunvan@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928950</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This grant requests funding for graduate students attending US Universities to travel to the following research conferences:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;-18th USENIX Conference on File and Storage Technologies (FAST 2020), February 24-27, 2020, Santa Clara, CA, USA.&lt;br/&gt;-17th USENIX Symposium on Networked Systems Design and Implementation (NSDI 2020), February 25-27, 2020 in Santa Clara, CA, USA.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The USENIX Association organizes conferences on computing innovation and research that build collaborations between researchers and practitioners from industry, government, and academia. These events provide educational, mentorship, and networking opportunities to graduate students in the computer sciences who attend. The research and computing knowledge shared and advanced at these conferences has practical and meaningful application to many tools used in daily life, as well as to the ethical, cultural, and social ramifications of computing technology. This grant allows the participation of students who would otherwise be unable to attend the conference, and extends the impact of the research presented to a broad audience of young researchers from across the country. USENIX is an open access organization, and all research and results presented and published at these events are freely available to the public.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This grant will support 20 students for the FAST 2020 meeting. FAST is a forum for research in storage systems, bringing together top researchers and practitioners from both industry and academia to explore new directions in the design, implementation, evaluation, and deployment of storage systems. The conference will consist of two and a half days of technical presentations, including refereed papers, Work-in-Progress reports, and two poster sessions. There will also be training sessions offered on the days prior to the technical sessions. FAST has been taking place annually since 2008, and bi-annually prior to that. This grant will support 20 students for the NSDI 2020 meeting. NSDI focuses on the design principles and challenges in the construction of large-scale networks and distributed systems. Particular areas of interest include cloud services, wireless, internet routing, peer-to-peer systems, sensor nets, scalable web services, data center networking, distributed malware, and distributed network measurement. NSDI unites researchers from across the networking and systems community—including computer networking, distributed systems, and operating systems—to foster cross-disciplinary approaches and to address shared research challenges.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/28/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/28/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2016092</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Camille</FirstName>
<LastName>Mulligan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Camille Mulligan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[camille@usenix.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000638474</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/28/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>USENIX Association</Name>
<CityName>LONG BEACH</CityName>
<ZipCode>986316410</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5105288649</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>16415 M ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>QJK1RVEY72A6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>USENIX ASSOCIATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[USENIX Association]]></Name>
<CityName>Berkeley</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>947102565</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2560 Ninth St Suite 215, Suite 2]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7354</Code>
<Text>CSR-Computer Systems Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7363</Code>
<Text>Networking Technology and Syst</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-4033b54e-7fff-a02e-4264-a368a7cdcb6a"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>This grant provided travel funding to assist US-based graduate students to attend two USENIX events in 2020, specifically the 17th </span><span>Symposium on Networked Systems Design and Implementation</span><span> (NSDI '20) and the </span><span>Conference on File and Storage Technologies (</span><span>FAST '20).&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>NSDI '20 took place February 25-27, 2020, in Santa Clara, CA at the Hyatt Regency Santa Clara and focused on the design principles of large-scale networks and distributed systems and, in particular, challenges that are shared across systems as diverse as internet routing, peer-to-peer file sharing, sensor nets, scalable web services, and distributed network measurement. FAST '20, which was held February 24-27, 2020 in the same location, </span><span>was a forum for innovative research in storage systems, and a premier publishing conference for professionals in the field of file and storage systems research and innovation.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Participation in these and similar conferences is a valuable and important part of the graduate school experience. It provides students with the opportunity to interact with more senior researchers in the field, and exposes students to leading edge work in the field. This grant made possible the participation of graduate level students who would otherwise be unable to attend the conferences, and extends the impact of research presented to a broad audience of young researchers from across the country. Participating students at each event were offered specific activities to enhance their interactions with senior researchers and organizers, including the student meetup, game night, birds-of-a-feather sessions, and the poster sessions/receptions. The NSF funding provided under this award allowed us to substantially increase the number of students we could support with grants for NSDI '20 and FAST '20.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Any student enrolled full-time at an accredited US university or college was eligible to apply for a grant. Grants had two components: 1) registration costs and 2) expenses. For those students selected, USENIX covered registration costs by providing students with a registration code for full student registration. For the expense portion, USENIX provided a check to assist the student with costs related to airfare and hotel. Variations in the flat rates offered depend on how far a student needed to travel and the amount they requested (i.e., some students may stay with a friend in the town of the conference and therefore did not have a hotel expense). We confirmed that the student recipients registered and attended the event.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The criteria we looked at in selecting grant recipients included:</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>&#9679;&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; Conference participation (e.g., presenting a poster)</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>&#9679;&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; Areas of study that significantly overlapped with the conference topics</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>&#9679;&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; Concision of supporting statement outlining the applicant?s research</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>&#9679;&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; Application history, prioritizing first time applicants and applicants who had not received a grant in the previous 12 months</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>&#9679;&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; Students from institutions not traditionally represented at USENIX events</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>&#9679;&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; Students from historically underrepresented communities and minorities</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>&#9679;&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; Class level and financial need</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The NSF funds supported a total of 43 grants for students to participate in the two events. Grants provided across the events are detailed below:&nbsp;</span></p> <ul> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>For NSDI '20, USENIX received 59 grant applications from students and awarded 31 grants. The NSF funds of $24,880 covered 23 of these grants, and all those awardees were enrolled at U.S. universities. There were 362 total attendees at NSDI '20, which included 126 student attendees.&nbsp;</span></p> </li> </ul> <ul> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>For FAST '20, USENIX received 53 grant applications from students and awarded 29 grants. The NSF funds of $25,120 covered 20 of these grants, and all those awardees were enrolled at U.S. universities. There were 408 total attendees at FAST '20, which included 90 student attendees in total. </span></p> </li> </ul> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/11/2022<br>      Modified by: Camille&nbsp;Mulligan</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2016092/2016092_10655174_1652288228351_IMG_1402--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2016092/2016092_10655174_1652288228351_IMG_1402--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Student Grant Recipient Photo FAST '20"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2016092/2016092_10655174_1652288228351_IMG_1402--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Student Grant Recipient Photo FAST '20"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Student Grant Recipients, FAST '20</div> <div class="imageCredit">USENIX</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Camille&nbsp;Mulligan</div> <div class="imageTitle">Student Grant Recipient Photo FAST '20</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2016092/2016092_10655174_1652288361605_ImagefromiOS(78)--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2016092/2016092_10655174_1652288361605_ImagefromiOS(78)--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Student Grant Recipient Photo NSDI '20"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2016092/2016092_10655174_1652288361605_ImagefromiOS(78)--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Student Grant Recipient Photo NSDI '20"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Student grant recipients, NSDI '20</div> <div class="imageCredit">USENIX</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Camille&nbsp;Mulligan</div> <div class="imageTitle">Student Grant Recipient Photo NSDI '20</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   This grant provided travel funding to assist US-based graduate students to attend two USENIX events in 2020, specifically the 17th Symposium on Networked Systems Design and Implementation (NSDI '20) and the Conference on File and Storage Technologies (FAST '20).  NSDI '20 took place February 25-27, 2020, in Santa Clara, CA at the Hyatt Regency Santa Clara and focused on the design principles of large-scale networks and distributed systems and, in particular, challenges that are shared across systems as diverse as internet routing, peer-to-peer file sharing, sensor nets, scalable web services, and distributed network measurement. FAST '20, which was held February 24-27, 2020 in the same location, was a forum for innovative research in storage systems, and a premier publishing conference for professionals in the field of file and storage systems research and innovation. Participation in these and similar conferences is a valuable and important part of the graduate school experience. It provides students with the opportunity to interact with more senior researchers in the field, and exposes students to leading edge work in the field. This grant made possible the participation of graduate level students who would otherwise be unable to attend the conferences, and extends the impact of research presented to a broad audience of young researchers from across the country. Participating students at each event were offered specific activities to enhance their interactions with senior researchers and organizers, including the student meetup, game night, birds-of-a-feather sessions, and the poster sessions/receptions. The NSF funding provided under this award allowed us to substantially increase the number of students we could support with grants for NSDI '20 and FAST '20.  Any student enrolled full-time at an accredited US university or college was eligible to apply for a grant. Grants had two components: 1) registration costs and 2) expenses. For those students selected, USENIX covered registration costs by providing students with a registration code for full student registration. For the expense portion, USENIX provided a check to assist the student with costs related to airfare and hotel. Variations in the flat rates offered depend on how far a student needed to travel and the amount they requested (i.e., some students may stay with a friend in the town of the conference and therefore did not have a hotel expense). We confirmed that the student recipients registered and attended the event.  The criteria we looked at in selecting grant recipients included: &#9679;      Conference participation (e.g., presenting a poster) &#9679;      Areas of study that significantly overlapped with the conference topics &#9679;      Concision of supporting statement outlining the applicant?s research &#9679;      Application history, prioritizing first time applicants and applicants who had not received a grant in the previous 12 months &#9679;      Students from institutions not traditionally represented at USENIX events &#9679;      Students from historically underrepresented communities and minorities &#9679;      Class level and financial need    The NSF funds supported a total of 43 grants for students to participate in the two events. Grants provided across the events are detailed below:    For NSDI '20, USENIX received 59 grant applications from students and awarded 31 grants. The NSF funds of $24,880 covered 23 of these grants, and all those awardees were enrolled at U.S. universities. There were 362 total attendees at NSDI '20, which included 126 student attendees.      For FAST '20, USENIX received 53 grant applications from students and awarded 29 grants. The NSF funds of $25,120 covered 20 of these grants, and all those awardees were enrolled at U.S. universities. There were 408 total attendees at FAST '20, which included 90 student attendees in total.                Last Modified: 05/11/2022       Submitted by: Camille Mulligan]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
