<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[EAGER: Poison Frogs and Toxic Arthropods – Diversification and parallel evolution of frog predators with their alkaloid-bearing prey]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>199877.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>199877</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Leslie J. Rissler</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lrissler@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924628</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Poison frogs have venomous substances in their skins, but they do not produce these chemicals on their own. Instead, they harvest these venoms from their arthropod diet: ants and mites. More than 800 different chemicals were found in these frogs. However, the diversity of ants and mites is so vast that understanding how poison frogs gain toxins from their arthropod food remains a mystery. This project will examine the connection between frog predators and toxic arthropods, which are valued more by the toxins they contain than by their nutritional value. This project will examine the diversity, genetics and evolution of toxic arthropods and their poison frog predators. The relevance of this project resides on the discovery of new knowledge that can then be shared with the community to advance our understanding of megadiverse regions like the South American rain forest. This basic research will provide insights into how the recycling of toxins occurs in natural ecosystems. The research team (St. John’s University, European and Latin-American partners) will provide learning experiences to underrepresented groups in STEM with workshops for students and open lectures for the public in NYC and beyond. SJU is an institution in the heart of the most ethnographically diverse county in the US with a large concentration of minority students. This work will involve training these scholars in tropical ecology, genomics and bioinformatics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Chemical defenses in poison frogs have a well-documented dietary origin. Yet little is known about the functional, phylogenomic biodiversity and ecological processes that connect the toxic arthropod base with their poison frog consumers. The movement of such defenses in trophic chains requires an intricate ecosystem of connections among interacting species. To answer this question, this project examines a model system centered on a section of the trophic chain that includes poison frogs and their alkaloid-bearing arthropod diet. The project addresses two major evolutionary and ecological dimensions: (1) phylogenomic and alkaloid diversities across poison frogs and their dietary ants and mites and (2) transcriptomics, physiological adaptations and evolutionary parallelisms evidenced by differential gene expression among the origins of alkaloid sequestration in poison frogs and their toxic arthropod diet. These goals will address how parallelisms, coevolution/codiversification and convergence evolved in poison frogs and their toxic arthropod under the context of bioaccumulation, differential gene expression and gene diversification. Such comparisons will contribute to a new level of understanding of the cycling of defensive toxins across biodiverse Neotropical communities. The proposed research will use predator-prey dynamics involving chemical defenses in some of the most threatened ecosystems, the Chocoan and Amazonian tropical forests, where biodiversity is being lost daily.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/10/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/10/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2016372</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Juan</FirstName>
<LastName>Santos Garcia</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Juan C Santos Garcia</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[santosj@stjohns.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000757833</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Saint John's University</Name>
<CityName>JAMAICA</CityName>
<ZipCode>114399000</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7189902920</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>8000 UTOPIA PWY</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>QMCKV4B31PG2</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ST JOHN'S UNIVERSITY, NEW YORK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>QMCKV4B31PG2</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Saint John's University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>114399000</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1127</Code>
<Text>Evolutionary Processes</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~199877</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Poison frogs have venomous substances in their skins, but they do not produce these chemicals on their own. Instead, they harvest these toxins from their bug diet: ants and mites. So far, more than 800 different chemicals were found in these frogs. Yet little is known about how the function, history, ecology, and biodiversity of specific bugs connect with the toxicity of their poison frog consumers. The movement of such defenses in trophic chains requires an intricate ecosystem of interactions among species. To answer this fundamental question, this project examined a model system centered on a section of the trophic chain that includes poison frogs and their alkaloid-bearing diet. The project addresses two major evolutionary and ecological dimensions: (1) how related and diverse are the alkaloids shared across poison frogs and their dietary ants and mites? and (2) what are the underlying genes that result in physiological adaptations and parallel evolution evidenced by differential gene expression in frogs that sequester alkaloids and their toxic arthropod diet? During the duration of this project, we explored the diversity, genetics and evolution of toxic arthropods and their poison frog predators. We first focused on the genetics of poison frogs by studying their transcriptomes (sequences of genetic instructions that code for proteins). This required the collection of fresh samples of frogs and their stomach content. From these samples, we extracted ribonucleic acid (RNA), which provides the information to build proteins. However, the information derived from sequencing machines require an intricate reassembly of the data, and this award supported the development of two software programs to achieve this goal. Over the two-year duration of this project, we focused on improving and developing those bioinformatics tools and tested them on the sequence data collected. This last component will continue in the coming years. We also characterized the biodiversity of poison frogs and described at least one new species (Leucostethus bilsa, see picture), a species of poison frog threatened by habitat destruction. Currently, the data generated with this project continues to be analyzed and explored. We aim to address how parallelisms, co-evolution/co-diversification evolved in poison frogs and their toxic arthropod diet under the context of bioaccumulation, different expression of genes, and gene diversification. Such comparisons will contribute to a new level of understanding of the cycling of defensive toxins across biodiverse communities. By discovering new species and publishing new data, this research aimed to protect two megadiverse and highly threatened ecosystems, the Chocoan and Amazonian tropical forests, where biodiversity is being lost daily. The research team (St. John?s University, European and Latin-American partners) shared experiences with underrepresented groups in STEM via online materials and talks for undergraduate students. SJU is an institution in the heart of the most ethnographically diverse county in the US with a large concentration of minority students. This work involved the training of many scholars from high school students to graduate students in different topics of tropical ecology, genomics, and bioinformatics.<br /><br />This Project Outcomes Report for the General Public is displayed verbatim as submitted by the Principal Investigator (PI) for this award. Any opinions, findings, and conclusions or recommendations expressed in this Report are those of the PI and do not necessarily reflect the views of the National Science Foundation; NSF has not approved or endorsed its content.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/29/2022<br>      Modified by: Juan&nbsp;C&nbsp;Santos Garcia</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Poison frogs have venomous substances in their skins, but they do not produce these chemicals on their own. Instead, they harvest these toxins from their bug diet: ants and mites. So far, more than 800 different chemicals were found in these frogs. Yet little is known about how the function, history, ecology, and biodiversity of specific bugs connect with the toxicity of their poison frog consumers. The movement of such defenses in trophic chains requires an intricate ecosystem of interactions among species. To answer this fundamental question, this project examined a model system centered on a section of the trophic chain that includes poison frogs and their alkaloid-bearing diet. The project addresses two major evolutionary and ecological dimensions: (1) how related and diverse are the alkaloids shared across poison frogs and their dietary ants and mites? and (2) what are the underlying genes that result in physiological adaptations and parallel evolution evidenced by differential gene expression in frogs that sequester alkaloids and their toxic arthropod diet? During the duration of this project, we explored the diversity, genetics and evolution of toxic arthropods and their poison frog predators. We first focused on the genetics of poison frogs by studying their transcriptomes (sequences of genetic instructions that code for proteins). This required the collection of fresh samples of frogs and their stomach content. From these samples, we extracted ribonucleic acid (RNA), which provides the information to build proteins. However, the information derived from sequencing machines require an intricate reassembly of the data, and this award supported the development of two software programs to achieve this goal. Over the two-year duration of this project, we focused on improving and developing those bioinformatics tools and tested them on the sequence data collected. This last component will continue in the coming years. We also characterized the biodiversity of poison frogs and described at least one new species (Leucostethus bilsa, see picture), a species of poison frog threatened by habitat destruction. Currently, the data generated with this project continues to be analyzed and explored. We aim to address how parallelisms, co-evolution/co-diversification evolved in poison frogs and their toxic arthropod diet under the context of bioaccumulation, different expression of genes, and gene diversification. Such comparisons will contribute to a new level of understanding of the cycling of defensive toxins across biodiverse communities. By discovering new species and publishing new data, this research aimed to protect two megadiverse and highly threatened ecosystems, the Chocoan and Amazonian tropical forests, where biodiversity is being lost daily. The research team (St. John?s University, European and Latin-American partners) shared experiences with underrepresented groups in STEM via online materials and talks for undergraduate students. SJU is an institution in the heart of the most ethnographically diverse county in the US with a large concentration of minority students. This work involved the training of many scholars from high school students to graduate students in different topics of tropical ecology, genomics, and bioinformatics.  This Project Outcomes Report for the General Public is displayed verbatim as submitted by the Principal Investigator (PI) for this award. Any opinions, findings, and conclusions or recommendations expressed in this Report are those of the PI and do not necessarily reflect the views of the National Science Foundation; NSF has not approved or endorsed its content.       Last Modified: 06/29/2022       Submitted by: Juan C Santos Garcia]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
