<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research: Expanding the Reach of Industrial Career Training for Graduate Students]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>26601.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>26601</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Swatee Naik</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>snaik@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924876</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The 16th annual Graduate Student Mathematical Modeling Camp (GSMMC) will be held June 9–12, 2021 at the University of Delaware, followed the week after by the 36th annual Mathematical Problems in Industry (MPI) workshop, June 14–18, 2021 at the University of Vermont.  GSMMC is a mentored, problem-solving workshop, at which small teams of Ph.D. students from across the U.S. are guided through successful mathematical modeling of real-world problems presented by faculty or experienced postdoctoral mentors. Under careful mentoring, student participants build their modeling, teamwork and presentation skills during the week: via the teamwork on modeling and simulating the problems; through the final team presentations made at the end of the week; and in writing the final reports that are produced. Training activities also include numerical simulations and the preparation of a final report outlining their discoveries.  These skills are put to use and consolidated the following week at MPI, where industrial participants present immediate modeling challenges facing their industries, on which academic participants (faculty, postdocs, and the Ph.D. students from GSMMC) work. Significant progress on the industrial problems is usually made, and Ph.D. student participants take the lead in presenting the findings to the industrial participants from industry in final presentations at the week's end. In addition to building their skillsets and resumes, student participants are exposed to valuable networking interactions with a range of industrial participants.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The GSMMC-MPI program is designed to integrate interdisciplinary research and education for graduate students. The GSMMC is focused on graduate student education and training: its chief intellectual merit lies in the development and analysis, by students, of the mathematical models for the problems presented. Problems are highly interdisciplinary, presenting students with a novel intellectual challenge. With the preparatory training provided by the GSMMC, students are ready for the more open-ended, research-level environment of MPI. The questions posed at MPI challenge participants to design new ways of modeling and analyzing industrial mathematics problems in emerging areas of technology. Mathematical modeling, analytical techniques, numerical simulations, and data analysis must all be used effectively. The collaborative approach to problem solving, which brings together mathematicians ranging from graduate students to experienced faculty, is central to the structure of MPI and provides significant additional training to graduate students, while promoting effective scientific communication. Full details for the Camp may be found at https://www.mathsci.udel.edu/events/conferences/gsmmc-2021, and for MPI at https://mpi2021.w3.uvm.edu/.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/20/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/20/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2016095</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Louis</FirstName>
<LastName>Rossi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>F</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Louis F Rossi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[rossi@math.udel.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000449334</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/20/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Edwards</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David A Edwards</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[dedwards@udel.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000439105</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/20/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Delaware</Name>
<CityName>NEWARK</CityName>
<ZipCode>197160099</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3028312136</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>220 HULLIHEN HALL</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Delaware</StateName>
<StateCode>DE</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DE00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>T72NHKM259N3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF DELAWARE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>T72NHKM259N3</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Delaware]]></Name>
<CityName>Newark</CityName>
<StateCode>DE</StateCode>
<ZipCode>197162553</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[210 Hullihen Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Delaware</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DE00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1260</Code>
<Text>INFRASTRUCTURE PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1271</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL MATHEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9263</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL SCIENCE &amp; ENGING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~26601</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="p1"><span> </span>In recent years, professional and governmental societies have become increasingly aware of the importance of providing mathematicians with exposure to and training in industrial mathematics.<span>&nbsp; </span>Not only does the industrial area provide an additional pool of professional opportunities for students, but also having highly-trained mathematicians working to advance industrial knowledge is in the best interests of the nation.<span>&nbsp; </span>To that end, this project funded the joint program of the education-focused Graduate Student Mathematical Modeling Camp ("Camp") and the research-focused Mathematical Problems in Industry Workshop ("MPI").<span>&nbsp;</span></p> <p class="p1"><span> </span>During the course of the project, nearly 50 graduate students attended the Camp.<span>&nbsp; </span>While there, they worked in teams with the guidance of invited faculty mentors on interdisciplinary problems typically inspired by industrial applications.<span>&nbsp; </span>The problems reflected a wide range of application areas:</p> <p class="p2">&nbsp;</p> <ul class="ul1"> <li class="li1">Climate modeling</li> <li class="li1">Colon cancer</li> <li class="li1">Control of parasitic insects</li> <li class="li1">Differential privacy</li> <li class="li1">Porous media filtration</li> </ul> <p class="p2">&nbsp;</p> <p class="p1">The problems are carefully chosen to promote a rich set of analytical and numerical problem-solving skills.<span>&nbsp; </span>The interactive nature of the group?s efforts also helps to foster "soft skills," such as teamwork and presentation skills.</p> <p class="p2">&nbsp;</p> <p class="p1"><span> </span>Campers then travel to MPI, where they join vertically-integrated teams of faculty, postdocs, and students to work on open-ended, research-level problems presented by industrial scientists in need of immediate solutions.<span>&nbsp; </span>Over the course of the grant, over 50 more faculty and postdocs participated in MPI, working on a wide range of problems, as listed below:</p> <p class="p2">&nbsp;</p> <ul class="ul1"> <li class="li1"><strong>&nbsp;</strong>Vironix (2 years): Data-based prediction/treatment of chronic lung, heart disease</li> <li class="li1"><strong>&nbsp;</strong>DEKA Research: Robotic control</li> <li class="li1"><strong>&nbsp;</strong>Goldman Sachs: Optimizing withdrawals from closed-end funds</li> <li class="li1"><strong>&nbsp;</strong>Renal Research Institute: Pattern recognition in sparse time series data</li> <li class="li1">Resource Systems Group: Differential privacy in travel data</li> <li class="li1">W. L. Gore: Evaporation from porous media filters</li> </ul> <p class="p2">&nbsp;</p> <p class="p1">The Camp and the MPI workshop complement each other and form a comprehensive program of interdisciplinary research, education and training that is unique among US institutions.</p> <p class="p2">&nbsp;</p> <p class="p1">The training that the students receive has substantial intellectual merit.<span>&nbsp; </span>Beyond learning new skills at the Camp and MPI, the students also discover how to synthesize their existing skills to real-world industrial problems.<span>&nbsp; </span>Perceiving such interdisciplinary connections will serve the students well, no matter their choice of career.<span>&nbsp; </span>Problem reports from all camps are posted online, which can serve as an invaluable educational resource for those searching for ways to illustrate how mathematics can be applied to industrial problems.</p> <p class="p2">&nbsp;</p> <p class="p1">The open-ended nature of the MPI problems poses a significant intellectual challenge to team members at all levels.<span>&nbsp; </span>The depth of analysis required has often formed the basis for further publishable research, and technical reports from all workshop problems are posted online.<span>&nbsp; </span>The results obtained at the MPI workshop have helped the companies involved to improve their production processes, causing positive effects that ripple throughout the larger economy.</p> <p class="p2">&nbsp;</p> <p class="p1">Both the Camp and MPI are proud of their record of inclusion of women and underrepresented groups, both as participants and mentors.<span>&nbsp; </span>During the grant period, the Campers were majority female, with over 15% from underrepresented groups.</p> <p class="p1">&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/07/2022<br>      Modified by: David&nbsp;A&nbsp;Edwards</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ In recent years, professional and governmental societies have become increasingly aware of the importance of providing mathematicians with exposure to and training in industrial mathematics.  Not only does the industrial area provide an additional pool of professional opportunities for students, but also having highly-trained mathematicians working to advance industrial knowledge is in the best interests of the nation.  To that end, this project funded the joint program of the education-focused Graduate Student Mathematical Modeling Camp ("Camp") and the research-focused Mathematical Problems in Industry Workshop ("MPI").   During the course of the project, nearly 50 graduate students attended the Camp.  While there, they worked in teams with the guidance of invited faculty mentors on interdisciplinary problems typically inspired by industrial applications.  The problems reflected a wide range of application areas:    Climate modeling Colon cancer Control of parasitic insects Differential privacy Porous media filtration    The problems are carefully chosen to promote a rich set of analytical and numerical problem-solving skills.  The interactive nature of the group?s efforts also helps to foster "soft skills," such as teamwork and presentation skills.    Campers then travel to MPI, where they join vertically-integrated teams of faculty, postdocs, and students to work on open-ended, research-level problems presented by industrial scientists in need of immediate solutions.  Over the course of the grant, over 50 more faculty and postdocs participated in MPI, working on a wide range of problems, as listed below:     Vironix (2 years): Data-based prediction/treatment of chronic lung, heart disease  DEKA Research: Robotic control  Goldman Sachs: Optimizing withdrawals from closed-end funds  Renal Research Institute: Pattern recognition in sparse time series data Resource Systems Group: Differential privacy in travel data W. L. Gore: Evaporation from porous media filters    The Camp and the MPI workshop complement each other and form a comprehensive program of interdisciplinary research, education and training that is unique among US institutions.   The training that the students receive has substantial intellectual merit.  Beyond learning new skills at the Camp and MPI, the students also discover how to synthesize their existing skills to real-world industrial problems.  Perceiving such interdisciplinary connections will serve the students well, no matter their choice of career.  Problem reports from all camps are posted online, which can serve as an invaluable educational resource for those searching for ways to illustrate how mathematics can be applied to industrial problems.   The open-ended nature of the MPI problems poses a significant intellectual challenge to team members at all levels.  The depth of analysis required has often formed the basis for further publishable research, and technical reports from all workshop problems are posted online.  The results obtained at the MPI workshop have helped the companies involved to improve their production processes, causing positive effects that ripple throughout the larger economy.   Both the Camp and MPI are proud of their record of inclusion of women and underrepresented groups, both as participants and mentors.  During the grant period, the Campers were majority female, with over 15% from underrepresented groups.         Last Modified: 07/07/2022       Submitted by: David A Edwards]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
