<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research: Development of a high-efficiency mass spectrometer: transitioning a high-efficiency ion source to a modern mass spectrometer]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>31403.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>31403</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Russell Kelz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rkelz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924747</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This EAR Instrumentation and Facilities Program award (a collaborative between Penn State and Carnegie Institution of Washington) will support the installation and testing of a newly developed, high-ionization-efficiency cavity ionization source on a modern multi-collector mass spectrometer, the Thermo-Fisher Triton.  The ion source development was supported previously by the EAR/IF Program (EAR-1758571).  If successful, the source augmented mass spectrometer promised significantly enhanced analytical precision for isotope ratio analysis with the potential for future transformative scientific advances in our understanding of the early evolution of Earth and planetary reservoirs (e.g., crust, mantle and core differentiation).  The project involves an early career researcher and will result in construction and operation of a fundamentally new type of mass spectrometer, which if successful, has potential for commercialization and broader community use.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The ultimate precision of mass spectrometry-based isotopic analyses is limited, in large part, by detector counting statistics.  The cavity ion source may present a major step forward in the ability to produce large ion beams from geologic samples and may make it able to achieve isotope-ratio precisions currently unattainable with modern thermal ionization mass spectrometers (TIMS).  Support will provide for installation of the developed ion source onto an existing Thermo-Fisher Triton TIMS and subsequent analytical testing.  The investigators have preliminary demonstrations that the source produces: 1) large, stable ion beams for long periods of time, and 2) higher ionization efficiency than traditional flat-filament thermal ionization sources for select elements. The source-enhanced instrument has significant potential to advance research on fundamental questions in the geosciences, from radiometric dating to tracing first-order chemical processes that formed and modify various reservoirs on Earth and other planets, by providing large increases in the analytical precision achievable for targeted radiogenic isotope ratio determinations  (e.g., Sm/Nd system for understanding the earliest history of Earth and the Solar System), that in allows for analysis of smaller rare samples than currently possible.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/06/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/06/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2016611</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
<LastName>Carlson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Richard W Carlson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[rcarlson@carnegiescience.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000447016</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/06/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Carnegie Institution of Washington</Name>
<CityName>WASHINGTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>200151305</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2023876400</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5241 BROAD BRANCH RD NW</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>ZQ12LY4L5H39</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CARNEGIE INSTITUTION OF WASHINGTON</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Department of Terrestrial Magnetism]]></Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>200151305</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5241 Broad Branch Road, NW]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1580</Code>
<Text>Instrumentation &amp; Facilities</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~31403</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="p1"><span class="s1">Mass spectrometry has become a heavily used technique in analytical chemistry because the mass of an element is among its most distinctive characteristics.&nbsp;&nbsp;Being able to measure precise isotopic compositions of elements is used to address a number of questions in Earth and planetary science including the use of radioactive isotopes as chronometers and tracers of chemical processes.&nbsp;&nbsp;The isotopic composition of elements also is a sensitive measure of how the element was made in stars, so being able to track isotopic variability related to the origin of the element has become a revealing approach to understand the processes that took what was once a dispersed cloud of dust of gas and turned it into the Sun and the planets of our Solar System.&nbsp;</span></p> <p class="p1"><span class="s1">The type of mass spectrometry pursued in this project began just after the end of the 19th century, but has been progressing rapidly in just the last 40 years to increase sensitivity and isotope ratio precision to the point of being able to determine ages of rocks to precisions of 0.002% (1 day in the life of a 60 year old individual corresponds to an age precision of 0.004%), and discover the initial compositional variability in the early Solar System before planets began to be formed.&nbsp;&nbsp;On the Earth, radiogenic isotope studies have greatly increased our understanding of the age of the planet, when it was hit by something big enough to form our Moon, when and how continents began to form, and how plate tectonics continually cycles material from Earth?s surface to its interior and back again - a process that may be necessary to form a habitable planet.</span></p> <p class="p1"><span class="s1">These advances in basic understanding in Earth and planetary sciences have come from being able to perform increasingly precise isotope analyses (to isotope ratio precisions of a few parts per million) on increasingly small samples (to femtograms - 10</span><span class="s2"><sup>-12</sup></span><span class="s1">g) using advanced mass spectrometers with continually increasing performance.&nbsp;</span></p> <p class="p1"><span class="s1">This project involved the design of a new type of ion source that creates positively charged atoms (ions) from samples loaded into a ?cavity?, basically a small tube.&nbsp; The cavity is heated to up to 2500</span><span class="s2"><sup>o</sup></span><span class="s1">C to more effectively ionize the sample atoms than conventional methods.&nbsp; Once ionized, the atoms are accelerated by electric fields into a conventional commercially available mass spectrometer that separates the atoms according to their mass and quantifies the size of each mass jon beam in order to calculate isotope ratios of the sample element.&nbsp; Our goals in the project were to provide up to a factor of 10 improvement in ionization efficiency which translates either into being able to analyze samples that are a factor of 10 smaller than presently possible or alternatively to create beams of 10 times the size of current techniques in order to improve isotope ratio precisions.&nbsp;</span></p> <p class="p1"><span class="s1">The scientific goal of the work, should the ion source design provide the expected performance increase, is to use the variety of what are known as ?short-lived radionuclides? to better understand the processes of planet formation and early differentiation.&nbsp; These radionuclides are those with half-lives much shorter than the age of the Solar System.&nbsp; They were present when the Solar System formed, but decayed away quickly with half-lives ranging from less than a million years up to 100 million years.&nbsp; Though they are long extinct, their existence is shown by the changes they made to the isotopic composition of the element into which they decayed.&nbsp; As existing mass spectrometers pushed isotope ratio precisions below 5 parts per million, these systems have provided new information on the composition of the dust from which Earth formed, the timing of core formation on Earth, the time of Moon formation, and the way in which Earth began to form the first continental crust over 4 billion years ago.&nbsp; While 5 ppm precision allows the realization that these radiogenic isotopic systems carry a lot of information about early Solar System history, pushing isotope ratio precisions below 1 ppm would allow full extraction of the detailed information on what Earth formed from, when it formed, and how it developed into the planet that we know - the only one we know of capable of sustaining life for over 3.5 billion years.&nbsp; Our goal with this project was to provide the means by which isotope ratio precisions could be pushed below this 1 ppm barrier.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/03/2022<br>      Modified by: Richard&nbsp;W&nbsp;Carlson</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[Mass spectrometry has become a heavily used technique in analytical chemistry because the mass of an element is among its most distinctive characteristics.  Being able to measure precise isotopic compositions of elements is used to address a number of questions in Earth and planetary science including the use of radioactive isotopes as chronometers and tracers of chemical processes.  The isotopic composition of elements also is a sensitive measure of how the element was made in stars, so being able to track isotopic variability related to the origin of the element has become a revealing approach to understand the processes that took what was once a dispersed cloud of dust of gas and turned it into the Sun and the planets of our Solar System.  The type of mass spectrometry pursued in this project began just after the end of the 19th century, but has been progressing rapidly in just the last 40 years to increase sensitivity and isotope ratio precision to the point of being able to determine ages of rocks to precisions of 0.002% (1 day in the life of a 60 year old individual corresponds to an age precision of 0.004%), and discover the initial compositional variability in the early Solar System before planets began to be formed.  On the Earth, radiogenic isotope studies have greatly increased our understanding of the age of the planet, when it was hit by something big enough to form our Moon, when and how continents began to form, and how plate tectonics continually cycles material from Earth?s surface to its interior and back again - a process that may be necessary to form a habitable planet. These advances in basic understanding in Earth and planetary sciences have come from being able to perform increasingly precise isotope analyses (to isotope ratio precisions of a few parts per million) on increasingly small samples (to femtograms - 10-12g) using advanced mass spectrometers with continually increasing performance.  This project involved the design of a new type of ion source that creates positively charged atoms (ions) from samples loaded into a ?cavity?, basically a small tube.  The cavity is heated to up to 2500oC to more effectively ionize the sample atoms than conventional methods.  Once ionized, the atoms are accelerated by electric fields into a conventional commercially available mass spectrometer that separates the atoms according to their mass and quantifies the size of each mass jon beam in order to calculate isotope ratios of the sample element.  Our goals in the project were to provide up to a factor of 10 improvement in ionization efficiency which translates either into being able to analyze samples that are a factor of 10 smaller than presently possible or alternatively to create beams of 10 times the size of current techniques in order to improve isotope ratio precisions.  The scientific goal of the work, should the ion source design provide the expected performance increase, is to use the variety of what are known as ?short-lived radionuclides? to better understand the processes of planet formation and early differentiation.  These radionuclides are those with half-lives much shorter than the age of the Solar System.  They were present when the Solar System formed, but decayed away quickly with half-lives ranging from less than a million years up to 100 million years.  Though they are long extinct, their existence is shown by the changes they made to the isotopic composition of the element into which they decayed.  As existing mass spectrometers pushed isotope ratio precisions below 5 parts per million, these systems have provided new information on the composition of the dust from which Earth formed, the timing of core formation on Earth, the time of Moon formation, and the way in which Earth began to form the first continental crust over 4 billion years ago.  While 5 ppm precision allows the realization that these radiogenic isotopic systems carry a lot of information about early Solar System history, pushing isotope ratio precisions below 1 ppm would allow full extraction of the detailed information on what Earth formed from, when it formed, and how it developed into the planet that we know - the only one we know of capable of sustaining life for over 3.5 billion years.  Our goal with this project was to provide the means by which isotope ratio precisions could be pushed below this 1 ppm barrier.          Last Modified: 10/03/2022       Submitted by: Richard W Carlson]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
