<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Science Learning +: Partnering for Equitable STEM Pathways for Underrepresented Youth]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>669981.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>669981</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DRL</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Alicia Santiago Gonzalez</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>asantiag@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924546</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This 4-year project addresses fundamental equity issues in informal Science, Technology, Engineering and Mathematics (STEM) learning. Access to, and opportunities within informal STEM learning (ISL) remain limited for youth from historically underrepresented backgrounds in both the United States and the United Kingdom. However, there is evidence that ISL experiences can expand opportunities for youth learning and development in STEM, for instance, increase positive attitudes towards educational aspirations and future careers/pursuits, improve grades and test scores in school settings, and decrease disciplinary action and dropout rates. Through research and development, this project brings together researchers and practitioners to focus on the experiences, practices and tools that will support equitable youth pathways into STEM. Working across conceptual frameworks and ISL settings (e.g. science centers, community groups, zoos) and universities in four urban contexts in two different nations, the partnership will produce a coherent knowledge base that strengthens and expands research plus practice partnerships, builds capacity towards transformative research and development, and develops new models and tools in support of equitable pathways into STEM at a global level. This project is funded through Science Learning+, which is an international partnership between the National Science Foundation (NSF) and the Wellcome Trust with the UK Economic and Social Research Council. The goal of this joint funding effort is to make transformational steps toward improving the knowledge base and practices of informal STEM experiences. Within NSF, Science Learning+ is part of the Advancing Informal STEM Learning (AISL) program that seeks to enhance learning in informal environments and to broaden access to and engagement in STEM learning experiences. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Equity Pathways project responds to three challenges at the intersections of ISL research and practice in the United States and the United Kingdom: 1) lack of shared understanding of how youth from historically underrepresented backgrounds perceive and experience ISL opportunities across national contexts, and the practices and tools needed to support empowered movement through ISL; 2) limited shared understanding and evidence of core high-leverage practices that support such youth in progressing within and across ISL, and 3) limited understanding of how ISL might be equitable and transformative for such youth seeking to develop their own pathways into STEM. The major goal of this Partnership is for practitioners and researchers, working with youth through design-based implementation research, survey and critical ethnography, to develop new understandings of how and under what conditions they participate in ISL over time and across settings, and how they may connect these experiences towards pathways into STEM. The project will result in: 1) New understandings of ISL pathways that are equitable and transformative for youth from historically underrepresented backgrounds; 2) A set of high leverage practices and tools that support equitable and transformative informal science learning pathways (and the agency youth need to make their way through them); and 3) Strengthened and increased professional capacity to broaden participation among youth from historically underrepresented backgrounds in STEM through informal science learning. The project will be carried out by research + practice partnerships in 4 cities: London &amp; Bristol, UK and Lansing, MI &amp; Portland, OR, US, involving university researchers (University College London, Michigan State University, Oregon State University/Institute for Learning Innovation) practitioners in science museums (@Bristol Science Centre, Brent Lodge Park Animal Centre, Impressions 5, Oregon Museum of Science &amp; Industry) and community-based centers (STEMettes, Knowle West Media Centre, Boys &amp; Girls Clubs of Lansing, and Girls, Inc. of the Pacific Northwest).]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/18/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/18/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2016707</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Angela</FirstName>
<LastName>Calabrese Barton</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Angela Calabrese Barton</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[angieCB@umich.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000100970</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/18/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Regents of the University of Michigan - Ann Arbor</Name>
<CityName>ANN ARBOR</CityName>
<ZipCode>481091079</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1109 GEDDES AVE, SUITE 3300</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>GNJ7BBP73WE9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MICHIGAN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Michigan Ann Arbor]]></Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>481091259</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7259</Code>
<Text>AISL</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0418</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0419</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04001819DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>04001920DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~1235</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~668746</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-f5c78a47-7fff-160d-fe77-e5f548dccd81"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The Science Learning+Partnership project, Partnering for Equitable STEM Pathways for Underrepresented Youth, or YESTEM, addressed fundamental equity issues in informal STEM learning. Access to, and opportunities within, ISL (informal STEM learning) remain limited for youth from historically underrepresented backgrounds in both the United States and the United Kingdom. However, there is evidence that ISL experiences can expand opportunities for youth learning and development in STEM, for instance, increase positive attitudes towards educational aspirations and future careers/pursuits, improve grades and test scores in school settings, and decrease disciplinary action and dropout rates.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr">&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr">The YESTEM project responded to three challenges at the intersections of ISL research and practice: 1) lack of shared understanding of how youth from historically underrepresented backgrounds perceive and experience ISL opportunities across national contexts, and the practices and tools needed to support empowered movement through ISL; 2) limited shared understanding and evidence of core high-leverage practices that support such youth in progressing within and across ISL, and 3) limited understanding of how ISL might be equitable and transformative for such youth seeking to develop their own pathways into STEM.&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>By engaging in participatory ethnography and design-based implementation research, the intellectual merit of this project is in the new knowledge, practices and materials co-generated by researchers and practitioners in the partnership, including:</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>1. A set of </span><span>Core Equitable Practices</span><span> that support equitable and transformative outcomes for youth</span><span>. &#8203;&#8203;Core Equitable Practices are pedagogical practices that support youth?s learning and engagement in STEM in empowering ways. When educators engage in Core Equitable Practices, they take the stance that educators and youth are co-learners, co-disruptors and co-creators of a more just world with and in STEM. These practices pay attention to whose ways of knowing and discourses are valued in STEM, and why that matters. We refer to these practices as </span><span>core</span><span> practices because they are meant to be a part of an educator?s everyday practice.&nbsp;</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>2. New insights into how </span><span>youth bid for more equitable practices in ISL,</span><span> and how educators can notice and respond to these bids.</span><span> Results from design-based implementation research revealed interactional moments where youth engage in bids to be legitimately and rightfully welcomed and present in STEM. These interactions always take place in local contexts, but they are also informed by social and historical structures and narratives that shape what it means to know, do and become in STEM and in their ISL programs.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>As educators took up youth bids using Core Equitable Practices, they challenged and transformed what participation in STEM for youth entailed and what meaningful representations of learning could look like. They humanized participation and valued youth as cultural and whole people through shifting acceptable discourses, norms and forms of participation.&nbsp;</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>In responding to bids productively, educators had to </span><span>pause-and-rethink</span><span> what was happening in-the-moment from the youth perspectives, and what this meant for youths? opportunities to become in ISL. Educators shifted their mindsets from focusing on youth in need of remediation to asset-based approaches such as rethinking new arrangements, tools, and forms of participation in STEM learning. Educators had to recognize how inequities are reproduced in their environments through dominant practices, narratives and structures.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>3. A </span><span>guiding framework</span><span> in support of learning about, enacting and reflecting on these Core Equitable Practices (?YESTEM Model?).</span><span> The YESTEM model provides the field with a way to reflect on, enact, and design new equitable and transformative experiences in ISL. The accompanying Tools and Materials</span><span> </span><span>flesh out the model in practice to build capacity for these experiences. These include: Research+Practice briefs on each practice (?Insights?), Educator Talk Moves, Youth Bids, and Practical Measures. These are packaged into ?Toolkits? that provide resources for understanding each Core Equitable Practice, its purpose and desired outcomes, ways to enact the practices, ways to notice when youth solicit educators? attention in ways related to the practices, and ways to check in and get a sense of how youth experience the practices.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The broader impact of this work results from the capacity building efforts made possible by the production of the practices, tools and guiding framework discussed above. Furthermore, in the US, our project reached five partner organizations, serving over 12 programs, 54 educators and over 2000 youth during the life of the grant.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/11/2023<br>      Modified by: Angela&nbsp;Calabrese Barton</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2016707/2016707_10473442_1683824605734_bigmouthfinal--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2016707/2016707_10473442_1683824605734_bigmouthfinal--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Big Mouth Project"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2016707/2016707_10473442_1683824605734_bigmouthfinal--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Big Mouth Project"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Big Mouth Project at Impression 5 Science Center: Planning & Enacting with the Practice of Reclaiming</div> <div class="imageCredit">A Calabrese Barton</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Angela&nbsp;Calabrese Barton</div> <div class="imageTitle">Big Mouth Project</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2016707/2016707_10473442_1683824660996_WebsiteScreenShot--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2016707/2016707_10473442_1683824660996_WebsiteScreenShot--rgov-800width.jpg" title="YESTEM.org"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2016707/2016707_10473442_1683824660996_WebsiteScreenShot--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="YESTEM.org"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Screenshot of YESTEM.org to show the links to tools and materials</div> <div class="imageCredit">A. Calabrese Barton</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Angela&nbsp;Calabrese Barton</div> <div class="imageTitle">YESTEM.org</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2016707/2016707_10473442_1683824831270_YouthResearchersforCEP--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2016707/2016707_10473442_1683824831270_YouthResearchersforCEP--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Youth Researchers YESTEM"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2016707/2016707_10473442_1683824831270_YouthResearchersforCEP--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Youth Researchers YESTEM"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Youth Researchers for Core Equitable Practices, YESTEM</div> <div class="imageCredit">A Calabrese Barton</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Angela&nbsp;Calabrese Barton</div> <div class="imageTitle">Youth Researchers YESTEM</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2016707/2016707_10473442_1683824911460_IMG_2157--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2016707/2016707_10473442_1683824911460_IMG_2157--rgov-800width.jpg" title="RPP session"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2016707/2016707_10473442_1683824911460_IMG_2157--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="RPP session"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Practice partner leading an RPP session</div> <div class="imageCredit">A Calabrese Barton</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Angela&nbsp;Calabrese Barton</div> <div class="imageTitle">RPP session</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2016707/2016707_10473442_1683824970229_CoreEquitablePracticesBriefPage1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2016707/2016707_10473442_1683824970229_CoreEquitablePracticesBriefPage1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Core Equitable Practices Brief"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2016707/2016707_10473442_1683824970229_CoreEquitablePracticesBriefPage1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Core Equitable Practices Brief"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Core Equitable Practices Research + Practice Brief, Page 1</div> <div class="imageCredit">A Calabrese Barton</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Angela&nbsp;Calabrese Barton</div> <div class="imageTitle">Core Equitable Practices Brief</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   The Science Learning+Partnership project, Partnering for Equitable STEM Pathways for Underrepresented Youth, or YESTEM, addressed fundamental equity issues in informal STEM learning. Access to, and opportunities within, ISL (informal STEM learning) remain limited for youth from historically underrepresented backgrounds in both the United States and the United Kingdom. However, there is evidence that ISL experiences can expand opportunities for youth learning and development in STEM, for instance, increase positive attitudes towards educational aspirations and future careers/pursuits, improve grades and test scores in school settings, and decrease disciplinary action and dropout rates.    The YESTEM project responded to three challenges at the intersections of ISL research and practice: 1) lack of shared understanding of how youth from historically underrepresented backgrounds perceive and experience ISL opportunities across national contexts, and the practices and tools needed to support empowered movement through ISL; 2) limited shared understanding and evidence of core high-leverage practices that support such youth in progressing within and across ISL, and 3) limited understanding of how ISL might be equitable and transformative for such youth seeking to develop their own pathways into STEM.    By engaging in participatory ethnography and design-based implementation research, the intellectual merit of this project is in the new knowledge, practices and materials co-generated by researchers and practitioners in the partnership, including:   1. A set of Core Equitable Practices that support equitable and transformative outcomes for youth. &#8203;&#8203;Core Equitable Practices are pedagogical practices that support youth?s learning and engagement in STEM in empowering ways. When educators engage in Core Equitable Practices, they take the stance that educators and youth are co-learners, co-disruptors and co-creators of a more just world with and in STEM. These practices pay attention to whose ways of knowing and discourses are valued in STEM, and why that matters. We refer to these practices as core practices because they are meant to be a part of an educator?s everyday practice.     2. New insights into how youth bid for more equitable practices in ISL, and how educators can notice and respond to these bids. Results from design-based implementation research revealed interactional moments where youth engage in bids to be legitimately and rightfully welcomed and present in STEM. These interactions always take place in local contexts, but they are also informed by social and historical structures and narratives that shape what it means to know, do and become in STEM and in their ISL programs.   As educators took up youth bids using Core Equitable Practices, they challenged and transformed what participation in STEM for youth entailed and what meaningful representations of learning could look like. They humanized participation and valued youth as cultural and whole people through shifting acceptable discourses, norms and forms of participation.     In responding to bids productively, educators had to pause-and-rethink what was happening in-the-moment from the youth perspectives, and what this meant for youths? opportunities to become in ISL. Educators shifted their mindsets from focusing on youth in need of remediation to asset-based approaches such as rethinking new arrangements, tools, and forms of participation in STEM learning. Educators had to recognize how inequities are reproduced in their environments through dominant practices, narratives and structures.    3. A guiding framework in support of learning about, enacting and reflecting on these Core Equitable Practices (?YESTEM Model?). The YESTEM model provides the field with a way to reflect on, enact, and design new equitable and transformative experiences in ISL. The accompanying Tools and Materials flesh out the model in practice to build capacity for these experiences. These include: Research+Practice briefs on each practice (?Insights?), Educator Talk Moves, Youth Bids, and Practical Measures. These are packaged into ?Toolkits? that provide resources for understanding each Core Equitable Practice, its purpose and desired outcomes, ways to enact the practices, ways to notice when youth solicit educators? attention in ways related to the practices, and ways to check in and get a sense of how youth experience the practices.   The broader impact of this work results from the capacity building efforts made possible by the production of the practices, tools and guiding framework discussed above. Furthermore, in the US, our project reached five partner organizations, serving over 12 programs, 54 educators and over 2000 youth during the life of the grant.                Last Modified: 05/11/2023       Submitted by: Angela Calabrese Barton]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
