<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[EAGER: Microcredentials for Integrating Computing Responsibly into Other Domains (MICRO)]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>299182.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>299182</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jeffrey Forbes</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jforbes@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925301</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Computing is fundamentally changing Americans’ professional and personal lives. Beyond the workforce demand for computer scientists, computing is becoming part of many fields, from engineering to art. Moreover, computing literacy is a fundamental and necessary skill for safely navigating information and systems in the world today. While the public education system wants to incorporate computing into standard educational practices, there is a dire shortage of teachers who are qualified to teach computing. Schools in rural and low-income areas are particularly unlikely to be able to offer computing courses, feeding existing underrepresentation problems that have contributed to a large number of vacant computing jobs, and to lack of diversity in the workforce. With the goal of increasing the number and diversity of students who participate in computing, this project will create a professional development (PD) model for teaching computing to K-12 science and math teachers who teach in rural and low-income areas so that they may spread computational literacy in their communities. The project’s model for doing this is based on online, competency-based instructional modules through which teachers can earn micro-credentials that demonstrate their knowledge and skills.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;The project team includes researchers from the International Society for Technology in Education, Georgia State University, and the Georgia Department of Education and aims to create and test the foundations for a computing education teacher preparation ecosystem that leverages the flexibility and accessibility afforded by micro-credentialing and online learning. The goals of this project are 1) to use purposeful and theory-driven instructional design to adapt existing Computer Science instruction into online modules that prepare preservice and in-service teachers to integrate computing into their non-computing courses; and 2) to produce and pilot a competency-based micro-credentialing system that will assess teachers’ knowledge and skills. The research component of this project will explore the following topics: (1) Effectiveness of online modules and micro-credentialing system to support teachers to integrate computing across grade bands and primary disciplines, (2) Self-efficacy of teachers while implementing computing-integrated activities in their classrooms, and (3) Perceived value of micro-credentials by teachers and their districts compared to university course credit. The researchers will collect data from teachers through assignments, assessments,  and artifacts created by engaging with the modules and completing the micro-credentials. Data sources will also include a) surveys given before and after the modules, b) written individual reflections, c) collaborative discussions within the module, and d) lesson plans that integrate computing and computing integration activities. Methods for data analysis will mix qualitative and quantitative procedures for collection and analyses, depending on the type of data and research question that the data address. The project will contribute to our knowledge of how to support teachers in rural and low-income areas to learn and teach computing by examining the process of how they acquire and implement computing concepts, and by examining the efficacy of a micro-credentialing system that is designed to evaluate their skills.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/12/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/12/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2016010</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Brendan</FirstName>
<LastName>Calandra</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Brendan Calandra</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[bcalandra@gsu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000482354</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/12/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lauren</FirstName>
<LastName>Margulieux</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lauren Margulieux</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[lmargulieux@gsu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000730121</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/12/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Bryan</FirstName>
<LastName>Cox</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Bryan Cox</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[bcox@doe.k12.ga.us]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000746536</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/12/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Georgia State University Research Foundation, Inc.</Name>
<CityName>ATLANTA</CityName>
<ZipCode>303032921</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4044133570</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>58 EDGEWOOD AVE NE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[FL 3]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>MNS7B9CVKDN7</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GEORGIA STATE UNIVERSITY RESEARCH FOUNDATION INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Georgia State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>303023977</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[30 Pryor St SW]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>055y</Code>
<Text>CISE Education and Workforce</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~299182</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong><span>Introduction/broader impacts</span></strong></p> <p><span>Computing is fundamentally changing Americans&rsquo; personal and professional lives. Beyond the workforce demand for technical skills, computing literacy is now a necessary skill for productively engaging in today&rsquo;s world. Our public education system has been responding to this change by incorporating computing into some standard educational practices, but there is a dire shortage of teachers qualified to teach computing, especially in rural and low-income areas. Integrated computing applies computational tools like computational thinking (CT) and programming to solve problems in non-computing disciplines, like language arts, math, or science. From a non-computing education perspective, integrated computing can be used to evolve the instructional practice of educators within core subject areas, providing a rationale to &lsquo;why&rsquo; a teacher should learn these concepts -- to solve problems or develop innovations within their own pedagogy. These innovations can provide students with increased agency, engagement, and understanding of traditional concepts within the target discipline while teaching technical skills in computing.&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span>Our aim for this EAGER grant was to create and test a micro-credential model for offering flexible, accessible, and high-quality professional development to teachers who are interested in integrating computational thinking and computing into their core curricula.&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span>The first year of this grant involved the design and development of three online micro-courses. These courses were designed between three partner institutions, Georgia State University, the Georgia Department of Education, and the International Society for Technology in Education. Courses were offered free of charge and are hosted online at https://gavirtualpd.catalog.instructure.com/browse/computerscience. Teachers completing the courses were also provided the opportunity to submit artifacts created during the courses to earn digital badges from ISTE towards their Integrated Computational Thinking Endorsement. </span></p> <p><span>The second and third years focused on the rollout of the project. We estimate that at least 556 teachers engaged with the micro-courses, and at least 458 teachers completed all 3 courses. This represents an 82% retention rate, which is much higher than expected for a free, self-paced, online series of courses. During our third year, we analyzed data collected from participating teachers, and we hosted a workshop for national leaders in computer science (CS) education in preservice teacher programs. The invitation-only workshop gathered 50 people from across the country to collate resources, share experiences, and make recommendations for colleges of education who are just beginning to include CS education in their programs.&nbsp;</span></p> <p><strong><span>Intellectual merit</span></strong></p> <p><span>To discern whether the MICRO self-paced online courses were an effective tool for introducing computing and helping teachers integrate computing across content areas, we examined the lessons that teacher participants created and we asked them about their understanding of and confidence in computing integration before and after they engaged with micro-courses. Our research questions and a brief overview of results are listed below:&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span>RQ1: How well does a self-paced online course prepare teachers to apply computing concepts and practices to an integrated activity? Results of artifact analysis reflected a positive impact on teachers&rsquo; ability to understand CS and CT concepts and to build lessons that incorporated these into their discipline areas, although some of the concepts were incorporated to a higher degree than others. Conversely, while they were present to an extent, programming practices did not show up as frequently as CT concepts in participant artifacts. These results will directly affect course redesign and can add to the literature on CS teacher training and CS education more generally.&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span>RQ2: How well does the activity reflect learning goals for the primary discipline? Artifacts analysis uncovered the incorporation of computing content alongside explicit references to core content standards. That is, participants were able to identify clear examples of CS and develop or modify content area lessons that expressed these concepts/practices.</span></p> <p><span>RQ3: How does a self-paced online course impact teachers&rsquo; perspectives on computing? Although participants did identify some barriers to the integration of computing into their content areas, survey results showed a significant increase in participants&rsquo; general confidence that CS concepts and practices can be integrated into core content areas and a burgeoning understanding of CS and its potential relation to content areas.&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span>These results will directly affect future scale-up efforts and add to the literature on CS teacher training and CS education more generally.&nbsp;</span></p> <p><strong><span>Conclusion</span></strong></p> <p><span>Because this micro-credentialing ecosystem is one of the first in computing education nationwide, it could serve as a model for computing education credentialing nationally. The current project included the design, development, and initial pilot of the micro-courses and badges. At scale, a model such as this could ultimately impact students' ability to participate in computing by increasing the number of teachers qualified to integrate CS into their existing curricula.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/04/2023<br>      Modified by: Lauren&nbsp;Margulieux</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Introduction/broader impacts  Computing is fundamentally changing Americans’ personal and professional lives. Beyond the workforce demand for technical skills, computing literacy is now a necessary skill for productively engaging in today’s world. Our public education system has been responding to this change by incorporating computing into some standard educational practices, but there is a dire shortage of teachers qualified to teach computing, especially in rural and low-income areas. Integrated computing applies computational tools like computational thinking (CT) and programming to solve problems in non-computing disciplines, like language arts, math, or science. From a non-computing education perspective, integrated computing can be used to evolve the instructional practice of educators within core subject areas, providing a rationale to ‘why’ a teacher should learn these concepts -- to solve problems or develop innovations within their own pedagogy. These innovations can provide students with increased agency, engagement, and understanding of traditional concepts within the target discipline while teaching technical skills in computing.   Our aim for this EAGER grant was to create and test a micro-credential model for offering flexible, accessible, and high-quality professional development to teachers who are interested in integrating computational thinking and computing into their core curricula.   The first year of this grant involved the design and development of three online micro-courses. These courses were designed between three partner institutions, Georgia State University, the Georgia Department of Education, and the International Society for Technology in Education. Courses were offered free of charge and are hosted online at https://gavirtualpd.catalog.instructure.com/browse/computerscience. Teachers completing the courses were also provided the opportunity to submit artifacts created during the courses to earn digital badges from ISTE towards their Integrated Computational Thinking Endorsement.   The second and third years focused on the rollout of the project. We estimate that at least 556 teachers engaged with the micro-courses, and at least 458 teachers completed all 3 courses. This represents an 82% retention rate, which is much higher than expected for a free, self-paced, online series of courses. During our third year, we analyzed data collected from participating teachers, and we hosted a workshop for national leaders in computer science (CS) education in preservice teacher programs. The invitation-only workshop gathered 50 people from across the country to collate resources, share experiences, and make recommendations for colleges of education who are just beginning to include CS education in their programs.   Intellectual merit  To discern whether the MICRO self-paced online courses were an effective tool for introducing computing and helping teachers integrate computing across content areas, we examined the lessons that teacher participants created and we asked them about their understanding of and confidence in computing integration before and after they engaged with micro-courses. Our research questions and a brief overview of results are listed below:   RQ1: How well does a self-paced online course prepare teachers to apply computing concepts and practices to an integrated activity? Results of artifact analysis reflected a positive impact on teachers’ ability to understand CS and CT concepts and to build lessons that incorporated these into their discipline areas, although some of the concepts were incorporated to a higher degree than others. Conversely, while they were present to an extent, programming practices did not show up as frequently as CT concepts in participant artifacts. These results will directly affect course redesign and can add to the literature on CS teacher training and CS education more generally.   RQ2: How well does the activity reflect learning goals for the primary discipline? Artifacts analysis uncovered the incorporation of computing content alongside explicit references to core content standards. That is, participants were able to identify clear examples of CS and develop or modify content area lessons that expressed these concepts/practices.  RQ3: How does a self-paced online course impact teachers’ perspectives on computing? Although participants did identify some barriers to the integration of computing into their content areas, survey results showed a significant increase in participants’ general confidence that CS concepts and practices can be integrated into core content areas and a burgeoning understanding of CS and its potential relation to content areas.   These results will directly affect future scale-up efforts and add to the literature on CS teacher training and CS education more generally.   Conclusion  Because this micro-credentialing ecosystem is one of the first in computing education nationwide, it could serve as a model for computing education credentialing nationally. The current project included the design, development, and initial pilot of the micro-courses and badges. At scale, a model such as this could ultimately impact students' ability to participate in computing by increasing the number of teachers qualified to integrate CS into their existing curricula.          Last Modified: 08/04/2023       Submitted by: Lauren Margulieux]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
