<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Impact: Redfining Electrical and Computer Engineering Faculty (iREDEFINE ECE); March 2020, Orlando, FL]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>98648.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>98648</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EEC</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Engineering Education and Centers</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Christine Grant</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cgrant@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927107</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Despite many efforts to increase diversity among electrical and computer engineering (ECE) faculty, the number of women and underrepresented minorities on ECE faculty remains alarmingly low. In ECE programs, women compose only 14.3% and 19.6% of tenured and tenure-track faculty positions, respectively, which is consistent with their low representation (17.4%) in all engineering tenured/tenure-track positions in the U.S. The percentage of Black or African American faculty in electrical and computer engineering is only 2.0% and 3.1%, respectively. Similarly, only 2.5% of electrical engineering faculty and 2.9% of computer engineering faculty are Hispanic. Research shows that an effective strategy to retain underrepresented groups in science, technology, engineering and mathematics (STEM) is to provide role models and mentors. Thus, the lack of faculty role models is a major contributing factor to the low representation of women and minority students in ECE programs, which further perpetuates the cycle of underrepresentation. “Impact: Redefining Electrical and Computer Engineering Faculty” (iREDEFINE ECE) is the expansion of an initiative designed to increase the numbers of such role models for women and underrepresented minorities in ECE programs through in-person workshops and year-round online mentoring activities. Surveys of past iREDEFINE participants verify the efficacy of the workshop approach and support the need for expansion to include year-round activities. In addition to providing operational support for iREDEFINE activities, this grant makes the in-person workshops accessible to students from institutions that may not have the financial resources to support the travel of their PhD students.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of the iREDEFINE program is to motivate and prepare PhD women and underrepresented minority students to pursue ECE faculty positions in US universities. The initiative consists of: 1) a workshop for women and underrepresented minority graduate ECE students at an annual meeting of the Electrical and Computer Engineering Department Heads Association (ECEDHA); 2) mini workshops at regional ECEDHA meetings; 3) a year-round online mentoring program; and 4) a database of iREDEFINE participants managed by ECEDHA and open to department heads and chairs to facilitate faculty recruitment from underrepresented groups. Extending the workshop to two days, adding workshops at regional conferences, implementing four structured virtual mentoring meetings, and introducing online communities increases the range of opportunities for iREDEFINE Scholars to interact and build a stronger rapport with ECE department heads, industry leaders, and their peers, equipping them with a broad and diverse professional network. By directly impacting 32 women and underrepresented minority participants, this project will help to increase the number of diverse students applying for academic positions in ECE departments and prepare them for successful academic careers. Furthermore, by connecting the students with role models who are academic leaders, participating in iREDEFINE catalyzes an interest in academic administration among iREDEFINE Scholars who will then become role models for the next generation of women and underrepresented minority ECE students. Finally, in addition to supporting participating students in their pursuit of academic careers, these activities also advance the knowledge on successful strategies to broaden the participation of women and underrepresented minorities in the ECE professoriate.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/03/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/03/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2016183</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Barry</FirstName>
<LastName>Sullivan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Barry J Sullivan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[bsullivan@marconisociety.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000303115</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/03/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Agnieszka</FirstName>
<LastName>Miguel</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Agnieszka Miguel</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[amiguel@seattleu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000483835</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/03/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Electrical and Computer Engineering Department Heads Association</Name>
<CityName>CHICAGO</CityName>
<ZipCode>606016769</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3122861382</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>180 N STETSON AVE STE 3500</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>Z58HQSU2NW45</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ELECTRICAL &amp; COMPUTER ENGINEERING DEPARTMENT HEADS ASSOCIATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Electrical and Computer Engineering Department Heads Association]]></Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>606016769</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[180 N Stetson Ave Ste 3400]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7680</Code>
<Text>EDA-Eng Diversity Activities</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>110E</Code>
<Text>EDUCATION RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7680</Code>
<Text>ENG DIVERSITY ACTIVITIES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9102</Code>
<Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~98648</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="Default">The iREDEFINE program motivates and prepares PhD women and minority students to pursue faculty positions in US universities. The iREDEFINE initiative has included workshops for women and underrepresented minority graduate ECE students at the annual meeting of the Electrical and Computer Engineering Department Heads Association (ECEDHA); mini workshops at regional ECEDHA meetings; and a year-round mentoring program.</p> <p class="Default">The iREDEFINE workshops provide extensive opportunities for ECE PhD students to interact with department chairs and learn about the ECE programs they represent, faculty positions in their departments, and the expectations from a new tenure-track faculty member. iREDEFINE Scholars also present their research accomplishments and participate in dedicated iREDEFINE programming including sessions on different types of institutions, advice about first years as a new tenure-track faculty member, negotiation strategies, CV review, and mock interviews. These sessions, organized by the iREDEFINE Committee and facilitated by ECE faculty and department heads, prepare women and underrepresented minority ECE PhD students for successful academic careers and provide excellent networking opportunities.</p> <p class="Default">Mentoring is one of the key factors that contribute to the success of new faculty. Some institutions offer structured mentoring programs for female and URM PhD students and/or junior faculty members while others lack the infrastructure to organize such programs. This project has created a mentoring network that will support the students as they advance in their academic careers and become faculty. Group mentoring sessions have been organized with facilitated conference calls every couple of months and online support platforms.</p> <p>The onset of COVID-19 and the resulting restrictions on travel and in-person meetings forced a shift to online workshops. Five virtual workshop sessions were conducted between June 2020 and April 2021.</p> <p><strong>Workshop 1: How to stay competitive as a graduating PhD student in the time of COVID-19</strong></p> <p>Due to the COVID-19 pandemic, graduate students are working from home and are not able to access their laboratories. In person collaborations and networking at conferences are impossible. Furthermore, universities are announcing hiring freezes. This session provided guidance from ECE department heads on steps students can take in the areas of research, teaching, and leadership &amp; professional development to stay competitive in pursuing the type of academic position they would like to obtain in the future.</p> <p><strong>25 student participants</strong></p> <p><strong><br /></strong></p> <p><strong>Workshop 2: Virtual Mentoring Session: ECE Department Hiring Opportunities</strong></p> <p>In this session, panelists from previous iREDEFINE programs shared their experiences while searching for an academic position and during the first year in their career. In addition, department heads covered topics such as how to stand out as a candidate, how to navigate the interview process, and how COVID has affected hiring at institutions.</p> <p><strong>26 student participants</strong></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Workshop 3: Networking with Department Chairs</strong></p> <p>This session provided an opportunity for ECE department chairs to meet with PhD ECE students; learn about their research, teaching, and leadership skills; help the students practice their networking skills and work on their elevator pitch; and answer their questions about academic careers.</p> <p><strong>18 student participants, 26 department heads</strong></p> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p><strong>Workshop 4: Negotiation Skills: Strategies for Success</strong></p> <p>This session focused on research-based strategies and improving negotiation skills, such as becoming aware of the issues, learning about the negotiation process, and practicing negotiation. The session also addressed strategies for continuing to build negotiation skills after the conclusion of the workshop.</p> <p><strong>19 student participants</strong></p> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p><strong>Workshop 5: CV Review with Department Chairs</strong></p> <p>This session provided an opportunity for PhD ECE students to participate in several mock interviews with ECE department chairs, providing them with the opportunity to practice their academic interview skills and ask questions about academic careers.&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>18 student participants, 26 department heads</strong></p> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p><strong>iREDEFINE 2022 Workshop</strong></p> <p>In March 2022, we were able to return to an in-person workshop at the ECEDHA Annual Conference in New Orleans. The workshop included sessions on negotiations, types of academic institutions, mock interviews, and student poster sessions. NSF funding supported participation of 33 students. Additionally, 4 students were supported by their departments.</p> <p>Participation in the ECEDHA focused programming provided by the online and in-person workshop sessions has prepared iREDEFINE Scholars to be successful in their academic careers. The opportunities to interact with a wide range of ECEDHA participants equips them with a broad and diverse professional network. Furthermore, by connecting the students with successful women and URM academic leaders, we have catalyzed an interest in academic administration among iREDEFINE Scholars who will then become role models for the next generation of women and URM ECE students.</p> <p class="Default">As of June 2023, not all 2020 and 2022 iREDEFINE Scholars have graduated. Out of the 39 participants from the 2020 online cohort, 5 obtained faculty positions, one is a postdoctoral researcher, and 19 work in industry. Out of the 37 2022 iREDEFINE scholars, 4 obtained faculty positions, three are post-doctoral researchers, 8 work in industry, and the rest have not graduated yet.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/03/2023<br>      Modified by: Agnieszka&nbsp;Miguel</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[The iREDEFINE program motivates and prepares PhD women and minority students to pursue faculty positions in US universities. The iREDEFINE initiative has included workshops for women and underrepresented minority graduate ECE students at the annual meeting of the Electrical and Computer Engineering Department Heads Association (ECEDHA); mini workshops at regional ECEDHA meetings; and a year-round mentoring program. The iREDEFINE workshops provide extensive opportunities for ECE PhD students to interact with department chairs and learn about the ECE programs they represent, faculty positions in their departments, and the expectations from a new tenure-track faculty member. iREDEFINE Scholars also present their research accomplishments and participate in dedicated iREDEFINE programming including sessions on different types of institutions, advice about first years as a new tenure-track faculty member, negotiation strategies, CV review, and mock interviews. These sessions, organized by the iREDEFINE Committee and facilitated by ECE faculty and department heads, prepare women and underrepresented minority ECE PhD students for successful academic careers and provide excellent networking opportunities. Mentoring is one of the key factors that contribute to the success of new faculty. Some institutions offer structured mentoring programs for female and URM PhD students and/or junior faculty members while others lack the infrastructure to organize such programs. This project has created a mentoring network that will support the students as they advance in their academic careers and become faculty. Group mentoring sessions have been organized with facilitated conference calls every couple of months and online support platforms.  The onset of COVID-19 and the resulting restrictions on travel and in-person meetings forced a shift to online workshops. Five virtual workshop sessions were conducted between June 2020 and April 2021.  Workshop 1: How to stay competitive as a graduating PhD student in the time of COVID-19  Due to the COVID-19 pandemic, graduate students are working from home and are not able to access their laboratories. In person collaborations and networking at conferences are impossible. Furthermore, universities are announcing hiring freezes. This session provided guidance from ECE department heads on steps students can take in the areas of research, teaching, and leadership &amp; professional development to stay competitive in pursuing the type of academic position they would like to obtain in the future.  25 student participants     Workshop 2: Virtual Mentoring Session: ECE Department Hiring Opportunities  In this session, panelists from previous iREDEFINE programs shared their experiences while searching for an academic position and during the first year in their career. In addition, department heads covered topics such as how to stand out as a candidate, how to navigate the interview process, and how COVID has affected hiring at institutions.  26 student participants     Workshop 3: Networking with Department Chairs  This session provided an opportunity for ECE department chairs to meet with PhD ECE students; learn about their research, teaching, and leadership skills; help the students practice their networking skills and work on their elevator pitch; and answer their questions about academic careers.  18 student participants, 26 department heads     Workshop 4: Negotiation Skills: Strategies for Success  This session focused on research-based strategies and improving negotiation skills, such as becoming aware of the issues, learning about the negotiation process, and practicing negotiation. The session also addressed strategies for continuing to build negotiation skills after the conclusion of the workshop.  19 student participants     Workshop 5: CV Review with Department Chairs  This session provided an opportunity for PhD ECE students to participate in several mock interviews with ECE department chairs, providing them with the opportunity to practice their academic interview skills and ask questions about academic careers.   18 student participants, 26 department heads     iREDEFINE 2022 Workshop  In March 2022, we were able to return to an in-person workshop at the ECEDHA Annual Conference in New Orleans. The workshop included sessions on negotiations, types of academic institutions, mock interviews, and student poster sessions. NSF funding supported participation of 33 students. Additionally, 4 students were supported by their departments.  Participation in the ECEDHA focused programming provided by the online and in-person workshop sessions has prepared iREDEFINE Scholars to be successful in their academic careers. The opportunities to interact with a wide range of ECEDHA participants equips them with a broad and diverse professional network. Furthermore, by connecting the students with successful women and URM academic leaders, we have catalyzed an interest in academic administration among iREDEFINE Scholars who will then become role models for the next generation of women and URM ECE students. As of June 2023, not all 2020 and 2022 iREDEFINE Scholars have graduated. Out of the 39 participants from the 2020 online cohort, 5 obtained faculty positions, one is a postdoctoral researcher, and 19 work in industry. Out of the 37 2022 iREDEFINE scholars, 4 obtained faculty positions, three are post-doctoral researchers, 8 work in industry, and the rest have not graduated yet.             Last Modified: 07/03/2023       Submitted by: Agnieszka Miguel]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
