<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[I-Corps:  Coupled High and Low-Frequency Ultrasonic for the Destruction of Organics]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ruth Shuman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rshuman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922160</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this I-Corps project is to advance the development of power ultrasound for the destruction of hazardous chemicals. This technology can potentially be used for industrial and laboratory organic waste treatment, remediation/treatment of polluted soils/sediments, and water and wastewater treatment. The technology offers a cost-effective method for degrading toxic organic pollutants, eliminating the use of costly activated carbon or other adsorbents, and generating in situ removal of organic contaminants at the source. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project explores translation of the sonochemistry associated with power ultrasound to develop a new environmental remediation technology for the degradation of pollutants such as PFAS, PCB, PAH, etc. Commercially available remedial approaches use sorption and stabilization techniques or incineration, but these are ineffective for certain classes of pollutants and incineration is an expensive alternative. This project explores sono-chemical reactions and sono-physical pyrolysis without requiring additional chemicals; the project will characterize the future optimization of parameters including frequency, transducer selection, and reactor geometry.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/28/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/28/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2016168</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jay</FirstName>
<LastName>Meegoda</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>N</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jay N Meegoda</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[meegoda@njit.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000453752</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/28/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>New Jersey Institute of Technology</Name>
<CityName>NEWARK</CityName>
<ZipCode>071021824</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9735965275</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>323 DR MARTIN LUTHER KING JR BLV</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NJ10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>SGBMHQ7VXNH5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NEW JERSEY INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[New Jersey Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>Newark</CityName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>071021982</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[University Heights]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NJ10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Project Outcomes Report &ndash; NSF Award# 2016168</p> <p>Project Title: I-Corps: Coupled High and Low-Frequency Ultrasonic for the Destruction of Organics.</p> <p>Recipient Organization: New Jersey Institute of Technology</p> <p>Project/Grant Period: 06/01/2020 &ndash; 11/30/21</p> <p>PI: Jay N. Meegoda</p> <p>This I-Corps project explored the translation of the sonochemistry associated with power ultrasound to develop a new environmental remediation technology for the degradation of pollutants such as PFAS, PCB, PAH, etc. Commercially available remedial approaches use sorption and stabilization techniques or incineration, but these are ineffective for certain classes of pollutants and incineration is an expensive alternative. This project explored the sono-chemical reactions and sono-physical pyrolysis without requiring additional chemicals. The broader impact/commercial potential of this I-Corps project was to advance the development of power ultrasound for the destruction of hazardous chemicals. This technology can potentially be used for industrial and laboratory organic waste treatment, remediation/treatment of polluted soils/sediments, and water and wastewater treatment. The technology offers a cost-effective method for degrading toxic organic pollutants, eliminating the use of costly activated carbon or other adsorbents, and generating in situ removal of organic contaminants at the source.&nbsp;The high-power ultrasound technology has received considerable attention, as ultrasound is a green and sustainable technology.</p> <p>The research idea for this project was based on prior NSF project (CMMI#1634857, $476,577.00, 9/2016-8/2021), "Remediation of Contaminated Sediments with Ultrasound and Ozone Nano-bubbles," PI Jay N. Meegoda, which&nbsp;&nbsp;investigated an innovative in-situ approach to remediate contaminated sediments.&nbsp;&nbsp;To evaluate the commercial potential and gain valuable market insights for the development of the ultrasonic technology for&nbsp;&nbsp;the destruction of organics, the team participated in the NSF I-Corps Team Program. The goal of the I-Corps project was to use the customer discovery and preparation of a business model canvas to find the market fit for technology and identity the early adaptor through customer discovery interviews to develop ultrasound technology for the remediation of emerging contaminants. &nbsp;</p> <p>The team identified and initiated interviews with the stakeholders of customer segment to learn about their problems and challenges to identify the market demand and find the market fit for ultrasound technology.</p> <p>In total team conducted 102 interviews with various stakeholders in the industry and gained insight into the market demand.&nbsp;During the interviews with the stakeholder of the customer segment MSW Landfill and Geo-Environmental Site Remediation Engineer, we identified a niche for the technology. The stakeholders in these two customer segments face challenges with an emerging contaminant, Per- and Polyfluoroalkyl Substances (PFAS), that has created quite complex challenges for the stakeholder, and their existing solutions are not much effective on these family of emerging contaminants. They are looking for new and innovative solutions. Using the process of elimination, the team was able to eliminate the two-customer segment and redefine the final two customer segments in the first two weeks of the I-corps boot camp.</p> <p>During our I-Corp final discovery, we found that treatment of PFAS contaminated landfill leachate was the best market fit for our technology. After our I-Corp team program, we conducted additional interviews and, with discussion with our industrial partner (TetraTech), we decided to shift our focus from the landfill leachate to the concentrated PFAS waste streams.&nbsp;&nbsp;Also, after the conclusion of the I-corps boot camp with 102 interviews with various stakeholders, the team visited five other organizations to develop firm collaborations and to proceed with the next step of submitting an NSF PFI-RP proposal. To gather preliminary data for the above proposal, the team purchased a batch reactor designed by NJIT and fabricated by PCT Systems. Using this reactor experiments were conducted on 2L PFAS-spiked solutions with a power density of 100W/L. Initial test results showed that for PFOA (with an initial concentration of 5 mg/L), PFOS (with an initial concentration of 5.9 mg/L) and. PFAS (mixture of PFOA and PFOS with an initial concentration of 6.3 mg/L) reached 87.9%, 63.8% and 73.1%&nbsp;&nbsp;total destruction, and 97.2%, 59.1% and 57.4% defluorination respectively. The degradation rate of PFOS was not impacted in the PFAS mixture when both types of PFAS in the solution with sonolysis treatment.&nbsp;&nbsp;Based on the preliminary experiment without optimizations, electrical energy per order (EE/O) for treatment of PFOA and PFOS ranged from 217KWh/m<sup>3</sup>&nbsp;to 1130KWh/m<sup>3</sup>, respectively.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/07/2022<br>      Modified by: Jay&nbsp;N&nbsp;Meegoda</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Project Outcomes Report &ndash; NSF Award# 2016168  Project Title: I-Corps: Coupled High and Low-Frequency Ultrasonic for the Destruction of Organics.  Recipient Organization: New Jersey Institute of Technology  Project/Grant Period: 06/01/2020 &ndash; 11/30/21  PI: Jay N. Meegoda  This I-Corps project explored the translation of the sonochemistry associated with power ultrasound to develop a new environmental remediation technology for the degradation of pollutants such as PFAS, PCB, PAH, etc. Commercially available remedial approaches use sorption and stabilization techniques or incineration, but these are ineffective for certain classes of pollutants and incineration is an expensive alternative. This project explored the sono-chemical reactions and sono-physical pyrolysis without requiring additional chemicals. The broader impact/commercial potential of this I-Corps project was to advance the development of power ultrasound for the destruction of hazardous chemicals. This technology can potentially be used for industrial and laboratory organic waste treatment, remediation/treatment of polluted soils/sediments, and water and wastewater treatment. The technology offers a cost-effective method for degrading toxic organic pollutants, eliminating the use of costly activated carbon or other adsorbents, and generating in situ removal of organic contaminants at the source. The high-power ultrasound technology has received considerable attention, as ultrasound is a green and sustainable technology.  The research idea for this project was based on prior NSF project (CMMI#1634857, $476,577.00, 9/2016-8/2021), "Remediation of Contaminated Sediments with Ultrasound and Ozone Nano-bubbles," PI Jay N. Meegoda, which  investigated an innovative in-situ approach to remediate contaminated sediments.  To evaluate the commercial potential and gain valuable market insights for the development of the ultrasonic technology for  the destruction of organics, the team participated in the NSF I-Corps Team Program. The goal of the I-Corps project was to use the customer discovery and preparation of a business model canvas to find the market fit for technology and identity the early adaptor through customer discovery interviews to develop ultrasound technology for the remediation of emerging contaminants.    The team identified and initiated interviews with the stakeholders of customer segment to learn about their problems and challenges to identify the market demand and find the market fit for ultrasound technology.  In total team conducted 102 interviews with various stakeholders in the industry and gained insight into the market demand. During the interviews with the stakeholder of the customer segment MSW Landfill and Geo-Environmental Site Remediation Engineer, we identified a niche for the technology. The stakeholders in these two customer segments face challenges with an emerging contaminant, Per- and Polyfluoroalkyl Substances (PFAS), that has created quite complex challenges for the stakeholder, and their existing solutions are not much effective on these family of emerging contaminants. They are looking for new and innovative solutions. Using the process of elimination, the team was able to eliminate the two-customer segment and redefine the final two customer segments in the first two weeks of the I-corps boot camp.  During our I-Corp final discovery, we found that treatment of PFAS contaminated landfill leachate was the best market fit for our technology. After our I-Corp team program, we conducted additional interviews and, with discussion with our industrial partner (TetraTech), we decided to shift our focus from the landfill leachate to the concentrated PFAS waste streams.  Also, after the conclusion of the I-corps boot camp with 102 interviews with various stakeholders, the team visited five other organizations to develop firm collaborations and to proceed with the next step of submitting an NSF PFI-RP proposal. To gather preliminary data for the above proposal, the team purchased a batch reactor designed by NJIT and fabricated by PCT Systems. Using this reactor experiments were conducted on 2L PFAS-spiked solutions with a power density of 100W/L. Initial test results showed that for PFOA (with an initial concentration of 5 mg/L), PFOS (with an initial concentration of 5.9 mg/L) and. PFAS (mixture of PFOA and PFOS with an initial concentration of 6.3 mg/L) reached 87.9%, 63.8% and 73.1%  total destruction, and 97.2%, 59.1% and 57.4% defluorination respectively. The degradation rate of PFOS was not impacted in the PFAS mixture when both types of PFAS in the solution with sonolysis treatment.  Based on the preliminary experiment without optimizations, electrical energy per order (EE/O) for treatment of PFOA and PFOS ranged from 217KWh/m3 to 1130KWh/m3, respectively.          Last Modified: 01/07/2022       Submitted by: Jay N Meegoda]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
