<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Community Climate Intervention Strategies Workshop; Boulder, CO; April 2020]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>48000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>48000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Bruce Hamilton</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bhamilto@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032920000</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This grant is in partial support of the Community Climate Intervention Strategies Workshop to be held April 15-17, 2020 at UCAR/NCAR in Boulder. Experts in emissions mitigation, carbon dioxide removal (CDR), solar radiation management (SRM), integrated assessment modeling (IAM), observations, ecological and societal impacts, ethics, and communication will collaboratively develop a unifying research framework and initiate working groups that will identify and address critical combined climate intervention research questions. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A climate intervention strategy framework that coordinates existing work and identifies innovative research efforts and future research needs across mitigation, climate intervention areas, and climate change impacts would be of great benefit. The objective of the workshop is to create such a unifying framework that will fortify climate intervention research through new partnerships to achieve the following: (1) construction of a portfolio of ethically-informed future scenarios that integrate mitigation, CDR, and SRM, (2) development of methods for collaborative impact analysis relevant to society and ecosystems so that common and relevant metrics and shared datasets can be developed and distributed, and (3) facilitation of communication to ensure research goals and methodologies balance the priorities of research communities as well as key climate-affected stakeholders. The workshop has the potential to transform many distinct assessments of climate intervention strategies into a comprehensive, interdisciplinary approach. The targeted result is end-to-end climate intervention assessments with societally-relevant outcomes. Planned participants in the workshop include nationally-recognized climate researchers, early career scientists, and graduate students from across the United States as well as internationally-recognized experts. Also planned is participation by attendees from underrepresented groups from the Arctic, developing countries, and indigenous communities.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/11/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/11/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2016205</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Elizabeth</FirstName>
<LastName>Page</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Elizabeth M Page</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[epage@ucar.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000776630</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/11/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Andrea</FirstName>
<LastName>Smith</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Andrea Smith</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[asmith5@ucar.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000817831</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/11/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University Corporation For Atmospheric Res</Name>
<CityName>BOULDER</CityName>
<ZipCode>803012252</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3034971000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3090 CENTER GREEN DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>YEZEE8W5JKA3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY CORPORATION FOR ATMOSPHERIC RESEARCH</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>YEZEE8W5JKA3</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University Corporation For Atmospheric Res]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>803012252</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5740</Code>
<Text>Climate &amp; Large-Scale Dynamics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7643</Code>
<Text>EnvS-Environmtl Sustainability</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>4444</Code>
<Text>INTERDISCIPLINARY PROPOSALS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~48000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-23ae7d0d-7fff-9fa3-7aec-f43d830be3b9"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The risks of climate change have continued to grow while projections suggest that no single pathway can limit warming to well below an additional 2 degrees Celsius.&nbsp; Coordinated work among physical, life, and social scientists, engineers and stakeholder communities is necessary to comprehensively understand how multiple types of climate interventions would interact in real-world scenarios.&nbsp; Studies of carbon dioxide removal (CDR) and solar radiation management (SRM) intervention techniques have largely investigated the two strategies separately.&nbsp; In recent years, several climate research studies have noted the need for investigating a portfolio of combined climate intervention scenarios.&nbsp;&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The Community Climate Intervention Strategies (CCIS) Steering Committee was established to&nbsp; convene the disparate research groups needed for the development of an interdisciplinary climate intervention research program. CCIS began its funded collaborative activities by hosting an eight-part webinar series in Summer 2020. The series featured 27 international experts that outlined the state of the science of various climate intervention approaches including SRM and CDR, as well as their potential impacts, how they might be simulated together, and what ethical considerations exist surrounding their potential use. Over 16 hours of recorded presentations are available on the CCIS website.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The CCIS team then convened an October 2020 workshop to discuss climate intervention research gaps and create recommendations for a collaborative interventions research framework. 250 international and interdisciplinary attendees participated in the three-day event. Physical and biological scientists constituted roughly half of participants, with the other half composed of social scientists, communication and education specialists, local stakeholders, policymakers, and representatives from nonprofit organizations. Recommendations from the workshop included the following: 1) create seven science-themed working groups as part of a CCIS research framework, 2) develop a CCIS communication and resource hub to facilitate exchange between scientists, stakeholders, and policymakers, and 3) integrate communication and interdisciplinary research design specialists within working groups and the CCIS program at large. The full meeting summary article is available at https://journals.ametsoc.org/view/journals/bams/103/2/BAMS-D-21-0053.1.xml.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The CCIS team began working toward these recommendations in 2021 by forming two of the seven recommended working groups, continuing to develop the CCIS website by adding a collaboration forum and a climate intervention research project and program database, and by submitting multiple multi-institution proposals to acquire additional project funding for continued collaboration services as well as combined intervention scenario research.&nbsp; Along the way and due to popular demand in the broader CCIS community, a 7-part 2021 webinar series was developed and delivered, adding another 10 hours of recordings that further describe the current state of climate intervention science and related socioeconomic processes, challenges and communication efforts in detail.&nbsp; These webinars, alongside the 2020 webinars, are being used by many professors for their climate and interdisciplinary courses, and have over 8,000 views.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Next steps include the further establishment of other CCIS science-themed working groups, continued exploration of funding for scenario-based research on combined interventions, and development of workshops and webinar series that will continue to bring researchers and stakeholders together in addressing the most urgent climate intervention research questions.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/29/2022<br>      Modified by: Andrea&nbsp;Smith</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   The risks of climate change have continued to grow while projections suggest that no single pathway can limit warming to well below an additional 2 degrees Celsius.  Coordinated work among physical, life, and social scientists, engineers and stakeholder communities is necessary to comprehensively understand how multiple types of climate interventions would interact in real-world scenarios.  Studies of carbon dioxide removal (CDR) and solar radiation management (SRM) intervention techniques have largely investigated the two strategies separately.  In recent years, several climate research studies have noted the need for investigating a portfolio of combined climate intervention scenarios.   The Community Climate Intervention Strategies (CCIS) Steering Committee was established to  convene the disparate research groups needed for the development of an interdisciplinary climate intervention research program. CCIS began its funded collaborative activities by hosting an eight-part webinar series in Summer 2020. The series featured 27 international experts that outlined the state of the science of various climate intervention approaches including SRM and CDR, as well as their potential impacts, how they might be simulated together, and what ethical considerations exist surrounding their potential use. Over 16 hours of recorded presentations are available on the CCIS website. The CCIS team then convened an October 2020 workshop to discuss climate intervention research gaps and create recommendations for a collaborative interventions research framework. 250 international and interdisciplinary attendees participated in the three-day event. Physical and biological scientists constituted roughly half of participants, with the other half composed of social scientists, communication and education specialists, local stakeholders, policymakers, and representatives from nonprofit organizations. Recommendations from the workshop included the following: 1) create seven science-themed working groups as part of a CCIS research framework, 2) develop a CCIS communication and resource hub to facilitate exchange between scientists, stakeholders, and policymakers, and 3) integrate communication and interdisciplinary research design specialists within working groups and the CCIS program at large. The full meeting summary article is available at https://journals.ametsoc.org/view/journals/bams/103/2/BAMS-D-21-0053.1.xml. The CCIS team began working toward these recommendations in 2021 by forming two of the seven recommended working groups, continuing to develop the CCIS website by adding a collaboration forum and a climate intervention research project and program database, and by submitting multiple multi-institution proposals to acquire additional project funding for continued collaboration services as well as combined intervention scenario research.  Along the way and due to popular demand in the broader CCIS community, a 7-part 2021 webinar series was developed and delivered, adding another 10 hours of recordings that further describe the current state of climate intervention science and related socioeconomic processes, challenges and communication efforts in detail.  These webinars, alongside the 2020 webinars, are being used by many professors for their climate and interdisciplinary courses, and have over 8,000 views. Next steps include the further establishment of other CCIS science-themed working groups, continued exploration of funding for scenario-based research on combined interventions, and development of workshops and webinar series that will continue to bring researchers and stakeholders together in addressing the most urgent climate intervention research questions.                Last Modified: 04/29/2022       Submitted by: Andrea Smith]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
