<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[2020 African Diaspora Joint Mathematics Workshops (ADJOINT)]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>49991.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>49991</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Swatee Naik</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>snaik@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924876</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This award will support the 2020 African Diaspora Joint Mathematics Workshop (ADJOINT) to be held online from June 15 – 26, 2020. The Mathematical Sciences Research Institute (MSRI) developed the ADJOINT program to provide opportunities for research collaboration to U.S. mathematical scientists, especially those from the African American community, who will work in small groups with research leaders on various research projects. The underlying goal of ADJOINT in to enhance the careers of its participants by catalyzing collaborative research projects, by creating formal mentorship opportunities, and by facilitating networking activities in the hope of creating a sense of belonging to a community of peers. The members of the research groups will be encouraged to build on the ADJOINT experience by planning and participating in research activities in the following year and beyond. Having core, productive groups of black research-active mathematical scientists in various fields will stimulate further participation by this community in these fields, and thus stimulate the fields as a whole.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;For two weeks in the summer of 2020, five research groups will participate in the ADJOINT program. During that time, participants will be working intensely in small groups comprised of 4-5 participants and led by a respected African American mathematical scientist with a well-established research program. Additionally, researchers will participate in professional development activities and a weekly colloquium series. Due to the COVID-19 pandemic, the 2020 research groups will collaborate virtually with materials and technical support provided by MSRI. After the summer, MSRI will provide researchers with the necessary support to travel (when it is safe to do so) to meet with their team members and proceed further with their research agenda, to attend and organize conferences to present results, and to become part of a network of research and career mentors. Furthermore, at a future date (possibly summer 2021) MSRI will host a one-week reunion onsite at MSRI’s facilities in Berkeley, CA to allow for in-person interaction between collaborators and to consolidate the sense of community among participants. More information about the ADJOINT program can be found at https://www.msri.org/web/msri/scientific/adjoint.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/20/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/20/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2016406</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Helene</FirstName>
<LastName>Barcelo</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Helene Barcelo</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[hbarcelo@msri.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000527688</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/20/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Mathematical Sciences Research Institute</Name>
<CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
<ZipCode>947200001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5106420143</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>17 GAUSS WAY</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>LWLJAPATKEL8</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MATHEMATICAL SCIENCES RESEARCH INSTITUTE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Mathematical Sciences Research Institute]]></Name>
<CityName>Berkeley</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>947205070</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[17 Gauss Way]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1260</Code>
<Text>INFRASTRUCTURE PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~49991</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The African Diaspora Joint Mathematics Workshop (ADJOINT) is designed to provide opportunities for U.S. mathematicians, especially those from the African Diaspora, to collaborate with distinguished African-American research leaders on cutting-edge mathematical and statistical research. Small research teams led by accomplished research leaders come together to develop a research project during the two-week long workshop in the summer and continue their research collaboration throughout the subsequent academic year. The 2020 ADJOINT workshop (June 15&ndash;16, 2020) brought together twenty-two participants, including five Research Leaders, to develop research projects in the areas of mathematical physics, mathematical biology, analysis and PDEs, statistics, and differential geometry.&nbsp; The groups were comprised of mathematical and statistical scientists, predominantly of African descent and at various career stages. The five research leaders, renowned researchers in their respective fields, were also predominantly of African descent. The 2020 ADJOINT Research Leaders included Tepper Gill (Howard University), Abba Gumel (Arizona State University), Ryan Hynd (University of Pennsylvania), Bonita V. Saunders (National Institute of Standards and Technology), and Craig Sutton (Dartmouth College).</p> <p>The 2020 ADJOINT program catalyzed research collaborations and provided support for ongoing collaborative research and conference participation, which increased the visibility of the researchers and developed a sense of community among the mathematicians who participated. Since 2020, all five research groups have presented their research at conferences and seminars, published papers and have been engaged in scholarly activities.</p> <p>Due to the pandemic, the 2020 ADJOINT workshop was held entirely virtually. In order to give the virtual participants an opportunity to meet in-person, the ADJOINT directorate planned a week-long reunion program to include all five of the 2020 research groups. The reunion took place in-person at MSRI from June 27&ndash;July 2, 2022.</p> <p>The ADJOINT directorate has continued to evaluate the program with the guidance of a commissioned consultant, Karen Peterman. The evaluation plan, which includes surveys and interviews of the participants, has elicited useful feedback that has been used to improve the program.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/21/2022<br>      Modified by: Helene&nbsp;Barcelo</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The African Diaspora Joint Mathematics Workshop (ADJOINT) is designed to provide opportunities for U.S. mathematicians, especially those from the African Diaspora, to collaborate with distinguished African-American research leaders on cutting-edge mathematical and statistical research. Small research teams led by accomplished research leaders come together to develop a research project during the two-week long workshop in the summer and continue their research collaboration throughout the subsequent academic year. The 2020 ADJOINT workshop (June 15&ndash;16, 2020) brought together twenty-two participants, including five Research Leaders, to develop research projects in the areas of mathematical physics, mathematical biology, analysis and PDEs, statistics, and differential geometry.  The groups were comprised of mathematical and statistical scientists, predominantly of African descent and at various career stages. The five research leaders, renowned researchers in their respective fields, were also predominantly of African descent. The 2020 ADJOINT Research Leaders included Tepper Gill (Howard University), Abba Gumel (Arizona State University), Ryan Hynd (University of Pennsylvania), Bonita V. Saunders (National Institute of Standards and Technology), and Craig Sutton (Dartmouth College).  The 2020 ADJOINT program catalyzed research collaborations and provided support for ongoing collaborative research and conference participation, which increased the visibility of the researchers and developed a sense of community among the mathematicians who participated. Since 2020, all five research groups have presented their research at conferences and seminars, published papers and have been engaged in scholarly activities.  Due to the pandemic, the 2020 ADJOINT workshop was held entirely virtually. In order to give the virtual participants an opportunity to meet in-person, the ADJOINT directorate planned a week-long reunion program to include all five of the 2020 research groups. The reunion took place in-person at MSRI from June 27&ndash;July 2, 2022.  The ADJOINT directorate has continued to evaluate the program with the guidance of a commissioned consultant, Karen Peterman. The evaluation plan, which includes surveys and interviews of the participants, has elicited useful feedback that has been used to improve the program.          Last Modified: 11/21/2022       Submitted by: Helene Barcelo]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
