<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[University of Minnesota/Blue Heron SSSE 2020]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>36375.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>36375</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06040100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OCE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>James Holik</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jholik@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927711</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[A request is made to fund Shipboard Scientific Support Equipment (SSSE) for the R/V Blue Heron, an 86-foot Coastal research vessel owned by the University of Minnesota and operated by the Large Lakes Observatory as part of the US Academic Research Fleet (ARF). Built in 1985 for fishing on the Grand Banks, Blue Heron was purchased by the University of Minnesota in 1997. She is outfitted with state-of-the-art research equipment, has berthing for 11 crew and scientists, and can operate 24 hours per day for up to 21 days in between port calls. The Blue Heron is part of the University National Oceanographic Laboratory System (UNOLS), and is available for charter by research scientists on any of the Great Lakes. In 2019, the vessel completed 81 funded days where 531 (66%) were for NSF. In 2020, Blue Heron is currently scheduled for 99 days, 84 of these (85%) will be for NSF. With this proposal, Minnesota provides technical descriptions and rationale for the acquisition of the following Equipment:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Radar upgrade for the R/V Blue Heron $21,605&lt;br/&gt;Forward looking sonar for the R/V Blue Heron $14,770&lt;br/&gt;      $36,375&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts&lt;br/&gt;The principal impact of the present proposal is under Merit Review Criterion 2 of the Proposal Guidelines (NSF 19-602). It provides infrastructure support for scientists to use the vessel and its shared-use instrumentation in support of their NSF-funded oceanographic research projects (which individually undergo separate review by the relevant research program of NSF).  The acquisition,  maintenance and operation of shared-use instrumentation allows NSF-funded researchers from any US university or lab access to working, calibrated instruments for their research, reducing the cost of that research, and expanding the base of potential researchers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/10/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/10/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2016614</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
<LastName>Ricketts</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Richard D Ricketts</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ricketts@d.umn.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000282492</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Minnesota Duluth</Name>
<CityName>DULUTH</CityName>
<ZipCode>558123031</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2187267582</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1035 UNIVERSITY DR RM 133</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MN08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>LPCTM8BS8NF3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MINNESOTA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>CB47L9C9MDX1</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Minnesota Duluth]]></Name>
<CityName>Duluth</CityName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>558123011</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2205 E. 5th Street, RLB rm 109]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MN08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5416</Code>
<Text>SHIPBOARD SCIENTIFIC SUPP EQUI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~36375</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The University of Minnesota Duluth upgraded our radar system and added a forward-looking sonar to the research vessel Blue Heron using funds provided by the National Science Foundation award OCE#2016614 &lsquo;University of Minnesota/Blue Heron SSSE 2020&rsquo;.&nbsp; The upgraded radar system and forward-looking sonar will allow the vessel to better serve the researchers who use the vessel.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Our previous radar system was nearing the end of its useful life, with parts of the system failing and no longer supported by the manufacturer.&nbsp; The forward-looking sonar was recommended during an assessment of the vessel&rsquo;s capabilities.&nbsp; Researchers had been requested the addition of the sonar to the vessel and these funds allowed us to meet those requests.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The new equipment is available to all users of the R/V Blue Heron, including the three National Science Foundation funded projects that are using the vessel in 2022.&nbsp; Besides the NSF funded projects, we are supporting several other projects in 2022: a State of Minnesota Department of Natural Resources cruise and multiple research and educational cruises funded by the University of Minnesota.&nbsp; Regarding the educational cruises, the University of Minnesota is funding nine cruises in 2022, which will expose over 200 undergraduates to scientific research on the Great Lakes.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/01/2022<br>      Modified by: Richard&nbsp;D&nbsp;Ricketts</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The University of Minnesota Duluth upgraded our radar system and added a forward-looking sonar to the research vessel Blue Heron using funds provided by the National Science Foundation award OCE#2016614 ‘University of Minnesota/Blue Heron SSSE 2020’.  The upgraded radar system and forward-looking sonar will allow the vessel to better serve the researchers who use the vessel.     Our previous radar system was nearing the end of its useful life, with parts of the system failing and no longer supported by the manufacturer.  The forward-looking sonar was recommended during an assessment of the vessel’s capabilities.  Researchers had been requested the addition of the sonar to the vessel and these funds allowed us to meet those requests.     The new equipment is available to all users of the R/V Blue Heron, including the three National Science Foundation funded projects that are using the vessel in 2022.  Besides the NSF funded projects, we are supporting several other projects in 2022: a State of Minnesota Department of Natural Resources cruise and multiple research and educational cruises funded by the University of Minnesota.  Regarding the educational cruises, the University of Minnesota is funding nine cruises in 2022, which will expose over 200 undergraduates to scientific research on the Great Lakes.             Last Modified: 03/01/2022       Submitted by: Richard D Ricketts]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
