<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Doctoral Dissertation Research: Investigating theories of the over-production of subject pronouns in bilinguals]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>16986.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>16986</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jorge Valdes Kroff</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jvaldesk@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927920</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[A fundamental skill that children must acquire is the ability to use language to refer to people and objects around them. Pronominal subjects like ‘he’ and ‘she’ are universal linguistic devices used to refer to a person mentioned or implied in previous discourse. Pronouns allow speakers to avoid redundancy or repetition, thus making languages more economical. At the same time, the ability to track referents in discourse develops over time. How children learn to interpret and appropriately use these referential devices is a central question in language acquisition research, particularly because mastering pronominal subjects takes up to adolescence. Studying this ability in the bilingual development of children who speak typologically different but syntactically similar languages in the way pronouns are expressed is critical to understand the complementing roles of linguistic and cognitive development in children and adolescents. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project investigates the acquisition and development of pronominal subject expression in school-age monolingual and bilingual children in order to assess potential developmental delays in bilingual populations and to examine how parents’ linguistic choices may influence children’s linguistic behavior. 200 children ages 6 to 13 will be compared to 90 adults (half monolinguals, half bilinguals who simultaneously acquired two languages). The bilingual population will be tested to evaluate the acquisitional differences of the socio-politically majority language and the minority language in a society with stable bilingualism and a strong education system in the minority language. Children’s comprehension and production will be measured through oral production and comprehension tasks. Because the pair of languages studied are null subject languages, the results will contribute to evaluate two competing accounts of subject over-production in the bilingual literature ––crosslinguistic influence versus cognitive load–– that are also central questions in the acquisition of syntax.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/04/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/20/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2017706</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Silvina</FirstName>
<LastName>Montrul</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Silvina A Montrul</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[montrul@illinois.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000274894</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/04/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Eider</FirstName>
<LastName>Etxebarria-Zuluaga</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Eider Etxebarria-Zuluaga</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[eetxeb2@illinois.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000819900</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/04/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</Name>
<CityName>URBANA</CityName>
<ZipCode>618013620</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>506 S WRIGHT ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>Y8CWNJRCNN91</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ILLINOIS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign]]></Name>
<CityName>Champaign</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>618207406</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1901 South First Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8374</Code>
<Text>DDRI Linguistics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1311</Code>
<Text>LINGUISTICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5952</Code>
<Text>SPAIN</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~16986</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project examines the bilingual development of children acquiring Basque, a national minority language, and Spanish. Investigating the linguistic development of school-age bilingual children is critical to understanding typical milestones of bilingual language acquisition and to evaluate potential developmental delays in the heritage/minority language. The study of school-age children is essential to document and provide positive empirical evidence of dual language development as well as bilingual programs that primarily teach using minority languages, particularly for the fields of education, educational policy, instruction, and curriculum development.</p> <p>The socio-political environment and educational programs of the Basque Country are quite unique in the sense that community members and government officials have worked arduously to cultivate positive linguistic attitudes and celebrate bilingualism in this bilingual region. The youngest generations are the fruit of decades of hard work, including the Standardization of Basque, the implementation of public bilingual programs, teacher training, and curriculum development, among other factors. This is an optimal environment for successful dual language development because parental commitment, governmental protection, and social prestige have collectively created a situation of stable bilingualism, which contributed to the Basque educational system being regarded as a global benchmark<strong> </strong>for bilingual education. This study allowed us to measure the linguistic outcomes of bilingual children's languages, as well as the success of educational programs that teach primarily in Basque.</p> <p>Specifically, we examined subject pronoun expression (SPE) in Basque and Spanish, two null subject languages (NSL). The production of third-person singular null and overt subject pronouns was tested in Spanish and Basque by 136 Spanish monolingual and Basque-Spanish bilingual children (ages 6, 8, and 12), as well as 60 monolingual and bilingual adults. Our results contribute to theoretical debates on the acquisition of interface phenomena in bilingualism and confirm the importance of academic and societal support of the heritage/minority language for its successful maintenance and transmission. Overall, this project found that SPE in NSLs is prolonged and extremely taxing to acquire, and it is vulnerable to crosslinguistic effects in bilingual environments. Our findings revealed that null/overt pronoun rates and distributions in contact situations between two NSLs are driven by pragmatic and crosslinguistic effects related to the referential properties of pronouns in the two languages (see also Giannakou, 2018).</p> <p>This project examined a particular circumstance of stable bilingualism fostered by social prestige, governmental protection, and minority-language-driven immersion programs in a small bilingual community in the Basque Country. In this particular community, the historical minority language (Basque) is overall well-preserved and prioritized in many aspects of their social, academic, and administrative lives, which is an atypical case in most bilingual environments around the world, including the Basque Country itself. Our results indicate that in such bilingual communities, bilingual children can develop equivalent command of both their native languages (i.e., Basque and Spanish) synchronously, as well as comparable mastery of Spanish as age-matched monolingual children, without showing developmental delays. That is, when bilingual children are educated in immersion programs with minority languages as vehicular instructional languages, the societal majority language is not hindered or hampered. Bilingual children can reach the same developmental patterns synchronously in both their languages and similar to monolingually-raised children when optimal, substantial, and continuous minority language exposure takes place: for both monolingual and bilingual children, sensitivity to the discursive constraints governing same-/switch-reference contexts is fully acquired around age 12/14 in both Spanish and Basque, and anaphora resolution strategies in complex sentences are fully acquired around age 12 in both Spanish and Basque.</p> <p>This bilingual scenario shows that community use and support can act as an efficient addition to education for optimal bilingual child upbringing when the minority language is not spoken at home. For government officials, these findings strengthen the importance of investing in immersion programs, implementing language revitalization measures, and overall expanding bilingual services for citizens. For parents, these findings emphasize the positive outcomes of attending minority language immersion programs during childhood. For community members and activists, these findings confirm that the communal use of the minority language is a powerful source of input that can effectively complement bilingual education, particularly in cases where the minority language is not spoken in the household. The reported findings are particularly influential for other communities fighting for the survival of endangered and minoritized languages, as well as communities trying to preserve and revitalize historical and immigrant minority languages. Minority language education, governmental investment and laws, as well as active societal use are key components to preserve, nourish, and enrich the linguistic heritage of bilingual communities.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/14/2023<br>      Modified by: Eider&nbsp;Etxebarria-Zuluaga</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project examines the bilingual development of children acquiring Basque, a national minority language, and Spanish. Investigating the linguistic development of school-age bilingual children is critical to understanding typical milestones of bilingual language acquisition and to evaluate potential developmental delays in the heritage/minority language. The study of school-age children is essential to document and provide positive empirical evidence of dual language development as well as bilingual programs that primarily teach using minority languages, particularly for the fields of education, educational policy, instruction, and curriculum development.  The socio-political environment and educational programs of the Basque Country are quite unique in the sense that community members and government officials have worked arduously to cultivate positive linguistic attitudes and celebrate bilingualism in this bilingual region. The youngest generations are the fruit of decades of hard work, including the Standardization of Basque, the implementation of public bilingual programs, teacher training, and curriculum development, among other factors. This is an optimal environment for successful dual language development because parental commitment, governmental protection, and social prestige have collectively created a situation of stable bilingualism, which contributed to the Basque educational system being regarded as a global benchmark for bilingual education. This study allowed us to measure the linguistic outcomes of bilingual children's languages, as well as the success of educational programs that teach primarily in Basque.  Specifically, we examined subject pronoun expression (SPE) in Basque and Spanish, two null subject languages (NSL). The production of third-person singular null and overt subject pronouns was tested in Spanish and Basque by 136 Spanish monolingual and Basque-Spanish bilingual children (ages 6, 8, and 12), as well as 60 monolingual and bilingual adults. Our results contribute to theoretical debates on the acquisition of interface phenomena in bilingualism and confirm the importance of academic and societal support of the heritage/minority language for its successful maintenance and transmission. Overall, this project found that SPE in NSLs is prolonged and extremely taxing to acquire, and it is vulnerable to crosslinguistic effects in bilingual environments. Our findings revealed that null/overt pronoun rates and distributions in contact situations between two NSLs are driven by pragmatic and crosslinguistic effects related to the referential properties of pronouns in the two languages (see also Giannakou, 2018).  This project examined a particular circumstance of stable bilingualism fostered by social prestige, governmental protection, and minority-language-driven immersion programs in a small bilingual community in the Basque Country. In this particular community, the historical minority language (Basque) is overall well-preserved and prioritized in many aspects of their social, academic, and administrative lives, which is an atypical case in most bilingual environments around the world, including the Basque Country itself. Our results indicate that in such bilingual communities, bilingual children can develop equivalent command of both their native languages (i.e., Basque and Spanish) synchronously, as well as comparable mastery of Spanish as age-matched monolingual children, without showing developmental delays. That is, when bilingual children are educated in immersion programs with minority languages as vehicular instructional languages, the societal majority language is not hindered or hampered. Bilingual children can reach the same developmental patterns synchronously in both their languages and similar to monolingually-raised children when optimal, substantial, and continuous minority language exposure takes place: for both monolingual and bilingual children, sensitivity to the discursive constraints governing same-/switch-reference contexts is fully acquired around age 12/14 in both Spanish and Basque, and anaphora resolution strategies in complex sentences are fully acquired around age 12 in both Spanish and Basque.  This bilingual scenario shows that community use and support can act as an efficient addition to education for optimal bilingual child upbringing when the minority language is not spoken at home. For government officials, these findings strengthen the importance of investing in immersion programs, implementing language revitalization measures, and overall expanding bilingual services for citizens. For parents, these findings emphasize the positive outcomes of attending minority language immersion programs during childhood. For community members and activists, these findings confirm that the communal use of the minority language is a powerful source of input that can effectively complement bilingual education, particularly in cases where the minority language is not spoken in the household. The reported findings are particularly influential for other communities fighting for the survival of endangered and minoritized languages, as well as communities trying to preserve and revitalize historical and immigrant minority languages. Minority language education, governmental investment and laws, as well as active societal use are key components to preserve, nourish, and enrich the linguistic heritage of bilingual communities.       Last Modified: 09/14/2023       Submitted by: Eider Etxebarria-Zuluaga]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
