<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Doctoral Dissertation Research: Forgive Us Our Debts: Market Expansion, Ethno-Racial Boundaries, and the Democratization of Bankruptcy]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>27650.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>27650</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Reginald Sheehan</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rsheehan@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925389</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Bankruptcy has long been a locus of struggle over whom is morally worthy of an economic rebirth. Early twentieth century America, as a key period of expanding credit markets and the institutionalization of bankruptcy, wrestled with these tensions. In particular, the Bankruptcy Act of 1898 unexpectedly resulted in skyrocketing personal bankruptcy filing rates, which helped to solidify the perception of bankruptcy as a means for the working person’s economic rebirth. Concurrent to this transformation, rising Southern and Eastern European immigration and the African American Great Migration led to a reconfiguration of America’s ethno-racial boundaries, including whom was deserving of credit. While prior research investigates these transformations as independent processes, scholarship has not examined disparities in bankruptcy access and outcomes along socio-economic and ethno-racial lines. By examining the expansion of bankruptcy in conjunction with rising non-Anglo migration, this project will shed light on how Americans delineated whom was worthy of a second chance through bankruptcy. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project investigates the transformation in the practice and discursive boundaries of deservingness in bankruptcy in America from 1880 to 1940. Drawing from rarely utilized bankruptcy records, in conjunction with census records, this research will quantitatively examine variation in bankruptcy practice, along the axes of ethnicity and race, socio-economic status, and state credit policy. This project will also engage in qualitative and quantitative discourse analyses of how social actors conceived of bankruptcy. Specifically, this dissertation’s aims are fourfold: to understand how state-level credit policy regimes affected why individuals filed for bankruptcy; to analyze how the socio-economic status and ethno-racial backgrounds of bankrupts changed over time; to examine how recovery from bankruptcy varied by socio-economic status and ethno-racial background; and to probe how these changes in the practice of bankruptcy relates to changing moral conceptions of credit, debt, and bankruptcy in American society. This study has the potential to advance social scientific understanding of how market expansion can coexist with the institutionalization of ethno-racial boundaries of worth.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/05/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/11/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2017548</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Shamus</FirstName>
<LastName>Khan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Shamus R Khan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[sk2905@columbia.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000537811</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/05/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate>12/11/2020</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Joshua</FirstName>
<LastName>Whitford</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Joshua D Whitford</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jw2212@columbia.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000542272</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/11/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nicholas</FirstName>
<LastName>Pang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nicholas A Pang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[nap2155@columbia.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000811081</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/05/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Columbia University</Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<ZipCode>10027</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2128546851</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>202 LOW LIBRARY 535 W 116 ST MC</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>F4N1QNPB95M4</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF COLUMBIA UNIVERSITY IN THE CITY OF NEW YORK, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>F4N1QNPB95M4</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Columbia University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>100275703</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>128Y</Code>
<Text>Law &amp; Science</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~27650</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This doctoral dissertation research improvement grant examined the social construction of American federal bankruptcy law from the Gilded Age to the post-World War II Era. Across the nineteenth century, federal legislators vociferously debated whether a federal bankruptcy statute would facilitate the extension of business credit across state lines or be employed by creditors to oppress small traders, farmers, and wage earners. After the law&rsquo;s enactment in 1898, however, this debate largely disappeared. By the period following the Second World War, bankruptcy was an accepted means for working class debtors to obtain debt relief, either immediately or after paying their creditors out of their future wages. This project explores the factors associated with this shift. How did bankruptcy become an accepted part of the American political economy and welfare state?</p> <p>To answer this question, the PI and co-PI examined new samples of census-linked bankruptcy petitions in comparison with survey data on working class debtors, a corpus of Congressional speech and media, and archival data on relevant policy actors. Social reformers&rsquo; efforts to create &ldquo;fair&rdquo; credit markets through Small Loan Laws (SLL), alongside rising bankruptcy rates, ultimately naturalized a conception of bankruptcy as morally &ldquo;caused&rdquo; by debtors, apart from creditor choices or malfeasance. As SLLs reduced real interest rates, they also led lenders to collateralize their relative risks through extending credit in states where it was legal to garnish debtors&rsquo; wages. In doing so, SLLs inadvertently spurred credit extension based on wages rather than property. The conception that debtors &ldquo;caused&rdquo; bankruptcy, in turn, led Great Depression Era legislators to focus on delineating who was &ldquo;deserving&rdquo; of bankruptcy protections and how insolvent individuals could prove their future &ldquo;creditworthiness&rdquo; and reenter financial markets. The 1938 Bankruptcy Act established a voluntary wage-earner payment system (Chapter XIII) for &ldquo;deserving&rdquo; white men while also formalizing provisions for immediate debt discharge (Chapter VII). Yet when few wage earners decided to honorably pay their debts over time, judicial actors in post-World War II America employed Chapter XIII bankruptcy as a debt collection system that reduced lenders&rsquo; risks against &ldquo;undeserving&rdquo; bankrupts. As Black people increasingly sought debt relief through bankruptcy protections, they were directed to Chapter XIII, irrespective of their economic interests. These payment plans increased the time and money that Black bankrupts needed to pay in order to regain their economic citizenship.</p> <p>In terms of intellectual merit, this research contributes to political and cultural understandings of social welfare. Whereas past studies on the emergence of personal bankruptcy law in the United States elaborates interest group and market expansion explanations, this study additionally uncovers how cultural conceptions of bankruptcy as a form of social welfare influenced the institutionalization of the law, as well as subsequent reforms during the Great Depression. Additionally, I incorporate insights from contemporary scholarship on credit markets to show how easy debt collection through the garnishment process was instrumental to the expansion of personal credit markets. High levels of credit extension, rather than strategic filings by debtors, can produce increases in personal bankruptcies. Finally, as part of this grant, the PI and co-PI constructed one of the first systematic datasets of bankruptcy petitions in the early twentieth century. It is temporally and geographically aligned with the only systematic survey of American personal debtors during this time period (Bureau of Labor Statistics Cost of Living Survey, 1918-1919).</p> <p>In terms of broader impacts, this project contributes to debates about bankruptcy in relation to American credit and welfare policy. It suggests that efforts to create fair credit markets (e.g., Equal Credit Opportunity Act, Consumer Financial Protection Bureau) have the potential to obscure the role of creditors in joint economic failures, like insolvency and bankruptcy. Therefore, in addition to constructing &ldquo;fair&rdquo; credit markets, policymakers can consider how to help Americans provide for themselves apart from markets. Additionally, it builds on past scholarship to underline how Chapter XIII&amp;;swage-earner payment system produces racially inequitable levels of debt relief through bankruptcy. American policymakers could explore how to reduce the role of judicial discretion as they consider potential reforms to the federal bankruptcy law.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/04/2023<br>      Modified by: Nicholas&nbsp;A&nbsp;Pang</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This doctoral dissertation research improvement grant examined the social construction of American federal bankruptcy law from the Gilded Age to the post-World War II Era. Across the nineteenth century, federal legislators vociferously debated whether a federal bankruptcy statute would facilitate the extension of business credit across state lines or be employed by creditors to oppress small traders, farmers, and wage earners. After the law’s enactment in 1898, however, this debate largely disappeared. By the period following the Second World War, bankruptcy was an accepted means for working class debtors to obtain debt relief, either immediately or after paying their creditors out of their future wages. This project explores the factors associated with this shift. How did bankruptcy become an accepted part of the American political economy and welfare state?  To answer this question, the PI and co-PI examined new samples of census-linked bankruptcy petitions in comparison with survey data on working class debtors, a corpus of Congressional speech and media, and archival data on relevant policy actors. Social reformers’ efforts to create "fair" credit markets through Small Loan Laws (SLL), alongside rising bankruptcy rates, ultimately naturalized a conception of bankruptcy as morally "caused" by debtors, apart from creditor choices or malfeasance. As SLLs reduced real interest rates, they also led lenders to collateralize their relative risks through extending credit in states where it was legal to garnish debtors’ wages. In doing so, SLLs inadvertently spurred credit extension based on wages rather than property. The conception that debtors "caused" bankruptcy, in turn, led Great Depression Era legislators to focus on delineating who was "deserving" of bankruptcy protections and how insolvent individuals could prove their future "creditworthiness" and reenter financial markets. The 1938 Bankruptcy Act established a voluntary wage-earner payment system (Chapter XIII) for "deserving" white men while also formalizing provisions for immediate debt discharge (Chapter VII). Yet when few wage earners decided to honorably pay their debts over time, judicial actors in post-World War II America employed Chapter XIII bankruptcy as a debt collection system that reduced lenders’ risks against "undeserving" bankrupts. As Black people increasingly sought debt relief through bankruptcy protections, they were directed to Chapter XIII, irrespective of their economic interests. These payment plans increased the time and money that Black bankrupts needed to pay in order to regain their economic citizenship.  In terms of intellectual merit, this research contributes to political and cultural understandings of social welfare. Whereas past studies on the emergence of personal bankruptcy law in the United States elaborates interest group and market expansion explanations, this study additionally uncovers how cultural conceptions of bankruptcy as a form of social welfare influenced the institutionalization of the law, as well as subsequent reforms during the Great Depression. Additionally, I incorporate insights from contemporary scholarship on credit markets to show how easy debt collection through the garnishment process was instrumental to the expansion of personal credit markets. High levels of credit extension, rather than strategic filings by debtors, can produce increases in personal bankruptcies. Finally, as part of this grant, the PI and co-PI constructed one of the first systematic datasets of bankruptcy petitions in the early twentieth century. It is temporally and geographically aligned with the only systematic survey of American personal debtors during this time period (Bureau of Labor Statistics Cost of Living Survey, 1918-1919).  In terms of broader impacts, this project contributes to debates about bankruptcy in relation to American credit and welfare policy. It suggests that efforts to create fair credit markets (e.g., Equal Credit Opportunity Act, Consumer Financial Protection Bureau) have the potential to obscure the role of creditors in joint economic failures, like insolvency and bankruptcy. Therefore, in addition to constructing "fair" credit markets, policymakers can consider how to help Americans provide for themselves apart from markets. Additionally, it builds on past scholarship to underline how Chapter XIII&amp;;swage-earner payment system produces racially inequitable levels of debt relief through bankruptcy. American policymakers could explore how to reduce the role of judicial discretion as they consider potential reforms to the federal bankruptcy law.       Last Modified: 10/04/2023       Submitted by: Nicholas A Pang]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
