<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[MRI: Acquisition of a High Pressure and Temperature True Triaxial Testing Equipment with a Multiphase Fluid Flow System]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>794593.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>794593</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Harsha Chelliah</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>hchellia@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927281</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The demand for better underground civil infrastructure requires an improved basic understanding of the complex behaviors of man-made or natural materials such as bedrocks. This MRI award supports the acquisition of a true triaxial testing equipment with the capability to simulate high pressure and temperature, three-dimensional stresses, and multiphase fluid flow conditions. Valuable experimental data will be generated to improve our understanding of coupled thermo-hydro-mechanical-chemical-biological (THMCB) interactions of these materials. The scientific knowledge gained will 1) improve the reliability of our civil infrastructure, 2) reduce risks and economic losses during subsurface exploration, 3) ensure a safe and permanent storage for pollutants, and 4) improve extraction of drinking water, hydrocarbons, and alternative energy sources. This project also will train future scientists and engineers as well as broadening the participation of women, underrepresented minorities, and persons with disabilities in STEM fields. Some educational activities will be pursued as part of this project, including the incorporation of equipment testing into existing undergraduate and graduate courses, Wyoming State Science Fair exhibits, and Engineering Summer Program classes. Other activities include establishment of an educational website, an outreach program for Wyoming School Districts, and annual workshops.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project aims to advance our understanding of the fundamental aspects of THMCB processes in solid and porous media. Acquisition of the instrument will provide the unique ability to reproduce most in-situ subsurface conditions or extreme conditions that are unattainable through conventional instruments. The equipment can apply three independent principal stresses, heat multiple pore fluids at the same temperature of a test specimen, and perform coupled process measurements over complex loading trajectories. The project will advance fundamental research on rock mechanics, materials science, geophysics, biological engineering, environmental engineering and sustainability, hydrologic science, transport phenomena, and THMCB processes. The project will 1) reveal the physics behind the complex failure mechanism of materials, 2) quantify three-dimensional material strengths, 3) determine the impact of chemical and biological processes on permeability, 4) develop new numerical techniques to study groundwater flows, 5) improve interpretation of geophysical data, and 6) advance multiphysics computational models for simulating coupled THMCB processes of porous materials. The project will promote regional and national research collaborations from universities, government agencies, research institutions and private companies to tackle critical issues like global warming, energy independence, water resource demands, and natural hazards.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is jointly funded by CBET-MRI Program and the Established Program to Stimulate Competitive Research (EPSCoR) Program.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/24/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/07/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2017874</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Vladimir</FirstName>
<LastName>Alvarado</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Vladimir Alvarado</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[valvarad@uwyo.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000516006</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/24/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dario</FirstName>
<LastName>Grana</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Dario Grana</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[dgrana@uwyo.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000654740</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/24/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kam</FirstName>
<LastName>Ng</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kam Ng</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[kng1@uwyo.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000690428</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/24/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Pejman</FirstName>
<LastName>Tahmasebi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Pejman Tahmasebi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[tahmasebi@mines.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000740622</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/24/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Wyoming</Name>
<CityName>LARAMIE</CityName>
<ZipCode>820712000</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3077665320</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1000 E UNIVERSITY AVE DEPARTMENT</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wyoming</StateName>
<StateCode>WY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WY00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>FDR5YF2K32X5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF WYOMING</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>FDR5YF2K32X5</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Wyoming]]></Name>
<CityName>Laramie</CityName>
<StateCode>WY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>820712000</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1000 E University Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wyoming</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WY00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>Major Research Instrumentation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EPSCoR Co-Funding</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~794593</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The high pressure and high temperature true triaxial (polyaxial) equipment with a multiphase flow system was installed in the Engineering Building at the University of Wyoming. Both off-site and on-site trainings were conducted by the vendor. The equipment has been successfully operated and run by trained students. The equipment has been used to study the effect of CO2, H2, stresses, temperature and treatments on rock behaviors in terms of mechanical properties and flow characteristics. Experimental results have been generated from this equipment. Some results have been presented in conferences and all experimental data will be disseminated in near future publications. This equipment has enabled researchers to successfully receive several research fundings to further improve the understanding of rock behaviors related to energy and civil infrastructure. In addition, this equipment has led to the additional support to purchase a high pressure and high temperature vessel for treatment of materials. This equipment is not only used to study rock behaviors but also can be used by researchers to study the behaviors of other materials, such as concrete and ceramics. Graduate students have been formally trained by the vendor on using this equipment. A new graduate course (rock mechanics and rock engineering) has been created and taught in Spring 2022 and will be taught biennially to train more students on understanding the testing capabilities of this equipment and experimental results. Equipment webpage at the University of Wyoming and videos have been developed to disseminate the application and features of this equipment to general public. This equipment has been demonstrated to a group of middle school female students in a workshop co-organized by the University of Wyoming Society of Women Engineers. Furthermore, lectures and hands-on operation of this equipment have been provided to high school students who attended the 2022 Summer Engineering Program at the University of Wyoming. The knowledge gained from this equipment will be useful for many applications and societal impacts. The outcomes will provide a safe storage for CO2 from emitting to our atmosphere, secure future energy resources, facilitate the development of more durable and advanced materials, increase the sustainability of our civil infrastructure, and increase the competitiveness of our economy.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/05/2023<br>      Modified by: Kam&nbsp;Ng</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The high pressure and high temperature true triaxial (polyaxial) equipment with a multiphase flow system was installed in the Engineering Building at the University of Wyoming. Both off-site and on-site trainings were conducted by the vendor. The equipment has been successfully operated and run by trained students. The equipment has been used to study the effect of CO2, H2, stresses, temperature and treatments on rock behaviors in terms of mechanical properties and flow characteristics. Experimental results have been generated from this equipment. Some results have been presented in conferences and all experimental data will be disseminated in near future publications. This equipment has enabled researchers to successfully receive several research fundings to further improve the understanding of rock behaviors related to energy and civil infrastructure. In addition, this equipment has led to the additional support to purchase a high pressure and high temperature vessel for treatment of materials. This equipment is not only used to study rock behaviors but also can be used by researchers to study the behaviors of other materials, such as concrete and ceramics. Graduate students have been formally trained by the vendor on using this equipment. A new graduate course (rock mechanics and rock engineering) has been created and taught in Spring 2022 and will be taught biennially to train more students on understanding the testing capabilities of this equipment and experimental results. Equipment webpage at the University of Wyoming and videos have been developed to disseminate the application and features of this equipment to general public. This equipment has been demonstrated to a group of middle school female students in a workshop co-organized by the University of Wyoming Society of Women Engineers. Furthermore, lectures and hands-on operation of this equipment have been provided to high school students who attended the 2022 Summer Engineering Program at the University of Wyoming. The knowledge gained from this equipment will be useful for many applications and societal impacts. The outcomes will provide a safe storage for CO2 from emitting to our atmosphere, secure future energy resources, facilitate the development of more durable and advanced materials, increase the sustainability of our civil infrastructure, and increase the competitiveness of our economy.       Last Modified: 09/05/2023       Submitted by: Kam Ng]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
