<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Assessing the Impact of Texas Science, Technology, Engineering, and Mathematics Academies on Students' Learning Environments, Educational Outcomes, and Career Path Decisions]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>200562.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>200562</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DGE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Graduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Earnestine Psalmonds</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Maintaining U.S. global competitiveness in science, technology, engineering, and math (STEM) industries requires increasing participation among traditionally underrepresented groups including people of color and women. Studies show creating more equal educational opportunities in the K-12 education system is an effective, socially just approach to expanding STEM participation. This study examines the impact of Texas Science, Technology, Engineering, and Math (T-STEM) academies on (a) STEM teacher labor markets and (b) students' educational and workforce outcomes. T-STEM academies are public high schools focused on improving instruction and academic performance in science and mathematics-related subjects and expanding the number of students entering STEM careers, particularly students who are underrepresented in STEM fields. Analyses draw on a statewide longitudinal student-level dataset covering all students in Texas over a 20-year period. This project is supported by the Education and Human Resources Core Research Program, which funds fundamental research in STEM learning and learning environments, broadening participation in STEM, and STEM workforce development.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project objectives are three-fold. First, the study documents whether students traditionally underrepresented in STEM fields have equitable access to high-quality STEM teachers across classrooms, schools, and districts. Although prior studies identify a teacher quality gap where disadvantaged students are assigned to less qualified and less effective teachers, no prior studies explore exposure to highly-qualified STEM teachers for advantaged and disadvantaged youth. Second, the study analyzes whether T-STEM academies reduce the STEM teacher quality gap. The third aim of the study is to assess the impact of T-STEM academies on student achievement in math, science, and reading, the likelihood of high school graduation, postsecondary enrollment and completion, as well as students' labor market earnings and the likelihood of employment in a STEM field.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/26/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/29/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2017950</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Knight</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David S Knight</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[dsknight@uw.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000730639</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/26/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Washington</Name>
<CityName>SEATTLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>981951016</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2065434043</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4333 BROOKLYN AVE NE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>HD1WMN6945W6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF WASHINGTON</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Washington]]></Name>
<CityName>Seattle</CityName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>981950001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4333 Brooklyn Ave NE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7980</Code>
<Text>ECR-EDU Core Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1544</Code>
<Text>GSE: Research on Gender in S&amp;E</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8212</Code>
<Text>Broaden Particip STEM Resrch</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8816</Code>
<Text>Workforce Development</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0417</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04001718DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~200562</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>The project was successful in accomplishing the proposed objectives. The first set of research studies explored the extent to which students underrepresented in science, technology, engineering, and math (STEM) fields have equitable access to high-quality STEM teachers across classrooms, schools, and districts. Findings indicated that the most experienced and qualified math and science teachers disproportionately work in school districts enrolling greater shares of economically advantaged students. Even within school districts, results showed that low-income students and students of color were less likely than their more advantaged peers to be assigned to a math or science classroom with an experienced educator.</span></p> <p><span>In a second set of studies, project leaders found that Texas STEM Academies help reduce disparities in access to well-qualified STEM teachers. One study found that these high schools recruited teachers with stronger qualifications, on average, while simultaneously enrolling a greater percentage of low-income students and students who identify as Black, Indigenous, Latinx, or another underrepresented racial/ethnic group. Another study showed Texas STEM Academies have slightly lower teacher turnover rates compared to similar high schools in the same district or county. Many Texas STEM Academies are charter schools, where teacher attrition is especially high. Results thus suggest that charter schools can potentially leverage the Texas STEM Academy model to improve learning environments through reductions in educator turnover.</span></p> <p><span>The third set of studies examines the impact of Texas STEM Academies on student outcomes. Several manuscripts are in analysis and development stages. Findings from these studies show Texas STEM Academies hold promise for improving students&rsquo; postsecondary and labor market outcomes; however, additional supports may be needed for students who are less prepared for college or who have had fewer opportunities to engage with rigorous academic curriculum.</span></p> <p><span>These studies are published in top-tiered academic journals from the fields of education and public policy. To further disseminate these results, researchers held informational meetings with state education agency leaders, created summary documents and policy briefs, and posted these resources to project websites and on social media. The project supported graduate students in quantitative education policy research and facilitated the creation of statistical programs and broader research infrastructure across multiple institutions of higher education.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/31/2022<br>      Modified by: David&nbsp;S&nbsp;Knight</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The project was successful in accomplishing the proposed objectives. The first set of research studies explored the extent to which students underrepresented in science, technology, engineering, and math (STEM) fields have equitable access to high-quality STEM teachers across classrooms, schools, and districts. Findings indicated that the most experienced and qualified math and science teachers disproportionately work in school districts enrolling greater shares of economically advantaged students. Even within school districts, results showed that low-income students and students of color were less likely than their more advantaged peers to be assigned to a math or science classroom with an experienced educator.  In a second set of studies, project leaders found that Texas STEM Academies help reduce disparities in access to well-qualified STEM teachers. One study found that these high schools recruited teachers with stronger qualifications, on average, while simultaneously enrolling a greater percentage of low-income students and students who identify as Black, Indigenous, Latinx, or another underrepresented racial/ethnic group. Another study showed Texas STEM Academies have slightly lower teacher turnover rates compared to similar high schools in the same district or county. Many Texas STEM Academies are charter schools, where teacher attrition is especially high. Results thus suggest that charter schools can potentially leverage the Texas STEM Academy model to improve learning environments through reductions in educator turnover.  The third set of studies examines the impact of Texas STEM Academies on student outcomes. Several manuscripts are in analysis and development stages. Findings from these studies show Texas STEM Academies hold promise for improving students’ postsecondary and labor market outcomes; however, additional supports may be needed for students who are less prepared for college or who have had fewer opportunities to engage with rigorous academic curriculum.  These studies are published in top-tiered academic journals from the fields of education and public policy. To further disseminate these results, researchers held informational meetings with state education agency leaders, created summary documents and policy briefs, and posted these resources to project websites and on social media. The project supported graduate students in quantitative education policy research and facilitated the creation of statistical programs and broader research infrastructure across multiple institutions of higher education.          Last Modified: 05/31/2022       Submitted by: David S Knight]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
