<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Travel Funds for 15th Dynamic Walking Conference; Hawley, Pennsylvania; May 11-14, 2020]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>10000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>10000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Eva Kanso</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ekanso@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032920000</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This grant supports the next generation of researchers in dynamic systems, robotics and control by providing funding for graduate students, post-doctoral fellows and junior faculty to travel to the Dynamic Walking Conference being held in May 2020. The aim of Dynamic Walking Conference is to provide insight into the fundamental principles that underlie legged locomotion and the dynamics of movement, both mechanical and biological. Critical, and overlapping, areas of interest are the design and control of autonomous walking robots, rehabilitation of humans and animals, and the design and control of prosthetic and exoskeletal devices. This annual conference includes a broad and growing community of roboticists and biomechanists. It encourages new and breaking results and aims to provide a forum for discussion and sharing of new ideas. This grant will be used to broaden participation from groups that are traditionally underrepresented in major robotics and biomechanics conferences, particularly from women, underrepresented minorities, and researchers from universities which do not typically have the funding to travel to these events.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This grant is specifically focused on broadening participation and greater inclusivity at the Dynamic Walking 2020 conference. Dynamic Walking is a single-track conference that focuses on all things related to walking and running of humans, animals, and robots. This including modeling system energetics, stability, and control; developing predictive principles and dynamic models; clinical evaluation and gait recovery for healthy and stroke, amputee, osteoarthritic, or other limited-mobility patients; analyzing empirical data in a conceptual framework; as well as design and evaluation of robots, prosthetics, and exoskeletons. Topics central to dynamic walking include energetics, stability and control, predictive principles and models, dynamic modeling, empirical data in a conceptual framework, and robot successes and failures. Participants include both academics and industry designers with a mixture of researchers studying human and animal legged locomotion and those designing and controlling walking robots. One goal of Dynamic walking is to bring together researchers from different fields, especially biomechanists and roboticists. Despite sharing a common interest in walking, these two groups typically lack a shared vocabulary and set of tools. As a result, a central focus for the conference is bridging these two disciplines and, ultimately, breaking down barriers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/02/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/23/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2017660</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Posa</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael Posa</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[posa@seas.upenn.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000754896</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/02/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Pennsylvania</Name>
<CityName>PHILADELPHIA</CityName>
<ZipCode>191046205</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2158987293</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3451 WALNUT ST STE 440A</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>GM1XX56LEP58</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF THE UNIVERSITY OF PENNSYLVANIA, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>GM1XX56LEP58</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Pennsylvania]]></Name>
<CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>191046202</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[220 S 33rd Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7569</Code>
<Text>Dynamics, Control and System D</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>030E</Code>
<Text>CONTROL SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>034E</Code>
<Text>Dynamical systems</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8024</Code>
<Text>Complex Systems</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~10000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>The aim of Dynamic Walking is to provide insight into the fundamental principles that underlie legged locomotion and the dynamics of movement, both mechanical and biological. Critical, and overlapping, areas of interest are the design and control of autonomous walking robots, rehabilitation of humans and animals, and the design and control of prosthetic and exoskeletal devices. Held annually since 2006, this independent conference has grown from a small meeting among a few colleagues to include a broad and growing community of roboticists and biomechanists.</span></p> <p><span>In contrast with most robotics conferences, Dynamic Walking does not publish its proceedings; as a result, the conference encourages new and breaking results, and aims to provide a forum for discussion and sharing of new ideas. People attend Dynamic Walking so that they can critically evaluate and share research with others in the field, not because they want to publish a paper. This emphasis on scientific discourse and discussion is the hallmark of Dynamic Walking, with a high rate of repeat attendance. Furthermore, the egalitarian nature of the informal discussions provides a unique opportunity for students to interact with (and challenge) their peers, and senior faculty members including pioneers of the field.</span></p> <p><span>However, the relatively small size of the event (recently, 150-200 attendees) and the emphasis on lively discourse has, despite best efforts, created an air of exclusivity where some, often young and first-time attendees, feel reluctant to speak out. Recent years have emphasized broadening the discourse and creating an environment that ensures all voices, especially those of doctoral students, are heard and feel welcomed. Through this National Science Foundation grant, we sought out new attendees from diverse underrepresented backgrounds and enabled ten students and postdoctoral scholars to attend the conference with zero or minimal out of pocket expenses.</span></p> <p><span>This project specifically worked to broaden participation from groups that are traditionally underrepresented in elite robotics and biomechanics conferences, particularly from women, underrepresented minorities, and researchers from universities which do not typically have the funding to travel to these events.</span></p> <p><span>Originally, these funds were intended to support attendance in May of 2020. As a result of the COVID-19 pandemic, the conference was delayed until 2022. With the return of in-person events, ten travel grants were successfully awarded for Dynamic Walking 2022, held in Madison, Wisconsin. Overall, the project was a successful, albeit small-scale, effort at broadening participation.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/17/2023<br>      Modified by: Michael&nbsp;Posa</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The aim of Dynamic Walking is to provide insight into the fundamental principles that underlie legged locomotion and the dynamics of movement, both mechanical and biological. Critical, and overlapping, areas of interest are the design and control of autonomous walking robots, rehabilitation of humans and animals, and the design and control of prosthetic and exoskeletal devices. Held annually since 2006, this independent conference has grown from a small meeting among a few colleagues to include a broad and growing community of roboticists and biomechanists.  In contrast with most robotics conferences, Dynamic Walking does not publish its proceedings; as a result, the conference encourages new and breaking results, and aims to provide a forum for discussion and sharing of new ideas. People attend Dynamic Walking so that they can critically evaluate and share research with others in the field, not because they want to publish a paper. This emphasis on scientific discourse and discussion is the hallmark of Dynamic Walking, with a high rate of repeat attendance. Furthermore, the egalitarian nature of the informal discussions provides a unique opportunity for students to interact with (and challenge) their peers, and senior faculty members including pioneers of the field.  However, the relatively small size of the event (recently, 150-200 attendees) and the emphasis on lively discourse has, despite best efforts, created an air of exclusivity where some, often young and first-time attendees, feel reluctant to speak out. Recent years have emphasized broadening the discourse and creating an environment that ensures all voices, especially those of doctoral students, are heard and feel welcomed. Through this National Science Foundation grant, we sought out new attendees from diverse underrepresented backgrounds and enabled ten students and postdoctoral scholars to attend the conference with zero or minimal out of pocket expenses.  This project specifically worked to broaden participation from groups that are traditionally underrepresented in elite robotics and biomechanics conferences, particularly from women, underrepresented minorities, and researchers from universities which do not typically have the funding to travel to these events.  Originally, these funds were intended to support attendance in May of 2020. As a result of the COVID-19 pandemic, the conference was delayed until 2022. With the return of in-person events, ten travel grants were successfully awarded for Dynamic Walking 2022, held in Madison, Wisconsin. Overall, the project was a successful, albeit small-scale, effort at broadening participation.          Last Modified: 07/17/2023       Submitted by: Michael Posa]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
