<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[EAGER: Hybridization and metabolic dysfunction in milkweeds]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>231538.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>231538</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Samuel Scheiner</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sscheine@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927175</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This research aims to understand how biochemical processes and pathways in the cell are disrupted when mating occurs across species. Two milkweed species, the common milkweed and the showy milkweed, form hybrids across a wide region of the central United States. The research will determine the extent of natural hybridization between these species and identify the cellular pathways that differ between species. This information will allow identification of cellular pathways that are disrupted when hybridization occurs. This work will shed light on both the organization of biochemical pathways and the mechanisms that keep species reproductively isolated. Understanding the effects of hybridization will become increasingly important as climate change and human disturbance cause species ranges to shift and bring previously isolated species into contact. The results of the project will be integrated into undergraduate courses to strengthen bioinformatics and introductory biology courses with a focus on quantitative reasoning, modeling, and simulations.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research addresses a fundamental gap in our understanding of metabolic pathways and how the metabolome changes during speciation. When species evolve in isolation and come back into contact, the hybrids they form often display variation outside of the parental means (transgressive segregation). By studying natural and hand-pollinated hybrids along with the parental species, the researchers will uncover the changes to the genetic architecture that occur as species diverge. The researchers will use (1) genotype-by-sequencing to reconstruct the history of hybridization across the region of sympatry and (2) a comprehensive global metabolomics study to identify how pathways are disrupted following hybridization. These data will identify where pathway changes are likely to accumulate and identify new metabolites of interest. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is jointly funded by the Evolutionary Processes Cluster in the Division of Environmental Biology and the Established Program to Stimulate Competitive Research (EPSCoR).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/20/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/20/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2017485</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Carrie</FirstName>
<LastName>Olson-Manning</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>F</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Carrie F Olson-Manning</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[colsonmanning@augie.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000801003</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/20/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Augustana University Association</Name>
<CityName>SIOUX FALLS</CityName>
<ZipCode>571970001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6052744090</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2001 S SUMMIT AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>South Dakota</StateName>
<StateCode>SD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>SD00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>W6YZCPTMFSD5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>AUGUSTANA UNIVERSITY ASSOCIATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Augustana College]]></Name>
<CityName>Sioux Falls</CityName>
<StateCode>SD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>571970002</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2001 S Summit Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>South Dakota</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>SD00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1127</Code>
<Text>Evolutionary Processes</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EPSCoR Co-Funding</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~231538</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-acddb88d-7fff-e5df-186b-78f28677c0c2"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Intellectual Merit</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>When two separate species meet, they can sometimes form hybrids, mixing the genetic material and creating a new organism with a combination of traits from both parental species.In this project, we studied the adaptations that allow the parents to survive in very different environments (dry western and humid eastern North America) and how the parental traits presented themselves in the hybrids.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Our results include a novel finding that when faced with stress, the parental species produce different sets of chemical compounds that allow them to cope with stressful environments. The hybrids display a wide-range of the stress-response chemicals produced by the parent species, but often they do so in a way that is insensitive to changes in the environment. This suggests that hybrids may not correctly respond to environmental signals, possibly making them less fit than their parent species.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>With garden experiments, we found that each parent is best-suited to its home environment and that the hybrids are generally not well suited to the parental environments. However, the hybrids survive well in the intermediate environment between the parental species environments and we know from previous experiments that the hybrids can form offspring with the parental species. This provides the opportunity for gene flow between these species, potentially introducing genetic variation that could allow each parental species to better adapt to their home environment.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Broader Impacts</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Understanding the consequences of hybridization will allow us to understand the impacts of climate change and invasive species. Although hybrids can sometimes provide novel genetic variation allowing the parental species to adapt to new environments, it also has the possibility to cause problems, interfering with reproduction or creating traits that are not advantageous in any environment. Opportunities for hybridization may become more common as climates change, possibly bringing previously isolated species into contact.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The work on this project provided training opportunities to a post-baccalaureate scientist and over a dozen undergraduate students. In addition to contributing to the scientific literature, the data collected was analyzed by undergraduates in a Bioinformatics course, teaching them about gene expression and metabolome analyses. The gardens are situated at public outdoor spaces, providing many opportunities for the researchers to interact with the general public and educate about how to protect and grow milkweeds, the host plant of the monarch butterfly.&nbsp;</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/09/2022<br>      Modified by: Carrie&nbsp;F&nbsp;Olson-Manning</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   Intellectual Merit When two separate species meet, they can sometimes form hybrids, mixing the genetic material and creating a new organism with a combination of traits from both parental species.In this project, we studied the adaptations that allow the parents to survive in very different environments (dry western and humid eastern North America) and how the parental traits presented themselves in the hybrids. Our results include a novel finding that when faced with stress, the parental species produce different sets of chemical compounds that allow them to cope with stressful environments. The hybrids display a wide-range of the stress-response chemicals produced by the parent species, but often they do so in a way that is insensitive to changes in the environment. This suggests that hybrids may not correctly respond to environmental signals, possibly making them less fit than their parent species. With garden experiments, we found that each parent is best-suited to its home environment and that the hybrids are generally not well suited to the parental environments. However, the hybrids survive well in the intermediate environment between the parental species environments and we know from previous experiments that the hybrids can form offspring with the parental species. This provides the opportunity for gene flow between these species, potentially introducing genetic variation that could allow each parental species to better adapt to their home environment.  Broader Impacts Understanding the consequences of hybridization will allow us to understand the impacts of climate change and invasive species. Although hybrids can sometimes provide novel genetic variation allowing the parental species to adapt to new environments, it also has the possibility to cause problems, interfering with reproduction or creating traits that are not advantageous in any environment. Opportunities for hybridization may become more common as climates change, possibly bringing previously isolated species into contact.  The work on this project provided training opportunities to a post-baccalaureate scientist and over a dozen undergraduate students. In addition to contributing to the scientific literature, the data collected was analyzed by undergraduates in a Bioinformatics course, teaching them about gene expression and metabolome analyses. The gardens are situated at public outdoor spaces, providing many opportunities for the researchers to interact with the general public and educate about how to protect and grow milkweeds, the host plant of the monarch butterfly.                 Last Modified: 12/09/2022       Submitted by: Carrie F Olson-Manning]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
