<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research: Development of a high-efficiency mass spectrometer: transitioning a high-efficiency ion source to a modern mass spectrometer]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>46019.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>46019</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Russell Kelz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rkelz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924747</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This EAR Instrumentation and Facilities Program award (a collaborative between Penn State and Carnegie Institution of Washington) will support the installation and testing of a newly developed, high-ionization-efficiency cavity ionization source on a modern multi-collector mass spectrometer, the Thermo-Fisher Triton.  The ion source development was supported previously by the EAR/IF Program (EAR-1758571).  If successful, the source augmented mass spectrometer promised significantly enhanced analytical precision for isotope ratio analysis with the potential for future transformative scientific advances in our understanding of the early evolution of Earth and planetary reservoirs (e.g., crust, mantle and core differentiation).  The project involves an early career researcher and will result in construction and operation of a fundamentally new type of mass spectrometer, which if successful, has potential for commercialization and broader community use.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The ultimate precision of mass spectrometry-based isotopic analyses is limited, in large part, by detector counting statistics.  The cavity ion source may present a major step forward in the ability to produce large ion beams from geologic samples and may make it able to achieve isotope-ratio precisions currently unattainable with modern thermal ionization mass spectrometers (TIMS).  Support will provide for installation of the developed ion source onto an existing Thermo-Fisher Triton TIMS and subsequent analytical testing.  The investigators have preliminary demonstrations that the source produces: 1) large, stable ion beams for long periods of time, and 2) higher ionization efficiency than traditional flat-filament thermal ionization sources for select elements. The source-enhanced instrument has significant potential to advance research on fundamental questions in the geosciences, from radiometric dating to tracing first-order chemical processes that formed and modify various reservoirs on Earth and other planets, by providing large increases in the analytical precision achievable for targeted radiogenic isotope ratio determinations  (e.g., Sm/Nd system for understanding the earliest history of Earth and the Solar System), that in allows for analysis of smaller rare samples than currently possible.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/06/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/06/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2017252</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jesse</FirstName>
<LastName>Reimink</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jesse Reimink</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jreimink@psu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000756255</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/06/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Pennsylvania State Univ University Park</Name>
<CityName>UNIVERSITY PARK</CityName>
<ZipCode>168021503</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8148651372</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>201 OLD MAIN</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>15</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA15</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NPM2J7MSCF61</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>THE PENNSYLVANIA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[The Pennsylvania State University]]></Name>
<CityName>University Park</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>168027000</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[411 Deike Building]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT/>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA"</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1580</Code>
<Text>Instrumentation &amp; Facilities</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1580</Code>
<Text>INSTRUMENTATION &amp; FACILITIES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~46019</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project designed and tested a new method of creating ions that may help produce much more precise data than can traditionally accomplished. In this project, we designed and built a modified cavity ion source that encloses a sample into a hot cavity that produces ion to then be separated by a mass spectrometer. We installed this modified cavity source on a commercially built mass spectrometer with the goal of testing the utility of such sources in commercial instruments. Our preliminary designs performed well but did not show reproduciblely better data than can be accomplished with traditional methods. The inability to reproduce our results regulalry may be due to inconsistencies in sample loading, or problems encountered in maintaining electrical voltages during high temperature operation. Another goal of the project was to test the style of mass fractionation that occurs within all mass spectrometers. Mass fractionation is the process by which the measured isotopic ratio changes during a run, due to various physical processes that occur during ionization processes. During this project, we established that mass fractionation in the cavity ion source occurs according to exponential law, which is identical to that which occurs in traditional methods. This result shows that cavity ion sources have future potential for routine analysis of unknown samples at high precisions. Further work needs to be done to achieve routine analyses that are clearly better than traditional methods. Our work was presented at an international conference and a peer-reviewed publication is underway.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/14/2023<br>      Modified by: Jesse&nbsp;Reimink</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project designed and tested a new method of creating ions that may help produce much more precise data than can traditionally accomplished. In this project, we designed and built a modified cavity ion source that encloses a sample into a hot cavity that produces ion to then be separated by a mass spectrometer. We installed this modified cavity source on a commercially built mass spectrometer with the goal of testing the utility of such sources in commercial instruments. Our preliminary designs performed well but did not show reproduciblely better data than can be accomplished with traditional methods. The inability to reproduce our results regulalry may be due to inconsistencies in sample loading, or problems encountered in maintaining electrical voltages during high temperature operation. Another goal of the project was to test the style of mass fractionation that occurs within all mass spectrometers. Mass fractionation is the process by which the measured isotopic ratio changes during a run, due to various physical processes that occur during ionization processes. During this project, we established that mass fractionation in the cavity ion source occurs according to exponential law, which is identical to that which occurs in traditional methods. This result shows that cavity ion sources have future potential for routine analysis of unknown samples at high precisions. Further work needs to be done to achieve routine analyses that are clearly better than traditional methods. Our work was presented at an international conference and a peer-reviewed publication is underway.        Last Modified: 03/14/2023       Submitted by: Jesse Reimink]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
