<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Doctoral Dissertation Research: Personality Traits of U.S. Courts of Appeals Judges]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>31300.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>31300</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Naomi Hall-Byers</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>nhallbye@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922672</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[A personality is a unique feature of individuals that defines and dictates everyday actions in their lives, including judges on the U.S Courts of Appeals. This project will develop individual personality profiles of these judges by mapping them onto the popular Big Five traits of openness, conscientiousness, extraversion, agreeableness, and neuroticism. This project then will incorporate the influence of those personality traits on judicial decision making and behavior at the U.S. Courts of Appeals.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will gather pre-confirmation writings and speeches for all available judges on the U.S. Courts of Appeals from 1947-2020, encompassing approximately 700 judges. Using cutting edge developments in textual analysis, estimates of the Big Five personality traits will be generated. With these estimates in hand, this project will examine how personality traits influence judicial behavior and, consequently, federal law. This project will generate personality trait estimates for federal court judges, as well as the underlying corpus of text documents used to generate them. Project data will be widely disseminated to the public.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/04/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/04/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2017311</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ryan</FirstName>
<LastName>Black</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ryan C Black</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[rcblack@msu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000572972</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/04/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jonathan</FirstName>
<LastName>King</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jonathan M King</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jonathan.king@mail.wvu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000819371</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/04/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Michigan State University</Name>
<CityName>EAST LANSING</CityName>
<ZipCode>488242600</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5173555040</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>426 AUDITORIUM RD RM 2</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>R28EKN92ZTZ9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MICHIGAN STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>VJKZC4D1JN36</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Michigan State University]]></Name>
<CityName>East Lansing</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>488241046</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[368 Farm Lane]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>128Y</Code>
<Text>Law &amp; Science</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~31300</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Jonathan M. King has completed research for his dissertation "Personality Trait Estimation of U.S. Circuit Court Judges" supported by the NSF Dissertation Improvement Grant. His work broadly examines how a judge's most unique characteristic -- their personality -- influences their decisions on the bench. Specifically, he examines the role of personality in U.S. Circuit Court judicial behavior.</p> <p>During his funding period, Jonathan collected, digitized, and generated machine-readable documents for over 55,000 textual documents of circuit court judges from 1987-2020. These texts in hand, he used advances in machine learning to translate the textual documents to personality trait estimates based on the popular "Big Five" personality trait spectrum. These trait estimates represent the first of their kind for U.S. Circuit judges.</p> <p>Through his research, Jonathan is able to answer important questions about the role of personality in judicial behavior. For example, are judges that are more conscientious -- that is, wanting to do their job well and dutifully -- more likely to adhere to Supreme Court precedent?&nbsp; Or, are judges that are less agreeable -- that is, less likely to want to work with others or be cooperative -- more likely to write a dissent in a case.&nbsp; These questions and more found the basis of Jonathan's dissertation research.</p> <p>King's research is the basis of his dissertation, expected to be completed in Spring 2023. This work is an important contribution to Law and Science as it provides insight into how a judge's personality influences their actions on the bench which, by extension, impacts law and policy in the United States.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/29/2022<br>      Modified by: Jonathan&nbsp;M&nbsp;King</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Jonathan M. King has completed research for his dissertation "Personality Trait Estimation of U.S. Circuit Court Judges" supported by the NSF Dissertation Improvement Grant. His work broadly examines how a judge's most unique characteristic -- their personality -- influences their decisions on the bench. Specifically, he examines the role of personality in U.S. Circuit Court judicial behavior.  During his funding period, Jonathan collected, digitized, and generated machine-readable documents for over 55,000 textual documents of circuit court judges from 1987-2020. These texts in hand, he used advances in machine learning to translate the textual documents to personality trait estimates based on the popular "Big Five" personality trait spectrum. These trait estimates represent the first of their kind for U.S. Circuit judges.  Through his research, Jonathan is able to answer important questions about the role of personality in judicial behavior. For example, are judges that are more conscientious -- that is, wanting to do their job well and dutifully -- more likely to adhere to Supreme Court precedent?  Or, are judges that are less agreeable -- that is, less likely to want to work with others or be cooperative -- more likely to write a dissent in a case.  These questions and more found the basis of Jonathan's dissertation research.  King's research is the basis of his dissertation, expected to be completed in Spring 2023. This work is an important contribution to Law and Science as it provides insight into how a judge's personality influences their actions on the bench which, by extension, impacts law and policy in the United States.       Last Modified: 11/29/2022       Submitted by: Jonathan M King]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
