<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RCN-UBE Incubator: Building the San Francisco Bay Network for Student Opportunities in Avian Research to enhance STEM education and assess urban impacts on avian ecology]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>74157.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>74157</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DBI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Amanda Simcox</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>asimcox@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928165</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The project will bring together a group of faculty, students, and volunteers to design an experiential learning and research program focused on the study of birds and their habitats. The program will introduce undergraduate students, especially those from underserved communities, to STEM activities in both the field and laboratory. It will be valuable in shedding light on the dynamics of bird populations in the South San Francisco Bay, which is an important portion of a north-south “highway in the sky” for birds that annually migrate between the northern and southern hemispheres. The project will advance biology education by providing opportunities for hands-on field research and follow-up lab activities for students who do not presently have access to such experiential learning in outdoor settings. It will advance fundamental knowledge by revealing how humans are influencing natural ecological systems, and whether those influences are beneficial or detrimental.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will create the foundation for a new Research Coordination Network: the San Francisco Bay Research Coordination Network for Student Opportunities in Avian Research. The new network will be composed of investigators from three universities (Stanford University, San Jose State University, and Santa Clara University), a community college (West Valley Community College), and a non-governmental organization (San Francisco Bay Bird Observatory). The intended products are planning workshops, prototypes of outdoor learning modules, and a detailed roadmap for growing and sustaining the program. Prototypes of outdoor learning modules will bring students and faculty into the field to collaboratively learn how to monitor and analyze data pertinent to understanding avian population dynamics in two field areas, Jasper Ridge Biological Preserve and the San Francisco Bay Bird Observatory Coyote Creek Field Station. Follow-up studies in the laboratories of the network participants will include analyses of data the students collect augmented by three decades of bird-census data available from both field sites. Students will also learn to apply cutting-edge analytical techniques such as genome sequencing and GIS tools. The network will bring together resources from the participating institutions to better serve the multicultural and economically disparate constituents of the region. It will demonstrate the need, value, and opportunities for career paths in environmental sciences. Exposure of students to these career paths will diversify their job prospects and train them to be effective stewards of the national and global resources upon which nations ultimately depend.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is being jointly funded by the Directorate for Biological Sciences, Division of Biological Infrastructure, and the Directorate for Education and Human Resources, Division of Undergraduate Education as part of their efforts to address the challenges posed in Vision and Change in Undergraduate Biology Education: A Call to Action (http://visionandchange/finalreport/).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/11/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/11/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2017935</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Anthony</FirstName>
<LastName>Barnosky</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Anthony Barnosky</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[tonybarnosky@stanford.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000731005</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/11/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Stanford University</Name>
<CityName>STANFORD</CityName>
<ZipCode>943052004</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6507232300</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>450 JANE STANFORD WAY</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>16</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA16</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>HJD6G4D6TJY5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>THE LELAND STANFORD JUNIOR UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Jasper Ridge Biological Preserve]]></Name>
<CityName>Stanford</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>943055020</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Stanford University]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>16</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA16</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>037Y</Code>
<Text>UBE - Undergraduate Biology Ed</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1998</Code>
<Text>IUSE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1664</Code>
<Text>RESEARCH COORD NETWK IN BIO SC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0420</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>04002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~74157</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>This project built the new <strong><span>San Francisco Bay Research Coordination Network for <em>S</em>tudent <em>O</em>pportunities in <em>A</em>vian <em>R</em>esearch (SOAR)</span></strong> composed of investigators from four universities, two community colleges, a museum, and three non-governmental organizations. <span>SOAR</span> coalesces a cadre of experts in research, teaching, and outreach, with a focus in ornithology.&nbsp;<span>&nbsp;</span></span></p> <p><span><span>The theme of SOAR is to use ornithologically-centered research to expose and train a diverse community of students in STEM areas related to environmental science and to conduct long-term studies on avian communities at Jasper Ridge Biological Preserve (JRBP) and Coyote Creek Field Station (CCFS), two field sites centrally located for participants. Both field sites are important stopovers for birds using the Pacific Flyway. Developed under an RCN-UBE incubator grant, the program pools expertise and resources of faculty, staff, environmental scientists, students, and volunteers from Stanford University, Santa Clara University, San Jose State University, University of California-Santa Cruz, West Valley Community College, Mission College, the San Francisco Bay Bird Observatory, iNaturalist, California Academy of Sciences, and eBird (Cornell Lab of Ornithology) to form the <strong><span>San Francisco Bay Research Coordination Network for Student Opportunities in Avian Research (SOAR). </span></strong><span>The overarching goals of SOAR are to: (1) <em>Provide experiential and inquiry-based learning that incorporates field settings, especially JRBP and CCFS; (2) Involve students in data acquisition and analysis; and (3) Provide STEM opportunities with a focus on enhancing Diversity, Equity, and Inclusion (DEI).</em></span></span></span></p> <p><em>Intellectual Merit</em></p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Four workshops crystallized the SOAR RCN participant list to include 26 people connected across two community colleges, two private universities, two public universities, three NGOs, and a museum. Through this collaboration: (1) the overall goals and objectives of the SOAR RCN were defined; (2) a logic model to guide activities was developed (Fig. 1); (3) seven education modules were defined and prototyped in student-training activities; (4) three new courses were identified for development; (5) three unifying research questions were identified; (6) an evaluation and assessment plan was produced; (7) a management structure and plan was crystallized and implemented; (8) a five-year plan for scheduling activities and delivering products was developed; (9) this proposal was developed and submitted.</p> <p><em>Broader Impacts</em></p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; A summary of broader impacts includes: (1) community-building activities were defined; (2) an internship for a student was piloted; (3) presentations about the project were given at the 2021 Annual Meeting of the Organization of Biological Field Stations and the 2022 Ecological Society of America Meetings; and (4) students involved in the project gained field- and lab-based STEM skills and learned to present their work at community venues.<em>&nbsp;</em></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/29/2022<br>      Modified by: Anthony&nbsp;Barnosky</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project built the new San Francisco Bay Research Coordination Network for Student Opportunities in Avian Research (SOAR) composed of investigators from four universities, two community colleges, a museum, and three non-governmental organizations. SOAR coalesces a cadre of experts in research, teaching, and outreach, with a focus in ornithology.    The theme of SOAR is to use ornithologically-centered research to expose and train a diverse community of students in STEM areas related to environmental science and to conduct long-term studies on avian communities at Jasper Ridge Biological Preserve (JRBP) and Coyote Creek Field Station (CCFS), two field sites centrally located for participants. Both field sites are important stopovers for birds using the Pacific Flyway. Developed under an RCN-UBE incubator grant, the program pools expertise and resources of faculty, staff, environmental scientists, students, and volunteers from Stanford University, Santa Clara University, San Jose State University, University of California-Santa Cruz, West Valley Community College, Mission College, the San Francisco Bay Bird Observatory, iNaturalist, California Academy of Sciences, and eBird (Cornell Lab of Ornithology) to form the San Francisco Bay Research Coordination Network for Student Opportunities in Avian Research (SOAR). The overarching goals of SOAR are to: (1) Provide experiential and inquiry-based learning that incorporates field settings, especially JRBP and CCFS; (2) Involve students in data acquisition and analysis; and (3) Provide STEM opportunities with a focus on enhancing Diversity, Equity, and Inclusion (DEI).  Intellectual Merit       Four workshops crystallized the SOAR RCN participant list to include 26 people connected across two community colleges, two private universities, two public universities, three NGOs, and a museum. Through this collaboration: (1) the overall goals and objectives of the SOAR RCN were defined; (2) a logic model to guide activities was developed (Fig. 1); (3) seven education modules were defined and prototyped in student-training activities; (4) three new courses were identified for development; (5) three unifying research questions were identified; (6) an evaluation and assessment plan was produced; (7) a management structure and plan was crystallized and implemented; (8) a five-year plan for scheduling activities and delivering products was developed; (9) this proposal was developed and submitted.  Broader Impacts       A summary of broader impacts includes: (1) community-building activities were defined; (2) an internship for a student was piloted; (3) presentations about the project were given at the 2021 Annual Meeting of the Organization of Biological Field Stations and the 2022 Ecological Society of America Meetings; and (4) students involved in the project gained field- and lab-based STEM skills and learned to present their work at community venues.           Last Modified: 09/29/2022       Submitted by: Anthony Barnosky]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
