<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[I-Corps: Water Purification Membranes Made using Green Solvents]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ruth Shuman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rshuman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922160</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this I-Corps project is the development of new green and non-toxic technologies for water treatment. Applications include providing safe tap water and improved water for systems operating at safe levels but with undesirable aesthetics. The technology can impact industrial and household applications.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project is based on the development of solvents to fabricate separations membranes for several applications, including drinking water treatment and face mask fabrication. The technology uses two environmentally friendly solvents, methyl 5-(dimethylamino)-2-methyl-5-oxopentanoate ("PolarClean") and gamma-valerolactone (GVL), as co-solvents to fabricate polysulfone (PSf) ultrafiltration membranes. Based on calculated solubility values, PolarClean/GVL co-solvents showed better performance together than independently. Previous viscosity studies suggest strong performance of this system.  The proposed project will explore translation of this technology.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/28/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/28/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2017133</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Isabel</FirstName>
<LastName>Escobar</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Isabel C Escobar</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[isabel.escobar@uky.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000482772</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/28/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Kentucky Research Foundation</Name>
<CityName>LEXINGTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>405260001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8592579420</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>500 S LIMESTONE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[109 KINKEAD HALL]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Kentucky</StateName>
<StateCode>KY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>KY06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>H1HYA8Z1NTM5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF KENTUCKY RESEARCH FOUNDATION, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Kentucky Research Foundation]]></Name>
<CityName>Lexington</CityName>
<StateCode>KY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>405260001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Kentucky</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>KY06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The world&rsquo;s drinking water is becoming increasingly unsafe through the growing concentrations of current contaminants and introduction of new contaminants. The filtration market is growing, with a moderate degree of competition, and the Bloomberg World Water Index has outperformed the oil, gas, and basic material indexes for a number of years. This suggests that a product that is technically sound with a unique value proposition and competitively priced to the market should be successful. Membrane filtration has the capability of addressing the need for safe drinking water. However, petroleum-derived hazardous solvents are involved in the fabrication of polymeric membranes, and in Europe, the use of petroleum-derived hazardous solvents is now severely restricted. Therefore, there is an urgent need to explore alternatives for traditional solvents, specifically green ones, enabling membrane filtration to meet future market demands. The water filter used here was developed using two environmentally friendly solvents to fabricate polysulfone (PSf) ultrafiltration membranes. The innovation could offer consumers considerable benefits including reduced health risks associated with solvent handling. Therefore, it would be familiar to customers and could be marketed as an &ldquo;improved&rdquo; product.</p> <p>This grant was used for the customer-discovery process to hear the specific pain points where this technology could help address a need in the market. Through NSF IIP 2017133 ICorps grant, 114 potential customers were interviewed, and it was determined that the best customer for this innovation would be process engineers at membrane manufacturing facilities. Through these interviews, it was also determined that their primary pain point was meeting wastewater regulations upon expanding operations.</p> <p>We determined that the most important value proposition to our customer base (i.e. process engineers in membrane manufacturing) is to meet regulations addressing wastewater treatment. Specifically, 22 interviews identified the main pain point of membrane manufacture to be the treatment of the wastewater, preferably via biodegradation, that is produced during membrane fabrication. About 30 end-users mentioned that membrane operation efficiency to be the most important to them.</p> <p>Again, thanks to the NSF ICorps grant, we developed the value proposition that <strong><em>we can provide a green process that the membrane manufacturers need to comply with new regulations when they expand</em></strong> (operations). We further propose to add green silver nanoparticles to the green processes without changing the value proposition. We propose that we can provide membrane manufacturers with the ability to save extra post treatment procedures to treat wastewater to comply with ever increasing wastewater permitting regulations. Furthermore, they will gain green initiatives and reduce post-treatment costs, making the 2<sup>nd</sup>/3<sup>rd</sup> manufacturer more competitive in the market, challenging the 1<sup>st </sup>manufacturer.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/15/2021<br>      Modified by: Isabel&nbsp;C&nbsp;Escobar</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The world’s drinking water is becoming increasingly unsafe through the growing concentrations of current contaminants and introduction of new contaminants. The filtration market is growing, with a moderate degree of competition, and the Bloomberg World Water Index has outperformed the oil, gas, and basic material indexes for a number of years. This suggests that a product that is technically sound with a unique value proposition and competitively priced to the market should be successful. Membrane filtration has the capability of addressing the need for safe drinking water. However, petroleum-derived hazardous solvents are involved in the fabrication of polymeric membranes, and in Europe, the use of petroleum-derived hazardous solvents is now severely restricted. Therefore, there is an urgent need to explore alternatives for traditional solvents, specifically green ones, enabling membrane filtration to meet future market demands. The water filter used here was developed using two environmentally friendly solvents to fabricate polysulfone (PSf) ultrafiltration membranes. The innovation could offer consumers considerable benefits including reduced health risks associated with solvent handling. Therefore, it would be familiar to customers and could be marketed as an "improved" product.  This grant was used for the customer-discovery process to hear the specific pain points where this technology could help address a need in the market. Through NSF IIP 2017133 ICorps grant, 114 potential customers were interviewed, and it was determined that the best customer for this innovation would be process engineers at membrane manufacturing facilities. Through these interviews, it was also determined that their primary pain point was meeting wastewater regulations upon expanding operations.  We determined that the most important value proposition to our customer base (i.e. process engineers in membrane manufacturing) is to meet regulations addressing wastewater treatment. Specifically, 22 interviews identified the main pain point of membrane manufacture to be the treatment of the wastewater, preferably via biodegradation, that is produced during membrane fabrication. About 30 end-users mentioned that membrane operation efficiency to be the most important to them.  Again, thanks to the NSF ICorps grant, we developed the value proposition that we can provide a green process that the membrane manufacturers need to comply with new regulations when they expand (operations). We further propose to add green silver nanoparticles to the green processes without changing the value proposition. We propose that we can provide membrane manufacturers with the ability to save extra post treatment procedures to treat wastewater to comply with ever increasing wastewater permitting regulations. Furthermore, they will gain green initiatives and reduce post-treatment costs, making the 2nd/3rd manufacturer more competitive in the market, challenging the 1st manufacturer.          Last Modified: 12/15/2021       Submitted by: Isabel C Escobar]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
