<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Doctoral Dissertation Research: Retirement Practices, Resource Management, and Financial Planning]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>19769.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>19769</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jeffrey Mantz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jmantz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927783</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This doctoral dissertation research project scientifically explores how resource and financial planning strategies are managed among aging populations. Focusing on an age-restricted retirement community, the researcher examines what experiences influence retirement behavior in older age, as well as how economic and ecological resources are understood and utilized among retirees. This work will shed light on the ways American retirement is shaping the future of the U.S. Southwest; what obstacles are inhibiting the possibility of retirement among future generations; and what influence the current demographic of retirees has in shaping these changes. A key impact of this project will be to expand academic and public discussions on aging by linking choices about and experiences of retirement with financial planning and life histories. Further, it will focus on the way population growth impacts resource planning and will increase public knowledge about the environmental resources in this region. In addition to training a graduate student in methods of scientific data collection and analysis, it will also provide valuable material for governmental and nongovernmental professionals working in the fields of aging policy, retirement planning, and urban development. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The researcher will shadow retirees, conduct media and archival research, and conduct in-depth interviews and life histories in order to understand how retirement is understood or experienced by older Americans, estate planners, municipal water officials, and relatives of retirees. The researcher has several specific goals. She intends to answer the following questions: What can retirement practices today illuminate about the American Dream, both how it is understood and the way it plays out locally in the West? How do retirement practices reveal internal differentiation among social groups? And how does the expansion of retirement communities in the American West shape present and future economic and ecological conditions and infrastructures? By answering these questions, the researcher will contribute to a greater understanding of resource management, as well as to the way heterogeneous groups build new forms of sociality. She proposes to combine ethnographic approaches with a robust historical framework in order to provide multi-dimensional insights into eldercare, finance, and the environment.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/25/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/20/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2017683</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Susan</FirstName>
<LastName>Gal</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Susan Gal</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[s-gal@uchicago.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000184647</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/25/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rachel</FirstName>
<LastName>Howard</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Rachel Howard</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[rhoward3@uchicago.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000804422</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/25/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Chicago</Name>
<CityName>CHICAGO</CityName>
<ZipCode>606375418</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7737028669</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5801 S ELLIS AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>ZUE9HKT2CLC9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CHICAGO</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>ZUE9HKT2CLC9</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Chicago]]></Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>606371115</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1126 E. 59th Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7605</Code>
<Text>Cult Anthro DDRI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1390</Code>
<Text>CULTURAL ANTHROPOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~19769</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>?Constructing the Oasis: Retirement Practices, Resource Management, and Financial Planning? was an ethnographic project that utilized a variety of methods and forms of data analysis, including from cultural anthropology; linguistic anthropology; science and technology studies; and the anthropology of aging. Research for this project was conducted between 2020-2022 in Phoenix, AZ, Denver, CO, and virtually over Zoom. The main outcomes of this project were a greater understanding of the ways that people plan for and experience retirement in the Sun Belt; how Baby Boomers finance life post-work; and the different environmental infrastructures that have made population growth in Phoenix both possible and pleasant. Secondary outcomes of this project were a greater understanding of the environmental effects of widespread migration to the Phoenix area as well as the history of retirement communities in the desert West.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>It is my hope that the intellectual outcomes of this project include: a greater appreciation for intra-disciplinary methodologies and forms of analysis; attention to pedagogical methods that implement multi-modal ethnography; and addition to general and anthropological knowledge about aging, retiring, and living in the desert West. This project contributes to anthropologies of aging and the good life in a U.S. marked by radically disparate futures within and between generations. As the narrative of the American Dream becomes entangled with the reality of economic and ecological instabilities, social tensions with far-reaching implications manifest. This project focuses on how such tensions impact cultural understandings of identities and how the social practices that index them affect material infrastructures. By ethnographically studying Sun City, this project has examined how the dream of American retirement is shaping the future of the American Southwest; how the dream of retirement is losing its conditions of possibility; and how the currently large demographic of retirees is experiencing and contributing to these changes.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>So far, the outcomes of this research have included a peer-reviewed essay in <em>Current Anthropology</em>, an essay published on <em>Edge Effects</em>, and a dissertation-in-progress.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/07/2023<br>      Modified by: Rachel&nbsp;Howard</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ ?Constructing the Oasis: Retirement Practices, Resource Management, and Financial Planning? was an ethnographic project that utilized a variety of methods and forms of data analysis, including from cultural anthropology; linguistic anthropology; science and technology studies; and the anthropology of aging. Research for this project was conducted between 2020-2022 in Phoenix, AZ, Denver, CO, and virtually over Zoom. The main outcomes of this project were a greater understanding of the ways that people plan for and experience retirement in the Sun Belt; how Baby Boomers finance life post-work; and the different environmental infrastructures that have made population growth in Phoenix both possible and pleasant. Secondary outcomes of this project were a greater understanding of the environmental effects of widespread migration to the Phoenix area as well as the history of retirement communities in the desert West.     It is my hope that the intellectual outcomes of this project include: a greater appreciation for intra-disciplinary methodologies and forms of analysis; attention to pedagogical methods that implement multi-modal ethnography; and addition to general and anthropological knowledge about aging, retiring, and living in the desert West. This project contributes to anthropologies of aging and the good life in a U.S. marked by radically disparate futures within and between generations. As the narrative of the American Dream becomes entangled with the reality of economic and ecological instabilities, social tensions with far-reaching implications manifest. This project focuses on how such tensions impact cultural understandings of identities and how the social practices that index them affect material infrastructures. By ethnographically studying Sun City, this project has examined how the dream of American retirement is shaping the future of the American Southwest; how the dream of retirement is losing its conditions of possibility; and how the currently large demographic of retirees is experiencing and contributing to these changes.     So far, the outcomes of this research have included a peer-reviewed essay in Current Anthropology, an essay published on Edge Effects, and a dissertation-in-progress.          Last Modified: 08/07/2023       Submitted by: Rachel Howard]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
