<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Doctoral Dissertation Research: Emigrant Political Rights in Latin America, Dual Citizenship, Voting, and Representation]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>25087.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>25087</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Reginald Sheehan</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rsheehan@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925389</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[For over a century, migrants abroad have supported the economic development of their homelands by sending remittances. Previous research has shown that this type of money transfers is instrumental to avoid financial crises in sending countries. In Latin America, remittances occupy one of the mainline items within the gross domestic product of several national economies. However, the economic contributions by citizens abroad have not translated into substantive political representation. Migrants contribute to the welfare of their households and the homeland economy, and yet, their political participation in polity of the place of birth remains incipient. Therefore, understanding the conditions that guided the creation and implementation of political rights and laws that govern them is critical for developing public policies aimed at reducing political inequalities for citizens abroad. After all, as previous research has shown, the political participation of migrants in their homeland also enhances their political involvement in the countries where they live as immigrants.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In the last thirty years, Latin American states have created legislation to approve political rights for its citizens abroad including dual citizenship, extraterritorial voting, and parliamentary representation. This legislation, however, has not always translated into substantive political rights. The scholarship on emigrant politics has focused on the approval of emigrant political rights without paying attention to the socio-legal conditions that led to various degrees of implementation. If Latin American states have created similar legislation on the books, why did different levels of substantive implementation emerge? This project studies the creation and implementation of political rights and laws for Latin American emigrants from a comparative perspective. It combines a two-phase process of data collection and analysis. First, using numerical data from nineteen countries in Latin America, this project employs Qualitative Comparative Analysis to develop a systematic cross-case analysis of causal conditions leading to the creation of emigrant laws. Second, combining data from interviews, newspaper articles, administrative records, official documents, and archives, this project deploys several cycles of qualitative coding techniques to trace divergent political trajectories of emigrants living abroad. Conceptually, this project emphasizes how violence, politicization of emigrants, and critical junctures of democratization influence policy decisions related to extraterritorial political rights. Findings from this research will provide insights into the differentiated conditions in which Latin American countries grant political rights to their citizens abroad, contributing to a growing literature on democratization and inclusion. Furthermore, this research project will explain the striking differences between how countries approve policy on paper and how they implement it on the ground.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/11/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/11/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2017145</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Cecilia</FirstName>
<LastName>Menjivar</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Cecilia Menjivar</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[menjivar@soc.ucla.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000460448</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/11/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Leydy</FirstName>
<LastName>Diossa-Jimenez</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Leydy J Diossa-Jimenez</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ldiossa@ucla.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000755768</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/11/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Los Angeles</Name>
<CityName>LOS ANGELES</CityName>
<ZipCode>900244201</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3107940102</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>10889 WILSHIRE BLVD STE 700</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>37</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA37</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>RN64EPNH8JC6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, LOS ANGELES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>NUDGYLBB4S99</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Los angeles]]></Name>
<CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>900951406</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Sociology/264 Haines Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>33</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA33</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>128Y</Code>
<Text>Law &amp; Science</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~25087</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Leydy Diossa-Jimenez has completed research for his dissertation "Emigrant Political Rights in Latin America, Dual Citizenship, Voting, and Representation," supported by the National Science Foundation. During the funding period, she interviewed former members of the executive, legislative, and judicial branches in Argentina, Colombia, and Mexico. As a historical-comparative sociologist, Diossa-Jimenez was interested in the political processes leading to the creation and implementation of emigrants' political rights (i.e., dual citizenship, extraterritorial voting, and parliamentary representation).</p> <p><br />The research supported by this award asked: (a) Why is it only recently that Latin American states recognized emigrants' political rights? (b) If Latin American states approved emigrant political rights in the same period, why did different levels of political inclusion emerge? And (c) What are the roles of political violence, the politicization of emigrants, and critical junctures in creating political rights and laws?</p> <p><br />Prior to the pandemic, Leydy Diossa-Jimenez undertook fieldwork in Colombia, Mexico, and Argentina. She spent 18 months of multi-sited fieldwork, archival research, and in-depth interviews in Argentina (6 months), Colombia (10 months), and Mexico (2 months). First, she searched for administrative records, official documents, and national archives to identify long-term patterns of democracy or authoritarianism. The effects of violence in the expulsion of populations abroad have been validated through data and official statistics (UN Refugees) showing the impact of political violence in the region. Second, her archival research provided evidence of political events influencing rights approval. These events were further explored during life-history interviews with victims of political violence. And third, newspaper articles helped identify sequences of critical junctures that were corroborated and expanded by archival research. She was able to adapt these various forms of data collection to Covid-related restrictions during the pandemic.</p> <p><br />This research makes a theoretical contribution to the studies of political rights and international migration by reconstructing the processes of creation and implementation of rights. While policy implementation trends via bottom-up and top-down demands are well noted, only some studies capture the process of policymaking from a comparative perspective. Conceptually, this project emphasizes how political violence, the politicization of emigrants, and the critical juncture influence extraterritorial political rights policy decisions. Furthermore, this research shows that the striking differences between how countries approve and implement policy on the ground are different mechanisms of political control of emigrants abroad. Although empirically focused on Latin America, the comparative analytical approach embedded in it underscores its theoretical relevance beyond this setting. The political rights of emigrants, who constitute an increasing segment of societies worldwide, are vital for understanding democratization projects and political change more broadly.</p> <p><br />This dissertation project is timely and relevant for migration policy beyond the empirical cases of its focus. Since Colombia's approval and implementation of voting and representation from abroad, several countries in the region have mimicked this policy. However, because these policies would give voice and vote to citizens outside the territory, some countries like Uruguay, Nicaragua, and Guatemala have concerns regarding the potential for national and internal conflict and possible tensions between members in and of the nation. The richness of comparative and qualitative data contributes to understanding the potential threats and advantages of incorporating migrants outside the national territory by creating and approving laws to recognize their political rights.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/05/2022<br>      Modified by: Leydy&nbsp;J&nbsp;Diossa-Jimenez</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Leydy Diossa-Jimenez has completed research for his dissertation "Emigrant Political Rights in Latin America, Dual Citizenship, Voting, and Representation," supported by the National Science Foundation. During the funding period, she interviewed former members of the executive, legislative, and judicial branches in Argentina, Colombia, and Mexico. As a historical-comparative sociologist, Diossa-Jimenez was interested in the political processes leading to the creation and implementation of emigrants' political rights (i.e., dual citizenship, extraterritorial voting, and parliamentary representation).   The research supported by this award asked: (a) Why is it only recently that Latin American states recognized emigrants' political rights? (b) If Latin American states approved emigrant political rights in the same period, why did different levels of political inclusion emerge? And (c) What are the roles of political violence, the politicization of emigrants, and critical junctures in creating political rights and laws?   Prior to the pandemic, Leydy Diossa-Jimenez undertook fieldwork in Colombia, Mexico, and Argentina. She spent 18 months of multi-sited fieldwork, archival research, and in-depth interviews in Argentina (6 months), Colombia (10 months), and Mexico (2 months). First, she searched for administrative records, official documents, and national archives to identify long-term patterns of democracy or authoritarianism. The effects of violence in the expulsion of populations abroad have been validated through data and official statistics (UN Refugees) showing the impact of political violence in the region. Second, her archival research provided evidence of political events influencing rights approval. These events were further explored during life-history interviews with victims of political violence. And third, newspaper articles helped identify sequences of critical junctures that were corroborated and expanded by archival research. She was able to adapt these various forms of data collection to Covid-related restrictions during the pandemic.   This research makes a theoretical contribution to the studies of political rights and international migration by reconstructing the processes of creation and implementation of rights. While policy implementation trends via bottom-up and top-down demands are well noted, only some studies capture the process of policymaking from a comparative perspective. Conceptually, this project emphasizes how political violence, the politicization of emigrants, and the critical juncture influence extraterritorial political rights policy decisions. Furthermore, this research shows that the striking differences between how countries approve and implement policy on the ground are different mechanisms of political control of emigrants abroad. Although empirically focused on Latin America, the comparative analytical approach embedded in it underscores its theoretical relevance beyond this setting. The political rights of emigrants, who constitute an increasing segment of societies worldwide, are vital for understanding democratization projects and political change more broadly.   This dissertation project is timely and relevant for migration policy beyond the empirical cases of its focus. Since Colombia's approval and implementation of voting and representation from abroad, several countries in the region have mimicked this policy. However, because these policies would give voice and vote to citizens outside the territory, some countries like Uruguay, Nicaragua, and Guatemala have concerns regarding the potential for national and internal conflict and possible tensions between members in and of the nation. The richness of comparative and qualitative data contributes to understanding the potential threats and advantages of incorporating migrants outside the national territory by creating and approving laws to recognize their political rights.       Last Modified: 11/05/2022       Submitted by: Leydy J Diossa-Jimenez]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
