<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[MRI: Acquisition of Nano-resolution Zeiss Xradia 620 Versa X-ray Computed Tomography with Phase Contrast and Lab Diffraction Contrast Tomography]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1202836.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1202836</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Guebre Tessema</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>gtessema@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924935</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This award from the Major Research Instrumentation Program supports the acquisition of a Zeiss Xradia 620 Versa Computed Tomography (Versa nanoCT) system at the University of Florida, where it will be accessible to students, researchers, industrial partners, and museum personnel. The Versa nanoCT is a non-destructive characterization tool that provides nano-scale 3D imaging of internal and external features of organic and inorganic specimens. The equipment’s versatility allows it to impact a variety of scientific fields, including materials science, vertebrate zoology, and biomedical engineering. The acquired data will be shared through open source networks and field-specific databases to reach researchers around the world and enable broad-scale data research initiatives. Additionally, the data collected will be implemented in graduate, undergraduate, and high-school education, 3D machine learning development, and public engagement activities via virtual museum collections.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The acquisition of a Zeiss Xradia 620 Versa Computed Tomography (Versa nanoCT) system introduces new research opportunities by providing nondestructive, 3D imaging that is essential for identifying critical microstructural or morphological features to fundamental material or biological processes, respectively. Additionally, the unique features of the Versa nanoCT, including the high X-ray source flux, 40X magnification optics, diffraction contrast tomography (LabDCT) and phase contrast, provide essential information that are typically unavailable outside of synchrotron facilities. The Versa nanoCT enables and supports research in three critical areas: (1) elucidating fundamental microstructure-property relationships to control the strength of structural metals and ceramics, (2) archiving morphological diversity to better understand the processes that drive the diversification of living and extinct organisms, and (3) monitoring cell-material interactions to guide tissue generation.  The instrument also supports educational initiatives at the graduate, undergraduate, and high-school level, support data support for 3D machine learning initiatives, and engage the public through outreach at the Florida Museum of Natural History (FLMNH) Education and Exhibition Center.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/28/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/07/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2017977</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Edward</FirstName>
<LastName>Stanley</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Edward L Stanley</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[elstanley@flmnh.ufl.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000606187</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/28/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Luisa</FirstName>
<LastName>Dempere</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Luisa A Dempere</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ldemp@mse.ufl.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000482831</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/28/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Amanda</FirstName>
<LastName>Krause</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Amanda R Krause</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[krause@cmu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000815439</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/28/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Florida</Name>
<CityName>GAINESVILLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>326111941</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3523923516</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1523 UNION RD RM 207</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NNFQH1JAPEP3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF FLORIDA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>D4GCCCMXR1H3</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Florida]]></Name>
<CityName>Gainesville</CityName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>326115500</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[207 Grinter Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>Major Research Instrumentation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~1202836</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>MRI: Acquisition of Nano-resolution Zeiss Xradia 620 Versa X-ray Computed Tomography with Phase Contrast and Lab Diffraction Contrast Tomography</strong></p> <p>PD/PI Name:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Amanda R Krause, Principal Investigator</strong></li> <li><strong>Luisa A Dempere, Co-Principal Investigator</strong></li> <li><strong>Edward L Stanley, Co-Principal Investigator</strong></li> </ul> <p>Organization:&nbsp;<strong>University of Florida</strong></p> <p>Project/Grant Period:<strong>08/01/2020 - 07/31/2023</strong></p> <p>Submitting Official (if other than PD\PI):</p> <ul> <li><strong>Luisa Dempere (Co-P.I.)</strong></li> </ul> <p>Submission Date:<strong>03/16/2023</strong></p> <p><strong>Accomplishments</strong></p> <p><strong>* What are the major goals of the project?</strong></p> <p>The acquisition of a Zeiss Xradia 620 Versa CT system has introduced cutting-edge 3D imaging capabilities at the UF, driving new research across five colleges and 6 departments while expanding resources available to external academic collaborators. The Versa CT has enabled and supported UF research in three critical areas: (1) elucidating fundamental microstructure-property relationships to control the strength of structural metals and ceramics, (2) archiving morphological diversity to understand better the processes that drive the diversification of living and extinct organisms, (3) monitoring cell-material interactions to guide tissue generation. These three critical research areas have benefited from the high-resolution, non-destructive, 3D data from the Versa CT because their previous characterization methods relied on either destructive methods, 2D images, or low-contrast images that obscure the specimen or studied behavior.&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>* What was accomplished under these goals and objectives ?</strong></p> <p>Major Activities:</p> <p>The instrument was acquired, installed, and advanced user training sessions were conducted with Zeiss, and the RSC staff, where different research groups were able to optimize data collection settings and instrument operation.</p> <p>Specific Objectives: Train a diverse independent user base.</p> <p>Significant Results: 23 Independent users in 5 colleges/6 Departments, one external academic user (University of Miami) and one museum supporting NSF programs.</p> <p>Key outcomes :</p> <p>In addition to program staff and faculty (6), as of March 15, 2023 we have trained 18 users to independently use the Versa CT. These users span 5 colleges (Engineering, Liberal Arts and Sciences, Medicine, Agricultural and Life Sciences, and Dentistry),six departments within UF (Entomology &amp; Nematology, Chemical Enginering, Materials Science and Engineering, Biology, Anthropology, Molecular Genetics, Prosthosdontics), and the Florida Museum of Natural History.<br /> From the start of tracking to date (March 15, 2023), roughly 5,226 h the system has been operated to produce research data and more than 1,200 hours have been used in data reconstruction and anaysis.</p> <p><strong>* What opportunities for training and professional development has the project provided?</strong></p> <p>The instrument is the first of its kind in the greater southeast region and provides access to users both at UF and its external partners.&nbsp;<br /> Zeiss was a corporate sponsor and presenter at the RSC virtual Open House in 2021 and 2022.&nbsp; This allowed the RSC to advertise the CT and the technique to researchers that previously had not considered the Versa XRM additional capabilities.</p> <p><strong>Impacts</strong></p> <p><strong>What is the impact on the development of the principal discipline(s) of the project?</strong></p> <p><span>The Versa CT will enable and support UF research in three critical areas: (1) elucidating fundamental microstructure-property relationships to control the strength of structural metals and ceramics, (2) archiving morphological diversity to better understand the processes that drive the diversification of living and extinct organisms, (3) monitoring cell-material interactions to guide tissue generation.<br /> <!--[if !supportLineBreakNewLine]--><br /> <!--[endif]--></span>The Versa CT directly supports <strong>oVert</strong>, an NSF-supported project that creates and freely disseminates CT datasets and digital 3D anatomical models of vertebrate specimens from US museums.&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>What is the impact on the development of human resources?</strong></p> <p>Courses in Materials Science and Engineering and Natural History teach the physics of the technique and provide hands-on experience in data acquisition. The produced 3D volumetric data is utilized to develop critical coding and statistical skills for the next generation of scientists and engineers.</p> <p><strong>What was the impact on teaching and&nbsp;</strong><strong>educational experiences?</strong></p> <p>New opportunities for (1) education and training efforts via classrooms and scientific research at UF, (2) the development of 3D machine learning initiatives by providing rare datasets, and (3) public engagement via virtual museum collections.&nbsp;The virtual museum provides opportunities to promote international collaboration and education.</p> <p><strong>What is the impact on society beyond science and technology?</strong></p> <p>The increased output of CT data has been made available to facilitate new exhibits, interactive activities, and educational modules through the Florida Museum of Natural History Education and Exhibition Center and nearby Cade Museum of Creativity and Innovation.&nbsp;These initiatives allow important and rare specimens to be viewed and analyzed worldwide by anyone with a computer and internet access, thereby greatly expanding US natural history collections' research and educational footprint through UF's oVert project. The oVert project has scanned and disseminated nearly 8,000 vertebrate specimens from 18 US collections. Until the acquisition of the Versa CT, most of these scans returned skeletal anatomy only, partially because none of the participating institutions had a machine that was able to recover soft tissue information without using destructive or invasive staining methods, which are unviable for rare specimens.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/16/2023<br>      Modified by: Luisa&nbsp;A&nbsp;Dempere</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ MRI: Acquisition of Nano-resolution Zeiss Xradia 620 Versa X-ray Computed Tomography with Phase Contrast and Lab Diffraction Contrast Tomography  PD/PI Name:  Amanda R Krause, Principal Investigator Luisa A Dempere, Co-Principal Investigator Edward L Stanley, Co-Principal Investigator   Organization: University of Florida  Project/Grant Period:08/01/2020 - 07/31/2023  Submitting Official (if other than PD\PI):  Luisa Dempere (Co-P.I.)   Submission Date:03/16/2023  Accomplishments  * What are the major goals of the project?  The acquisition of a Zeiss Xradia 620 Versa CT system has introduced cutting-edge 3D imaging capabilities at the UF, driving new research across five colleges and 6 departments while expanding resources available to external academic collaborators. The Versa CT has enabled and supported UF research in three critical areas: (1) elucidating fundamental microstructure-property relationships to control the strength of structural metals and ceramics, (2) archiving morphological diversity to understand better the processes that drive the diversification of living and extinct organisms, (3) monitoring cell-material interactions to guide tissue generation. These three critical research areas have benefited from the high-resolution, non-destructive, 3D data from the Versa CT because their previous characterization methods relied on either destructive methods, 2D images, or low-contrast images that obscure the specimen or studied behavior.   * What was accomplished under these goals and objectives ?  Major Activities:  The instrument was acquired, installed, and advanced user training sessions were conducted with Zeiss, and the RSC staff, where different research groups were able to optimize data collection settings and instrument operation.  Specific Objectives: Train a diverse independent user base.  Significant Results: 23 Independent users in 5 colleges/6 Departments, one external academic user (University of Miami) and one museum supporting NSF programs.  Key outcomes :  In addition to program staff and faculty (6), as of March 15, 2023 we have trained 18 users to independently use the Versa CT. These users span 5 colleges (Engineering, Liberal Arts and Sciences, Medicine, Agricultural and Life Sciences, and Dentistry),six departments within UF (Entomology &amp; Nematology, Chemical Enginering, Materials Science and Engineering, Biology, Anthropology, Molecular Genetics, Prosthosdontics), and the Florida Museum of Natural History.  From the start of tracking to date (March 15, 2023), roughly 5,226 h the system has been operated to produce research data and more than 1,200 hours have been used in data reconstruction and anaysis.  * What opportunities for training and professional development has the project provided?  The instrument is the first of its kind in the greater southeast region and provides access to users both at UF and its external partners.   Zeiss was a corporate sponsor and presenter at the RSC virtual Open House in 2021 and 2022.  This allowed the RSC to advertise the CT and the technique to researchers that previously had not considered the Versa XRM additional capabilities.  Impacts  What is the impact on the development of the principal discipline(s) of the project?  The Versa CT will enable and support UF research in three critical areas: (1) elucidating fundamental microstructure-property relationships to control the strength of structural metals and ceramics, (2) archiving morphological diversity to better understand the processes that drive the diversification of living and extinct organisms, (3) monitoring cell-material interactions to guide tissue generation.    The Versa CT directly supports oVert, an NSF-supported project that creates and freely disseminates CT datasets and digital 3D anatomical models of vertebrate specimens from US museums.   What is the impact on the development of human resources?  Courses in Materials Science and Engineering and Natural History teach the physics of the technique and provide hands-on experience in data acquisition. The produced 3D volumetric data is utilized to develop critical coding and statistical skills for the next generation of scientists and engineers.  What was the impact on teaching and educational experiences?  New opportunities for (1) education and training efforts via classrooms and scientific research at UF, (2) the development of 3D machine learning initiatives by providing rare datasets, and (3) public engagement via virtual museum collections. The virtual museum provides opportunities to promote international collaboration and education.  What is the impact on society beyond science and technology?  The increased output of CT data has been made available to facilitate new exhibits, interactive activities, and educational modules through the Florida Museum of Natural History Education and Exhibition Center and nearby Cade Museum of Creativity and Innovation. These initiatives allow important and rare specimens to be viewed and analyzed worldwide by anyone with a computer and internet access, thereby greatly expanding US natural history collections' research and educational footprint through UF's oVert project. The oVert project has scanned and disseminated nearly 8,000 vertebrate specimens from 18 US collections. Until the acquisition of the Versa CT, most of these scans returned skeletal anatomy only, partially because none of the participating institutions had a machine that was able to recover soft tissue information without using destructive or invasive staining methods, which are unviable for rare specimens.        Last Modified: 03/16/2023       Submitted by: Luisa A Dempere]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
