<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[MRI: Development of an Energy Loss Optical Scintillation System (ELOSS), for Heavy-Ion Particle Identification (PID) to Advance Nuclear Physics Experiments]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>588000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>588000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Allena K. Opper</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>aopper@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928958</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This Major Research Instrumentation award will support development and deployment of a novel instrument that will precisely identify heavy-ion particles to advance nuclear science studies with rare-isotope beams. The Energy Loss Optical Scintillation System (ELOSS) will advance the research infrastructure for radiation-detection physics and technology, which will lead to breakthroughs in nuclear physics and nuclear astrophysics. ELOSS will also help realize the unprecedented discovery potential of the Facility for Rare Isotope Beams (FRIB), currently under construction on the campus of Michigan State University. FRIB will be the world’s premier rare-isotope beam facility producing a majority (~80%) of the isotopes that are created in the cosmos, which then decay into the elements found on Earth. Studying these short-lived rare atomic nuclei will help scientists understand the origins of the elements. The same isotopes are needed to develop a predictive model of atomic nuclei and how they interact, and advance knowledge in materials science, nuclear medicine, and homeland security. ELOSS will allow significant advances in multi-messenger nuclear astrophysics studies, the physics of neutron stars, and the exploration of the forces that bind nucleons into nuclei.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;State-of-the-art experimental equipment like ELOSS will tap FRIB’s unprecedented discovery potential by studying isotopes at a high beam rate and high performance. The ELOSS device will broadly impact radiation-detection physics and technology. It will generate new insights into the physics processes, technological aspects, and operational parameters of the modern gas-based detector combined with advanced solid-state photo-sensors, under harsh heavy-ion beam conditions. Its operational principle is based on the detection of pure noble-gas scintillation for particle identification in nuclear physics experiments with heavy ions and is highly innovative. The expected benefit for identifying nuclear reaction products will be a superior energy resolution — three times better than present technology. This will lead to an unprecedented element-identification capability, a uniform response over large detection areas, and a high counting rate capability (above 100 kHz). As a result, ELOSS is expected to provide new opportunities for experiments with rare-isotope beams at FRIB.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/11/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/07/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2017986</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Steven</FirstName>
<LastName>Lidia</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Steven Lidia</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[Lidia@frib.msu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000658775</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/13/2022</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Remco</FirstName>
<LastName>Zegers</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>G</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Remco G Zegers</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[zegers@nscl.msu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000508973</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/11/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alexandra</FirstName>
<LastName>Gade</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alexandra Gade</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[gade@nscl.msu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000328675</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/11/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Marco</FirstName>
<LastName>Cortesi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Marco Cortesi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[cortesi@nscl.msu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000706055</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/11/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Michigan State University</Name>
<CityName>EAST LANSING</CityName>
<ZipCode>488242600</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5173555040</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>426 AUDITORIUM RD RM 2</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>R28EKN92ZTZ9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MICHIGAN STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>VJKZC4D1JN36</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Michigan State University]]></Name>
<CityName>East Lansing</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>488242600</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[640 South Shaw Lane]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>Major Research Instrumentation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~588000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Energy Loss Optical Scintillation System (ELOSS) development project aimed at advancing instrumentation for heavy-ion identification in nuclear physics experiments using rare-isotope beams. ELOSS is a cutting-edge technology that makes use of a novel detector scheme to provide particle identification information at the forefront of nuclear physics experiments.</p> <p>FRIB is the world?s premier rare-isotope beam facility capable of producing the majority (~80%) of the isotopes that are created in the cosmos, which then decay into the elements and isotopes found on Earth. Studying these short-lived rare atomic nuclei will help scientists to understand the origins of chemical elements. The same isotopes are needed to develop a predictive model of atomic nuclei and how they interact. This will also advance knowledge in materials science, nuclear medicine, and homeland security. About 40% of the experiments performed at FRIB are expected to gain from the use of the novel ELOSS detector. It will allow significant progress in multi-messenger nuclear astrophysics studies, the physics of neutron stars, and the exploration of the forces that bind nucleons into nuclei. With state-of-the-art experimental equipment like ELOSS, FRIB will be able to study isotopes at high beam rates and with high performance. In addition to providing new opportunities for the low-energy nuclear physics program, achieved at one of the most advanced heavy-ion accelerator, ELOSS also provided significant information on the development and operational parameters of gas-based detectors that use advanced solid-state photosensors. Such information will benefit heavy-ion detector physics, but may also be crucial for applications in other fields of research as well. ELOSS is expected to serve the FRIB user community over the next decades as a key component of the S800 spectrometer. As a result this will enhance the scientific outcomes of many user programs.</p> <p>The most prominent features of ELOSS performance are: the high energy resolution that can be achieved (resolution in &Delta;E/E of better than 0.4%, a factor of three improvement over the presently used ionization chamber) for a wide range of atomic numbers (Z) and the ability to operate at a high counting rate (at least one order of magnitude higher than the current &Delta;E/E detector technology). Unlike the conventional ionization chamber, ELOSS also provides timing information with good resolution: below 100 ps full-width at half-maximum (FWHM) across the full active volume. It also provides a moderate localization capability (a few mm FWHM).</p> <p>The ELOSS project has allowed us to train students and young researchers in modern cutting-edge detection techniques, enabling them to participate in forefront nuclear physics experiments at the world most advanced rare-isotope beam facility. The project directly involved undergraduate students in the ELOSS development, construction, and testing, and it is the subject of a Ph.D. thesis.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/24/2023<br>      Modified by: Marco&nbsp;Cortesi</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Energy Loss Optical Scintillation System (ELOSS) development project aimed at advancing instrumentation for heavy-ion identification in nuclear physics experiments using rare-isotope beams. ELOSS is a cutting-edge technology that makes use of a novel detector scheme to provide particle identification information at the forefront of nuclear physics experiments.  FRIB is the world?s premier rare-isotope beam facility capable of producing the majority (~80%) of the isotopes that are created in the cosmos, which then decay into the elements and isotopes found on Earth. Studying these short-lived rare atomic nuclei will help scientists to understand the origins of chemical elements. The same isotopes are needed to develop a predictive model of atomic nuclei and how they interact. This will also advance knowledge in materials science, nuclear medicine, and homeland security. About 40% of the experiments performed at FRIB are expected to gain from the use of the novel ELOSS detector. It will allow significant progress in multi-messenger nuclear astrophysics studies, the physics of neutron stars, and the exploration of the forces that bind nucleons into nuclei. With state-of-the-art experimental equipment like ELOSS, FRIB will be able to study isotopes at high beam rates and with high performance. In addition to providing new opportunities for the low-energy nuclear physics program, achieved at one of the most advanced heavy-ion accelerator, ELOSS also provided significant information on the development and operational parameters of gas-based detectors that use advanced solid-state photosensors. Such information will benefit heavy-ion detector physics, but may also be crucial for applications in other fields of research as well. ELOSS is expected to serve the FRIB user community over the next decades as a key component of the S800 spectrometer. As a result this will enhance the scientific outcomes of many user programs.  The most prominent features of ELOSS performance are: the high energy resolution that can be achieved (resolution in &Delta;E/E of better than 0.4%, a factor of three improvement over the presently used ionization chamber) for a wide range of atomic numbers (Z) and the ability to operate at a high counting rate (at least one order of magnitude higher than the current &Delta;E/E detector technology). Unlike the conventional ionization chamber, ELOSS also provides timing information with good resolution: below 100 ps full-width at half-maximum (FWHM) across the full active volume. It also provides a moderate localization capability (a few mm FWHM).  The ELOSS project has allowed us to train students and young researchers in modern cutting-edge detection techniques, enabling them to participate in forefront nuclear physics experiments at the world most advanced rare-isotope beam facility. The project directly involved undergraduate students in the ELOSS development, construction, and testing, and it is the subject of a Ph.D. thesis.          Last Modified: 10/24/2023       Submitted by: Marco Cortesi]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
