<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Doctoral Dissertation Research: Impact of Various Storage Temperatures andTtime on Microbiome of Forensically Relevant Biological Samples]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>30527.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>30527</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Reginald Sheehan</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rsheehan@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925389</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The confirmatory identification of forensically relevant body fluids is a fundamental part to forensic investigations as this information can aid investigators in crime scene reconstruction and resolving mixtures such as those often encountered in sexual assault cases.  The majority of current body fluid identification methods are presumptive, and the sample consumption is not ideal for forensic casework. For new methods to be accepted into the community, methods should be robust, reliable, sensitive, and confirmatory to each body fluid while producing stable results over time.  This study aims to determine how short- and long-term storage conditions of human biological samples impact the microbial community structures associated with these samples, and to determine whether these conditions impact the accuracy of a newly developed microbial signature-based method for the body fluid identification.  Biological sample storage regulations were created without microbial evidence in mind, and it is therefore important to determine whether these samples are stable under various storage times and temperatures. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will 1) look at the microbial signatures of each body fluid to determine whether there are significant differences in their compositions once stored at various temperatures at extended periods of time and 2) determine whether these storage conditions impact the accuracy of the previously developed body fluid identification method.  Samples from ten individuals will be stored at four different temperatures (-20째C, 4째C, 25째C, 37째C) for 3 storage periods (30 days, 60 days, 90 days). To evaluate these changes, 16S rDNA dual-index high throughput sequencing will be performed using the MiSeq FGx sequencing platform. Data analysis will follow the mothur MiSeq SOP.  The variation in bacterial signatures will be assessed between all temperature/time groups. Ensemble subspace classification and L1-norm regularized classification methods previously developed will be tested using the bacterial structures obtained to determine how storage conditions may impact the classification accuracy.  The findings from this study will be useful in streamlining the previously developed body fluid identification method and will provide additional suggestions for standard operating procedures.  This is not only useful for the forensic science community but can contribute to stability, standardization, and mobility of microbial research as a whole.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/05/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/05/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2017519</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Baneshwar</FirstName>
<LastName>Singh</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Baneshwar Singh</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[bsingh@vcu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000783139</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/05/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Denise</FirstName>
<LastName>Wohlfahrt</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Denise Wohlfahrt</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[wohlfahrtdm@vcu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000818736</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/05/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Virginia Commonwealth University</Name>
<CityName>RICHMOND</CityName>
<ZipCode>232849005</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8048286772</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>910 WEST FRANKLIN ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>VA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>MLQFL4JSSAA9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>VIRGINIA COMMONWEALTH UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Virginia Commonwealth University]]></Name>
<CityName>Richmond</CityName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>232843079</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1015 Floyd Ave., Harris Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>VA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>128Y</Code>
<Text>Law &amp; Science</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~30527</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The purpose of this research was to better streamline a bacteria signature-based body fluid identification method and to provide standard operating procedures to crime labs on sample collection and storage. Specifically, this research aimed to determine how short- and long-term storage (up to 90 days) of forensically relevant body fluids at various temperatures impact bacterial community structures associated with these samples, and to determine if these variations impact the accuracy of our previously developed body fluid identification method. Biological sample storage regulations were not created with microbial evidence in mind, so determining whether storage time and temperatures impact these bacterial communities was of the utmost importance.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Saliva, venous blood, feces, semen, menstrual blood, and vaginal fluid samples from ten individuals (n=728) were stored at four different temperatures (-20&deg;C, 4&deg;C, 25&deg;C, 37&deg;C) for three storage periods (30 days, 60 days, 90 days). To evaluate these changes, variable region four (V4) of 16S rDNA dual-index high throughput sequencing was performed on a MiSeq FGx sequencing platform. Statistical analyses were implemented to determine whether the bacterial DNA yields and communities significantly differed. Various storage temperatures impacted average bacterial DNA yield significantly, but this did not impact bacterial community structure, regardless of storage period&#8203;s&#8203;. While some individual variations ca&#8203;n &#8203;exist&#8203;&nbsp;between donors, the lack of significant differences in bacterial community structures&nbsp;&#8203;at various temperatures and storage time, &#8203;suggest that the&nbsp;&#8203;newly developed &#8203;bacterial signature based method for&nbsp;&#8203;accurate prediction of &#8203;forensically relevant&nbsp;&#8203;human &#8203;body fluid&nbsp;&#8203;samples &#8203;remains robust.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The future integration of our method with a commercially available high throughput sequencing panel will assist the crime lab practitioner to utilize a method that is capable of not only the individualization of a person of interest but can also identify the source of a biological sample. This method for the confirmatory identification of human body fluids will be based in science and will strengthen the criminal justice system because these samples will be identified from evidence samples with known error rates, an important criterion for forensic cases. The utility of microbial data is expanding globally, and it is therefore becoming more important than ever to determine what factors impact the microbiome. This is not only a great aid to the forensic community but can&nbsp;also &#8203;contribute&nbsp;&#8203;in&#8203;&nbsp;standardization of&nbsp;&#8203;other &#8203;microbiological research&#8203; areas&#8203;.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/30/2022<br>      Modified by: Baneshwar&nbsp;Singh</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The purpose of this research was to better streamline a bacteria signature-based body fluid identification method and to provide standard operating procedures to crime labs on sample collection and storage. Specifically, this research aimed to determine how short- and long-term storage (up to 90 days) of forensically relevant body fluids at various temperatures impact bacterial community structures associated with these samples, and to determine if these variations impact the accuracy of our previously developed body fluid identification method. Biological sample storage regulations were not created with microbial evidence in mind, so determining whether storage time and temperatures impact these bacterial communities was of the utmost importance.      Saliva, venous blood, feces, semen, menstrual blood, and vaginal fluid samples from ten individuals (n=728) were stored at four different temperatures (-20&deg;C, 4&deg;C, 25&deg;C, 37&deg;C) for three storage periods (30 days, 60 days, 90 days). To evaluate these changes, variable region four (V4) of 16S rDNA dual-index high throughput sequencing was performed on a MiSeq FGx sequencing platform. Statistical analyses were implemented to determine whether the bacterial DNA yields and communities significantly differed. Various storage temperatures impacted average bacterial DNA yield significantly, but this did not impact bacterial community structure, regardless of storage period&#8203;s&#8203;. While some individual variations ca&#8203;n &#8203;exist&#8203; between donors, the lack of significant differences in bacterial community structures &#8203;at various temperatures and storage time, &#8203;suggest that the &#8203;newly developed &#8203;bacterial signature based method for &#8203;accurate prediction of &#8203;forensically relevant &#8203;human &#8203;body fluid &#8203;samples &#8203;remains robust.     The future integration of our method with a commercially available high throughput sequencing panel will assist the crime lab practitioner to utilize a method that is capable of not only the individualization of a person of interest but can also identify the source of a biological sample. This method for the confirmatory identification of human body fluids will be based in science and will strengthen the criminal justice system because these samples will be identified from evidence samples with known error rates, an important criterion for forensic cases. The utility of microbial data is expanding globally, and it is therefore becoming more important than ever to determine what factors impact the microbiome. This is not only a great aid to the forensic community but can also &#8203;contribute &#8203;in&#8203; standardization of &#8203;other &#8203;microbiological research&#8203; areas&#8203;.              Last Modified: 11/30/2022       Submitted by: Baneshwar Singh]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
