<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Doctoral Dissertation Research: Translation, Scientization, and Branding in Medical Markets]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>25109.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>25109</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jeffrey Mantz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jmantz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927783</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Natural products, broadly sourced from plants and animal parts, are consumed worldwide to enhance general health and well-being. A lucrative industry that manufactures and sells natural products as medicines and dietary supplements increasingly relies on scientific evidence of these products’ medical effectiveness as communicated by medical professionals, scientists, marketers, and government agencies in official reports and routine conversations. This linguistic anthropological dissertation project investigates how scientific research on the effectiveness of natural products is translated into everyday language to market their therapeutic properties. Research findings will be disseminated to medical professionals in the pharmaceutical industry, scientific academies, government agencies, and NGOs who seek to educate about scientific literacy to help the public make informed decisions about the consumption of natural products. The research will further aid policy makers in introducing and regulating natural products in national health care systems. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research investigate how scientific terminologies and language are used to brand natural products as effective medicine and communicate their value in different national and global medical markets. The researcher will carry out linguistic and ethnographic research in farms, laboratories, and marketplaces where natural products are cultivated, manufactured, studied, and marketed to consumers. Using the methods of participant observation to study work activities, semi-structured interviews, analyzing scientific papers, and media and archival research, the researcher will examine how networks between the government, the farming industry, scientists, pharmaceutical companies, and consumers facilitate communication about the scientific properties of natural products. The results of this research will contribute to anthropological theories about science’s role in shaping social institutions, government, and global markets, by providing empirical data on the use of language in creating scientific evidence.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/12/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/12/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2017457</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sonia</FirstName>
<LastName>Das</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>N</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sonia N Das</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[sd99@nyu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000200459</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/12/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Hyemin</FirstName>
<LastName>Lee</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Hyemin Lee</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[hyeminlee@nyu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000819341</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/12/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>New York University</Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<ZipCode>100121019</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2129982121</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>70 WASHINGTON SQ S</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NX9PXMKW5KW8</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NEW YORK UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Seoul National University]]></Name>
<CityName>Seoul</CityName>
<StateCode/>
<ZipCode>08826</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1 Gwanakro, Gwanakgu]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>KS</CountryCode>
<CountryName>Korea, South</CountryName>
<StateName>RI REQUIRED</StateName>
<CountryFlag>0</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>"07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7605</Code>
<Text>Cult Anthro DDRI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1390</Code>
<Text>CULTURAL ANTHROPOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~25109</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This research project investigates how scientific research on the effectiveness of natural products is translated into everyday language to market their therapeutic properties. As a response to the constant demand for well-being and a growing public interest in general health due to the COVID-19 pandemic, the natural product industry has experienced an upward trend in sales in national and global markets. Hence became important is crafting more efficient branding narratives by translating scientific accounts on natural products' medical effectiveness into a more consumer-friendly language that encompasses a worldwide audience. Understanding these translation practices and processes will address answers to key questions on how the language of scientific evidence travels and transforms through different social spaces, such as in laboratories, farm fields, and national and global markets.</p> <p>The co-PI Hyemin Lee, under the supervision of the PI Dr. Sonia Das of New York University, conducted 18-month ethnographic research in South Korea, specifically in eleven regions where the production, manufacture, and sales of natural products significantly led the local economy. The co-PI carried out participant observations and interviews with scientists, staff, and farmers at a natural product transnational corporation based in Seoul, South Korea. Due to the pandemic, the co-PI used non-face-to-face qualitative research methods, such as conducting remote interviews, participating in live-streamed meetings and events, and observing online conversations and interactions. The ethnographic fieldwork was supplemented with archival and media research, where the co-PI compiled various documents and video collections from on-site and digital archives.</p> <p>During the research period, the co-PI collected written and spoken narratives on the scientific properties of natural products from various people who took part in the natural product industry. These included scientists, farmers, manufacturers, individual sellers, and employers working at natural product companies. The collected narratives ranged from written forms and documents, diaries, presentation slides, and conference materials to verbal interactions, anecdotes, and branding/marketing repertoires. In delivering crucial information such as product details and benefits to the consumer public, the narratives indicated that the natural product industry increasingly relied on scientific accounts that elucidated the medical effectiveness of natural products.</p> <p>Some narratives of scientific properties differed in the levels of the scientific details and linguistic features, although there had been continuous, public-private efforts of scientizing and promoting natural products. These narratives further included descriptions of historical, political-economic relations in farming, sales, and branding practices which might conflict with official narratives by the natural product industry. Also, the co-PI found that new narratives emerged and circulated as close communications and collaborative interactions among industry partakers established a shared understanding of scientific evidence for the medical effectiveness of the natural product. These observations show that these narratives are not just collections of stories about scientific findings but are key to the production and transformation of historical and sociocultural relations; and simultaneously, these relations enable, shape, and constrain the articulation and circulation of scientific narratives in social life.</p> <p>In addition, the co-PI closely followed a cultural heritage project initiated by an association comprised of the stakeholders in the natural product industry: scientists, local farmers, manufacturers, and sellers. The co-PI observed ongoing debates by individuals and communities who participated in the project, specifically on how to redefine the natural product as having a living culture. For example, controversies arose as scientific evidence of natural products' therapeutic properties was deemed not significant in shaping cultural heritage narratives, although the role of scientific research on therapeutic mechanisms and properties had grown more and more critical in the natural product industry. In this respect, this research carefully examined another translational route where the language of scientific evidence travels from scientific research papers to anthropological and folklore studies narratives.</p> <p>This research contributes to the anthropological conversation about science's role in shaping and conditioning the scope of traditional medicines in global markets by providing empirical data on the use of scientific evidence for branding. In analyzing how public and private sectors collaboratively used scientific accounts to promote natural products, this research also advances anthropological understandings of the government's role in regulatory policies and processes. This research may interest policymakers and those working in the medical/pharmaceutical industries since the research presents an integrative approach to natural product regulations by touching upon core objectives commonly adopted in regulatory policies, such as access, safety, efficacy, and quality. Also, government agencies and others who develop consumer education programs may find this research beneficial, as the research analyzes branding narratives and practices targeted to reach out to domestic and global consumers. Lastly, those involved in the bio-sovereignty movement, cultural heritage policies, and other related fields may find this research a relevant case study, as it accounts for the processes, controversies, and debates developed in a grassroots cultural heritage project.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/11/2022<br>      Modified by: Hyemin&nbsp;Lee</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This research project investigates how scientific research on the effectiveness of natural products is translated into everyday language to market their therapeutic properties. As a response to the constant demand for well-being and a growing public interest in general health due to the COVID-19 pandemic, the natural product industry has experienced an upward trend in sales in national and global markets. Hence became important is crafting more efficient branding narratives by translating scientific accounts on natural products' medical effectiveness into a more consumer-friendly language that encompasses a worldwide audience. Understanding these translation practices and processes will address answers to key questions on how the language of scientific evidence travels and transforms through different social spaces, such as in laboratories, farm fields, and national and global markets.  The co-PI Hyemin Lee, under the supervision of the PI Dr. Sonia Das of New York University, conducted 18-month ethnographic research in South Korea, specifically in eleven regions where the production, manufacture, and sales of natural products significantly led the local economy. The co-PI carried out participant observations and interviews with scientists, staff, and farmers at a natural product transnational corporation based in Seoul, South Korea. Due to the pandemic, the co-PI used non-face-to-face qualitative research methods, such as conducting remote interviews, participating in live-streamed meetings and events, and observing online conversations and interactions. The ethnographic fieldwork was supplemented with archival and media research, where the co-PI compiled various documents and video collections from on-site and digital archives.  During the research period, the co-PI collected written and spoken narratives on the scientific properties of natural products from various people who took part in the natural product industry. These included scientists, farmers, manufacturers, individual sellers, and employers working at natural product companies. The collected narratives ranged from written forms and documents, diaries, presentation slides, and conference materials to verbal interactions, anecdotes, and branding/marketing repertoires. In delivering crucial information such as product details and benefits to the consumer public, the narratives indicated that the natural product industry increasingly relied on scientific accounts that elucidated the medical effectiveness of natural products.  Some narratives of scientific properties differed in the levels of the scientific details and linguistic features, although there had been continuous, public-private efforts of scientizing and promoting natural products. These narratives further included descriptions of historical, political-economic relations in farming, sales, and branding practices which might conflict with official narratives by the natural product industry. Also, the co-PI found that new narratives emerged and circulated as close communications and collaborative interactions among industry partakers established a shared understanding of scientific evidence for the medical effectiveness of the natural product. These observations show that these narratives are not just collections of stories about scientific findings but are key to the production and transformation of historical and sociocultural relations; and simultaneously, these relations enable, shape, and constrain the articulation and circulation of scientific narratives in social life.  In addition, the co-PI closely followed a cultural heritage project initiated by an association comprised of the stakeholders in the natural product industry: scientists, local farmers, manufacturers, and sellers. The co-PI observed ongoing debates by individuals and communities who participated in the project, specifically on how to redefine the natural product as having a living culture. For example, controversies arose as scientific evidence of natural products' therapeutic properties was deemed not significant in shaping cultural heritage narratives, although the role of scientific research on therapeutic mechanisms and properties had grown more and more critical in the natural product industry. In this respect, this research carefully examined another translational route where the language of scientific evidence travels from scientific research papers to anthropological and folklore studies narratives.  This research contributes to the anthropological conversation about science's role in shaping and conditioning the scope of traditional medicines in global markets by providing empirical data on the use of scientific evidence for branding. In analyzing how public and private sectors collaboratively used scientific accounts to promote natural products, this research also advances anthropological understandings of the government's role in regulatory policies and processes. This research may interest policymakers and those working in the medical/pharmaceutical industries since the research presents an integrative approach to natural product regulations by touching upon core objectives commonly adopted in regulatory policies, such as access, safety, efficacy, and quality. Also, government agencies and others who develop consumer education programs may find this research beneficial, as the research analyzes branding narratives and practices targeted to reach out to domestic and global consumers. Lastly, those involved in the bio-sovereignty movement, cultural heritage policies, and other related fields may find this research a relevant case study, as it accounts for the processes, controversies, and debates developed in a grassroots cultural heritage project.          Last Modified: 10/11/2022       Submitted by: Hyemin Lee]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
