<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Workshop: Building Leadership Capacity for Systemic, Scalable and Sustainable Change in Undergraduate Biology Education; Spring, 2019]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>17686.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>17686</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DBI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Amanda Simcox</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>asimcox@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928165</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[There is an increasing need for building campus leadership capacity to facilitate institutional change that improves undergraduate Biology student learning, retention and graduation. While the approaches for making these improvements are well-known, their application on campuses is still not wide-spread. To facilitate implementation of these improvements, campus leaders play critical roles. In particular, those leaders with decision-making authority over budget, personnel and policy (e.g., deans) can either be gatekeepers or gateways to promoting the success of these efforts. A recent review makes the case for the need to develop shared leadership models in higher education to more effectively solve the increasingly complex problems facing colleges and universities. However, there is no clear definition of the skills required to lead using this type of model, nor are there manuals, workshops or other resources to help leaders develop these competencies. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed workshop will bring together positional leaders to reflect on both their experience and the current leadership development literature to define the set of distinctive competencies required to lead scalable, sustainable systemic institutional change. These competencies will be defined and then used as the basis for building resources that will be geared toward developing these competencies in positional leaders across the country. The set of competencies will be published in a summary article and used to create a plan for the development of leadership program resources. Participants will also contribute to the development of resources that can be made widely available for higher education leadership programs offered through higher education associations and other organizations. This will develop leaders who can more effectively implement, scale and sustain institutional change efforts geared towards improving undergraduate Biology student access, persistence and graduation of underrepresented minority students. This work may also lead to additional workshops to develop corresponding competencies for faculty, staff and students who are participants in campus change projects. Finally, this work will contribute to the development of new research questions regarding how well leaders who have been exposed to the new resources exhibit the competencies and use them to more effectively lead campus change efforts. This award is supported by the Division of Biological Infrastructure in the Biological Sciences Directorate and the Division of Undergraduate Education in the Education and Human Resources Directorate.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/18/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/17/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2017799</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Susan</FirstName>
<LastName>Elrod</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Susan Elrod</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[slelrod@iusb.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000643314</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/18/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Indiana University</Name>
<CityName>BLOOMINGTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>474057000</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3172783473</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>107 S INDIANA AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IN09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>YH86RTW2YVJ4</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF INDIANA UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>YH86RTW2YVJ4</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Indiana University]]></Name>
<CityName>Bloomington</CityName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>474013654</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IN09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>037Y</Code>
<Text>UBE - Undergraduate Biology Ed</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1998</Code>
<Text>IUSE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0418</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01001819DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>04001819DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~17685</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This Building Leadership Capacity project resulted in the articulation of eight categories of specific leadership competencies, or "change leader moves", that contribute to&nbsp;implementing, scaling, and sustaining campus change initiatives. The eight categories are: create vision, develop strategy, foster diversity, lead people and teams, advocate and navigate politics, communicate effectively, sensemaking and learning, and prepare for success over the long-term.&nbsp;Each category contains 5-12 sub-moves that characterize the category with more specific actions leaders can take. A worksheet for change leaders has been developed that helps them understand the moves and identify which moves they should make, along with other resources to help leaders and leadership teams assess their change initiative context and how it might present opportunities or challenges for successfully implementing and sustaining change over the long term.&nbsp;The description of the change leader moves in a useable framework has already proven useful to those who have been involved in testing and providing input.</p> <p>Seventy-six (76) individuals were engaged in or consulted with during the project timeframe to make contributions to and provide input on the Change Leader Moves. These individuals encompassed faculty leaders, program directors, project coordinators, department chairs, deans, associate deans, provosts, associate provosts, and campus presidents. They were from 37 different institutions of higher education that ranged from large, research universities to public comprehensive and minority-serving universities to smaller private colleges. Nine (9) national organizations, associations or national projects also provided input and several others were also engaged in learning about the project. Thirteen (13) webinars and four (4) project meetings were conducted to not only solicit input but to engage leaders in learning about the emerging resources.&nbsp;</p> <p>The project continues to develop unique perspectives and resources regarding the articulation and operationalization of change leadership.&nbsp;It has engaged leaders beyond Biology (or even STEM-specific) education as institutional change projects necessarily involve departments and units across a university.&nbsp;The final development of a full Toolkit for Systemic Change in Higher Education with additional resources for change leaders and change leader teams is under development in a separate project with funding from The Bill &amp; Melinda Gates Foundation.&nbsp;The results of this work will make contributions to the change leadership and management literature within higher education at a variety of institutional types regarding a variety of institutional change project outcomes. In the end, the goal is to create more effective leaders who will be able to more effectively make the changes needed to improve student learning, success, and inclusion.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/02/2022<br>      Modified by: Susan&nbsp;Elrod</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This Building Leadership Capacity project resulted in the articulation of eight categories of specific leadership competencies, or "change leader moves", that contribute to implementing, scaling, and sustaining campus change initiatives. The eight categories are: create vision, develop strategy, foster diversity, lead people and teams, advocate and navigate politics, communicate effectively, sensemaking and learning, and prepare for success over the long-term. Each category contains 5-12 sub-moves that characterize the category with more specific actions leaders can take. A worksheet for change leaders has been developed that helps them understand the moves and identify which moves they should make, along with other resources to help leaders and leadership teams assess their change initiative context and how it might present opportunities or challenges for successfully implementing and sustaining change over the long term. The description of the change leader moves in a useable framework has already proven useful to those who have been involved in testing and providing input.  Seventy-six (76) individuals were engaged in or consulted with during the project timeframe to make contributions to and provide input on the Change Leader Moves. These individuals encompassed faculty leaders, program directors, project coordinators, department chairs, deans, associate deans, provosts, associate provosts, and campus presidents. They were from 37 different institutions of higher education that ranged from large, research universities to public comprehensive and minority-serving universities to smaller private colleges. Nine (9) national organizations, associations or national projects also provided input and several others were also engaged in learning about the project. Thirteen (13) webinars and four (4) project meetings were conducted to not only solicit input but to engage leaders in learning about the emerging resources.   The project continues to develop unique perspectives and resources regarding the articulation and operationalization of change leadership. It has engaged leaders beyond Biology (or even STEM-specific) education as institutional change projects necessarily involve departments and units across a university. The final development of a full Toolkit for Systemic Change in Higher Education with additional resources for change leaders and change leader teams is under development in a separate project with funding from The Bill &amp; Melinda Gates Foundation. The results of this work will make contributions to the change leadership and management literature within higher education at a variety of institutional types regarding a variety of institutional change project outcomes. In the end, the goal is to create more effective leaders who will be able to more effectively make the changes needed to improve student learning, success, and inclusion.        Last Modified: 06/02/2022       Submitted by: Susan Elrod]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
