<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Enhancing Biology Education Research by Bridging Disciplinary Boundaries between Discipline-based Education Research in Biology and Learning Sciences.]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>49745.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>49745</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DBI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Amanda Simcox</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>asimcox@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928165</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[A working knowledge of biology is increasingly important as society grapples with new genetic technologies, conservation, and the impacts of climate change. To help ensure a scientifically literate society that is prepared to deal with these issues, it is thus in the national interest to develop effective methods of teaching biological concepts. To that end, collaborations between scientists in discipline-based education research in biology (DBER-BIO) and learning sciences (LS; including cognitive, educational, and developmental psychology) have resulted in new theories and pedagogical strategies that advance understanding of learning in biology. Despite the benefits, however, these partnerships are relatively uncommon. Although the DBER-BIO and LS communities share the goal of understanding learning, connecting the two groups is often hindered by differences in training, methodologies, and practices. To facilitate collaboration between DBER-BIO and LS, the PI team will host a one-day workshop. The goals of the workshop are to develop connections between researchers from different disciplines, increase awareness of differences and similarities in perspectives towards education research, and equip participants with strategies for engaging in interdisciplinary work. Fostering these interdisciplinary collaborations will result in improved research on learning in biology that will ultimately improve undergraduate biology education.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will support a one-day workshop for researchers in the LS and DBER-BIO communities. The workshop will foster interdisciplinary connections and identify strategies for collaboration through three activities: small group work, a panel discussion session with researchers who have experience in interdisciplinary collaborations, and a poster session. By the end of the workshop, it is anticipated that participants will have gained an appreciation of the value of interdisciplinary research and be equipped to pursue it. Data collected during the workshop will include discussion comments, collaborative strategies, and responses to an end-of-workshop survey. This data will be analyzed qualitatively using an in vivo approach for the first cycle of coding and focused coding for the second cycle to identify workshop outcomes. In turn, these will be evaluated to determine if the anticipated outcomes were met and to identify barriers to and facilitators of interdisciplinary collaboration as well as productive collaborative strategies. The PI team intends to share the results of this analysis through a meeting report, thus enabling the insights and strategies generated in the workshop to reach a broad audience.This project is being jointly funded by the Directorate for Biological Sciences, Division of Biological Infrastructure, and the Directorate for Education and Human Resources, Division of Undergraduate Education as part of their efforts to address the challenges posed in "Vision and Change in Undergraduate Biology Education: A Call to Action" (http://visionandchange/finalreport).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/19/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/19/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2017278</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Melanie</FirstName>
<LastName>Peffer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Melanie Peffer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[melanie.peffer@colorado.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000743188</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/19/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Colorado at Boulder</Name>
<CityName>BOULDER</CityName>
<ZipCode>803090001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3034926221</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3100 MARINE ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[STE 481 572 UCB]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>SPVKK1RC2MZ3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>THE REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF COLORADO</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Colorado at Boulder]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>803031058</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>037Y</Code>
<Text>UBE - Undergraduate Biology Ed</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1998</Code>
<Text>IUSE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1664</Code>
<Text>RESEARCH COORD NETWK IN BIO SC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0420</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>04002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~49745</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p> <div class="public-DraftStyleDefault-block public-DraftStyleDefault-ltr"><span>Effective science education is important for the well being of our society. Science education requires two things. First, we need deep science knowledge. Second, we need deep knowledge of how people learn. </span><span class="adverb"><span>Traditionally</span></span><span class="hardreadability"><span>, people with deep science knowledge are not the same people with deep knowledge of  learning</span></span><span>. Within the last ten years, researchers called for these two groups of people to work together. </span><span class="hardreadability"><span> For example, if we combine biology knowledge with knowledge of how people learn, we can better understand how people learn science</span></span><span>. When people from different backgrounds work together, we call it </span><span>interdisciplinary research</span><span>.&nbsp;</span></div> <div> <div class="public-DraftStyleDefault-block public-DraftStyleDefault-ltr"><span><br /></span></div> </div> <div> <div class="public-DraftStyleDefault-block public-DraftStyleDefault-ltr"><span class="hardreadability"><span>Interdisciplinary research in science education is a powerful way to find out new things about how people learn science</span></span><span>. Interdisciplinary research is also difficult. Since it is difficult, many people do not do interdisciplinary research. </span><span class="hardreadability"><span><span> </span></span><span><span>Our goal for this project was to help people do interdisciplinary research in science education</span></span></span><span>.&nbsp;</span></div> </div> <div> <div class="public-DraftStyleDefault-block public-DraftStyleDefault-ltr"><span><br /></span></div> </div> <div> <div class="public-DraftStyleDefault-block public-DraftStyleDefault-ltr"><span>We held two professional development workshops. We invited people from a different disciplinary backgrounds. During the workshops, we also seeded people into interdisciplinary groups. We exposed participants to a variety of different viewpoints. This included different ways people can design research and different methodologies. Workshop participants also generated lists of strategies for interdisciplinary collaboration. Workshop participants were also exposed to different flavors of interdisciplinary research. For example, in our first workshop we held a panelist discussion. Finally, we collected notes from both workshops, and gave a post-workshop survey.</span></div> </div> <div> <div class="public-DraftStyleDefault-block public-DraftStyleDefault-ltr"><span><br /></span></div> </div> <div> <div class="public-DraftStyleDefault-block public-DraftStyleDefault-ltr"><span>During the workshops, participants learned how to overcome differences and work </span><span class="adverb"><span>effectively</span></span><span> together. </span><span class="hardreadability"><span>We expect that these relationships will lead to better understanding of how people lean in science</span></span><span>. </span><span class="hardreadability"><span>If we have a better idea of how people learn science, this will lead to a more </span></span><span class="adverb"><span>scientifically</span></span><span class="hardreadability"><span> literate workforce</span></span><span>. </span><span class="hardreadability"><span>We expect that attendees also passed these insights along to their research mentees and classroom students</span></span><span>.&nbsp;</span></div> </div> <div> <div class="public-DraftStyleDefault-block public-DraftStyleDefault-ltr"><span><br /></span></div> </div> <div> <div class="public-DraftStyleDefault-block public-DraftStyleDefault-ltr"><span>We collected data during the workshops. These findings were  published in the peer-review journal, PLOS-ONE. We found three  reasons why people struggle with interdisciplinary research in science education. </span><span class="veryhardreadability"><span>These reasons included trouble with practical differences between disciplines, not feeling like they belonged, and struggles to work as a team</span></span><span>. We found that people often felt isolated in their interdisciplinary endeavors. We found an increase in interdisciplinary collaboration among participants at our first workshop. Our findings give important directions for future professional development workshops. Interdisciplinary professional development workshops are an effective strategy for fostering new interdisciplinary collaborations.&nbsp;</span></div> </div> <div> <div class="public-DraftStyleDefault-block public-DraftStyleDefault-ltr"><span><br /></span></div> </div> <div> <div class="public-DraftStyleDefault-block public-DraftStyleDefault-ltr"><span>We also started a Blog for our community. The blog highlights  interdisciplinary research and/or perspectives on interdisciplinary research in education. We designed the style of the Blog to be accessible to all. The blog was also a place for researchers to hone their communication skills. For example, participants received one on one coaching on how to write for the general public.&nbsp;</span></div> </div> <div> <div class="public-DraftStyleDefault-block public-DraftStyleDefault-ltr"><span><br /></span></div> </div> </p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/01/2022<br>      Modified by: Melanie&nbsp;Peffer</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Effective science education is important for the well being of our society. Science education requires two things. First, we need deep science knowledge. Second, we need deep knowledge of how people learn. Traditionally, people with deep science knowledge are not the same people with deep knowledge of  learning. Within the last ten years, researchers called for these two groups of people to work together.  For example, if we combine biology knowledge with knowledge of how people learn, we can better understand how people learn science. When people from different backgrounds work together, we call it interdisciplinary research.       Interdisciplinary research in science education is a powerful way to find out new things about how people learn science. Interdisciplinary research is also difficult. Since it is difficult, many people do not do interdisciplinary research.  Our goal for this project was to help people do interdisciplinary research in science education.        We held two professional development workshops. We invited people from a different disciplinary backgrounds. During the workshops, we also seeded people into interdisciplinary groups. We exposed participants to a variety of different viewpoints. This included different ways people can design research and different methodologies. Workshop participants also generated lists of strategies for interdisciplinary collaboration. Workshop participants were also exposed to different flavors of interdisciplinary research. For example, in our first workshop we held a panelist discussion. Finally, we collected notes from both workshops, and gave a post-workshop survey.       During the workshops, participants learned how to overcome differences and work effectively together. We expect that these relationships will lead to better understanding of how people lean in science. If we have a better idea of how people learn science, this will lead to a more scientifically literate workforce. We expect that attendees also passed these insights along to their research mentees and classroom students.        We collected data during the workshops. These findings were  published in the peer-review journal, PLOS-ONE. We found three  reasons why people struggle with interdisciplinary research in science education. These reasons included trouble with practical differences between disciplines, not feeling like they belonged, and struggles to work as a team. We found that people often felt isolated in their interdisciplinary endeavors. We found an increase in interdisciplinary collaboration among participants at our first workshop. Our findings give important directions for future professional development workshops. Interdisciplinary professional development workshops are an effective strategy for fostering new interdisciplinary collaborations.        We also started a Blog for our community. The blog highlights  interdisciplinary research and/or perspectives on interdisciplinary research in education. We designed the style of the Blog to be accessible to all. The blog was also a place for researchers to hone their communication skills. For example, participants received one on one coaching on how to write for the general public.              Last Modified: 06/01/2022       Submitted by: Melanie Peffer]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
