<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research: Using Big Data to Analyze Maritime Conflict]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>81991.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>81991</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Lee Walker</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lwalker@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927174</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Maritime conflict has been on the rise globally, with hotspots across the world's regions. Despite growing coverage in the news media, among think tanks, and great attention from policy makers and politicians, there is limited systematic data on conflict incidents in maritime regions. This project will fill two important gaps. First, it will generate a multi-faceted dataset on maritime conflict that will be shared publicly for use by scholars and journalists. Second, although theorists have offered many competing accounts for what to expect in the realm of maritime conflict, there have yet to be any compelling empirical investigations of what has taken place in the past decade. This project will develop data collection techniques that will be applicable to a range of maritime conflict-affected regions, which also have substantial national security implications.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Social scientists have increasingly turned to data-driven approaches to answer important questions regarding international security. Within the world of conflict research, comprehensive datasets have played a critical role in advancing scientific knowledge (e.g. AidData, COW, ACLED). Thus far, however, there has been limited systematic empirical analysis of maritime conflict; a major hurdle is a lack of data. In this project, the PIs acquire and consolidate comprehensive data on maritime incidents and make substantial progress toward empirically testing and resolving competing theories for how maritime conflict may play out over the next decade. The project refines prevailing theories of power transition, taking into account the slow but steady change in maritime capabilities of superpowers as well as the growing economic and political interdependence among nation-states since the end of the Cold War, to generate new testable hypotheses. The analysis utilizes the overlapping EEZ zones and territorial waters, variation in off-shore natural resource distribution, and changes in domestic politics to test the proposed hypotheses. The data will be made publicly available and legible to other social scientists so that experts can replicate it for their own research purposes.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/07/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/07/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2017096</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nico</FirstName>
<LastName>Ravanilla</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nico Ravanilla</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[nravanilla@ucsd.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000661373</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/07/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-San Diego</Name>
<CityName>LA JOLLA</CityName>
<ZipCode>920930021</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8585344896</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>9500 GILMAN DRIVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>50</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA50</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>UYTTZT6G9DT1</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, SAN DIEGO</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-San Diego]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>920930934</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>50</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA50</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>118Y</Code>
<Text>Security &amp; Preparedness</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~81991</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project, entitled Collaborative Research: Using Big Data to Analyze Maritime Conflict, was a direct attempt to better understand the challenges and dynamics of South China Sea conflict. The research team, consisting of scholars and research assistants from multiple Southeast Asian countries, conducted a project with multiple methods of data collection and analysis. With the help of the National Science Foundation (NSF), the SCSDI project was able to collect an event dataset from 2010 to 2020 consisting of 1,241 datapoints, conduct two waves of online surveys in six countries across Southeast Asia, organize a policy/scholarship conference at Emory University and pilot survey of fisherfolk in the Philippines and Vietnam.</p> <p>The results from these efforts are numerous. First, the team was able to post both their event dataset and survey data publicly (scsdi.org) as well as write a working paper entitled &ldquo;Audience Cost or Posturing Premium? How Empty Threats Benefit Leaders in Small Countries.&rdquo; Additionally they wrote a policy whitepaper published by the Woodrow Wilson Center&rsquo;s China program, have a detailed outline for a book manuscript on &ldquo;The Politics of Regional Hegemony&rdquo;, organized a policy and scholarly conference on the South China Sea, developed a survey design for fisherfolk survey and trained multiple research assistants who have since gone on to start PhDs.</p> <p>Finally, with these results in hand we were able to engage with policy makers in the United States as well as in multiple countries across Southeast Asia including the Philippines, Vietnam and Singapore. Here we were able to share our findings and discuss how best to use these data points in decision making.</p> <p>Overall this project has been a success. Our data collection has provided much needed insights into maritime conflict in this region for both scholars and policy makers alike. These outcomes now provide us with a greater understanding that can be used not only for academic literature but also for constructive political dialogue between stakeholders. We hope that this new information can be used proactively to build bridges between nations and minimize potential conflict in the future.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/12/2023<br>      Modified by: Nico&nbsp;Ravanilla</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project, entitled Collaborative Research: Using Big Data to Analyze Maritime Conflict, was a direct attempt to better understand the challenges and dynamics of South China Sea conflict. The research team, consisting of scholars and research assistants from multiple Southeast Asian countries, conducted a project with multiple methods of data collection and analysis. With the help of the National Science Foundation (NSF), the SCSDI project was able to collect an event dataset from 2010 to 2020 consisting of 1,241 datapoints, conduct two waves of online surveys in six countries across Southeast Asia, organize a policy/scholarship conference at Emory University and pilot survey of fisherfolk in the Philippines and Vietnam.  The results from these efforts are numerous. First, the team was able to post both their event dataset and survey data publicly (scsdi.org) as well as write a working paper entitled "Audience Cost or Posturing Premium? How Empty Threats Benefit Leaders in Small Countries." Additionally they wrote a policy whitepaper published by the Woodrow Wilson Center’s China program, have a detailed outline for a book manuscript on "The Politics of Regional Hegemony", organized a policy and scholarly conference on the South China Sea, developed a survey design for fisherfolk survey and trained multiple research assistants who have since gone on to start PhDs.  Finally, with these results in hand we were able to engage with policy makers in the United States as well as in multiple countries across Southeast Asia including the Philippines, Vietnam and Singapore. Here we were able to share our findings and discuss how best to use these data points in decision making.  Overall this project has been a success. Our data collection has provided much needed insights into maritime conflict in this region for both scholars and policy makers alike. These outcomes now provide us with a greater understanding that can be used not only for academic literature but also for constructive political dialogue between stakeholders. We hope that this new information can be used proactively to build bridges between nations and minimize potential conflict in the future.       Last Modified: 04/12/2023       Submitted by: Nico Ravanilla]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
