<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Doctoral Dissertation Research: Family Membership, Marital Status, and Citizenship]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>25199.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>25199</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Naomi Hall-Byers</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>nhallbye@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922672</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Marital status and membership in a traditional family have been central in defining a sense of belonging in the nation. Since the early years of the American Republic, the ideal citizen has been imagined as married and part of a family. This project will examine how the state created laws and policies designed to regulate the lives of single people, and how status as a single person shaped individual’s relationship to the state and their claim to citizenship.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will focus on five groups of single people in the U.S. during the first half of the 20th century: World War I veterans, single immigrants, young single women, transients, and young unemployed single men during the Depression. Based on theories of citizenship, gender, and mobility, this project will employ a qualitative analysis of archival collections and documents to analyze the various legal responses of the state to the perceived threat of singleness. By analyzing the legal history of single people and the state, this research will provide insight into laws and policies aimed at nontraditional families and singleness. Ultimately, this study will assess how family membership and marital status, and the lack thereof, have shaped an understanding of citizenship.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/11/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/11/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2017635</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Doris</FirstName>
<LastName>Brossard</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Doris Brossard</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[doris.brossard@rutgers.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000818810</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/11/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jennifer</FirstName>
<LastName>Mittelstadt</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jennifer Mittelstadt</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jmittel@history.rutgers.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000819050</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/11/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Rutgers University New Brunswick</Name>
<CityName>NEW BRUNSWICK</CityName>
<ZipCode>089018559</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8489320150</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3 RUTGERS PLZ</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NJ12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>M1LVPE5GLSD9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RUTGERS, THE STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Rutgers University New Brunswick]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>089018554</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NJ06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>128Y</Code>
<Text>Law &amp; Science</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~25199</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>My project explores the question: how did the American state in the early twentieth century understand its responsibility and obligations towards single people? Historians of gender and the state have emphasized that one&rsquo;s place in the patriarchal family determined how the state defined its responsibilities towards individuals. My dissertation asks: what happened to the people who moved or existed outside of the family &ndash; that is, single people? Far from ignoring them, state officials and social welfare reformers were obsessed with single people. They saw them as both vulnerable and dangerous to the social and moral order of society. Indeed, by moving outside of the family, single people left a traditional site of governance. Anxious to control the threat they represented, policy makers and reformers created programs that aimed at bringing single people back under some form of governance. The programs they created ranged from economic benefits, sexual and moral education, surveillance, to detention and deportation. I argue that the level and kind of state responsibility that single people were entitled to depended on whether state officials and reformers imagined them as being able to return to the family.</p> <p>My project uses archival sources documenting programs created for five groups of single people &ndash; immigrants, young women, World War I soldiers, transients, and young unemployed people during the Depression. By analyzing the papers of several governmental agencies and social welfare organizations, I highlight how prevalent the concern for single people was at the beginning of the early twentieth century. I show that state officials&rsquo; and reformers&rsquo; anxiety to bring single people back under control pushed them to debate the ethical and moral obligations of the state towards single people. Single people, I demonstrate, were at the center of the process of state formation.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/24/2022<br>      Modified by: Doris&nbsp;Brossard</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ My project explores the question: how did the American state in the early twentieth century understand its responsibility and obligations towards single people? Historians of gender and the state have emphasized that one’s place in the patriarchal family determined how the state defined its responsibilities towards individuals. My dissertation asks: what happened to the people who moved or existed outside of the family &ndash; that is, single people? Far from ignoring them, state officials and social welfare reformers were obsessed with single people. They saw them as both vulnerable and dangerous to the social and moral order of society. Indeed, by moving outside of the family, single people left a traditional site of governance. Anxious to control the threat they represented, policy makers and reformers created programs that aimed at bringing single people back under some form of governance. The programs they created ranged from economic benefits, sexual and moral education, surveillance, to detention and deportation. I argue that the level and kind of state responsibility that single people were entitled to depended on whether state officials and reformers imagined them as being able to return to the family.  My project uses archival sources documenting programs created for five groups of single people &ndash; immigrants, young women, World War I soldiers, transients, and young unemployed people during the Depression. By analyzing the papers of several governmental agencies and social welfare organizations, I highlight how prevalent the concern for single people was at the beginning of the early twentieth century. I show that state officials’ and reformers’ anxiety to bring single people back under control pushed them to debate the ethical and moral obligations of the state towards single people. Single people, I demonstrate, were at the center of the process of state formation.       Last Modified: 12/24/2022       Submitted by: Doris Brossard]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
