<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Doctoral Dissertation Research: A Comparative Analysis of Migration]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>31400.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>31400</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Naomi Hall-Byers</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>nhallbye@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922672</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Migration within and across borders has important political, social, and economic implications. This project will analyze migration corridors as a conceptual process. As a consequence, this research will alter theories of migration based on relevant laws and policies, media discourse, and trade agreements. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In this ethnographic study employing a mixed methods approach including interviews and macro-level analyses, this project will examine the development and shifting formation of migration corridors. In doing so, this research will analyze the often intersecting travel itineraries of female migrant workers. By examining migration as a process within and across migration corridors, this project provides an advance in theoretical understanding of migration.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/14/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/14/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2017774</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Calvin</FirstName>
<LastName>Morrill</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Calvin Morrill</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[cmorrill@law.berkeley.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000450195</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/14/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Shikha</FirstName>
<LastName>Silliman Bhattacharjee</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Shikha Silliman Bhattacharjee</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[shikhasb@berkeley.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000821304</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/14/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Berkeley</Name>
<CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
<ZipCode>947101749</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5106433891</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1608 4TH ST STE 201</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>GS3YEVSS12N6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>NUDGYLBB4S99</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Berkeley]]></Name>
<CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>947101749</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Sponsored Projects Office]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>128Y</Code>
<Text>Law &amp; Science</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~31400</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Labour supply chains for migrant workers in the global economy</p> <p>This aspect of the work explores the potential for Assemblage Theory to supplement current approaches to studying labor migration in law and the social sciences. Based upon a study of women&rsquo;s migration for garment and domestic work in India, I lay out the <em>labor supply chain assemblage </em>(LSCA)<em> </em>as a framework for understanding how workers find employment across multi-site, dynamic trajectories.&nbsp; Migration into temporary employment requires workers to move between jobs on an ongoing basis. Accordingly, studying labor supply chains as fluid assemblages defined by labor market conditions, component elements, and various agents provides a methodology for analyzing frequent job searches, across recruitment geographies, that include a range of recruitment actors. By accommodating temporal, territorial, and relational analysis, this approach provides insight into how labor migration processes for migrant garment and domestic workers in India articulate with the development of markets, working conditions, and social hierarchies&mdash;including on the basis of gender and caste.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Flexible planning and employment as risk factors for migrant workers</p> <p>This paper introduces the term <em>zones of compounded informality</em> to demarcate locations wherein regulatory exclusions in distinct domains interact to escalate the impact of exclusions for people who live and work in these areas. Based upon a study of India&rsquo;s Delhi, National Capital Region (Delhi-NCR), I explain how the convergence of flexible planning and employment produces zones of compounded informality. Circular migrant workers in the Delhi-NCR overwhelmingly live and work in these zones, wherein unstable employment and housing perpetuate nomadic migration. Zones of compounded informality, moreover, interact with other legal and procedural pathways to further condition access to legal and social protection. Based on ethnographic field work and a survey of 981 workers, I consider how zones of compounded informality in the Delhi-NCR interact with India&rsquo;s <em>Aadhar </em>biometric identification system to variegate access to the franchise and India&rsquo;s Targeted Public Distribution System (PDS) while in the city. The coda explains how zones of compounded informality illuminate the conditions under which millions of internal migrant workers fled India&rsquo;s megacities in the wake of COVID 19.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Supply chain oppression and legal exclusion</p> <p>Persistent exploitation of farmworkers is a defining problem of our time. An estimated 32 percent of the global population is employed in agriculture. At the base of global food systems, agricultural workers sustain the world&rsquo;s population while systematically excluded from labor rights protections. Through an analysis of restrictions on labor rights for agricultural workers in 110 countries, this article distills a typology of legal exclusion that persists to date across the globe. These exclusions articulate with labor exploitation at the base of agri-food supply chains, and economic and social hierarchies constructed by race, caste, indigeneity, gender, and migration status. How can we upend this legal architecture of oppression, rooted in racialized and gendered capitalism? The global understanding advanced in this article is critical to dismantling legal architectures of oppression. At the national level, it provides a framework for identifying and addressing layered mechanisms of legal exclusion in particular jurisdictions. Moreover, since agricultural supply chains operate globally, it provides importance guidance for protecting workers rights on agri-food supply chains, including through binding due diligence legislation in headquarter economies of lead firms, enforceable brand agreements, and inclusion of labor rights in food safety and environmental standards. Finally, due to the structure of monopsony capitalism, in order to raise the floor for agricultural workers worldwide, legal exclusions must be ratcheted up across jurisdictions. Global analysis, then, provides a roadmap for strengthening international standards and global campaigns.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/26/2023<br>      Modified by: Calvin&nbsp;Morrill</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Labour supply chains for migrant workers in the global economy  This aspect of the work explores the potential for Assemblage Theory to supplement current approaches to studying labor migration in law and the social sciences. Based upon a study of women’s migration for garment and domestic work in India, I lay out the labor supply chain assemblage (LSCA) as a framework for understanding how workers find employment across multi-site, dynamic trajectories.  Migration into temporary employment requires workers to move between jobs on an ongoing basis. Accordingly, studying labor supply chains as fluid assemblages defined by labor market conditions, component elements, and various agents provides a methodology for analyzing frequent job searches, across recruitment geographies, that include a range of recruitment actors. By accommodating temporal, territorial, and relational analysis, this approach provides insight into how labor migration processes for migrant garment and domestic workers in India articulate with the development of markets, working conditions, and social hierarchies&mdash;including on the basis of gender and caste.     Flexible planning and employment as risk factors for migrant workers  This paper introduces the term zones of compounded informality to demarcate locations wherein regulatory exclusions in distinct domains interact to escalate the impact of exclusions for people who live and work in these areas. Based upon a study of India’s Delhi, National Capital Region (Delhi-NCR), I explain how the convergence of flexible planning and employment produces zones of compounded informality. Circular migrant workers in the Delhi-NCR overwhelmingly live and work in these zones, wherein unstable employment and housing perpetuate nomadic migration. Zones of compounded informality, moreover, interact with other legal and procedural pathways to further condition access to legal and social protection. Based on ethnographic field work and a survey of 981 workers, I consider how zones of compounded informality in the Delhi-NCR interact with India’s Aadhar biometric identification system to variegate access to the franchise and India’s Targeted Public Distribution System (PDS) while in the city. The coda explains how zones of compounded informality illuminate the conditions under which millions of internal migrant workers fled India’s megacities in the wake of COVID 19.        Supply chain oppression and legal exclusion  Persistent exploitation of farmworkers is a defining problem of our time. An estimated 32 percent of the global population is employed in agriculture. At the base of global food systems, agricultural workers sustain the world’s population while systematically excluded from labor rights protections. Through an analysis of restrictions on labor rights for agricultural workers in 110 countries, this article distills a typology of legal exclusion that persists to date across the globe. These exclusions articulate with labor exploitation at the base of agri-food supply chains, and economic and social hierarchies constructed by race, caste, indigeneity, gender, and migration status. How can we upend this legal architecture of oppression, rooted in racialized and gendered capitalism? The global understanding advanced in this article is critical to dismantling legal architectures of oppression. At the national level, it provides a framework for identifying and addressing layered mechanisms of legal exclusion in particular jurisdictions. Moreover, since agricultural supply chains operate globally, it provides importance guidance for protecting workers rights on agri-food supply chains, including through binding due diligence legislation in headquarter economies of lead firms, enforceable brand agreements, and inclusion of labor rights in food safety and environmental standards. Finally, due to the structure of monopsony capitalism, in order to raise the floor for agricultural workers worldwide, legal exclusions must be ratcheted up across jurisdictions. Global analysis, then, provides a roadmap for strengthening international standards and global campaigns.          Last Modified: 01/26/2023       Submitted by: Calvin Morrill]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
