<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Community Facility Support: Travel support for student participation at the 2020 Electron Backscatter Diffraction Topical Conference; Ann Arbor, MI - June 2020]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>20000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>20000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>David Lambert</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dlambert@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924736</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This award will support early career scientists to attend a topical conference on electron backscatter diffraction. The conference will contribute significantly to training of students and early career investigators and provide a venue for multidisciplinary discussions and exchange of ideas and concepts, from the fundamental (academic) to the applied aspects (industry). The tutorial that opens this topical conference will provide not only basic training that will be particularly useful to students and early career investigators, but also access to a number of expert users from a variety of fields.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This topical conference series has become the de facto meeting in North America for training, development and application of this core microanalytical technique. This conference will provide a venue for ideas to be shared between the primary disciplines utilizing the technique: geoscience, materials science, data science, and engineering. The exchange of cutting-edge knowledge from and between these communities will facilitate dissemination of knowledge and further research developments.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/06/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/06/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2018988</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sarah</FirstName>
<LastName>Brownlee</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sarah J Brownlee</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[brownlee.sj@gmail.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000596580</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/06/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Allison</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John E Allison</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[johnea@umich.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000397242</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/06/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Regents of the University of Michigan - Ann Arbor</Name>
<CityName>ANN ARBOR</CityName>
<ZipCode>481091079</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1109 GEDDES AVE, SUITE 3300</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>GNJ7BBP73WE9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MICHIGAN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Regents of the University of Michigan]]></Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3003 S. State Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1580</Code>
<Text>Instrumentation &amp; Facilities</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~20000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The project titled '<span>Community Facility Support: Travel support for student participation at the 2020 Electron Backscatter Diffraction Topical Conference; Ann Arbor, MI - June 2020'</span>&nbsp;supported participation of early career investigators in the 2020 Electron Backscatter Diffraction (EBDS) topical conference. Due to the Covid-19 pandemic, the topical conference was not held in 2020, but was actually held virtually in 2022. The conference was 3 days long, including 1 full day of tutorials on EBSD methods and data analysis techniques, and 2 days of oral presentations and discussion, as well as 1 poster session. Early career participants included both undergraduate and graduate students, as well as postdoctoral researchers.</p> <p>There were a total of 26 early career participants that were reimbursed for their registration fee. Although 32 participants were eligible, only 26 requested reimbursement. All who requested reimbursement were fully reimbursed for their $75 registration fee.</p> <p>12 of the early career participants were female. We did not collect other demographic data.</p> <p>By reimbursing these early career participants, we were able to broaden the participation in the meeting, particularly for early career investigators. This resulted in increased access to this valuable educational training experience that spans multiple disciplines across materials science and engineering and the geosciences.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/02/2023<br>      Modified by: Sarah&nbsp;J&nbsp;Brownlee</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The project titled 'Community Facility Support: Travel support for student participation at the 2020 Electron Backscatter Diffraction Topical Conference; Ann Arbor, MI - June 2020' supported participation of early career investigators in the 2020 Electron Backscatter Diffraction (EBDS) topical conference. Due to the Covid-19 pandemic, the topical conference was not held in 2020, but was actually held virtually in 2022. The conference was 3 days long, including 1 full day of tutorials on EBSD methods and data analysis techniques, and 2 days of oral presentations and discussion, as well as 1 poster session. Early career participants included both undergraduate and graduate students, as well as postdoctoral researchers.  There were a total of 26 early career participants that were reimbursed for their registration fee. Although 32 participants were eligible, only 26 requested reimbursement. All who requested reimbursement were fully reimbursed for their $75 registration fee.  12 of the early career participants were female. We did not collect other demographic data.  By reimbursing these early career participants, we were able to broaden the participation in the meeting, particularly for early career investigators. This resulted in increased access to this valuable educational training experience that spans multiple disciplines across materials science and engineering and the geosciences.       Last Modified: 05/02/2023       Submitted by: Sarah J Brownlee]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
