<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RCN-UBE Incubator: Teaching Logical Reasoning Skills in Undergraduate Biology Courses]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>75000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>75000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DBI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sophie George</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Logical thinking and reasoning skills are critical for student success in college STEM courses. However, explicit instruction and assessment of logical reasoning are generally not a part of introductory science classes. This project will address this disconnect by creating a broad and diverse network of educators and researchers, the aim of which will be to develop a robust set of print and digital course materials for helping students in introductory biology courses build these skills. The creation of high-quality resources that improve a vital educational pathway at a foundational stage will result in a better prepared and more diverse STEM-educated workforce.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The members of the network created by this project will collaborate to develop and disseminate the logical reasoning resources and instructional materials. To that end, network members will first develop common definitions of critical thinking and logical reasoning that are informed by existing frameworks from the American Philosophical Society and other sources. Drawing on the framework of inoculation theory, the network will then design curricular materials that train students to recognize logical reasoning errors (e.g., common logical fallacies) and distortions or manipulations of scientific thinking (e.g., unfalsifiable pseudoscience). The materials developed will be disseminated at network-led workshops and implemented in college-level biology courses nationwide in partnership with organizations affiliated with network members and through cultivating collaborations with the broader community of STEM educators. Project products will bolster undergraduate biology education by furnishing high-quality resources that will equip students with the rigorous logical reasoning skills they need to succeed in STEM careers. This project is being jointly funded by the Directorate for Biological Sciences, Division of Biological Infrastructure, and the Directorate for Education and Human Resources, Division of Undergraduate Education as part of their efforts to address the challenges posed in "Vision and Change in Undergraduate Biology Education: A Call to Action" (http://visionandchange/finalreport).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/08/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/08/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2018270</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Oscar</FirstName>
<LastName>Fernandez</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Oscar E Fernandez</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ofernand@wellesley.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000545030</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/08/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mays</FirstName>
<LastName>Imad</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mays Imad</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mimad@conncoll.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000819133</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/08/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Susannah</FirstName>
<LastName>McGowan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Susannah McGowan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[susannah.mcgowan@georgetown.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000819542</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/08/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ryan</FirstName>
<LastName>Korstange</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ryan Korstange</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[Ryan.korstange@mtsu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000819562</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/08/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Joya</FirstName>
<LastName>Mukerji</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Joya Mukerji</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[joya.mukerji@csus.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000819108</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/08/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Pima County Community College District- NORTHWEST CAMPUS</Name>
<CityName>TUCSON</CityName>
<ZipCode>857090001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5202064955</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>7600 N SHANNON RD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AZ03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>VG8BQP9ALFF9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PIMA COUNTY COMMUNITY COLLEGE DISTRICT</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>H77GBPTJEPX3</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Pima County Community College District - West Campus]]></Name>
<CityName>Tucson</CityName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>857090001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2202 West Anklam Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AZ03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>037Y</Code>
<Text>UBE - Undergraduate Biology Ed</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1998</Code>
<Text>IUSE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1664</Code>
<Text>RESEARCH COORD NETWK IN BIO SC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0420</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>04002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~75000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Major Activities:</strong></p> <ul> </ul> <p>The major foundational work in this grant happened at the frequent meetings of the steering committee and the primary investigators. The primary investigator meetings were focused on ironing out the logistics of keeping the project moving forward, and on troubleshooting any challenges that arose between the meetings of the steering committee.</p> <p>The steering committee meetings were the place where foundational work happened. Early meetings focused on collaboratively drafting comprehensive definitions to five key questions:&nbsp;</p> <ol> <li>What is critical thinking (CT)?</li> <li>What is logical reasoning (LR)?</li> <li>What is LR in STEM?</li> <li>How to teach LR in STEM?</li> <li>How to assess it LR?</li> </ol> <p>After these <a href="https://sites.google.com/view/teaching-logical-reasoning/definitions">foundational definitions</a> were finalized, we divided the steering committee into project committees to focus their work on specific projects and deliverables. We created an assessment team to focus on the review of pre-existing critical thinking assessments and the creation of an assessment plan for measuring the development of students&rsquo; critical thinking and logical reasoning skills as a result of the educational interventions we were creating elsewhere in this project. The educational interventions team focused on developing first a format for standardized lesson plans that could be easily utilized by a variety of faculty members, and then on developing prototype lessons that prioritize the development of critical thinking and logical reasoning skills in specific STEM classes. Finally, a communications team worked on building a project website and focused on other information dissemination matters.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <ul> </ul> <p><strong>Specific Objectives:</strong></p> <ul> </ul> <p>The specific objectives that have been fulfilled align with the major aims of the project. Collaborative definitions of foundational concepts have been created, finalized, and published on the project website. A network has been formed both in the steering committee, and by additional outreach through the summer conference. Major pre-existing critical thinking assessments have been reviewed, and an approach to a formative alternative has been outlined and justified. A format for critical thinking and logical reasoning lessons has been established, and several lessons have been proposed.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <ul> </ul> <p><strong>Significant Results:</strong></p> <ul> </ul> <p>Our goal all along has been to create resources that are both effective- in that they contribute to students development of logical reasoning tasks and that are easy to use by faculty - and accessible to both students and faculty. The significant results associated with this grant relate to the creation and dissemination of these critical thinking and logical reasoning interventions.&nbsp;</p> <p>Sample lessons have been created by steering committee members. These lessons are meant to include everything necessary for use in class, with minimal preparation on the part of the instructor of record. The list of these sample assignments is available on the <a href="https://sites.google.com/view/teaching-logical-reasoning/course-materials/sample-assignments?authuser=0">project website</a>.</p> <p>Lesson plans include the following:&nbsp;</p> <ul> </ul> <ol> <li>Logical fallacies (for Biology for non-majors)</li> <li> Arguments, Imposter Syndrome, and Conspiracy Theories</li> <li>Science in the News</li> <li>Using Logical Reasoning in Formulating and Evaluating Hypotheses for Applying Gauss&rsquo; Law.&nbsp;</li> </ol>  <ul> </ul> <p>In addition, a system of review and further dissemination of lessons has been created in order to cultivate the creation and revision of other assignments as the network grows.&nbsp;</p> <p>Dissemination of these good lessons is available through the project website, and actively through synchronous network extension events.&nbsp;</p> <p><em>Website:</em> Includes polished versions of our foundational definitions, sample lesson plans, assessment strategies, and an overview of the team members.</p> <p><em>Network Extension Events</em>: A two day conference was held in July 2021 with the purpose of furthering the network of STEM educators who are prepared to and interested in teaching logical reasoning and critical thinking in STEM courses. <br /> <br /> This conference brought together 72 STEM educators with the expressed purpose of including them into the CT/LR network.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <ul> </ul> <p><strong>Key outcomes or other achievements:</strong></p> <ul> </ul> <p>Intentional and careful thinking about the way that CT/LR is introduced in introductory STEM courses provides an essential foundation for later success in those courses. The faculty involved in all aspects of this project - PI&rsquo;s, Steering Committee Members, and new Network participants all see the value in this work more explicitly today than when they first were involved in the project. Further, the wide appeal of this work is marked by external interest in the project. Stylus has approached the PI&rsquo;s about writing a book related to some of this content, and several network members are working on conference proposals including these concepts.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Products</strong></p> <ul> <li>Project website: <a href="https://sites.google.com/view/teaching-logical-reasoning/">https://sites.google.com/view/teaching-logical-reasoning/</a></li> <li>Crowdsourced, researched definitions of critical thinking and logical reasoning in STEM: https://sites.google.com/view/teaching-logical-reasoning/definitions</li> <li>Assessment instrument review: https://sites.google.com/view/teaching-logical-reasoning/assessment-resources</li> <li>Assignments: https://sites.google.com/view/teaching-logical-reasoning/course-materials/sample-assignments?authuser=0</li> <li>July 8 and July 29 recording of Keynote Speakers Maureen Linker and Bayo Akomolafe&nbsp;</li> <li>Gathered a community of STEM educators who are now meeting monthly to discuss how to move this work forward.</li> <li>Currently, the steering committee is working on writing a manuscript of the results of the study. </li> <li>Several members of the steering committee will be presenting at the Society of Neuroscience annual conference as well as the AAC&amp;U STEM conference in November 2021. Abstract proposals were submitted and accepted. </li> </ul> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p class="Default">&nbsp;</p> <p class="Pa3">&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/19/2021<br>      Modified by: Mays&nbsp;Imad</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Major Activities:    The major foundational work in this grant happened at the frequent meetings of the steering committee and the primary investigators. The primary investigator meetings were focused on ironing out the logistics of keeping the project moving forward, and on troubleshooting any challenges that arose between the meetings of the steering committee.  The steering committee meetings were the place where foundational work happened. Early meetings focused on collaboratively drafting comprehensive definitions to five key questions:   What is critical thinking (CT)? What is logical reasoning (LR)? What is LR in STEM? How to teach LR in STEM? How to assess it LR?   After these foundational definitions were finalized, we divided the steering committee into project committees to focus their work on specific projects and deliverables. We created an assessment team to focus on the review of pre-existing critical thinking assessments and the creation of an assessment plan for measuring the development of students’ critical thinking and logical reasoning skills as a result of the educational interventions we were creating elsewhere in this project. The educational interventions team focused on developing first a format for standardized lesson plans that could be easily utilized by a variety of faculty members, and then on developing prototype lessons that prioritize the development of critical thinking and logical reasoning skills in specific STEM classes. Finally, a communications team worked on building a project website and focused on other information dissemination matters.       Specific Objectives:    The specific objectives that have been fulfilled align with the major aims of the project. Collaborative definitions of foundational concepts have been created, finalized, and published on the project website. A network has been formed both in the steering committee, and by additional outreach through the summer conference. Major pre-existing critical thinking assessments have been reviewed, and an approach to a formative alternative has been outlined and justified. A format for critical thinking and logical reasoning lessons has been established, and several lessons have been proposed.        Significant Results:    Our goal all along has been to create resources that are both effective- in that they contribute to students development of logical reasoning tasks and that are easy to use by faculty - and accessible to both students and faculty. The significant results associated with this grant relate to the creation and dissemination of these critical thinking and logical reasoning interventions.   Sample lessons have been created by steering committee members. These lessons are meant to include everything necessary for use in class, with minimal preparation on the part of the instructor of record. The list of these sample assignments is available on the project website.  Lesson plans include the following:     Logical fallacies (for Biology for non-majors)  Arguments, Imposter Syndrome, and Conspiracy Theories Science in the News Using Logical Reasoning in Formulating and Evaluating Hypotheses for Applying Gauss’ Law.       In addition, a system of review and further dissemination of lessons has been created in order to cultivate the creation and revision of other assignments as the network grows.   Dissemination of these good lessons is available through the project website, and actively through synchronous network extension events.   Website: Includes polished versions of our foundational definitions, sample lesson plans, assessment strategies, and an overview of the team members.  Network Extension Events: A two day conference was held in July 2021 with the purpose of furthering the network of STEM educators who are prepared to and interested in teaching logical reasoning and critical thinking in STEM courses.     This conference brought together 72 STEM educators with the expressed purpose of including them into the CT/LR network.       Key outcomes or other achievements:    Intentional and careful thinking about the way that CT/LR is introduced in introductory STEM courses provides an essential foundation for later success in those courses. The faculty involved in all aspects of this project - PI’s, Steering Committee Members, and new Network participants all see the value in this work more explicitly today than when they first were involved in the project. Further, the wide appeal of this work is marked by external interest in the project. Stylus has approached the PI’s about writing a book related to some of this content, and several network members are working on conference proposals including these concepts.     Products  Project website: https://sites.google.com/view/teaching-logical-reasoning/ Crowdsourced, researched definitions of critical thinking and logical reasoning in STEM: https://sites.google.com/view/teaching-logical-reasoning/definitions Assessment instrument review: https://sites.google.com/view/teaching-logical-reasoning/assessment-resources Assignments: https://sites.google.com/view/teaching-logical-reasoning/course-materials/sample-assignments?authuser=0 July 8 and July 29 recording of Keynote Speakers Maureen Linker and Bayo Akomolafe  Gathered a community of STEM educators who are now meeting monthly to discuss how to move this work forward. Currently, the steering committee is working on writing a manuscript of the results of the study.  Several members of the steering committee will be presenting at the Society of Neuroscience annual conference as well as the AAC&amp;U STEM conference in November 2021. Abstract proposals were submitted and accepted.                Last Modified: 09/19/2021       Submitted by: Mays Imad]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
