<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[MRI: Acquisition of a 500 MHz Nuclear Magnetic Resonance (NMR) Spectrometer and Equipped with Solid-State Probes]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>559783.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>559783</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tanya Whitmer</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>twhitmer@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922912</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This award is supported by the Major Research Instrumentation and the Chemistry Research Instrumentation programs. Johns Hopkins University is acquiring a 500 MHz nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) spectrometer equipped with solid state capabilities and other probes to support Professor Rebekka Klausen and colleagues Howard Fairbrother, Sara Thoi and Adelina Voutchkova-Kostal from George Washington University. This spectrometer allows research in a variety of fields such as those that accelerate chemical reactions of significant economic importance, as well as permitting study of biologically relevant species. In general, NMR spectroscopy is one of the most powerful tools available to chemists for the elucidation of the structure of molecules. It is used to identify unknown substances, to characterize specific arrangements of atoms within molecules, and to study the dynamics of interactions between molecules in solution or in the solid state. Access to state-of-the-art NMR spectrometers is essential to chemists who are carrying out frontier research. This instrument is an integral part of teaching as well as research and research training of undergraduate and graduate students in chemistry and biochemistry at this institution and nearby universities such as Georgetown University and the US Naval Academy. The instrument is also used on university NMR Summer School and in collaboration with museums to study cultural heritage materials.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The award of the NMR spectrometer is aimed at enhancing research and education at all levels. It especially impacts spectroscopic studies of polymeric materials based on main group elements. The instrumentation is also used for studying supramolecular materials as well as analyzing conjugated polymer blends and surface-immobilized polymers. In addition, it provides information for exploring biodegradable polymer-functionalized nanocellulose composites and for the study of cultural-heritage materials. The spectrometer is also used to identify phosphorus(III)-oxyanions relevant to agriculture and food safety.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/06/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/07/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2018176</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Adelina</FirstName>
<LastName>Voutchkova-Kostal</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Adelina Voutchkova-Kostal</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[avoutchkova@gwu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000588514</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/06/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>V. Sara</FirstName>
<LastName>Thoi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>V. Sara Thoi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[sarathoi@jhu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000715548</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/06/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rebekka</FirstName>
<LastName>Klausen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Rebekka Klausen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[klausen@jhu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000674816</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/06/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Howard</FirstName>
<LastName>Fairbrother</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Howard Fairbrother</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[howardf@jhu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000311078</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/06/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Johns Hopkins University</Name>
<CityName>BALTIMORE</CityName>
<ZipCode>212182608</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4439971898</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3400 N CHARLES ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MD07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>FTMTDMBR29C7</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>JOHNS HOPKINS UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>FTMTDMBR29C7</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Johns Hopkins University]]></Name>
<CityName>Baltimore</CityName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>212182686</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1101 E 33rd St Suite B001]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MD07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>Major Research Instrumentation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~559783</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The primary outcome of the award &ldquo;<strong>MRI: Acquisition of a 500 MHz Nuclear Magnetic Resonance (NMR) Spectrometer and Equipped with Solid-State Probes</strong>&rdquo; was the acquisition of the spectrometer and probes mentioned in the title, a type of instrument used to collect spectroscopic data on materials that are either insoluble or cannot be handled in solution. This represents a major investment in research infrastructure. Additional outcomes include scientific impact and the professional development of early career scientific researchers.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Intellectual Merit Outcomes. Over the three-year course of this award (2021&ndash;2023), we published five peer-reviewed publications containing data collected on the acquired instrument. Two more manuscripts have been submitted. Three of those manuscripts include at least one undergraduate researcher as a co-author. Four graduate dissertations were completed that reported data collected on the solid-state spectrometer. The research activities related to these publications addressed fundamental questions in macromolecular chemistry, such as the synthesis of polymers impossible to prepare from conventional precursors, and in energy science, such as methods for improving the function of novel batteries. A submitted manuscript addresses problems in the detection and sensing of harmful particulate matter.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Over the course of this award, the PI and co-PI&rsquo;s received several awards recognizing the impact of their research activities. Klausen was named one of 2 winners of the 2022 ACS Macro Letters / Biomacromolecules / Macromolecules Young Investigator Award and was named a finalist for Blavatnik National Award for Young Scientists (2021 and 2022). The co-PI Thoi received the Rising Star award from the American Chemical Society Women Chemist&rsquo;s Committee, the Dreyfus Teacher-Scholar award, and the Henry Gray Award from the American Chemical Society.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Broader Impacts Outcomes. As part of the educational activities conducted under this award, two graduate students from JHU Chemistry took on the role of &ldquo;NMR Teaching Assistant&rdquo;, thereby receiving training and professional development opportunities in the maintenance and usage of NMR technology. This helps create a competitive Science Technology Engineering Math (STEM) workforce. Indeed, the 4 PhD graduates mentioned above have found research positions in academia and industry within the US. The PI organized virtual and in-person gatherings of researchers across the DC-Baltimore corridor to discuss opportunities enabled by the instrument acquisition, which dissemination results to communities of interest and led to overlap of researchers in industry, government, and academia (including research institutions, primarily undergraduate institutions, and historically Black colleges and universities).</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>In summary, the intellectual merit outcomes of this award include research activities that addressed fundamental questions in macromolecular chemistry, such as the synthesis of polymers impossible to prepare from conventional precursors, and in energy science, such as methods for improving the function of novel batteries. The broader impacts outcomes include broadening participation, training a competitive and diverse STEM work force, and investing in research infrastructure.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/19/2023<br>      Modified by: Rebekka&nbsp;Klausen</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The primary outcome of the award "MRI: Acquisition of a 500 MHz Nuclear Magnetic Resonance (NMR) Spectrometer and Equipped with Solid-State Probes" was the acquisition of the spectrometer and probes mentioned in the title, a type of instrument used to collect spectroscopic data on materials that are either insoluble or cannot be handled in solution. This represents a major investment in research infrastructure. Additional outcomes include scientific impact and the professional development of early career scientific researchers.      Intellectual Merit Outcomes. Over the three-year course of this award (2021&ndash;2023), we published five peer-reviewed publications containing data collected on the acquired instrument. Two more manuscripts have been submitted. Three of those manuscripts include at least one undergraduate researcher as a co-author. Four graduate dissertations were completed that reported data collected on the solid-state spectrometer. The research activities related to these publications addressed fundamental questions in macromolecular chemistry, such as the synthesis of polymers impossible to prepare from conventional precursors, and in energy science, such as methods for improving the function of novel batteries. A submitted manuscript addresses problems in the detection and sensing of harmful particulate matter.     Over the course of this award, the PI and co-PI’s received several awards recognizing the impact of their research activities. Klausen was named one of 2 winners of the 2022 ACS Macro Letters / Biomacromolecules / Macromolecules Young Investigator Award and was named a finalist for Blavatnik National Award for Young Scientists (2021 and 2022). The co-PI Thoi received the Rising Star award from the American Chemical Society Women Chemist’s Committee, the Dreyfus Teacher-Scholar award, and the Henry Gray Award from the American Chemical Society.     Broader Impacts Outcomes. As part of the educational activities conducted under this award, two graduate students from JHU Chemistry took on the role of "NMR Teaching Assistant", thereby receiving training and professional development opportunities in the maintenance and usage of NMR technology. This helps create a competitive Science Technology Engineering Math (STEM) workforce. Indeed, the 4 PhD graduates mentioned above have found research positions in academia and industry within the US. The PI organized virtual and in-person gatherings of researchers across the DC-Baltimore corridor to discuss opportunities enabled by the instrument acquisition, which dissemination results to communities of interest and led to overlap of researchers in industry, government, and academia (including research institutions, primarily undergraduate institutions, and historically Black colleges and universities).     In summary, the intellectual merit outcomes of this award include research activities that addressed fundamental questions in macromolecular chemistry, such as the synthesis of polymers impossible to prepare from conventional precursors, and in energy science, such as methods for improving the function of novel batteries. The broader impacts outcomes include broadening participation, training a competitive and diverse STEM work force, and investing in research infrastructure.           Last Modified: 09/19/2023       Submitted by: Rebekka Klausen]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
