<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Doctoral Dissertation Research: Female Great Ape Behavior and Reproduction in Forest Fragments]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>25200.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>25200</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rebecca Ferrell</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rferrell@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927850</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This doctoral dissertation project examines how habitat fragmentation affects wild female chimpanzees (Pan troglodytes), specifically assessing the consequences of forest fragmentation and food availability on female behavior and reproductive performance. The project will advance fundamental knowledge about species responses to environmental change. In addition, as human land use rapidly alters  forests, understanding how primates cope with habitat loss and fragmentation is of paramount import to their successful conservation. Results will help stakeholders develop and adopt efficient management plans for forest fragments to ensure the protection of chimpanzees and related biodiversity. This project also presents opportunities for training through public outreach and by engaging undergraduate students in field data collection and analyses. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This study will take advantage of two forest fragments which are similar in population density but differ in terms of food abundance and proximity to a larger chimpanzee population. Fragmentation usually co-occurs with substantial loss of food resources, as is the case for one of the forest fragments under investigation. However, the other fragment is still comprised of primary forest, presenting a powerful natural experiment through which to test the effect of fragmentation independent of food availability. The overarching hypothesis of this project is that female behavior will be more impacted by food availability and isolation than fragmentation. Alternatively, female chimpanzees may have sufficient behavioral flexibility due to their fluid social system to mitigate negative consequences of fragmentation. By integrating novel and existing ecological and behavioral datasets, this project will test how habitat fragmentation impacts female chimpanzee subgrouping patterns, dispersal and ultimately, reproductive performance. Subgrouping data will be collected through full day focal follow of adult females and monthly nest surveys along line transects. Female dispersal behavior will be assessed through genetic data, which will be generated from non-invasively collected fecal samples. Finally, female reproductive performance will be characterized from two metrics: the adult female-clinging infant ratio and C-peptide values measured through non-invasively collected urine samples.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/06/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/06/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2018584</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Carson</FirstName>
<LastName>Murray</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Carson M Murray</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[cmmurray@gwu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000623122</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/06/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sylvain</FirstName>
<LastName>Nyandwi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sylvain Nyandwi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[snyandwi@gwu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000819005</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/06/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>George Washington University</Name>
<CityName>WASHINGTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>200520042</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2029940728</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1918 F ST NW</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>ECR5E2LU5BL6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GEORGE WASHINGTON UNIVERSITY (THE)</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[The George Washington University]]></Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>200520086</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1922 F Street NW]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7608</Code>
<Text>Bio Anthro DDRI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1392</Code>
<Text>Biological Anthropology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~25200</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Female Chimpanzee Behavior and Reproduction in Forest Fragments in Rwanda</strong></p> <p>Primates around the world face a conservation crisis as human land use rapidly alters tropical forests. Thus, understanding how primates cope with habitat loss and fragmentation is of paramount import to their successful conservation. The main goal of this study was to investigate how habitat fragmentation affects wild female chimpanzees (<em>Pan troglodytes</em>). Specifically, this project assessed the consequences of fragmentation and food availability on female behavior and reproductive performance. Results will help stakeholders develop and adopt efficient management plans for forest fragments to ensure the protection of chimpanzees and related biodiversity. This project also serves as an opportunity for training by engaging three undergraduate Rwandan students in field data collection. Their involvement in this project prepared them to design their own future studies.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>This study took advantage of two forest fragments in Rwanda which are similar in population density but differ in terms of food abundance and proximity to a larger chimpanzee population. Fragmentation usually co-occurs with substantial loss of food resources, as is the case for one of the forest fragments under investigation. However, the other fragment is still comprised of primary forest, presenting a powerful natural experiment through which to test the effect of fragmentation independent of food availability. By integrating novel and existing ecological and behavioral datasets, this project is testing how habitat fragmentation impacts female chimpanzee subgrouping patterns, dispersal and ultimately, reproductive performance.</p> <p>Analyses are ongoing but preliminary results demonstrate that subgroup sizes are larger in the fragment with more primary forest. This is expected based on the documented relationship between food availability and subgroup size in this species. However, ongoing analyses will relate these factors directly and invesitage the downstream effects on female reproduction.</p> <p>The co-PI for this project has been actively advising ecotourism and conservation efforts based on his research and extensive experience in the study populations.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/04/2022<br>      Modified by: Carson&nbsp;M&nbsp;Murray</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Female Chimpanzee Behavior and Reproduction in Forest Fragments in Rwanda  Primates around the world face a conservation crisis as human land use rapidly alters tropical forests. Thus, understanding how primates cope with habitat loss and fragmentation is of paramount import to their successful conservation. The main goal of this study was to investigate how habitat fragmentation affects wild female chimpanzees (Pan troglodytes). Specifically, this project assessed the consequences of fragmentation and food availability on female behavior and reproductive performance. Results will help stakeholders develop and adopt efficient management plans for forest fragments to ensure the protection of chimpanzees and related biodiversity. This project also serves as an opportunity for training by engaging three undergraduate Rwandan students in field data collection. Their involvement in this project prepared them to design their own future studies.      This study took advantage of two forest fragments in Rwanda which are similar in population density but differ in terms of food abundance and proximity to a larger chimpanzee population. Fragmentation usually co-occurs with substantial loss of food resources, as is the case for one of the forest fragments under investigation. However, the other fragment is still comprised of primary forest, presenting a powerful natural experiment through which to test the effect of fragmentation independent of food availability. By integrating novel and existing ecological and behavioral datasets, this project is testing how habitat fragmentation impacts female chimpanzee subgrouping patterns, dispersal and ultimately, reproductive performance.  Analyses are ongoing but preliminary results demonstrate that subgroup sizes are larger in the fragment with more primary forest. This is expected based on the documented relationship between food availability and subgroup size in this species. However, ongoing analyses will relate these factors directly and invesitage the downstream effects on female reproduction.  The co-PI for this project has been actively advising ecotourism and conservation efforts based on his research and extensive experience in the study populations.           Last Modified: 09/04/2022       Submitted by: Carson M Murray]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
