<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[MRI: Acquisition of an Integrated Spectral Analysis Instrument]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>104424.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>104424</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ECCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jenshan Lin</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jenlin@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927360</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This project will support the acquisition of a modern, research grade Integrated Spectral Analysis instrument to enhance and drive forward research and training programs across multiple fields at The University of Tulsa. The instrument will consist of two parts. The first part consists of a state-of-the-art Optical Spectrum Analyzer (OSA) that can measure how the power in an optical signal is distributed over a range of wavelengths, perform calculations on the signal quality particularly with respect to interference and noise, and provide all of this functionality in real time without the need for extensive processing on a computer to recover critical experimental data. Measurement of optical power over wavelength in real time provides the ability to characterize the chemistry and physics of advanced materials, such as advanced light-emitting diodes, materials for advanced flexible electronics, and the visualization and measurement of chemical reactions. The wavelength and signal quality measurements enable studies of advanced fiber optic systems, including Gigabit optical communication for next generation internet and networks of advanced optical sensors for monitoring seismic activity. The second part of the instrument consists of the optical sources needed to probe the materials and provide input to the communication and sensor systems. The sources provide signals and optical power at the wavelengths of interest and in the format needed to conduct the research and analysis. The instrument will support research and both graduate and undergraduate student training in Electrical and Computer Engineering, Chemistry, Biochemistry, Geosciences, and Physics, including new courses developed based on the instrument’s capabilities. The instrument will enhance and build outreach programs for regional STEM teachers and high-school students, and expand opportunities for collaboration with commercial entities.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will acquire, install, and commission a state-of-the art Integrated Spectral Analysis instrument for research, training, and outreach by faculty and students at the University of Tulsa. The instrument will consist of a state-of-the-art Optical Spectrum Analyzer (OSA), broadband sources covering the ultraviolet to near-infrared for probing materials and chemical reactions, tuned sources for measuring phenomena at specific wavelengths, and high speed tunable data sources for evaluating wired and wireless high-speed optical communication systems. Initially targeted research areas include optical wireless, materials and structures for improved LED efficiency and color quality, wavelength encoded distributed sensing of microseismics, in-situ electrochemical analysis of flexible electrode materials, and photophysical properties of organic dyes as visible-light photoredox catalysts. The instrument will be housed in Rayzor Hall which allows easy access to all faculty and buildings within the College of Engineering and Natural Sciences. Existing physical infrastructure, including mounting racks, cabling, connectors, and electrical isolation, will allow integration of the sources and OSA into a single, cohesive unit and provide the support needed to maintain system operation.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/31/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/31/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2018644</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
<LastName>LoPresti</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>G</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Peter G LoPresti</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[peter-lopresti@utulsa.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000191257</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/31/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Scott</FirstName>
<LastName>Holmstrom</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Scott A Holmstrom</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[scotth@utulsa.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000398373</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/31/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Peifen</FirstName>
<LastName>Zhu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Peifen Zhu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[pzhu@missouri.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000735787</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/31/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Tulsa</Name>
<CityName>TULSA</CityName>
<ZipCode>741049700</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9186312192</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>800 S TUCKER DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oklahoma</StateName>
<StateCode>OK</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OK01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>P23YK1EKPS51</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TULSA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Tulsa]]></Name>
<CityName>Tulsa</CityName>
<StateCode>OK</StateCode>
<ZipCode>741049700</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[800 South Tucker Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oklahoma</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OK01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>Major Research Instrumentation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>091E</Code>
<Text>Light generation &amp; detection</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>094E</Code>
<Text>Optoelectronic devices</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>095E</Code>
<Text>Photonic integration</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>106E</Code>
<Text>Mixed signal technologies</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8028</Code>
<Text>Sensor Technology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~104424</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Under this Major Research Instrumention grant, The University of Tulsa (TU) acquired a modern, reserach grade Integrated Spectral Analysis (ISA) instrument in support of graduate and undergraduate research and training programs in Electrical and Computer Engineering, Computer Science, Chemistry, Engineering Physics, and Geosciences. The instrument components consisted of an Optical Spectrum Analyzer and several optical sources operating in the infrared and visible wavelengths. The instrument was assembled in Rayzor Hall on the TU campus and became operational in the fall of 2021.</p> <p>The ISA instrument allows researchers to explore, measure, and design the optical properties and operation of individual materials, optical devices, and entire optical systems. Each of the optical sources provides either light input over a range of wavelengths or optical signals (such as those used in fiber-optic communication links) at a controlled wavelength. The sources providing a range of wavelengths will be used to explore the operation of optical fiber and key optical networking components, the range of wavelengths absorbed and/or emitted by a range of chemical and solid state materials, and the wavelengths reflected by novel optical sensors whose properties vary in response to changes in temperature, pressure, and other external factors. Targeted applications include the analysis and design of more efficient LEDs capable of emitting white light similar in appearance to that of incandescent bulbs, new chemical materials for a varitey of sensor applications, the understanding and control of key chemical reactions, and new systems and components for optical communication systems.</p> <p>The ISA instrument will provide opportunities for training, instruction, and industry collaboration in addition to the research benefits. Two students, one undergraduate and one graduate, have already received training in use of the instrument. The instrument will be integrated into the Optical Networking class in spring 2022, providing students with the skills and knowledge required to pursue careers in network engineering, for which there is high demand in Oklahoma and the surrounding states. Additional laboratory activities for existing classes, as well as the development of new classes based on the instrument's capabilities, will help train a broader range of undergraduate students across multiple disciplines. Graduate students participating in the research activities described previously will obtain valuable skills in instruments and analysis techniques critical to success in their chosen fields upon graduation. The instrument's capabilities and the potential for training network engineers has attracted attention from TU alumni within local industry, leading to the ongoing construction of a new network engineering facility which should open by the fall of 2022.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/18/2021<br>      Modified by: Peter&nbsp;G&nbsp;Lopresti</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Under this Major Research Instrumention grant, The University of Tulsa (TU) acquired a modern, reserach grade Integrated Spectral Analysis (ISA) instrument in support of graduate and undergraduate research and training programs in Electrical and Computer Engineering, Computer Science, Chemistry, Engineering Physics, and Geosciences. The instrument components consisted of an Optical Spectrum Analyzer and several optical sources operating in the infrared and visible wavelengths. The instrument was assembled in Rayzor Hall on the TU campus and became operational in the fall of 2021.  The ISA instrument allows researchers to explore, measure, and design the optical properties and operation of individual materials, optical devices, and entire optical systems. Each of the optical sources provides either light input over a range of wavelengths or optical signals (such as those used in fiber-optic communication links) at a controlled wavelength. The sources providing a range of wavelengths will be used to explore the operation of optical fiber and key optical networking components, the range of wavelengths absorbed and/or emitted by a range of chemical and solid state materials, and the wavelengths reflected by novel optical sensors whose properties vary in response to changes in temperature, pressure, and other external factors. Targeted applications include the analysis and design of more efficient LEDs capable of emitting white light similar in appearance to that of incandescent bulbs, new chemical materials for a varitey of sensor applications, the understanding and control of key chemical reactions, and new systems and components for optical communication systems.  The ISA instrument will provide opportunities for training, instruction, and industry collaboration in addition to the research benefits. Two students, one undergraduate and one graduate, have already received training in use of the instrument. The instrument will be integrated into the Optical Networking class in spring 2022, providing students with the skills and knowledge required to pursue careers in network engineering, for which there is high demand in Oklahoma and the surrounding states. Additional laboratory activities for existing classes, as well as the development of new classes based on the instrument's capabilities, will help train a broader range of undergraduate students across multiple disciplines. Graduate students participating in the research activities described previously will obtain valuable skills in instruments and analysis techniques critical to success in their chosen fields upon graduation. The instrument's capabilities and the potential for training network engineers has attracted attention from TU alumni within local industry, leading to the ongoing construction of a new network engineering facility which should open by the fall of 2022.       Last Modified: 12/18/2021       Submitted by: Peter G Lopresti]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
