<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[MRI: Acquisition of a 500 MHz Nuclear Magnetic Resonance (NMR) Spectrometer for Research and Training]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>454300.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>454300</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tanya Whitmer</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>twhitmer@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922912</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This award is supported by the Major Research Instrumentation and the Chemistry Research Instrumentation programs. The State University of New York (SUNY) at Buffalo is acquiring a 500 MHz nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) spectrometer equipped with an automatic sample changer to support Professor Steven Diver and colleagues: Timothy Cook, Bing Gong, Janet Morrow and Javid Rzavev. This spectrometer allows research in a variety of fields such as those that accelerate chemical reactions of significant economic importance, as well as permitting study of biologically-relevant species. In general, NMR spectroscopy is one of the most powerful tools available to chemists for the elucidation of the structure of molecules. NMR is used to identify unknown substances, to characterize specific arrangements of atoms within molecules, and to study the dynamics of interactions between molecules in solution or in the solid state. Access to state-of-the-art NMR spectrometers is important to chemists who are carrying out frontier research. This instrument is an integral part of teaching as well as research and research training of undergraduate and graduate students in chemistry and biochemistry at this institution and nearby universities in Western New York such as Canisius College, D’Youville College, Hauptman-Woodward Medical Research Institute and Medaille College.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The award of the NMR spectrometer is aimed at enhancing research and education at all levels. This instrument acquisition impacts studies of chalcogen-containing cationic dyes used in photocatalysis. The instrumentation is used in investigations of small molecules activation using coordination-driven self-assembly and nanoporous organic structures based on folding and assembly. In addition, the spectrometer provides information to aid the design, preparation, and studies of size-selective macrocycle catalysts of importance in manufacturing. The instrument is also used to explore the use of iron(III) coordination complexes and magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) contrast agents and guides the design of polymer assembly with defined molecular architectures.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/15/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/07/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2018160</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Janet</FirstName>
<LastName>Morrow</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Janet R Morrow</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jmorrow@buffalo.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000441317</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/15/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Steven</FirstName>
<LastName>Diver</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>T</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Steven T Diver</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[diver@buffalo.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000425170</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/15/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Bing</FirstName>
<LastName>Gong</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Bing Gong</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[bgong@buffalo.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000296438</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/15/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Javid</FirstName>
<LastName>Rzayev</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Javid Rzayev</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jrzayev@buffalo.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000096206</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/15/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Timothy</FirstName>
<LastName>Cook</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Timothy Cook</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[trcook@buffalo.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000727237</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/15/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>SUNY at Buffalo</Name>
<CityName>AMHERST</CityName>
<ZipCode>142282577</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7166452634</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>520 LEE ENTRANCE STE 211</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>26</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY26</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>LMCJKRFW5R81</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH FOUNDATION FOR THE STATE UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>GMZUKXFDJMA9</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Department of Chemistry]]></Name>
<CityName>Amherst</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>142603000</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[305 Natural Sciences Complex]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>26</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY26</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1938</Code>
<Text>Chemical Instrumentation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8037</Code>
<Text>Advanced Manufacturing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~454300</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The major goal of this project is the modernization of the NMR capabilities for undergraduates, graduate students and postdocs engaged in research and coursework in the Chemistry Department at the University at Buffalo (UB). The 500 MHz Nuclear Magnetic Resonance (NMR) spectrometer provides increased capabilities that empower new experiments and expedites characterization efforts needed to publish papers and to make conference presentations, thereby disseminating research results to the communities of interest in a timely manner. The autosampler feature has resulted in a more efficient work flow, maximized use of the new instrument and reduced the time users spend acquiring data, thus improving productivity across all user groups. Overall, the department has over one hundred researchers, including graduate students, undergraduates, postdoctoral researchers and additional undergraduate students participating in a summer Research Experience for Undergraduates (REU) program at UB. The instrument has primarily facilitated routine characterization of new organic compounds, organometallic complexes and soluble polymers, data which is crucial for making scientific conclusions. In addition, faculty users from Primarily Undergraduate Institutions (PUI) in the Buffalo area have access to the instrument to help them with their research and enhance their educational activities. The NMR instrument is housed in UB Department of Chemistry?s Magnetic Resonance Center and has been successfully incorporated into the management plan of this facility, generating user fees that result in its sustainable operation and coverage of its cost of operation. Though primarily a research instrument, the NMR spectrometer has also positively impacted undergraduate chemistry and medicinal chemistry majors in upper level lab courses, helping to prepare these students for future graduate work and employment outcomes. For instance, the upper level organic laboratory teaches NMR for deducing molecular structure and incorporates NMR analysis into all the lab experiments. The new instrument supplies multinuclear and 2D spectra needed for learning how to assign structure in both problems and for the characterization of products. A number of publications have been published that acknowledge this MRI grant, and we expect the sustainable operation of this instrument to provide additional publications over the next decade. The experiments possible with this new instrument have brought together researchers which has both enhanced existing collaborations and led to new ones. In summary, the new 500 MHz NMR spectrometer has helped modernize routine compound characterization at the University at Buffalo through increased efficiency and enhanced capabilities, leading to enhanced research productivity and improved training opportunities for undergraduate and graduate students through research and coursework.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/09/2023<br>      Modified by: Steven&nbsp;T&nbsp;Diver</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The major goal of this project is the modernization of the NMR capabilities for undergraduates, graduate students and postdocs engaged in research and coursework in the Chemistry Department at the University at Buffalo (UB). The 500 MHz Nuclear Magnetic Resonance (NMR) spectrometer provides increased capabilities that empower new experiments and expedites characterization efforts needed to publish papers and to make conference presentations, thereby disseminating research results to the communities of interest in a timely manner. The autosampler feature has resulted in a more efficient work flow, maximized use of the new instrument and reduced the time users spend acquiring data, thus improving productivity across all user groups. Overall, the department has over one hundred researchers, including graduate students, undergraduates, postdoctoral researchers and additional undergraduate students participating in a summer Research Experience for Undergraduates (REU) program at UB. The instrument has primarily facilitated routine characterization of new organic compounds, organometallic complexes and soluble polymers, data which is crucial for making scientific conclusions. In addition, faculty users from Primarily Undergraduate Institutions (PUI) in the Buffalo area have access to the instrument to help them with their research and enhance their educational activities. The NMR instrument is housed in UB Department of Chemistry?s Magnetic Resonance Center and has been successfully incorporated into the management plan of this facility, generating user fees that result in its sustainable operation and coverage of its cost of operation. Though primarily a research instrument, the NMR spectrometer has also positively impacted undergraduate chemistry and medicinal chemistry majors in upper level lab courses, helping to prepare these students for future graduate work and employment outcomes. For instance, the upper level organic laboratory teaches NMR for deducing molecular structure and incorporates NMR analysis into all the lab experiments. The new instrument supplies multinuclear and 2D spectra needed for learning how to assign structure in both problems and for the characterization of products. A number of publications have been published that acknowledge this MRI grant, and we expect the sustainable operation of this instrument to provide additional publications over the next decade. The experiments possible with this new instrument have brought together researchers which has both enhanced existing collaborations and led to new ones. In summary, the new 500 MHz NMR spectrometer has helped modernize routine compound characterization at the University at Buffalo through increased efficiency and enhanced capabilities, leading to enhanced research productivity and improved training opportunities for undergraduate and graduate students through research and coursework.          Last Modified: 08/09/2023       Submitted by: Steven T Diver]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
