<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[CC* Regional: Small Institution Multiple Organization Regional OneOklahoma Friction Free Network (SI-MORe-OFFN)]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>232275.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>232275</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OAC</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure (OAC)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kevin Thompson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kthompso@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924220</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The Small Institution Multiple Organization Regional OneOklahoma Friction Free Network (SI-MORe-OFFN) project makes advanced cyberinfrastructure tools and services available to five smaller campuses in Oklahoma, covering scientific disciplines from chemistry and agriculture to health and nursing by connecting these campuses to the OneOklahoma Friction Free Network (OFFN). The five targeted campuses are Redlands Community College, University of Science and Arts of Oklahoma, Oklahoma State University Institute of Technology, Oklahoma State University in Oklahoma City and Oklahoma Christian University. The project provides new and diverse research collaboration opportunities for faculty across Oklahoma and enables the smaller, target institutions to expand their research and education activities. The project also has a significant educational impact for undergraduate and community college students at these metropolitan and rural campuses by providing them with additional STEM and cyber-infrastructure educational opportunities as well as exposure to leading researchers and cyber-infrastructure practitioners.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The SI-MORe-OFFN project extends the OneOklahoma Friction Free Network to five smaller institutions by implementing Science DMZs, Data Transfer Nodes and network performance monitoring capabilities at identified locations and integrating these with other similar capabilities across Oklahoma. In addition, the project enhances the skills and abilities of technical personnel at each campus and facilitates cross-campus collaborations, including shared uses of computing tools, scientific equipment, and educational materials by engaging faculty and students in the larger OneOklahoma CyberInfrastructure Initiative (OneOCII). OFFN is managed by OneNet, Oklahoma’s research and education network, and scientific leadership is provided by the University of Oklahoma.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/28/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/21/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2018453</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>April</FirstName>
<LastName>Goode</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>April D Goode</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[april@onenet.net]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000843229</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/15/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dany</FirstName>
<LastName>Doughan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>I</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Dany I Doughan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ddoughan@usao.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000819990</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/28/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Brian</FirstName>
<LastName>Burkhart</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Brian C Burkhart</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[brian@onenet.net]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000820098</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/21/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Brian</FirstName>
<LastName>Burkhart</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Brian C Burkhart</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[brian@onenet.net]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000820098</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/28/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate>09/21/2021</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Vonley</FirstName>
<LastName>Royal</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Vonley R Royal</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[von@onenet.net]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000820157</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/28/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate>09/21/2021</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sky</FirstName>
<LastName>Pettett</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sky P Pettett</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[sky@onenet.net]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000820074</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/28/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jon</FirstName>
<LastName>Fields</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME>Sr</PI_SUFX_NAME>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jon J Fields</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jjfields1@gmail.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000819947</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/28/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate>03/22/2021</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>OKLAHOMA STATE REGENTS FOR HIGHER EDUCATION</Name>
<CityName>OKLAHOMA CITY</CityName>
<ZipCode>731046217</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4056309620</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>655 RESEARCH PKWY STE 200</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oklahoma</StateName>
<StateCode>OK</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OK05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>KMULKMS8G9T8</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OKLAHOMA STATE REGENTS FOR HIGHER EDUCATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[OKLAHOMA STATE REGENTS FOR HIGHER EDUCATION]]></Name>
<CityName>Oklahoma City</CityName>
<StateCode>OK</StateCode>
<ZipCode>731043603</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[655 Research Parkway, Suite 200]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oklahoma</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OK05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8080</Code>
<Text>Campus Cyberinfrastructure</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~232275</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-e0956179-7fff-d29b-4c17-be8904820835"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Intellectual Merit</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The Small Institution Multiple Organization Regional OneOklahoma Friction Free Network project deployed advanced cyberinfrastructure tools and services to five small college campuses in Oklahoma&mdash;Oklahoma Christian University, Oklahoma State University Institute of Technology, Oklahoma State University - Oklahoma City, Redlands Community College, and University of Science and Arts of Oklahoma. Building on previous NSF-funded initiatives, this grant provided 10Gbps high-speed reliable connectivity to institutions that had not yet been able to take advantage of the opportunity to modernize their research networks. The project connected these five campuses to the OneOklahoma Friction Free Network (OFFN), Oklahoma&rsquo;s Science DMZ, managed by OneNet. The connections enabled researchers to move large datasets quickly and reliably via an ultra-high-speed network and permitted faculty and students to connect to supercomputers across the state, increasing their computational capabilities. These new computing resources are contributing to research initiatives in a wide range of disciplines, including chemistry, data science, nursing, agriculture, cybersecurity, ecology, geography, psychology and sociology, and promise to support future STEM education curriculum development.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Broader Impacts</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>As a result of these additional OFFN campus connections, OneNet has created new and diverse research collaboration capabilities across Oklahoma that have enabled faculty and students at smaller institutions to expand their research and education activities. Oklahoma has many underserved rural areas that lack basic resources and infrastructure. Access to even one new resource has the potential to cause a large positive ripple effect.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>By providing additional STEM and cyber-infrastructure educational opportunities as well as exposure to leading researchers and cyber-infrastructure practitioners, the OFFN connection has produced a significant educational impact for undergraduate and community college students on both rural and metropolitan campuses. Faculty are now learning to use and integrate these tools into their classroom instructional materials and curriculum. Increased comfort levels with technology boost students&rsquo; abilities to move on to more complex research in the future. Being able to train students properly using 21st-century tools is essential to ensuring that Oklahoma can keep pace with national and international research efforts that will help pave the way for further grant funding and research initiatives.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>As Oklahoma&rsquo;s research and education network, OneNet promotes OFFN as an interdisciplinary tool&mdash;one that can significantly alter the path of undergraduate research activities throughout the state. OFFN institutions host weekly calls where researchers share their experiences with using the system and brainstorm new ideas. In an effort to expand utilization, OneNet has also started a faculty outreach effort at our partner schools to educate them about the network and how they might harness it for both themselves and their students. Furthermore, OneNet encourages institutions to think of the OFFN connection as a recruiting tool to help retain local talent, as faculty and students can conduct higher-level research without moving to a different area of the state or a different state altogether. These efforts work together to strengthen the Oklahoma workforce and economy.&nbsp;&nbsp;</span></p> <div><span><br /></span></div> </span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/21/2022<br>      Modified by: April&nbsp;D&nbsp;Goode</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Intellectual Merit The Small Institution Multiple Organization Regional OneOklahoma Friction Free Network project deployed advanced cyberinfrastructure tools and services to five small college campuses in Oklahoma&mdash;Oklahoma Christian University, Oklahoma State University Institute of Technology, Oklahoma State University - Oklahoma City, Redlands Community College, and University of Science and Arts of Oklahoma. Building on previous NSF-funded initiatives, this grant provided 10Gbps high-speed reliable connectivity to institutions that had not yet been able to take advantage of the opportunity to modernize their research networks. The project connected these five campuses to the OneOklahoma Friction Free Network (OFFN), Oklahoma’s Science DMZ, managed by OneNet. The connections enabled researchers to move large datasets quickly and reliably via an ultra-high-speed network and permitted faculty and students to connect to supercomputers across the state, increasing their computational capabilities. These new computing resources are contributing to research initiatives in a wide range of disciplines, including chemistry, data science, nursing, agriculture, cybersecurity, ecology, geography, psychology and sociology, and promise to support future STEM education curriculum development.  Broader Impacts As a result of these additional OFFN campus connections, OneNet has created new and diverse research collaboration capabilities across Oklahoma that have enabled faculty and students at smaller institutions to expand their research and education activities. Oklahoma has many underserved rural areas that lack basic resources and infrastructure. Access to even one new resource has the potential to cause a large positive ripple effect.  By providing additional STEM and cyber-infrastructure educational opportunities as well as exposure to leading researchers and cyber-infrastructure practitioners, the OFFN connection has produced a significant educational impact for undergraduate and community college students on both rural and metropolitan campuses. Faculty are now learning to use and integrate these tools into their classroom instructional materials and curriculum. Increased comfort levels with technology boost students’ abilities to move on to more complex research in the future. Being able to train students properly using 21st-century tools is essential to ensuring that Oklahoma can keep pace with national and international research efforts that will help pave the way for further grant funding and research initiatives. As Oklahoma’s research and education network, OneNet promotes OFFN as an interdisciplinary tool&mdash;one that can significantly alter the path of undergraduate research activities throughout the state. OFFN institutions host weekly calls where researchers share their experiences with using the system and brainstorm new ideas. In an effort to expand utilization, OneNet has also started a faculty outreach effort at our partner schools to educate them about the network and how they might harness it for both themselves and their students. Furthermore, OneNet encourages institutions to think of the OFFN connection as a recruiting tool to help retain local talent, as faculty and students can conduct higher-level research without moving to a different area of the state or a different state altogether. These efforts work together to strengthen the Oklahoma workforce and economy.               Last Modified: 11/21/2022       Submitted by: April D Goode]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
