<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[CC* Planning: Designing a Process to Improve Research Computing Infrastructure at City Tech]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>99183.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>99183</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OAC</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure (OAC)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kevin Thompson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kthompso@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924220</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[New York City College of Technology, a comprehensive college within the City University of New York and a Hispanic-Serving Institution, is creating a five-year strategic plan for cyberinfrastructure (CI) and future investments and strategic management in research computing resources.  A team of faculty engaged in international high-performance computing projects are convening a broad-based stakeholder group to consider issues of CI governance and leadership, high-performance computing, data infrastructure, and faculty training and workforce development. The ecosystem of CI users includes researchers working on particle physics, galaxy formation, genomics and integrative systems biology, and protein dynamics and drug discovery, as well as faculty in a broad range of domains who need to learn the fundamentals of research computing, and students who are exposed to CI through their faculty mentors. These stakeholders are considering how to construct laterally and vertically integrated partnerships that draw upon the expertise of practitioners from New York State Education and Research Network, The Carpentries, and the NSF Established Program to Stimulate Competitive Research.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of the CC* planning initiative is to design a flexible, extensible, accessible research cyberinfrastructure (CI) that is capable of meeting the evolving computational needs of City Tech’s most advanced CI users while cultivating a long tail of impact within the larger CI ecosystem. Identified institutional needs include a faculty-led governance structure, systematic rather than ad hoc resource acquisition policies to avoid the creation of silos, increased professional CI support for users, and the creation of a stable and sustainable starting point for systemic CI planning and governance. This planning grant provides that starting point. The work of the project will proceed through a combination of forums, Working Groups, and consultations from entities with expertise in CI development. Topics for investigation include a faculty led leadership structure, data, HPC, and stakeholder engagement. Project deliverables are a five-year Cyberinfrastructure Master Plan and planning for future proposal submissions to the NSF MRI and CC* programs to seek partial support for implementation of the Master Plan.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/11/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/02/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2018892</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ariyeh</FirstName>
<LastName>Maller</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ariyeh Maller</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[amaller@citytech.cuny.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000070819</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/11/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Justin</FirstName>
<LastName>Vazquez-Poritz</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>F</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Justin F Vazquez-Poritz</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jvazquez-poritz@citytech.cuny.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000532203</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/11/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Andrea</FirstName>
<LastName>Ferroglia</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Andrea Ferroglia</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[aferroglia@citytech.cuny.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000574746</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/11/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jeremy</FirstName>
<LastName>Seto</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jeremy Seto</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jseto@citytech.cuny.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000647297</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/11/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mai</FirstName>
<LastName>Zahran</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mai Zahran</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mzahran@citytech.cuny.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000820280</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/11/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>CUNY New York City College of Technology</Name>
<CityName>BROOKLYN</CityName>
<ZipCode>112011909</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7182605560</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>300 JAY ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>DD5KCJHVVCV7</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH FOUNDATION OF THE CITY UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[CUNY New York City College of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>Brooklyn</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>112012902</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[300 Jay Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8080</Code>
<Text>Campus Cyberinfrastructure</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~99183</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>New York City College of Technology, the largest public college of technology in the North East, provides degree programs that are aligned with the professional workforce needs of industries critical to the nation's technological leadership within the global economy. This is directly linked with the opportunities provided for students to work with faculty on computationally-intensive areas such as particle physics, galactic modeling, genomics and drug discovery.</p> <p>This NSF planning grant project has enabled the college to conduct an ambitious, ecosystem-wide analysis of our research cyberinfrastructure that is carefully aligned with our major science drivers to build the essential spectrum of computing and data services needed to meet current and future directions in STEM research. In order to involve all stakeholders in this consensus-driven process, a College Research Council composed of faculty and staff from across the campus was created as a way to coordinate and communicate researcher needs, activities and accomplishments.</p> <p>Plans are underway to create a computational research center to help connect faculty researchers with computational resources, students with internship opportunities, and surrounding industries with computational expertise. Training workshops are being provided to help faculty across a wide range of disciplines learn how to apply various computational tools and resources to their research, such as our high-performance computer cluster as well as the Open Science Pool. Moreover, our computer cluster is in the process of being upgraded and expanded, with the possibility of linking it with the Open Science Pool.</p> <p>This will broaden access to advanced cyberinfrastructure research opportunities for underrepresented students at our college as well as at CUNY community colleges across the New York City area which are Minority Serving and Hispanic Serving Institutions. This is a critical component in order for New York City College of Technology to continue to be one of the top engines of economic mobility for underrepresented students within the New York City area.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/14/2023<br>      Modified by: Justin&nbsp;F&nbsp;Vazquez-Poritz</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ New York City College of Technology, the largest public college of technology in the North East, provides degree programs that are aligned with the professional workforce needs of industries critical to the nation's technological leadership within the global economy. This is directly linked with the opportunities provided for students to work with faculty on computationally-intensive areas such as particle physics, galactic modeling, genomics and drug discovery.  This NSF planning grant project has enabled the college to conduct an ambitious, ecosystem-wide analysis of our research cyberinfrastructure that is carefully aligned with our major science drivers to build the essential spectrum of computing and data services needed to meet current and future directions in STEM research. In order to involve all stakeholders in this consensus-driven process, a College Research Council composed of faculty and staff from across the campus was created as a way to coordinate and communicate researcher needs, activities and accomplishments.  Plans are underway to create a computational research center to help connect faculty researchers with computational resources, students with internship opportunities, and surrounding industries with computational expertise. Training workshops are being provided to help faculty across a wide range of disciplines learn how to apply various computational tools and resources to their research, such as our high-performance computer cluster as well as the Open Science Pool. Moreover, our computer cluster is in the process of being upgraded and expanded, with the possibility of linking it with the Open Science Pool.  This will broaden access to advanced cyberinfrastructure research opportunities for underrepresented students at our college as well as at CUNY community colleges across the New York City area which are Minority Serving and Hispanic Serving Institutions. This is a critical component in order for New York City College of Technology to continue to be one of the top engines of economic mobility for underrepresented students within the New York City area.       Last Modified: 08/14/2023       Submitted by: Justin F Vazquez-Poritz]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
