<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RCN-UBE Incubator: REAL (R in Education and Assessment of Learning)]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>74866.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>74866</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DBI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Amanda Simcox</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>asimcox@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928165</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Knowing how to use math and computing skills effectively has become essential to working in science, particularly for biologists in recent years. However, because of the rapid pace of change in biological and computing technologies, many faculty members find themselves teaching skills which are also new to them or that they had to learn independently. In this project, the research team seeks to develop a network of researchers and educators who will collaborate to increase their own computing and statistical skills, while also developing "best practices" of how to teach these skills to students. Using the programming language R, a free and open source coding language that is increasingly used in the biological sciences, the R in Education and Assessment of Learning (REAL) network will establish an inclusive, sustainable community of biology educators and biology education researchers who will both teach and use R for the betterment of biology research and education nationwide. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The REAL network aims to support the training of biology researchers in quantitative and computational methods; foster collaborations for the development, sharing and assessment of educational modules for quantitative skills and of R-code for biology education researchers; and to catalyze the development of common standards and best practices for the training of undergraduates and graduate students in quantitative and computational skills. The network’s central activity involves training an initial cohort of beginners in R to develop, assess and disseminate biology classroom modules to teach quantitative skills using R and/or develop and test R code scripts and packages tailored specifically for biology education research. REAL trainees will develop novel educational modules to infuse effective, up-to-date quantitative skills into the biology curriculum, rigorously assess the impact of their teaching, and make significant contributions to education research both at the interface of biology and computing and at the edges of current statistical practice. The REAL Network will increase the number of biology faculty with the skills to effectively teach quantitative and computational skills to biology undergraduates, contributing to a new generation of biologists ready to tackle the research and data analysis challenges posed by the development of novel high-throughput technologies. In addition, these faculty will also be better equipped to rigorously assess the educational outcomes of their students, leading to improved teaching practices and allowing for the development of common standards and best practices unique to the training of biologists in quantitative methods.This project is being jointly funded by the Directorate for Biological Sciences, Division of Biological Infrastructure, and the Directorate for Education and Human Resources, Division of Undergraduate Education as part of their efforts to address the challenges posed in Vision and Change in Undergraduate Biology Education: A Call to Action (http://visionandchange/finalreport/).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/23/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/23/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2018592</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Abha</FirstName>
<LastName>Ahuja</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Abha Ahuja</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[abha@minerva.kgi.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000818863</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/23/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Natalia</FirstName>
<LastName>Caporale</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Natalia Caporale</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ncaporale@ucdavis.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000766997</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/23/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Emily</FirstName>
<LastName>Weigel</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>G</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Emily G Weigel</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[emily.weigel@biosci.gatech.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000818772</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/23/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
<LastName>Erdmann</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Robert M Erdmann</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[rerdmann@umn.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000811874</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/23/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Minnesota-Twin Cities</Name>
<CityName>MINNEAPOLIS</CityName>
<ZipCode>554552009</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6126245599</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>200 OAK ST SE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>KABJZBBJ4B54</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MINNESOTA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Minnesota Rochester]]></Name>
<CityName>Rochester</CityName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>559044199</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[111 S Broadway, Suite 300]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MN01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>037Y</Code>
<Text>UBE - Undergraduate Biology Ed</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1998</Code>
<Text>IUSE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1664</Code>
<Text>RESEARCH COORD NETWK IN BIO SC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0420</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>04002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~74866</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p id="docs-internal-guid-7218f126-7fff-aa0f-cfe3-e928f5b67052" style="line-height: 1.38; text-indent: 36pt; margin-top: 12pt; margin-bottom: 12pt;" dir="ltr"><span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">The REAL (R in Education and Assessment of Learning) network was established with the primary goal of creating an inclusive network of biology educators who are trained in the programming language R.&nbsp; The participating educators have been empowered to share their newfound expertise with a new generation of student biologists who, as a result, will be taught in a way that better positions them to tackle the challenges of contemporary and future data collection methods and technologies.&nbsp; In addition, the newly trained biology faculty learning community participants are in a better position to assess the successes and failures of students within their courses and institutions, which will in turn put them in a better position to steer and drive the adoption of evidence-based best practices in quantitative biology education.</span></p> <p style="line-height: 1.38; text-indent: 36pt; margin-top: 12pt; margin-bottom: 12pt;" dir="ltr"><span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">12 participants were selected from a broad pool of over 100 applicants, underscoring the desire within the biology education community for this type of training and community building.&nbsp; Demographic information provided by participants showed them to represent a diverse cross-section of the biology education community, in terms of race/ethnicity, gender identity, sexual orientation, first-generation status, and institutional affiliation.&nbsp; The participants participated in an eight week short course in the basics of the R language, which a post-course evaluation indicates led to a significant increase in participant ability and comfort with using R for a range of purposes, including their own research and teaching. Next, participants contributed to two smaller learning communities - one devoted to using R in education research, and the other focused on the production of education materials and curriculum.&nbsp; The initial results of both learning communities were shared with the broader biology education community at the 2022 Annual Meeting of the Society for the Advancement of Biology Education Research.</span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/05/2022<br>      Modified by: Robert&nbsp;M&nbsp;Erdmann</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[The REAL (R in Education and Assessment of Learning) network was established with the primary goal of creating an inclusive network of biology educators who are trained in the programming language R.  The participating educators have been empowered to share their newfound expertise with a new generation of student biologists who, as a result, will be taught in a way that better positions them to tackle the challenges of contemporary and future data collection methods and technologies.  In addition, the newly trained biology faculty learning community participants are in a better position to assess the successes and failures of students within their courses and institutions, which will in turn put them in a better position to steer and drive the adoption of evidence-based best practices in quantitative biology education. 12 participants were selected from a broad pool of over 100 applicants, underscoring the desire within the biology education community for this type of training and community building.  Demographic information provided by participants showed them to represent a diverse cross-section of the biology education community, in terms of race/ethnicity, gender identity, sexual orientation, first-generation status, and institutional affiliation.  The participants participated in an eight week short course in the basics of the R language, which a post-course evaluation indicates led to a significant increase in participant ability and comfort with using R for a range of purposes, including their own research and teaching. Next, participants contributed to two smaller learning communities - one devoted to using R in education research, and the other focused on the production of education materials and curriculum.  The initial results of both learning communities were shared with the broader biology education community at the 2022 Annual Meeting of the Society for the Advancement of Biology Education Research.       Last Modified: 12/05/2022       Submitted by: Robert M Erdmann]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
