<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[MRI: Acquisition of a High Resolution MicroCT System]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>275692.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>275692</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Wendy C. Crone</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>wcrone@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924681</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This Major Research Instrumentation (MRI) award provides support for the acquisition of a high-resolution X-Ray microCT imaging system to enhance research and education at the City College of New York (CUNY). This instrument will enable tomographic imaging and modeling that spans from a few millimeters to sub-micrometers—enabling fundamental research in a broad range of fields at CUNY and nearby institutions. New knowledge that will be gained from this research could lead to major medical advances in diagnosis and therapeutics—enhancing the quality of life for US citizens. This microCT system will foster synergistic collaboration between faculty in engineering, science, and medicine in the New York City area. The instrumentation will be used to enable training for graduate, undergraduate and high school students in imaging processing, numerical modeling, finite element analysis and research design. &lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;This instrument will enable a wide variety of image-based studies on the mechanical behavior of biological tissues.  In addition to basic characterization of intact and damaged tissues, the instrumentation will enable the researchers to map subcellular markers of inflammation markers and cytokines in response to mechanical loading and to generate images of tissues during loading.  This will advance  fundamental understanding of the microstructural deformations that occur during loading, and how this alters mechanical behavior of these tissues. For example, the researchers will conduct potentially transformative fundamental  research on the imaging and numerical modeling of the rupture of human fibroatheromas due to microcalcifications, multiscale imaging and modeling of knee fatigue damage and repair,  the structure-function relationship in trabecular bone, the role of tissue damage in bone mechanotransduction and brain damage due to blunt impacts to the head.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/09/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/09/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2018485</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ali</FirstName>
<LastName>Sadegh</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ali M Sadegh</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[sadegh@ccny.cuny.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000330072</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/09/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Luis</FirstName>
<LastName>Cardoso</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Luis Cardoso</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[cardoso@ccny.cuny.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000122322</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/09/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Adrian</FirstName>
<LastName>Rodriguez-Contreras</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Adrian Rodriguez-Contreras</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[arodrig@sci.ccny.cuny.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000522557</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/09/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mitchell</FirstName>
<LastName>Schaffler</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mitchell Schaffler</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mschaffler@ccny.cuny.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000540105</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/09/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>CUNY City College</Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<ZipCode>100319101</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2126505418</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>160 CONVENT AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>L952KGDMSLV5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH FOUNDATION OF THE CITY UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[CUNY City College]]></Name>
<CityName>New York</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>100319101</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[160 Convent Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>Major Research Instrumentation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>028E</Code>
<Text>BIOMECHANICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>070Z</Code>
<Text>MB-Mechanobiology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~275692</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The goal of this proposal was to acquire a Bruker-SkyScan 1272 High-resolution X-Ray MicroCT imaging system for enhancement of research and teaching at the City College of New York. This instrument allow us acquiring 3D images of the internal structures of biological tissues for Biomedical research and numerical modeling. The system was installed at CCNY in March 2021 and a few months later the in-situ loading stage was also delivered. Five researchers received direct training from Bruker's technician and we started providing access to the users of the system.</p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Intellectual Outcomes</span>: The MicroCT imaging system is being used in several research areas, including cardiovascular, musculoskeletal, hearing disability, stem cell-based tissue engineering, tissue damage, fracture, and for the development of improved imaging approaches. In particular, we use the microCT system to scan the human coronary vessels of individuals that suffered myocardial infarction, to advance our understanding of the mechanisms of plaque rupture that play an important role in heart attacks. We have focused our attention on the role of microcalcifications, which are detected using microCT, as a biomarker of high plaque rupture risk. Another major research area that has benefited of this system is the study of mechanotransduction by osteocytes in bone through the analysis of bone fluid flow in different animal models. The microCT has been instrumental in characterizing changes in tissue microarchitecture and mineralization as a consequence of osteoporosis, mechanical disuse or osteogenesis imperfecta. The microCT provide us with quantitative 3D data that is used to compare the effect of different mechanical environments and pharmaceutical therapies on these musculoskeletal diseases. Another major area of interest by researchers at CCNY is the study of microdamage on bone mechanotransduction and fracture. MicroCT has been instrumental in assessing changes in musculoskeletal tissues as a consequence of excess mechanical loading in animal models, and how bone microdamage plays an important role in bone signaling to initiate bone remodeling. Most recently, the system has been used to quantify the amount and distribution of mineralization in 3D tissue engineering scaffolds seeded with stem cells that are stimulated to differentiate into bone cells. It is expected that the use of this microCT will help us characterize different approaches to determine the optimal conditions for such tissue-engineered constructs, which could be used as tissue implants. Regarding the development of new imaging approaches, we are testing and developing a number of contrast agents with the goal of improve the simultaneous imaging of soft and hard tissues. The instrument?s high resolution capabilities, when combined with soft tissue contrast, provide unique means to investigate the interaction of multiple tissue types in a complex organ, such as the hearing system or knee joints. Overall, this instrument has enhanced and opened new research avenues for researchers at CCNY.</p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Broader Impact outcomes</span>: The acquisition and access to the new microCT system represents a significant technological impact for our institution and researchers. The acquisition of this unique imaging platform has a very positive and broad impact on basic science and applied bioengineering research in several STEM fields, including cardiovascular, biomechanics, tissue engineering, stem cells and hearing loss. Also, the advanced imaging capabilities of this instrument enhances our research infrastructure and foster synergistic collaboration between faculty in engineering, science, and medical institutions. There is also a significant educational impact on the training of human resources at the PhD, Masters and Bachelor levels. Sophisticated imaging infrastructure for teaching and research is also important to attract high school students to STEM fields, as demonstrated by the summer science camp, where high school students learn the basics of microCT scanning and image processing. This instrument provide unique access to students from underrepresented groups, to stimulate its inclusion and retention at CCNY educational programs. Finally, the research conducted using this instrument has a broad societal impact, due to the clinical relevance of biomedical research enabled by such state-of the-art system. We expect this system may contribute to improve our understanding of several diseases, diagnosis and therapeutics, thus, positively impacting society welfare in general.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/29/2022<br>      Modified by: Luis&nbsp;Cardoso</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The goal of this proposal was to acquire a Bruker-SkyScan 1272 High-resolution X-Ray MicroCT imaging system for enhancement of research and teaching at the City College of New York. This instrument allow us acquiring 3D images of the internal structures of biological tissues for Biomedical research and numerical modeling. The system was installed at CCNY in March 2021 and a few months later the in-situ loading stage was also delivered. Five researchers received direct training from Bruker's technician and we started providing access to the users of the system.  Intellectual Outcomes: The MicroCT imaging system is being used in several research areas, including cardiovascular, musculoskeletal, hearing disability, stem cell-based tissue engineering, tissue damage, fracture, and for the development of improved imaging approaches. In particular, we use the microCT system to scan the human coronary vessels of individuals that suffered myocardial infarction, to advance our understanding of the mechanisms of plaque rupture that play an important role in heart attacks. We have focused our attention on the role of microcalcifications, which are detected using microCT, as a biomarker of high plaque rupture risk. Another major research area that has benefited of this system is the study of mechanotransduction by osteocytes in bone through the analysis of bone fluid flow in different animal models. The microCT has been instrumental in characterizing changes in tissue microarchitecture and mineralization as a consequence of osteoporosis, mechanical disuse or osteogenesis imperfecta. The microCT provide us with quantitative 3D data that is used to compare the effect of different mechanical environments and pharmaceutical therapies on these musculoskeletal diseases. Another major area of interest by researchers at CCNY is the study of microdamage on bone mechanotransduction and fracture. MicroCT has been instrumental in assessing changes in musculoskeletal tissues as a consequence of excess mechanical loading in animal models, and how bone microdamage plays an important role in bone signaling to initiate bone remodeling. Most recently, the system has been used to quantify the amount and distribution of mineralization in 3D tissue engineering scaffolds seeded with stem cells that are stimulated to differentiate into bone cells. It is expected that the use of this microCT will help us characterize different approaches to determine the optimal conditions for such tissue-engineered constructs, which could be used as tissue implants. Regarding the development of new imaging approaches, we are testing and developing a number of contrast agents with the goal of improve the simultaneous imaging of soft and hard tissues. The instrument?s high resolution capabilities, when combined with soft tissue contrast, provide unique means to investigate the interaction of multiple tissue types in a complex organ, such as the hearing system or knee joints. Overall, this instrument has enhanced and opened new research avenues for researchers at CCNY.  Broader Impact outcomes: The acquisition and access to the new microCT system represents a significant technological impact for our institution and researchers. The acquisition of this unique imaging platform has a very positive and broad impact on basic science and applied bioengineering research in several STEM fields, including cardiovascular, biomechanics, tissue engineering, stem cells and hearing loss. Also, the advanced imaging capabilities of this instrument enhances our research infrastructure and foster synergistic collaboration between faculty in engineering, science, and medical institutions. There is also a significant educational impact on the training of human resources at the PhD, Masters and Bachelor levels. Sophisticated imaging infrastructure for teaching and research is also important to attract high school students to STEM fields, as demonstrated by the summer science camp, where high school students learn the basics of microCT scanning and image processing. This instrument provide unique access to students from underrepresented groups, to stimulate its inclusion and retention at CCNY educational programs. Finally, the research conducted using this instrument has a broad societal impact, due to the clinical relevance of biomedical research enabled by such state-of the-art system. We expect this system may contribute to improve our understanding of several diseases, diagnosis and therapeutics, thus, positively impacting society welfare in general.       Last Modified: 06/29/2022       Submitted by: Luis Cardoso]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
