<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[MRI: Acquisition of Ion Mill for TEM Sample Preparation]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>136051.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>136051</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Leonard Spinu</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lspinu@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922665</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This award from the Major Research Instrumentation program supports Smith College with the acquisition of Transmission Electron Microscopy sample preparation tool.  Acquisition of this tool greatly expands Smith’s capabilities to make non-biological samples for study in the electron microscope, and thus opens new research areas to Smith faculty and students, who are the primary users of the tool.  This tool allows researchers at Smith to offer undergraduates accessible pathways into meaningful materials research in their first two years of college and opens doors for women and underrepresented minorities who make up 100% of Smith students.  Involvement with research in the early college years is known to positively affect retention of women and under-represented minorities in the sciences.  In addition, students gain meaningful skills such as how to make samples for the electron microscope, how to use an electron microscope, and how to analyze the results.  These skills are valued in graduate programs and in industries that rely on materials development.  Acquisition of this tool also increases the ability of the faculty to mentor women undergraduates of all racial and economic backgrounds in the physical and materials sciences.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award from the Major Research Instrumentation program supports Smith College with the acquisition of a Transmission Electron Microscopy (TEM) sample preparation tool.  Acquisition of this tool greatly expands Smith’s capabilities to make non-biological samples for study in the electron microscope, and thus opens new research areas to Smith faculty and students, who are the primary users of the tool. The acquisition of the ion mill will enable scientists at Smith College to make high quality cross-sectional TEM specimen, improved quality plan-view TEM specimen, and to train Smith College undergraduates to make TEM cross-sectional samples and improved plan-view samples. Acquisition of this tool greatly improves the opportunities for current and future Smith faculty and students to enter into collaborations with researchers at other institutions who engage in research on fabrication of hard/brittle materials and especially thin films on substrates such as silicon, GaAs or other semiconductor materials.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/24/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/24/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2018560</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Joyce</FirstName>
<LastName>Palmer-Fortune</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Joyce Palmer-Fortune</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jfortune@smith.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000558992</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/24/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Smith College</Name>
<CityName>NORTHAMPTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>010636304</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4135842700</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>10 ELM ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>KRDJLRA9X6F3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>THE TRUSTEES OF THE SMITH COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Smith College]]></Name>
<CityName>Northampton</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>010636303</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[McConnell Hall Room 323]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>Major Research Instrumentation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~136051</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The main outcome of this NMRI was achieved!&nbsp; We were able to purchase the Ion Mill, and the PI was trained as both a user and as a provider of routine maintenance.&nbsp; The Ion mill has been operational since March 2021, and has been in use continuously since then, approximately 6 months.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>A total of about 35 plan-view samples have been made and examined to date.&nbsp; We can reproducibly see the microstructure of the thin film thermometers in these initial results.&nbsp;</p> <p>We also had secondary objectives related to giving more women and minorities access to working in a lab and gaining research skills with this equipment.&nbsp; We also wanted to make this available to other research groups within Smith and at nearby colleges.&nbsp; Toward those goals:</p> <p>1) Three students were trained as users of the Ion mill in March 2021, and have successfully made TEM samples using this equipment.&nbsp; All three students were women with an interest in Physics or Engineering, and one was a student of color and first-generation college student. All 3 of these students are on track for advanced work after graduation in physics or a related field.</p> <p>2) Starting in the fall 2021, 5 more students are in training, all women, 1 student of color, one other first generation college student.&nbsp; These students are all first-year students, so I cannot say at this point whether they are on track for advanced work in PHY or related fields.</p> <p>3) We received one request to use the Ion mill by another researcher at Smith College in the physics department.&nbsp; That researcher was trained and was able to use the Ion Mill to prepare two samples.&nbsp;</p> <p>We are looking forward to more students having access to research and success at making TEM samples with this Ion mill, and we are also looking forward to collaborations that this equipment will make possible, not just within the PHY dept., but across departments and with colleagues at nearby institutions.&nbsp;</p> <p>@font-face  {font-family:"Cambria Math";  panose-1:2 4 5 3 5 4 6 3 2 4;  mso-font-charset:0;  mso-generic-font-family:roman;  mso-font-pitch:variable;  mso-font-signature:-536870145 1107305727 0 0 415 0;}@font-face  {font-family:Calibri;  panose-1:2 15 5 2 2 2 4 3 2 4;  mso-font-charset:0;  mso-generic-font-family:swiss;  mso-font-pitch:variable;  mso-font-signature:-536859905 -1073732485 9 0 511 0;}p.MsoNormal, li.MsoNormal, div.MsoNormal  {mso-style-unhide:no;  mso-style-qformat:yes;  mso-style-parent:";  margin:0in;  mso-pagination:widow-orphan;  font-size:12.0pt;  font-family:"Calibri",sans-serif;  mso-ascii-font-family:Calibri;  mso-ascii-theme-font:minor-latin;  mso-fareast-font-family:Calibri;  mso-fareast-theme-font:minor-latin;  mso-hansi-font-family:Calibri;  mso-hansi-theme-font:minor-latin;  mso-bidi-font-family:"Times New Roman";  mso-bidi-theme-font:minor-bidi;}p  {mso-style-noshow:yes;  mso-style-priority:99;  mso-margin-top-alt:auto;  margin-right:0in;  mso-margin-bottom-alt:auto;  margin-left:0in;  mso-pagination:widow-orphan;  font-size:12.0pt;  font-family:"Times New Roman",serif;  mso-fareast-font-family:"Times New Roman";}.MsoChpDefault  {mso-style-type:export-only;  mso-default-props:yes;  font-family:"Calibri",sans-serif;  mso-ascii-font-family:Calibri;  mso-ascii-theme-font:minor-latin;  mso-fareast-font-family:Calibri;  mso-fareast-theme-font:minor-latin;  mso-hansi-font-family:Calibri;  mso-hansi-theme-font:minor-latin;  mso-bidi-font-family:"Times New Roman";  mso-bidi-theme-font:minor-bidi;}div.WordSection1  {page:WordSection1;}</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/30/2021<br>      Modified by: Joyce&nbsp;Palmer-Fortune</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The main outcome of this NMRI was achieved!  We were able to purchase the Ion Mill, and the PI was trained as both a user and as a provider of routine maintenance.  The Ion mill has been operational since March 2021, and has been in use continuously since then, approximately 6 months.    A total of about 35 plan-view samples have been made and examined to date.  We can reproducibly see the microstructure of the thin film thermometers in these initial results.   We also had secondary objectives related to giving more women and minorities access to working in a lab and gaining research skills with this equipment.  We also wanted to make this available to other research groups within Smith and at nearby colleges.  Toward those goals:  1) Three students were trained as users of the Ion mill in March 2021, and have successfully made TEM samples using this equipment.  All three students were women with an interest in Physics or Engineering, and one was a student of color and first-generation college student. All 3 of these students are on track for advanced work after graduation in physics or a related field.  2) Starting in the fall 2021, 5 more students are in training, all women, 1 student of color, one other first generation college student.  These students are all first-year students, so I cannot say at this point whether they are on track for advanced work in PHY or related fields.  3) We received one request to use the Ion mill by another researcher at Smith College in the physics department.  That researcher was trained and was able to use the Ion Mill to prepare two samples.   We are looking forward to more students having access to research and success at making TEM samples with this Ion mill, and we are also looking forward to collaborations that this equipment will make possible, not just within the PHY dept., but across departments and with colleagues at nearby institutions.   @font-face  {font-family:"Cambria Math";  panose-1:2 4 5 3 5 4 6 3 2 4;  mso-font-charset:0;  mso-generic-font-family:roman;  mso-font-pitch:variable;  mso-font-signature:-536870145 1107305727 0 0 415 0;}@font-face  {font-family:Calibri;  panose-1:2 15 5 2 2 2 4 3 2 4;  mso-font-charset:0;  mso-generic-font-family:swiss;  mso-font-pitch:variable;  mso-font-signature:-536859905 -1073732485 9 0 511 0;}p.MsoNormal, li.MsoNormal, div.MsoNormal  {mso-style-unhide:no;  mso-style-qformat:yes;  mso-style-parent:";  margin:0in;  mso-pagination:widow-orphan;  font-size:12.0pt;  font-family:"Calibri",sans-serif;  mso-ascii-font-family:Calibri;  mso-ascii-theme-font:minor-latin;  mso-fareast-font-family:Calibri;  mso-fareast-theme-font:minor-latin;  mso-hansi-font-family:Calibri;  mso-hansi-theme-font:minor-latin;  mso-bidi-font-family:"Times New Roman";  mso-bidi-theme-font:minor-bidi;}p  {mso-style-noshow:yes;  mso-style-priority:99;  mso-margin-top-alt:auto;  margin-right:0in;  mso-margin-bottom-alt:auto;  margin-left:0in;  mso-pagination:widow-orphan;  font-size:12.0pt;  font-family:"Times New Roman",serif;  mso-fareast-font-family:"Times New Roman";}.MsoChpDefault  {mso-style-type:export-only;  mso-default-props:yes;  font-family:"Calibri",sans-serif;  mso-ascii-font-family:Calibri;  mso-ascii-theme-font:minor-latin;  mso-fareast-font-family:Calibri;  mso-fareast-theme-font:minor-latin;  mso-hansi-font-family:Calibri;  mso-hansi-theme-font:minor-latin;  mso-bidi-font-family:"Times New Roman";  mso-bidi-theme-font:minor-bidi;}div.WordSection1  {page:WordSection1;}       Last Modified: 09/30/2021       Submitted by: Joyce Palmer-Fortune]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
