<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[MRI: Acquisition of an X-ray Computed Tomography Scanner for Three-Dimensional Characterization of a Wide Range of Geological and Biological Archives]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>489934.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>489934</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OCE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kandace Binkley</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kbinkley@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927577</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Critical information, unavailable from any other source, is contained within natural geological and/or biological archives and a large multi-disciplinary academic community across the United States is developing and applying state-of-the art technologies to extract and interpret this information with growing accuracy and precision. Much of it is structural, and macro- and microscale 3D imaging provide a critical first step in the characterization of samples and quantification of structural data. Yet facilities currently available to the United States academic community for the three-dimensional characterization of geological and biological samples, are limited. This award provides for the acquisition of a Geotek Rotating X-ray Computed Tomography (RXCT) scanner to be housed within the National Science Foundation (NSF)-supported Seafloor Samples Laboratory (SFSL) at the Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution (WHOI). The scanner will be operated as a center to service the existing and growing need for 3D imaging and analysis within the ocean sciences community. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The RXCT scanner will facilitate the 3D characterization and analysis of geological and biological archives readily accessible to researchers across the US. Open access to non-destructive, macro- and microscale imaging of corals, shellfish and other marine calcifiers, sediment cores, wood and speleothems, transforming researchers' ability to address critical questions about environmental change and its impacts on living systems. Furthermore, open access to 3D imaging will drive the development of new technologies for the quantification, analysis, interpretation and 3D animation of structural data. Digital 3D images and animations will be shared across the world, via multiple media types, connecting science with the public, and inspiring the next generation of scientists.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/22/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/22/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2018314</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Anne</FirstName>
<LastName>Cohen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Anne Cohen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[acohen@whoi.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000525918</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/22/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jeffrey</FirstName>
<LastName>Donnelly</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jeffrey Donnelly</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jdonnelly@whoi.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000107180</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/22/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution</Name>
<CityName>WOODS HOLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>025431535</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5082893542</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>266 WOODS HOLE RD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>GFKFBWG2TV98</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WOODS HOLE OCEANOGRAPHIC INSTITUTION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution]]></Name>
<CityName>Woods Hole</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>025431535</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[266, Woods Hole Rd]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>Major Research Instrumentation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~489934</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="Default">Essential information is contained within natural geological and/or biological archives and a large multi-disciplinary academic community across the United States is developing and applying state-of-the art technologies to extract and interpret this information with growing accuracy and precision. Much of it is structural, and macro- and microscale 3D imaging provide a critical first step in the characterization of samples and quantification of structural data. The acquisition of the Geotek Rotating X-ray Computed Tomography (RXCT) scanner housed within the National Science Foundation (NSF)-supported Seafloor Samples Laboratory (SFSL) at the Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution (WHOI) now provides for this growing need for 3D imaging and analysis within the US ocean sciences community.&nbsp;</p> <p class="Default">The RXCT scanner makes 3D characterization and analysis of geological and biological archives readily accessible to researchers across the US. Open access to non-destructive, macro- and microscale imaging of corals, shellfish and other marine organisms, sediment cores, wood and speleothems, and is transforming our ability to address critical questions about climate change and its impacts on living systems. Furthermore, access to 3D imaging may drive the development of new technologies for the quantification, analysis, interpretation and 3D animation of structural data. Digital 3D images and animations will be shared across the world, via multiple media types, connecting our science with the public, and inspiring the next generation of scientists.&nbsp;</p> <p class="Default">The societal benefits and outcomes of the research enabled by the RXCT scanner are potentially far reaching, providing critical information on climate and environmental change, and how these changes impact living systems, including human communities. For example, understanding the drivers of changes in tropical cyclone activity is of critical societal interest as damaging storms, in combination with rising sea levels, threaten the economic landscape of North American coastal regions. The benefits to the scientific community of access to 3D imaging of scientific samples are also far-reaching, providing unprecedented opportunity for public engagement in environmental science and a platform for inspiring, educating and training the next generation of scientists. The RXCT scanner is housed and operated by the WHOI SFSL greatly enhancing the research, education and training capacity of the facility and complementing existing capabilities.&nbsp;</p> <p class="Default">&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/05/2022<br>      Modified by: Jeffrey&nbsp;Donnelly</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[Essential information is contained within natural geological and/or biological archives and a large multi-disciplinary academic community across the United States is developing and applying state-of-the art technologies to extract and interpret this information with growing accuracy and precision. Much of it is structural, and macro- and microscale 3D imaging provide a critical first step in the characterization of samples and quantification of structural data. The acquisition of the Geotek Rotating X-ray Computed Tomography (RXCT) scanner housed within the National Science Foundation (NSF)-supported Seafloor Samples Laboratory (SFSL) at the Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution (WHOI) now provides for this growing need for 3D imaging and analysis within the US ocean sciences community.  The RXCT scanner makes 3D characterization and analysis of geological and biological archives readily accessible to researchers across the US. Open access to non-destructive, macro- and microscale imaging of corals, shellfish and other marine organisms, sediment cores, wood and speleothems, and is transforming our ability to address critical questions about climate change and its impacts on living systems. Furthermore, access to 3D imaging may drive the development of new technologies for the quantification, analysis, interpretation and 3D animation of structural data. Digital 3D images and animations will be shared across the world, via multiple media types, connecting our science with the public, and inspiring the next generation of scientists.  The societal benefits and outcomes of the research enabled by the RXCT scanner are potentially far reaching, providing critical information on climate and environmental change, and how these changes impact living systems, including human communities. For example, understanding the drivers of changes in tropical cyclone activity is of critical societal interest as damaging storms, in combination with rising sea levels, threaten the economic landscape of North American coastal regions. The benefits to the scientific community of access to 3D imaging of scientific samples are also far-reaching, providing unprecedented opportunity for public engagement in environmental science and a platform for inspiring, educating and training the next generation of scientists. The RXCT scanner is housed and operated by the WHOI SFSL greatly enhancing the research, education and training capacity of the facility and complementing existing capabilities.          Last Modified: 12/05/2022       Submitted by: Jeffrey Donnelly]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
