<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Doctoral Dissertation Research in DRMS: Individual differences in Type 1 thought: The other half of human intelligence]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>30356.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>30356</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Robert O'Connor</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>roconnor@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927263</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This research project is designed to extend our understanding of intelligence to types of thinking that have been largely ignored in the intelligence literature. IQ tests are among the most powerful predictors of individual achievement and outcomes, including education, salary, and health. Prominent theories of intelligence and IQ tests have focused on a cluster of cognitive abilities that require effortful, deliberative, working memory-heavy processing such as logical, spatial, and verbal abilities, which fall under the umbrella of what psychologists call Type 2 reasoning. Intelligence research has largely ignored a second class of abilities—called Type 1 abilities—which operate automatically, effortlessly, and without working memory (such as recognizing your mother in a photo, or solving 1+1 = X). This program of research will investigate whether individual differences in Type 1 abilities are the “other half” of human intelligence, alongside Type 2 abilities. This work may improve aptitude testing and placement in educational and professional settings. Additionally, the proposed work has potential to improve education and training methods by providing an unprecedented evidence-based approach to developing individualized learning skill profiles, allowing education to be tailored to individual abilities.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Currently, the dominant theory about the nature of intelligence holds that it is a unitary entity. Research has consistently found that a single measure of general intelligence (the g factor) can predict all other specific cognitive abilities (such as verbal skills, math skills, and even interpersonal skills). However, this work has largely failed to test Type 1 abilities due to a number of assumptions that have since been demonstrated to be false, such as the notion that individuals do not vary in their Type 1 abilities. Surprising preliminary evidence suggests that despite the g factor’s broad predictive ability, it may be unrelated to Type 1 abilities. This would mean that what we know about Type 2 intelligence from traditional IQ tests may not apply to Type 1 abilities. This project will develop tests to measure individual differences in Type 1 abilities and use them to investigate whether Type 1 abilities are unitary or contain multiple factors. Second, the project will contribute to emerging evidence about the independence of Type 1 abilities from Type 2 abilities by examining the relationship between Type 1 abilities and a battery of existing IQ tests. Finally, we will address the real-world implications of the ability to measure Type 1 IQ by investigating what life outcomes Type 1 IQ predicts.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/08/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/08/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2018073</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Keela</FirstName>
<LastName>Thomson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Keela Thomson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[keelat@andrew.cmu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000818532</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/08/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
<LastName>Oppenheimer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Daniel M Oppenheimer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[oppenheimer@cmu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000644791</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/08/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Carnegie-Mellon University</Name>
<CityName>PITTSBURGH</CityName>
<ZipCode>152133815</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4122688746</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5000 FORBES AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>U3NKNFLNQ613</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CARNEGIE MELLON UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>U3NKNFLNQ613</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Carnegie-Mellon University]]></Name>
<CityName>Pittsburgh</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>152133815</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5000 Forbes Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1321</Code>
<Text>Decision, Risk &amp; Mgmt Sci</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~30356</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The most prominent finding in the literature on individual differences in intelligence is what is known as the "positive manifold": on average people who are good at one cognitive task are good at all cognitive tasks.&nbsp; Verbal intelligence is correlated with mathematical intelligence which is correlated with interpersonal intelligence which is correlated with kinesthetic intelligence and so on.&nbsp; This has led scholars of intelligence to speculate that there is a single factor that underlies individual differences in mental ability, which is known as general g.<br /> <br /> However, while scholars have examined dozens of domains, such domains have typically had one thing in common - they require working memory, what Decision Scientists would call "Type 2" thinking.&nbsp; Type 2 thinking is characterized as deliberate, conscious, and effortful - solving logic puzzles or doing complex math, for example.&nbsp; In contrast, Type&nbsp;1 thinking is characterized as automatic, associative, unconscious, and largely effortless - recognizing a friend's face or walking without falling on a flat surface while sober.&nbsp; Historically, Type 1 thinking has not been thought of as "intelligence" and scholars believed that there weren't much in the way of individual differences.&nbsp; <br /> <br /> Recent work has led us to revise this assumption.&nbsp; Studies in developmental psychology have suggested robust individual differences in Type 1 thinking.&nbsp; But to date, nobody knows if they fall within the positive manifold, or if they form a distinct type of intelligence.&nbsp; The present project aimed to test the stability of differences in Type 1 thought, develop valid and reliable measurements of these differences, and see if Type 1 thought represents unique variance in explaining why some people are more cognitively capable than others.</p> <p>In this research program, we created several Type 1 tests that relied on implicit pattern recognition.&nbsp; For example, one task was a video game in which alien ships appeared on different quadrants of the screen, and players had to press the appropriate keyboard key to &ldquo;shoot at the enemy ships&rdquo; as quickly as possible.&nbsp; Unbeknownst to the people playing the game, there was a hidden pattern in where the ships appeared.&nbsp; While nobody consciously recognized the pattern, participants did, over time, learn the predictive cues and begin to anticipate the next ship&rsquo;s location, which enabled them to become faster.&nbsp;&nbsp; Critically, some people implicitly learned the patterns faster than other people, and this difference was stable and reliable.&nbsp;</p> <p>We then compared people&rsquo;s abilities on the Type 1 tests that we had developed to classic tests of IQ &ndash; tests of Type 2 thinking.&nbsp;&nbsp; &nbsp;We found that while all tests of Type 2 thinking were highly correlated with each other (replicating the classic pattern that has been observed for 100 years) some of the Type 1 tests were not related to standard IQ measures.&nbsp; In other words, we have identified a novel type of intelligence.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>This is the first psychometrically distinct form of intelligence to have been identified in nearly 100 years (previous alternate accounts of intelligence such as Gardner&rsquo;s &ldquo;Multiple Intelligence,&rdquo; Sternberg&rsquo;s &ldquo;triarchic intelligence,&rdquo; or Goleman&rsquo;s &ldquo;EQ&rdquo; have all highly correlated with standard IQ measures).&nbsp;&nbsp; It expands our understanding of what intelligence is, opens the door to the development of novel approaches to training and education, and may be useful for personnel selection and understanding of how different people can most effectively contribute to organizations.&nbsp;</p> <p>The grant also funded the training of promising young scientists at both the undergraduate and graduate (PhD) level, and created a number of methodological innovations that will help advance scientific inquiry moving forward.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/27/2023<br>      Modified by: Daniel&nbsp;M&nbsp;Oppenheimer</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The most prominent finding in the literature on individual differences in intelligence is what is known as the "positive manifold": on average people who are good at one cognitive task are good at all cognitive tasks.  Verbal intelligence is correlated with mathematical intelligence which is correlated with interpersonal intelligence which is correlated with kinesthetic intelligence and so on.  This has led scholars of intelligence to speculate that there is a single factor that underlies individual differences in mental ability, which is known as general g.    However, while scholars have examined dozens of domains, such domains have typically had one thing in common - they require working memory, what Decision Scientists would call "Type 2" thinking.  Type 2 thinking is characterized as deliberate, conscious, and effortful - solving logic puzzles or doing complex math, for example.  In contrast, Type 1 thinking is characterized as automatic, associative, unconscious, and largely effortless - recognizing a friend's face or walking without falling on a flat surface while sober.  Historically, Type 1 thinking has not been thought of as "intelligence" and scholars believed that there weren't much in the way of individual differences.      Recent work has led us to revise this assumption.  Studies in developmental psychology have suggested robust individual differences in Type 1 thinking.  But to date, nobody knows if they fall within the positive manifold, or if they form a distinct type of intelligence.  The present project aimed to test the stability of differences in Type 1 thought, develop valid and reliable measurements of these differences, and see if Type 1 thought represents unique variance in explaining why some people are more cognitively capable than others.  In this research program, we created several Type 1 tests that relied on implicit pattern recognition.  For example, one task was a video game in which alien ships appeared on different quadrants of the screen, and players had to press the appropriate keyboard key to "shoot at the enemy ships" as quickly as possible.  Unbeknownst to the people playing the game, there was a hidden pattern in where the ships appeared.  While nobody consciously recognized the pattern, participants did, over time, learn the predictive cues and begin to anticipate the next ship’s location, which enabled them to become faster.   Critically, some people implicitly learned the patterns faster than other people, and this difference was stable and reliable.   We then compared people’s abilities on the Type 1 tests that we had developed to classic tests of IQ &ndash; tests of Type 2 thinking.    We found that while all tests of Type 2 thinking were highly correlated with each other (replicating the classic pattern that has been observed for 100 years) some of the Type 1 tests were not related to standard IQ measures.  In other words, we have identified a novel type of intelligence.    This is the first psychometrically distinct form of intelligence to have been identified in nearly 100 years (previous alternate accounts of intelligence such as Gardner’s "Multiple Intelligence," Sternberg’s "triarchic intelligence," or Goleman’s "EQ" have all highly correlated with standard IQ measures).   It expands our understanding of what intelligence is, opens the door to the development of novel approaches to training and education, and may be useful for personnel selection and understanding of how different people can most effectively contribute to organizations.   The grant also funded the training of promising young scientists at both the undergraduate and graduate (PhD) level, and created a number of methodological innovations that will help advance scientific inquiry moving forward.        Last Modified: 04/27/2023       Submitted by: Daniel M Oppenheimer]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
