<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[CC* Compute: High-Performance Computing Backbone for Accelerating Campus-Wide and Regional Research]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>397196.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>397196</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OAC</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure (OAC)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kevin Thompson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kthompso@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924220</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Villanova University is acquiring a high-performance computing resource to expand the capabilities of at least 27 identified researchers in engineering, physical sciences, and social sciences. The grant also prepares students for the STEM workforce through engagement in computational research, education via the creation and modification of ten undergraduate and graduate courses, and student training in high performance computing operations. The impact of this grant extends well beyond Villanova University by establishing the Southeastern Pennsylvania High-Performance Computing Consortium to create new collaborative opportunities between Villanova and non-Villanova researchers, and by connecting Villanova to the broader Open Science Grid network to distribute resources to researchers nationally.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The grant focuses on three objectives to expand Villanova’s computational infrastructure for research and education. First, this work establishes new computational hardware – including 1,184 central processing units (CPUs), 10,240 graphical processing units (GPUs), and 448 terabytes (TB) of data storage – along with complementary software and networking resources.  Second, resource usage expands fundamental research in seven project areas relevant to the mission of the National Science Foundation, including (1) materials for fusion energy applications, (2) causes of various nasal sinus diseases, (3) ion transport in energy storage devices, (4) speech perception and language processing, (5) river behavior, (6) nonlinear mechanical behavior, and (7) machine learning algorithms.  Finally, practices are developed to mitigate the costs associated with growing and maintaining the computing resource.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/16/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/16/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2018933</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Aaron</FirstName>
<LastName>Wemhoff</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Aaron Wemhoff</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[aaron.wemhoff@villanova.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000524063</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/16/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ryan</FirstName>
<LastName>Jorn</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ryan P Jorn</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ryan.jorn@Villanova.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000716625</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/16/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate>08/16/2022</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Cereceda</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David Cereceda</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[david.cereceda@villanova.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000796251</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/16/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jonathan</FirstName>
<LastName>Graziola</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jonathan Graziola</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jonathan.graziola@villanova.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000816508</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/16/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate>03/28/2022</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Villanova University</Name>
<CityName>VILLANOVA</CityName>
<ZipCode>190851603</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6105194220</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>800 LANCASTER AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>EYNYSU6L8ZX6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>VILLANOVA UNIVERSITY IN THE STATE OF PENNSYLVANIA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>EYNYSU6L8ZX6</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Villanova University]]></Name>
<CityName>Villanova</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>190851603</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[800 Lancaster Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8080</Code>
<Text>Campus Cyberinfrastructure</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~397196</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The two major outcomes from this grant are the transformative advancement of research computing at Villanova University through the procurement and installation of its first campus-wide high performance computing (HPC) cluster. The management of the cluster, in turn, has enabled the establishment of a core facility in research computing called the Centralized Research Computing Facility (CRCF), which is the first core facility at Villanova University. Other outcomes related to the presence of HPC and the managing core facility are (1) the production of 8 peer-reviewed journal and conference publications from Villanova researchers through use of the HPC cluster, (2) the generation of about 20 grant proposals from Villanova researchers for use of the cluster, resulting in awarded funding of approximately $3 million, (3) the integration of the HPC cluster into new educational experiences for undergraduate and graduate students in 9 Villanova courses (some with multiple sections), (4) the connection of the cluster to the external Open Science Grid, achieving an average of 21% of cluster utilization by the external high throughput computing service, (5) the development and management of policies surrounding cluster use, (6) the establishment of personal connections between CRCF and many HPC experts at other institutions both locally and nationally, (7) the unprecedented teaming between the various Villanova campus offices, including faculty and IT personnel, to work together towards building a unique and sustainable computational research capability, and (8) the providing of myriad educational opportunities such as a new user training workflow, webinars, tutorials, office hours, and a core group of superusers for specific applications software to provide novice users guidance on their computational research endeavors.</p> <p>The intellectual merit of the award has enabled novel large-scale computational research in fields such as computational chemistry, mechanical engineering, electrical and computer engineering, civil and environmental engineering, psychology, computing science, biology, romance languages, physics, and business. Specific areas of research include molecular dynamics modeling, computational fluid dynamics, data mining, machine learning, and statistics. The cluster is currently fully utilized, as evidenced by a growing number of users (141 as of June 2023), an increasing number of users that use the cluster in a given month (peaking at 26 in April 2023) and a low average idling rate of 25%.</p> <p>The broader impacts of the award are twofold: (1) the various social, technological, and educational impacts by the individual research projects enabled by the presence of the HPC cluster, and (2) the developed human resources and institutional infrastructure enabled by the HPC cluster. The human resources development has grown via educational opportunities using the cluster, the growth of relationships between computational researchers and IT staff on the Villanova campus, and the integration of leadership opportunities for students both as software superusers as well as through the student seat on the HPC management team. The institutional infrastructure has been bolstered through the creation of a roadmap of policies and procedures for establishing future core facilities on the Villanova campus.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/05/2023<br>      Modified by: Aaron&nbsp;Wemhoff</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The two major outcomes from this grant are the transformative advancement of research computing at Villanova University through the procurement and installation of its first campus-wide high performance computing (HPC) cluster. The management of the cluster, in turn, has enabled the establishment of a core facility in research computing called the Centralized Research Computing Facility (CRCF), which is the first core facility at Villanova University. Other outcomes related to the presence of HPC and the managing core facility are (1) the production of 8 peer-reviewed journal and conference publications from Villanova researchers through use of the HPC cluster, (2) the generation of about 20 grant proposals from Villanova researchers for use of the cluster, resulting in awarded funding of approximately $3 million, (3) the integration of the HPC cluster into new educational experiences for undergraduate and graduate students in 9 Villanova courses (some with multiple sections), (4) the connection of the cluster to the external Open Science Grid, achieving an average of 21% of cluster utilization by the external high throughput computing service, (5) the development and management of policies surrounding cluster use, (6) the establishment of personal connections between CRCF and many HPC experts at other institutions both locally and nationally, (7) the unprecedented teaming between the various Villanova campus offices, including faculty and IT personnel, to work together towards building a unique and sustainable computational research capability, and (8) the providing of myriad educational opportunities such as a new user training workflow, webinars, tutorials, office hours, and a core group of superusers for specific applications software to provide novice users guidance on their computational research endeavors.  The intellectual merit of the award has enabled novel large-scale computational research in fields such as computational chemistry, mechanical engineering, electrical and computer engineering, civil and environmental engineering, psychology, computing science, biology, romance languages, physics, and business. Specific areas of research include molecular dynamics modeling, computational fluid dynamics, data mining, machine learning, and statistics. The cluster is currently fully utilized, as evidenced by a growing number of users (141 as of June 2023), an increasing number of users that use the cluster in a given month (peaking at 26 in April 2023) and a low average idling rate of 25%.  The broader impacts of the award are twofold: (1) the various social, technological, and educational impacts by the individual research projects enabled by the presence of the HPC cluster, and (2) the developed human resources and institutional infrastructure enabled by the HPC cluster. The human resources development has grown via educational opportunities using the cluster, the growth of relationships between computational researchers and IT staff on the Villanova campus, and the integration of leadership opportunities for students both as software superusers as well as through the student seat on the HPC management team. The institutional infrastructure has been bolstered through the creation of a roadmap of policies and procedures for establishing future core facilities on the Villanova campus.       Last Modified: 08/05/2023       Submitted by: Aaron Wemhoff]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
