<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[MRI: Acquisition of a High-Speed Camera for a Primarily Undergraduate Institution]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>53290.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>53290</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Shahab Shojaei-Zadeh</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sshojaei@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928045</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This NSF Major Research Instrumentation award will support the acquisition of a Phantom VEO 640L high-speed camera which is a critical research instrument toward cutting-edge research and education across campus at Western New England University (WNE), particularly within the departments of Mechanical Engineering and Biomedical Engineering. The speed, resolution, and memory of this camera will enable researchers at WNE to conduct pioneering research in the areas of energy-thermo-fluids, material science, and biomedical engineering. WNE is a primarily undergraduate institution, with a high proportion of first-generation, minority, and non-traditional students. This project will provide research experiences to undergraduates and will open doors for additional research opportunities thereafter, especially for women and minorities. The proposed equipment will enhance WNE's engineering curriculum as undergraduate research activities are integrated in senior design projects. In addition, it will provide research training opportunities for students who will be involved in the proposed research activities. Moreover, the proposed work will increase partnership between academia and industry.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The high-speed camera will be used to advance knowledge in transport phenomena in proton exchange membrane (PEM) fuel cells, shear stress distribution of a mechanical pulsating jet, nanomanufacturing of silica-coated nanoparticles, and diagnostic tests for neglected infectious disease. The studies on PEM fuel cells transport phenomena will include; (i) liquid water droplet deformation and removal on the surface of the gas diffusion layer and under the influence of acoustic pressure waves, (ii) variation of liquid-gas two-phase flow pressure drop in PEM fuel cell flow channel during emergence and growth of liquid water droplets, (iii) deformation of liquid water droplet under mechanical vibrations in PEM fuel cells, and (iv) destabilized capillary-scale two-phase flow in microchannels. All of these phenomena occur in orders of milliseconds and therefore, studying them will require high-speed imaging. The shear stress distribution of a mechanical pulsating jet will be investigated by measuring the spatial and temporal shear stress distribution on a flat surface at various Reynolds numbers, stand-off distances, pulsating frequencies and nozzle exit speeds. The findings will be used to further improve the performance of the impinging jet for various applications and to validate numerous numerical studies on this topic. The high-speed camera will also be used to study the capillary fluid instabilities during Nanomanfucaturing of silica-coated nanoparticles using Electrospraying, which holds great promise to solve the long-standing scalability issue in manufacturing of advanced structured nanomaterials. In the Department of Biomedical Engineering, microfluidic flows will be studied to achieve enhanced sample preparation performance in diagnostic tests for neglected infectious diseases. The results obtained in this study can be a transformational factor for this particular application as well as across a number of point-of-care microfluidic platforms for use in low-resource environments.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/24/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/20/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2018150</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mehdi</FirstName>
<LastName>Mortazavi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mehdi Mortazavi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mmortazavi@wpi.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000731209</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/24/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Anthony</FirstName>
<LastName>Santamaria</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Anthony Santamaria</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[anthony.santamaria@wne.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000702958</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/24/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Rust</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael J Rust</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mrust@wne.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000539461</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/24/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jingru</FirstName>
<LastName>Benner</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jingru Benner</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jingru.benner@wne.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000731179</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/24/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jingzhou</FirstName>
<LastName>Zhao</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jingzhou Zhao</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jingzhou.zhao@binghamton.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000756971</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/24/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Western New England University</Name>
<CityName>SPRINGFIELD</CityName>
<ZipCode>011192655</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4137821373</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1215 WILBRAHAM RD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>J6QJVY8JCQH3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WESTERN NEW ENGLAND UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>J6QJVY8JCQH3</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Western New England University]]></Name>
<CityName>Springfield</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>011192684</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1215 Wilbraham Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1415</Code>
<Text>PMP-Particul&amp;MultiphaseProcess</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~53290</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This award provided funding to purchase a VEO 640L high-speed camera as a critical research instrument toward cutting-edge research and education across campus at Western New England University (WNE). Engineering undergraduate ang graduate students were trained to operate this camera to gather experimental data for their research projects. In one undergraduate research project, the camera was used to study the relation between pressure drop in the gas flow channel of a proton exchange membrane (PEM) fuel cell and droplet size. The camera was synchronized with a pressure transducer and visualized emergence and growth of liquid water droplets in the channel. Results showed that pressure drop values instantly change when a droplet emerges from the surface of the porous layer, as shown in Figure 1. Experiments were conducted for a range of superficial gas velocity and it was observed that the pressure drop changes faster at higher velocities. Images were analyzed to obtain the droplet detachment size. The combination of pressure drop at detachment and droplet size obtained from images were used to predict the drag force required to detach droplets from the surface of the channel. Droplet interfacial geometries were further studied and it was observed that the contact line expanded in downstream of the droplet as droplet grew in size, as shown in Figure 2.</p> <p>In another research task, droplet oscillation in the gas flow channel of PEM fuel cells was investigated. High-speed imaging of droplets under the influence of shear gas flow revealed that droplets undergo oscillatory deformation patterns prior to detachment from the surface of the channel, as shown in Figure 3. This figure shows a droplet in the gas flow channel when air flow was from left to right with a superficial velocity of 10.76 m/s. The time interval between Figures 3b and 3c is 5 ms and droplet oscillation can be observed in this time period. A similar observation can be achieved in Figures 3d and 3e. Image analysis revealed that droplet oscillation occurred both in horizontal (i.e. stream-wise) and vertical (i.e. perpendicular to stream-wise direction, in plane of the image) directions. However, results showed greater oscillations in the horizontal direction. The range of oscillation was larger for experiments conducted at higher superficial gas velocities, suggesting a greater interaction between forces from the core gas flow and surface tension effects.</p> <p>In this task, the advancing and receding contact angles were also measured for two superficial gas velocities of 4.17 m/s and 10.76 m/s, as shown in Figure 4. The t* shown in this figure is the non-dimensionalized residence time of the droplet, defined as the ratio between time lapsed from droplet emergence to droplet residence time. The residence time was defined as the time interval during which the droplet emerged from the surface of the GDL until it detached. Results indicated that the droplet demonstrates a larger advancing contact angle upon detachment for the lower superficial gas velocity. Similarly, the receding contact angle was larger for the lower superficial gas velocity. Droplet contact angle values are plotted as a function of t* in Figure 4b. The figure shows that the advancing contact angles increase over time while the receding contact angles decrease. In addition, changes in the advancing contact angles are less than changes in the receding contact angles. However, the figure shows almost an identical difference between the advancing and receding contact angles at time of detachment for two different superficial gas velocities (55 and 56 degrees for 10.76 m/s and 4.17 m/s superficial velocities, respectively).</p> <p>In another task, droplet removal from the flow channel of PEM fuel cells was studied by high-speed imaging. The goal of this task was to visualize droplet interfacial geometry when acoustic pressure waves were superimposed on air flow in the channel. Results indicated that this method of active water removal can transfer the droplet to an unstable mode after one complete rocking cycle, as shown in Figure 5. This figure shows two attempts of superimposition. The two attempts were conducted 18.40 s and 25.70 s after droplet emergence, respectively. Droplet removal was not achieved in the first attempt, mainly since the droplet was small and the inertial forces within the droplet could not overcome the surface tension effects. However, droplet removal was achieved after one complete rocking motion in the second attempt, when the droplet was slightly larger in size. In this task, three different droplet oscillation patterns were identified, depending on the size of the droplet, as shown in Figure 6. For small, medium, and large sizes of a droplet, the three oscillation patterns that were observed were rocking, prolate, and oblate modes, respectively.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/19/2021<br>      Modified by: Mehdi&nbsp;Mortazavi</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2018150/2018150_10701455_1632087957077_fig1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2018150/2018150_10701455_1632087957077_fig1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 1"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2018150/2018150_10701455_1632087957077_fig1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 1"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Profiles of pressure drop for different superficial gas velocities</div> <div class="imageCredit">Mehdi Mortazavi</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Mehdi&nbsp;Mortazavi</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 1</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2018150/2018150_10701455_1632088150283_fig2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2018150/2018150_10701455_1632088150283_fig2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 2"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2018150/2018150_10701455_1632088150283_fig2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 2"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Droplet interfacial geometry when superficial air velocity was 10.76 m/s.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Mehdi Mortazavi</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Mehdi&nbsp;Mortazavi</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 2</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2018150/2018150_10701455_1632088442454_fig4--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2018150/2018150_10701455_1632088442454_fig4--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 4"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2018150/2018150_10701455_1632088442454_fig4--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 4"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">(a) Images of droplets at two different superficial gas velocities and at different t* values. The advancing and recedingcontact angle values are shown with red and green numbers, respectively. (b) Contact angles at different t*=1 values.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Mehdi Mortazavi</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Mehdi&nbsp;Mortazavi</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 4</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2018150/2018150_10701455_1632088766867_fig3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2018150/2018150_10701455_1632088766867_fig3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 3"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2018150/2018150_10701455_1632088766867_fig3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 3"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Droplet interfacial profile in the presence of shear gas flow with a superficial gas velocity of 10.76 m/s.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Mehdi Mortazavi</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Mehdi&nbsp;Mortazavi</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 3</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2018150/2018150_10701455_1632088871867_fig5--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2018150/2018150_10701455_1632088871867_fig5--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 5"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2018150/2018150_10701455_1632088871867_fig5--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 5"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Two attempts of superimposing acoustic pressure waves in an "on demand" configuration.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Mehdi Mortazavi</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Mehdi&nbsp;Mortazavi</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 5</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2018150/2018150_10701455_1632088977321_fig6--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2018150/2018150_10701455_1632088977321_fig6--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 6"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2018150/2018150_10701455_1632088977321_fig6--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 6"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Different oscillation patterns were observed during the continuous mode of superimposition.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Mehdi Mortazavi</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Mehdi&nbsp;Mortazavi</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 6</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This award provided funding to purchase a VEO 640L high-speed camera as a critical research instrument toward cutting-edge research and education across campus at Western New England University (WNE). Engineering undergraduate ang graduate students were trained to operate this camera to gather experimental data for their research projects. In one undergraduate research project, the camera was used to study the relation between pressure drop in the gas flow channel of a proton exchange membrane (PEM) fuel cell and droplet size. The camera was synchronized with a pressure transducer and visualized emergence and growth of liquid water droplets in the channel. Results showed that pressure drop values instantly change when a droplet emerges from the surface of the porous layer, as shown in Figure 1. Experiments were conducted for a range of superficial gas velocity and it was observed that the pressure drop changes faster at higher velocities. Images were analyzed to obtain the droplet detachment size. The combination of pressure drop at detachment and droplet size obtained from images were used to predict the drag force required to detach droplets from the surface of the channel. Droplet interfacial geometries were further studied and it was observed that the contact line expanded in downstream of the droplet as droplet grew in size, as shown in Figure 2.  In another research task, droplet oscillation in the gas flow channel of PEM fuel cells was investigated. High-speed imaging of droplets under the influence of shear gas flow revealed that droplets undergo oscillatory deformation patterns prior to detachment from the surface of the channel, as shown in Figure 3. This figure shows a droplet in the gas flow channel when air flow was from left to right with a superficial velocity of 10.76 m/s. The time interval between Figures 3b and 3c is 5 ms and droplet oscillation can be observed in this time period. A similar observation can be achieved in Figures 3d and 3e. Image analysis revealed that droplet oscillation occurred both in horizontal (i.e. stream-wise) and vertical (i.e. perpendicular to stream-wise direction, in plane of the image) directions. However, results showed greater oscillations in the horizontal direction. The range of oscillation was larger for experiments conducted at higher superficial gas velocities, suggesting a greater interaction between forces from the core gas flow and surface tension effects.  In this task, the advancing and receding contact angles were also measured for two superficial gas velocities of 4.17 m/s and 10.76 m/s, as shown in Figure 4. The t* shown in this figure is the non-dimensionalized residence time of the droplet, defined as the ratio between time lapsed from droplet emergence to droplet residence time. The residence time was defined as the time interval during which the droplet emerged from the surface of the GDL until it detached. Results indicated that the droplet demonstrates a larger advancing contact angle upon detachment for the lower superficial gas velocity. Similarly, the receding contact angle was larger for the lower superficial gas velocity. Droplet contact angle values are plotted as a function of t* in Figure 4b. The figure shows that the advancing contact angles increase over time while the receding contact angles decrease. In addition, changes in the advancing contact angles are less than changes in the receding contact angles. However, the figure shows almost an identical difference between the advancing and receding contact angles at time of detachment for two different superficial gas velocities (55 and 56 degrees for 10.76 m/s and 4.17 m/s superficial velocities, respectively).  In another task, droplet removal from the flow channel of PEM fuel cells was studied by high-speed imaging. The goal of this task was to visualize droplet interfacial geometry when acoustic pressure waves were superimposed on air flow in the channel. Results indicated that this method of active water removal can transfer the droplet to an unstable mode after one complete rocking cycle, as shown in Figure 5. This figure shows two attempts of superimposition. The two attempts were conducted 18.40 s and 25.70 s after droplet emergence, respectively. Droplet removal was not achieved in the first attempt, mainly since the droplet was small and the inertial forces within the droplet could not overcome the surface tension effects. However, droplet removal was achieved after one complete rocking motion in the second attempt, when the droplet was slightly larger in size. In this task, three different droplet oscillation patterns were identified, depending on the size of the droplet, as shown in Figure 6. For small, medium, and large sizes of a droplet, the three oscillation patterns that were observed were rocking, prolate, and oblate modes, respectively.                      Last Modified: 09/19/2021       Submitted by: Mehdi Mortazavi]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
