<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RCN-UBE Incubator: Diversifying and integrating marine education at field stations along a latitudinal gradient]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>74445.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>74445</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DBI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Amanda Simcox</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>asimcox@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928165</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Hands-on learning at field stations is transformative and has positive outcomes on student's knowledge and long-term engagement with science. Abstract concepts are brought to life in the field because the natural world stimulates students’ curiosity, encourages active participation, and builds team camaraderie. For these reasons and more, the recommendations for implementing change in undergraduate biology education (e.g., ‘integrating core concepts’, ‘focus on student-centered learning’; AAAS 2011) are exemplified by field coursework and research. Despite their proven benefits, opportunities for fieldwork in undergraduate biology education are waning. This is alarming in light of rapidly increasing human impacts on ecosystems, and the growing disconnect between people and nature. To address this ‘nature deficit’, the Diversify and Integrate Marine Education at Stations (DIMES) network will engage scientists and learners at marine stations along the west coast of the North America to create a unified curriculum that documents change in biodiversity while combining fieldwork and computational literacy in undergraduate education. By connecting participants from a variety of academic institutions, the DIMES network will diversify the undergraduate audience served by marine stations. By integrating a field curriculum across western North America, educators will engage students with pressing scientific questions in an age of rapid biological change. This network will leverage the existing undergraduate teaching at participating marine laboratories and expand their reach to new students who lack access to experiential learning.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Field courses share a common philosophy centered on local natural history and experiential learning, but this knowledge is rarely placed within a broader context in an explicit, quantitative manner – a shortcoming in an era of global human impacts. The proposed unified field curriculum will integrate the traditional place-based approach within a biogeographic framework by developing innovative modules that combine data across the network to address questions at larger spatial and temporal scales. By linking explicitly environmental change, biogeography, and natural history, the DIMES network will maintain the relevance of curricula offered at these stations and export the modules to other institutions. Moreover, the network will develop a partnership of educators from diverse institutions that span R1 to community college, and that vary in their shore access, to expand the reach of marine stations beyond their walls. This network of instructors will develop curricula and assessment tools that can be implemented in classrooms with varying levels of field time, with the goal of identifying mechanisms to minimize the hypothesized learning gap between students with and without shore access.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is being jointly funded by the Directorate for Biological Sciences, Division of Biological Infrastructure, and the Directorate for Education and Human Resources, Division of Undergraduate Education as part of their efforts to address the challenges posed in Vision and Change in Undergraduate Biology Education: A Call to Action (http://visionandchange/finalreport/).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/29/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/29/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2018116</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
<LastName>Denny</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mark W Denny</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mwdenny@stanford.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000252116</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/29/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Fiorenza</FirstName>
<LastName>Micheli</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Fiorenza Micheli</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[micheli@stanford.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000254439</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/29/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Stanford University</Name>
<CityName>STANFORD</CityName>
<ZipCode>943052004</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6507232300</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>450 JANE STANFORD WAY</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>16</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA16</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>HJD6G4D6TJY5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>THE LELAND STANFORD JUNIOR UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Hopkins Marine Station]]></Name>
<CityName>Pacific Grove</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>939503024</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[120 Ocean View Blvd]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>19</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA19</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>037Y</Code>
<Text>UBE - Undergraduate Biology Ed</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1998</Code>
<Text>IUSE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1664</Code>
<Text>RESEARCH COORD NETWK IN BIO SC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0420</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>04002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~74445</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Field courses are known to be transformative experiences in undergraduate education, in large part due to their shared teaching philosophy centered on natural history and experiential learning. Despite demonstrated benefits for student knowledge and long-term engagement with science, opportunities for fieldwork in undergraduate biology education are waning. Moreover, local natural history lessons are rarely placed within a broader geographic context in an explicit manner &ndash; a shortcoming in an era of global human impacts. To address these shortcomings, we conceived the <em>Diversifying and Integrating Marine Education at Stations</em> (DIMES) network to leverage virtual resources for remote learning and develop a unified curriculum that documents change in marine biodiversity along the west coast of North America.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Intellectual merit</strong></p> <p>We developed a general framework for pedagogical assessment that would apply to the field-based and virtual teaching modules. We discussed current peer-reviewed literature on pedagogical assessment for CUREs (course based undergraduate research experiences) to find pre-existing assessments we could use and adapt to help guide our assessment. We developed 16 learning objectives that focus on the scientific method, quantitative skills, and mastering content knowledge of intertidal and subtidal ecosystems:</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Student learning objectives for rocky shores</strong></p> <ol> <li>Identify and classify common rocky shores species </li> <li>Understand the interplay of abiotic and biotic factors that influence the abundance and distribution of species</li> <li>Explore fundamental principles of ecology as they relate to rocky shores</li> <li>Describe the importance of natural history, biogeography, and the role of long-term monitoring programs on advancing ecology and informing environmental management</li> <li>Describe potential impacts of human activities and climate change on rocky shores</li> <li>Use literature review to inform research questions</li> <li>Distinguish between observations and experiments and the types of questions they address</li> <li>Work collaboratively as part of a research team</li> <li>Collect data using a variety of sampling methods designed for intertidal and subtidal rocky shores</li> </ol> <p>10.&nbsp; Access/collect data from environmental sensors</p> <p>11.&nbsp; Process data and enter it into a multi-user database</p> <p>12.&nbsp; Mine data from past/existing ecological studies to provide context and comparisons for collected data</p> <p>13.&nbsp; Analyze data by graphing and using statistics to determine differences, patterns, and trends</p> <p>14.&nbsp; Develop research questions, state hypotheses, develop conceptual models, and determine future directions for research based upon data analysis and literature review</p> <p>15.&nbsp; Design and execute an experiment / observational study to address a research question</p> <p>16.&nbsp; Present research findings to others in the form of reports, posters, or oral presentations.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Based on these objectives, our group identified two guiding research questions to be covered in the curriculum modules: (1) How are selected organisms distributed across space and time, and (2) How are these patterns related to abiotic and biotic drivers? We next reviewed three curriculum projects to determine how well they addressed the draft DIMES student learning objectives and guiding research questions.&nbsp;The process of reviewing exemplary curricula allowed us to determine how best to build upon existing projects, fill in gaps where these projects did not adequately address aspects of the DIMES goals and define what types of new educational resources needed development.&nbsp;Collaborators at four of the DIMES nodes (UABC Ensenada, Mexico; Hopkins Marine Station, California; OIMB Oregon; University of Alaska Fairbanks) brought the objectives of DIMES to their online and in-person classes in 2020-2022. Each instructor tested their own DIMES integrated curriculum in their standard classes focused on intertidal and subtidal rocky shores.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Broader impacts</strong></p> <p>Our work benefits society by creating publicly available resources in the form of teaching modules and an archive of ecological data, videos, and images. All of the resources have been (and will continue to be) deposited in permanent digital repositories and are intended for educational use by K-12 and undergraduate instructors. We expect that these resources will be particularly useful when teaching and researching the consequences of climate change on marine biodiversity. For example, a lesson plan on historical ecology was developed at Hopkins Marine Station (<a href="https://purl.stanford.edu/sn779ny6113">https://purl.stanford.edu/sn779ny6113</a>), which includes (1) an introduction to historical ecology and the relevant literature, (2) an introduction to the common intertidal organisms, and (3) a virtual exercise to quantify intertidal organisms along a long-term ecological transect. At UABC Enseneda, step-by-step videos of the ecosystems (<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NEVB3h0lWl4">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NEVB3h0lWl4</a>), and a field experiment on abalone transplantation (<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cdKNYXlrubc&amp;t=137s">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cdKNYXlrubc&amp;t=137s</a>), were made to introduce students to the field, many of which had never visited these ecosystems. In 2022, instructors implemented a unified intertidal monitoring protocol with students; these methods, photoquadrats and data have been uploaded to a permanent digital repository (<a href="https://purl.stanford.edu/kv041ng6595">https://purl.stanford.edu/kv041ng6595</a>). We have also developed video survey methods for underwater data collection in collaboration with students (<a href="https://purl.stanford.edu/km092my4610">https://purl.stanford.edu/km092my4610</a>); video transects from the kelp forests of the Monterey Peninsula are available (<a href="https://purl.stanford.edu/wp446bg1851">https://purl.stanford.edu/wp446bg1851</a>). In addition to the societal benefit of education, the video and image archives provide an important baseline for understanding the continued effects of climate change on our coastal ecosystems.</p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">&nbsp;</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/20/2022<br>      Modified by: Mark&nbsp;W&nbsp;Denny</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Field courses are known to be transformative experiences in undergraduate education, in large part due to their shared teaching philosophy centered on natural history and experiential learning. Despite demonstrated benefits for student knowledge and long-term engagement with science, opportunities for fieldwork in undergraduate biology education are waning. Moreover, local natural history lessons are rarely placed within a broader geographic context in an explicit manner &ndash; a shortcoming in an era of global human impacts. To address these shortcomings, we conceived the Diversifying and Integrating Marine Education at Stations (DIMES) network to leverage virtual resources for remote learning and develop a unified curriculum that documents change in marine biodiversity along the west coast of North America.     Intellectual merit  We developed a general framework for pedagogical assessment that would apply to the field-based and virtual teaching modules. We discussed current peer-reviewed literature on pedagogical assessment for CUREs (course based undergraduate research experiences) to find pre-existing assessments we could use and adapt to help guide our assessment. We developed 16 learning objectives that focus on the scientific method, quantitative skills, and mastering content knowledge of intertidal and subtidal ecosystems:     Student learning objectives for rocky shores  Identify and classify common rocky shores species  Understand the interplay of abiotic and biotic factors that influence the abundance and distribution of species Explore fundamental principles of ecology as they relate to rocky shores Describe the importance of natural history, biogeography, and the role of long-term monitoring programs on advancing ecology and informing environmental management Describe potential impacts of human activities and climate change on rocky shores Use literature review to inform research questions Distinguish between observations and experiments and the types of questions they address Work collaboratively as part of a research team Collect data using a variety of sampling methods designed for intertidal and subtidal rocky shores   10.  Access/collect data from environmental sensors  11.  Process data and enter it into a multi-user database  12.  Mine data from past/existing ecological studies to provide context and comparisons for collected data  13.  Analyze data by graphing and using statistics to determine differences, patterns, and trends  14.  Develop research questions, state hypotheses, develop conceptual models, and determine future directions for research based upon data analysis and literature review  15.  Design and execute an experiment / observational study to address a research question  16.  Present research findings to others in the form of reports, posters, or oral presentations.     Based on these objectives, our group identified two guiding research questions to be covered in the curriculum modules: (1) How are selected organisms distributed across space and time, and (2) How are these patterns related to abiotic and biotic drivers? We next reviewed three curriculum projects to determine how well they addressed the draft DIMES student learning objectives and guiding research questions. The process of reviewing exemplary curricula allowed us to determine how best to build upon existing projects, fill in gaps where these projects did not adequately address aspects of the DIMES goals and define what types of new educational resources needed development. Collaborators at four of the DIMES nodes (UABC Ensenada, Mexico; Hopkins Marine Station, California; OIMB Oregon; University of Alaska Fairbanks) brought the objectives of DIMES to their online and in-person classes in 2020-2022. Each instructor tested their own DIMES integrated curriculum in their standard classes focused on intertidal and subtidal rocky shores.     Broader impacts  Our work benefits society by creating publicly available resources in the form of teaching modules and an archive of ecological data, videos, and images. All of the resources have been (and will continue to be) deposited in permanent digital repositories and are intended for educational use by K-12 and undergraduate instructors. We expect that these resources will be particularly useful when teaching and researching the consequences of climate change on marine biodiversity. For example, a lesson plan on historical ecology was developed at Hopkins Marine Station (https://purl.stanford.edu/sn779ny6113), which includes (1) an introduction to historical ecology and the relevant literature, (2) an introduction to the common intertidal organisms, and (3) a virtual exercise to quantify intertidal organisms along a long-term ecological transect. At UABC Enseneda, step-by-step videos of the ecosystems (https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NEVB3h0lWl4), and a field experiment on abalone transplantation (https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cdKNYXlrubc&amp;t=137s), were made to introduce students to the field, many of which had never visited these ecosystems. In 2022, instructors implemented a unified intertidal monitoring protocol with students; these methods, photoquadrats and data have been uploaded to a permanent digital repository (https://purl.stanford.edu/kv041ng6595). We have also developed video survey methods for underwater data collection in collaboration with students (https://purl.stanford.edu/km092my4610); video transects from the kelp forests of the Monterey Peninsula are available (https://purl.stanford.edu/wp446bg1851). In addition to the societal benefit of education, the video and image archives provide an important baseline for understanding the continued effects of climate change on our coastal ecosystems.                Last Modified: 10/20/2022       Submitted by: Mark W Denny]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
