<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Mechanically Driven Growth of Hydrocarbons at Sliding Interfaces to Control Degradation and Wear]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>289847.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>289847</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Lucy T. Zhang</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>luzhang@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925016</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Although tribology has been an active field of study, the limited understanding of friction and wear processes continues to lead to failure of the moving systems used in various applications. Although current approaches to protecting the surfaces by deposition of damage-resistant coatings provide temporary solutions, eventually the coatings degrade and wear off. This award supports fundamental research to elucidate how the damage in the materials can be reversed by in-situ replenishment of protective coatings. Insights from this study will enable repair of the damaged surfaces without having to disassemble the entire mechanical system. Not only will this research promote scientific advances, but it will also improve the performance of the mechanical part assemblies. It will provide a new solution to more reliable and energy-efficient transportation and manufacturing systems, in which repair of the surfaces will prolong the operation lifetimes significantly. This award will also offer new educational opportunities for undergraduate and graduate students in the areas of materials science, mechanics, and surface science, with an emphasis on recruiting and retaining women and minorities in STEM disciplines. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Mechanically induced surface degradation creates a significant problem for mechanical assemblies and is the major cause for the loss of usefulness. High-contact pressure and shear during relative movement of the sliding interfaces causes local heating and as well as complex compression. For a correct combination of materials in sliding contact, these conditions may induce tribochemical reactions leading to the formation of protective films directly at the contact. This project focuses on understanding the friction- and wear-induced deformation of catalytic metal interfaces immersed in a hydrocarbon environment, which causes an in-situ growth of layered carbon films on the sliding surface. To elucidate the material growth processes, this research will combine in-situ Raman analysis of the surfaces exposed to stresses during macroscale tribology tests, with electron microscopy post-characterization of the wear track cross-sections. The characterization data will be correlated with the mechanical characteristics of the films to evaluate the triboactive response of the dynamic system to the applied mechanical stresses, and to quantify the damage tolerance of the grown films in different environments. The research will also investigate alternative solutions to tribocatalysis activation.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is jointly supported by the Civil, Mechanical, and Manufacturing Innovations Division and the Chemical, Bioengineering, Environmental and Transport Systems Division in the Engineering Directorate.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/07/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/07/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2018132</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Diana</FirstName>
<LastName>Berman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Diana Berman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[Diana.Berman@unt.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000731199</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/07/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of North Texas</Name>
<CityName>DENTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>762035017</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9405653940</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1155 UNION CIR #305250</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>G47WN1XZNWX9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF NORTH TEXAS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>WXELJHR4N3S6</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of North Texas]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>762035017</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1417</Code>
<Text>Interfacial Engineering Progra</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1630</Code>
<Text>Mechanics of Materials and Str</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>022E</Code>
<Text>SOLID MECHANICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>024E</Code>
<Text>MATERIALS DESIGN</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>027E</Code>
<Text>NANOMECHANICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9102</Code>
<Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9161</Code>
<Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~289847</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Although tribology has been among the most active fields of study, the limited understanding of friction and wear processes and their effect on materials reconstruction continues to lead to the failure of the moving systems used in various applications. Current approaches to protecting the surfaces by deposition of damage-resistant coatings provide only temporary solutions since the coatings degrade and wear off. To address this concern, this project focused on understanding the friction- and wear-induced reconstruction of materials at hydrocarbon/catalytic metal interfaces as an approach for in-situ synthesis of carbon films during sliding. A total of ten journal papers have been disseminated to the materials and surface science research communities. The results also led to the submission of one patent application covering the surface protection technology developed based on the research outcomes.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Intellectuall merit: A number of significant intelllectual merit results on the process of in-situ carbon film formation were found throughout this research. First, based on the concept of tribocatalysis, summarized for a range of hydrocarbon sources, catalytic surfaces and sliding conditions (Figure 1), a database of the parameters and conditions for the platinum-ethanol sliding system has been created. It was used to monitor the evolution of the tribofilm formation to understand the limits of the tribocatalytic activity of the systems. Second, MD simulations were used to unravel the phenomena observed during mechanochemically-activated formation of carbon structures, facilitated by the presence of catalytically-reactive Pt-Au film. They revealed higher sensitivity of the hydrocarbon molecules' scission and reconstruction to temperature than the applied load, which supports the experimental observations and is in agreement with the proposed Arrhenius model (Figure 2). Quantitative analysis of the materials' chemistry and composition inside the wear tracks has unraveled the graphitic structure of the formed films &nbsp;(Figure 3). Finally, the structure and properties of carbon films formed for the Pt/ethanol system were compared to alternative material precursors, such as longer chain hydrocarbons and Cu and Ni catalysts.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Understanding the thermodynamic and kinetic aspects governing the materials reconstruction and repair processes as well as controllable acceleration of the tribocatalytic reaction under reduced temperature conditions creates a new fundamental concept of the materials processing approach. It presents the correlation of structure-property-processing pertaining to the advancement of surface science and mechanics.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Broader impacts: The broader impacts of this project are demonstrated through the opportunities provided to undergraduate and graduate students. Funding of this work supported the completion of thesis work for two students (1 doctorate and 1 master's) as well as partial research support for several undergraduate (3 female) and graduate (1 female) students assisting in the project. The students gained hands-on experience in materials synthesis, testing, and characterization, as well as computer modeling work relevant to the project. Based on the conducted research, students received several major awards at national and international conferences and had the opportunity to present the outcomes of their research to local industries. This contributed to the development of the future workforce for the U.S. industry needs as supported by the students&rsquo; success in receiving industry positions after graduation. &nbsp;Several new lectures, classes, and online video presentations were developed based on the scope of this award.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/14/2023<br>      Modified by: Diana&nbsp;Berman</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2018132/2018132_10683342_1689282687695_Figure1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2018132/2018132_10683342_1689282687695_Figure1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Schematic of the mechanically-driven formation of carbon film"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2018132/2018132_10683342_1689282687695_Figure1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Schematic of the mechanically-driven formation of carbon film"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The concept of the carbon film formation in presence of hydrocarbon sources near the contact interface subjected to local stresses and temperature increase.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Diana Berman</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Diana&nbsp;Berman</div> <div class="imageTitle">Schematic of the mechanically-driven formation of carbon film</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2018132/2018132_10683342_1689282582452_Figure2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2018132/2018132_10683342_1689282582452_Figure2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Experimental and simulation results"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2018132/2018132_10683342_1689282582452_Figure2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Experimental and simulation results"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Analysis of the carbon growth rate indicate direct dependence on applied load and temperature conditions</div> <div class="imageCredit">Diana Berman</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Diana&nbsp;Berman</div> <div class="imageTitle">Experimental and simulation results</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2018132/2018132_10683342_1689282834223_Figure3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2018132/2018132_10683342_1689282834223_Figure3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Example of the formed carbon film"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2018132/2018132_10683342_1689282834223_Figure3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Example of the formed carbon film"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Characterization of the formed carbon film using Raman and transmission electron microscopy analysis indicate mostly graphitic nature of the material.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Diana Berman</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Diana&nbsp;Berman</div> <div class="imageTitle">Example of the formed carbon film</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Although tribology has been among the most active fields of study, the limited understanding of friction and wear processes and their effect on materials reconstruction continues to lead to the failure of the moving systems used in various applications. Current approaches to protecting the surfaces by deposition of damage-resistant coatings provide only temporary solutions since the coatings degrade and wear off. To address this concern, this project focused on understanding the friction- and wear-induced reconstruction of materials at hydrocarbon/catalytic metal interfaces as an approach for in-situ synthesis of carbon films during sliding. A total of ten journal papers have been disseminated to the materials and surface science research communities. The results also led to the submission of one patent application covering the surface protection technology developed based on the research outcomes.     Intellectuall merit: A number of significant intelllectual merit results on the process of in-situ carbon film formation were found throughout this research. First, based on the concept of tribocatalysis, summarized for a range of hydrocarbon sources, catalytic surfaces and sliding conditions (Figure 1), a database of the parameters and conditions for the platinum-ethanol sliding system has been created. It was used to monitor the evolution of the tribofilm formation to understand the limits of the tribocatalytic activity of the systems. Second, MD simulations were used to unravel the phenomena observed during mechanochemically-activated formation of carbon structures, facilitated by the presence of catalytically-reactive Pt-Au film. They revealed higher sensitivity of the hydrocarbon molecules' scission and reconstruction to temperature than the applied load, which supports the experimental observations and is in agreement with the proposed Arrhenius model (Figure 2). Quantitative analysis of the materials' chemistry and composition inside the wear tracks has unraveled the graphitic structure of the formed films  (Figure 3). Finally, the structure and properties of carbon films formed for the Pt/ethanol system were compared to alternative material precursors, such as longer chain hydrocarbons and Cu and Ni catalysts.     Understanding the thermodynamic and kinetic aspects governing the materials reconstruction and repair processes as well as controllable acceleration of the tribocatalytic reaction under reduced temperature conditions creates a new fundamental concept of the materials processing approach. It presents the correlation of structure-property-processing pertaining to the advancement of surface science and mechanics.      Broader impacts: The broader impacts of this project are demonstrated through the opportunities provided to undergraduate and graduate students. Funding of this work supported the completion of thesis work for two students (1 doctorate and 1 master's) as well as partial research support for several undergraduate (3 female) and graduate (1 female) students assisting in the project. The students gained hands-on experience in materials synthesis, testing, and characterization, as well as computer modeling work relevant to the project. Based on the conducted research, students received several major awards at national and international conferences and had the opportunity to present the outcomes of their research to local industries. This contributed to the development of the future workforce for the U.S. industry needs as supported by the students’ success in receiving industry positions after graduation.  Several new lectures, classes, and online video presentations were developed based on the scope of this award.             Last Modified: 07/14/2023       Submitted by: Diana Berman]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
