<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[CC* Planning: Shepherd University CI and Regional Connectivity]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>99999.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>99999</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OAC</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure (OAC)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kevin Thompson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kthompso@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924220</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This project explores the benefits and costs of bringing fiber optic connectivity and Internet2 access to the Shepherd University campus in West Virginia. This project benefits students, researchers and technology developers in the four-state region (West Virginia, Maryland, Pennsylvania, and Virginia). Network connectivity for research and education is a critical issue in many parts of the United States. West Virginia has several cyber-isolated regions including the Shepherdstown area that is home to Shepherd University. Rivers, mountain ranges, state lines and right-of-way issues stand between the campus and the major technology corridors and dense communication networks nearby. Bridging these barriers would boost the research and educational capacity at this state-supported primarily undergraduate institution.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This planning project incorporates the following components. (1) Identify Regional Optical Networks (RONs) capable of bringing Internet2 connectivity to the Shepherd University campus. Identify possible fiber routes from each RON to the campus region. Evaluate costs including for the problematic last-mile portion. (2) Select the most cost-effective route. Work with one or more dark fiber providers and government agencies to engineer a detailed plan that addresses geographical and political boundaries including county and state lines. Enumerate local work permits that would be required. (3) Determine sustainability with projections of ongoing costs. Plan for preferred and alternative sources of revenue. Engage critical partners from the faculty and administration of Shepherd University and other colleges in the region. (4) Create a detailed cyberinfrastructure plan for the campus. Design the Science DMZ and define the relationship between the Internet2-enabled research network and the university’s enterprise networks. Plan for secure access to Internet2 and related networks such as EduRoam. Plan for preferred and alternative network architectures. (5) If implementation is justified, identify one or more funding mechanisms for full Internet2 connectivity.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/16/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/16/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2018360</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jason</FirstName>
<LastName>Miller</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jason R Miller</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jmill02@shepherd.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000819016</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/16/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
<LastName>Warburton</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Robert J Warburton</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[rwarburt@shepherd.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000819221</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/16/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Shepherd University</Name>
<CityName>SHEPHERDSTOWN</CityName>
<ZipCode>254437000</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3048765358</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>301 KING ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>West Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>WV</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WV02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>RJB5GKJBUY15</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SHEPHERD UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>RJB5GKJBUY15</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Shepherd University]]></Name>
<CityName>Shepherdstown</CityName>
<StateCode>WV</StateCode>
<ZipCode>254435000</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[P.O. Box 5000]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>West Virginia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WV02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8080</Code>
<Text>Campus Cyberinfrastructure</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~99999</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Shepherd University has developed a plan for a pilot upgrade to its campus cyber infrastructure. Shepherd University is a state-supported, primarily undergraduate school in Shepherdstown WV. The University has had limited options for Internet access due to its proximity to rivers, mountains, and state lines. Thanks to a planning grant from the National Science Foundation, Shepherd University has developed a detailed plan that is scheduled for implementation in 2023. This implementation will be used to evaluate actual costs as well as actual research and educational benefits of high-speed Internet connectivity. The pilot network could be extended later to incorporate the entire campus.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>At the start of the planning project, Shepherd University had limited connectivity between the Internet and its campus. In fact, the connection relied on a single, low-bandwidth, overhead copper wire. There were no known feasible options for connecting any of the nation&rsquo;s growing fiber optic networks to the Shepherdstown campus. This situation was projected to become a bottleneck for researchers and educators due to their growing demand for computer network services.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The NSF-funded planning project enabled Shepherd University to work with experts across WV and around the region. Shepherd received invaluable input from state-funded agencies such as WVNet, academic optical network providers such as CAAREN and Internet2, commercial optical network providers, network equipment manufacturers, and computer networking consultants. As a result, the project was able to present the University with maps, schematics, and plans for several possible buildouts, covering a range of budget and impact levels. In the end, the University decided to build a pilot network that will connect labs at the College of STEM and College of Business, and the University IT Department, to the Internet via a commercial service provider. The pilot network will use 100% fiber optic cabling and advanced switching equipment that will be capable of delivering up to 10X the bandwidth that the University relies on currently. With this plan in place, Shepherd University secured funding, including a grant from the US Department of Education, that should enable its implementation and evaluation in 2022 and 2023.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>This planning project delivered on its promises. The project started with no known options and ended with an implementation ready to begin. The project had intellectual merit in that it will foster big-data analysis and collaborative research that connects Shepherd University faculty with the scientific community. The project will have broader impacts in that it will enable more creative and integrative instruction in which Shepherd University students engage with other students of science across the nation and around the world.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/21/2022<br>      Modified by: Robert&nbsp;J&nbsp;Warburton</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Shepherd University has developed a plan for a pilot upgrade to its campus cyber infrastructure. Shepherd University is a state-supported, primarily undergraduate school in Shepherdstown WV. The University has had limited options for Internet access due to its proximity to rivers, mountains, and state lines. Thanks to a planning grant from the National Science Foundation, Shepherd University has developed a detailed plan that is scheduled for implementation in 2023. This implementation will be used to evaluate actual costs as well as actual research and educational benefits of high-speed Internet connectivity. The pilot network could be extended later to incorporate the entire campus.     At the start of the planning project, Shepherd University had limited connectivity between the Internet and its campus. In fact, the connection relied on a single, low-bandwidth, overhead copper wire. There were no known feasible options for connecting any of the nation’s growing fiber optic networks to the Shepherdstown campus. This situation was projected to become a bottleneck for researchers and educators due to their growing demand for computer network services.      The NSF-funded planning project enabled Shepherd University to work with experts across WV and around the region. Shepherd received invaluable input from state-funded agencies such as WVNet, academic optical network providers such as CAAREN and Internet2, commercial optical network providers, network equipment manufacturers, and computer networking consultants. As a result, the project was able to present the University with maps, schematics, and plans for several possible buildouts, covering a range of budget and impact levels. In the end, the University decided to build a pilot network that will connect labs at the College of STEM and College of Business, and the University IT Department, to the Internet via a commercial service provider. The pilot network will use 100% fiber optic cabling and advanced switching equipment that will be capable of delivering up to 10X the bandwidth that the University relies on currently. With this plan in place, Shepherd University secured funding, including a grant from the US Department of Education, that should enable its implementation and evaluation in 2022 and 2023.      This planning project delivered on its promises. The project started with no known options and ended with an implementation ready to begin. The project had intellectual merit in that it will foster big-data analysis and collaborative research that connects Shepherd University faculty with the scientific community. The project will have broader impacts in that it will enable more creative and integrative instruction in which Shepherd University students engage with other students of science across the nation and around the world.           Last Modified: 10/21/2022       Submitted by: Robert J Warburton]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
