<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[MRI: Acquisition of Plasma Multi-ion-source Focused Ion Beam Microscope]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1297022.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1297022</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Guebre Tessema</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>gtessema@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924935</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This award from the Major Research Instrumentation program supports the acquisition of a state-of-the-art focused ion beam /scanning electron microscope outfitted with advanced detectors and automation tools.  The instrument enables and supports a diverse range of research projects and programs, within academia and industry, that involve three-dimensional, multi-modal characterization and patterning of microstructures. Such three-dimensional analysis is particularly important for developing materials processing strategies for additive manufacturing and for understanding mechanisms leading to material degradation and failure.  In addition, the nanopatterning capabilities of the instrument provide precision engineering of novel nanometer-scale optical and mechanical devices. The location of the instrument within the Research Triangle Nanotechnology Network, a node of the NSF National Nanotechnology Coordinated Infrastructure (NNCI), provides enhanced access to researchers from across the nation, impacting local universities, not-for-profit institutions and industries. The instrument will be integrated into the curriculum developed under an NSF-funded National Research Traineeship program, which brings together the materials science, statistics and machine learning communities to develop new approaches to materials informatics research. Workshops and training modules will be developed to broaden participation from minority institutions and to educate a new generation of researchers at the intersection of statistics and materials science.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award supports the acquisition of an inductively coupled plasma (ICP) multi-ion source focused-ion beam/ scanning electron microscope (pFIB/SEM) to support the ongoing and future research of numerous faculty, postdoctoral and student researchers from across five academic departments at North Carolina State University and regional universities. In addition, the instrument will be broadly utilized by other academic and industry research communities via the Research Triangle Nanotechnology Network, a node of the NSF National Nanotechnology Coordinated Infrastructure (NNCI). The instrument is outfitted specifically for statistically meaningful quantitative characterization of material microstructures in three dimensions across length scales from nano meter to millimeter. The coupling of automation tools with the rapid sputtering rates unlocks the ability to: 1) study material properties governed by complex hierarchical material microstructures, 2) study three dimensional microstructures in materials that would be susceptible to artifacts from ion implantation using conventional Ga ion sources, and 3) pattern large area yet high fidelity (nanometer-scale resolution) patterns in a variety of materials. The broader impacts of the infrastructure lie in leveraging the unique capabilities of the North Carolina State Analytical Instrumentation Facility in training a diverse user-base and in developing education modules at the graduate, undergraduate and K-12 levels.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/11/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/11/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2018964</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Djamel</FirstName>
<LastName>Kaoumi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Djamel Kaoumi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[dkaoumi@ncsu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000795537</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/11/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Shadow</FirstName>
<LastName>Huang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Shadow Huang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[hshuang@ncsu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000561748</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/11/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jacob</FirstName>
<LastName>Jones</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jacob L Jones</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jacobjones@ncsu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000294327</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/11/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ola</FirstName>
<LastName>Harrysson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ola L Harrysson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[harrysson@ncsu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000483264</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/11/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Elizabeth</FirstName>
<LastName>Dickey</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Elizabeth C Dickey</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ecdickey@andrew.cmu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000343941</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/11/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>North Carolina State University</Name>
<CityName>RALEIGH</CityName>
<ZipCode>27607</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9195152444</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2601 WOLF VILLAGE WAY</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>U3NVH931QJJ3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORTH CAROLINA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>N8DMK1K4C2K5</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[North Carolina State University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>276957907</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>Major Research Instrumentation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~1297022</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>The primary goal of this project was to acquire&nbsp;an inductively coupled plasma (ICP) multi-ion source focused-ion beam/ scanning electron microscope (pFIB/SEM) to support the ongoing and future research at NC State University and regional universities and businesses. The instrument was installed and integrated in the NC State University?s Analytical Instrumentation facility, which provides access to state-of-the-art materials characterization equipment.&nbsp; </span>The acquired instrument is equipped specifically for&nbsp;statistically meaningful quantitative characterization&nbsp;of material microstructures in three dimensions across dimensions from&nbsp;nanometers to<sup>&nbsp;</sup>millimeters. The coupling of automation tools with the rapid sputtering rates unlocks the ability to: 1) study material properties governed complex hierarchical material microstructures, 2) study three-dimensional microstructures in materials that would be susceptible to ion implantation using conventional Ga ion sources and 3) pattern large area yet high fidelity (nm-scale resolution) patterns in a variety of materials.&nbsp; <span>The instrument in managed and maintained by professional staff within the NC State University Analytical Instrumentation Facility, who have developed operation and training procedures for the various functionalities of the microscope. Students and researchers are trained by AIF staff to independently operate the microscope. &nbsp;</span>The instrument is broadly available to<span> faculty, postdoctoral researchers and student researchers at NC State University, as well as </span>the regional and national<span> academic and industry research community via the Research Triangle Nanotechnology Network, a node of the NSF National Nanotechnology Coordinated Infrastructure (NNCI).&nbsp; The instrument is also used in K-12 outreach activities, such as the summer </span>Materials Camp at NC State University, to introduce the student to state-of-the-art nanotechnology.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/24/2021<br>      Modified by: Elizabeth&nbsp;C&nbsp;Dickey</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The primary goal of this project was to acquire an inductively coupled plasma (ICP) multi-ion source focused-ion beam/ scanning electron microscope (pFIB/SEM) to support the ongoing and future research at NC State University and regional universities and businesses. The instrument was installed and integrated in the NC State University?s Analytical Instrumentation facility, which provides access to state-of-the-art materials characterization equipment.  The acquired instrument is equipped specifically for statistically meaningful quantitative characterization of material microstructures in three dimensions across dimensions from nanometers to millimeters. The coupling of automation tools with the rapid sputtering rates unlocks the ability to: 1) study material properties governed complex hierarchical material microstructures, 2) study three-dimensional microstructures in materials that would be susceptible to ion implantation using conventional Ga ion sources and 3) pattern large area yet high fidelity (nm-scale resolution) patterns in a variety of materials.  The instrument in managed and maintained by professional staff within the NC State University Analytical Instrumentation Facility, who have developed operation and training procedures for the various functionalities of the microscope. Students and researchers are trained by AIF staff to independently operate the microscope.  The instrument is broadly available to faculty, postdoctoral researchers and student researchers at NC State University, as well as the regional and national academic and industry research community via the Research Triangle Nanotechnology Network, a node of the NSF National Nanotechnology Coordinated Infrastructure (NNCI).  The instrument is also used in K-12 outreach activities, such as the summer Materials Camp at NC State University, to introduce the student to state-of-the-art nanotechnology.          Last Modified: 10/24/2021       Submitted by: Elizabeth C Dickey]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
