<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[DOCTORAL DISSERTATION RESEARCH IN DRMS Collective Response to Scarcity: How the Resource Environment Shapes Social Networks]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>39191.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>39191</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Claudia Gonzalez-Vallejo</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>clagonza@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924710</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The success or failure of an organization hinges on its ability to effectively process information.  Effective information processing requires people to acquire information themselves and to communicate with one another.  The communication patterns that emerge from people’s choices about when, and with whom, to communicate have direct consequences for the speed at which information moves around an organization, and the validity of that information.  These processes and factors are especially important for organizations responding to causal shocks or crises in their resource environments (e.g., financial actors facing the 2008 Housing Market Crash, all citizens facing the COVID-19 Pandemic).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Doctoral Dissertation Research Improvement Grant (DDRIG) explores the communication networks that emerge among people reacting to changes in their resource environment.  We apply an experimental method plus agent-based modeling to zero-in on the causal relationship between resource availability and communication network structure.  Our overarching hypothesis is that when resources become increasingly scarce, people connect with fewer communication partners, and increase their rate of communication with each partner.  Thus, social networks will shrink in size and become more densely connected in response to resource scarcity.   The reverse pattern of communication occurs in times of abundance.  We also assess the adaptive efficacy of these collective communication strategies in response to resource shocks to draw conclusions that will be helpful in designing and managing organizational responses to crises.  The results of this investigation will help us understand, and anticipate, the way environmental shocks – like an economic recession or pandemic – affect an organization’s ability to effectively manage information.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/20/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/20/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2018173</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Reid</FirstName>
<LastName>Hastie</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Reid Hastie</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[reid.hastie@chicagobooth.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000635599</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/20/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kariyushi</FirstName>
<LastName>Rao</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kariyushi Rao</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[kariyushi@uchicago.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000818322</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/20/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Chicago</Name>
<CityName>CHICAGO</CityName>
<ZipCode>606375418</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7737028669</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5801 S ELLIS AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>ZUE9HKT2CLC9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CHICAGO</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>ZUE9HKT2CLC9</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Chicago]]></Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>606371610</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5807 South Woodlawn Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1321</Code>
<Text>Decision, Risk &amp; Mgmt Sci</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~39191</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Kariyushi Rao has completed research for her dissertation, "Collective Response to Scarcity: How the Resource Environment Shapes Social Networks," supported by the NSF Dissertation Improvement Grant.&nbsp; The primary objective of this research program was to increase our scientific understanding of how people react to changes in the levels of resources in their (economic) environments.&nbsp; Specifically, Rao was interested in testing whether changes in resource levels affect the structure of social/communication networks.</p> <p><br />During her funding period, Rao conducted 5 laboratory experiments, and constructed a rudimentary agent-based model of the decision task (that will serve as the foundation for a more flexible model of the experimental task, which she continues to develop in order to gain insights into experimental participants' behavior).&nbsp; The 5 experiments progressed from studies of solo individuals performing a multi-armed bandit foraging task to earn monetary bonus payoffs, to solo individuals performing the same task with additional "side information" provided from random samples or from prior human participants, to six-member teams performing the same task (payoffs were earned by each team member independently versus competitively).</p> <p>The basic solo individual study (Experiment 1) showed that participants shifted their explore/exploit strategy ratio differently when resources dropped across search trials ("scarcity shock") versus when resources increased across trials ("abundance shock").&nbsp; Essentially searchers reacted more quickly to scarcity shocks and shifted to higher explore/exploit ratios, compared to reactions to abundance shocks (or no change in resource levels).&nbsp; These results are consistent with behavioral reactions to increases and decreases in resource levels in behavioral ecology prey selection games (Garrett &amp; Daw, 2020) and financial tasks (Huijsmans, et al., 2006; Khaw, et al., 2017).&nbsp; Rao's results are now being modeled (post-dissertation) using an agent-based searcher framework, and will result in a manuscript for publication.&nbsp;</p> <p>Next, two versions of the search with "side information" experiment were conducted, one with the side information sourced from a random mechanical sample of search observations (Experiment 2)); the other with side information sourced from a human participant who had performed the same task previously (Experiment 3).&nbsp; In both experiments, side information was used by participants to substantially increase search efficacy (and earnings).&nbsp; And, in both experiments there were strategic shifts in the explore/exploit ratio (less exploitation and more exploration following a scarcity shock); although the resource shock effects were reduced by the availability of side information. The conclusion may be subtle, but Rao believes it is conceptually important to compare searchers' use of side information sourced from another human player versus from a mechanical random sampling algorithm.&nbsp; The small, but reliable result was a tendency to attend more to information from the human source compared to the mechanical random-sample source.&nbsp; Agent-based models are being constructed as a theoretical foundation to interpret the results from these two studies.&nbsp;</p> <p>Finally, two experiments were conducted with six-member teams performing exactly the same search task.&nbsp; "Side information" was replaced with current information available from other participants simultaneously performing the same task.&nbsp; Thus, the teams were inter-dependent informationally (to various degrees as information sampling from team mates was optional).&nbsp; In Experiment 4 payoffs were individual and independent; in Experiment 5 a token competitive bonus was awarded to the top 3 (out of 6) performers on each team.&nbsp; Two findings stand out as most informative scientifically:&nbsp; Participants paid more attention to current observations of other participants (in the two networked-team studies) compared to historical observations of similar participants performing in the past (in the prior solo participant Experiment 3).&nbsp; And, introducing even a token competitive incentive dropped inter-participant information-sharing, and dropped it to a degree that reliably reduced earnings.&nbsp;</p> <p>Rao's experiments form the basis of her dissertation, which was completed and published in 2021.&nbsp; The dissertation is an important contribution to cognitive and social network science, because it provides new insights into the effect of shifts in environmental resource levels on individual search behavior, and on within-group communication.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/10/2021<br>      Modified by: Kariyushi&nbsp;Rao</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Kariyushi Rao has completed research for her dissertation, "Collective Response to Scarcity: How the Resource Environment Shapes Social Networks," supported by the NSF Dissertation Improvement Grant.  The primary objective of this research program was to increase our scientific understanding of how people react to changes in the levels of resources in their (economic) environments.  Specifically, Rao was interested in testing whether changes in resource levels affect the structure of social/communication networks.   During her funding period, Rao conducted 5 laboratory experiments, and constructed a rudimentary agent-based model of the decision task (that will serve as the foundation for a more flexible model of the experimental task, which she continues to develop in order to gain insights into experimental participants' behavior).  The 5 experiments progressed from studies of solo individuals performing a multi-armed bandit foraging task to earn monetary bonus payoffs, to solo individuals performing the same task with additional "side information" provided from random samples or from prior human participants, to six-member teams performing the same task (payoffs were earned by each team member independently versus competitively).  The basic solo individual study (Experiment 1) showed that participants shifted their explore/exploit strategy ratio differently when resources dropped across search trials ("scarcity shock") versus when resources increased across trials ("abundance shock").  Essentially searchers reacted more quickly to scarcity shocks and shifted to higher explore/exploit ratios, compared to reactions to abundance shocks (or no change in resource levels).  These results are consistent with behavioral reactions to increases and decreases in resource levels in behavioral ecology prey selection games (Garrett &amp; Daw, 2020) and financial tasks (Huijsmans, et al., 2006; Khaw, et al., 2017).  Rao's results are now being modeled (post-dissertation) using an agent-based searcher framework, and will result in a manuscript for publication.   Next, two versions of the search with "side information" experiment were conducted, one with the side information sourced from a random mechanical sample of search observations (Experiment 2)); the other with side information sourced from a human participant who had performed the same task previously (Experiment 3).  In both experiments, side information was used by participants to substantially increase search efficacy (and earnings).  And, in both experiments there were strategic shifts in the explore/exploit ratio (less exploitation and more exploration following a scarcity shock); although the resource shock effects were reduced by the availability of side information. The conclusion may be subtle, but Rao believes it is conceptually important to compare searchers' use of side information sourced from another human player versus from a mechanical random sampling algorithm.  The small, but reliable result was a tendency to attend more to information from the human source compared to the mechanical random-sample source.  Agent-based models are being constructed as a theoretical foundation to interpret the results from these two studies.   Finally, two experiments were conducted with six-member teams performing exactly the same search task.  "Side information" was replaced with current information available from other participants simultaneously performing the same task.  Thus, the teams were inter-dependent informationally (to various degrees as information sampling from team mates was optional).  In Experiment 4 payoffs were individual and independent; in Experiment 5 a token competitive bonus was awarded to the top 3 (out of 6) performers on each team.  Two findings stand out as most informative scientifically:  Participants paid more attention to current observations of other participants (in the two networked-team studies) compared to historical observations of similar participants performing in the past (in the prior solo participant Experiment 3).  And, introducing even a token competitive incentive dropped inter-participant information-sharing, and dropped it to a degree that reliably reduced earnings.   Rao's experiments form the basis of her dissertation, which was completed and published in 2021.  The dissertation is an important contribution to cognitive and social network science, because it provides new insights into the effect of shifts in environmental resource levels on individual search behavior, and on within-group communication.       Last Modified: 10/10/2021       Submitted by: Kariyushi Rao]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
