<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[2020 Diversity &amp; Inclusion Research Conference]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>95452.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>95452</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Fay Cobb Payton</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Diversity &amp; Inclusion (D&amp;I) refers to the collection of initiatives and activities that aim to expand or facilitate the participation of members of underprivileged and underrepresented groups within companies, organizations and other entities. The need for D&amp;I is particularly significant in Science, Technology, Engineering and Mathematics (STEM) fields, where the representation levels of women and members of disadvantaged groups are particularly low. This underrepresentation has deleterious consequences for modern society, in which STEM disciplines fuel innovations at the heart of virtually every sector of the economy. Increasing the representation and inclusion of all groups can benefit society both by opening STEM career opportunities to broader segments of the population, and by ensuring that the fruits of innovative Research &amp; Development activities are enjoyed equally by all members of society. Historically, D&amp;I has been grounded primarily in qualitative methodologies, such the detection and remediation of unconscious bias, multicultural training, or creating opportunities to include members of underrepresented groups in educational, research, and other activities. More recently, a growing body of work is emerging that applies scientific research methodologies to D&amp;I, including innovative ways of measuring and analyzing various aspects of D&amp;I, identifying meaningful D&amp;I initiatives, and tracking the impact of those initiatives. The annual Diversity and Inclusion Research Conference (DIRC) aims to recognize and disseminate these novel research activities, and to help establish D&amp;I Research as a field of academic inquiry with significant potential for both basic and applied research.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The third annual DIRC event, DIRC20, is a virtual event that includes TED-style talks, panels, workshops, interactive activities and other D&amp;I-related experiences to showcase&lt;br/&gt;the power of D&amp;I Research as a tool to make society more inclusive and equitable. DIRC20 brings together researchers, practitioners, students, policymakers and others who&lt;br/&gt;either conduct D&amp;I Research, or who face real-world problems related to D&amp;I that can be addressed through D&amp;I Research. DIRC20 purposefully creates connections between and among participants, to encourage the increased pursuit of basic academic research on D&amp;I, to identify the opportunity for real-world applications of D&amp;I Research, and to foster collaborations and partnerships that will increase participation across many sectors of the economy, ultimately driving society toward greater inclusion and equity.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/23/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/23/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2018153</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gilda</FirstName>
<LastName>Barabino</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gilda A Barabino</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[Gbarabino@olin.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000480870</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/23/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Paolo</FirstName>
<LastName>Gaudiano</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Paolo Gaudiano</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[pgaudiano@ccny.cuny.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000779494</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/23/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>CUNY City College</Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<ZipCode>100319101</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2126505418</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>160 CONVENT AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>L952KGDMSLV5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH FOUNDATION OF THE CITY UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>U7WPB7AFN7M2</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[CUNY City College]]></Name>
<CityName>New York</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>100319101</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[160 Convent Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1714</Code>
<Text>Special Projects - CNS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~95452</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This NSF grant supported planning and execution of the 2020 Diversity &amp; Inclusion Research Conference (DIRC), which was held as a virtual event on Nov 12-13, 2020.</p> <p>The goal of the DIRC series is to establish Diversity &amp; Inclusion Research as a field of academic and applied research, and in particular to bring together researchers who use scientific approaches to study D&amp;I as a way of identifying problems, pinpointing root causes, and exploring solutions. DIRC20 was the third annual event in the series.</p> <h1>Audience</h1> <p>Because of the COVID-19 pandemic, approximately 6 months prior to the event we decided to switch from an in-person event to a virtual event. In spite of the logistical challenges that resulted, DIRC20 drew over 500 attendees. Furthermore, rather than trying to imitate the in-person experience with an online platform, we took full advantage of the virtual format to offer a wide range of experiences, including some that would not have been possible in person.</p> <p>The audience represented a wide range of backgrounds and sectors. Based on registrant?s email addresses, we identified participants from:</p> <ul> <li>Large corporations, including the likes of AstraZeneca, Barilla, BNY Mellon, Chevron, Citi, Facebook, Google, McCann, Mayo Clinic, the Navy Federal Credit Union, Pfizer, the San Antonio Spurs, Sysco, Upwork, Wayfair and Wyndham.</li> <li>Academic institutions, including the likes of Columbia University, Cornell University, CUNY, Duke, Harvard University, Johns Hopkins University, Michigan State University, New York University, Stony Brook University, Tufts University, UC Berkeley, University of Florida, University of Maryland, University of Pennsylvania and Virginia Tech University.</li> <li>Foundations, government agencies and nonprofit associations, including the American Bar Association, Anita B.org, the Association of Women in Science, FDNY, Federal Home Loan Bank, Kapor Center, National Audobon Society, National Radio Astronomy Observatory, the National Science Foundation, NOAA, Rotary International and the YMCA.</li> </ul> <h1>Content</h1> <p>The content was organized as follows:</p> <ul> <li>Nine TED-style talks</li> <li>Six panels</li> <li>Eight workshops</li> <li>Two immersive / Virtual reality films</li> <li>Ten virtual booths</li> </ul> <p>All panels and TED-style talks were pre-recorded and made available 24 hours prior to the official start of the live portion of the conference.</p> <p>During the live portion (Nov 17-19), all panelists, speakers and the author of the immersive films took part in live Q&amp;A sessions. These sessions were also recorded.</p> <p>After the conference, all recorded content was edited and made available on the conference website.</p> <p>In addition, DIRC20 featured eight D&amp;I-related workshops conducted by a mixture of academic and private-sector entities. These workshops, which provided practical hands-on experience on a variety of topics related to D&amp;I, were added in response to attendee demand from prior years? DIRC events.</p> <h1>Presenters</h1> <p>DIRC brought together academics, researchers and professionals from various industries to discuss how to leverage diversity and inclusion research to create more inclusive workplaces and promote greater inclusion and equality throughout society.</p> <p>The event was characterized by a significant level of diversity. Out of 47 presenters, we had:</p> <ul> <li>Gender: 13 men, 33 women, one openly transgender man</li> <li>Race / ethnicity: 21 white, 18 Black or African American, 3 Latinx and 3 Asian</li> <li>Industry sectors: 16 members of academia, 7 nonprofits, 17 startups/entrepreneurs, 2 corporate, and 2 government</li> </ul> <p>Similarly, while demographic information about attendees was not collected, the audience was visibly much more diverse than typical research conferences.</p> <p>One unique aspect of DIRC20 is the strong representation of speakers from STEM backgrounds or doing work using STEM-based approaches. This is perhaps the aspect of DIRC that most differentiates it from every other event: typical STEM events dedicate minimal or no time to Diversity &amp; Inclusion, while most Diversity &amp; Inclusion events focus primarily on practical advice, opinions, narrations of individual experiences; to the extent that research is included in these other events, it tends to be limited to reports of statistical data to highlight inequities.</p> <p>Through a combination of talks and panels, the audience was able to gain significant knowledge on how research can support the field of Diversity &amp; Inclusion. The audience was also able to find information and in some cases visit staffed booths from the partner organizations.</p> <h2>Intellectual Merit:</h2> <p>The DIRC events are advancing Diversity &amp; Inclusion Research as a field of academic inquiry, showing the power of leveraging scientific methodology to address meaningful societal issues.</p> <h2>Broader Impacts:</h2> <p>The DIRC events impacts society in two complementary ways: first, it draws people from diverse background into scientific disciplines where women and members of minorities are often underrepresented; second, it demonstrates how scientific methods themselves can be used to address significant societal problems related to issues of diversity, equity and inclusion.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/19/2021<br>      Modified by: Paolo&nbsp;Gaudiano</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This NSF grant supported planning and execution of the 2020 Diversity &amp; Inclusion Research Conference (DIRC), which was held as a virtual event on Nov 12-13, 2020.  The goal of the DIRC series is to establish Diversity &amp; Inclusion Research as a field of academic and applied research, and in particular to bring together researchers who use scientific approaches to study D&amp;I as a way of identifying problems, pinpointing root causes, and exploring solutions. DIRC20 was the third annual event in the series. Audience  Because of the COVID-19 pandemic, approximately 6 months prior to the event we decided to switch from an in-person event to a virtual event. In spite of the logistical challenges that resulted, DIRC20 drew over 500 attendees. Furthermore, rather than trying to imitate the in-person experience with an online platform, we took full advantage of the virtual format to offer a wide range of experiences, including some that would not have been possible in person.  The audience represented a wide range of backgrounds and sectors. Based on registrant?s email addresses, we identified participants from:  Large corporations, including the likes of AstraZeneca, Barilla, BNY Mellon, Chevron, Citi, Facebook, Google, McCann, Mayo Clinic, the Navy Federal Credit Union, Pfizer, the San Antonio Spurs, Sysco, Upwork, Wayfair and Wyndham. Academic institutions, including the likes of Columbia University, Cornell University, CUNY, Duke, Harvard University, Johns Hopkins University, Michigan State University, New York University, Stony Brook University, Tufts University, UC Berkeley, University of Florida, University of Maryland, University of Pennsylvania and Virginia Tech University. Foundations, government agencies and nonprofit associations, including the American Bar Association, Anita B.org, the Association of Women in Science, FDNY, Federal Home Loan Bank, Kapor Center, National Audobon Society, National Radio Astronomy Observatory, the National Science Foundation, NOAA, Rotary International and the YMCA.  Content  The content was organized as follows:  Nine TED-style talks Six panels Eight workshops Two immersive / Virtual reality films Ten virtual booths   All panels and TED-style talks were pre-recorded and made available 24 hours prior to the official start of the live portion of the conference.  During the live portion (Nov 17-19), all panelists, speakers and the author of the immersive films took part in live Q&amp;A sessions. These sessions were also recorded.  After the conference, all recorded content was edited and made available on the conference website.  In addition, DIRC20 featured eight D&amp;I-related workshops conducted by a mixture of academic and private-sector entities. These workshops, which provided practical hands-on experience on a variety of topics related to D&amp;I, were added in response to attendee demand from prior years? DIRC events. Presenters  DIRC brought together academics, researchers and professionals from various industries to discuss how to leverage diversity and inclusion research to create more inclusive workplaces and promote greater inclusion and equality throughout society.  The event was characterized by a significant level of diversity. Out of 47 presenters, we had:  Gender: 13 men, 33 women, one openly transgender man Race / ethnicity: 21 white, 18 Black or African American, 3 Latinx and 3 Asian Industry sectors: 16 members of academia, 7 nonprofits, 17 startups/entrepreneurs, 2 corporate, and 2 government   Similarly, while demographic information about attendees was not collected, the audience was visibly much more diverse than typical research conferences.  One unique aspect of DIRC20 is the strong representation of speakers from STEM backgrounds or doing work using STEM-based approaches. This is perhaps the aspect of DIRC that most differentiates it from every other event: typical STEM events dedicate minimal or no time to Diversity &amp; Inclusion, while most Diversity &amp; Inclusion events focus primarily on practical advice, opinions, narrations of individual experiences; to the extent that research is included in these other events, it tends to be limited to reports of statistical data to highlight inequities.  Through a combination of talks and panels, the audience was able to gain significant knowledge on how research can support the field of Diversity &amp; Inclusion. The audience was also able to find information and in some cases visit staffed booths from the partner organizations. Intellectual Merit:  The DIRC events are advancing Diversity &amp; Inclusion Research as a field of academic inquiry, showing the power of leveraging scientific methodology to address meaningful societal issues. Broader Impacts:  The DIRC events impacts society in two complementary ways: first, it draws people from diverse background into scientific disciplines where women and members of minorities are often underrepresented; second, it demonstrates how scientific methods themselves can be used to address significant societal problems related to issues of diversity, equity and inclusion.       Last Modified: 09/19/2021       Submitted by: Paolo Gaudiano]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
