<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RCN-UBE Incubator: Developing a Faculty Network in a Biodiversity Hotspot: the Research Experiences in Southern California For Undergraduate Ecologists Network]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>71011.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>71011</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DBI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Amanda Simcox</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>asimcox@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928165</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Ecology is inherently multidisciplinary and often requires inquiry over long periods and across large spatial scales. Although engaging undergraduates in authentic ecological research is a critical component in the training of professional ecologists, most undergraduate research, particularly at primarily undergraduate institutions (PUIs), is limited in time and spatial scales. In addition, research is often carried out with a student being "siloed" in the faculty mentor's lab and thus isolated from his/her/their research peers. To address these issues and to provide more research opportunities for students, the project team aims to develop the Research Experiences in Southern California for Undergraduate Ecologists Network (RESCUE-net). By bringing faculty from across the region together, RESCUE-net will also catalyze new research collaborations and allow participating faculty to share expertise and resources. Collaborations will focus on preserving the California Floristic Province, a biodiversity hotspot.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This grant supports the formation of RESCUE-net, a network of faculty in southern California dedicated to developing opportunities to attract and train diverse students for the conservation workforce and improve student learning while enhancing the scope of faculty research programs at PUIs and building a community of researchers who identify as teacher-scholars. In a series of meetings and workshops, the members of RESCUE-net will work together to identify 1) barriers to providing authentic, collaborative research experiences to a diverse group of undergraduates; and 2) concrete ways the network can enhance undergraduate research at PUIs and bring that research into the classroom. Using this information, RESCUE-net will develop a framework that enables more undergraduates to conduct student-centered research projects that address the many environmental challenges facing the California Floristic Province.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is being jointly funded by the Directorate for Biological Sciences, Division of Biological Infrastructure, and the Directorate for Education and Human Resources, Division of Undergraduate Education as part of their efforts to address the challenges posed in "Vision and Change in Undergraduate Biology Education: A Call to Action" (http://visionandchange/finalreport).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/11/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/11/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2018545</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nina</FirstName>
<LastName>Karnovsky</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nina J Karnovsky</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[nina.karnovsky@pomona.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000104442</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/11/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Wallace</FirstName>
<LastName>Meyer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME>III</PI_SUFX_NAME>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Wallace M Meyer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[wallace.meyer@pomona.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000422601</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/11/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Pomona College</Name>
<CityName>CLAREMONT</CityName>
<ZipCode>917114434</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9096218328</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>550 N COLLEGE AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>27</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA27</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>Q9VBQSV2CBY5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>POMONA COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Pomona College]]></Name>
<CityName>Claremont</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>917114302</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Department of Biology, 175 W. Si]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>27</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA27</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>037Y</Code>
<Text>UBE - Undergraduate Biology Ed</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1998</Code>
<Text>IUSE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1664</Code>
<Text>RESEARCH COORD NETWK IN BIO SC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0420</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>04002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~71011</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The primary objectives of RCN-UBE RESCUE-Net were: (1) identify faculty and student needs, (2) build the community by gathering members of the network through presentations, information sessions, and hosting meetings (3) discuss future goals of network, specific educational approaches, and diversity, equity and inclusion (DEI) in the network, and (4) develop a DEI focused Code of Conduct for RESCUE-Net.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Identifying and addressing faculty and student needs:</strong></p> <p>We developed a survey for faculty participants, the results of which helped us to build a network that addressed faculty and student needs. We received 36 responses to our open survey from faculty at 21 different PUI institutions across Southern California. Responses were overwhelmingly positive about the development of a region-wide undergraduate research network. There was strong support for the development of both coordinated CUREs (course based undergraduate research experiences) and the development of coordinated multi-site research projects (MSRPs). Early-career scientists generally were excited about participating in CUREs, while senior faculty were more interested in multi-site research projects. Early-career scientists were more interested in CUREs as these could improve course development and could increase levels of engagement of students. A few early-career faculty were cautious about allocating too much time away from their primary research objectives by participating in multi-site research projects. The opposite pattern was observed for some faculty nearing retirement as they were less willing to modify courses and more willing to explore novel research paths. Interest in both types of activities is high (97% of faculty respondents were highly interested in participating in at least one component; 83% were highly interested in CUREs; 74% in multi-site research projects). Multiple paths for participation will support a more diverse subset of PUI faculty within the network.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>In addition, our survey sought to identify barriers to faculty and student participation. It was clear that time and fiscal pressures (funding for student stipends and laboratory supplies) were the main barriers to faculty participation. Faculty communicated that funding/stipends are required to attract first-generation, low-income students who need a job while in college. Faculty also identified logistical challenges, particularly any travel requirements, as a barrier to student participation. These findings along with an intentional focus on DEI considerations shaped how we designed RESCUE-Net activities and how we budgeted for these activities.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p><strong>Building community</strong></p> <p>We held a series of virtual (due to COVID-19) meetings amongst network collaborators (steering committee members, faculty collaborators and PIs). Virtual meetings ran from May 26, 2021 through October 30, 2021.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>At our first meeting, there was excitement among attendees and significant interest from other faculty that were not able to attend. To continue these conversations, we began virtual lunch discussions to enable collaborators to propose ideas and offer opportunities for different faculty to participate. During these meetings, we developed specific multi-site research and course-based research projects. We focused on diversity, equity and inclusion (DEI) and discussed how all aspects of our program will have a DEI focus (e.g., ways to create inclusive research experiences, attract diverse students, and support diverse faculty).</p> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p>Participants also contributed information to the RESCUE-Net website (rescue-Net.org). Each faculty collaborator, steering committee member and the PIs uploaded a profile that included their research interests this will allow faculty to connect with others with similar interests.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>During the last meeting we finalized plans for proposal submission.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Developing a DEI Code of Conduct for RESCUE-Net</strong></p> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p>On November 3, 2021 five faculty members from 4 institutions participated in a 4 hour workshop provided by AdvanceGeo to begin to develop this Code of Conduct. All of RESCUE-Net activities will be guided by principles outlined in our Code of Conduct. The Code of Conduct will reflect our commitment to diversity, equity, inclusion, safety, justice and belonging. The Code will guide inter- and intra-faculty, student, and staff interactions and will apply to classroom spaces, field settings, conferences, workshops, informal meetings and vehicles. There will be multiple mechanisms in place to report violations of Code of Conduct, safe from retaliation. We agreed that the Code of Conduct will be a living document and will be reviewed annually. In addition, RESCUE-Net faculty, students and staff will be able to attend workshops on bystander intervention and ways to create spaces free from harassment, bullying, and microaggressions. Development of the first iteration of the Code of Conduct was carried out by the DEI working group.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Final products from the RCN-UBE grant were the establishment of the network, the RESCUE-Net website (rescue-Net.org), the finalization of plans for future goals and the submission of the RESCUE-NET implementation grant (NSF #2217253).</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/01/2022<br>      Modified by: Wallace&nbsp;M&nbsp;Meyer</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The primary objectives of RCN-UBE RESCUE-Net were: (1) identify faculty and student needs, (2) build the community by gathering members of the network through presentations, information sessions, and hosting meetings (3) discuss future goals of network, specific educational approaches, and diversity, equity and inclusion (DEI) in the network, and (4) develop a DEI focused Code of Conduct for RESCUE-Net.     Identifying and addressing faculty and student needs:  We developed a survey for faculty participants, the results of which helped us to build a network that addressed faculty and student needs. We received 36 responses to our open survey from faculty at 21 different PUI institutions across Southern California. Responses were overwhelmingly positive about the development of a region-wide undergraduate research network. There was strong support for the development of both coordinated CUREs (course based undergraduate research experiences) and the development of coordinated multi-site research projects (MSRPs). Early-career scientists generally were excited about participating in CUREs, while senior faculty were more interested in multi-site research projects. Early-career scientists were more interested in CUREs as these could improve course development and could increase levels of engagement of students. A few early-career faculty were cautious about allocating too much time away from their primary research objectives by participating in multi-site research projects. The opposite pattern was observed for some faculty nearing retirement as they were less willing to modify courses and more willing to explore novel research paths. Interest in both types of activities is high (97% of faculty respondents were highly interested in participating in at least one component; 83% were highly interested in CUREs; 74% in multi-site research projects). Multiple paths for participation will support a more diverse subset of PUI faculty within the network.     In addition, our survey sought to identify barriers to faculty and student participation. It was clear that time and fiscal pressures (funding for student stipends and laboratory supplies) were the main barriers to faculty participation. Faculty communicated that funding/stipends are required to attract first-generation, low-income students who need a job while in college. Faculty also identified logistical challenges, particularly any travel requirements, as a barrier to student participation. These findings along with an intentional focus on DEI considerations shaped how we designed RESCUE-Net activities and how we budgeted for these activities.        Building community  We held a series of virtual (due to COVID-19) meetings amongst network collaborators (steering committee members, faculty collaborators and PIs). Virtual meetings ran from May 26, 2021 through October 30, 2021.     At our first meeting, there was excitement among attendees and significant interest from other faculty that were not able to attend. To continue these conversations, we began virtual lunch discussions to enable collaborators to propose ideas and offer opportunities for different faculty to participate. During these meetings, we developed specific multi-site research and course-based research projects. We focused on diversity, equity and inclusion (DEI) and discussed how all aspects of our program will have a DEI focus (e.g., ways to create inclusive research experiences, attract diverse students, and support diverse faculty).     Participants also contributed information to the RESCUE-Net website (rescue-Net.org). Each faculty collaborator, steering committee member and the PIs uploaded a profile that included their research interests this will allow faculty to connect with others with similar interests.      During the last meeting we finalized plans for proposal submission.        Developing a DEI Code of Conduct for RESCUE-Net     On November 3, 2021 five faculty members from 4 institutions participated in a 4 hour workshop provided by AdvanceGeo to begin to develop this Code of Conduct. All of RESCUE-Net activities will be guided by principles outlined in our Code of Conduct. The Code of Conduct will reflect our commitment to diversity, equity, inclusion, safety, justice and belonging. The Code will guide inter- and intra-faculty, student, and staff interactions and will apply to classroom spaces, field settings, conferences, workshops, informal meetings and vehicles. There will be multiple mechanisms in place to report violations of Code of Conduct, safe from retaliation. We agreed that the Code of Conduct will be a living document and will be reviewed annually. In addition, RESCUE-Net faculty, students and staff will be able to attend workshops on bystander intervention and ways to create spaces free from harassment, bullying, and microaggressions. Development of the first iteration of the Code of Conduct was carried out by the DEI working group.     Final products from the RCN-UBE grant were the establishment of the network, the RESCUE-Net website (rescue-Net.org), the finalization of plans for future goals and the submission of the RESCUE-NET implementation grant (NSF #2217253).          Last Modified: 08/01/2022       Submitted by: Wallace M Meyer]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
