<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[MRI: Acquisition of gas chromatograph/mass spectrometer]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>105878.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>105878</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>John Yellen</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jyellen@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928759</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Funds from the Major Research Instrumentation program will support the acquisition of a high resolution Gas Chromatograph/Mass Spectrometer (GC/MS) at Wesleyan University.  The GC/MS will be used to study organic residues from ancient contexts, and to model environmental variation and degradation of the organic compounds found in such residues. GC/MS is used to separate, identify, and quantify the individual compounds within a complex organic mixture, and high quality instrumentation is necessary to identify the trace quantities remaining in ancient samples. These compounds can be used to identify the source plant or blend of organic ingredients used to make an ancient perfume, medicine, spiced wine, or other organic commodity. The GC/MS will also be used to generate comprehensive profiles ( chemical “fingerprints”) of modern plants, and identify intermediate compounds produced when organics degrade.  The chemical reference data produced by the investigators will be contributed to publicly accessible data libraries such as the National Institute of Standards and Technology, and may be of use to manufacturing and cosmetic/pharmaceutical industries concerned with organic product safety, as well as forensic and environmental scientists. The data obtained will also be used to populate the first open-access database of ancient organic results for the archaeological community. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will develop and refine the potential of organic residue analysis as a methodology to study ancient economy and environment.  It will investigate ecological variation by collecting and chemically profiling specimens of the same plant species across a range of microclimates.  By studying variation among plants which ancient authors identified as having variable properties, the project will investigate the impact of local ecologies, for example by determining how climate variation might cause plants to express different quantities of medicinally-active ingredients. These findings may have implications for modern biopharmaceutical development. The project will also model how certain organic materials degrade over time. Finally, the GC/MS will be core to Wesleyan’s Advanced Integrated Laboratory course, where students carry out contract research projects for faculty labs while developing skill sets specifically required for work in industry and leading research labs. The integration of the GC/MS into courses planned across Wesleyan’s humanities and social science curriculum will draw new constituencies into STEM, facilitate cross-disciplinary research, and provide students with skills-based scientific training that will be directly applicable to future careers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/20/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/20/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2018821</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Andrea</FirstName>
<LastName>Roberts</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Andrea Roberts</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[AROBERTS01@WESLEYAN.EDU]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000597278</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/20/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kate</FirstName>
<LastName>Birney</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kate Birney</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[kbirney@wesleyan.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000765094</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/20/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Wesleyan University</Name>
<CityName>MIDDLETOWN</CityName>
<ZipCode>064593208</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8606853683</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>237 HIGH ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[FL 3]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CT01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>ZETJL6DKF963</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WESLEYAN UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Wesleyan University]]></Name>
<CityName>Middletown</CityName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>064593208</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[237 High St]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CT01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>Major Research Instrumentation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~105878</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The NSF-MRI grant supported the purchase of a new Gas-Chromatography/Mass Spectrometry &nbsp;(GC-MS) instrument for use in research at the intersection of archaeology, chemistry and environmental science. &nbsp;Research generated by the new instrument focused on two interrelated areas: "forensic fingerprinting" of ancient biomarkers, and "environmental fingerprinting" of key medicinal and aromatic plant species.</p> <p><em>Forensic Fingerprinting</em>: Organic residue analysis (ORA) uses phytochemical fingerprints, often fatty acid biomarkers as they preserve well in ancient samples, to identify a botanical source or source ingredients in ancient containers. These can range from simple commodities (olive oil) to complex, blended mixtures in ancient perfumes, spiced wines and medicines. However the condition of biomarkers in archaeological samples (which are analyzed using GC-MS) &nbsp;vary considerably and differ from modern signatures, as heat, sunlight, and vessel type will affect the resulting fingerprint.&nbsp;The project modeled the thermo- and photo-oxidation pathways of biomarkers from three key plant species with an important commercial role in the ancient Mediterranean: &nbsp;<em>Olea europea</em>&nbsp;(oleic acid and pure olive oil), <em>Crocus sativus</em> (safranal and isophorone), and<em> Styrax Officinalis</em> (cinnamic acid and coumarin), used to spice wines and as a medicinal resin. In addition to generating a series of 'snapshots' for these biomarkers, each reflecting different stages of exposure, the project was able to identify two additional, previously unrecognized biomarkers for <em>Crocus sativus, </em>point towards potential differences in the olive oil signatures found in glass and ceramic vessels<em>,&nbsp;</em>and&nbsp;successfully demonstrated the stability and reliability of key biomarkers used in the identification of plant resins.</p> <p>As analysis of these oxidation pathways are useful for archaeological, forensic, and food scientists, the reference fingerprints generated by these research efforts are being refined for contribution to the National Institutes of Standards and Technology spectral reference libraries, thus contributing to long-term knowledge infrastructure.</p> <p><em>Environmental Fingerprinting: </em>Over the course of the grant - though limited by COVID restrictions - the&nbsp;lab began&nbsp;a program to systematically collect samples of the same plant species from different locations areound the Mediterranean, to examine how microclimate impacts their phytochemical profiles. These included <em>Iris germanica</em>, <em>Crocus&nbsp;sativus, </em>and <em>Rhus coriara, </em>commercial and medicinal plant species used in perfumes and medicinal mixtures described by Greek and Roman doctors. The work&nbsp;generated new regional reference fingerprints useful for archaeological organic residue analysis. In aggregate, these fingerprints may help archaeologists and scholars of ancient medicine not only to identify the plant material contained within an ancient vessel, but also its origin, shedding light on local environments and economic networks. The research also has medical implications: our lab identified two previously unrecognized compounds in Moroccan <em>Iris germanica</em>&nbsp;- bioactive compounds which have been shown to absorb UV and inhibit melanogenesis. This is the first pharmacological evidence supporting the use of iris for dermatological ailments, as described by ancient Romans.</p> <p><em>Research Skills and Job Training:&nbsp;</em>The new GC-MS was key to the independent contract research projects carried out by advanced STEM students in Wesleyan's Advanced Integrated Chemistry Lab. In addition, over the last two years, class modules centered on organic residue and plant analyses have also been integrated into undergraduate classes in Classics and Archaeology, drawing new constituencies of students in the humaniities and social sciences into STEM. All students, the majority of whom were women, and half of whom were women of color, received training in GC-MS techniques that are widely used in industry, whether in food science, forensic analysis, or medical laboratories.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/29/2022<br>      Modified by: Kate&nbsp;Birney</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The NSF-MRI grant supported the purchase of a new Gas-Chromatography/Mass Spectrometry  (GC-MS) instrument for use in research at the intersection of archaeology, chemistry and environmental science.  Research generated by the new instrument focused on two interrelated areas: "forensic fingerprinting" of ancient biomarkers, and "environmental fingerprinting" of key medicinal and aromatic plant species.  Forensic Fingerprinting: Organic residue analysis (ORA) uses phytochemical fingerprints, often fatty acid biomarkers as they preserve well in ancient samples, to identify a botanical source or source ingredients in ancient containers. These can range from simple commodities (olive oil) to complex, blended mixtures in ancient perfumes, spiced wines and medicines. However the condition of biomarkers in archaeological samples (which are analyzed using GC-MS)  vary considerably and differ from modern signatures, as heat, sunlight, and vessel type will affect the resulting fingerprint. The project modeled the thermo- and photo-oxidation pathways of biomarkers from three key plant species with an important commercial role in the ancient Mediterranean:  Olea europea (oleic acid and pure olive oil), Crocus sativus (safranal and isophorone), and Styrax Officinalis (cinnamic acid and coumarin), used to spice wines and as a medicinal resin. In addition to generating a series of 'snapshots' for these biomarkers, each reflecting different stages of exposure, the project was able to identify two additional, previously unrecognized biomarkers for Crocus sativus, point towards potential differences in the olive oil signatures found in glass and ceramic vessels, and successfully demonstrated the stability and reliability of key biomarkers used in the identification of plant resins.  As analysis of these oxidation pathways are useful for archaeological, forensic, and food scientists, the reference fingerprints generated by these research efforts are being refined for contribution to the National Institutes of Standards and Technology spectral reference libraries, thus contributing to long-term knowledge infrastructure.  Environmental Fingerprinting: Over the course of the grant - though limited by COVID restrictions - the lab began a program to systematically collect samples of the same plant species from different locations areound the Mediterranean, to examine how microclimate impacts their phytochemical profiles. These included Iris germanica, Crocus sativus, and Rhus coriara, commercial and medicinal plant species used in perfumes and medicinal mixtures described by Greek and Roman doctors. The work generated new regional reference fingerprints useful for archaeological organic residue analysis. In aggregate, these fingerprints may help archaeologists and scholars of ancient medicine not only to identify the plant material contained within an ancient vessel, but also its origin, shedding light on local environments and economic networks. The research also has medical implications: our lab identified two previously unrecognized compounds in Moroccan Iris germanica - bioactive compounds which have been shown to absorb UV and inhibit melanogenesis. This is the first pharmacological evidence supporting the use of iris for dermatological ailments, as described by ancient Romans.  Research Skills and Job Training: The new GC-MS was key to the independent contract research projects carried out by advanced STEM students in Wesleyan's Advanced Integrated Chemistry Lab. In addition, over the last two years, class modules centered on organic residue and plant analyses have also been integrated into undergraduate classes in Classics and Archaeology, drawing new constituencies of students in the humaniities and social sciences into STEM. All students, the majority of whom were women, and half of whom were women of color, received training in GC-MS techniques that are widely used in industry, whether in food science, forensic analysis, or medical laboratories.        Last Modified: 11/29/2022       Submitted by: Kate Birney]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
