<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Doctoral Dissertation Research: Examining the role of competition in primate dietary morphology]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>10000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>10000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rebecca Ferrell</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rferrell@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927850</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This doctoral dissertation project examines how competition affects primate adaptive processes, testing the central hypothesis that primates respond to competition over food resources by focusing feeding on underutilized resources. Using measures of tooth shape to analyze traits, and stable isotope analysis to examine diet and canopy use, this project looks at differences between primate pairs by comparing populations that live together to populations that live separately. The study can provide new information relevant to conservation management programs to prevent further primate extinction by documenting the impacts of increased competition due to habitat loss. Data collected for this project create undergraduate internship opportunities and provide training in the protocols and procedures of conducting original research. Results from this research will be incorporated into learning modules based on the themes of primate diet and conservation. These learning modules will be utilized by a local non-profit educational programming group that provides scientific activities to elementary and middle school students. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project asks two research questions: 1) do closely-related primate species focus their diet on a few key food items when they live together compared to the same species when they occur separately? and 2) do closely-related primate species display morphological traits and isotopic signatures that reflect focus on fewer key resources when they live together compared to the same species when they occur separately? These questions will be tested using ecometric measures to quantify tooth shape and stable isotope data to represent diet and canopy use. By combining methods to analyze tooth shape and isotopic signatures related to habitual canopy level occupation, this project will provide new perspectives on how to reconstruct dietary behaviors and resource competition.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/04/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/20/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2018642</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tessa</FirstName>
<LastName>Cicak</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Tessa Cicak</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[cicak001@umn.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000720346</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/04/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kieran</FirstName>
<LastName>McNulty</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kieran P McNulty</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[kmcnulty@umn.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000274758</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/04/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Minnesota-Twin Cities</Name>
<CityName>MINNEAPOLIS</CityName>
<ZipCode>554552009</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6126245599</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>200 OAK ST SE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>KABJZBBJ4B54</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MINNESOTA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Minnesota]]></Name>
<CityName>Minneapolis</CityName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>554552070</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[301 19th Ave S, 395 Humphrey Cen]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7608</Code>
<Text>Bio Anthro DDRI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1392</Code>
<Text>Biological Anthropology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~10000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><div class="page" title="Page 8"> <div class="layoutArea"> <div class="column"> <p class="p1"><span class="s1"><span style="white-space: pre;"> </span>This project tested the hypothesis that primates respond to competition over food resources by focusing their feeding on underutilized resources. This shift in feeding focus was hypothesized to cause change to primate tooth shape and dietary isotopes. Because teeth and isotopes have been shown to accurately reflect diet, dental shape analyses were employed to analyze the degree of dental trait change, and isotope analysis further examined differences in diet between primate species-pairs in cases where they live together and in cases where they live separately. This project invesitgated 1) do closely-related primate species focus their diet on a few key food items when they live together compared to the same species when they occur separately? and, 2) do closely-related primate species display morphological traits and isotopic signatures that reflect a focus on fewer key resources when they live together compared to the same species when they occur separately? Understanding how primates vary their food intake when a competitor is present can have impacts for developing conservatin strategies or predicting how species will respond to increased or decreased strain on seasonal resources.&nbsp;</span></p> <p class="p1"><span class="s1"><span style="white-space: pre;"> </span>The outcome from the first question was addressed using a comparative analysis of all published</span>&nbsp;data of feeding behaviors in seven primates, with the goal of measuring subtle differences in food intake from non-fruit resources. The results of this analysis are interpreted as indicating certain primate taxa do modify their behavior to feed on less preferred resources when facing competition from other primate taxa.&nbsp;</p> <p class="p1"><span style="white-space: pre;"> </span>The outcome from the second question was addressed by measuring shape change in primate teeth and also by examining dietary isotopes from primate hair. The combination of these two methods was novel in that it both established a dietary signal driven by adaptation through the examination of tooth shape and it compared those shape changes against the in-life diet, as measured from the chemical analysis of the primate hair. The results of this second investigation were mixed. Some site combinations and species pairs displayed patterns indicating competition may have shaped dental shape differences. Other pairs of primates did not show a strong signal. This may be due to subtle differences between sites in terms of overall climate variables such as rainfall, temperature, and seasonal events such as flooding.&nbsp;</p> <div class="page" title="Page 204"> <div class="layoutArea"> <div class="column"> <p><span><span style="white-space: pre;"> </span>This project indicates there is some support for&nbsp;</span>secondary resource use at sites with higher levels of competition and that this differential is reflected in dental adaptations for processing tough or fibrous resources. However, such behavioral modifications were not observed within every species pair or at every site. What this does indicate is that primate dietary behavior is highly varied and and methods for mitgating competition between species likley is different at each individual primate site.&nbsp;</p> </div> </div> </div> </div> </div> </div><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/27/2023<br>      Modified by: Kieran&nbsp;P&nbsp;Mcnulty</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[    This project tested the hypothesis that primates respond to competition over food resources by focusing their feeding on underutilized resources. This shift in feeding focus was hypothesized to cause change to primate tooth shape and dietary isotopes. Because teeth and isotopes have been shown to accurately reflect diet, dental shape analyses were employed to analyze the degree of dental trait change, and isotope analysis further examined differences in diet between primate species-pairs in cases where they live together and in cases where they live separately. This project invesitgated 1) do closely-related primate species focus their diet on a few key food items when they live together compared to the same species when they occur separately? and, 2) do closely-related primate species display morphological traits and isotopic signatures that reflect a focus on fewer key resources when they live together compared to the same species when they occur separately? Understanding how primates vary their food intake when a competitor is present can have impacts for developing conservatin strategies or predicting how species will respond to increased or decreased strain on seasonal resources.   The outcome from the first question was addressed using a comparative analysis of all published data of feeding behaviors in seven primates, with the goal of measuring subtle differences in food intake from non-fruit resources. The results of this analysis are interpreted as indicating certain primate taxa do modify their behavior to feed on less preferred resources when facing competition from other primate taxa.   The outcome from the second question was addressed by measuring shape change in primate teeth and also by examining dietary isotopes from primate hair. The combination of these two methods was novel in that it both established a dietary signal driven by adaptation through the examination of tooth shape and it compared those shape changes against the in-life diet, as measured from the chemical analysis of the primate hair. The results of this second investigation were mixed. Some site combinations and species pairs displayed patterns indicating competition may have shaped dental shape differences. Other pairs of primates did not show a strong signal. This may be due to subtle differences between sites in terms of overall climate variables such as rainfall, temperature, and seasonal events such as flooding.       This project indicates there is some support for secondary resource use at sites with higher levels of competition and that this differential is reflected in dental adaptations for processing tough or fibrous resources. However, such behavioral modifications were not observed within every species pair or at every site. What this does indicate is that primate dietary behavior is highly varied and and methods for mitgating competition between species likley is different at each individual primate site.              Last Modified: 10/27/2023       Submitted by: Kieran P Mcnulty]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
