<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[I-Corps:  Antimicrobial technologies for treatment of urban storm, industrial, and HVAC waters]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ruth Shuman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rshuman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922160</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this I-Corps project is the development of environmentally friendly antimicrobial porous media. Current methods of controlling microbes, especially bacterial levels in industrial process waters such as HVAC and e-coating of vehicles, result in significant dispersal of chemical biocides and low rates of water recycling. Another area of concern is stormwater where large surges of flow are commonly not treated. As a result, recreational waterways can become impaired and beaches closed due to microbial contamination. Development of methods consuming minimal chemicals and energy can potentially improve industrial process efficiency, resulting in significant savings due to lower water and biocide consumption, with the further benefit of reducing the exposure of workers and the downstream environment to these toxic chemicals. In stormwater applications, the inexpensive media can be coupled to existing sediment removal systems where gravity enables treatment.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project explores translation of a high-permeability durable porous media where biocides are affixed rather than released, enabling significant reductions in microbial loads. A novel technology can incorporate biocides into marine coatings, and, through chemical modification, at the surface of plastics. Such materials may significantly reduce microbial concentrations through lysing of bacteria present in water streams during passage through the media. The treatment occurs rapidly, with only seconds of exposure to the media required, while high levels of antimicrobial performance remain even after large volumes (e.g., tens of thousands of pore-volumes) of water are flushed through the media.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/18/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/12/2023</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041, 47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2018172</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gregory</FirstName>
<LastName>O'Mullan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gregory D O'Mullan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[gregory.omullan@qc.cuny.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000518134</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/18/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>William</FirstName>
<LastName>Blanford</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>William J Blanford</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[william.blanford@qc.cuny.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000781056</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/18/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>CUNY Queens College</Name>
<CityName>FLUSHING</CityName>
<ZipCode>113671575</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7189975400</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>6530 KISSENA BLVD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>EJABWGUJM228</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH FOUNDATION OF THE CITY UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[CUNY Queens College]]></Name>
<CityName>Flushing</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>113671597</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[65 30 Kissena Blvd]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The objective of this project was to explore the unmet needs that may exist for antimicrobial technologies, with a particular focus on water treatment. These technologies aim to reduce the maintenance/cleaning of water systems and eliminate harmful bacteria that create risks to public health and liability for property/business owners. The project explored the existing technologies and the gaps in, or limitations of, currently available technologies for handling and treatment of urban stormwater, industrial process water, and HVAC/cooling tower water. The initial technology focus was on the development and use of novel porous media for filter beds (e.g., similar to sand filters used in swimming pools) capable of treating large volumes of water without clogging like traditional filter membranes and without the constant addition of harmful chemicals into the water stream.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>This project also trained three project participants, two professors and one former graduate student, who had primarily academic work experiences, in the challenges and opportunities present for technology development and transfer from academic concepts to products filling unique, real-world market needs. This training experience involved completion of the innovation-corp training program, exposure to ICORPs mentors who had business experience relevant to water treatment technologies, and involvement of the project participants in customer discovery interviews. These interviews provided the opportunity to discuss the needs of potential end users and existing market competitors.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Through conducting an expansive series of interviews, the project participants learned that HVAC cooling tower water treatment and microbial control is an area of expanding need, driven chiefly by changing city- or state-scale regulations and liability control. Urban stormwater control was also identified as an area of expanding regulation and a possible future market in need of technological solutions for distributed (end-of-pipe, rather than centralized treatment plants) microbial control. Still, the current focus of end-users (businesses and municipalities) was primarily on particle and nutrient removal, not microbial control. It was discovered that end users in all sectors, and especially those attempting to limit liability, were hesitant to adopt new water treatment technologies unless they had substantial proof-of-concept demonstrations at the field scale and that new technologies were more likely to be initially used as secondary treatment strategies in parallel to well-established approaches (e.g., chlorination) until there was a record of larger market use. This indicated that finding visible, large-scale first adopters was a key to market entry. As the project proceeded, it was determined that there was an opportunity to develop new kinds of antimicrobial materials (e.g., antimicrobial PVC) rather than just focusing on new antimicrobial coatings of filter media. Two patents, one for antimicrobial porous media and one for antimicrobial modification of plastics, and one publication describing a lab-scale technology demonstration have been developed in association with this project.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/23/2023<br>      Modified by: William&nbsp;J&nbsp;Blanford</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The objective of this project was to explore the unmet needs that may exist for antimicrobial technologies, with a particular focus on water treatment. These technologies aim to reduce the maintenance/cleaning of water systems and eliminate harmful bacteria that create risks to public health and liability for property/business owners. The project explored the existing technologies and the gaps in, or limitations of, currently available technologies for handling and treatment of urban stormwater, industrial process water, and HVAC/cooling tower water. The initial technology focus was on the development and use of novel porous media for filter beds (e.g., similar to sand filters used in swimming pools) capable of treating large volumes of water without clogging like traditional filter membranes and without the constant addition of harmful chemicals into the water stream.     This project also trained three project participants, two professors and one former graduate student, who had primarily academic work experiences, in the challenges and opportunities present for technology development and transfer from academic concepts to products filling unique, real-world market needs. This training experience involved completion of the innovation-corp training program, exposure to ICORPs mentors who had business experience relevant to water treatment technologies, and involvement of the project participants in customer discovery interviews. These interviews provided the opportunity to discuss the needs of potential end users and existing market competitors.     Through conducting an expansive series of interviews, the project participants learned that HVAC cooling tower water treatment and microbial control is an area of expanding need, driven chiefly by changing city- or state-scale regulations and liability control. Urban stormwater control was also identified as an area of expanding regulation and a possible future market in need of technological solutions for distributed (end-of-pipe, rather than centralized treatment plants) microbial control. Still, the current focus of end-users (businesses and municipalities) was primarily on particle and nutrient removal, not microbial control. It was discovered that end users in all sectors, and especially those attempting to limit liability, were hesitant to adopt new water treatment technologies unless they had substantial proof-of-concept demonstrations at the field scale and that new technologies were more likely to be initially used as secondary treatment strategies in parallel to well-established approaches (e.g., chlorination) until there was a record of larger market use. This indicated that finding visible, large-scale first adopters was a key to market entry. As the project proceeded, it was determined that there was an opportunity to develop new kinds of antimicrobial materials (e.g., antimicrobial PVC) rather than just focusing on new antimicrobial coatings of filter media. Two patents, one for antimicrobial porous media and one for antimicrobial modification of plastics, and one publication describing a lab-scale technology demonstration have been developed in association with this project.          Last Modified: 08/23/2023       Submitted by: William J Blanford]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
