<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[MRI: Acquisition of a State-of-the-Art Analytical Ultracentrifuge for Biomedical and Materials Research]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>342909.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>342909</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DBI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jennifer Weller</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jweller@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922224</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[An award is made to the University of Arizona to support the purchase of an analytical ultracentrifuge (AUC). More than 20 laboratories will use the new AUC, with research programs spanning basic biology, chemistry, materials science, and even biomedical research. As part of the research effort, 235 students, including 22 postdoctoral, 68 graduate and 145 undergraduate students will benefit from training with the state-of-the-art instrumentation. The training opportunities will be extended to collaborating schools and institutions across the Southwest. The University of Arizona is a Hispanic Serving Institution and hosts many programs supporting diversity and inclusion of under-represented groups, many of which will benefit from training with the new instrument. The AUC will also be used in the undergraduate lab courses, where students will test hypotheses they generate for structure and function of various enzymes. In addition, a “hands-on” demonstration showing the basic principles of ultracentrifugation will be developed in the outreach course for delivery at schools throughout Arizona.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Research that will be facilitated by the AUC includes the investigation of a new enzyme mechanisms involving filament formation, DNA binding by viral replicative proteins, protein-protein interactions in cell signaling, and liquid droplet formation by intrinsically disordered proteins. The AUC will facilitate a range of research projects by providing rapid and accurate assessment of ligand binding affinity, stoichiometry, and when mechanisms of inhibition involve alterations of quaternary structure. Chemical labeling (and completeness of labeling) of proteins can be detected, as well as any effects on quaternary structure, solubility, and aggregation. Aggregation is a major roadblock to many structural and functional studies, and the new AUC will be used to assess protein preparation stability and aggregation. The masses and polydispersity of lipid containing nanodiscs will be analyzed to understand the effect of chain and headgroup size, structure, and chemistry on lipid packing. Materials science research will also benefit from the analysis of nanoparticles made from tungsten, molybdenum, and titanium.  Results from these studies will be disseminated through peer-reviewed journals, presentations at scientific meetings, and through classes and public outreach presentations.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/21/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/07/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2018942</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nancy</FirstName>
<LastName>Horton</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nancy C Horton</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[nhorton@email.arizona.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000326134</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/21/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Matthew</FirstName>
<LastName>Cordes</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Matthew Cordes</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[cordes@email.arizona.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000287775</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/21/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Eli</FirstName>
<LastName>Chapman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Eli Chapman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[chapman@pharmacy.arizona.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000649675</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/21/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Marty</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>T</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael T Marty</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mtmarty@email.arizona.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000780729</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/21/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Chad</FirstName>
<LastName>Park</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>K</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Chad K Park</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ckpark@arizona.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000818513</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/21/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Arizona</Name>
<CityName>TUCSON</CityName>
<ZipCode>85721</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5206266000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>845 N PARK AVE RM 538</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AZ07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>ED44Y3W6P7B9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ARIZONA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[The University of Arizona]]></Name>
<CityName>Tucson</CityName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>857210106</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1041 E. Lowell St. #404]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AZ07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>Major Research Instrumentation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~342909</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>&nbsp;<strong style="text-shadow: #000000 0px 0px 0px !important;">Intellectual Merit outcomes:</strong></p> <p style="text-shadow: #000000 0px 0px 0px !important;">&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; The Beckman Optima Analytical Ultracentrifuge &nbsp;has facilitated ongoing biomedical research in six laboratories at the University of Arizona. One of these studies involves the investigation of a new mechanism of enzyme regulation using enzyme polymerization (a.k.a. filamentation). Such studies advance our understanding of enzyme regulation in general, as well as in the study of particular enzymes many of which are important in human disease. A better understanding of how these enzymes function will provide new opportunities for therapeutic interventions. Further, these studies can inspire new nanomaterials, biomarkers and diagnostics, as well as new biomedical research products. Additional studies involved Flu virus membrane proteins, the results of which should provide for more reliable methods of drug development against flu infections. Another involved the analysis of exosomes related to cardiomyopathies in order to develop new biomarkers for heart disease diagnosis and treatments. One of the participating labs studied model membrane proteins to understand how proteins take a signal like light and turn it into a nerve impulse used in sight, and finally two labs studied proteins important for drug discovery in neurodegeneration, cancer, and other human diseases. As a result of these studies, three graduate students earned their PhD degrees, six presentations were made at national conferences, one review and two original scientific research articles were published.</p> <p><strong style="text-shadow: #000000 0px 0px 0px !important;">Broader Impact outcomes:</strong></p> <p style="text-shadow: #000000 0px 0px 0px !important;">&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; The purchase and installation of the Beckman Optima Analytical Ultracentrifuge greatly enhanced the research infrastructure in the southwest region of the United States (Arizona and New Mexico) as it is only the second such instrument in the area. This instrument has the very unique capability of determining the native molecular weights of macromolecules in solution, even when present as mixtures of different sizes. The instrument allowed for new training opportunities, including workshops and one-on-one trainings, which contributed to the career advancement of graduate students (4 total) towards their Ph.D. degrees, and to postdoctoral students (5 total) towards publications and future job applications. The educational goals of this project were met by the teaching of over 300 undergraduate students in an undergraduate biochemistry course, and 8 undergraduate students in designing and presenting scientific demonstrations to middle school students. The outreach goals were met through presentation of those demonstrations to over 200 local middle school students from Title I schools, which were composed of students predominantly from under-represented groups. Additional outreach was performed via laboratory tours to local high school students from under-served communities to show how research is done at the University of Arizona, and also included opportunities for the visiting students to meet with financial aide and academic advisors. Scientific outreach increases the appreciation and understanding of science by the general public, and also encourages students into scientific careers to increase workforce diversity, which improves all aspects of workforce development and outcomes.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/06/2023<br>      Modified by: Nancy&nbsp;C&nbsp;Horton</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Intellectual Merit outcomes:      The Beckman Optima Analytical Ultracentrifuge  has facilitated ongoing biomedical research in six laboratories at the University of Arizona. One of these studies involves the investigation of a new mechanism of enzyme regulation using enzyme polymerization (a.k.a. filamentation). Such studies advance our understanding of enzyme regulation in general, as well as in the study of particular enzymes many of which are important in human disease. A better understanding of how these enzymes function will provide new opportunities for therapeutic interventions. Further, these studies can inspire new nanomaterials, biomarkers and diagnostics, as well as new biomedical research products. Additional studies involved Flu virus membrane proteins, the results of which should provide for more reliable methods of drug development against flu infections. Another involved the analysis of exosomes related to cardiomyopathies in order to develop new biomarkers for heart disease diagnosis and treatments. One of the participating labs studied model membrane proteins to understand how proteins take a signal like light and turn it into a nerve impulse used in sight, and finally two labs studied proteins important for drug discovery in neurodegeneration, cancer, and other human diseases. As a result of these studies, three graduate students earned their PhD degrees, six presentations were made at national conferences, one review and two original scientific research articles were published.  Broader Impact outcomes:      The purchase and installation of the Beckman Optima Analytical Ultracentrifuge greatly enhanced the research infrastructure in the southwest region of the United States (Arizona and New Mexico) as it is only the second such instrument in the area. This instrument has the very unique capability of determining the native molecular weights of macromolecules in solution, even when present as mixtures of different sizes. The instrument allowed for new training opportunities, including workshops and one-on-one trainings, which contributed to the career advancement of graduate students (4 total) towards their Ph.D. degrees, and to postdoctoral students (5 total) towards publications and future job applications. The educational goals of this project were met by the teaching of over 300 undergraduate students in an undergraduate biochemistry course, and 8 undergraduate students in designing and presenting scientific demonstrations to middle school students. The outreach goals were met through presentation of those demonstrations to over 200 local middle school students from Title I schools, which were composed of students predominantly from under-represented groups. Additional outreach was performed via laboratory tours to local high school students from under-served communities to show how research is done at the University of Arizona, and also included opportunities for the visiting students to meet with financial aide and academic advisors. Scientific outreach increases the appreciation and understanding of science by the general public, and also encourages students into scientific careers to increase workforce diversity, which improves all aspects of workforce development and outcomes.          Last Modified: 07/06/2023       Submitted by: Nancy C Horton]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
