<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[MRI:  Acquisition of a high-speed stereoscopic particle image velocimetry system for research and teaching at the University of St. Thomas]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>424013.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>424013</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Shahab Shojaei-Zadeh</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sshojaei@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928045</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Complex fluid flows play a critical role in many important areas of society and technology including transportation, energy, defense, and the environment.  Examples of complex flow phenomena include flows with chemical reactions, flows involving both liquids and gases, and flows that interact with structures.  The proposal will fund the acquisition of an instrument referred to as a particle image velocimeter.  A broad portfolio of research projects has been developed to leverage the proposed instrument as well as expertise from a variety of disciplines.  Projects will investigate the mechanism and control of destructive combustion instabilities, drag reduction for ships and pipelines using microbubbles, and the conversion of acoustic noise into useful energy, to name a few.  These efforts can directly lead to advancements in the efficiency, reliability, and safety of these systems while reducing environmental impacts.  The proposed projects enabled by the instrument includes collaborations across disciplines as well as project teams spanning a variety of regional higher-education institutions.  Additional broader impacts include use of the instrument in multiple undergraduate and graduate courses, outreach activities including a K-12 summer STEM program for female students and enhanced preparation of undergraduate researchers for graduate study.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The University of St. Thomas proposes an instrument acquisition project to fund a high-speed stereoscopic particle image velocimetry system. The objective is to use the requested system to support research and teaching needs of major faculty users and their collaborators, faculty users at the University of Minnesota and Dunwoody College of Technology, and additional St. Thomas engineering faculty and students. The instrument will enable a broad range of interdisciplinary research integrating fluid dynamics, data science, modeling and simulation, and digital image analysis. A wide range of physical phenomena will be investigated that require detailed 3-D measurements taken at high-speeds to better understand the important details of the flow behavior.  Immediate plans include the study of fluid/structure interactions, multiphase flows, acoustic/flow interactions, flow instabilities, and flow transitions. These flows exhibit complexities including competing and coexisting instability mechanisms, phase boundaries, density gradients, and multiscale features in space and time. The instrument will further be used within the curriculum for topics such as fluid mechanics and heat transfer, experimental methods, engineering design, verification and validation of numerical simulations, and big data mining and visualization. Finally, the instrument enables extensive validation of increasingly sophisticated modeling and simulation tools both as a research activity and with industry partnerships.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/25/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/20/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2018403</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Cheol-Hong</FirstName>
<LastName>Min</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Cheol-Hong Min</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[cmin@stthomas.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000715574</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/25/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
<LastName>Hoft</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Thomas A Hoft</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[hoft@stthomas.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000660848</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/25/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
<LastName>Shepard</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>G</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Thomas G Shepard</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[thomas.shepard@stthomas.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000611572</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/25/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Forliti</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David J Forliti</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[dforliti@stthomas.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000380024</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/25/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Abraham</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John P Abraham</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jpabraham@stthomas.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000511532</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/25/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of St. Thomas</Name>
<CityName>SAINT PAUL</CityName>
<ZipCode>551051096</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6519626038</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2115 SUMMIT AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MN04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>MEQUD34ZB1Y6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ST. THOMAS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>MEQUD34ZB1Y6</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of St. Thomas]]></Name>
<CityName>St. Paul</CityName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>551051079</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2115 Summit Ave, Mail OSS 100]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MN04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>Major Research Instrumentation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~424013</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The goal of the project was to acquire a high-speed particle image velocimetry system to support research and education at the University of St. Thomas.&nbsp; The acquired instrument consists of three cameras, a dual-head pulsed laser, and associated accessories.&nbsp; The system has flexibility to make two- or three-dimensional measurements of flow velocities within measurement planes or volumes.&nbsp; The system has been received, installed, and optimized and a wide range of research projects have been initiated ranging from turbulent flows related to aerospace applications, liquid/bubble flows, and biomedical applications.&nbsp; Collaborations with researchers from academia and industry are underway or in the planning stage to maximize the usage of the instrument.&nbsp; Activities to validate modeling and simulation tools using PIV data is already underway.&nbsp; The instrument has already been used in a fluid mechanics class where undergraduates have had a chance to use the system and learn to process and analyze the unique data produced by this instrument, and plans are in place to continue to utilize the instrument in multiple courses.&nbsp; A maintenance program has also been established to ensure availability and health of the components of the instrument.&nbsp;</p> <p>Intellectual Merit</p> <p>Several projects have been initiated which have or will use the new instrumentation.&nbsp; Applications range from energy and propulsion, blood flow through blocked arteries, and the dynamics of bubbly flows.&nbsp; Future projects will investigate drag reduction, control of combustion instabilities, and energy harvesting.&nbsp; These problems are on the forefront of several industries and the research conducted will lead to important advancements.&nbsp;</p> <p>Broader Impacts</p> <p>The instrument has already had a substantial impact on the development of over a dozen undergraduate students who have had experience with the system.&nbsp; Several of these students will be involved in publications both for conferences and journal articles.&nbsp; These students additionally benefit by gaining research experiences that can open opportunities to continue their education by attending graduate school&mdash;to date three have already applied to graduate schools.&nbsp; &nbsp;&nbsp;These students learn about fluid mechanics, lasers, optics, data analysis, and experimental methods.&nbsp; The University of St. Thomas has or is pursuing collaborations with a variety of partners including other universities as well as members of various industries.&nbsp; These collaborations even include projects with K-12 students and educators.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/19/2022<br>      Modified by: David&nbsp;J&nbsp;Forliti</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The goal of the project was to acquire a high-speed particle image velocimetry system to support research and education at the University of St. Thomas.  The acquired instrument consists of three cameras, a dual-head pulsed laser, and associated accessories.  The system has flexibility to make two- or three-dimensional measurements of flow velocities within measurement planes or volumes.  The system has been received, installed, and optimized and a wide range of research projects have been initiated ranging from turbulent flows related to aerospace applications, liquid/bubble flows, and biomedical applications.  Collaborations with researchers from academia and industry are underway or in the planning stage to maximize the usage of the instrument.  Activities to validate modeling and simulation tools using PIV data is already underway.  The instrument has already been used in a fluid mechanics class where undergraduates have had a chance to use the system and learn to process and analyze the unique data produced by this instrument, and plans are in place to continue to utilize the instrument in multiple courses.  A maintenance program has also been established to ensure availability and health of the components of the instrument.   Intellectual Merit  Several projects have been initiated which have or will use the new instrumentation.  Applications range from energy and propulsion, blood flow through blocked arteries, and the dynamics of bubbly flows.  Future projects will investigate drag reduction, control of combustion instabilities, and energy harvesting.  These problems are on the forefront of several industries and the research conducted will lead to important advancements.   Broader Impacts  The instrument has already had a substantial impact on the development of over a dozen undergraduate students who have had experience with the system.  Several of these students will be involved in publications both for conferences and journal articles.  These students additionally benefit by gaining research experiences that can open opportunities to continue their education by attending graduate school&mdash;to date three have already applied to graduate schools.    These students learn about fluid mechanics, lasers, optics, data analysis, and experimental methods.  The University of St. Thomas has or is pursuing collaborations with a variety of partners including other universities as well as members of various industries.  These collaborations even include projects with K-12 students and educators.        Last Modified: 01/19/2022       Submitted by: David J Forliti]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
