<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[MRI: Acquisition of a Focused Ion Beam Scanning Electron Microscope]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>495254.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>495254</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Guebre Tessema</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>gtessema@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924935</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This Major Research Instrumentation award supports the acquisition of a dual-beam focused ion beam (FIB)/scanning electron microscope (SEM). The dual-beam FIB/SEM uses an ion beam to cut and shape solid materials at the nanometer size scale for making small samples for microscopy studies and for micro- and nano-scale property measurements. An electron beam is used in parallel with the ion beam to create scanning electron microscopy images of the material as the ion beam slices and/or shapes the solid. In order to handle the tiny specimens created using the ion beam, the instrument will have a nano-manipulator comprising a fine needle tip that can be welded to the sample, and the sample can then be removed and sent to another microscope for property measurements. The ability to slice, section, and shape solids with nanoscale resolution will enable students to understand microstructures, phases and interfaces in their  lab-based courses that use  the instrument.  Education on campus will be strengthened by incorporating the FIB into three courses including one of the required undergraduate laboratory courses and into senior thesis and graduate-level research. Students, postdocs and faculty from diverse scientific disciplines will make daily use of the FIB, yielding a total user pool of ~150 unique users per year. In addition, the FIB will be professionally marketed for use by industry and is expected to draw additional industrial users to campus. The instrument will also be incorporated into our campus tours and outreach efforts, where nanoscale science may help attract young people’s interest in science and engineering during high school visits and similar on-campus engineering events.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The dual-beam focused ion beam (FIB)/scanning electron microscope (SEM) with enhanced backscattered electron detector, gas injection system, and nanomanipulator acquired with this Major Research Instrumentation award will strengthen education and research activities as well as bolster federal, state and industrial research. The FIB will enable versatile sample preparation for transmission electron microscopy (TEM) studies as well as opening new avenues to extend current research to include measurement of micro-scale anisotropic properties, interfaces and phase boundaries using FIB-prepared sections. The instrument will support multi-disciplinary research and education programs including ceramic, glass, metal, biomaterials, chemistry and geology/geochemistry studies at Alfred University.  FIB sample preparation is key in the study of advanced materials, for example studies of sub-surface and internal defects and localized plastic deformation, linking creation of flaws to additive manufacturing and processing conditions, and tracking subtle changes in microstructure and chemistry at internal and external surfaces and interfaces.  As such, the requested FIB will become a centerpiece in making transformational progress in the ceramics-centric areas of education and research at Alfred University.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/15/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/15/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2018306</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Scott</FirstName>
<LastName>Misture</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Scott Misture</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[misture@alfred.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000160296</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/15/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gabrielle</FirstName>
<LastName>Gaustad</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gabrielle Gaustad</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[gaustad@alfred.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000560036</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/15/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kun</FirstName>
<LastName>Wang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kun Wang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[wang@alfred.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000796928</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/15/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Alfred University</Name>
<CityName>ALFRED</CityName>
<ZipCode>148021205</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6078712026</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1 SAXON DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>23</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY23</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>J1B5PBG573T1</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ALFRED UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Alfred University]]></Name>
<CityName>Alfred</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>148021205</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1 Saxon Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>23</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY23</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>Major Research Instrumentation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~495254</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>A scanning electron microscope with focused ion beam milling capability (FIB/SEM) was purchased using the Major Research Instrumentation grant.&nbsp; A Thermo Fisher Scientific (FEI) Scios 2 HiVac instrument was procured, installed, tested, and training of on-campus users was completed, all over the course of the one-year project.&nbsp; The new instrument was immediately evaluated by several users on campus after the training sessions, including three graduate students, two faculty and the lead lab technician.&nbsp; This initial team of users made FIB-cut samples and performed high-magnification imaging using exceedingly challenging samples which included high entropy metallic alloys and oxide nanosheet nanostructures. The instrument exceeded specifications and is currently open for general use on campus and by off-campus collaborators.&nbsp; Thus far, the primary users include two faculty and three graduate students, and data has already been included in three Ph.D. dissertations which are in preparation. Thus far, two of the co-PIs&nbsp; have personally run all training sessions with interested graduate students, postdocs and with the Ph.D.-level laboratory technician. &nbsp;While there are not yet any accepted publications which contain data from the new instrument, several are forthcoming and we have successfully fully trained two advanced users, both graduate students, one of whom is from an underrepresented group.&nbsp;</p> <p>The acquisition of the new instrument has been publicized to the university community via press releases and initial industrial projects are under discussion.&nbsp; Broader use of the instrument is anticipated as the on-campus team builds expertise and experience over the coming months. The instrument use pricing scheme for off-campus users has been communicated to our industrial outreach staff and included in price sheets, and additional industrial use is anticipated starting in early 2022. Separately from the NSF MRI grant, Alfred University has procured a Thermo Fisher Scientific transmission electron microscope (S/TEM), so that the FIB/SEM can be used to prepare samples for S/TEM analysis as well, thus even further extending its broader use and impact.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/30/2021<br>      Modified by: Scott&nbsp;Misture</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2018306/2018306_10685701_1640885479813_FIB_Floccule--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2018306/2018306_10685701_1640885479813_FIB_Floccule--rgov-800width.jpg" title="FIB section through a porous 2-D oxide assembly"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2018306/2018306_10685701_1640885479813_FIB_Floccule--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="FIB section through a porous 2-D oxide assembly"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The image shows the ion beam cut into a porous floccule comprising 2-D MnO2 nanosheets.  Cross-sectioning such fragile and high-porosity solids is now feasible with the new instrument, providing insight into charge storage and catalysis functions.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Scott Misture, Alfred University</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Scott&nbsp;Misture</div> <div class="imageTitle">FIB section through a porous 2-D oxide assembly</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ A scanning electron microscope with focused ion beam milling capability (FIB/SEM) was purchased using the Major Research Instrumentation grant.  A Thermo Fisher Scientific (FEI) Scios 2 HiVac instrument was procured, installed, tested, and training of on-campus users was completed, all over the course of the one-year project.  The new instrument was immediately evaluated by several users on campus after the training sessions, including three graduate students, two faculty and the lead lab technician.  This initial team of users made FIB-cut samples and performed high-magnification imaging using exceedingly challenging samples which included high entropy metallic alloys and oxide nanosheet nanostructures. The instrument exceeded specifications and is currently open for general use on campus and by off-campus collaborators.  Thus far, the primary users include two faculty and three graduate students, and data has already been included in three Ph.D. dissertations which are in preparation. Thus far, two of the co-PIs  have personally run all training sessions with interested graduate students, postdocs and with the Ph.D.-level laboratory technician.  While there are not yet any accepted publications which contain data from the new instrument, several are forthcoming and we have successfully fully trained two advanced users, both graduate students, one of whom is from an underrepresented group.   The acquisition of the new instrument has been publicized to the university community via press releases and initial industrial projects are under discussion.  Broader use of the instrument is anticipated as the on-campus team builds expertise and experience over the coming months. The instrument use pricing scheme for off-campus users has been communicated to our industrial outreach staff and included in price sheets, and additional industrial use is anticipated starting in early 2022. Separately from the NSF MRI grant, Alfred University has procured a Thermo Fisher Scientific transmission electron microscope (S/TEM), so that the FIB/SEM can be used to prepare samples for S/TEM analysis as well, thus even further extending its broader use and impact.       Last Modified: 12/30/2021       Submitted by: Scott Misture]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
