<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[MRI: Acquisition of PeakForce Kelvin Probe Force Microscopy Package and Upgrade for Dimension Icon Scanning Probe Microscopy System]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>40110.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>40110</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Z.  Ying</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cying@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928428</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Nontechnical Description:&lt;br/&gt;This project funds upgrades to a scanning probe microscope that is central to the research, teaching, and outreach activities at Appalachian State University. This system is critical to four different physics and chemistry research groups on campus and enables continued collaborations with several institutions, including Duke University and the Rochester Institute of Technology. Research performed using the upgraded system will be conducted primarily by undergraduates and Masters students and will focus on the development and characterization of electronic materials such as organic semiconductors and atomically thin crystals. It benefits the public by helping to develop renewable power sources and performant electronic technologies. In addition to research, the instrument is used daily for teaching and is integrated into Appalachian's graduate-level courses on microscopy techniques, materials science, and nanoscience. The microscope is also regularly featured in educational outreach and recruiting events, such as campus open house tours and Appalachian's Science, Technology, Engineering, Arts and Mathematics (STEAM) Expo, a science festival event that gathers approximately 2,500 K-12 students annually. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical Description:&lt;br/&gt;This award allows the addition of two nanoscale imaging modes, Peakforce Kelvin Probe Force Microscopy and Quantitative Nanomechanical Mapping, to the existing Dimension Icon scanning probe microscope at Appalachian. Kelvin Probe microscopy characterizes changes in the work function of a material at the nanoscale, whereas nanomechanical mapping images the spatial variations of the strain and elastic modulus. The team uses these modes to: (1) investigate and optimize the morphology of field-effect and photovoltaic devices based on organic semiconductor blends; (2) characterize local doping in van der Waals heterostructures; (3) image the local strain that arises from Moire effects in twisted van der Waals heterostructures; and (4) characterize the nanoscale morphology of switchable elastomeric materials based on metal-coordination complex crosslinked polymer networks.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/13/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/13/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2018889</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Francois</FirstName>
<LastName>Amet</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Francois Amet</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ametf@appstate.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000708264</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/13/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tonya</FirstName>
<LastName>Coffey</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Tonya S Coffey</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[coffeyts@appstate.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000498974</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/13/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Appalachian State University</Name>
<CityName>BOONE</CityName>
<ZipCode>286080001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8282627459</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>438 ACADEMY ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>F1NAKY5L1425</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>APPALACHIAN STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Appalachian State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Boone</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>286079999</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[438 Academy St]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>Major Research Instrumentation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7697</Code>
<Text>INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~40110</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-b51f5488-7fff-b078-4e44-c07d94556e82"> </span></p> <p><a name="_GoBack"></a>This proposal funded upgrades to an existing scanning probe microscopy (SPM) system at Appalachian State University. This system is a Bruker Dimension Icon microscope and was purchased in 2008 with MRI funds (fund number 0821124). It is still used daily for research, teaching, and outreach, and it is an integral part of the curriculum of the department of Physics and Astronomy at Appalachian. The upgrades were installed on November 13, 2020, and included new operating software to replace the obsolete software installed in 2008. Additionally, the funding provided new advanced scanning modes, including Peakforce KPFM (Kelvin Probe Force Microscopy) and QNM (Quantitative Nanomechanical Mapping). These new modes provide valuable information on the electrostatic and mechanical properties of materials at the nanoscale. The updated SPM system directly benefits four research groups in the departments of Physics and Chemistry at Appalachian State University, and it enables continued collaborations with Wake Forest University, Duke University, Lincoln Memorial University and the Rochester Institute of Technology.&nbsp;</p> <p>This funding has an impact on several research projects that benefit society by investigating promising power sources and electronics that are cleaner, cheaper, or more efficient than those commercially available. For example, KPFM imaging provided key insights in our recent analysis of the processing and performance of metal halide perovskite semiconducting thin films. It demonstrated how surface treatment of those thin films can improve their performance, since it helps reduce their contact resistance, reduce their surface roughness, and reduce electrostatic potential inhomogeneities at their surface. Figure 1 shows the dramatic reduction of the roughness of a&nbsp;metal perovskite film after surface treatment. Figure 2 shows that the surface potential of the perovskite film without the surface treatment is much less uniform than it is after the surface treatment. Another area of research that benefits from the new SPM system is the fabrication and characterization of novel superconducting devices based on two-dimensional materials such as graphene. The microscope allows the control of the device cleanliness at every step of the fabrication, which in turn yields devices with remarkable electronic performance.&nbsp;</p> <p>The microscope offers exciting training opportunities to students at Appalachian State University, as well as outreach capabilities that have a significant impact on its broader community. Indeed, seven graduate students and two undergraduates directly benefited from the installation of the upgraded SPM system. At Appalachian State, four students recently received training, which allowed one of them to complete his Master&rsquo;s thesis on &ldquo;Kelvin Probe Force Microscopy Imaging and Characterization of Organic Photovoltaics." The three others gathered data which was used in a paper published in Nanoletters entitled &ldquo;The Multiterminal inverse AC Josephson effect&rdquo;. &nbsp;Data acquired with the system were also included in a PhD dissertation completed at Wake Forest University entitled "Metal Halide Perovskite: Innovations in Applications and Processing," as well as in an upcoming peer-reviewed publication, written in collaboration with our collaborators at the Rochester Institute of Technology, on the "Optimal morphology, H-aggregation, and ternary blend excited state disruption in equilibrated squaraine-based all small molecule solar-cells." Additionally, the microscope is regularly featured in educational outreach and recruiting events, such as campus open house tours and App State's annual STEAM Expo Day, an NC Science Festival event. Although this event was suspended due to COVID-19, the next STEAM Expo is currently scheduled for April 2022.</p> <p dir="ltr">&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/30/2021<br>      Modified by: Francois&nbsp;Amet</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2018889/2018889_10685126_1639415371686_3Dtopo--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2018889/2018889_10685126_1639415371686_3Dtopo--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Topographical maps of perovskite films"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2018889/2018889_10685126_1639415371686_3Dtopo--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Topographical maps of perovskite films"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Three dimensional topographical maps of the perovskite film without (left) and with (right) the surface treatment</div> <div class="imageCredit">Tonya Coffey</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Tonya&nbsp;S&nbsp;Coffey</div> <div class="imageTitle">Topographical maps of perovskite films</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2018889/2018889_10685126_1639415550426_surfacepotential--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2018889/2018889_10685126_1639415550426_surfacepotential--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Surface potential maps of the perovskite films"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2018889/2018889_10685126_1639415550426_surfacepotential--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Surface potential maps of the perovskite films"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Surface potential maps of the perovskite film without (left) and with (right) the surface treatment</div> <div class="imageCredit">Tonya Coffey</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Tonya&nbsp;S&nbsp;Coffey</div> <div class="imageTitle">Surface potential maps of the perovskite films</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[    This proposal funded upgrades to an existing scanning probe microscopy (SPM) system at Appalachian State University. This system is a Bruker Dimension Icon microscope and was purchased in 2008 with MRI funds (fund number 0821124). It is still used daily for research, teaching, and outreach, and it is an integral part of the curriculum of the department of Physics and Astronomy at Appalachian. The upgrades were installed on November 13, 2020, and included new operating software to replace the obsolete software installed in 2008. Additionally, the funding provided new advanced scanning modes, including Peakforce KPFM (Kelvin Probe Force Microscopy) and QNM (Quantitative Nanomechanical Mapping). These new modes provide valuable information on the electrostatic and mechanical properties of materials at the nanoscale. The updated SPM system directly benefits four research groups in the departments of Physics and Chemistry at Appalachian State University, and it enables continued collaborations with Wake Forest University, Duke University, Lincoln Memorial University and the Rochester Institute of Technology.   This funding has an impact on several research projects that benefit society by investigating promising power sources and electronics that are cleaner, cheaper, or more efficient than those commercially available. For example, KPFM imaging provided key insights in our recent analysis of the processing and performance of metal halide perovskite semiconducting thin films. It demonstrated how surface treatment of those thin films can improve their performance, since it helps reduce their contact resistance, reduce their surface roughness, and reduce electrostatic potential inhomogeneities at their surface. Figure 1 shows the dramatic reduction of the roughness of a metal perovskite film after surface treatment. Figure 2 shows that the surface potential of the perovskite film without the surface treatment is much less uniform than it is after the surface treatment. Another area of research that benefits from the new SPM system is the fabrication and characterization of novel superconducting devices based on two-dimensional materials such as graphene. The microscope allows the control of the device cleanliness at every step of the fabrication, which in turn yields devices with remarkable electronic performance.   The microscope offers exciting training opportunities to students at Appalachian State University, as well as outreach capabilities that have a significant impact on its broader community. Indeed, seven graduate students and two undergraduates directly benefited from the installation of the upgraded SPM system. At Appalachian State, four students recently received training, which allowed one of them to complete his Master’s thesis on "Kelvin Probe Force Microscopy Imaging and Characterization of Organic Photovoltaics." The three others gathered data which was used in a paper published in Nanoletters entitled "The Multiterminal inverse AC Josephson effect".  Data acquired with the system were also included in a PhD dissertation completed at Wake Forest University entitled "Metal Halide Perovskite: Innovations in Applications and Processing," as well as in an upcoming peer-reviewed publication, written in collaboration with our collaborators at the Rochester Institute of Technology, on the "Optimal morphology, H-aggregation, and ternary blend excited state disruption in equilibrated squaraine-based all small molecule solar-cells." Additionally, the microscope is regularly featured in educational outreach and recruiting events, such as campus open house tours and App State's annual STEAM Expo Day, an NC Science Festival event. Although this event was suspended due to COVID-19, the next STEAM Expo is currently scheduled for April 2022.            Last Modified: 12/30/2021       Submitted by: Francois Amet]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
