<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[CC* Compute: Compute Cluster for Computational Sciences at Louisiana State University Health Sciences Center – New Orleans (LSUHSC-NO)]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>399458.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>399458</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OAC</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure (OAC)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Amy Apon</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>awapon@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925184</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This project at Louisiana State University Health Sciences Center New Orleans (LSUHSC-NO) constructs a scalable 26-node high-performance computing cluster (HPC) named Tigerfish. Tigerfish provides LSUHSC-NO researchers with uninterrupted, local access to HPC resources to enable and accelerate their biomedical research. The project provides training to new and existing HPC users to ease their transition to utilizing both Tigerfish and other nationally available HPC resources to meet increasing computational needs of their research. Tigerfish supports research and education within multiple disciplines at LSUHSC-NO including Bioinformatics, Biostatistics, Computational Biology, Genetics, Computational Genomics, Microbiology, Neurology, and Proteomics. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project has broader impacts for the community including training the next generation of researchers as a part of the Tiger Scholars program which provides high-school students with the opportunity to be exposed to the capabilities of HPC in research. Tigerfish is available as a computing resource supporting a high school, undergraduate, and postbaccalaureate student summer research program that provides summer research experiences to students coming to study at LSUHSC-NO from various parts of the country. Tigerfish provides an essential platform for our outreach to regional historically black colleges and universities which lack their own HPC resources for intensive computing. The recently launched Bioinformatics and Genomics program is able to access Tigerfish as an essential resource for their highly intensive computational needs and serves as a resource for the newly established MS Biomedical Sciences-Bioinformatics Track program. Finally, Tigerfish resources are shared with Open Science Grid for LSUHSC-NO to play its part in making HPC more accessible nationally.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/29/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/28/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2018936</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Carmen</FirstName>
<LastName>Canavier</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Carmen C Canavier</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ccanav@lsuhsc.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000350586</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/29/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mohamad</FirstName>
<LastName>Qayoom</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mohamad A Qayoom</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mqayoo@lsuhsc.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000668805</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/29/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate>07/28/2020</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Christopher</FirstName>
<LastName>Taylor</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Christopher M Taylor</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ctay15@lsuhsc.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000668809</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/28/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kenneth</FirstName>
<LastName>Boe</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME>Jr</PI_SUFX_NAME>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kenneth J Boe</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[kboe@lsuhsc.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000796457</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/29/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Andrew</FirstName>
<LastName>Chapple</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>G</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Andrew G Chapple</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[achapp@lsuhsc.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000796582</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/29/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Chindo</FirstName>
<LastName>Hicks</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Chindo Hicks</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[chick3@lsuhsc.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000796736</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/29/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Louisiana State University Health Sciences Center</Name>
<CityName>NEW ORLEANS</CityName>
<ZipCode>701127021</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5045684804</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>433 BOLIVAR ST STE 815</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
<StateCode>LA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>LA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>M7KCJ79FAVH5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>LOUISIANA STATE UNIVERSITY HEALTH SCIENCES CENTER-NEW ORLEANS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>Z7ZNZH7LJ778</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Louisiana State University Health Sciences Center]]></Name>
<CityName>New Orleans</CityName>
<StateCode>LA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>701122223</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[433 Bolivar St]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>LA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8080</Code>
<Text>Campus Cyberinfrastructure</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~399458</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>NSF award 2018936 was issued to the Louisiana State University Health Sciences Center (LSUHSC) and provided funding to purchase a high performance computing cluster (named Tigerfish) to be used by researchers at the health sciences center.&nbsp; The award also provided funding to support installation and deployment of the cluster along with personnel to help support users of the cluster in migrating their current computing workflows to the new equipment.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>Project Outcomes were as follows:</p> <p class="p1">1) Acquisition and deployment of Tigerfish</p> <p class="p1">The principle investigators (PIs) worked with information technology support staff at LSUHSC to perform the required state bidding process for acquisition of substantial equipment.&nbsp; We developed a specification for the bid and worked with state procurment personnel to put the designed cluster out to bid and select the vendor that could most cost-effectively meet the requirments.&nbsp; The team then worked with the vendor to take delivery of the cluster and install it in our server room.</p> <p class="p1">2) Training a team to manage and maintain Tigerfish</p> <p class="p1">Information technology support staff were trained by the vendor to manage and maintain the new cluster.&nbsp; Over the course of the award, these personnel attended training and worked with the PIs to effectively set up and maintain Tigerfish for enterprise research usage.</p> <p class="p1">3) Integrating Tigerfish with Open Science Grid for sharing resources</p> <p class="p1">The team worked with the Open Science Grid (OSG) personnel to integrate Tigerfish into the OSG computing resources which allows for users throughout the country to submit jobs for running on OSGs collection of computing resources.&nbsp; This integration was effectively tuned to provide OSG with roughly 20% of the computing capacity of Tigerfish, reserving the remaining 80% for LSUHSC internal usage.</p> <p class="p1">4) Educating and encourage users to migrate their workflowsto utilize Tigerfish</p> <p class="p1">The team developed an introductory training seminar and delivered it in person to potential users on the LSUHSC campus.&nbsp; This introductory seminar was repeated and offered by Zoom for participants to attend remotely who could not attend the first session in person.&nbsp; This Zoom training was recorded and is maintained as an enduring resource for new users of the Tigerfish cluster.&nbsp; It is maintained as a resource on our newly developed High Performance Computing (HPC) web portal.&nbsp; The HPC Web Portal also provides links to various resources for new Tigerfish users and methods of contact for them to get assistance with the cluster.</p> <p class="p1">Overall, the Tigerfish HPC has provided researchers at the LSUHSC campus with a new computing resource that allows them to perform complex computational analysis on their data that was not available prior to this award.&nbsp; To date, Tigerfish has supported research projects involving DNA Sequencing, Computational Neuroscience, and Genomics research.&nbsp; So far, four peer reviewed journal articles, one peer reviewed book chapter and two conference presentation abstracts have been supported by the Tigerfish cluster.&nbsp; Tigerfish presently has 43 users across 15 different departments at LSUHSC and has become a key resource to advance the institutions mission of further developing computational capactity to support complex biomedical research.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/11/2023<br>      Modified by: Christopher&nbsp;M&nbsp;Taylor</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ NSF award 2018936 was issued to the Louisiana State University Health Sciences Center (LSUHSC) and provided funding to purchase a high performance computing cluster (named Tigerfish) to be used by researchers at the health sciences center.  The award also provided funding to support installation and deployment of the cluster along with personnel to help support users of the cluster in migrating their current computing workflows to the new equipment.    Project Outcomes were as follows: 1) Acquisition and deployment of Tigerfish The principle investigators (PIs) worked with information technology support staff at LSUHSC to perform the required state bidding process for acquisition of substantial equipment.  We developed a specification for the bid and worked with state procurment personnel to put the designed cluster out to bid and select the vendor that could most cost-effectively meet the requirments.  The team then worked with the vendor to take delivery of the cluster and install it in our server room. 2) Training a team to manage and maintain Tigerfish Information technology support staff were trained by the vendor to manage and maintain the new cluster.  Over the course of the award, these personnel attended training and worked with the PIs to effectively set up and maintain Tigerfish for enterprise research usage. 3) Integrating Tigerfish with Open Science Grid for sharing resources The team worked with the Open Science Grid (OSG) personnel to integrate Tigerfish into the OSG computing resources which allows for users throughout the country to submit jobs for running on OSGs collection of computing resources.  This integration was effectively tuned to provide OSG with roughly 20% of the computing capacity of Tigerfish, reserving the remaining 80% for LSUHSC internal usage. 4) Educating and encourage users to migrate their workflowsto utilize Tigerfish The team developed an introductory training seminar and delivered it in person to potential users on the LSUHSC campus.  This introductory seminar was repeated and offered by Zoom for participants to attend remotely who could not attend the first session in person.  This Zoom training was recorded and is maintained as an enduring resource for new users of the Tigerfish cluster.  It is maintained as a resource on our newly developed High Performance Computing (HPC) web portal.  The HPC Web Portal also provides links to various resources for new Tigerfish users and methods of contact for them to get assistance with the cluster. Overall, the Tigerfish HPC has provided researchers at the LSUHSC campus with a new computing resource that allows them to perform complex computational analysis on their data that was not available prior to this award.  To date, Tigerfish has supported research projects involving DNA Sequencing, Computational Neuroscience, and Genomics research.  So far, four peer reviewed journal articles, one peer reviewed book chapter and two conference presentation abstracts have been supported by the Tigerfish cluster.  Tigerfish presently has 43 users across 15 different departments at LSUHSC and has become a key resource to advance the institutions mission of further developing computational capactity to support complex biomedical research.          Last Modified: 08/11/2023       Submitted by: Christopher M Taylor]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
