<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[I-Corps:  Laparoscopic Induction Heaters for Biomedical Applications]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ruth Shuman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rshuman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922160</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this I-Corps project is the development of miniature induction heaters to heat electrically conductive materials in hard-to-reach places within the human body.  The goal is to develop smaller, more focused magnetic field applicators that may be used in patients having metallic implants (e.g., hip replacement implants, stents, etc.) otherwise ineligible to receive current magnetic nanoparticle-based cancer therapies.  Additionally, the aim is to enable the development of new medical procedures requiring in situ, non-contact heating of electrically conductive materials in relatively inaccessible places within the human body.    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project is to explore translation of miniature induction-heating devices for biomedical applications, such as in laparoscopic procedures with the intention of treating intra-peritoneal metastatic cancer such as ovarian cancer using magnetic fluid hyperthermia (MFH).  Capabilities include generating an alternating magnetic field of up to 18 kA/m at a frequency of 290kHz.  With this field intensity, it is possible to heat a stainless-steel disk to more than 500°C and a suspension of iron oxide magnetic nanoparticles to maximum temperatures ranging from 39°C to 96°C, depending on particle concentration.  Translational research includes: a) development of novel magnetic field generators allowing a more localized MFH prostate cancer therapy, b) further exploration of the concept of having miniature induction heaters to heat electrically conductive materials in hard-to-reach places within the human body, c) determining the capabilities of the technology in heating magnetic nanoparticles to kill cancer cells in vitro and d) determining the devices' capabilities in heating magnetic nanoparticles to ablate porcine tissues and estimate severity and extent of tissue damage under different operating conditions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/10/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/10/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2019736</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Eduardo</FirstName>
<LastName>Juan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Eduardo J Juan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ejuan@ece.uprm.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000479819</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Puerto Rico Mayaguez</Name>
<CityName>MAYAGUEZ</CityName>
<ZipCode>006806475</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7878312065</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>259 BLVD ALFONSO VALDES</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Puerto Rico</StateName>
<StateCode>PR</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PR00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>GZRNJ1GZDBM1</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF PUERTO RICO</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>RD8QJEHNYLJ7</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Puerto Rico Mayaguez]]></Name>
<CityName>Mayaguez</CityName>
<StateCode>PR</StateCode>
<ZipCode>006809000</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Call Box 9000, Road 108 km. 1.0]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Puerto Rico</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PR00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>For the last seven years, our research group has worked on the development of miniature induction heaters capable of heating electrically conductive materials in hard-to-reach places within the human body.&nbsp; Our main application has been cancer treatment, but we are exploring other applications as well.&nbsp; Our team successfully completed the I-Corps program at the University of Perto Rico-Mayaguez (UPRM) site in May 2019 with 39 interviews (cancer patients, surgeons). Later, we won a travel award that was used to conduct 20 interviews to surgical oncologists at MD Anderson Cancer Center (Houston, TX). During the interviews, we were able to define who could be our early adopter (urologic oncologists) and what questions needed to be answered for surgical oncologists to decide buying our product in the future.&nbsp; Based on the results of these interviews, we stipulated that our technology would fall under the <strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">medical device market segment</span></strong>, that our <strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">users</span></strong> would be <strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">surgical oncologists</span></strong> treating prostate and potentially other types of cancer and that the <strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">paying customer</span></strong> would be <strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">administrators of hospitals</span></strong> at which these procedures will be conducted.&nbsp; In order to further validate the market and business model related to the commercialization of our technology, we applied for and participated in the NSF I-Corps Teams program.</p> <p>The major goals of this I-Corps Teams project were to: a) expand our knowledge of the business canvas concept and b) perform at least 100 customer discovery interviews to evolve the business model of our technology into one that is commercially feasible.&nbsp;&nbsp; &nbsp;</p> <p>Our team participated in the Upstate New York cohort, which took place in virtual format on July-August 2020.&nbsp; The team actively participated in all requires activities and performed a total of 100 interviews (1 in-person, 49 via phone, 50 via videoconference).&nbsp; The interviewees consisted mostly of physicians from different specialties, engineers, hospital administrators and industrial induction heaters manufacturers.&nbsp; Interviews were performed in Puerto Rico and in ten US states.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>After performing the 100 interviews and analyzing the data obtained from them, we found that our technology has commercial potential for cancer treatment, with urologic oncologists being our primary users and hospital administrators being the paying customers.&nbsp; We found, at the moment, no other applications for our technology in medical areas outside of cancer.&nbsp; We found, however, a potential application in the aerospace industry.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/01/2022<br>      Modified by: Eduardo&nbsp;J&nbsp;Juan</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ For the last seven years, our research group has worked on the development of miniature induction heaters capable of heating electrically conductive materials in hard-to-reach places within the human body.  Our main application has been cancer treatment, but we are exploring other applications as well.  Our team successfully completed the I-Corps program at the University of Perto Rico-Mayaguez (UPRM) site in May 2019 with 39 interviews (cancer patients, surgeons). Later, we won a travel award that was used to conduct 20 interviews to surgical oncologists at MD Anderson Cancer Center (Houston, TX). During the interviews, we were able to define who could be our early adopter (urologic oncologists) and what questions needed to be answered for surgical oncologists to decide buying our product in the future.  Based on the results of these interviews, we stipulated that our technology would fall under the medical device market segment, that our users would be surgical oncologists treating prostate and potentially other types of cancer and that the paying customer would be administrators of hospitals at which these procedures will be conducted.  In order to further validate the market and business model related to the commercialization of our technology, we applied for and participated in the NSF I-Corps Teams program.  The major goals of this I-Corps Teams project were to: a) expand our knowledge of the business canvas concept and b) perform at least 100 customer discovery interviews to evolve the business model of our technology into one that is commercially feasible.      Our team participated in the Upstate New York cohort, which took place in virtual format on July-August 2020.  The team actively participated in all requires activities and performed a total of 100 interviews (1 in-person, 49 via phone, 50 via videoconference).  The interviewees consisted mostly of physicians from different specialties, engineers, hospital administrators and industrial induction heaters manufacturers.  Interviews were performed in Puerto Rico and in ten US states.     After performing the 100 interviews and analyzing the data obtained from them, we found that our technology has commercial potential for cancer treatment, with urologic oncologists being our primary users and hospital administrators being the paying customers.  We found, at the moment, no other applications for our technology in medical areas outside of cancer.  We found, however, a potential application in the aerospace industry.          Last Modified: 02/01/2022       Submitted by: Eduardo J Juan]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
