<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Expanding Access to Ecological Research Innovation and the Power of the Data Revolution]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>70071.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>70071</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Matthew Kane</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mkane@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927186</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Many of the large, complex challenges in ecology and environmental science will need new approaches, incorporating new data and collaborations with experts in neighboring fields of science. To help address this, a cohort of twenty graduate students and early career scientists from a variety of disciplines will meet to foster collaborations in innovative ecological research methods and the role of big data in emerging ideas through a series of activities at the 2020 Ecological Society of America (ESA) Annual Meeting in Salt Lake City, August 2-7, 2020. This project will help to advance ecological research by providing opportunities, particularly for students and early career scientists from underrepresented groups in science, to learn novel ways of harnessing the deluge of data in ecology expected to yield transformative results for science and society. By explicitly encouraging scientific research into environmental issues that disproportionately impact the communities of participants, follow-on research will have far reaching impacts on policy, resource management decisions and programs in communities of color, low income communities and tribal communities. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The cohort of graduate students and early career scientists from underrepresented groups will be drawn from a variety of disciplines, and will meet to foster collaborations in innovative ecological research methods and the role of big data in emerging ideas through a series of activities at the 2020 ESA Annual Meeting. Research skills workshops, diversity networks and focused conversations on: i) Expanding Access to Ecological Research Innovation; and ii) The Power of the Data Revolution will be followed by two cohort web meetings to facilitate exchange of ideas. This project will enable ESA to better understand the use of participant cohort strategies to support diverse graduate students and early career scientists within an expanding field with many sub-disciplines that extend into others. This project will provide twenty participants with the exposure, skills training, and networking to increase the likelihood of becoming contributing members of the extended ecological research community. Over time, many will act as role models for their communities and will inspire new students to enter and persevere in science, helping to create a sustainable critical mass of scientists that reflects the breadth of society in the U.S.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/23/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/23/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2019532</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Catherine</FirstName>
<LastName>O'Riordan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Catherine A O'Riordan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[Coriordan@esa.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000210527</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/23/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Teresa</FirstName>
<LastName>Mourad</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Teresa M Mourad</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[teresa@esa.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000281505</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/23/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Ecological Society of America</Name>
<CityName>WASHINGTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>200363415</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2028338773</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1990 M ST NW</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[STE 700]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>DBRGTD7EY3M1</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ECOLOGICAL SOCIETY OF AMERICA INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Ecological Society of America]]></Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>200363415</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1990 M St., NW Suite 700]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7959</Code>
<Text>MacroSysBIO &amp; NEON-Enabled Sci</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~70071</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project was conceived to introduce graduate students and early career scientists from underrepresented minority groups to a range of research opportunities in ecological science using big data.&nbsp; Participants were selected across a wide range of subdisciplines in ecology and environmental science to encourage cross-disciplinary cohort building and research collaboration. An initial group of 19 participants (84% Black, Indigenous, or People of Color (BIPOC)) worked together virtually for the first year of the project. With support from a planning team, Dr. Alycia Crall NEON, subsequently, Data Carpentries) and Dr. Marty Downs (LTER National Coordination Office/NCEAS), activities included attending sessions focused on Harnessing the Ecological Data Revolution at the 2020 ESA Annual Meeting from August 3-6, held virtually due to covid, as well as daily group discussions with data scientists.</p> <p>In fall 2021, participants were invited to attend a face-to-face workshop held near Baltimore, MD. Attendees included nine of the 2020 cohort and an additional eight new participants. The workshop began with two days of training in Data Carpentries and brought three data scientists and a science communication expert who served as faculty during the week. Members of the Planning Team and the list of resource experts are available at <a href="https://www.esa.org/seeds/meetings/power-of-data-workshop/">https://www.esa.org/seeds/meetings/power-of-data-workshop/</a>.</p> <p>They introduced participants to several data repositories of ecological data and built awareness of science communication principles. Consulting with the workshop faculty, attendees worked in multidisciplinary teams and applied new ideas gained to pitch research ideas in a culminating session to guest scientists who gave feedback to participants. &nbsp;After the workshop, participants were also invited to a session on grant writing and a follow up session on diversity, equity, inclusion and justice (DEIJ) in STEM fields.</p> <p>The group continued to join a series of cohort meetings and webchats throughout the two years. External evaluations indicated their strong interest in hands-on skill building in big data (beyond the scope of the project). Creating a Slack Channel for the group enabled participants to interact with a wider community of data scientists (EDSIN Slack group, 115 members).</p> <p>Results of this activity has indicated that this professional development approach to building a community of BIPOC scientists using big data in ecological research led to increased confidence in seeking out and utilizing large ecological datasets to answer key questions that could not have been answered previously. Participants also indicated the value of being involved in a broader network of data scientists to learn about new job or funding opportunities and support.</p> <p>There is a great need for additional opportunities to learn data science skills in general and to develop key skills with specific datasets. Developing a community approach extends far beyond skills building to providing support, both for ESA and for BIPOC participants as we confront and navigate issues of DEIJ in STEM.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/17/2022<br>      Modified by: Catherine&nbsp;A&nbsp;O'riordan</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2019532/2019532_10665937_1663431285817_2021PODgroup8888--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2019532/2019532_10665937_1663431285817_2021PODgroup8888--rgov-800width.jpg" title="2021 POD workshop"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2019532/2019532_10665937_1663431285817_2021PODgroup8888--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="2021 POD workshop"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">2021 Interdisciplinary Power of Data workshop attendees</div> <div class="imageCredit">ESA</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Teresa&nbsp;M&nbsp;Mourad</div> <div class="imageTitle">2021 POD workshop</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2019532/2019532_10665937_1663431368135_2021PODwithAndrewElmore8843--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2019532/2019532_10665937_1663431368135_2021PODwithAndrewElmore8843--rgov-800width.jpg" title="2021 POD attendees with Andrew Elmore"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2019532/2019532_10665937_1663431368135_2021PODwithAndrewElmore8843--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="2021 POD attendees with Andrew Elmore"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">2021 Power of Data workshop attendees consulting with Andrew Elmore</div> <div class="imageCredit">ESA</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Teresa&nbsp;M&nbsp;Mourad</div> <div class="imageTitle">2021 POD attendees with Andrew Elmore</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2019532/2019532_10665937_1663431749426_2021PODwithKellyHondula8839.jpeg--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2019532/2019532_10665937_1663431749426_2021PODwithKellyHondula8839.jpeg--rgov-800width.jpg" title="2021 POD attendees with Kelly Hondula"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2019532/2019532_10665937_1663431749426_2021PODwithKellyHondula8839.jpeg--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="2021 POD attendees with Kelly Hondula"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">2021 Power of Data workshop small team work with Kelly Hondula</div> <div class="imageCredit">ESA</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Teresa&nbsp;M&nbsp;Mourad</div> <div class="imageTitle">2021 POD attendees with Kelly Hondula</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2019532/2019532_10665937_1663431827591_2021PODwithKlaus-peterKoepfli8849--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2019532/2019532_10665937_1663431827591_2021PODwithKlaus-peterKoepfli8849--rgov-800width.jpg" title="2021 POD with Klaus-peter Koepfli"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2019532/2019532_10665937_1663431827591_2021PODwithKlaus-peterKoepfli8849--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="2021 POD with Klaus-peter Koepfli"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">2021 Power of Data workshop small team with Klaus-peter Koepfli</div> <div class="imageCredit">ESA</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Teresa&nbsp;M&nbsp;Mourad</div> <div class="imageTitle">2021 POD with Klaus-peter Koepfli</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2019532/2019532_10665937_1663432080359_2021PODgroupatfinalsession--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2019532/2019532_10665937_1663432080359_2021PODgroupatfinalsession--rgov-800width.jpg" title="2021 POD workshop final session"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2019532/2019532_10665937_1663432080359_2021PODgroupatfinalsession--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="2021 POD workshop final session"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">2021 Power of Data workshop attendees at final session</div> <div class="imageCredit">ESA</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Teresa&nbsp;M&nbsp;Mourad</div> <div class="imageTitle">2021 POD workshop final session</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2019532/2019532_10665937_1663432276770_2021PODnetworkinglunchwithQuinHolifield8890--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2019532/2019532_10665937_1663432276770_2021PODnetworkinglunchwithQuinHolifield8890--rgov-800width.jpg" title="2021 POD networking lunch"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2019532/2019532_10665937_1663432276770_2021PODnetworkinglunchwithQuinHolifield8890--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="2021 POD networking lunch"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">2021 Power of Data workshop networking lunch with guest, Quin Holifield, USFS</div> <div class="imageCredit">ESA</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Teresa&nbsp;M&nbsp;Mourad</div> <div class="imageTitle">2021 POD networking lunch</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project was conceived to introduce graduate students and early career scientists from underrepresented minority groups to a range of research opportunities in ecological science using big data.  Participants were selected across a wide range of subdisciplines in ecology and environmental science to encourage cross-disciplinary cohort building and research collaboration. An initial group of 19 participants (84% Black, Indigenous, or People of Color (BIPOC)) worked together virtually for the first year of the project. With support from a planning team, Dr. Alycia Crall NEON, subsequently, Data Carpentries) and Dr. Marty Downs (LTER National Coordination Office/NCEAS), activities included attending sessions focused on Harnessing the Ecological Data Revolution at the 2020 ESA Annual Meeting from August 3-6, held virtually due to covid, as well as daily group discussions with data scientists.  In fall 2021, participants were invited to attend a face-to-face workshop held near Baltimore, MD. Attendees included nine of the 2020 cohort and an additional eight new participants. The workshop began with two days of training in Data Carpentries and brought three data scientists and a science communication expert who served as faculty during the week. Members of the Planning Team and the list of resource experts are available at https://www.esa.org/seeds/meetings/power-of-data-workshop/.  They introduced participants to several data repositories of ecological data and built awareness of science communication principles. Consulting with the workshop faculty, attendees worked in multidisciplinary teams and applied new ideas gained to pitch research ideas in a culminating session to guest scientists who gave feedback to participants.  After the workshop, participants were also invited to a session on grant writing and a follow up session on diversity, equity, inclusion and justice (DEIJ) in STEM fields.  The group continued to join a series of cohort meetings and webchats throughout the two years. External evaluations indicated their strong interest in hands-on skill building in big data (beyond the scope of the project). Creating a Slack Channel for the group enabled participants to interact with a wider community of data scientists (EDSIN Slack group, 115 members).  Results of this activity has indicated that this professional development approach to building a community of BIPOC scientists using big data in ecological research led to increased confidence in seeking out and utilizing large ecological datasets to answer key questions that could not have been answered previously. Participants also indicated the value of being involved in a broader network of data scientists to learn about new job or funding opportunities and support.  There is a great need for additional opportunities to learn data science skills in general and to develop key skills with specific datasets. Developing a community approach extends far beyond skills building to providing support, both for ESA and for BIPOC participants as we confront and navigate issues of DEIJ in STEM.          Last Modified: 09/17/2022       Submitted by: Catherine A O'riordan]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
