<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research: Social Norms, Trust, and Intergenerational Flow of Innovations]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>371079.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>371079</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kwabena Gyimah-Brempong</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kgyimahb@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927466</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Increased productivity and economic growth partly depends on adoption of improved technology which in turn depends on the transmission of information about new technologies.  Young people tend to learn about new technologies before their parents who own productive resources and are wedded to old technologies and may not trust the new information they learn from the young.  On the other hand, young people may mistrust elders and may not reveal appropriate information they think elders will not accept, thus slowing technical progress and economic growth.  This research project will use theory and experiments to study how social norms affect the intergenerational flow of technological information and how best to solve this friction in information flow.  In addition to intergenerational transmission of information, the research also studies whether there is a gender dimension to the intergenerational flow of technological information.  The results of this study could influence the design of effective information interventions that induce intergenerational flows of knowledge to speed up technical progress. The results will offer valuable information on the constraints in the economic empowerment of young women. The results of this research has the potential to increase the pace of innovation and accelerate economic growth, and improve the living standards of Americans.    &lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;This research project will leverage a collaboration with NGO partners in 150 junior high schools to study the barriers in intergenerational flow of knowledge. The project focuses on beliefs held by parents regarding the level and relevance of students’ school-taught technical  knowledge, as well as students’ assessments of parents’ beliefs. It examines whether parents and students hold systematically biased beliefs; relates these biases to conventional roles prescribed for different configurations of parents and students by gender; and measures the effects of beliefs on intergenerational communication patterns, parents’ acquisition of new technical knowledge, and the empowerment of youth. The research proceeds in four stages. First, a baseline survey will collect household demographics of participants in a school-based technical education program. Second, the PIs will elicit parents’ and students’ beliefs in interviews; and deliver technical information to a random subset of parents and students. Third, the PIs will survey  productive inputs allocated to youth for their home production, the acquisition of new technical knowledge among parents as well as communication patterns between students and parents. Finally, the study will track the impact of the information interventions on production patterns after two school years.  The results of this research has the potential to increase the pace of innovation and accelerate economic growth, thus improving the living standards of Americans.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/07/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/22/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2019117</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Arja</FirstName>
<LastName>Dayal</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Arja Dayal</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[adayal@poverty-action.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000820082</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/07/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate>03/22/2021</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Andreas</FirstName>
<LastName>Holzinger</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Andreas Holzinger</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[aholzinger@poverty-action.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000843307</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/22/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate>12/22/2021</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Walker</FirstName>
<LastName>Higgins</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Walker Higgins</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[whiggins@poverty-action.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000862875</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/22/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Innovations for Poverty Action</Name>
<CityName>WASHINGTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>200363001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2036729507</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1701 RHODE ISLAND AVE NW FL 4</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>XP5MJA6GL8B7</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>INNOVATIONS FOR POVERTY ACTION A NONPROFIT CORP</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Innovations for Poverty Action]]></Name>
<CityName>Monrovia</CityName>
<StateCode/>
<ZipCode/>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4th FL, StC BLDG, Tubman BLVD]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>LI</CountryCode>
<CountryName>Liberia</CountryName>
<StateName>RI REQUIRED</StateName>
<CountryFlag>0</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT/>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>""</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1320</Code>
<Text>Economics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~371079</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Pareto efficiency in intra-household resource allocation is a convenient benchmark in economic modelling. This assumption, however, is challenged when information that guides decisions does not flow freely within households, such as when household members hide information because social norms prescribe obligations that they may not want. While barriers to information flows driven by conflicting preferences present a challenge for efficient household models, alternative models do not provide clear policy recommendations because lifting these barriers involves difficult tradeoffs.</p> <p>This study hypothesizes barriers to information flows in production that are not caused by conflicts in preferences. Instead, household members fail to coordinate their efforts in interactions that would foster information flows because there is an information asymmetry<br />about whether one party has relevant expertise in these interactions. This information asymmetry leads each party to form expectations about opponent behavior that are partially anchored to the status quo in production. Because household members miscoordinate due<br />to inaccurate mutual expectations, the theory implies mutually agreeable interactions that can be exploited to achieve policy goals via careful design of informational interventions. We focus on a situation that involves sharing of production knowledge across generations<br />within the household. Developing countries typically lack resources to train agricultural extension officers to visit distant rural households. With a good historical track record in rural America and subsequently in other parts of the world, a school-based approach to the diffusion of agricultural innovations offers promises to amplify the diffusion of innovations, empower youth with life supporting skills and strenthen rurla education. Amplifying the effects of this school-based program, however, requires overcoming an information asymmetry between students and parents regarding students? learning progress in schools that is well-documented in developing countries.</p> <p>Partnering with the 4-H school-based agricultural education program in Liberia, we use a field experiment to investigate if this information asymmetry hinders farm interactions between students and elders in their households. We study two hypotheses using randomized treatments. First, is there room to increase farm interactions by providing program information (in the form of a promotional video) to elders? Second, on top of providing 1 st -order information to elders, is there room to increase farm interactions by providing 2 nd -order information (information about elders? expectations of students? learning progress, in the form of encouragement messages) to students?</p> <p>In a two-year experiment, we investigate how these randomized treatments alter household responses to the program, such as students' participation in the program, time allocation, farm management activities, and communication with elders. We then trace students? and elders' knowledge and adoption of promoted cultivation practices. Two rounds of data collection took place under the funding of NSF.</p> <p>First was a qualitative data collection, which aimed to find out the impacts of 4-H and potential barriers to impact. The second round was baseline data collection in June ? August 2021. During this round of<br />data collection we determined the impact of the program 5-7 months after its start (in January 2021). Following a screening procedure that helped identify students with more pre- program farming activities outside schools, we surveyed 3915 students on their demographic<br />and household information, farming practices, beliefs, and activities, as well as tests on knowledge of farm management practices and agricultural innovations. We then conducted more intensive surveys involving randomized treatments among 1002 out of the 3915 students. For each of these students, we sampled one elder. For these 1002<br />households, we delivered promotional videos (either strong or weak version) to elders and conducted immediate follow-up surveys; we provided encouragement messages&nbsp;(that involves elders? expectations about their learning progress and a basic nudge that reminds students to diffuse program knowledge to elders) to students and conducted immediate folllow-up surveys.</p> <p><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Results</span></strong><br />First, we find positive treatment effects of the program 5-7 months after its start, which laid the foundation for our study of intergenerational information flows, most importantly in students' usage of agricultural innovations and intention to look after farms. Second, during our follow-up surveys of elders and students, we find that our treatments, promotional videos and encouragement messages, are effective in changing the behavior of subjects. We have secured funds for subsequent midline and endline surveys in the randomized experiments from other organizations.</p> <p>An initial analysis of our midline survey (conducted in May ? July 2022) suggests that these initial impacts of randomized household-level treatments translate into impacts on substantive outcomes. Besides results on 1st-order information, our comparison of the strong and weak messages arms indicate that 2nd-order information is effective:</p> <ul> <li>&nbsp;Students' knowledge on promoted practices improves by 0.2 SD.</li> <li>The likelihood of surveyed farm being continuously cultivated increases by 8 percentage points.</li> <li>The likelihood of students managing farms with intensive cultivation increases.</li> <li>Studentss enrollment in the same school improves by 1.7 percentage points and students' likelihood of paying school fees in time improves by 6 percentage points.</li> </ul><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/24/2023<br>      Modified by: Walker&nbsp;Higgins</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Pareto efficiency in intra-household resource allocation is a convenient benchmark in economic modelling. This assumption, however, is challenged when information that guides decisions does not flow freely within households, such as when household members hide information because social norms prescribe obligations that they may not want. While barriers to information flows driven by conflicting preferences present a challenge for efficient household models, alternative models do not provide clear policy recommendations because lifting these barriers involves difficult tradeoffs.  This study hypothesizes barriers to information flows in production that are not caused by conflicts in preferences. Instead, household members fail to coordinate their efforts in interactions that would foster information flows because there is an information asymmetry about whether one party has relevant expertise in these interactions. This information asymmetry leads each party to form expectations about opponent behavior that are partially anchored to the status quo in production. Because household members miscoordinate due to inaccurate mutual expectations, the theory implies mutually agreeable interactions that can be exploited to achieve policy goals via careful design of informational interventions. We focus on a situation that involves sharing of production knowledge across generations within the household. Developing countries typically lack resources to train agricultural extension officers to visit distant rural households. With a good historical track record in rural America and subsequently in other parts of the world, a school-based approach to the diffusion of agricultural innovations offers promises to amplify the diffusion of innovations, empower youth with life supporting skills and strenthen rurla education. Amplifying the effects of this school-based program, however, requires overcoming an information asymmetry between students and parents regarding students? learning progress in schools that is well-documented in developing countries.  Partnering with the 4-H school-based agricultural education program in Liberia, we use a field experiment to investigate if this information asymmetry hinders farm interactions between students and elders in their households. We study two hypotheses using randomized treatments. First, is there room to increase farm interactions by providing program information (in the form of a promotional video) to elders? Second, on top of providing 1 st -order information to elders, is there room to increase farm interactions by providing 2 nd -order information (information about elders? expectations of students? learning progress, in the form of encouragement messages) to students?  In a two-year experiment, we investigate how these randomized treatments alter household responses to the program, such as students' participation in the program, time allocation, farm management activities, and communication with elders. We then trace students? and elders' knowledge and adoption of promoted cultivation practices. Two rounds of data collection took place under the funding of NSF.  First was a qualitative data collection, which aimed to find out the impacts of 4-H and potential barriers to impact. The second round was baseline data collection in June ? August 2021. During this round of data collection we determined the impact of the program 5-7 months after its start (in January 2021). Following a screening procedure that helped identify students with more pre- program farming activities outside schools, we surveyed 3915 students on their demographic and household information, farming practices, beliefs, and activities, as well as tests on knowledge of farm management practices and agricultural innovations. We then conducted more intensive surveys involving randomized treatments among 1002 out of the 3915 students. For each of these students, we sampled one elder. For these 1002 households, we delivered promotional videos (either strong or weak version) to elders and conducted immediate follow-up surveys; we provided encouragement messages (that involves elders? expectations about their learning progress and a basic nudge that reminds students to diffuse program knowledge to elders) to students and conducted immediate folllow-up surveys.  Results First, we find positive treatment effects of the program 5-7 months after its start, which laid the foundation for our study of intergenerational information flows, most importantly in students' usage of agricultural innovations and intention to look after farms. Second, during our follow-up surveys of elders and students, we find that our treatments, promotional videos and encouragement messages, are effective in changing the behavior of subjects. We have secured funds for subsequent midline and endline surveys in the randomized experiments from other organizations.  An initial analysis of our midline survey (conducted in May ? July 2022) suggests that these initial impacts of randomized household-level treatments translate into impacts on substantive outcomes. Besides results on 1st-order information, our comparison of the strong and weak messages arms indicate that 2nd-order information is effective:   Students' knowledge on promoted practices improves by 0.2 SD. The likelihood of surveyed farm being continuously cultivated increases by 8 percentage points. The likelihood of students managing farms with intensive cultivation increases. Studentss enrollment in the same school improves by 1.7 percentage points and students' likelihood of paying school fees in time improves by 6 percentage points.        Last Modified: 02/24/2023       Submitted by: Walker Higgins]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
