<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Standardized Testing of Adult NIRS Oximetry Sensors using a Modular Phantom and Closed-loop Controlled Saturation System]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>138146.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>138146</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Steve Zehnder</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>szehnder@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927014</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Near-infrared spectroscopy (NIR) systems for NIRS-based cerebral oximeters (devices to measure brain oxygen level) represent a powerful and increasingly common approach for clinical detection of desaturation events (significant drops in oxygen level) with the potential to adversely impact tissue viability. Improved methods for standardized testing of adult cerebral oximeters will complement clinical testing currently required for regulatory clearance. Optimal test methods could be incorporated into current standards for cerebral oximeters and developed into a medical device development tool. The availability of a novel tool for effective, least-burdensome evaluation of adult cerebral oximeter device performance has the potential to lead to improvements in clinical performance that will impact patients undergoing surgical procedures where cerebral impairment is a significant risk. Furthermore, the proposed research will be seamlessly integrated with educational, mentoring, and outreach activities to advance the cross-disciplinary program in the field of Biophotonics Imaging and Regulatory Sciences.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This proposal aims to develop and validate a series of novel phantom-based test methods for adult NIRS oximetry. The components of this work will include: 1) Developing 3D-printed neurovascular module (NVM) incorporating a closed loop blood circulation system that enables controlled modulation of blood oxygenation, and silicone-based layers that replicate the geometry and optical properties of superficial layers in the adult head; 2) Investigating the effect of key confounding factors, including the thickness of extracerebral layers (e.g., scalp/skull, subarachnoid space), epidermal pigmentation level, and total blood concentration, on saturation measurement accuracy in two clinical cerebral oximeters; 3) Performing Monte Carlo simulations to elucidate light-tissue interactions during adult cerebral oximetry, including the effect of confounding factors.&lt;br/&gt;----&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/19/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/19/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2019254</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yu</FirstName>
<LastName>Chen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Yu Chen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ychen8@umass.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000505109</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/19/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Massachusetts Amherst</Name>
<CityName>AMHERST</CityName>
<ZipCode>01003</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4135450698</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>COMMONWEALTH AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>VGJHK59NMPK9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MASSACHUSETTS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>MLBQUML9JJT6</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Massachusetts Amherst]]></Name>
<CityName>Amherst</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>010039290</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[S617 Life Science Laboratories]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1642</Code>
<Text>Special Initiatives</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7236</Code>
<Text>BIOPHOTONICS, IMAGING &amp;SENSING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01001920DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~138146</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Near-Infrared Spectroscopy (NIRS) is a non-invasive sensing modality that is mainly used to monitor blood oxygenation in the brain. It has gained popularity due to these systems being portable, compact as well as having the ability to give the user real-time information on a subject?s blood oxygenation. Although there are many publications centered around the development of Monte Carlo (MC) simulations to extract information about near-infrared spectroscopy (NIRS) devices, most of these publications do not focus on validating best practices for <em>in silico</em> modeling, nor look into the optimization of test methods, making standardization a much more difficult task. In this project, we verified the <em>in silico</em> model with the analytically calculated reflectance based on previous mathematical models of reflectance. In addition, we optimized the number of photons and model geometrical configurations for simulation. &nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>In addition, we investigated the effects of NIRS probe placement. For example, whether the reading will change when an NIRS device is placed with source-detector orientation perpendicular or parallel to the vascular channels, or when the source is placed directly above or in between the channels. We simulated the NIRS orientations that run parallel and perpendicular to the channels in the phantom. We also tested the <em>in silico</em> simulation where the source is placed over a channel and when it?s placed in between channels to determine if positioning of the NIRS device in different manners would affect the results.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>This project aids in the development of benchtop test methods based on the computational modeling of light-tissue interactions, which can provide insights that clarify the behavior of clinical devices and facilitate the optimization of the phantom design. The creation of such an <em>in silico</em> model will allow us to: 1) rapidly prototype many <em>in silico</em> phantom configurations; and 2) extract information that might not otherwise be possible. The availability of such a tool for effective, least-burdensome evaluation of device performance has the potential to lead to improvements in clinical performance that will impact patients undergoing surgical procedures where cerebral impairment is a significant risk.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/11/2022<br>      Modified by: Yu&nbsp;Chen</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Near-Infrared Spectroscopy (NIRS) is a non-invasive sensing modality that is mainly used to monitor blood oxygenation in the brain. It has gained popularity due to these systems being portable, compact as well as having the ability to give the user real-time information on a subject?s blood oxygenation. Although there are many publications centered around the development of Monte Carlo (MC) simulations to extract information about near-infrared spectroscopy (NIRS) devices, most of these publications do not focus on validating best practices for in silico modeling, nor look into the optimization of test methods, making standardization a much more difficult task. In this project, we verified the in silico model with the analytically calculated reflectance based on previous mathematical models of reflectance. In addition, we optimized the number of photons and model geometrical configurations for simulation.        In addition, we investigated the effects of NIRS probe placement. For example, whether the reading will change when an NIRS device is placed with source-detector orientation perpendicular or parallel to the vascular channels, or when the source is placed directly above or in between the channels. We simulated the NIRS orientations that run parallel and perpendicular to the channels in the phantom. We also tested the in silico simulation where the source is placed over a channel and when it?s placed in between channels to determine if positioning of the NIRS device in different manners would affect the results.     This project aids in the development of benchtop test methods based on the computational modeling of light-tissue interactions, which can provide insights that clarify the behavior of clinical devices and facilitate the optimization of the phantom design. The creation of such an in silico model will allow us to: 1) rapidly prototype many in silico phantom configurations; and 2) extract information that might not otherwise be possible. The availability of such a tool for effective, least-burdensome evaluation of device performance has the potential to lead to improvements in clinical performance that will impact patients undergoing surgical procedures where cerebral impairment is a significant risk.          Last Modified: 05/11/2022       Submitted by: Yu Chen]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
