<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[EWSHM 2020 Student Travel Grant. To Be Held in Palermo, Italy, July 6-9, 2020]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>10000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>10000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ECCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Svetlana Tatic-Lucic</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>staticlu@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924627</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[NSF actively promotes the inclusion of students in technical conferences and in the advancement of scientific research. To this affect the PI requests that the CCSS program, within the ECCS Division of the Engineering Directorate at the NSF, sponsor travel of 10 graduate or undergraduate students from U.S. Institutions for attending the 10th European Workshop on Structural Health Monitoring (EWSHM 2020), to be held in Palermo (Italy) from July 6-9, 2020.  The NSF support is expected to significantly promote student participation in the Meetings and to provide a unique opportunity for them to learn about emerging fields in structural health monitoring (SHM).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of EWSHM 2020 Conference is to provide an open and interdisciplinary forum for researchers from a wide range of areas to discuss the latest advancements and breakthroughs in the field of SHM. The conference covers many interesting topics including, (1) Physical principles monitoring: mechanical, acoustic, electrical, thermal; (2) Signal processing, pattern recognition, modal analysis; (3) Sensors and sensor networks: nano/micro sensors, MEMS, wireless; (4) Remote sensing; (5) SHM in action: aerospace, marine, civil engineering, railway, energy generation; (6) Smart cities and SHM for the IoT; and (7) Autonomous systems, automotive; and (8) Biomedical applications and human performance monitoring. The topics represent the forefronts of Structural Health Monitoring research and applications. The NSF support is expected to significantly promote student participation in the meeting and to provide an opportunity for them to learn about emerging fields in SHM. The awardees will be part of a forum that fosters innovation and entrepreneurship through the work of people from academia and industry. Therefore, the Workshop will serve as a valuable event for U.S. students to connect with international experts in SHM in order to gain new knowledge for their future career development.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/12/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/31/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2019275</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Piervincenzo</FirstName>
<LastName>Rizzo</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Piervincenzo Rizzo</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[pir3@pitt.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000487801</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/12/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Pittsburgh</Name>
<CityName>PITTSBURGH</CityName>
<ZipCode>152600001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4126247400</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4200 FIFTH AVENUE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>MKAGLD59JRL1</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF PITTSBURGH - OF THE COMMONWEALTH SYSTEM OF HIGHER EDUCATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Pittsburgh]]></Name>
<CityName>Pittsburgh</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>152132303</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7564</Code>
<Text>CCSS-Comms Circuits &amp; Sens Sys</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~10000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This travel grant supported the travel of students from U.S. Institutions to the 10<sup>th</sup> European Workshop on Structural Health Monitoring, held at Palermo (Italy) in July 2022. This Workshop represented a forum where experts from around the world discussed the latest advancements and breakthroughs in the field of Structural Health Monitoring (SHM) and more broadly in the fields of nondestructive evaluation, smart materials and intelligent systems. The Workshop fostered the discussion and identification of key and emerging challenges and opportunities in research, development, and field applications. Despite the uncertainties related to COVI19 and political instabilities in Eastern Europe, the EWSHM 2022 set the record for the most attended EWSHM in history. About 430+ works were presented are confirmed form nearly 40 different countries.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>To be eligible, the applicant had to present his/her work and be the first author of the paper.</p> <p>Seven graduate students (three female, four male) were awarded. The grantees had access to all the sessions and the social events. The papers were published after peer-review in one of the three volumes of the proceedings (a total of 330 papers were published). One of the grantee won the best student paper award. This was a stiff competition based on double-bind peer-review from experts in the field of SHM.</p> <p>The grant was awarded in the form of a travel expenses reimbursement after the completion of the Workshop. Eligible expenses were registration, airfare, lodging, and meals.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/12/2023<br>      Modified by: Piervincenzo&nbsp;Rizzo</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2019275/2019275_10657548_1686591469241_ProceedingsVol.3bis--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2019275/2019275_10657548_1686591469241_ProceedingsVol.3bis--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Workshop Proceedings"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2019275/2019275_10657548_1686591469241_ProceedingsVol.3bis--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Workshop Proceedings"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Cover of the Third Volume of the Proceedings</div> <div class="imageCredit">https://m.media-amazon.com/images/I/61KuUQrPGlL._AC_UF1000,1000_QL80_.jpg</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Piervincenzo&nbsp;Rizzo</div> <div class="imageTitle">Workshop Proceedings</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This travel grant supported the travel of students from U.S. Institutions to the 10th European Workshop on Structural Health Monitoring, held at Palermo (Italy) in July 2022. This Workshop represented a forum where experts from around the world discussed the latest advancements and breakthroughs in the field of Structural Health Monitoring (SHM) and more broadly in the fields of nondestructive evaluation, smart materials and intelligent systems. The Workshop fostered the discussion and identification of key and emerging challenges and opportunities in research, development, and field applications. Despite the uncertainties related to COVI19 and political instabilities in Eastern Europe, the EWSHM 2022 set the record for the most attended EWSHM in history. About 430+ works were presented are confirmed form nearly 40 different countries.     To be eligible, the applicant had to present his/her work and be the first author of the paper.  Seven graduate students (three female, four male) were awarded. The grantees had access to all the sessions and the social events. The papers were published after peer-review in one of the three volumes of the proceedings (a total of 330 papers were published). One of the grantee won the best student paper award. This was a stiff competition based on double-bind peer-review from experts in the field of SHM.  The grant was awarded in the form of a travel expenses reimbursement after the completion of the Workshop. Eligible expenses were registration, airfare, lodging, and meals.          Last Modified: 06/12/2023       Submitted by: Piervincenzo Rizzo]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
