<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Engaging Doctoral Students in Autonomic and Self-Organizing Computing Systems Research]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>7500.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>7500</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OAC</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure (OAC)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ashok Srinivasan</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>asriniva@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922122</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The new IEEE IEEE International Conference on Autonomic Computing and Self-Organizing Systems (ACSOS) Conference, a merger of The IEEE International Conference on Autonomic Computing (ICAC) and the IEEE International Conference on Self-Adaptive and Self-Organizing Systems (SASO), is a premier conference in the fields of autonomic computing, self-adaptation and self-organization.  The conference, to be held online in August 2020, brings together researchers and industry practitioners to develop self-adapting, self-organizing, and automatic systems for addressing a number of challenges in the field, for example developing novel modeling techniques for interactions between local and global behaviors.  The project will support a diverse array of students to participate in the doctoral symposium at the conference, to engage deeply with the ACSOS research community.  The students will also have the opportunity to participate in all other conference activities, which are being modified to an online format.  The project serves the national interest, as stated by NSF's mission, to promote the progress of science as it provides a forum to disseminate research efforts, connect researchers, and train the next generation of scholars.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Recruitment efforts will focus on various underrepresented groups in science and engineering.  For the doctoral symposium, students will attend oral and poster presentations of research projects, and participate in a professional training and career development session to receive advice from experts in the field. That session will include tips on conducting research efficiently and ethically, writing and presenting research papers, seeking jobs in leading industry and academia after graduation, and realizing long-term professional and academic objectives. The funding provided by NSF will have a significant impact on the careers of the future generation of researchers in autonomic computing, while encouraging diversity in the field.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/22/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/22/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2019541</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Miaoqing</FirstName>
<LastName>Huang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Miaoqing Huang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mqhuang@uark.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000557777</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/22/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Arkansas</Name>
<CityName>FAYETTEVILLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>727013124</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4795753845</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1125 W MAPLE ST STE 316</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arkansas</StateName>
<StateCode>AR</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AR03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>MECEHTM8DB17</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ARKANSAS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Arkansas]]></Name>
<CityName>Fayetteville</CityName>
<StateCode>AR</StateCode>
<ZipCode>727011201</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[227 N Harmon Avenue #504]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arkansas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AR03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7361</Code>
<Text>EDUCATION AND WORKFORCE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>026Z</Code>
<Text>NSCI: National Strategic Computing Initi</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7923</Code>
<Text>SMALL PROJECT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~7500</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The objective of this project is to financially support students from US institutions to attend the annual ACSOS (IEEE International Conference on Autonomic Computing and Self-Organizing Systems) conference from 2020 to 2022. Due to the COVID-19 pandemic, the ACSOS conferences were held as virtual events in these three years. Therefore, financial support was awarded to US students in the form of registration grants. Overall, 18 students from 12 US institutions received registration grants, 9 in the Year 2020, 4 in the Year 2021, and 5 in the Year 2022. Participation in the conferences provides the following opportunities to the awardees.</p> <p>(1) Be exposed to the state-of-the-art research in the related disciplines.</p> <p>(2) Present their work to the research community at the main conference, doctoral symposium, and affiliated workshops.</p> <p>(3) Make contacts with fellow researchers through social activities.</p> <p>In addition to providing registration grants to US students, special sessions on professional training and career development were organized on topics of ethics, academic paper writing, seeking job in academia and industry. Following are the 5 presentations given in the special sessions.</p> <p>(1) "How to write a good paper?"</p> <p>(2) "How to land an academic job?"</p> <p>(3) "What do you need to prepare to secure a position in industry?"</p> <p>(4) "What ethics do you need to follow in your profession and your career?"</p> <p>(5) "IoT and Big Data technologies for context-driven applications."</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/31/2023<br>      Modified by: Miaoqing&nbsp;Huang</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The objective of this project is to financially support students from US institutions to attend the annual ACSOS (IEEE International Conference on Autonomic Computing and Self-Organizing Systems) conference from 2020 to 2022. Due to the COVID-19 pandemic, the ACSOS conferences were held as virtual events in these three years. Therefore, financial support was awarded to US students in the form of registration grants. Overall, 18 students from 12 US institutions received registration grants, 9 in the Year 2020, 4 in the Year 2021, and 5 in the Year 2022. Participation in the conferences provides the following opportunities to the awardees.  (1) Be exposed to the state-of-the-art research in the related disciplines.  (2) Present their work to the research community at the main conference, doctoral symposium, and affiliated workshops.  (3) Make contacts with fellow researchers through social activities.  In addition to providing registration grants to US students, special sessions on professional training and career development were organized on topics of ethics, academic paper writing, seeking job in academia and industry. Following are the 5 presentations given in the special sessions.  (1) "How to write a good paper?"  (2) "How to land an academic job?"  (3) "What do you need to prepare to secure a position in industry?"  (4) "What ethics do you need to follow in your profession and your career?"  (5) "IoT and Big Data technologies for context-driven applications."          Last Modified: 10/31/2023       Submitted by: Miaoqing Huang]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
