<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Building Credit Histories]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>325998.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>325998</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Nancy Lutz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>nlutz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927280</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The 2008 financial crisis, the preceding credit boom, and the subsequent credit contraction&lt;br/&gt;have highlighted the importance of access to credit for individual households for the health of the financial system and the economy. To guide policy proposals aimed at expanding access to credit for credit-worthy households, there is a need to know the forces behind the initiation and evolution of credit. This research project analyzes novel data and proposes a new theory to understand the behavior of emerging borrowers (borrowers who have only recently obtained their first line of credit or credit card) and their creditors. The empirical analysis documents new facts about how emerging borrowers expand their access to credit and how this process differs from the process for established borrowers. The project further develops a theoretical model of the interaction between borrowers and lenders. The theory provides guidance on policies aimed at expanding access to credit, such as allowing credit-reporting agencies to use non-traditional sources of information to assess the risk profiles of emerging borrowers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project uses a novel dataset obtained from a credit reporting agency, which allows for examination of the behavior of individual lines of credit (credit cards) for borrowers over time. The project documents the effects of opening a new credit line on a borrower’s relations with existing and future lenders. Opening a new credit card by a borrower seems to be interpreted by lenders as a positive news and is associated with an expansion of existing credit lines. This force is much more pronounced for emerging borrowers than for established ones. The theoretical part of the project offers a dynamic model with multiple competing lenders who have heterogeneous private information about a consumer’s creditworthiness. The model incorporates selection and signaling mechanisms present when credit records aggregate information across lenders. One implication of this model is that while additional credit dilutes the value of existing loans by raising default risk, borrowers that receive larger additional loans pose lower default risk to their incumbent lenders than those who receive smaller additional loans. This theoretical prediction is tested and supported by the data.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/24/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/28/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2019160</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Natalia</FirstName>
<LastName>Kovrijnykh</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Natalia Kovrijnykh</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[natalia.kovrijnykh@asu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000819067</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/24/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ariel</FirstName>
<LastName>Zetlin-Jones</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ariel Zetlin-Jones</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[azj@andrew.cmu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000819154</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/24/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Igor</FirstName>
<LastName>Livshits</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Igor Livshits</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[igor.livshits@phil.frb.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000852292</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/28/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Arizona State University</Name>
<CityName>TEMPE</CityName>
<ZipCode>852813670</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4809655479</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>660 S MILL AVENUE STE 204</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AZ04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NTLHJXM55KZ6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ARIZONA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[AZ Board of Regents on behalf of Arizona State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Tempe</CityName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>852876011</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[P.O. Box 876011]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AZ04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1320</Code>
<Text>Economics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1320</Code>
<Text>ECONOMICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~325998</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Access to credit is critical for socio-economic well-being, as it facilitates households' ability to withstand economic shocks and smooth consumption over time. An individual's access to credit is in large part determined by their credit history. But how does one start building a credit history?</p> <p>This research explores how emerging borrowers---those borrowers who have only recently obtained their first credit product---expand their credit access. Using new evidence on emerging borrowers, we show that the mere fact of an emerging borrower obtaining a loan plays an important role in building their credit history. Building a credit history through borrowing complements the conventional view of one's credit history reflecting past repayments.</p> <p>We document that incumbent lenders typically increase credit limits to borrowers who open additional credit cards, and that this increase is especially pronounced for emerging borrowers. Our interpretation of this finding is that lenders perceive credit offered by other lenders as revealing new, favorable information about the borrower. Motivated by our empirical observation, we develop a parsimonious model of credit-history building in which lenders have dispersed information about a borrower's creditworthiness. In the model, by accepting a loan, a borrower conveys information from one lender (whose loan they accept in an early stage) to other lenders. By building their credit history in this fashion, more creditworthy borrowers are able to obtain subsequent loans with better terms from other lenders.</p> <p>Similar to existing models with borrowing from multiple lenders, our model features debt dilution---taking an additional loan increases the probability of default on the initial loan. In contrast to the existing models, our theory generates a novel counterintuitive prediction that we refer to as "more dilution, lower default risk:" when the original lender faces uncertainty about how much his early loan will be diluted, he is actually <em>more </em>likely to be repaid when the borrower accepts a <em>larger </em>additional loan from another lender. This counterintuitive prediction is borne out in our data. We show that among <em>emerging </em>borrowers who open an additional credit card, their probability of future delinquency is <em>decreasing </em>in the size of their new card's credit limit, as our model predicts. At the same time, unconditionally, opening a new credit card increases the probability of future delinquency as in standard models of debt dilution. That is, our novel implication that more dilution is associated with a lower default risk coexists with the conventional one that dilution increases default risk, both in the model and in the data.</p> <p>Our model provides insights into welfare implications of publicly recording borrowers' credit histories. We show that availability of credit records does not necessarily make borrowers better off. Relatedly, more precise information---e.g., arising from an improvement in lenders' statistical models---is not always welfare improving.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/30/2023<br>      Modified by: Natalia&nbsp;Kovrijnykh</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Access to credit is critical for socio-economic well-being, as it facilitates households' ability to withstand economic shocks and smooth consumption over time. An individual's access to credit is in large part determined by their credit history. But how does one start building a credit history?  This research explores how emerging borrowers---those borrowers who have only recently obtained their first credit product---expand their credit access. Using new evidence on emerging borrowers, we show that the mere fact of an emerging borrower obtaining a loan plays an important role in building their credit history. Building a credit history through borrowing complements the conventional view of one's credit history reflecting past repayments.  We document that incumbent lenders typically increase credit limits to borrowers who open additional credit cards, and that this increase is especially pronounced for emerging borrowers. Our interpretation of this finding is that lenders perceive credit offered by other lenders as revealing new, favorable information about the borrower. Motivated by our empirical observation, we develop a parsimonious model of credit-history building in which lenders have dispersed information about a borrower's creditworthiness. In the model, by accepting a loan, a borrower conveys information from one lender (whose loan they accept in an early stage) to other lenders. By building their credit history in this fashion, more creditworthy borrowers are able to obtain subsequent loans with better terms from other lenders.  Similar to existing models with borrowing from multiple lenders, our model features debt dilution---taking an additional loan increases the probability of default on the initial loan. In contrast to the existing models, our theory generates a novel counterintuitive prediction that we refer to as "more dilution, lower default risk:" when the original lender faces uncertainty about how much his early loan will be diluted, he is actually more likely to be repaid when the borrower accepts a larger additional loan from another lender. This counterintuitive prediction is borne out in our data. We show that among emerging borrowers who open an additional credit card, their probability of future delinquency is decreasing in the size of their new card's credit limit, as our model predicts. At the same time, unconditionally, opening a new credit card increases the probability of future delinquency as in standard models of debt dilution. That is, our novel implication that more dilution is associated with a lower default risk coexists with the conventional one that dilution increases default risk, both in the model and in the data.  Our model provides insights into welfare implications of publicly recording borrowers' credit histories. We show that availability of credit records does not necessarily make borrowers better off. Relatedly, more precise information---e.g., arising from an improvement in lenders' statistical models---is not always welfare improving.          Last Modified: 08/30/2023       Submitted by: Natalia Kovrijnykh]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
