<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[CC* Networking Infrastructure: Research on the Hill]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>483522.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>483522</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OAC</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure (OAC)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kevin Thompson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kthompso@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924220</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Alabama Agricultural &amp; Mechanical University’s Research on the Hill Network (RotH Net) is a dedicated and frictionless network fabric to serve as a Science DMZ for multidisciplinary research programs. The RotH Net provides a secure digital workspace where researchers can compute, store, and share research data on a 10G connection to Internet2. This network fabric facilitates transfers of large datasets from projects serving multiple research labs. Data collected from Unmanned Aerial Systems (UAS) for scientists and farmers to evaluate crops at scale while simultaneously creating crop maps and large consistent datasets that were previously imaginable. Normalized Difference Vegetation Index images will prescribe fertilizer applications, estimate yields, and identify weeds. Other facilities dedicated to data-intensive science are enabled by the project, including research into Ion Accelerator Technology and Ion beam modification of materials.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The RotH Net includes a full set of science DMZ components serving to re-architect the campus border to support high performance science data flows across campus and external to the campus network. One additional component is the Open Storage Network (OSN) pod, a set of deployable units of distributed storage with minimal administrative overhead and petabyte-sized storage capable of high-throughput, and high-speed large volume data transfers. The OSN provides a cyberinfrastructure (CI) service to address specific data storage, transfer, sharing, and access, challenges. The project also supports a fiber extension connecting campus research facilities and paving the way for flexible growth in high performance research and education network connectivity.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/29/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/12/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2019080</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ernst</FirstName>
<LastName>Cebert</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ernst Cebert</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ernst.cebert@aamu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000111597</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/29/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Andrew</FirstName>
<LastName>Scott</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Andrew R Scott</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[andrew.scott@aamu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000396051</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/29/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jian</FirstName>
<LastName>Fu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jian Fu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jian.fu@aamu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000521629</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/29/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Damian</FirstName>
<LastName>Clarke</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Damian A Clarke</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[damian.clarke@aamu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000526374</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/29/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate>10/12/2021</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Raziq</FirstName>
<LastName>Yaqub</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Raziq Yaqub</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[raziq.yaqub@aamu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000742899</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/29/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate>10/12/2021</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Raziq</FirstName>
<LastName>Yaqub</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Raziq Yaqub</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[raziq.yaqub@aamu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000742899</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>10/12/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Alabama A&amp;M University</Name>
<CityName>NORMAL</CityName>
<ZipCode>357627500</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2563728186</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4900 MERIDIAN STREET NW</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Alabama</StateName>
<StateCode>AL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AL05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>JDVGS67MSLH7</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ALABAMA A &amp; M UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Alabama A&M University]]></Name>
<CityName>Huntsville</CityName>
<StateCode>AL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>358111000</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4900 Meridian Street N]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Alabama</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AL05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8080</Code>
<Text>Campus Cyberinfrastructure</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~483522</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>PROJECT OBJECTIVES</strong></p> <p>The project aimed to establish an inclusive research environment to encourage scholarly pursuits, with objectives to:</p> <p style="padding-left: 30px;">a. Facilitate engagement in research, innovation, discoveries, and creative ventures by faculty, students, and staff.</p> <p style="padding-left: 30px;">b. Establish infrastructure and training programs to foster a culture of research and creativity.</p> <p><strong>ACCOMPLISHMENTS:</strong></p> <p style="padding-left: 30px;">a) Completed Dark Fiber Installation in collaboration with Huntsville Utilities (HU): The project successfully installed dark fiber, linking AAMU's main campus to the AAMU Research Farm, located 9 miles away. This installation supports research activities, significantly boosting bandwidth and enabling data transmission to the Open Storage Node (OSN).</p> <p style="padding-left: 30px;">b) Procurement and Installation of an Open Storage Network (OSN) storage node: The acquisition and setup of the OSN node were completed. Vendor discussions ensured alignment with project requirements.</p> <p style="padding-left: 30px;">c) Acquisition of Network Switches for simulations: The project procured network switches for simulating extragalactic jets and real-time power grid and EV data. Product alignment with the project's network needs was successfully achieved through vendor meetings.</p> <p style="padding-left: 30px;">d) Purchase and implementation of a Data Transfer Node (DTN) and perfSONAR servers: Vendor meetings were conducted to understand product functionalities. The budget approval and implementation of DTN and perfSONAR are successfully accomplished.</p> <p>The primary goal was to enhance AAMU's Cyber Infrastructure (CI) for top-tier research outcomes, which was achieved through Dark Fiber and OSN installation, along with necessary equipment procurement and implementation.</p> <p>The Principal Investigator (PI) participated in two conferences for professional development: The 32nd International Conference on Computer Communications and Networks (ICCCN 2023) and The IEEE International Conference on Cloud Computing (CLOUD).</p> <p><strong>OPINION</strong></p> <ol> <li>Impact on Research Environment: The project's success in establishing an inclusive and forward-thinking research environment has been positively received. Faculty, students, and staff can now engage in research and innovative ventures, providing them with the tools and infrastructure necessary to foster a culture of creativity.</li> <li>Advancements in Cyber Infrastructure: The enhancement of AAMU's Cyber Infrastructure signifies a substantial step forward. The improved bandwidth and technology installations will allow for more sophisticated research endeavors, which, in turn, support scientific innovation and academic pursuits.</li> <li>Academic and Research Potential: The successful acquisition and installation of necessary hardware, such as the Open Storage Network (OSN) and Data Transfer Node (DTN), underscores the institution's commitment to providing cutting-edge resources for researchers, enabling them to explore and experiment with new technologies.</li> </ol> <p><strong>RECOMMENDATIONS</strong></p> <ol> <li>Sustained Support: To maintain and expand the achieved outcomes, additional funding may be needed. NSF&rsquo;s support will ensure the ongoing success of the infrastructure improvements and research capabilities established by the project. The PI also suggests funding allocations for the expansion or upgrades of cyberinfrastructure or technology systems to accommodate evolving research needs. This might include scaling up bandwidth, integrating new tools, or extending research infrastructure to other areas of study.</li> <li>Training and Skill Development Programs: The PI proposes funding for training programs that can help faculty, students, and staff maximize the potential of the enhanced infrastructure. This could involve workshops, courses, or certification programs focused on new technologies and research methodologies.</li> <li>Research Outreach Initiatives: The PI recommends financial support for organizing conferences, seminars, or symposiums that promote knowledge sharing and networking among researchers. Encouraging such forums can facilitate information exchange, collaboration, and the sharing of best practices.</li> </ol> <p>Submitted by&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>DR. RAZIQ YAQUB</strong></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/29/2023<br>      Modified by: Raziq&nbsp;Yaqub</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ PROJECT OBJECTIVES  The project aimed to establish an inclusive research environment to encourage scholarly pursuits, with objectives to: a. Facilitate engagement in research, innovation, discoveries, and creative ventures by faculty, students, and staff. b. Establish infrastructure and training programs to foster a culture of research and creativity.  ACCOMPLISHMENTS: a) Completed Dark Fiber Installation in collaboration with Huntsville Utilities (HU): The project successfully installed dark fiber, linking AAMU's main campus to the AAMU Research Farm, located 9 miles away. This installation supports research activities, significantly boosting bandwidth and enabling data transmission to the Open Storage Node (OSN). b) Procurement and Installation of an Open Storage Network (OSN) storage node: The acquisition and setup of the OSN node were completed. Vendor discussions ensured alignment with project requirements. c) Acquisition of Network Switches for simulations: The project procured network switches for simulating extragalactic jets and real-time power grid and EV data. Product alignment with the project's network needs was successfully achieved through vendor meetings. d) Purchase and implementation of a Data Transfer Node (DTN) and perfSONAR servers: Vendor meetings were conducted to understand product functionalities. The budget approval and implementation of DTN and perfSONAR are successfully accomplished.  The primary goal was to enhance AAMU's Cyber Infrastructure (CI) for top-tier research outcomes, which was achieved through Dark Fiber and OSN installation, along with necessary equipment procurement and implementation.  The Principal Investigator (PI) participated in two conferences for professional development: The 32nd International Conference on Computer Communications and Networks (ICCCN 2023) and The IEEE International Conference on Cloud Computing (CLOUD).  OPINION  Impact on Research Environment: The project's success in establishing an inclusive and forward-thinking research environment has been positively received. Faculty, students, and staff can now engage in research and innovative ventures, providing them with the tools and infrastructure necessary to foster a culture of creativity. Advancements in Cyber Infrastructure: The enhancement of AAMU's Cyber Infrastructure signifies a substantial step forward. The improved bandwidth and technology installations will allow for more sophisticated research endeavors, which, in turn, support scientific innovation and academic pursuits. Academic and Research Potential: The successful acquisition and installation of necessary hardware, such as the Open Storage Network (OSN) and Data Transfer Node (DTN), underscores the institution's commitment to providing cutting-edge resources for researchers, enabling them to explore and experiment with new technologies.   RECOMMENDATIONS  Sustained Support: To maintain and expand the achieved outcomes, additional funding may be needed. NSF’s support will ensure the ongoing success of the infrastructure improvements and research capabilities established by the project. The PI also suggests funding allocations for the expansion or upgrades of cyberinfrastructure or technology systems to accommodate evolving research needs. This might include scaling up bandwidth, integrating new tools, or extending research infrastructure to other areas of study. Training and Skill Development Programs: The PI proposes funding for training programs that can help faculty, students, and staff maximize the potential of the enhanced infrastructure. This could involve workshops, courses, or certification programs focused on new technologies and research methodologies. Research Outreach Initiatives: The PI recommends financial support for organizing conferences, seminars, or symposiums that promote knowledge sharing and networking among researchers. Encouraging such forums can facilitate information exchange, collaboration, and the sharing of best practices.   Submitted by   DR. RAZIQ YAQUB             Last Modified: 10/29/2023       Submitted by: Raziq Yaqub]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
