<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[The Inclusive Engineering Consortium Workshop &amp; travel support for Electrical &amp; Computer Engineering Department Heads Association (ECEDHA) Conference March 18-21, 2020, Orl]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>99975.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>99975</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EEC</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Engineering Education and Centers</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Christine Grant</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cgrant@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927107</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The Inclusive Engineering Consortium is a novel collaboration among the 15 accredited Electrical and Computer Engineering programs at the nation’s Historically Black Colleges and Universities and 2 Hispanic Serving Institutions. The overall Consortium vision is to be a collaboration of Minority Serving Institutions working as one to advance the Electrical and Computer Engineering enterprise. It is organized as a virtual multi-university super department with broadly based strengths in education, scholarship and service. Collectively, the Consortium can function as the equal of any Electrical and Computer Engineering program, accomplish more and have a greater impact on its students, faculty and staff through access to resources and opportunities not available to its members individually. Thus, the Consortium enables research and educational collaboration of teams from its partners working as peers with faculty, staff and students from the largest research-intensive universities in the United States.  A full-day workshop at the 2020 annual meeting of the Electrical and Computer Engineering Department Heads Association in Orlando, Florida, brings Consortium members together with academic leaders in Electrical and Computer Engineering throughout the country. This workshop is a major step in testing strategies developed within the Consortium to more fully and productively engage joint cross-institutional teams in the US education and research enterprise. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The majority of Inclusive Engineering Consortium members participated in the National Science Foundation-funded Experimental Centric Pedagogy project. Through this experience, Consortium member institutions have developed a culture of collaboration with effective methods of implementation. This initial collaboration is being leveraged and extended. The hypothesis is that there are windows of opportunity open through the establishment of research and educational collaborations between Consortium members with research-intensive institutions. This is especially true since its member institutions serve a unique population of minority students. The Consortium is developing the infrastructure and programs to facilitate collaborations between faculty, students and staff among its member departments based on lessons learned from the successful Experiment Centric Pedagogy educational program and, more generally, the science of team science. It is also addressing how best to build a different type of team structure with research-intensive universities, industry, and other external constituencies. Preparation for the workshop includes defining and refining a process and set of tools for successful collaboration with each type of partner, especially research-intensive universities. The workshop activities are structured to test the collaboration process and tools for research-intensive universities by actively engaging Consortium partner faculty with department heads from research-intensive universities and other faculty attending the Electrical and Computer Engineering Department Heads Association meeting. This is an important step in creating the organizational support structure and activities necessary to realize the Consortium’s grand vision of graduating more and better prepared minority engineers, increasing efficiency and productivity at Minority Serving Institutions, and developing a sustainable and effective infrastructure to support minority students, faculty and staff at all universities. In time, as the Consortium grows beyond the disciplines of Electrical and Computer Engineering, this model can be replicated and implemented for other areas of engineering education.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/28/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/28/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2019308</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ben</FirstName>
<LastName>Oni</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ben Oni</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[boni@tuskegee.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000707284</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/28/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Tuskegee University</Name>
<CityName>TUSKEGEE INSTITUTE</CityName>
<ZipCode>360881923</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3347278970</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1200 W MONTGOMERY RD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Alabama</StateName>
<StateCode>AL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AL03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>U9JCYEXFEEU4</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TUSKEGEE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Tuskegee University]]></Name>
<CityName>Tuskegee</CityName>
<StateCode>AL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>360881923</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1200 W. Montgomery Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Alabama</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AL03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7680</Code>
<Text>EDA-Eng Diversity Activities</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>110E</Code>
<Text>EDUCATION RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7680</Code>
<Text>ENG DIVERSITY ACTIVITIES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~99975</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Outcomes Report for Award Number </strong><strong>2019308</strong><strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p>The original goal of the project was to test ideas developed within the Inclusive Engineering Consortium (IEC) to engage joint IEC-R1 teams more fully and productively in the US education and research enterprise through a full-day workshop at the March 2020 annual meeting of the Electrical and Computer Engineering Department Heads Association (ECEDHA).</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Due to the disruptions and limitations caused by the COVID-19 pandemic, the in-person workshop planned for March 2020 was canceled and replaced by a series of ten online mini-workshops. In addition to sessions on collaborations with predominantly white institutions (PWIs), the list of topics for the mini-workshops was expanded in response to the COVID-19 emergency and the need to address social justice in engineering education. Additional topics included distance delivery of curriculum, teaming, best practices from industry, leadership for faculty and students, and anti-racism practice in engineering.</p> <p><br /> Ten online mini-workshop sessions were conducted, including three sessions on Anti-Racism Practice in Engineering: Exploring, Learning &amp; Solutions (ARPELS). The ARPELS workshop series was designed to nurture an understanding of how personal and institutional biases and inequitable practices affect underrepresented minority faculty and students in electrical and computer engineering and develop frameworks that help to counter them. Starting with IEC faculty and then extending to a wider audience, these sessions aimed to identify actionable steps to mitigate the effects of these biases in engineering education and facilitate collaboration across individuals and institutions in a way that leads to tangible change.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Specific objectives were set for the ten workshop sessions:</p> <ul> <li>IEC partners played a key role in helping position the overall ECE community to implement the type of online instruction necessitated by the COVID-19 pandemic through their Experiment Centric Pedagogy (ECP) project.&nbsp; To sustain its robust collaborative community during these difficult times, three of the mini-workshop sessions were dedicated to the impact of COVID on teaching and student mentoring. These sessions were also offered to better enable IEC faculty to participate in online meetings with their counterparts from all engineering disciplines and universities because they had already shared their ideas, problems, concerns, etc., among themselves. This was particularly useful for online workshops and summits presented by ECEDHA.&nbsp;</li> <li>Addressing the original workshop objective of building understanding on IEC-PWI collaborations, there were two sessions that focused on the experiences of minority faculty and/or faculty from Minority Serving Institutions.&nbsp;</li> <li>The original in-person workshop also had activities built on the Science of Team Science, to enable collaborators to work together better as teams. About a month prior to the scheduled ECEDHA meeting, IEC invited Professor Russ Korte of George Washington University to present an Overview of Team Science. Professor Korte led two online workshop sessions on this topic.</li> <li>The ARPELS workshop series had the additional objective of creating shared understanding and promote the development of anti-racist practices and skills that can be applied at IEC institutions and PWIs (e.g., metrics, initiatives, partnerships).</li> </ul> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Given the objectives described above, the project delivered the following results:</p> <ul> <li>Teaching and Learning During COVID - The experiences of faculty and students during this difficult period were documented through a related RAPID grant (NSF Award #2031717), which was introduced to the IEC community at the first of the three sessions on this general topic.&nbsp;Beginning with a session on sharing online teaching experiences, the sessions in this area addressed reopening plans for Fall 2020 and the transition to online of a Summer 2020 Mega REU/RET program.</li> <li>IEC-PWI Collaborations ? Two sessions addressed this topic. The first covered IEC-R1 collaborations from the viewpoint of HBCUs and HSIs and featured IEC faculty who had previously participated in large-scale research collaborations within NSF Engineering Research Centers at the hosting R1 institutions. The second session on minority faculty experiences at R1 Institutions invited six African American ECE faculty from PWIs to share their career experiences. </li> <li>Team Science ? The first session of this two-part workshop provided a means for faculty to begin to understand and practice some of the concepts of team science through topics of common interest. The second session demonstrated how faculty can work together, share ideas, and suggest innovative, possible solutions to problems that can be better addressed with collaboration among several institutions rather than a single one, given topics of mutual interest and an avenue to do so.</li> <li>Anti-Racism (ARPELS) Workshop Series - The discussions that were part of each workshop showed that a key issue that must be addressed, in part because it is so uncomfortable for most organizations, is what constitutes good practice in anti-racism. The workshop sessions explored the role IEC can play in developing and promoting anti-racist practices in engineering education.&nbsp;</li> </ul> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/29/2022<br>      Modified by: Ben&nbsp;Oni</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Outcomes Report for Award Number 2019308      The original goal of the project was to test ideas developed within the Inclusive Engineering Consortium (IEC) to engage joint IEC-R1 teams more fully and productively in the US education and research enterprise through a full-day workshop at the March 2020 annual meeting of the Electrical and Computer Engineering Department Heads Association (ECEDHA).     Due to the disruptions and limitations caused by the COVID-19 pandemic, the in-person workshop planned for March 2020 was canceled and replaced by a series of ten online mini-workshops. In addition to sessions on collaborations with predominantly white institutions (PWIs), the list of topics for the mini-workshops was expanded in response to the COVID-19 emergency and the need to address social justice in engineering education. Additional topics included distance delivery of curriculum, teaming, best practices from industry, leadership for faculty and students, and anti-racism practice in engineering.    Ten online mini-workshop sessions were conducted, including three sessions on Anti-Racism Practice in Engineering: Exploring, Learning &amp; Solutions (ARPELS). The ARPELS workshop series was designed to nurture an understanding of how personal and institutional biases and inequitable practices affect underrepresented minority faculty and students in electrical and computer engineering and develop frameworks that help to counter them. Starting with IEC faculty and then extending to a wider audience, these sessions aimed to identify actionable steps to mitigate the effects of these biases in engineering education and facilitate collaboration across individuals and institutions in a way that leads to tangible change.     Specific objectives were set for the ten workshop sessions:  IEC partners played a key role in helping position the overall ECE community to implement the type of online instruction necessitated by the COVID-19 pandemic through their Experiment Centric Pedagogy (ECP) project.  To sustain its robust collaborative community during these difficult times, three of the mini-workshop sessions were dedicated to the impact of COVID on teaching and student mentoring. These sessions were also offered to better enable IEC faculty to participate in online meetings with their counterparts from all engineering disciplines and universities because they had already shared their ideas, problems, concerns, etc., among themselves. This was particularly useful for online workshops and summits presented by ECEDHA.  Addressing the original workshop objective of building understanding on IEC-PWI collaborations, there were two sessions that focused on the experiences of minority faculty and/or faculty from Minority Serving Institutions.  The original in-person workshop also had activities built on the Science of Team Science, to enable collaborators to work together better as teams. About a month prior to the scheduled ECEDHA meeting, IEC invited Professor Russ Korte of George Washington University to present an Overview of Team Science. Professor Korte led two online workshop sessions on this topic. The ARPELS workshop series had the additional objective of creating shared understanding and promote the development of anti-racist practices and skills that can be applied at IEC institutions and PWIs (e.g., metrics, initiatives, partnerships).      Given the objectives described above, the project delivered the following results:  Teaching and Learning During COVID - The experiences of faculty and students during this difficult period were documented through a related RAPID grant (NSF Award #2031717), which was introduced to the IEC community at the first of the three sessions on this general topic. Beginning with a session on sharing online teaching experiences, the sessions in this area addressed reopening plans for Fall 2020 and the transition to online of a Summer 2020 Mega REU/RET program. IEC-PWI Collaborations ? Two sessions addressed this topic. The first covered IEC-R1 collaborations from the viewpoint of HBCUs and HSIs and featured IEC faculty who had previously participated in large-scale research collaborations within NSF Engineering Research Centers at the hosting R1 institutions. The second session on minority faculty experiences at R1 Institutions invited six African American ECE faculty from PWIs to share their career experiences.  Team Science ? The first session of this two-part workshop provided a means for faculty to begin to understand and practice some of the concepts of team science through topics of common interest. The second session demonstrated how faculty can work together, share ideas, and suggest innovative, possible solutions to problems that can be better addressed with collaboration among several institutions rather than a single one, given topics of mutual interest and an avenue to do so. Anti-Racism (ARPELS) Workshop Series - The discussions that were part of each workshop showed that a key issue that must be addressed, in part because it is so uncomfortable for most organizations, is what constitutes good practice in anti-racism. The workshop sessions explored the role IEC can play in developing and promoting anti-racist practices in engineering education.               Last Modified: 06/29/2022       Submitted by: Ben Oni]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
