<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Doctoral Dissertation Research in Economics: Improved Public Primary Healthcare and Informal Provider Responses]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>31500.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>31500</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kwabena Gyimah-Brempong</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kgyimahb@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927466</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Understanding the response of those not directly affected by policy changes is a central part of economic science.  This award funds a research on how informal providers respond to major public health care reforms. The research uses modern research methods to study how other suppliers respond to changes in public health policies with particular focus on primary health care.  Particularly, the research focuses on how the policy change affects the quality and quantity of services provided by informal healthcare providers.  This allows researchers to measure the total direct and indirect effects of the policy changes on both suppliers and consumers of health care, especially those with low incomes who are more likely to use informal health care services. The research will use surveys to collect rich data on patient, provider, and households for the analyses.  The focus of the research will be on the mechanisms through which the policy changes affect providers that are not directly affected by the policy change.   The results of this research project can provide important inputs into policies that improve access to better healthcare for low income people, hence improve their health.  The research results are applicable to other parts of the world, hence establish the US as the global leader in health care reform.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research project will use survey data to estimate a structural model of demand and informal provider behavior to assess the direct and indirect welfare effects of improved public healthcare provision.  The project makes three contributions to the literature. First, it exploits the opportunity to collect an extensive set of survey data before and after a large public health reform to analyze the effects of improved public healthcare on patient outcomes in a low income environment. Second, the project constructs a structural model of informal provider behavior that accounts for price and quality decisions. Third, it uses a novel combination of standardized patients and provider and household data to identify the key parameters of the model. Taken together, this framework allows the researchers to examine the general equilibrium effects of improved public primary healthcare and inform the design and evaluation of future public health reforms.  The research results are applicable to other parts of the world, hence establish the US as the global leader in health care reform.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/22/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/22/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2019071</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Janet</FirstName>
<LastName>Currie</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Janet Currie</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jcurrie@princeton.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000131704</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/22/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Patrick</FirstName>
<LastName>Agte</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Patrick Agte</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[pagte@princeton.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000795690</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/22/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Princeton University</Name>
<CityName>PRINCETON</CityName>
<ZipCode>085442001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6092583090</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1 NASSAU HALL</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NJ12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NJ1YPQXQG7U5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>THE TRUSTEES OF PRINCETON UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Princeton University]]></Name>
<CityName>Princeton</CityName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>085442020</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Off. of Research & Proj. Admin.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NJ12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1320</Code>
<Text>Economics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~31500</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Supply-side responses to public health reforms can have important welfare effects. Accounting for the behavior of informal providers is especially important in the healthcare sector in low- and middle-income countries which are characterized by high rates of informal healthcare utilization and low provider quality. This study aims to examine this channel in the context of a large public healthcare reform in rural India. As part of the reform, &#65279;public subcenters, the lowest tier in India&rsquo;s public healthcare system, are upgraded to basic outpatient care facilities by adding a new semi-skilled healthcare worker.</p> <p>We collaborate with the Government of Rajasthan to exploit the staggered rollout of the upgrades using a difference-in-difference design. We examine the impact of the reform on health-related outcomes and quantify how much of the overall welfare effect is driven by changes in prices and quality of informal providers. At this point, we completed baseline surveys with public and private providers and households to measure prices, healthcare quality, and market shares. Our baseline results document the need for the reform: out-of-pocket spending is high, public primary healthcare utilization is low, and informal providers have high profit margins. However, we also document gaps in infrastructure availability, which could limit the effects of the reform.</p> <p>Around half of our sample facilities have received the semi-skilled healthcare workers in May 2022. We argue that the ad-hoc decisions by local officials led to quasi-random variation in the rollout decisions. Consistent with this argument, we document that treatment and control areas have similar levels and trends in terms of monthly patient load and prenatal care visits according to administrative data. We will conduct the endline surveys in spring 2023 measure changes in main outcomes.</p> <p>We expect the study will contribute to the design and evaluation of public health reforms. Many low- and middle-income countries have similar public healthcare systems to India and also experience high rates of informal healthcare utilization. Examining whether the provision of basic outpatient care can be moved effectively to the lowest tier in the public healthcare system can have important lessons for India and other countries. Our study further emphasizes the importance of considering market responses when evaluating the effect of such policies.&nbsp; For example, patients who stick with informal providers might still benefit from the reform if informal providers lower their prices or increase their quality in response to an improved public healthcare option in the market. We will work closely together with the state government of Rajasthan to disseminate the results to other public officials. Information on provider choices can also inform the design of future policies.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/08/2022<br>      Modified by: Patrick&nbsp;Agte</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Supply-side responses to public health reforms can have important welfare effects. Accounting for the behavior of informal providers is especially important in the healthcare sector in low- and middle-income countries which are characterized by high rates of informal healthcare utilization and low provider quality. This study aims to examine this channel in the context of a large public healthcare reform in rural India. As part of the reform, &#65279;public subcenters, the lowest tier in India’s public healthcare system, are upgraded to basic outpatient care facilities by adding a new semi-skilled healthcare worker.  We collaborate with the Government of Rajasthan to exploit the staggered rollout of the upgrades using a difference-in-difference design. We examine the impact of the reform on health-related outcomes and quantify how much of the overall welfare effect is driven by changes in prices and quality of informal providers. At this point, we completed baseline surveys with public and private providers and households to measure prices, healthcare quality, and market shares. Our baseline results document the need for the reform: out-of-pocket spending is high, public primary healthcare utilization is low, and informal providers have high profit margins. However, we also document gaps in infrastructure availability, which could limit the effects of the reform.  Around half of our sample facilities have received the semi-skilled healthcare workers in May 2022. We argue that the ad-hoc decisions by local officials led to quasi-random variation in the rollout decisions. Consistent with this argument, we document that treatment and control areas have similar levels and trends in terms of monthly patient load and prenatal care visits according to administrative data. We will conduct the endline surveys in spring 2023 measure changes in main outcomes.  We expect the study will contribute to the design and evaluation of public health reforms. Many low- and middle-income countries have similar public healthcare systems to India and also experience high rates of informal healthcare utilization. Examining whether the provision of basic outpatient care can be moved effectively to the lowest tier in the public healthcare system can have important lessons for India and other countries. Our study further emphasizes the importance of considering market responses when evaluating the effect of such policies.  For example, patients who stick with informal providers might still benefit from the reform if informal providers lower their prices or increase their quality in response to an improved public healthcare option in the market. We will work closely together with the state government of Rajasthan to disseminate the results to other public officials. Information on provider choices can also inform the design of future policies.             Last Modified: 08/08/2022       Submitted by: Patrick Agte]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
