<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[MRI: Development of A Magneto-Optical Spectroscopy System for Investigation of Spintronic and Quantum Materials]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>642485.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>642485</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Z.  Ying</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cying@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928428</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Nontechnical Description:&lt;br/&gt;Many technological breakthroughs are enabled by the discovery of new materials. Once new materials are synthesized, their new properties and potential applications are revealed via careful and advanced characterization measurements. This project funds the development of a unique optical characterization instrument to study a wide range of quantum materials and magnetic materials. The instrument enables multiple types of measurements of light-matter interaction at the same area of samples placed in a magnetic field and at low temperatures. Both linear light-matter interactions and nonlinear interactions, when two light photons are combined to a single photon, are studied. Researchers use the instrument to investigate atomically thin materials, with the thickness of the layers or films only one atom or a few atoms, and materials with a large number of tiny magnets in them. These materials could potentially be used to build memory devices for storing a large amount of data in the information age of the future. In addition to building the instrument in an experimental facility, the team develops courses and training materials for students and users. These students will become the future workforce in the scientific and technological sectors and contribute to building a globally competitive economy.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical Description:&lt;br/&gt;The team develops a magneto-optical spectroscopy system to promote and advance studies of spintronic and quantum materials in the state of Texas and beyond. The key instrument includes (i) a closed-cycle magneto-optical cryostat; (ii) high-resolution spectrometers for inelastic light scattering (Raman and Brillouin scattering) as well as magneto-optical Kerr effect and second harmonic generation; (iii) a custom-made sample handling system so that one can change samples without warming up the cryostat to improve the efficiency of the operation. The instrument facilitates the discoveries and fundamental understanding of magnetic and quantum materials. Examples of materials to be investigated include van der Waals heterostructures consisting of transition metal dichalcogenides, topological materials with long-range magnetic order and superconductors. By performing several spectroscopy measurements on the same sample, one may gain comprehensive information that is difficult to obtain otherwise. The fundamental understanding of spintronic and quantum materials will have a broad impact on information storage and processing technologies.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/09/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/07/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2019130</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Xiaoqin</FirstName>
<LastName>Li</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Xiaoqin Li</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[elaineli@physics.utexas.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000325774</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/09/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jean Anne</FirstName>
<LastName>Incorvia</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jean Anne C Incorvia</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[incorvia@austin.utexas.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000767215</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/09/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Texas at Austin</Name>
<CityName>AUSTIN</CityName>
<ZipCode>787121139</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5124716424</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>110 INNER CAMPUS DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>25</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX25</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>V6AFQPN18437</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT AUSTIN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>X5NKD2NFF2V3</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[The University of Texas at Austin]]></Name>
<CityName>Austin</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>787121192</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2515 speedway]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>25</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX25</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>Major Research Instrumentation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7697</Code>
<Text>INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8990</Code>
<Text>Optics and Photonics</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~642485</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
