<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[I-Corps:  Polymer-free durable carbon nanotube (CNT) film membrane]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ruth Shuman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rshuman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922160</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this I-Corps project is to investigate applications of polymer-free carbon nanotube (CNT) membrane filters. Membranes currently in commercial use are predominantly made of polymer materials but suffer frequently from membrane clogging and surface fouling.  The membrane fouling problem is further exacerbated in certain bioprocessing applications. Polymer-free CNT sheet membranes are strong and chemically robust even at extreme temperatures.  They resist surface fouling and are uniquely suited for bioprocessing applications such as removing bacteria and viruses from solutions for sterilization; and harvesting cells, vaccines and monoclonal antibodies. Because of these unique properties, polymer-free CNT sheet membranes have the potential to greatly accelerate vaccine development and drastically lower the cost of biopharmaceutical production, making them more available, accessible, and affordable for patients.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project is to explore the translation of polymer-free membranes. Polymer membranes widely in use today suffer from membrane surface fouling, polymer degradation and poor resistance to organic solvents, chemicals and elevated temperature. Although CNT has long been recognized as well suited for this application due to its chemical stability, its hydrophobic nature has hindered efforts to make CNT membrane filters without the use of polymer binders. Available CNT/polymer composite membrane filters do not meet the stringent application requirements, i.e., high flux rate, chemical stability, mechanical stability, and fouling resistance. This technology provides an efficient purification method to render highly uniform CNTs with clean nanotube structure. Such purification is critical for subsequent processes to densify and fortify CNT sheet membranes to produce the desired pore size and mechanical strength in the absence of any polymer binder. This project will investigate the technical specifications of a polymer-free CNT membrane filter for bioprocessing.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/08/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/08/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2020016</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dan</FirstName>
<LastName>Freeman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Dan Freeman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[freemand@udel.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000647835</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/08/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Delaware</Name>
<CityName>NEWARK</CityName>
<ZipCode>197160099</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3028312136</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>220 HULLIHEN HALL</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Delaware</StateName>
<StateCode>DE</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DE00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>T72NHKM259N3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF DELAWARE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>T72NHKM259N3</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Delaware]]></Name>
<CityName>Newark</CityName>
<StateCode>DE</StateCode>
<ZipCode>197160099</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[210 Hullihen Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Delaware</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DE00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>NSF I-Corps Teams grant 2020016 enabled the 4<sup>th</sup> Phase Water Technologies team to conduct over 200 interviews and follow-up meetings with potential customers from March 31, 2020 to May 31, 2022. The potential customers include scientists/engineers, CEOs and CTOs from aerospace and defense industry, semiconductor industry, specialty chemical manufacturing companies, bioprocessing and biopharmaceutical companies, aquaculture and membrane R&amp;D managers.</p> <p>With multiple pivots, these interviews have resulted in unique value propositions for densified carbon nanotube (DCN) film membrane in three major market segments: 1) DCN membrane as a durable, fouling-resistant, universally compatible, smart filtration membrane; 2) DCN membrane as lightweight, durable and superior electromagnetic interference (EMI) shielding; 3) DCN membrane as lightweight, strong and durable structural component in aerospace and defense industry.</p> <p>There is strong demand for fouling-resistant, universally compatible filtration membranes to replace plastic filtration membranes, especially in the ?small volume high value? filtration applications. DCN membranes meet these stringent requirements in filtration with hydrophilicity, high chemical and structural stability and extreme temperature tolerance. In addition, DCN membranes have great potential in aerospace and defense industry due to their exceptional strength, ductility, lightweight (80% lighter than steel) and high conductivity.</p> <p>This project has led to the following key outcomes:</p> <p>1) a partnership agreement with O?Pake Institute at Alvernia University to leverage their expertise in semiconductor chip manufacturing and their resources in market outreach and technology licensing;</p> <p>2) a non-disclosure agreement and material transfer agreement with Entegris, Inc.--- a leader in contamination control for semiconductor industry;</p> <p>3) a licensing agreement with Hydrenesis, Inc. on the use of DCN membrane as structural component in aerospace and defense industry.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/03/2023<br>      Modified by: Dan&nbsp;Freeman</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ NSF I-Corps Teams grant 2020016 enabled the 4th Phase Water Technologies team to conduct over 200 interviews and follow-up meetings with potential customers from March 31, 2020 to May 31, 2022. The potential customers include scientists/engineers, CEOs and CTOs from aerospace and defense industry, semiconductor industry, specialty chemical manufacturing companies, bioprocessing and biopharmaceutical companies, aquaculture and membrane R&amp;D managers.  With multiple pivots, these interviews have resulted in unique value propositions for densified carbon nanotube (DCN) film membrane in three major market segments: 1) DCN membrane as a durable, fouling-resistant, universally compatible, smart filtration membrane; 2) DCN membrane as lightweight, durable and superior electromagnetic interference (EMI) shielding; 3) DCN membrane as lightweight, strong and durable structural component in aerospace and defense industry.  There is strong demand for fouling-resistant, universally compatible filtration membranes to replace plastic filtration membranes, especially in the ?small volume high value? filtration applications. DCN membranes meet these stringent requirements in filtration with hydrophilicity, high chemical and structural stability and extreme temperature tolerance. In addition, DCN membranes have great potential in aerospace and defense industry due to their exceptional strength, ductility, lightweight (80% lighter than steel) and high conductivity.  This project has led to the following key outcomes:  1) a partnership agreement with O?Pake Institute at Alvernia University to leverage their expertise in semiconductor chip manufacturing and their resources in market outreach and technology licensing;  2) a non-disclosure agreement and material transfer agreement with Entegris, Inc.--- a leader in contamination control for semiconductor industry;  3) a licensing agreement with Hydrenesis, Inc. on the use of DCN membrane as structural component in aerospace and defense industry.          Last Modified: 01/03/2023       Submitted by: Dan Freeman]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
