<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Suicide and Technology for War (Scholars Award)]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>38497.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>38497</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Christine Leuenberger</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cleuenbe@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927563</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Suicide warfare—a timely topic in post-9/11 world— has occupied important space around the world, especially since the twentieth century. Internationally comparative in scope, this project explores the ethics of engineering for homeland security. In any country at war, it may be rational to act in what appears to be an irrational matter, and suicide missions are a key instance of this phenomenon. Suicide warfare for homeland defense, albeit against enemy forces, first requires human sacrifice, thus raising far more ethical issues than technological ones. Focusing on engineering communities in two nations that used suicide as a form or warfare, the project aims to answer a set of inter-related questions: (1) How and why did engineers support organized suicide attacks for homeland defense? (2) How was the moral sensitivity of peacetime reduced to support the desperate act as evil but necessary? (3) At what cost (and to whom) does society in war benefit from a given engineering project? and, (4) What are the acceptable costs of suicide as a technology acceptable for national defense? Project results will be used to create educational materials, public presentations, and publications in popular outlets.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project uses historical methods to analyze the period from 1914 to 1961, during which World War I, World War II, and the Cold War each elevated the importance of patriotic self-sacrifice for national causes. Critical analyses of these materials enable a series of comparisons of social practices and technological dimensions by which different nations created their versions of suicide warfare in the air by actively shaping the notions of suicide for homeland defense. Popular literature, posters, government publications, and more are used to uncover the socio-technological context in which suicide warfare in the air took shape, and how and why this differed across social contexts. Overall, this project contributes to scholarship on engineering ethics, the history of technology, and Science and Technology Studies.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/18/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/20/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2020976</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Takashi</FirstName>
<LastName>Nishiyama</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Takashi Nishiyama</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[tnishiya@brockport.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000591387</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/18/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>SUNY College at Brockport</Name>
<CityName>BROCKPORT</CityName>
<ZipCode>144202997</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5853952444</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>350 NEW CAMPUS DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>25</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY25</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>TCMMHB95V224</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>THE RESEARCH FOUNDATION FOR THE STATE UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[The Research Foundation (SUNY) at The College at Brockport]]></Name>
<CityName>Brockport</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>144202932</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[350 New Campus Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>25</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY25</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>129Y</Code>
<Text>ER2-Ethical &amp; Responsible Res</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~38497</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This NSF project examines the disparity between actual suicide warfare in the air (as executed by Kamikaze pilots and others) and misconceptions of it. The history of technology helps to solve this puzzle. My study historicizes warfare in the air to understand how it had taken shape during the twentieth century and why it remains misrepresented in the United States. It focuses on the period from 1941 to 1956 and, more broadly, from 1914 to 1961, during which World War I, World War II, and the Cold War each elevated the importance of patriotic self-sacrifice for national causes. This original, comparative research on a controversial issue seeks to better promote responsible research and development in the twenty-first century.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Key findings from my archival research are as follows. During World War II, the Soviet Union (1941&ndash;45), followed by Nazi Germany (1943&ndash;45) and kamikaze Japan (1944&ndash;45), each launched suicide ramming attacks in and from the air. The United States, however, entertained only skewed, highly motivated images filtered by geopolitics, media censorship and leaks, racist propaganda, geographical distance, leadership, and timing of key events of the war. In the early years of the Cold War, by (mis)appropriating the wartime experiences and technologies of Germany and Japan, the U.S. military actively reshaped notions of &ldquo;suicide&rdquo; for homeland defense. The goal was to counter potential Soviet nuclear air attacks through premeditated suicide ramming. The Japanese kamikaze of World War II provided a useful point of reference. The media, engineers, and pilots were mobilized in reshaping the notion of patriotism and suicide for a national cause.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>As for intellectual merits, my research aims to reconceptualize suicide actions as acts not only of individual pilots, but also of an organized warfare technological system that uses conventional resources (such as nation-state, R&amp;D centers, patriotism, and media) in response to aspects of war that seem irrational. In so doing, my study complicates our (mis)understandings of &ldquo;suicide warfare&rdquo; by analyzing how they were disputed, negotiated, and compromised in the United States at times of war. By analyzing the making of the notions of &ldquo;suicide,&rdquo; my in-depth study of Japan and America in wartime&mdash;with references to Germany and the Soviet Union&mdash;adds another dimension to our existing scholarship in war studies. In so doing, I ask our academic communities to be more inclusive of culturally nuanced, empirically based explorations of human experiences of suicide warfare across national borders.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>This study carries a broad impact beyond academe by breaking down common&nbsp;</p> <p>national/cultural stereotypes by historicizing them. More specifically, my research does so by examining the context and content of suicide warfare, a timely topic of global importance today in our post 9/11 world. My work seeks to dismantle stubborn stereotypes in the wider public domain by exposing the futility of the prevalent West/non-West dichotomy. The idea that the world is divided into the West and the non-West is a misconception&mdash;one that profoundly impacts our understanding of past, present, and future events. With focus on Japan (and the Soviet Union), my transnational history of suicide warfare highlights a certain commonality in humanity, moving beyond this false dichotomy. Japan and the United States&mdash;as well as Germany and to a lesser extent, the Soviet Union&mdash;all shared a transnational experience: a desperation that led them to resort to a similar solution that entailed premeditated suicide ramming attacks, albeit for different reasons. My research shows that thoughts and actions associated with suicide warfare were far more common in the twentieth century than is commonly recognized. World wars provided grounds for ideas among warring nations (Western and non-Western alike) about how to defend the homeland. It is through this lens that I like to lead the effort in society toward less othering of the &ldquo;non-Western&rdquo; peoples behind suicide missions, highlighting how people think and what they do and why&mdash;beyond the binary construct. This study thus broadens societal views about different ways of doing the same thing (i.e. homeland defense) in the world, raising awareness in the United States and elsewhere about life-and-death issues.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/03/2023<br>      Modified by: Takashi&nbsp;Nishiyama</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This NSF project examines the disparity between actual suicide warfare in the air (as executed by Kamikaze pilots and others) and misconceptions of it. The history of technology helps to solve this puzzle. My study historicizes warfare in the air to understand how it had taken shape during the twentieth century and why it remains misrepresented in the United States. It focuses on the period from 1941 to 1956 and, more broadly, from 1914 to 1961, during which World War I, World War II, and the Cold War each elevated the importance of patriotic self-sacrifice for national causes. This original, comparative research on a controversial issue seeks to better promote responsible research and development in the twenty-first century.      Key findings from my archival research are as follows. During World War II, the Soviet Union (1941&ndash;45), followed by Nazi Germany (1943&ndash;45) and kamikaze Japan (1944&ndash;45), each launched suicide ramming attacks in and from the air. The United States, however, entertained only skewed, highly motivated images filtered by geopolitics, media censorship and leaks, racist propaganda, geographical distance, leadership, and timing of key events of the war. In the early years of the Cold War, by (mis)appropriating the wartime experiences and technologies of Germany and Japan, the U.S. military actively reshaped notions of "suicide" for homeland defense. The goal was to counter potential Soviet nuclear air attacks through premeditated suicide ramming. The Japanese kamikaze of World War II provided a useful point of reference. The media, engineers, and pilots were mobilized in reshaping the notion of patriotism and suicide for a national cause.      As for intellectual merits, my research aims to reconceptualize suicide actions as acts not only of individual pilots, but also of an organized warfare technological system that uses conventional resources (such as nation-state, R&amp;D centers, patriotism, and media) in response to aspects of war that seem irrational. In so doing, my study complicates our (mis)understandings of "suicide warfare" by analyzing how they were disputed, negotiated, and compromised in the United States at times of war. By analyzing the making of the notions of "suicide," my in-depth study of Japan and America in wartime&mdash;with references to Germany and the Soviet Union&mdash;adds another dimension to our existing scholarship in war studies. In so doing, I ask our academic communities to be more inclusive of culturally nuanced, empirically based explorations of human experiences of suicide warfare across national borders.     This study carries a broad impact beyond academe by breaking down common   national/cultural stereotypes by historicizing them. More specifically, my research does so by examining the context and content of suicide warfare, a timely topic of global importance today in our post 9/11 world. My work seeks to dismantle stubborn stereotypes in the wider public domain by exposing the futility of the prevalent West/non-West dichotomy. The idea that the world is divided into the West and the non-West is a misconception&mdash;one that profoundly impacts our understanding of past, present, and future events. With focus on Japan (and the Soviet Union), my transnational history of suicide warfare highlights a certain commonality in humanity, moving beyond this false dichotomy. Japan and the United States&mdash;as well as Germany and to a lesser extent, the Soviet Union&mdash;all shared a transnational experience: a desperation that led them to resort to a similar solution that entailed premeditated suicide ramming attacks, albeit for different reasons. My research shows that thoughts and actions associated with suicide warfare were far more common in the twentieth century than is commonly recognized. World wars provided grounds for ideas among warring nations (Western and non-Western alike) about how to defend the homeland. It is through this lens that I like to lead the effort in society toward less othering of the "non-Western" peoples behind suicide missions, highlighting how people think and what they do and why&mdash;beyond the binary construct. This study thus broadens societal views about different ways of doing the same thing (i.e. homeland defense) in the world, raising awareness in the United States and elsewhere about life-and-death issues.                   Last Modified: 05/03/2023       Submitted by: Takashi Nishiyama]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
