<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Doctoral Dissertation Research: Social and environmental drivers of dengue risk across urban landscapes]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>17999.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>17999</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jeffrey Mantz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jmantz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927783</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This project investigates the social and environmental conditions in cities that contribute to mosquito-borne diseases such as dengue. This work is motivated by the dramatic rates of urbanization seen across the world, and the complex role that urban environments play in maintaining mosquito populations and driving disease transmission. Despite the public health importance of dengue, there is little known about how factors such as city structure, human population density, and human behaviors come together to affect disease risk. To examine these factors, these scientists will gather information from diverse sources such as public health records, household mosquito collections, satellite imagery, and community-based conversations. On-the-ground work will be conducted in an urban environment that has a high incidence of dengue. This work is part of a collaboration with the local health department, so that findings will support ongoing disease prevention strategies. As a Doctoral Dissertation Research Improvement award, this project will provide support to enable a promising student to establish an independent research career.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;There are no widely-available vaccines or effective treatment options for dengue. Therefore, disease prevention is centered around controlling mosquito populations. The scientists propose that to effectively control mosquito populations and disease transmission, there must be a greater understanding of the social and environmental dynamics in cities that affect mosquito ecology, human exposure to mosquitoes, and virus transmission. This project asks (1) what factors drive differences in rates of dengue across cities; (2) how does dengue risk vary within a city, based on the interactions between every-day human behaviors and social and environmental conditions; and (3) how will improvements to public services and environmental conditions affect rates of dengue in a city? These efforts will contribute to an inter-disciplinary framework for studying urban mosquito-borne diseases, grounded in spatial sciences. The work will also result in disease modeling tools that can be used to plan public health interventions in growing cities around the world.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/18/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/20/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2020853</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Maria</FirstName>
<LastName>Diuk-Wasser</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Maria Diuk-Wasser</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mad2256@columbia.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000535119</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/18/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Pallavi</FirstName>
<LastName>Kache</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Pallavi A Kache</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[pak2136@columbia.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000813661</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/18/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Columbia University</Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<ZipCode>10027</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2128546851</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>202 LOW LIBRARY 535 W 116 ST MC</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>F4N1QNPB95M4</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF COLUMBIA UNIVERSITY IN THE CITY OF NEW YORK, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>F4N1QNPB95M4</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Columbia University]]></Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>100276902</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2960 Broadway]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8857</Code>
<Text>Geography &amp; Spatial Sci-DDRI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1352</Code>
<Text>GEOGRAPHY AND SPATIAL SCIENCES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~17999</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The rise of vector-borne diseases transmitted by the&nbsp;<em>Aedes&nbsp;</em>spp. mosquitoes is attributed, in part, to the dramatic rates of contemporary urbanization. Over the past 30 years, scientists have developed a wealth of knowledge around the drivers of heterogeneity in&nbsp;<em>Aedes</em>-borne disease risk within and between cities. However, in current&nbsp;<em>Aedes</em>-borne disease research<em>,&nbsp;</em>characterizations of ?urban? are oversimplified, with the built environment and social institutions of the city often relegated to a background context. To mitigate the spread of&nbsp;<em>Aedes</em>-borne diseases, under the dual global pressures of urbanization and climate change, there is an urgent need to incorporate the multi-dimensionality of urban systems in driving&nbsp;<em>Aedes</em>-borne disease risk. This project is anchored in socio-ecological sciences, and tailored to the complexities of urban eco-epidemiological dynamics. Herein, theory and methods from ecology, epidemiology, geography, and urban science are synthesized to develop and implement a novel urban systems approach for&nbsp;<em>Aedes</em>-borne diseases.</p> <p>The first sub-project establishes the theoretical foundation for this approach, integrating concepts from three bodies of knowledge: ?cities as complex adaptive systems?, hierarchical patch systems theory, and relational geography. In the framework, cities are conceptualized as hierarchically-structured patches of different land uses and characteristics. Patch composition determines localized disease risk, while patch configuration and connectivity contribute to emergent patterns of disease risk and spread. Complexity is added to the system by considering the cross-scale and dynamical processes occurring within a city. Furthermore, the framework establishes how individual and collective social structures interact with the biophysical landscape to generate risk. The empirical research for this dissertation uses a range of data sets, from open source remotely-sensed environmental data and census-derived socio-economic data to fine-scale household survey and entomological data. The second sub-project is carried out at the scale of the city, and examines how extreme climate and weather conditions in Colombia differentially affects the onset of peak dengue incidence for urban settlements with varying landscape and socio-economic properties. Using Bayesian spatio-temporal hierarchical models we discovered that extreme temperature anomalies (10?12?C) result in an earlier onset of dengue risk for high-elevation compared to low-elevation settlements, which experience increases in dengue risk two to four months after extreme temperature anomalies. Furthermore, the risk of dengue after extremely dry conditions is higher and extends for a longer duration in highly urban areas compared to areas with a low proportion of the population living in urban settlements. These findings indicate the potential for landscape-specific dengue early warning and forecasting frameworks.</p> <p>The third sub-project is based in a mid-sized, rapidly growing city (Ibagu?) embedded within the Andes Mountains of Colombia, and establishes homogenous urban typologies of dengue risk. Measuring dengue incidence across census block and higher order urban sections, we show that distinctive signatures of incidence can emerge from interactions between heterogeneous socio-environmental composition and configuration. Finally, the last sub-project is carried out at the household and neighborhood scale in Ibagu?, and examines how water governance and neighborhood-based social processes drive household-level dengue risk. We documented the role of collective societal memory of water scarcity in fostering a culture of water storage. We determined that neighborhood-based metrics of social cohesion do not necessarily translate to dengue household preventative practices and that to scale dengue prevention strategies, public health agencies may consider interventions rooted in ?place-making? to foster linkages between perceived neighborhood-level versus household-level risk.</p> <p>This dissertation demonstrates how trans-disciplinary research bridges urban science, ecology, and public health research communities, and provides a pathway for mosquito-borne disease interventions to be incorporated into national-level early warning systems as well as community-based initiatives that collectively, set cities on more healthy and sustainable trajectories for the 21<sup>st</sup>&nbsp;century.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/26/2023<br>      Modified by: Maria&nbsp;Diuk-Wasser</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2020853/2020853_10698848_1695643691205_Box1_SocialActors--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2020853/2020853_10698848_1695643691205_Box1_SocialActors--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Human social actors of the urban system"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2020853/2020853_10698848_1695643691205_Box1_SocialActors--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Human social actors of the urban system"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">We build complexity onto the urban landscape by considering human actors at multiple levels of social organization, and uncovering ways that people are characterized, aggregated, and interconnected.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Pallavi Kache</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Pallavi&nbsp;A&nbsp;Kache</div> <div class="imageTitle">Human social actors of the urban system</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2020853/2020853_10698848_1695643811582_Box2_Workflow_New--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2020853/2020853_10698848_1695643811582_Box2_Workflow_New--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Work-flow: Implementing the urban systems framework"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2020853/2020853_10698848_1695643811582_Box2_Workflow_New--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Work-flow: Implementing the urban systems framework"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">We build a work-flow, showing how landscape analyses, socio-behavioral research, and mixed qualitative-quantitative modeling can be used to implement an urban systems framework</div> <div class="imageCredit">Pallavi Kache</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Pallavi&nbsp;A&nbsp;Kache</div> <div class="imageTitle">Work-flow: Implementing the urban systems framework</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The rise of vector-borne diseases transmitted by the Aedes spp. mosquitoes is attributed, in part, to the dramatic rates of contemporary urbanization. Over the past 30 years, scientists have developed a wealth of knowledge around the drivers of heterogeneity in Aedes-borne disease risk within and between cities. However, in current Aedes-borne disease research, characterizations of ?urban? are oversimplified, with the built environment and social institutions of the city often relegated to a background context. To mitigate the spread of Aedes-borne diseases, under the dual global pressures of urbanization and climate change, there is an urgent need to incorporate the multi-dimensionality of urban systems in driving Aedes-borne disease risk. This project is anchored in socio-ecological sciences, and tailored to the complexities of urban eco-epidemiological dynamics. Herein, theory and methods from ecology, epidemiology, geography, and urban science are synthesized to develop and implement a novel urban systems approach for Aedes-borne diseases.  The first sub-project establishes the theoretical foundation for this approach, integrating concepts from three bodies of knowledge: ?cities as complex adaptive systems?, hierarchical patch systems theory, and relational geography. In the framework, cities are conceptualized as hierarchically-structured patches of different land uses and characteristics. Patch composition determines localized disease risk, while patch configuration and connectivity contribute to emergent patterns of disease risk and spread. Complexity is added to the system by considering the cross-scale and dynamical processes occurring within a city. Furthermore, the framework establishes how individual and collective social structures interact with the biophysical landscape to generate risk. The empirical research for this dissertation uses a range of data sets, from open source remotely-sensed environmental data and census-derived socio-economic data to fine-scale household survey and entomological data. The second sub-project is carried out at the scale of the city, and examines how extreme climate and weather conditions in Colombia differentially affects the onset of peak dengue incidence for urban settlements with varying landscape and socio-economic properties. Using Bayesian spatio-temporal hierarchical models we discovered that extreme temperature anomalies (10?12?C) result in an earlier onset of dengue risk for high-elevation compared to low-elevation settlements, which experience increases in dengue risk two to four months after extreme temperature anomalies. Furthermore, the risk of dengue after extremely dry conditions is higher and extends for a longer duration in highly urban areas compared to areas with a low proportion of the population living in urban settlements. These findings indicate the potential for landscape-specific dengue early warning and forecasting frameworks.  The third sub-project is based in a mid-sized, rapidly growing city (Ibagu?) embedded within the Andes Mountains of Colombia, and establishes homogenous urban typologies of dengue risk. Measuring dengue incidence across census block and higher order urban sections, we show that distinctive signatures of incidence can emerge from interactions between heterogeneous socio-environmental composition and configuration. Finally, the last sub-project is carried out at the household and neighborhood scale in Ibagu?, and examines how water governance and neighborhood-based social processes drive household-level dengue risk. We documented the role of collective societal memory of water scarcity in fostering a culture of water storage. We determined that neighborhood-based metrics of social cohesion do not necessarily translate to dengue household preventative practices and that to scale dengue prevention strategies, public health agencies may consider interventions rooted in ?place-making? to foster linkages between perceived neighborhood-level versus household-level risk.  This dissertation demonstrates how trans-disciplinary research bridges urban science, ecology, and public health research communities, and provides a pathway for mosquito-borne disease interventions to be incorporated into national-level early warning systems as well as community-based initiatives that collectively, set cities on more healthy and sustainable trajectories for the 21st century.             Last Modified: 09/26/2023       Submitted by: Maria Diuk-Wasser]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
