<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[MRI: Acquisition of a High Performance Data Acquisition System to Enable Experimental and Computational Research on the System Level Response of the Built Environment]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>607704.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>607704</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Wendy C. Crone</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>wcrone@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924681</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This Major Research Instrumentation (MRI) award supports the acquisition of a versatile, high-performance data acquisition system (DAQ) for fundamental research at the NSF Large High-Performance Outdoor Shake Table (LHPOST) at UC San Diego. To advance fundamental knowledge, it is vital to collect and disseminate highly accurate earthquake engineering experimental datasets that are well documented.  Such data on system-level behavior of civil infrastructure during earthquakes--from the initiation of damage to the onset of collapse--are scarce. The MRI- enabled LHPOST facility will allow researchers to conduct in-depth seismic response studies of complex large-scale civil infrastructure systems—pushing the boundaries of knowledge on resilient communities and contributing to enhanced design codes and standards to promote public safety.  Research activities will broadly impact science, technology and engineering practice and the data collected from the new DAQ system will be integrated into course work that will bring the laboratory experience into the classroom, reaching a large number of students, particularly underrepresented students.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;The LHPOST is currently being upgraded from its current single-degree-of-freedom (SDOF) configuration to a full six-degree-of-freedom (6-DOF) capability-- to reproduce all six components of ground motion experienced during earthquakes. The DAQ system will complement this upgrade--providing higher resolution (24-bit, 768 channels, max sampling rate of 25.6 kS/sec per channel), superior aliasing rejection with user-configurable digital anti-aliasing filters, and zero skew time between different channels, thus enabling accurate recordings from very small (ambient vibrations) to very large (seismic testing) motions. This will facilitate the generation of critical landmark datasets to support the development, calibration, and validation of high-fidelity 3D computational models of civil infrastructure systems that will progressively shift the current reliance on physical testing to simulation-based assessment and design. The instrumentation will help to enable potentially transformative research on soil-structure interaction, hybrid testing and measurement of structural response during dynamic loading.  The high-quality data enabled by this instrumentation will be made available through the Natural Hazards Engineering Research Infrastructure (NHERI) repository—serving a global community of researchers and catalyzing collaborative research.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/10/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/10/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2020745</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lelli</FirstName>
<LastName>VanDenEinde</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lelli VanDenEinde</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[lelli@egrove.education]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000725547</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Joel</FirstName>
<LastName>Conte</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Joel P Conte</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jpconte@ucsd.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000460140</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jose</FirstName>
<LastName>Restrepo</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jose Restrepo</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jrestrepo@ucsd.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000486725</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Machel</FirstName>
<LastName>Morrison</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Machel L Morrison</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mmorrison@ucsd.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000788940</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Veronica</FirstName>
<LastName>Eliasson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Veronica Eliasson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[eliasson@mines.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000587680</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-San Diego</Name>
<CityName>LA JOLLA</CityName>
<ZipCode>920930021</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8585344896</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>9500 GILMAN DRIVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>50</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA50</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>UYTTZT6G9DT1</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, SAN DIEGO</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-San Diego]]></Name>
<CityName>La Jolla</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>920930085</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[9500 Gilman Drive, Mail Code 008]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>50</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA50</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>Major Research Instrumentation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>036E</Code>
<Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>037E</Code>
<Text>GEOTECHNICAL ENGINEERING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>038E</Code>
<Text>FOUNDATION ENGINEERING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>040E</Code>
<Text>Haz mitigation of structural sys</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>043E</Code>
<Text>EARTHQUAKE ENGINEERING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1057</Code>
<Text>CIS BASE RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1576</Code>
<Text>NATIONL EARTHQK HZRD REDCT PRG</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7231</Code>
<Text>CYBERINFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9102</Code>
<Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9263</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL SCIENCE &amp; ENGING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~607704</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-181b1ac8-7fff-51df-d5aa-26b46432eca0"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The large, high-performance, outdoor shake table (LHPOST6) at UC San Diego is a one-of-a-kind experimental facility and the largest in the U.S. for conducting earthquake engineering research. It can reproduce all six components of ground motion experienced during earthquakes. Testing structures at large scale under realistic ground shaking is essential to understand the seismic response behavior of civil infrastructure systems. This enables researchers to improve design codes and standards, validate 3D models, and develop accurate decision-making tools necessary to build and maintain sustainable and disaster-resilient communities. To support this research, it is vital to collect and disseminate earthquake engineering experimental datasets that are well documented and made widely available through the NHERI Data Depot repository. Datasets about the behavior of civil infrastructure systems during earthquakes from the initiation of damage to the onset of collapse are scarce and sorely needed.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>To obtain important quantitative data from the landmark tests conducted on the LHPOST6, it is imperative that instrumentation and sensors are interfaced with a high accuracy, versatile and high-performance data acquisition (DAQ) system. Under this MRI award, a DAQ system was developed that would enable higher resolution and cleaner data to be recorded during tests conducted on the LHPOST6.&nbsp; The DAQ system that was built under this award consists of 12 nodes with 64 channels each (for a total of 768 measurement channels) at 24- bit Analog-to-Digital resolution, simultaneous sampling, and a sampling rate up to 25.6 kS/s per channel. The DAQ provides user-configurable filters and the ability to sample data from channels simultaneously enabling accurate recordings from very small (ambient vibrations) to very large (seismic testing) motions.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The facility's top priority is to provide highly reliable measurements and high-quality data to the researchers and/or commercial clients. However, the new DAQ system also provides the opportunity for researchers to explore the use of new measurement/sensor technologies such as Digital Image Correlation techniques to measure the motion and deformation of test specimens.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Research activities at the LHPOST6 facility using the new DAQ system will broadly impact science, engineering and education. These landmark experiments will push the boundaries of knowledge in earthquake engineering and the collection of high-quality data is vital to their success. By providing high-resolution and accurate data, the DAQ system will enable researchers to conduct in-depth seismic response studies of complex large-scale structural, geotechnical and soil-foundation-structural systems. The resulting datasets will support the development, calibration, and validation of computational models that will progressively shift the current reliance on physical testing to simulation-based assessment and design of civil infrastructure. Furthermore, data collected from the DAQ system will promote teaching and training as new course modules that bring the laboratory experience into the classroom can be developed to reach a broader number of students.</span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/12/2022<br>      Modified by: Lelli&nbsp;Vandeneinde</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2020745/2020745_10684486_1655060541119_1.LHPOST6landscape--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2020745/2020745_10684486_1655060541119_1.LHPOST6landscape--rgov-800width.jpg" title="NHERI@UC San Diego LHPOST6 Facility"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2020745/2020745_10684486_1655060541119_1.LHPOST6landscape--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="NHERI@UC San Diego LHPOST6 Facility"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Facility where Data Acquisition System (DAQ) build with these MRI funds will be utilized</div> <div class="imageCredit">UC San Diego</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Lelli&nbsp;Vandeneinde</div> <div class="imageTitle">NHERI@UC San Diego LHPOST6 Facility</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2020745/2020745_10684486_1655060781319_5.SingleNodeinServerRack--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2020745/2020745_10684486_1655060781319_5.SingleNodeinServerRack--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Single DAQ node in a server rack"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2020745/2020745_10684486_1655060781319_5.SingleNodeinServerRack--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Single DAQ node in a server rack"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">This photo shows a single node and terminal blocks configured in the server rack which are located under the LHPOST6 shaking table. The remaining 11 nodes have been removed from the racks and wrapped up and stored in a climate controlled room to protect them from the elements while not in use.</div> <div class="imageCredit">UC San Diego</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Lelli&nbsp;Vandeneinde</div> <div class="imageTitle">Single DAQ node in a server rack</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   The large, high-performance, outdoor shake table (LHPOST6) at UC San Diego is a one-of-a-kind experimental facility and the largest in the U.S. for conducting earthquake engineering research. It can reproduce all six components of ground motion experienced during earthquakes. Testing structures at large scale under realistic ground shaking is essential to understand the seismic response behavior of civil infrastructure systems. This enables researchers to improve design codes and standards, validate 3D models, and develop accurate decision-making tools necessary to build and maintain sustainable and disaster-resilient communities. To support this research, it is vital to collect and disseminate earthquake engineering experimental datasets that are well documented and made widely available through the NHERI Data Depot repository. Datasets about the behavior of civil infrastructure systems during earthquakes from the initiation of damage to the onset of collapse are scarce and sorely needed.  To obtain important quantitative data from the landmark tests conducted on the LHPOST6, it is imperative that instrumentation and sensors are interfaced with a high accuracy, versatile and high-performance data acquisition (DAQ) system. Under this MRI award, a DAQ system was developed that would enable higher resolution and cleaner data to be recorded during tests conducted on the LHPOST6.  The DAQ system that was built under this award consists of 12 nodes with 64 channels each (for a total of 768 measurement channels) at 24- bit Analog-to-Digital resolution, simultaneous sampling, and a sampling rate up to 25.6 kS/s per channel. The DAQ provides user-configurable filters and the ability to sample data from channels simultaneously enabling accurate recordings from very small (ambient vibrations) to very large (seismic testing) motions. The facility's top priority is to provide highly reliable measurements and high-quality data to the researchers and/or commercial clients. However, the new DAQ system also provides the opportunity for researchers to explore the use of new measurement/sensor technologies such as Digital Image Correlation techniques to measure the motion and deformation of test specimens.  Research activities at the LHPOST6 facility using the new DAQ system will broadly impact science, engineering and education. These landmark experiments will push the boundaries of knowledge in earthquake engineering and the collection of high-quality data is vital to their success. By providing high-resolution and accurate data, the DAQ system will enable researchers to conduct in-depth seismic response studies of complex large-scale structural, geotechnical and soil-foundation-structural systems. The resulting datasets will support the development, calibration, and validation of computational models that will progressively shift the current reliance on physical testing to simulation-based assessment and design of civil infrastructure. Furthermore, data collected from the DAQ system will promote teaching and training as new course modules that bring the laboratory experience into the classroom can be developed to reach a broader number of students.       Last Modified: 06/12/2022       Submitted by: Lelli Vandeneinde]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
