<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research: Leader Behaviors and Experiences across Life Domains]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>93886.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>93886</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tara Behrend</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tsbehren@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928053</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Individuals in leadership roles represent a large group of the nation’s workforce, and their behaviors not only affect organizational effectiveness but also influence the prosperity and welfare of people in their nonwork domains. Despite their importance, prior research has paid limited attention to the nonwork domain, including family, community, and personal life, contexts that are antecedents and consequences of leadership role occupancy, leadership development, and day-to-day variation of leadership behaviors. This project takes a life-span and holistic approach to analyze how nonwork domain variables, such as community involvement and volunteering activities, lead to and are shaped by leadership role occupancy. Further, the project provides critical insights on how nonwork domain experiences might promote leadership development and how leadership development might contribute to leaders’ growth and thriving in other nonwork domains. Lastly, the project will help to uncover how and when leaders’ day-to-day behaviors and their nonwork domain experiences mutually influence each other. These findings will inform business organizations seeking to promote leadership to facilitate their economic competitiveness, and will also inform society regarding how leadership in one context may contribute to the welfare of organizations more generally.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;We know very little regarding how leadership in one organizational context may influence leadership and work behavior more generally, or the reciprocal relationships between leadership in multiple domains.  Adopting a multi-method approach, this project will conduct three empirical studies. First, the project will use archival data (National Longitudinal Survey of Youth, NLSY) collected by the U.S. Bureau of Labor Statistics (NLSY 79, NLSY 79 Children and Young Adults, and NLSY 97) to examine how individuals’ nonwork experiences and their leadership role occupancy at work influence each other reciprocally. The project will use mixture latent Markov modeling to capture and predict the leadership role transition patterns. Second, the project will use a longitudinal design collecting multi-wave, multi-source data to examine the interplay between leaders’ nonwork experiences and their leadership development processes using latent change score models.  The third study takes a within-person perspective and analyzes how leaders’ work and nonwork experiences and behaviors are interconnected on a daily basis. The project will conduct an experience sampling study over 10 consecutive days, capturing fluctuations of leaders’ work and nonwork behaviors and experiences that are otherwise missed by surveys separated by longer time intervals; it will use dynamic structural equation modeling (DSEM) in data analysis. Lastly, by triangulating findings of three studies using different methods, the project will promote a more comprehensive understanding of how leaders’ work and nonwork experience affect each other across different time frames and life stages.  Findings from the project will inform organizational theories regarding leadership, as well as life course perspectives that focus on the interplay between work and non-work domains, especially regarding leadership.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/08/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/08/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2020883</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Songqi</FirstName>
<LastName>Liu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Songqi Liu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[sqliu@gsu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000677060</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/08/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Georgia State University Research Foundation, Inc.</Name>
<CityName>ATLANTA</CityName>
<ZipCode>303032921</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4044133570</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>58 EDGEWOOD AVE NE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[FL 3]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>MNS7B9CVKDN7</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GEORGIA STATE UNIVERSITY RESEARCH FOUNDATION INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Georgia State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>303032425</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[35 Broad Street NE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8031</Code>
<Text>SoO-Science Of Organizations</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~93886</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project studies the mutual influence between leaders&rsquo; behaviors and experiences in work and nonwork domains. To this end, the project focuses on addressing three broad research questions: (1) How do individuals&rsquo; behaviors and experiences in nonwork domains and their <em>leadership role occupancy</em> influence each other? (2) How do leaders&rsquo; behaviors and experiences in nonwork domains and their <em>leadership development</em> at work influence each other? (3) How do day-to-day <em>leaders&rsquo; behaviors and experiences</em> in work and nonwork domains influence each other?</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Despite the delay in data collection caused by the pandemic, the project has generated several working papers that were presented at the 2022 Society for Industrial and Organizational Psychology annual conference. [Zhou, Z. E. (Co-Chair), Busse, K. A. (Co-Chair), &amp; Day, D. V. (Discussant) (2022). Leadership Across Domains: Nonwork Predictors and Outcomes of Leader Role Occupancy [Symposium]. Society for Industrial and Organizational Psychology Annual Conference, Seattle, WA, United States. Saldivar, U. &amp; Liao, C. (2022). Cross-Domain Leadership: A Critical Review and Agenda for Future Research. Liu., X. &amp; Zhou, L. (2022). Childhood Social Class and Leader Emergence in Adulthood: Mediating Role of Volunteering. Stotler, D., Liu, S., &amp; Hartnell, C. A. (2022). The Apple Doesn&rsquo;t Fall Far from the Tree: Examining the Mother-to-Child Crossover of Leadership Role Occupancy Busse, K. A., Thomas, A., &amp; Zhou, E. Z. (2022). The Spillover and Crossover Effects of Leadership Role Occupancy.] In particular, using data from the National Longitudinal Survey of the Youth, the project found that individuals were more likely to occupy a leadership role at work in their early 30s, if their mothers were leaders at work 18 years ago (while these young adults were in their adolescent years). In addition, this cross-generational effect was mediated by young adults&rsquo; self-esteem and gender ideology, with the latter path being more pronounced for women than for men. The project also produced a review paper on the cross-domain leadership research. The paper uncovered that extant cross-domain research has primarily focused on how leaders influence followers&rsquo; family experiences, with a recent emergence of studies examining how leaders&rsquo; nonwork experiences affect their own work-related behaviors. By identifying gaps and limitations in the current cross-domain leadership research, we suggest promising directions for future research, including developing theories linking multiple role occupancy with leadership development, the examination of nonwork domains beyond family (e.g., personal life and community), and taking a dynamic (e.g., life-span development and/or within-person) perspective to examine leadership across life domains.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The project has provided graduate students at Baruch College, Michigan State University, and Georgia State University with research skills training. Specifically, five graduate students have participated in revising the research model, the IRB application, and data collection protocols given the ongoing challenge created by the pandemic. The project has also given them opportunity to improve data analysis and manuscript writing skills. Furthermore, as part of the project, data collection for the proposed daily diary study of leaders and partners and longitudinal study of leaders and subordinates are still ongoing.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/22/2022<br>      Modified by: Songqi&nbsp;Liu</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project studies the mutual influence between leaders’ behaviors and experiences in work and nonwork domains. To this end, the project focuses on addressing three broad research questions: (1) How do individuals’ behaviors and experiences in nonwork domains and their leadership role occupancy influence each other? (2) How do leaders’ behaviors and experiences in nonwork domains and their leadership development at work influence each other? (3) How do day-to-day leaders’ behaviors and experiences in work and nonwork domains influence each other?     Despite the delay in data collection caused by the pandemic, the project has generated several working papers that were presented at the 2022 Society for Industrial and Organizational Psychology annual conference. [Zhou, Z. E. (Co-Chair), Busse, K. A. (Co-Chair), &amp; Day, D. V. (Discussant) (2022). Leadership Across Domains: Nonwork Predictors and Outcomes of Leader Role Occupancy [Symposium]. Society for Industrial and Organizational Psychology Annual Conference, Seattle, WA, United States. Saldivar, U. &amp; Liao, C. (2022). Cross-Domain Leadership: A Critical Review and Agenda for Future Research. Liu., X. &amp; Zhou, L. (2022). Childhood Social Class and Leader Emergence in Adulthood: Mediating Role of Volunteering. Stotler, D., Liu, S., &amp; Hartnell, C. A. (2022). The Apple Doesn’t Fall Far from the Tree: Examining the Mother-to-Child Crossover of Leadership Role Occupancy Busse, K. A., Thomas, A., &amp; Zhou, E. Z. (2022). The Spillover and Crossover Effects of Leadership Role Occupancy.] In particular, using data from the National Longitudinal Survey of the Youth, the project found that individuals were more likely to occupy a leadership role at work in their early 30s, if their mothers were leaders at work 18 years ago (while these young adults were in their adolescent years). In addition, this cross-generational effect was mediated by young adults’ self-esteem and gender ideology, with the latter path being more pronounced for women than for men. The project also produced a review paper on the cross-domain leadership research. The paper uncovered that extant cross-domain research has primarily focused on how leaders influence followers’ family experiences, with a recent emergence of studies examining how leaders’ nonwork experiences affect their own work-related behaviors. By identifying gaps and limitations in the current cross-domain leadership research, we suggest promising directions for future research, including developing theories linking multiple role occupancy with leadership development, the examination of nonwork domains beyond family (e.g., personal life and community), and taking a dynamic (e.g., life-span development and/or within-person) perspective to examine leadership across life domains.     The project has provided graduate students at Baruch College, Michigan State University, and Georgia State University with research skills training. Specifically, five graduate students have participated in revising the research model, the IRB application, and data collection protocols given the ongoing challenge created by the pandemic. The project has also given them opportunity to improve data analysis and manuscript writing skills. Furthermore, as part of the project, data collection for the proposed daily diary study of leaders and partners and longitudinal study of leaders and subordinates are still ongoing.          Last Modified: 08/22/2022       Submitted by: Songqi Liu]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
