<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID:Collaborative Research: Micro- and macro-ecological succession in anchialine habitats during creation via volcanism]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>59855.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>59855</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Leslie J. Rissler</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lrissler@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924628</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Lava flows create new, initially sterile habitats. The identity of the initial colonizers of these habitats, subsequent invaders, and the repeatability of this process is important for understanding the establishment of ecosystem processes like nutrient cycling. Identifying steps in habitat maturation also shapes conservation strategies for endangered species and rare environments. These processes are virtually unknown in the anchialine ecosystem, which consists of coastal, landlocked bodies of water influenced by fresh and oceanic waters. Anchialine habitats are rare worldwide but are concentrated in Hawaii. Hawaiian anchialine habitats are home to a diverse array of animals, plants, and microbes, many of which are found nowhere else. In 2018 lava flows from the Kilauea volcano created several new anchialine habitats on the east coast of Hawaii, presenting an exceptional chance to examine how ecology emerges in the anchialine ecosystem. The researchers will leverage this opportunity to detail how these unusual habitats change over time. Microbial and animal communities will be characterized as they become established. This research will advance our understanding of the anchialine ecosystem, especially its microbes, which may prove useful for future medical or commercial applications. Underrepresented groups in STEM (including native Hawaiians and Pacific Islanders) will take an active role in this research.     &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Hundreds of microbial samples will be collected during a time series in anchialine habitats undergoing development. Microbial community structure will be analyzed using DNA sequencing technology. These “young” communities will be compared to ones previously characterized from other, “mature” Hawaiian anchialine habitats. This research will address the repeatability of anchialine community formation and whether new habitats are converging on microbial communities similar to those in established habitats. To complement these microbial analyses, presence and abundance of a keystone shrimp species in the new anchialine habitats will also be assessed. Population genomic tools will be used to test the origins of the colonizing shrimp, as the lava flows may have caused local extinctions in this species. Physiological experiments in shrimp will also be performed to examine thermal adaptations stemming from elevated temperatures due to volcanic activity. Because shrimp act as important grazers on the microbial communities, correlations between shrimp abundance and microbial community composition will also be explored.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/16/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/16/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2020099</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Justin</FirstName>
<LastName>Havird</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Justin C Havird</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jhavird@utexas.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000633562</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/16/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Texas at Austin</Name>
<CityName>AUSTIN</CityName>
<ZipCode>787121139</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5124716424</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>110 INNER CAMPUS DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>25</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX25</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>V6AFQPN18437</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT AUSTIN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>X5NKD2NFF2V3</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Texas at Austin]]></Name>
<CityName>Austin</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>787121188</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2506 Speedway, NMS building]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>25</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX25</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1127</Code>
<Text>Evolutionary Processes</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~59855</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Anchialine habitats represent a unique ecosystem composed of ponds, pools, and caves found near the coast, with subterranean to the freshwater aquifer and oceanic seawater. These habitats harbor endemic organisms, many of which are endangered, but we are just beginning to learn about the microbes that form the base of the anchialine food web. Here, we examined anchialine habitats that were created in 2018 during lava flows in Hawaii. This is the first time naturally formed anchialine habitats have been studied during the early stages of their lifespan.</p> <p>We found that newly created habitats had microbial communities that were very different from those in established anchialine habitats that were formed hundreds or thousands of years ago. This suggests microbial communities in the anchialine ecosystem may take many years to become established, ?climax? communities. Specifically, the newer habitats are depleted for algae compared to established communities and also lack traces of larger animals (crustaceans and molluscs), which are common in established communities. We suggest that temperature plays a large role in this process, as the new ponds remain relatively hot due to continued geothermal activity. We also found that each of the three newly created ponds we examined had a statistically unique microbial community, even though these ponds are within meters of each other and share underground connections. This supports previous studies suggesting microbial communities in these habitats are highly endemic, reflecting the high degree of endemism in larger anchialine organisms. Finally, we examined microbial communities at three different times in these new ponds over the course of ~2 years. We found that communities did change with time, and in a similar way in each of the three ponds we examined. However, they showed no indication of converging towards more established communities. Together, these results suggest microbial succession in anchialine habitats is a long process. Therefore, we recommend that special conservation status be given to young anchialine habitats due to their distinctive microbes. Established anchialine habitats damaged by human activities may also take many years to recover. &nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;We also used this project as an opportunity to examine the gut microbiome in an endemic anchialine shrimp found in Hawaii, <em>Halocaridina rubra</em>. Briefly, we found that gut microbiomes were distinct from environmental microbial communities and that gut microbiomes were similar between wild-caught shrimp and those maintained in laboratory aquaria for years. This suggests there may be a specific gut microbiome in anchialine shrimps, which could aid in digestion and be inherited vertically from parents to offspring. We also found that bacterial communities in this microbiome are fairly simple and are dominated by a single species.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>We used the elevated temperatures in the newly created hot ponds as a natural laboratory to examine thermal physiology in anchialine species. We found shrimp from the new, hot ponds could tolerate higher temperatures than those from older, cooler habitats. This difference was maintained when shrimp were acclimated to the same, cool temperatures in the lab for several months. This suggests there may be a genetic basis for increased thermal tolerance in shrimp from the new, hot ponds. Preliminary genetic profiling of shrimp collected from nearby ponds before and after the creation of the new hot ponds also suggests genetic changes may have occurred in this population. Ongoing work will expand on these results to explore thermal physiology in anchialine species, with implications for how organisms in this ecosystem may respond to climate change.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>This work supported training of many students, including graduate students at the University of Texas and undergraduates from multiple institutions. We also worked with native Hawaiians during this project, whose insights and support were critical. Finally, we used anchialine organisms to engage with the public about the importance of biodiversity. &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/30/2023<br>      Modified by: Justin&nbsp;C&nbsp;Havird</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2020099/2020099_10664689_1685462973619_20191112_124615--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2020099/2020099_10664689_1685462973619_20191112_124615--rgov-800width.jpg" title="New Hot Pond"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2020099/2020099_10664689_1685462973619_20191112_124615--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="New Hot Pond"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">A newly created anchialine habitat near Hilo, Hawaii</div> <div class="imageCredit">Justin Havird</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Justin&nbsp;C&nbsp;Havird</div> <div class="imageTitle">New Hot Pond</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2020099/2020099_10664689_1685463054206_DSCN4697--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2020099/2020099_10664689_1685463054206_DSCN4697--rgov-800width.jpg" title="New Hot Pond2"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2020099/2020099_10664689_1685463054206_DSCN4697--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="New Hot Pond2"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">A newly created anchialine habitat near Hilo, HAwaii</div> <div class="imageCredit">Justin Havird</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Justin&nbsp;C&nbsp;Havird</div> <div class="imageTitle">New Hot Pond2</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2020099/2020099_10664689_1685463162640_IMG_2682--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2020099/2020099_10664689_1685463162640_IMG_2682--rgov-800width.jpg" title="New Hot Pond3"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2020099/2020099_10664689_1685463162640_IMG_2682--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="New Hot Pond3"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Newly created anchialine habitat near Hilo, Hawaii</div> <div class="imageCredit">Troy Sakihara</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Justin&nbsp;C&nbsp;Havird</div> <div class="imageTitle">New Hot Pond3</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2020099/2020099_10664689_1685463249366_20221111_122721--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2020099/2020099_10664689_1685463249366_20221111_122721--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Established Pond"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2020099/2020099_10664689_1685463249366_20221111_122721--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Established Pond"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Established anchialine habitat with orange crust community on Maui</div> <div class="imageCredit">Justin Havird</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Justin&nbsp;C&nbsp;Havird</div> <div class="imageTitle">Established Pond</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2020099/2020099_10664689_1685463352094_DSCN4677--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2020099/2020099_10664689_1685463352094_DSCN4677--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Anchialine shrimp"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2020099/2020099_10664689_1685463352094_DSCN4677--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Anchialine shrimp"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Halocaridina rubra in an anchialine habitat</div> <div class="imageCredit">Justin Havird</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Justin&nbsp;C&nbsp;Havird</div> <div class="imageTitle">Anchialine shrimp</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2020099/2020099_10664689_1685463476137_Pregnant_Hrub_shopped--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2020099/2020099_10664689_1685463476137_Pregnant_Hrub_shopped--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Anchialine shrimp in lab"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2020099/2020099_10664689_1685463476137_Pregnant_Hrub_shopped--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Anchialine shrimp in lab"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Halocaridina rubra in the lab</div> <div class="imageCredit">Justin Havird</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Justin&nbsp;C&nbsp;Havird</div> <div class="imageTitle">Anchialine shrimp in lab</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Anchialine habitats represent a unique ecosystem composed of ponds, pools, and caves found near the coast, with subterranean to the freshwater aquifer and oceanic seawater. These habitats harbor endemic organisms, many of which are endangered, but we are just beginning to learn about the microbes that form the base of the anchialine food web. Here, we examined anchialine habitats that were created in 2018 during lava flows in Hawaii. This is the first time naturally formed anchialine habitats have been studied during the early stages of their lifespan.  We found that newly created habitats had microbial communities that were very different from those in established anchialine habitats that were formed hundreds or thousands of years ago. This suggests microbial communities in the anchialine ecosystem may take many years to become established, ?climax? communities. Specifically, the newer habitats are depleted for algae compared to established communities and also lack traces of larger animals (crustaceans and molluscs), which are common in established communities. We suggest that temperature plays a large role in this process, as the new ponds remain relatively hot due to continued geothermal activity. We also found that each of the three newly created ponds we examined had a statistically unique microbial community, even though these ponds are within meters of each other and share underground connections. This supports previous studies suggesting microbial communities in these habitats are highly endemic, reflecting the high degree of endemism in larger anchialine organisms. Finally, we examined microbial communities at three different times in these new ponds over the course of ~2 years. We found that communities did change with time, and in a similar way in each of the three ponds we examined. However, they showed no indication of converging towards more established communities. Together, these results suggest microbial succession in anchialine habitats is a long process. Therefore, we recommend that special conservation status be given to young anchialine habitats due to their distinctive microbes. Established anchialine habitats damaged by human activities may also take many years to recover.     We also used this project as an opportunity to examine the gut microbiome in an endemic anchialine shrimp found in Hawaii, Halocaridina rubra. Briefly, we found that gut microbiomes were distinct from environmental microbial communities and that gut microbiomes were similar between wild-caught shrimp and those maintained in laboratory aquaria for years. This suggests there may be a specific gut microbiome in anchialine shrimps, which could aid in digestion and be inherited vertically from parents to offspring. We also found that bacterial communities in this microbiome are fairly simple and are dominated by a single species.     We used the elevated temperatures in the newly created hot ponds as a natural laboratory to examine thermal physiology in anchialine species. We found shrimp from the new, hot ponds could tolerate higher temperatures than those from older, cooler habitats. This difference was maintained when shrimp were acclimated to the same, cool temperatures in the lab for several months. This suggests there may be a genetic basis for increased thermal tolerance in shrimp from the new, hot ponds. Preliminary genetic profiling of shrimp collected from nearby ponds before and after the creation of the new hot ponds also suggests genetic changes may have occurred in this population. Ongoing work will expand on these results to explore thermal physiology in anchialine species, with implications for how organisms in this ecosystem may respond to climate change.     This work supported training of many students, including graduate students at the University of Texas and undergraduates from multiple institutions. We also worked with native Hawaiians during this project, whose insights and support were critical. Finally, we used anchialine organisms to engage with the public about the importance of biodiversity.                       Last Modified: 05/30/2023       Submitted by: Justin C Havird]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
