<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[CAREER - The Winding Roads to Effective Teaching: Characterizing the Progressions in Instructional Knowledge and Practices of STEM Faculty]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/20/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>445893.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>445893</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Dawn Rickey</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>drickey@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924674</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[National initiatives to improve undergraduate science education build upon decades of research on and development of effective teaching practices. These evidence-based instructional practices (EBIPs) promote students' conceptual understanding and favorable attitudes about science, technology, engineering, and mathematics (STEM), with the greatest impacts observed among women and members of underrepresented groups. By improving retention rates and attracting a more diverse student population to the sciences, these research-based ways of teaching science can help address the national need to educate STEM-literate graduates and advance workforce development goals. The challenge is fostering the effective use of these teaching practices on a national scale. STEM faculty members are at the core of any successful instructional reform, yet surprisingly little is known about them with respect to their teaching. As extensive resources and efforts are currently focused on transforming STEM instructional practices at the college level nationally, there is a critical need to characterize STEM faculty members' knowledge base for teaching, instructional practices, relationships between the two, as well as progressions of this knowledge and these practices over time. Moreover, there is a need to characterize these progressions under varying reform environments (short workshops versus semester-long professional development; different departmental and institutional culture around teaching), as well as for faculty at various points of their academic career. Results of this foundational research will provide critical insight into the diverse progressions of STEM faculty members' knowledge base for teaching and instructional practices, which will inform current national and local reform efforts that aim at the widespread implementation of EBIPs in STEM courses in college settings.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This NSF Faculty Early Career Development project will address a wide gap in the discipline-based education research literature about STEM faculty members' knowledge base for teaching and instructional practices. Specifically, the project will characterize how STEM faculty members' practical theories and their integration with instructional practices evolve in the contexts of different (a) levels of experience as faculty members; (b) climate, culture, and rewards structures of departments and institutions; and (c) formal and informal professional development experiences. The research is grounded in the Teacher-Centered Systemic Reform Model, which describes faculty members' decision-making processes about teaching and influences impacting these processes. A convergent, longitudinal mixed methods design will be implemented to address the research questions. Quantitative data will include surveys, classroom observations, and course artifacts. The qualitative component will consist of an embedded collective case study. Data collected will include interviews with faculty and course artifacts. These research activities will result in an enhanced understanding of STEM faculty members' a) pedagogical content knowledge (PCK) elements, b) orientations toward teaching and beliefs about teaching, and c) instructional practices, as well as d) alignment among these three constructs under various contexts (e.g., faculty at different levels of their academic career, faculty experiencing different types of departmental and institutional climate, and faculty participating in different types of formal and informal professional development). This foundational research will further inform the theoretical framework and provide critical insights on effective practices for STEM faculty professional development to the STEM community at large. The research and education program will be fully integrated: one component of the education program, a professional development program for STEM faculty at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln (UNL), will serve as the context for part of the study; in turn, the results of the study will inform the design and implementation of the professional development program but will also provide opportunities to offer one-on-one teaching consultations with UNL STEM faculty and will inform the design of a graduate-level curriculum on reformed instructional practices.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/28/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/28/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2021491</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Marilyne</FirstName>
<LastName>Stains</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Marilyne Stains</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mstains@virginia.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000249536</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/28/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Virginia Main Campus</Name>
<CityName>CHARLOTTESVILLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>229034833</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4349244270</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1001 EMMET ST N</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>VA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>JJG6HU8PA4S5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RECTOR &amp; VISITORS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Virginia Main Campus]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>229034833</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>VA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1998</Code>
<Text>IUSE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7980</Code>
<Text>ECR-EDU Core Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8209</Code>
<Text>Improv Undergrad STEM Ed(IUSE)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8817</Code>
<Text>STEM Learning &amp; Learning Environments</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0418</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04001819DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~445893</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Instructional reform efforts focused on the propagation of evidence-based instructional practices in science courses at postsecondary institutions have been extensive over the last decades. Research on instructional change has demonstrated that these propagation efforts have encountered significant challenges. These challenges are varied (e.g., institutional policies and culture, classroom infrastructures, limited pedagogical training) and all influence faculty members&rsquo; instructional decision making. These findings have highlighted the importance for reform efforts to integrate faculty&rsquo;s needs. However, the lack of research on science faculty members&rsquo; instructional practices, ways of thinking and knowledge about teaching makes that task challenging. This project aimed to address this issue by exploring science faculty&rsquo;s knowledge base for teaching, instructional practices, relationships between the two, as well as progressions of element of their knowledge base over time.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Selected <strong>key project outcomes </strong>are highlighted below:</p> <p>The research team provided valid and reliable evidence that didactic teaching, also known as lecturing, was the dominant instructional style in the undergraduate science curriculum at research intensive institutions in the North America. This study, which was one of the largest observation-based studies, demonstrated the extensive work that is still required to provide learning environments in science courses that are aligned with research on how people learn. This study provides a baseline that researchers can use to monitor the impact of instructional reforms.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Two qualitative studies conducted during this project demonstrated that beliefs about teaching held by new assistant professors in chemistry were mostly aligned with their instructional practices, except for the group of faculty members who held the most student-centered beliefs. For this group, their instructional practices were only marginally student-centered. These studies also showed that as these new professors gained teaching experience, they were able to express more beliefs but that the beliefs were of similar nature. Factors that coincided with a shift towards student-centered beliefs included access and use of chemical education research journal and researchers, repeated opportunities to teach the same course, and instructor's continued learning efforts with respect to teaching.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Study undertaken in this project showed no relationship between faculty members&rsquo; descriptions of their peers&rsquo; perceptions of departmental climate around teaching and their level of use of evidence-based instructional practices. Moreover, the study demonstrated the challenge in measuring departmental climate around teaching. Indeed, participating faculty members struggled to describe several of the constructs necessary to characterize a climate. These findings highlight a need for departments to establish policies, practices, and expectations with respect to teaching.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The <strong>intellectual merit</strong> of the project lies in the advances that were made in the development and refinement of methods to measure instructional practices, instructor thinking about teaching, and contextual factors. First, we developed a new method to facilitate the analysis of data collected through a widely used observation protocol, the Classroom Observation Protocol for Undergraduate STEM (COPUS). This new method allowed us to establish a national baseline for the nature of instructional practices provided in science courses at the undergraduate level. Second, we conducted an extensive literature review and analysis of our own data to show that the factor structure of a popular survey used to measure instructors&rsquo; orientations towards teaching (the Approaches to Teaching Inventory) is not reproducible and provided recommendations for use of the instrument in a study. Third, we developed a new instrument that provides valid and reliable information about the climate around teaching in a science department. Climate around teaching is often mentioned by faculty in surveys and interviews as a reason for limiting their uses of evidence-based instructional practices. However, prior surveys measuring climate were not focused on the department and had limitations in the standards used for their development, rendering difficult the testing of the assertion that the climate around teaching in a department influences the use of innovative instructional practices. This new instrument, the Departmental Climate around Teaching (DCaT) survey, provides the community a rigorous tool to explore the relationship between instructional decision-making and departmental climate.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The <strong>broader impacts</strong> include the development of a research tool that is provided free of charge to researchers and instructors. This tool, called the COPUS Analyzer, allows researchers and instructors to leverage data collected via COPUS in order to 1) characterize their instructional practice as either didactic, interactive lecturing, or student-centered, and 2) to explore patterns of their behaviors and their students&rsquo; behaviors during class time. Other broader impacts include the institutionalization at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln and the University of Virginia of courses that provide pedagogical training to science graduate students interested in pursuing an academic career. Finally, this project provided training in discipline-based education research to five postdoctoral scholars, three graduate students, and seven undergraduate students. All postdoctoral alumni are contributing to educating and supporting the success of the next generation of scientists and citizen at their respective institutions.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/05/2022<br>      Modified by: Marilyne&nbsp;Stains</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Instructional reform efforts focused on the propagation of evidence-based instructional practices in science courses at postsecondary institutions have been extensive over the last decades. Research on instructional change has demonstrated that these propagation efforts have encountered significant challenges. These challenges are varied (e.g., institutional policies and culture, classroom infrastructures, limited pedagogical training) and all influence faculty members’ instructional decision making. These findings have highlighted the importance for reform efforts to integrate faculty’s needs. However, the lack of research on science faculty members’ instructional practices, ways of thinking and knowledge about teaching makes that task challenging. This project aimed to address this issue by exploring science faculty’s knowledge base for teaching, instructional practices, relationships between the two, as well as progressions of element of their knowledge base over time.     Selected key project outcomes are highlighted below:  The research team provided valid and reliable evidence that didactic teaching, also known as lecturing, was the dominant instructional style in the undergraduate science curriculum at research intensive institutions in the North America. This study, which was one of the largest observation-based studies, demonstrated the extensive work that is still required to provide learning environments in science courses that are aligned with research on how people learn. This study provides a baseline that researchers can use to monitor the impact of instructional reforms.     Two qualitative studies conducted during this project demonstrated that beliefs about teaching held by new assistant professors in chemistry were mostly aligned with their instructional practices, except for the group of faculty members who held the most student-centered beliefs. For this group, their instructional practices were only marginally student-centered. These studies also showed that as these new professors gained teaching experience, they were able to express more beliefs but that the beliefs were of similar nature. Factors that coincided with a shift towards student-centered beliefs included access and use of chemical education research journal and researchers, repeated opportunities to teach the same course, and instructor's continued learning efforts with respect to teaching.     Study undertaken in this project showed no relationship between faculty members’ descriptions of their peers’ perceptions of departmental climate around teaching and their level of use of evidence-based instructional practices. Moreover, the study demonstrated the challenge in measuring departmental climate around teaching. Indeed, participating faculty members struggled to describe several of the constructs necessary to characterize a climate. These findings highlight a need for departments to establish policies, practices, and expectations with respect to teaching.        The intellectual merit of the project lies in the advances that were made in the development and refinement of methods to measure instructional practices, instructor thinking about teaching, and contextual factors. First, we developed a new method to facilitate the analysis of data collected through a widely used observation protocol, the Classroom Observation Protocol for Undergraduate STEM (COPUS). This new method allowed us to establish a national baseline for the nature of instructional practices provided in science courses at the undergraduate level. Second, we conducted an extensive literature review and analysis of our own data to show that the factor structure of a popular survey used to measure instructors’ orientations towards teaching (the Approaches to Teaching Inventory) is not reproducible and provided recommendations for use of the instrument in a study. Third, we developed a new instrument that provides valid and reliable information about the climate around teaching in a science department. Climate around teaching is often mentioned by faculty in surveys and interviews as a reason for limiting their uses of evidence-based instructional practices. However, prior surveys measuring climate were not focused on the department and had limitations in the standards used for their development, rendering difficult the testing of the assertion that the climate around teaching in a department influences the use of innovative instructional practices. This new instrument, the Departmental Climate around Teaching (DCaT) survey, provides the community a rigorous tool to explore the relationship between instructional decision-making and departmental climate.        The broader impacts include the development of a research tool that is provided free of charge to researchers and instructors. This tool, called the COPUS Analyzer, allows researchers and instructors to leverage data collected via COPUS in order to 1) characterize their instructional practice as either didactic, interactive lecturing, or student-centered, and 2) to explore patterns of their behaviors and their students’ behaviors during class time. Other broader impacts include the institutionalization at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln and the University of Virginia of courses that provide pedagogical training to science graduate students interested in pursuing an academic career. Finally, this project provided training in discipline-based education research to five postdoctoral scholars, three graduate students, and seven undergraduate students. All postdoctoral alumni are contributing to educating and supporting the success of the next generation of scientists and citizen at their respective institutions.                Last Modified: 07/05/2022       Submitted by: Marilyne Stains]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
