<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[GCR: Collaborative Research: Fine-grain generation of multiscale patterns in programmable organoids using microrobots]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>250000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>250000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01060400</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OIA</Abbreviation>
<LongName>OIA-Office of Integrative Activities</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Dragana Brzakovic</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dbrzakov@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925033</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[People with diseased or defective vital organs often need organ replacement to survive, but the availability of replacement organs is severely restricted by shortages of suitable tissue-matched donors and complexities such as postmortem organ deterioration and immunological rejection. These problems could be overcome by using high fidelity artificially-grown organs, but achieving that goal faces daunting and long-standing scientific and engineering challenges that  this project  aims to begin to meet. The project will focus on proof-of-concept generation of microscale patterns in a liver organoid to mimic the anatomical structure of lobules arranged in hexagonal patterns. The researchers will use microrobots to dynamically regulate gene expression in 3D vascularized liver organoids to generate the lobule like patterns. The results of this project will define a new area of robot-assisted biological design. This research will result in new biological rules, synthetic biology tools, and microrobotics that can be applied in numerous disciplines. If successful, another broader impact will be the demonstration of a method that could be used to create a new, in vitro, native-like organoid for biological and medical research, opening the door for research into the creation and repair of synthetic human organs.  The project includes research training for graduate students and postdoctoral researchers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Conventional methods of reproducing biological patterns in vitro suffer from multiple limitations. Previous research on pattern formation has largely relied on delivering global stimuli and studying reaction-diffusion mediated patterning of cell fates in the cell culture. Such methods yield only static patterns and give neither precise spatial nor temporal control over gene expression and resulting biological tissue formation. Current tissue engineering capabilities such as 3D printing and optogenetics are also unable to recapitulate the multiscale self-assembled patterns evident in native-like organs. The proposed approach will enable precise control of microrobots to achieve dynamic control over patterning in 3D biological systems, creating a paradigm shift in the field. The proof-of-concept goal is to modulate localized gene expression in engineered 3D tissue constructs to control the emergence of multiscale patterns. Machine learning will be used to derive and characterize desired multiscale patterns, synthetic biology to endow the stem cells with genetic circuits that can differentiate the cells to form desired tissue constructs, and microrobots to alter localized gene expression to form multiscale patterns in tissue constructs. In particular, the researchers will develop and control microrobots capable of sustaining and carrying engineered sender cells, drive the microrobots and associated sender cells within a vascularized 3D liver organoid to specific locations, and use the microrobot controlled sender cells to communicate with endothelial cells, inducing these endothelial cells to secrete Wnt and generate gradients controlling liver lobule zonation. This patterned lobule zonation will regulate the metabolic activity of the liver organoids.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/25/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/09/2023</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.083</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2021069</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Angela</FirstName>
<LastName>Belcher</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Angela M Belcher</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[belcher@mit.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000372918</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/09/2023</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ron</FirstName>
<LastName>Weiss</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ron Weiss</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[rweiss@mit.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000527225</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/25/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate>01/09/2023</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Massachusetts Institute of Technology</Name>
<CityName>CAMBRIDGE</CityName>
<ZipCode>021394301</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6172531000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>77 MASSACHUSETTS AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>E2NYLCDML6V1</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MASSACHUSETTS INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>E2NYLCDML6V1</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Massachusetts Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021394307</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[77 Massachusetts Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>062Y</Code>
<Text>GCR-Growing Convergence Resear</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~250000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Our Growing Convergence Research (GCR) seed grant was a collaboration among MIT, the University of Delaware (UDel), and Boston University (BU), where we worked at the interface of synthetic biology, micro-robotics, and machine learning to control biological signaling precisely. We combined synthetic biology that endows human-induced pluripotency stem cells (hiPSCs) with communication and decision-making capabilities with microrobots that interact with the cells to precisely control both cell differentiation and spatial organization using machine learning. Together, these technologies enable the engineering of stem cells that can synthesize multi-scale patterns to create native-like complete organs, including the liver, pancreas, kidney, and others. The high fidelity in artificial organ design expected from our convergence research can address the problems in vital organ replacement.</p> <p>In collaboration with the UDel team, we engineered hiPSCs capable of communicating with each other using a cell-cell contact-based biological signaling called synthetic Notch system. The engineered hiPSCs are also programmed with the decision-making capacity to differentiate into a desired cell fate upon activating the biological signaling. Then, we inserted the magnetically actuated microrobots into cells and moved them precisely to the desired locations using magnetic fields. We found that the microrobot insertion conserved the biological functionality of the cells without adversely affecting cell health.</p> <p>In collaboration with the BU team, we optimized the number of microrobots required to be inserted into the cells for effective biological signaling. Also, we have proposed a framework for learning spatiotemporal properties in a formal language. We showed that specifications in this language can be learned from data. The framework utilizes machine learning techniques to learn the language specifications. We showcased the learning framework and parameter synthesis approach in an example of a reaction-diffusion chemical network.</p> <p>The results of this seed project enabled our collaboration in a recently funded NSF GCR grant, in which our goal is to develop end-to-end computational and experimental procedures for the formation of multi-scale liver-like patterns. The results obtained as part of this collaboration were communicated at conferences such as the 4th Annual Conference on Learning for Dynamics and Control (L4DC) and the 2022 IEEE RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems (IROS).</p> <p>We have incorporated multiple convergence initiatives to bring the three research fields together, including in-person training on iPSC training and Microrobot controls. The project included a broad range of outreach activities, including a workshop with middle-school girls and their parents (led by UDel), a synthetic biology summer program (led by MIT), and participation in the ambassadors? program at BU.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/18/2023<br>      Modified by: Angela&nbsp;M&nbsp;Belcher</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Our Growing Convergence Research (GCR) seed grant was a collaboration among MIT, the University of Delaware (UDel), and Boston University (BU), where we worked at the interface of synthetic biology, micro-robotics, and machine learning to control biological signaling precisely. We combined synthetic biology that endows human-induced pluripotency stem cells (hiPSCs) with communication and decision-making capabilities with microrobots that interact with the cells to precisely control both cell differentiation and spatial organization using machine learning. Together, these technologies enable the engineering of stem cells that can synthesize multi-scale patterns to create native-like complete organs, including the liver, pancreas, kidney, and others. The high fidelity in artificial organ design expected from our convergence research can address the problems in vital organ replacement.  In collaboration with the UDel team, we engineered hiPSCs capable of communicating with each other using a cell-cell contact-based biological signaling called synthetic Notch system. The engineered hiPSCs are also programmed with the decision-making capacity to differentiate into a desired cell fate upon activating the biological signaling. Then, we inserted the magnetically actuated microrobots into cells and moved them precisely to the desired locations using magnetic fields. We found that the microrobot insertion conserved the biological functionality of the cells without adversely affecting cell health.  In collaboration with the BU team, we optimized the number of microrobots required to be inserted into the cells for effective biological signaling. Also, we have proposed a framework for learning spatiotemporal properties in a formal language. We showed that specifications in this language can be learned from data. The framework utilizes machine learning techniques to learn the language specifications. We showcased the learning framework and parameter synthesis approach in an example of a reaction-diffusion chemical network.  The results of this seed project enabled our collaboration in a recently funded NSF GCR grant, in which our goal is to develop end-to-end computational and experimental procedures for the formation of multi-scale liver-like patterns. The results obtained as part of this collaboration were communicated at conferences such as the 4th Annual Conference on Learning for Dynamics and Control (L4DC) and the 2022 IEEE RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems (IROS).  We have incorporated multiple convergence initiatives to bring the three research fields together, including in-person training on iPSC training and Microrobot controls. The project included a broad range of outreach activities, including a workshop with middle-school girls and their parents (led by UDel), a synthetic biology summer program (led by MIT), and participation in the ambassadors? program at BU.       Last Modified: 10/18/2023       Submitted by: Angela M Belcher]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
