<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[NSF Student Travel Grant for the 2020 IEEE International Conference on Network Protocols (ICNP)]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>15000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>15000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ann Von Lehmen</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>avonlehm@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924756</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This travel grant is used to support US based graduate students to attend IEEE International Conference on Network Protocols (ICNP), to be held in Madrid, Spain, October 13-16, 2020. ICNP is a conference that covers all aspects of network protocols, including design, analysis, specification, verification, implementation, and performance. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This travel grant aims to broaden ICNP participation by lowering the financial barrier of attendance for graduate students, in particular female and underrepresented students, at institutions in the Unites States. Enabling students to attend a high-quality conference at an early stage of a researcher's academic career is a wise investment in the future of the field. Priority will be given to the students who will substantially benefit from attending this conference but have limited travel funds, as well as junior graduate students who will attend the conference for the first time.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/23/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/23/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2021676</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Chen</FirstName>
<LastName>Qian</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Chen Qian</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[cqian12@ucsc.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000662845</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/23/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Santa Cruz</Name>
<CityName>SANTA CRUZ</CityName>
<ZipCode>950641077</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8314595278</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1156 HIGH ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>19</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA19</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>VXUFPE4MCZH5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA SANTA CRUZ</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Santa Cruz]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>950641077</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>19</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA19</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7363</Code>
<Text>Networking Technology and Syst</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~15000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project provided funding to support US-based graduate students to attend the ICNP 2022 conference in Lexington, Kentucky. Funding was provided to 15 US-based students, allowing them to attend the conference and meet other researchers from both industry and academia. All students from under-represented groups were offered funding. These awards were used to partially defray the conference registration fee, air ticket, and accommodation fee.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>ICNP 2022 included the 11 main technical sessions, poster and demo sessions, and workshops, broadly covering the field of networking. This high-quality technical program taught grant recipients about cutting edge research. By supporting graduate students to attend ICNP 2022, the grant specified in this proposal increases the dissemination of the conference research results to a larger and a more diverse audience, which otherwise would not have been able to attend. This grant contributes to the strength and inclusiveness of the research community, and leads to the long term health and vitalization of ICNP.</p> <p>ICNP is one of the most respected conferences in the field of computer networks. The students themselves benefit from the opportunity to meet and interact with many other researchers in a favorable setting, and from seeing research presented that may be related to what they are working on or may inspire them to try a new direction. The research community benefits from the improvement of the students in the pipeline, and the introduction of new researcher perspectives. Additionally, everybody benefits from the increased diversity of participants attending the conference.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/10/2023<br>      Modified by: Chen&nbsp;Qian</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project provided funding to support US-based graduate students to attend the ICNP 2022 conference in Lexington, Kentucky. Funding was provided to 15 US-based students, allowing them to attend the conference and meet other researchers from both industry and academia. All students from under-represented groups were offered funding. These awards were used to partially defray the conference registration fee, air ticket, and accommodation fee.    ICNP 2022 included the 11 main technical sessions, poster and demo sessions, and workshops, broadly covering the field of networking. This high-quality technical program taught grant recipients about cutting edge research. By supporting graduate students to attend ICNP 2022, the grant specified in this proposal increases the dissemination of the conference research results to a larger and a more diverse audience, which otherwise would not have been able to attend. This grant contributes to the strength and inclusiveness of the research community, and leads to the long term health and vitalization of ICNP.  ICNP is one of the most respected conferences in the field of computer networks. The students themselves benefit from the opportunity to meet and interact with many other researchers in a favorable setting, and from seeing research presented that may be related to what they are working on or may inspire them to try a new direction. The research community benefits from the improvement of the students in the pipeline, and the introduction of new researcher perspectives. Additionally, everybody benefits from the increased diversity of participants attending the conference.                Last Modified: 05/10/2023       Submitted by: Chen Qian]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
