<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[The Evaluation of Ocean Reanalyses in Their Determining Trends in Global Ocean Heat Content with a Novel Method]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>156494.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>168494</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06040300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OCE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Baris Uz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bmuz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924557</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Detecting and understanding oceanic change and variability has become increasingly important, given the fact that they serve as major evidence for climate change as well as the need to interpret climate variability patterns such as the much-debated recent global surface warming slowdown. Central to this issue is the ability to reliably represent the ocean state globally and over its full depth. Many researchers have turned to describe and understand oceanic change and variability from ocean reanalyses (ORA), which are the combination of ocean models, atmospheric forcings, and ocean observations through various data assimilation methods and potentially provide more accurate information than observation-only or model-only based ocean estimations. Also, ORAs provide more variables and quantities to interpret and understand the oceanic change and variability. At present, estimates from ORAs, especially their temporal evolutions, are still sensitive to the change of the observing system, the errors of the dynamical model, atmospheric forcing, and the data assimilation methods. Many of the uncertainties are often flow dependent and are hard to identify and estimate. This research proposes a novel, yet simple way to discover the possible systematic errors and biases in the temperature estimates from ORAs and then utilizes the most physically consistent ORAs to perform analysis on the changes in global and regional OHC. The proposed study can potentially provide a unified view for the recently much-debated global surface warming hiatus, and will advance understanding of the decadal variability of ocean heat uptake as well as provide useful implications about the imbalance of radiation at the top of the atmosphere. The project will support an early career scientist and a graduate student contributing to building the next generation of scientists. In addition, it will contribute to the development of k-12 educational material explaining the role of the oceans in regulating climate change.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In this project, a simple but rarely used method will be used to evaluate a large set of the existing ORA products and determine if they are suitable for examining climatic-scale changes in global and regional ocean heat content (OHC). This evaluation is based on examining the changes of the thermal-steric and halo-steric contributions to the global steric height over time. To first order, the size of the global halo-steric component should be very small, as it is controlled by changes in freshwater input into the global ocean. After evaluating existing ORAs, the ones selected as having the smallest potential errors in long-term OHC will be analyzed with a goal to better understand the processes that determine the observed OHC change and variability. The team will assess whether the decadal-scale slight reduction in surface temperature was real and whether it reflected transport of extra heat to deeper layers of the ocean. Researchers will also carry out the analyses with a focus to separate the contributions of isopycnal movement (heave) and change in water mass properties along isopycnals (spiciness). If available in the selected ORAs, the vertical heat flux and the associated dynamical variables will also be examined.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/11/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/11/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2021274</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Xinfeng</FirstName>
<LastName>Liang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Xinfeng Liang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[xfliang@udel.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000701061</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/11/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Delaware</Name>
<CityName>NEWARK</CityName>
<ZipCode>197160099</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3028312136</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>220 HULLIHEN HALL</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Delaware</StateName>
<StateCode>DE</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DE00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>T72NHKM259N3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF DELAWARE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Delaware]]></Name>
<CityName>Newark</CityName>
<StateCode>DE</StateCode>
<ZipCode>197060099</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[210 Hullihen Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Delaware</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DE00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1610</Code>
<Text>PHYSICAL OCEANOGRAPHY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1324</Code>
<Text>CLIMATE VARIABILITY AND PREDICTABILITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01001718DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01001920DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~156494</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~12000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The original goal of this project is to evaluate&nbsp;a large set of ocean reanalysis (ORA) products and determine if they are suitable for examining climatic-scale changes in global and regional ocean heat content. As conducting the proposed studies, the PIs realized the importance of identifying the &ldquo;truth&rdquo; of the ocean states and expanded the datasets to include available gridded Argo products.</p> <p>The PIs analyzed some of the publicly available ocean data products to identify the robust signals in ocean variability and changes, and in the meantime, to quantify the uncertainty associated with those ocean variability and changes. More specifically, the PIs conducted intercomparisons of temporal and spatial variability in global ocean temperature and salinity from multiply gridded Argo-based products. Those studies revealed significant discrepancies in the various gridded Argo-based products in regions like the Southern Ocean and the North Atlantic. Conclusions on changes and variability in those regions could thus be product-dependent. These results can serve as valuable references for colleagues who will use one or more of those Argo-based products.&nbsp;</p> <p>The PIs also conducted a few studies examining changes of temperature and salinity in different layers of the global ocean and exploring the contributions of internal oceanic variability to those changes. The PIs found that the vertical redistributions of ocean heat and salt contents contribute significantly to the upper ocean temperature and salinity changes, which have been used to infer the energy imbalance of the climate system and changes in global water cycles, respectively. These studies indicate that the ocean cannot be considered as a simple passive reservoir of heat and salt. Ocean dynamic processes should be considered in interpreting ocean changes, particularly those in the relatively well-observed upper ocean.</p> <p>The PIs further investigated dynamic processes that are related to the vertical transport of ocean properties. In particular, the PIs examined the oceanic vertical velocity from ECCO (Estimating the Circulation and Climate of the Ocean) ocean state estimate. The results suggest that the ocean deep water could return to the upper ocean in a way different from the classical &ldquo;uniform upwelling&rdquo; or the famous &ldquo;ocean conveyor belt&rdquo; pictures. Vertically coherent upwelling and downwelling appear in the Southern Ocean and act as &ldquo;pipes&rdquo; to connect the upper and abyssal oceans. These structures are vitally important for the vertical exchanges of mass, properties, and tracers, particularly when external forcing (e.g., extra heat and carbon) continues acting on the sea surface. These zonally varying structures are usually canceled out in the conventional zonally averaged views. In addition, the PIs found intense subsurface upwelling associated with the major western boundary currents (WBCs) in the subtropical ocean basins, a potentially important yet neglected component of the global ocean circulation.</p> <p>Some results from this project have been published in five peer-reviewed journal articles. Four other journal articles are currently under review or in preparation for submission soon. The results were also disseminated through formal presentations in national and international conferences and invited talks to academic institutions. This project also supported the career development of the lead-PI, the training of a few graduate students at the University of South Florida (USF) and the University of Delaware (UD), as well as one REU summer student. The PI also included some of the findings into oceanography and climate courses he taught at USF and UD.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/21/2021<br>      Modified by: Xinfeng&nbsp;Liang</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The original goal of this project is to evaluate a large set of ocean reanalysis (ORA) products and determine if they are suitable for examining climatic-scale changes in global and regional ocean heat content. As conducting the proposed studies, the PIs realized the importance of identifying the "truth" of the ocean states and expanded the datasets to include available gridded Argo products.  The PIs analyzed some of the publicly available ocean data products to identify the robust signals in ocean variability and changes, and in the meantime, to quantify the uncertainty associated with those ocean variability and changes. More specifically, the PIs conducted intercomparisons of temporal and spatial variability in global ocean temperature and salinity from multiply gridded Argo-based products. Those studies revealed significant discrepancies in the various gridded Argo-based products in regions like the Southern Ocean and the North Atlantic. Conclusions on changes and variability in those regions could thus be product-dependent. These results can serve as valuable references for colleagues who will use one or more of those Argo-based products.   The PIs also conducted a few studies examining changes of temperature and salinity in different layers of the global ocean and exploring the contributions of internal oceanic variability to those changes. The PIs found that the vertical redistributions of ocean heat and salt contents contribute significantly to the upper ocean temperature and salinity changes, which have been used to infer the energy imbalance of the climate system and changes in global water cycles, respectively. These studies indicate that the ocean cannot be considered as a simple passive reservoir of heat and salt. Ocean dynamic processes should be considered in interpreting ocean changes, particularly those in the relatively well-observed upper ocean.  The PIs further investigated dynamic processes that are related to the vertical transport of ocean properties. In particular, the PIs examined the oceanic vertical velocity from ECCO (Estimating the Circulation and Climate of the Ocean) ocean state estimate. The results suggest that the ocean deep water could return to the upper ocean in a way different from the classical "uniform upwelling" or the famous "ocean conveyor belt" pictures. Vertically coherent upwelling and downwelling appear in the Southern Ocean and act as "pipes" to connect the upper and abyssal oceans. These structures are vitally important for the vertical exchanges of mass, properties, and tracers, particularly when external forcing (e.g., extra heat and carbon) continues acting on the sea surface. These zonally varying structures are usually canceled out in the conventional zonally averaged views. In addition, the PIs found intense subsurface upwelling associated with the major western boundary currents (WBCs) in the subtropical ocean basins, a potentially important yet neglected component of the global ocean circulation.  Some results from this project have been published in five peer-reviewed journal articles. Four other journal articles are currently under review or in preparation for submission soon. The results were also disseminated through formal presentations in national and international conferences and invited talks to academic institutions. This project also supported the career development of the lead-PI, the training of a few graduate students at the University of South Florida (USF) and the University of Delaware (UD), as well as one REU summer student. The PI also included some of the findings into oceanography and climate courses he taught at USF and UD.       Last Modified: 12/21/2021       Submitted by: Xinfeng Liang]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
