<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Stress Neurobiology Workshop, Columbia, SC, May 12-15, 2020]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>14400.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>14400</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IOS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kathleen Lynch</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>klynch@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922095</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The main goal of the Stress Neurobiology Workshop is to bring together researchers from all professional levels (undergraduate student to full professor) and from diverse disciplines to share and discuss recent findings toward understand the physiology associated with stress responses.  Based on prior meetings, the Workshop will have a significantly broad attendance profile, attracting members from many fields and thereby facilitating multidisciplinary discussions related to stress research. The Workshop focuses on stress-related effects that integrate multiple systems, including physiology, immune, endocrine, and autonomic responses, as well as behavioral outcomes and resilience to stress-related disorders from a preclinical perspective. The meeting is focused on fundamental mechanisms through which organisms respond to stress in multiple species across the lifespan. This workshop, which takes place at the University of South Carolina in Columbia, SC, is the 6th of a biannual workshop series that offers the only small meeting focused on the neurobiology of stress that is open to students and PIs alike. This Workshop provides an opportunity for extensive face-to-face interactions among researchers and trainees with overlapping interests. The meeting also provides some historical perspective, introducing young investigators to the iconic researchers in stress neurobiology and their seminal work. More than half of the speakers are women at different career stages, from diverse cultural or ethnic backgrounds, and with different academic credentials. The research presented at this meeting will ultimately advance the understating of how stress affects brain and behavior and will also help train the next generation of scientists in this field.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In recent years there have been significant advances in understanding the neurobiology of stress, including the neuronal circuits, neurochemistry, and genetics that mediate stress responses and stress adaptation that will be the focus of our meeting. Many of these advances are supported by exciting new approaches to studying the brain and brain-body interactions such as optogenetics or chemogenetics, emerging conceptual understanding of brain-body communication via exosomes and the microbiome, as well as improvements in the analysis of large data sets, imaging and bioinformatics. This workshop focuses on stress susceptibility across the lifespan, highlighting different mechanisms contributing to resilience in stress responses from adolescence to senescence using different stress models and animal species. Additional sessions emphasize the range of structural, behavioral, genomic, and physiological processes associated with stress with sessions on the HPA axis, autonomic function, and synaptic plasticity. The scientific program includes two keynote lectures, five plenary sessions with five speakers each; two roundtable sessions, one of which is dedicated to harassment/discrimination-free scientific environment; two poster sessions (trainee presenters only); and a data blitz presentation for the travel award recipients (Graduate student and Postdoctoral fellows). A major goal of this this four-day workshop is to promote the professional development of trainees of all stages, new investigators, under-represented groups, and women. The requested funds will be used to support travel awards for trainees to attend the meeting. The vigorous scientific exchange at these meetings also generates new ideas and forges novel collaborations that support future advances.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/23/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/23/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2021810</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Claudia</FirstName>
<LastName>Grillo</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Claudia A Grillo</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[claudia.grillo@uscmed.sc.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000612849</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/23/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lawrence</FirstName>
<LastName>Reagan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lawrence Reagan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[lpreagan@uscmed.sc.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000637952</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/23/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of South Carolina at Columbia</Name>
<CityName>COLUMBIA</CityName>
<ZipCode>292083403</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8037777093</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1600 HAMPTON ST # 414</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>South Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>SC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>SC06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>J22LNTMEDP73</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF SOUTH CAROLINA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>J22LNTMEDP73</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of South Carolina-Alumni Center]]></Name>
<CityName>Columbia</CityName>
<StateCode>SC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>292013158</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[900 Senate St]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>South Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>SC06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7714</Code>
<Text>Modulation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1096</Code>
<Text>NEURAL SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1228</Code>
<Text>MINORITY INVOLVEMENT -- BIO</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~14400</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Stress Neurobiology Workshop successfully took place in Columbia SC from May 10 to May 13, 2022. During the meeting, we were able to accomplish our main objectives such as:</p> <ul> <li>Bring together researchers (principal investigators and trainees) who study stress-brain interactions and the basic neurobiology of these interactions.</li> <li>Provide a forum to emphasize how behavioral, developmental, genetic, neural, and physiological processes are influenced by stress, and integrate these findings into how organisms adapt to stress.</li> <li>Promote exchange between stress researchers based in different disciplines.</li> <li>Foster a community of basic science stress researchers.</li> <li>Promote the professional development of new investigators, women and underrepresented groups that have research programs with a stress component.</li> <li>Provide a venue to discuss issues of harassment and discrimination, and how to address these problems.</li> <li>Nurture career development of undergraduate, graduate students and postdoctoral researchers.</li> </ul> <p>The funds provided by the NSF were crucial to support participation of trainees, with targeted strategies for recruitment of a diverse attendee roster.&nbsp;Nineteen trainees were supported by the NSF funds, and five trainees were supported by a private donor. Dr. Claudia Grillo (Principal Investigator on this proposal) served as the Chair of the selection committee for the Travel Awards, ensuring consideration of the inclusion of women and underrepresented groups in the selection process. The abstracts were distributed by Dr. Grillo to a six-member committee and each candidate was reviewed and ranked by at least two members of the committee. Drs. Matthew Hill (University Calgary), Ilia Karatsoreos (University of Massachusetts), Linda Rinaman (Florida State University), Katie Morrison (West Virginia University), Larry Reagan (University of South Carolina), and Claudia Grillo (University of South Carolina) served on the committee. The travel awardees received funds to help defray the cost of travel to attend the 2022 Stress Neurobiology Workshop.</p> <p>Nineteen trainees were supported by the NSF funds, and five trainees were supported by a private donor. The awardees represented 19 different Institutions and 15 different states; additionally, one of the awardees was from Canada. The awardees were able to present their findings on Wednesday May 11<sup>th</sup>&nbsp;in a Data Blitz session chaired by Dr. Grillo. This session consisted of a five-minute oral presentation by each award winner, in addition to the poster presentation.&nbsp;On Thursday, May 12<sup>th</sup> there was a roundtable discussion on harassment. Dr. Rhonda Davis, Head of the Office of Diversity and Inclusion at NSF participated and helped us to organize this session. Additional professional development opportunities for trainees were available during &ldquo;meet the investigator&rdquo; roundtable discussions held during breakfast hour on Thursday.</p> <p>&nbsp;Undergraduate students, graduate students and post-doctoral fellows acquired new knowledge in a small, intimate setting that allowed them to directly interact with leaders in stress neurobiology. All trainees could actively participate in the opening reception, Data Blitz session, poster sessions, plenary sessions, discussion periods and the roundtable breakfasts planned to allow trainees to interact with senior investigators and networking. &nbsp;We also had a session for identification/discussion of trainee-specific funding opportunities. The NSF funds allowed a greater number of trainees to attend the meeting and thereby benefit from these career development opportunities.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/14/2023<br>      Modified by: Claudia&nbsp;A&nbsp;Grillo</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Stress Neurobiology Workshop successfully took place in Columbia SC from May 10 to May 13, 2022. During the meeting, we were able to accomplish our main objectives such as:  Bring together researchers (principal investigators and trainees) who study stress-brain interactions and the basic neurobiology of these interactions. Provide a forum to emphasize how behavioral, developmental, genetic, neural, and physiological processes are influenced by stress, and integrate these findings into how organisms adapt to stress. Promote exchange between stress researchers based in different disciplines. Foster a community of basic science stress researchers. Promote the professional development of new investigators, women and underrepresented groups that have research programs with a stress component. Provide a venue to discuss issues of harassment and discrimination, and how to address these problems. Nurture career development of undergraduate, graduate students and postdoctoral researchers.   The funds provided by the NSF were crucial to support participation of trainees, with targeted strategies for recruitment of a diverse attendee roster. Nineteen trainees were supported by the NSF funds, and five trainees were supported by a private donor. Dr. Claudia Grillo (Principal Investigator on this proposal) served as the Chair of the selection committee for the Travel Awards, ensuring consideration of the inclusion of women and underrepresented groups in the selection process. The abstracts were distributed by Dr. Grillo to a six-member committee and each candidate was reviewed and ranked by at least two members of the committee. Drs. Matthew Hill (University Calgary), Ilia Karatsoreos (University of Massachusetts), Linda Rinaman (Florida State University), Katie Morrison (West Virginia University), Larry Reagan (University of South Carolina), and Claudia Grillo (University of South Carolina) served on the committee. The travel awardees received funds to help defray the cost of travel to attend the 2022 Stress Neurobiology Workshop.  Nineteen trainees were supported by the NSF funds, and five trainees were supported by a private donor. The awardees represented 19 different Institutions and 15 different states; additionally, one of the awardees was from Canada. The awardees were able to present their findings on Wednesday May 11th in a Data Blitz session chaired by Dr. Grillo. This session consisted of a five-minute oral presentation by each award winner, in addition to the poster presentation. On Thursday, May 12th there was a roundtable discussion on harassment. Dr. Rhonda Davis, Head of the Office of Diversity and Inclusion at NSF participated and helped us to organize this session. Additional professional development opportunities for trainees were available during "meet the investigator" roundtable discussions held during breakfast hour on Thursday.   Undergraduate students, graduate students and post-doctoral fellows acquired new knowledge in a small, intimate setting that allowed them to directly interact with leaders in stress neurobiology. All trainees could actively participate in the opening reception, Data Blitz session, poster sessions, plenary sessions, discussion periods and the roundtable breakfasts planned to allow trainees to interact with senior investigators and networking.  We also had a session for identification/discussion of trainee-specific funding opportunities. The NSF funds allowed a greater number of trainees to attend the meeting and thereby benefit from these career development opportunities.        Last Modified: 02/14/2023       Submitted by: Claudia A Grillo]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
