<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Doctoral Dissertation Research in DRMS: Assembling Teams Supported by Augmented Intelligence]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>31916.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>31916</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Robert O'Connor</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>roconnor@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927263</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Diversity can yield measurable benefits for teams and organizations. Prior research shows that functional diversity––the degree to which  team  members  differ  in terms of their experience or background––can positively influence team functioning through the increase of information, skills, ability, and knowledge that diversity may bring. Though emerging societal norms advocate diversity and inclusion, hardwired tendencies create an attraction to people who are similar and familiar. This poses a challenge to organizations seeking to leverage the benefits of diversity in teams. Can technologies help organizations and their co-workers assemble more diverse teams? This Doctoral Dissertation Research Improvement Grant (DDRIG) seeks to understand  how  augmented  intelligence technologies can facilitate people to assemble in functional diverse teams. The findings and applications of this research will contribute to stakeholder communities that are invested in increasing diversity in teams. The research will also deliver a team recommender system to the public for enabling participants to assemble their own teams using augmented intelligence, and enabling participants to discuss and learn about diversity.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research involves a program of laboratory experiments controlling the presence and absence of human agency and augmented intelligence when individuals are assembling  teams. The project will assess the formation processes of teams assembled (a) randomly, (b) by participants, and (c) by participants using augmented intelligence. The research will examine the three team formation conditions and analyze participants’ search queries, decisions to invite or accept invitations from potential teammates, their resulting teams’ composition, and performance. The project will also study their interaction processes and outcomes after the team is formed.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/13/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/13/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2021117</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Noshir</FirstName>
<LastName>Contractor</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Noshir S Contractor</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[nosh@northwestern.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000470079</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/13/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Leslie</FirstName>
<LastName>DeChurch</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Leslie A DeChurch</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[dechurch@northwestern.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000532400</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/13/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Diego</FirstName>
<LastName>Gomez-Zara</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Diego A Gomez-Zara</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[dgomezara@nd.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000808488</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/13/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Northwestern University</Name>
<CityName>EVANSTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>602080001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3125037955</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>633 CLARK STREET</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>EXZVPWZBLUE8</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORTHWESTERN UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Northwestern University]]></Name>
<CityName>Evanston</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>602080834</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2145 Sheridan Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1321</Code>
<Text>Decision, Risk &amp; Mgmt Sci</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~31916</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><div class="page" title="Page 280"> <div class="layoutArea"> <div class="column"> <p>This project examines the impact of recommender systems on team composition and performance. We studied the specific effects of personal &shy;agency (i.e., when users are allowed to choose their teammates) and algorithmic diversity (i.e., using rules and scripts to maximize team diversity) when individuals choose teammates. We conducted a laboratory study with 386 participants to test the effect of the recommender system on individuals&rsquo; teaming experience, team processes, and team outcomes. Our results indicate that teams are more likely to benefit from diversity when they can self&shy;-assemble teams guided by a computational system.&nbsp;</p> <p><br />This project contributes to research on teams by explaining the effects of diversity and agency on team composition, processes, and performance. Results indicate that diversity alone is not enough to guarantee teams&rsquo; success. When providing agency to this pro&shy;cess, participants had a better experience and results than teams randomly assembled or self&shy; assembled. A small intervention in the recommender system&rsquo;s algorithm allowed participants to form teams with higher gender diversity levels and a better balance of experts and novices than the search-driven algorithm. The current findings provide nuance on the effects of diver&shy;sity on teams. By giving insights into how diversity and agency influence teams, this project deepens our understanding of team formation and its con&shy; sequences.&nbsp;</p> <p><br />This award also facilitated the development of our team formation platform, <em>MyDreamTeam</em>. The platform will help people self-assemble teams using recommender algorithms developed during this research. MyDreamTeam is available at <a href="https://v2mdt.soc.northwestern.edu/" target="_blank">https://v2mdt.soc.northwestern.edu/</a>. People can use it for free. Managers and instructors can create an account and invite their employees and students to self-assemble teams. MyDreamTeam can be used by other institutions for (a) conducting new experiments about team formation and diversity, (b) enabling participants to assemble their own teams using augmented intelligence, and (c) enabling participants to discuss and learn about diversity.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> </div> </div> </div><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/27/2022<br>      Modified by: Diego&nbsp;A&nbsp;Gomez-Zara</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[    This project examines the impact of recommender systems on team composition and performance. We studied the specific effects of personal &shy;agency (i.e., when users are allowed to choose their teammates) and algorithmic diversity (i.e., using rules and scripts to maximize team diversity) when individuals choose teammates. We conducted a laboratory study with 386 participants to test the effect of the recommender system on individuals’ teaming experience, team processes, and team outcomes. Our results indicate that teams are more likely to benefit from diversity when they can self&shy;-assemble teams guided by a computational system.    This project contributes to research on teams by explaining the effects of diversity and agency on team composition, processes, and performance. Results indicate that diversity alone is not enough to guarantee teams’ success. When providing agency to this pro&shy;cess, participants had a better experience and results than teams randomly assembled or self&shy; assembled. A small intervention in the recommender system’s algorithm allowed participants to form teams with higher gender diversity levels and a better balance of experts and novices than the search-driven algorithm. The current findings provide nuance on the effects of diver&shy;sity on teams. By giving insights into how diversity and agency influence teams, this project deepens our understanding of team formation and its con&shy; sequences.    This award also facilitated the development of our team formation platform, MyDreamTeam. The platform will help people self-assemble teams using recommender algorithms developed during this research. MyDreamTeam is available at https://v2mdt.soc.northwestern.edu/. People can use it for free. Managers and instructors can create an account and invite their employees and students to self-assemble teams. MyDreamTeam can be used by other institutions for (a) conducting new experiments about team formation and diversity, (b) enabling participants to assemble their own teams using augmented intelligence, and (c) enabling participants to discuss and learn about diversity.              Last Modified: 09/27/2022       Submitted by: Diego A Gomez-Zara]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
