<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Broadening participation in Economics through professional mentoring]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>11/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>254795.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>254795</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Nancy Lutz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>nlutz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927280</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This award funds a graduate student mentoring program that is part of a broader suite of efforts that work to broaden participation in  Economics. The mentoring program is conducted by the investigator in collaboration with the American Economic Association's Committee on the Status of Minority Groups in the Economics Profession. The mentoring program helps students from under-represented groups navigate a number of critical stages in their development as scientists as they go from the early stages of graduate study through completing dissertation research and starting their first post-doctoral position. Students meet regularly with their program mentors at a variety of professional conferences around the country. An annual workshop brings all participants together for research presentations; this workshop is held in conjunction with a summer program aimed at undergraduate students who are interested in careers in Social and Economic Science. The graduate students benefit from both working with their own mentors and are able to serve as mentors in turn to more junior students. The mentoring program also promotes the research and professional development of the student participants by funding travel to other professional conferences, travel to work with mentors or access data, and funds for other research expenses. Increasing the number of graduate-trained economists is in the national interest for multiple reasons. The Office of Personnel Management (OPM) in 2016 called for continued work to close the skill gap in the Economics profession, which is a Government-wide high-risk mission critical occupation (MCO).  Experience demonstrates that some graduates of the mentoring program will go on to government service. Others will contribute by working as professors to train future generations of economists.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Program participants will be followed over time to help evaluate program success; this evaluation will include the full group of efforts to broaden participation by Hispanics, Blacks, and Native Americans in the Economics profession. Evaluation results will be used to develop new ideas and methods for future mentoring efforts.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/19/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/19/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2021600</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Marie</FirstName>
<LastName>Mora</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>T</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Marie T Mora</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mmora16@msudenver.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000649279</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/19/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Missouri-Saint Louis</Name>
<CityName>SAINT LOUIS</CityName>
<ZipCode>631214400</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3145165897</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1 UNIVERSITY BLVD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MO01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>GWCTP4CQ1E65</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MISSOURI SYSTEM</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Missouri-Saint Louis]]></Name>
<CityName>Saint Louis</CityName>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>631214400</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[One University Blvd]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MO01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1320</Code>
<Text>Economics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8050</Code>
<Text>Science of Broadening Participation</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01001718DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~254794</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>OVERVIEW </strong></p> <p>African Americans, Hispanics/Latinos, and Native Americans have traditionally been underrepresented in U.S. STEM disciplines, including economics.&nbsp;This NSF project has funded the American Economic Association Mentoring Program (AEAMP) - one of the signature programs of the AEA Committee on the Status of Minority Groups in the Economics Profession (CSMGEP) which matches economics Ph.D. students and new Ph.D. graduates from traditionally underrepresented groups in the U.S. economics profession with senior economists as mentors, thus broadening participation in an often-overlooked STEM field.</p> <p>One key activity is the AEA Summer Mentoring Pipeline Conference (SMPC) that brings together the mentees, their mentors, undergraduate students in the AEA Summer Program (another CSMGEP program), and other senior economists in and outside of academia. Mentees present their research, meet with mentors, participate in panels and other professional development activities, and network with economists at all stages, from undergraduate students to distinguished senior economists. Moreover, this project supported mentees to present research, meet their mentors, and network at other major conferences. It also hosted a real-time annual Job Market Bootcamp for mentees (for both academic and non-academic jobs), and starting in 2022, an early-career tenure-track mentoring workshop.</p> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p><strong>PROJECT OUTCOMES</strong></p> <p><strong><em>SMPC. </em></strong>During this project, four SMPCs were held (2018, 2019, 2021 (virtual), and 2022) that included approximately 120 participants for each of&nbsp; the in-person conferences.</p> <p><em><strong>Graduates.</strong> </em>At least 40 mentees graduated with their Ph.D.s in economics or applied economics fields from at least 27 Ph.D.-granting institutions across the country, ranging from highly-selective "elite" institutions (e.g., Stanford, MIT, Cornell) to prestigious state universities (e.g., University of Pennsylvania, Texas A&amp;M University, University of California Berkeley, University of Minnesota) to major public and private universities (e.g., Howard University, UNC Greensboro, CUNY Graduate Center).</p> <p><strong><em>Employment.</em> </strong>Some graduates secured post-doc positions (including at Brown University), with the vast majority securing more permanent employment as faculty at a variety of institutions (including Harvard, Duke, Howard, Wesleyan, Florida State, University of Washington, UNC Chapel Hill, and others) and in non-academic positions (e.g., U.S. Department of Labor, U.S. Census Bureau, Bureau of Economic Analysis, USDA, American Cancer Society, Inter-American Development Bank, Mathematica, PwC).</p> <p><strong><em>Presentations. </em></strong>In addition to the 32 presentations given by mentees during the SMPCs, the project supported 52 presentations at other major conferences (e.g., AEA/ASSA, Southern Economic Association, Western Economic Association International, etc.).&nbsp;</p> <p><strong><em>Publications. </em></strong>Mentees published at least eight refereed journal articles (single- or co-authored) during this project, including in the <em>Journal of Public Economics, Contemporary Economic Policy, Journal of Industrial Economics, Economics of Education Review, American Journal of Agricultural Economics</em>, <em>Review of Black Political Economy</em>. &nbsp;</p> <p><strong><em>AEA Funding and Institutionalization. </em></strong>The AEA began funding the AEAMP near the conclusion of this project, reflecting another measure of success as the project activities are now institutionalized within the U.S. economics profession.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>INTELLECTUAL MERIT</strong></p> <p>Given the vast underrepresentation of African Americans, Hispanics/Latinos, and Native Americans in the U.S. economics profession, academic and applied research and subsequent policy recommendations which directly (and indirectly) affect the economic outcomes of these populations are often shaped without the perspectives of members of these groups, resulting in incomplete information about what actually occurs "on the ground". Thus, an increase in the number and representation of African Americans, Hispanics/Latinos, and Native Americans in economics should lead to more informed economic and public policy formulation, discussion, and implementation.&nbsp;</p> <p>Moreover, beyond serving as role models for students and other faculty members of all races/ethnicities, having a diverse economics faculty expands the range of perspectives and experiences to which students in economics courses are exposed. A diversified economics profession further expands the range of perspectives and experiences that economists and those interacting with economists encounter outside academia. &nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>BROADER IMPACTS</strong></p> <p>Having more informed economic and public policy formulation, discussion, and implementation will not only affect African Americans, Hispanics/Latinos, and Native Americans. Their economic outcomes impact the U.S. overall, especially when considering that combined, these groups represent one-third of the U.S. population. As such, their outcomes affect national economic growth, prosperity, national security, and global competitiveness.</p> <p>Moreover, academic economists find employment beyond Economics Departments; many find work in schools of public policy, health, social work, business, and law.&nbsp; Beyond serving as role models for students and other faculty members of all races/ethnicities, having a diverse faculty in these venues expands the range of perspectives and experiences to which students in a variety of disciplines are exposed, and serves to offset preconceived notions and stereotypes some students might have about diverse populations.&nbsp;</p> <p>This level of exposure to members of different races/ethnicities also helps prepare students and employees to work productively in an increasingly diverse and globally competitive workforce.&nbsp; Moreover, the academic and applied research conducted by the mentees as students and in their academic and non-academic careers is often highly interdisciplinary, covering a variety of disciplines:&nbsp; health, crime, finance, women and development, immigration, discrimination, stratification, education, history, and others.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/03/2023<br>      Modified by: Marie&nbsp;T&nbsp;Mora</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ OVERVIEW   African Americans, Hispanics/Latinos, and Native Americans have traditionally been underrepresented in U.S. STEM disciplines, including economics. This NSF project has funded the American Economic Association Mentoring Program (AEAMP) - one of the signature programs of the AEA Committee on the Status of Minority Groups in the Economics Profession (CSMGEP) which matches economics Ph.D. students and new Ph.D. graduates from traditionally underrepresented groups in the U.S. economics profession with senior economists as mentors, thus broadening participation in an often-overlooked STEM field.  One key activity is the AEA Summer Mentoring Pipeline Conference (SMPC) that brings together the mentees, their mentors, undergraduate students in the AEA Summer Program (another CSMGEP program), and other senior economists in and outside of academia. Mentees present their research, meet with mentors, participate in panels and other professional development activities, and network with economists at all stages, from undergraduate students to distinguished senior economists. Moreover, this project supported mentees to present research, meet their mentors, and network at other major conferences. It also hosted a real-time annual Job Market Bootcamp for mentees (for both academic and non-academic jobs), and starting in 2022, an early-career tenure-track mentoring workshop.     PROJECT OUTCOMES  SMPC. During this project, four SMPCs were held (2018, 2019, 2021 (virtual), and 2022) that included approximately 120 participants for each of  the in-person conferences.  Graduates. At least 40 mentees graduated with their Ph.D.s in economics or applied economics fields from at least 27 Ph.D.-granting institutions across the country, ranging from highly-selective "elite" institutions (e.g., Stanford, MIT, Cornell) to prestigious state universities (e.g., University of Pennsylvania, Texas A&amp;M University, University of California Berkeley, University of Minnesota) to major public and private universities (e.g., Howard University, UNC Greensboro, CUNY Graduate Center).  Employment. Some graduates secured post-doc positions (including at Brown University), with the vast majority securing more permanent employment as faculty at a variety of institutions (including Harvard, Duke, Howard, Wesleyan, Florida State, University of Washington, UNC Chapel Hill, and others) and in non-academic positions (e.g., U.S. Department of Labor, U.S. Census Bureau, Bureau of Economic Analysis, USDA, American Cancer Society, Inter-American Development Bank, Mathematica, PwC).  Presentations. In addition to the 32 presentations given by mentees during the SMPCs, the project supported 52 presentations at other major conferences (e.g., AEA/ASSA, Southern Economic Association, Western Economic Association International, etc.).   Publications. Mentees published at least eight refereed journal articles (single- or co-authored) during this project, including in the Journal of Public Economics, Contemporary Economic Policy, Journal of Industrial Economics, Economics of Education Review, American Journal of Agricultural Economics, Review of Black Political Economy.    AEA Funding and Institutionalization. The AEA began funding the AEAMP near the conclusion of this project, reflecting another measure of success as the project activities are now institutionalized within the U.S. economics profession.     INTELLECTUAL MERIT  Given the vast underrepresentation of African Americans, Hispanics/Latinos, and Native Americans in the U.S. economics profession, academic and applied research and subsequent policy recommendations which directly (and indirectly) affect the economic outcomes of these populations are often shaped without the perspectives of members of these groups, resulting in incomplete information about what actually occurs "on the ground". Thus, an increase in the number and representation of African Americans, Hispanics/Latinos, and Native Americans in economics should lead to more informed economic and public policy formulation, discussion, and implementation.   Moreover, beyond serving as role models for students and other faculty members of all races/ethnicities, having a diverse economics faculty expands the range of perspectives and experiences to which students in economics courses are exposed. A diversified economics profession further expands the range of perspectives and experiences that economists and those interacting with economists encounter outside academia.       BROADER IMPACTS  Having more informed economic and public policy formulation, discussion, and implementation will not only affect African Americans, Hispanics/Latinos, and Native Americans. Their economic outcomes impact the U.S. overall, especially when considering that combined, these groups represent one-third of the U.S. population. As such, their outcomes affect national economic growth, prosperity, national security, and global competitiveness.  Moreover, academic economists find employment beyond Economics Departments; many find work in schools of public policy, health, social work, business, and law.  Beyond serving as role models for students and other faculty members of all races/ethnicities, having a diverse faculty in these venues expands the range of perspectives and experiences to which students in a variety of disciplines are exposed, and serves to offset preconceived notions and stereotypes some students might have about diverse populations.   This level of exposure to members of different races/ethnicities also helps prepare students and employees to work productively in an increasingly diverse and globally competitive workforce.  Moreover, the academic and applied research conducted by the mentees as students and in their academic and non-academic careers is often highly interdisciplinary, covering a variety of disciplines:  health, crime, finance, women and development, immigration, discrimination, stratification, education, history, and others.       Last Modified: 01/03/2023       Submitted by: Marie T Mora]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
