<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Research: Moral foundation frame effectiveness in sustainable policy introductions</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>30500.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>30500</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SMA</Abbreviation>
<LongName>SBE Off Of Multidisciplinary Activities</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Mary Feeney</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mfeeney@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927197</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Across much of the United States, the public does not consider water policy a divisive topic; however as the limits of regional water resources are approached and water demands must be prioritized, there is high potential for water policy to become politically charged with liberals and conservatives maintaining divergent positions. The ability of water policy communicators to minimize polarization will affect the degree to which stakeholders are willing to work together toward water solutions. Research indicates that communicators can reduce polarization by purposefully framing natural resources challenges with moral positions, such as fairness, loyalty, and harm, that vary in resonance across the political spectrum. However, such studies focus primarily on issues such as climate change, where partisan opinions have already taken hold, not studies in which the objective is to prevent partisanship from forming. Further, few studies sufficiently model the competitive environment of policy introductions, with public officials and outside interests vying to define issues for the public, and with social cues, such as the political affiliations of spokespeople, indicating the positions that fellow partisans are expected to take. This project addresses these gaps, with an experimental assessment of the use of moral frames to prevent partisanship in competitive water policy introductions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The study will be conducted in two parts. First, Rasch modelling will be used to develop a water knowledge assessment. The assessment will be combined with a survey of water beliefs and administered to a sample of potential voters. The results will provide a detailed assessment of the public's comprehension of basic water science and regional water issues, indicate water subtopics from which polarization could develop, and identify the sources voters trust for water information. Based on these findings, the second part of the study will use an experimental design to simulate a competitive policy introduction. Two aspects of policy frames that convey value priorities will be assessed: moral foundations expressed through language and communicator identities that function as partisan decision heuristics. Additionally, characteristics of message recipients that moderate framing effects will be assessed including political self-identity and participant water knowledge as measured using the assessment developed in part one. From this research, a model will be created that describes how the influence of frame stimuli and the moderating characteristics of message recipients affect citizen-level sustainable policy decisions under competitive conditions. The research will clarify the conditions under which moral foundation frames restrain division on potentially divisive policy and provide more complete understanding of the degree to which non-competitive moral foundation framing studies set realistic expectations for frame effectiveness in applied policy scenarios. Findings of the research will be used to frame a series of publications about regional water challenges that increase water science literacy and promote informed citizen-level decision making. Research findings will also be published in a water communicator guide and shared with regional decision makers through Water Schools to help government officials and other community leaders guide productive water policy discourse.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/19/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/13/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2021590</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Martha</FirstName>
<LastName>Monroe</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Martha Monroe</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mcmonroe@ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3523923516</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000501250</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/19/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sarah</FirstName>
<LastName>Hundemer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sarah E Hundemer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>shundemer@ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8507765070</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000813574</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/19/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Florida</Name>
<CityName>GAINESVILLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>326111941</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3523923516</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1523 UNION RD RM 207</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NNFQH1JAPEP3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF FLORIDA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>D4GCCCMXR1H3</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Florida]]></Name>
<CityName>GAINESVILLE</CityName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>326112002</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1 UNIVERSITY OF FLORIDA]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>125Y</Code>
<Text>Science of Science</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7626</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE OF SCIENCE POLICY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~30500</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Our first study aimed to determine the public&rsquo;s level of water knowledge in the Floridan aquifer region, and the degree to which political partisanship affects public acceptance of water science. The findings indicate that a large portion of Florida and Georgia residents lack the water science knowledge needed to competently participate in water discussion and make citizen-level voting decisions on water topics. Moreover, some partisan individuals demonstrate a willingness to reject what they perceive to be the beliefs of water scientists. Specifically, this behavior was observed on the impact of climate change on water availability and on the adequacy of water supply to meet demand 20 years in the future. These results suggest that efforts to increase public knowledge could be unproductive with some segments of the population. Furthermore, the partisan basis on which the rejection of water science occurred suggests that partisanship could heighten as water challenges more robustly enter the public consciousness. Though this study was conducted in Florida and Georgia, the water topics on which this behavior was observed are not region specific. Therefore, the observed polarization risk likely applies at broader regional and national scales.</p> <p>This research clarified the potential for water partisanship in the Floridan aquifer region. Because water is not yet a highly intrusive topic for most people in the region, it was not known to what extent partisanship was positioned to emerge as water issues escalate due to growth and climate change. Now the likelihood of heightened water partisanship has been made visible for public officials and interventional strategies can be designed to minimize partisanship development. In addition, this work provides a reproducible method for other researchers to assess polarization potential in their regions and on other topics poised to emerge in prominence (e.g., green technologies, climate adaptation).</p> <p>The second study addressed a major gap in policy framing literature. While it had been empirically demonstrated that moral foundation frames and source cues have the capacity to amplify or constrain political partisanship, few studies had examined the effectiveness of moral foundation frames and source cues in combination or in competitive conditions with parties attempting to persuade potential voters to opposing sides. These are the real world conditions that determine policy communication effectiveness.</p> <p>This research exposed the complexity of the water communication environment through an experiment in which Florida and Georgia residents indicated their support for a fictional water policy that was advocated for and opposed by politically-identified sources with moral arguments. The findings indicate that moral foundation frames and politically-identifiable source cues can have fundamentally different effects on policy support. While moral frames yielded changes in net water policy support levels, politically-identified source cues affected the distribution of that support across the political spectrum. Both of these impacts are important for policy acceptance and should be recognized and attended to by communicators and policy makers. Competition between alternative moral arguments and opposing source cues moderated framing effects, heightening political division in some scenarios and abating division in others. These findings call into question the expectations set by simple framing studies. Furthermore, the findings establish a new line of research aimed at more precisely defining the conditions that moderate the effectiveness of moral frames.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/30/2021<br>      Modified by: Sarah&nbsp;E&nbsp;Hundemer</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Our first study aimed to determine the public’s level of water knowledge in the Floridan aquifer region, and the degree to which political partisanship affects public acceptance of water science. The findings indicate that a large portion of Florida and Georgia residents lack the water science knowledge needed to competently participate in water discussion and make citizen-level voting decisions on water topics. Moreover, some partisan individuals demonstrate a willingness to reject what they perceive to be the beliefs of water scientists. Specifically, this behavior was observed on the impact of climate change on water availability and on the adequacy of water supply to meet demand 20 years in the future. These results suggest that efforts to increase public knowledge could be unproductive with some segments of the population. Furthermore, the partisan basis on which the rejection of water science occurred suggests that partisanship could heighten as water challenges more robustly enter the public consciousness. Though this study was conducted in Florida and Georgia, the water topics on which this behavior was observed are not region specific. Therefore, the observed polarization risk likely applies at broader regional and national scales.  This research clarified the potential for water partisanship in the Floridan aquifer region. Because water is not yet a highly intrusive topic for most people in the region, it was not known to what extent partisanship was positioned to emerge as water issues escalate due to growth and climate change. Now the likelihood of heightened water partisanship has been made visible for public officials and interventional strategies can be designed to minimize partisanship development. In addition, this work provides a reproducible method for other researchers to assess polarization potential in their regions and on other topics poised to emerge in prominence (e.g., green technologies, climate adaptation).  The second study addressed a major gap in policy framing literature. While it had been empirically demonstrated that moral foundation frames and source cues have the capacity to amplify or constrain political partisanship, few studies had examined the effectiveness of moral foundation frames and source cues in combination or in competitive conditions with parties attempting to persuade potential voters to opposing sides. These are the real world conditions that determine policy communication effectiveness.  This research exposed the complexity of the water communication environment through an experiment in which Florida and Georgia residents indicated their support for a fictional water policy that was advocated for and opposed by politically-identified sources with moral arguments. The findings indicate that moral foundation frames and politically-identifiable source cues can have fundamentally different effects on policy support. While moral frames yielded changes in net water policy support levels, politically-identified source cues affected the distribution of that support across the political spectrum. Both of these impacts are important for policy acceptance and should be recognized and attended to by communicators and policy makers. Competition between alternative moral arguments and opposing source cues moderated framing effects, heightening political division in some scenarios and abating division in others. These findings call into question the expectations set by simple framing studies. Furthermore, the findings establish a new line of research aimed at more precisely defining the conditions that moderate the effectiveness of moral frames.          Last Modified: 08/30/2021       Submitted by: Sarah E Hundemer]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
