<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>N-Amino peptide-derived beta-sheet mimics</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/07/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>215119.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>215119</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Pui Ho</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>puiho@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032920000</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>With this award, the Chemistry of Life Processes Program in the Chemistry Division is funding Professor Juan Del Valle from the University of South Florida. The project is an investigation of a new class of modified peptides that mimic protein structure. Proteins are the workhorses of the cell, and interactions between proteins govern many biological processes. The ability to modify these interactions with designed molecules (peptides) has been a long-standing challenge in chemistry. Professor Del Valle's work focuses on the mimicry of beta-sheets. This is a protein structure that is notoriously difficult to study due its tendency to clump together (aggregate). This research provides a toolkit for generating stable and aggregation-resistant mimics of the protein beta sheets.  The project is also providing graduate and undergraduate students with rigorous training in laboratory research and scientific communication. The project is linked to the Tampa Preparatory School in an outreach effort providing internships to high school students. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research project integrates molecular design, chemical synthesis, conformational analysis, and biological studies to fully characterize the properties of backbone-aminated peptides. The Del Valle laboratory recently established methods to prepare C-alpha-substituted N-amino peptides (NAPs) through conventional solid-phase peptide synthesis. This project develops optimal synthetic protocols toward cyclic, macrocyclic, and polyaminated NAP variants for bi-facial beta-strand mimicry. The motifs are evaluated in model systems for their specific effects on beta-sheet stability and self-association using a combination of nuclear magnetic resonance spectroscopy, circular dichroism, and X-ray diffraction. The discrete impact of NAP constraints on protease/serum stability and passive membrane permeability relative to control peptides are being examined.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/27/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/27/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2021265</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Juan</FirstName>
<LastName>Del Valle</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Juan Del Valle</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jdelvalle@nd.edu</EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000684159</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/27/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Notre Dame</Name>
<CityName>NOTRE DAME</CityName>
<ZipCode>465565708</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5746317432</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>940 Grace Hall</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IN02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>824910376</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF NOTRE DAME DU LAC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>048994727</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Notre Dame]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>465565708</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IN02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6883</Code>
<Text>Chemistry of Life Processes</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01001718DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~215119</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Intellectual merit: Protein-protein interactions (PPIs) control a vast array of cellular processes. Despite the importance of well-defined protein-protein interfaces in promoting various diseases, the development of molecules capable of disrupting these interactions remains a significant challenge. PPIs are governed by recognition events between peptide secondary structures (a-helices, beta-sheets, beta-turns), which provide design cues for the development of chemical probes. However, removal of ordered peptide domains from the context of their surrounding environment compromises folding and stability.&nbsp; During this award period, our goal was to develop a new class of&nbsp; beta-strand mimics &nbsp;based on peptides featuring backbone <em>N</em>-amination. <em>The long-term goal of this work is to provide the scientific community with a versatile molecular toolkit for mimicry of protein beta</em><em>-strand and beta</em><em>-sheet domains.</em> We have successfully carried out the synthesis of N-amino peptides that stabilize beta-sheet folds and can serve as minimal ligands of beta-sheet-rich proteins that are difficult to target. We have demonstrated the versatility of this approach through the design of soluble peptide mimics that bind beta-amyloid and tau &ndash; proteins that assemble to form toxic fibrils in humans. Our synthetic advancements have also enabled us to prepare antimicrobial beta-sheet mimics, N-heteroatom-subtituted natural products, and other stabilized secondary structures based on N-aminated peptides. This work sets the stage for the rational design of minimalist protein mimics that can be used to modulate a variety of biological pathways.</p> <p>Broader impacts: The project led to 8 peer-reviewed publications which have been made available to public. The data has also been presented in conferences. The project provided outstanding training opportunities for graduate students to acquire skills in organic synthesis, chemical biology and biophysical analysis. This project also integrated teaching, research and outreach activities to provide hands-on laboratory experience to high school and undergraduate students.</p> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/28/2021<br>      Modified by: Juan&nbsp;Del Valle</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Intellectual merit: Protein-protein interactions (PPIs) control a vast array of cellular processes. Despite the importance of well-defined protein-protein interfaces in promoting various diseases, the development of molecules capable of disrupting these interactions remains a significant challenge. PPIs are governed by recognition events between peptide secondary structures (a-helices, beta-sheets, beta-turns), which provide design cues for the development of chemical probes. However, removal of ordered peptide domains from the context of their surrounding environment compromises folding and stability.  During this award period, our goal was to develop a new class of  beta-strand mimics  based on peptides featuring backbone N-amination. The long-term goal of this work is to provide the scientific community with a versatile molecular toolkit for mimicry of protein beta-strand and beta-sheet domains. We have successfully carried out the synthesis of N-amino peptides that stabilize beta-sheet folds and can serve as minimal ligands of beta-sheet-rich proteins that are difficult to target. We have demonstrated the versatility of this approach through the design of soluble peptide mimics that bind beta-amyloid and tau &ndash; proteins that assemble to form toxic fibrils in humans. Our synthetic advancements have also enabled us to prepare antimicrobial beta-sheet mimics, N-heteroatom-subtituted natural products, and other stabilized secondary structures based on N-aminated peptides. This work sets the stage for the rational design of minimalist protein mimics that can be used to modulate a variety of biological pathways.  Broader impacts: The project led to 8 peer-reviewed publications which have been made available to public. The data has also been presented in conferences. The project provided outstanding training opportunities for graduate students to acquire skills in organic synthesis, chemical biology and biophysical analysis. This project also integrated teaching, research and outreach activities to provide hands-on laboratory experience to high school and undergraduate students.             Last Modified: 11/28/2021       Submitted by: Juan Del Valle]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
