<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[BPC-A: Institute for African-American Mentoring in Computing Sciences (iAAMCS)]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>500000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>500000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jeffrey Forbes</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jforbes@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925301</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The University of Florida will document and demonstrate the impact of the Institute for African-American Mentoring in Computing Sciences (iAAMCS, pronounced ‘I am CS’) on broadening participation in computing. iAAMCS is intended to serve as a national resource to students, faculty, and industry professionals. A major goal of iAAMCS is to significantly increase the number of Black/African Americans pursuing and completing the Ph.D. in computing fields through a national mentoring model. The programs and activities implemented as a part of this model focus on leveraging and developing evidence-based strategies to encourage African American’s participation in computing, specifically at the Ph.D. level and beyond. Although representation in attainment of computer science degrees at the bachelor's level is on par with representation in the country (African Americans represent 13.4% of the U.S. population), African Americans represent approximately 0.8% and 1.2% of the master's and Ph.D. recipients, respectively. Furthermore, African Americans represent 1.4% of the tenure-track faculty at Ph.D. granting institutions. The fact that there is a larger number of African Americans at the bachelor's degree level provides evidence that there is a sufficient pool of talent to pursue graduate education in computing.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;This project involves the extensive assessment and dissemination of new and existing iAAMCS data, while continuing key programmatic interventions that support student mentoring. Over this award period, the collective impact of iAAMCS on the field and profession of computing will be documented, along with the experiences and impact of iAAMCS on its participants. This effort involves re-analyzing existing qualitative and quantitative longitudinal data, in addition to collecting new survey responses and interview data. Further documentation of the impact and usefulness of iAAMCS resources will be provided. New educational research will be pursued related to the concepts of cascade mentoring, self-efficacy, intersectionality, and computer science identity development. The results of this comprehensive analysis of iAAMCS will address several gaps in the literature related to African Americans in Computing.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/28/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/13/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2021755</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Juan</FirstName>
<LastName>Gilbert</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Juan E Gilbert</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[juan@ufl.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000282507</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/28/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kyla</FirstName>
<LastName>McMullen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kyla McMullen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[kyla@cise.ufl.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000634976</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/28/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Florida</Name>
<CityName>GAINESVILLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>326111941</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3523923516</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1523 UNION RD RM 207</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NNFQH1JAPEP3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF FLORIDA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>D4GCCCMXR1H3</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Florida]]></Name>
<CityName>Gainseville</CityName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>326112002</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1 UNIVERSITY OF FLORIDA]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>055Y</Code>
<Text>CISE Education and Workforce</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7482</Code>
<Text>BROADENING PARTIC IN COMPUTING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~500000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Institute for African-American Mentoring in Computing Sciences (iAAMCS, pronounced ?i am cs?) was an NSF Broadening Participation in Computing Alliance (BPC-A) that provided a national ecosystem by connecting students and faculty through short and long-term programmatic activities to build community and advance Blacks/African-Americans in computing research. Despite increased enrollment in computer science departments across the United States, the persistence of Black/African-American students remains primarily unchanged since the mid-1990s, particularly at the doctoral degree level. Less than 50 percent of the Black/African-American students that enter computer science PhD programs finish. However, of those Black/African-American computer science PhD students that engaged in iAAMCS activities, 86 percent completed their PhD. iAAMCS was successful in broadening the participation of Blacks/African-Americans in computing research, specifically at the PhD level. iAAMCS was also successful in building an ecosystem for Black/African-American researchers that have connected to each other through the iAAMCS programs and built a community of scholars. These scholars now have each other and they are making progress in their PhD programs and beyond. iAAMCS undergraduate students were exposed to research with mentors of color through iAAMCS programs. These students now understand research and some are in PhD programs. iAAMCS graduate students that were the only one in their department now have a network of peers and mentors to help them navigate the PhD program. iAAMCS faculty members have connected to other faculty and students for collaborations and mentoring opportunities as well. The iAAMCS network brought together undergraduates, graduate students, faculty and research scientists to form this community and breakdown isolation. Also, the iAAMCS Guidelines are a resource for any computer science department to use and those will remain available.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/28/2022<br>      Modified by: Juan&nbsp;E&nbsp;Gilbert</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Institute for African-American Mentoring in Computing Sciences (iAAMCS, pronounced ?i am cs?) was an NSF Broadening Participation in Computing Alliance (BPC-A) that provided a national ecosystem by connecting students and faculty through short and long-term programmatic activities to build community and advance Blacks/African-Americans in computing research. Despite increased enrollment in computer science departments across the United States, the persistence of Black/African-American students remains primarily unchanged since the mid-1990s, particularly at the doctoral degree level. Less than 50 percent of the Black/African-American students that enter computer science PhD programs finish. However, of those Black/African-American computer science PhD students that engaged in iAAMCS activities, 86 percent completed their PhD. iAAMCS was successful in broadening the participation of Blacks/African-Americans in computing research, specifically at the PhD level. iAAMCS was also successful in building an ecosystem for Black/African-American researchers that have connected to each other through the iAAMCS programs and built a community of scholars. These scholars now have each other and they are making progress in their PhD programs and beyond. iAAMCS undergraduate students were exposed to research with mentors of color through iAAMCS programs. These students now understand research and some are in PhD programs. iAAMCS graduate students that were the only one in their department now have a network of peers and mentors to help them navigate the PhD program. iAAMCS faculty members have connected to other faculty and students for collaborations and mentoring opportunities as well. The iAAMCS network brought together undergraduates, graduate students, faculty and research scientists to form this community and breakdown isolation. Also, the iAAMCS Guidelines are a resource for any computer science department to use and those will remain available.        Last Modified: 01/28/2022       Submitted by: Juan E Gilbert]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
