<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[I-Corps: Removing Oxygen for Food Storage and Transport]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ruth Shuman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rshuman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922160</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this I-Corps project is the development of a method to remove oxygen from food storage and transport containers to decrease produce spoilage. Every year $160 billion worth of food is wasted in America at every stage of the supply chain.  Improving food storage would improve this figure and enable environmentally sustainable transport options. The proposed technology may be implemented in several possible stages of the supply chain from farm storage, transportation (truck or ship), grocery store coolers, and for home use in personal refrigerators. This project will explore various paths for technology translation. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project is based on the development of a reversible reaction of excited oxygen with a novel material. The material acts like an oxygen sponge, absorbing oxygen when irradiated with light, and releasing oxygen under warm, dark conditions. This allows the consumption of oxygen to be controlled using light, while the release can be manipulated with heat. The reaction occurs at low partial pressures of oxygen and can create oxygen-free environments. The oxygen may be stored in the material and released under gentle heating. This material and process may be used to remove or reduce oxygen from a space, creating an anerobic environment.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/11/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/11/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2021553</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Theresa</FirstName>
<LastName>McCormick</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Theresa McCormick</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[t.m.mccormick@pdx.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000662010</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/11/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Portland State University</Name>
<CityName>PORTLAND</CityName>
<ZipCode>972015522</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5037259900</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1600 SW 4TH AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OR01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>H4CAHK2RD945</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PORTLAND STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>H4CAHK2RD945</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Portland State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Portland</CityName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<ZipCode>972070751</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1025 SW Mill St]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OR01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="MsoNormal"><span style="font-size: 12.0pt; line-height: 107%;">This I-Corps award was made to investigate potential market fit for the oxygen separation technology developed at Portland State University in the laboratory of Dr. Theresa McCormick, Co-Founder of AirOmatix. Initially we were interested in the produce market and removing oxygen from food storage containers to increase shelf-life and minimize food waste. During the I-Corps program we talked to over 30 farmers, restaurant owners, and grocery store employees.&nbsp; We learned there was insufficient market interest in this type of technology since most food spoilage was not occurring in transportation and storage. As such we realized that we needed to pivot.&nbsp; </span></p> <p class="MsoNormal"><span style="font-size: 12pt; line-height: 107%; font-family: Arial, sans-serif; background-image: initial; background-position: initial; background-size: initial; background-repeat: initial; background-attachment: initial; background-origin: initial; background-clip: initial;">Since this project occurred during the early days of the pandemic, we turned our attention to addressing emerging challenges facing the world. Specifically, we thought we could use our technology to develop an alternative to traditional, alcohol-based, hand sanitizers.&nbsp; We tested the market need for a device that could sanitize hands with concentrated, reactive oxygen gas. The target customer would be health care providers and their main pain would be the time and unwanted side-effects like skin irritation from prolonged use of alcohol-based hand sanitizers. Through these customer interviews we found that, although a small number of providers had significant problems with hand sanitizers, the bigger issue was lack of compliance to hand cleaning protocols by health care workers. Therefore, we explored the the market for hand-sanitizer monitoring stations that would use our sanitizing technology. However, our I-Corps work allowed us to discover that this monitoring innovation would have easier adoption using current hand-sanitizer technology. </span></p> <p class="MsoNormal"><span style="font-size: 12pt; line-height: 107%; font-family: Arial, sans-serif; background-image: initial; background-position: initial; background-size: initial; background-repeat: initial; background-attachment: initial; background-origin: initial; background-clip: initial;">Near the end of our I-Corps program, reports of Covid-related shortages in the oxygen supply chain where making headlines and we started to investigate our technology for generating medical oxygen, especially in the home health setting. We continued our customer discovery work in this area with over 30 additional interviews and have decided to continue the company in this vein. Specifically, developing portable oxygen concentrators for home health patients where our technology offers competitive advantages like higher oxygen purity and flow rates than existing portable oxygen concentrators.&nbsp; </span></p> <p><span style="font-family: Arial, sans-serif; font-size: 12pt;">Since completing the Lean Start-up training and the I-Corps program in 2020, AirOmatix has made great strides toward commercialization. That same year, AirOmatix secured an exclusive license for the technology and pending patent from Portland State University. In June 2021, AirOmatix applied for an NSF Phase I grant to develop portable oxygen concentrators that was awarded in April, 2022. As part of the NSF Phase I grant, AirOmatix participated in a commercialization Bootcamp that reinforced and built upon what we learned from I-Corps. Through these programs we have interviewed over 140 customers and stakeholders to identify market needs, revise our target market and customer segmentation. We have clarified our value propositions and completed a business model canvas that&nbsp;</span><span style="font-family: Arial, sans-serif; font-size: 16px;">outlines&nbsp;</span><span style="font-family: Arial, sans-serif; font-size: 12pt;">our on-going growth and business development. In addition, these programs have allowed Dr. McCormick to provide more entrepreneurial training to students under her supervision at Portland State University.</span></p> <div id="_mcePaste" class="mcePaste" style="position: absolute; left: -10000px; top: 0px; width: 1px; height: 1px; overflow: hidden;"><span style="font-size: 11.0pt; line-height: 107%;">contemporaneous</span></div><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/21/2023<br>      Modified by: Theresa&nbsp;Mccormick</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[This I-Corps award was made to investigate potential market fit for the oxygen separation technology developed at Portland State University in the laboratory of Dr. Theresa McCormick, Co-Founder of AirOmatix. Initially we were interested in the produce market and removing oxygen from food storage containers to increase shelf-life and minimize food waste. During the I-Corps program we talked to over 30 farmers, restaurant owners, and grocery store employees.  We learned there was insufficient market interest in this type of technology since most food spoilage was not occurring in transportation and storage. As such we realized that we needed to pivot.   Since this project occurred during the early days of the pandemic, we turned our attention to addressing emerging challenges facing the world. Specifically, we thought we could use our technology to develop an alternative to traditional, alcohol-based, hand sanitizers.  We tested the market need for a device that could sanitize hands with concentrated, reactive oxygen gas. The target customer would be health care providers and their main pain would be the time and unwanted side-effects like skin irritation from prolonged use of alcohol-based hand sanitizers. Through these customer interviews we found that, although a small number of providers had significant problems with hand sanitizers, the bigger issue was lack of compliance to hand cleaning protocols by health care workers. Therefore, we explored the the market for hand-sanitizer monitoring stations that would use our sanitizing technology. However, our I-Corps work allowed us to discover that this monitoring innovation would have easier adoption using current hand-sanitizer technology.  Near the end of our I-Corps program, reports of Covid-related shortages in the oxygen supply chain where making headlines and we started to investigate our technology for generating medical oxygen, especially in the home health setting. We continued our customer discovery work in this area with over 30 additional interviews and have decided to continue the company in this vein. Specifically, developing portable oxygen concentrators for home health patients where our technology offers competitive advantages like higher oxygen purity and flow rates than existing portable oxygen concentrators.    Since completing the Lean Start-up training and the I-Corps program in 2020, AirOmatix has made great strides toward commercialization. That same year, AirOmatix secured an exclusive license for the technology and pending patent from Portland State University. In June 2021, AirOmatix applied for an NSF Phase I grant to develop portable oxygen concentrators that was awarded in April, 2022. As part of the NSF Phase I grant, AirOmatix participated in a commercialization Bootcamp that reinforced and built upon what we learned from I-Corps. Through these programs we have interviewed over 140 customers and stakeholders to identify market needs, revise our target market and customer segmentation. We have clarified our value propositions and completed a business model canvas that outlines our on-going growth and business development. In addition, these programs have allowed Dr. McCormick to provide more entrepreneurial training to students under her supervision at Portland State University. contemporaneous       Last Modified: 03/21/2023       Submitted by: Theresa Mccormick]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
