<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Mega-constellations of Satellites and Optical / Infrared Astronomy]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>49967.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>49967</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AST</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ashley  Vanderley</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bevander@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922428</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This award is to fund a workshop to explore the impact of the forthcoming increase in the number of satellites in orbit to ground-based astronomy.  The number of satellites in orbit will increase by several thousand in the coming few years and may double or triple in the coming decade.  These satellites are in lower-Earth orbit than many of the existing satellites and have found to be highly reflective in optical wavelengths.  This optical brightness will impact the ability of astronomers to conduct their investigations, especially near twilight.  This workshop will bring together experts in astronomy and the satellite industry to discuss the challenge and explore solutions, resulting in a public white paper for the entire community.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Several companies have licenses to launch low-Earth orbit non-geosynchronous satellite constellations of hundreds to thousands of satellites to provide broadband internet globally.  The design and orbital parameters of these satellites has led to optical reflectivity much brighter than expected, even visible to the naked eye.  Fainter reflections from other NGSO satellites are still expected to be bright enough to saturate pixels in CCDs, rendering many nighttime images unusable.  These reflections are especially bright at twilight, when optical ground-based observatories conduct a large portion of the near-Earth object observations (e.g. potentially hazardous asteroids).  These NGSO constellations are being built-out and satellites launched at the same time optical and infrared astronomy is moving to deep and wide field-of-view surveys.  This workshop’s purpose is to quantify the scope of the problem and to bring together experts to discuss potential mitigation strategies for the coming years.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/12/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/12/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2021148</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Charles Mattias</FirstName>
<LastName>Mountain</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Charles Mattias Mountain</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[Matt.Mountain.NSF@aura-astronomy.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000693831</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/12/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Association of Universities for Research in Astronomy, Inc.</Name>
<CityName>TUCSON</CityName>
<ZipCode>857194933</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2024832101</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>950 N CHERRY AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AZ07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>LFDKLGTB62C4</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ASSOCIATION OF UNIVERSITIES FOR RESEARCH IN ASTRONOMY, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Association of Universities for Research in Astronomy, Inc.]]></Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>200041111</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1331 Pennsylvania Ave. NW, Ste 1]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1798</Code>
<Text/>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~49967</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><strong>Project Overview</strong>:</span></p> <p>Over the next few years, the projected level of satellite constellations in low earth orbit will seriously impact our ability to conduct ground-based astronomical research. The brightness and sheer numbers of these satellites may actually prohibit some areas of research, like the continuing search for some classes of near-earth asteroids that could represent potential threats to life on Earth.</p> <p>Two virtual workshops were held to address the impacts of Mega-Constellations on Astronomy. SATCON1 focused on quantifying the impacts on astronomical data and exploring strategies, on behalf of both observatories and satellite operators, to mitigate those impacts. Several recommendations resulted. SATCON2 took up where SATCON1 left off, focusing on paths to implement those recommendations.</p> <p>Both workshops utilized the talent and energy of Working Group members (4 WGs for each workshop) who spent several weeks prior to and following the actual events, researching, drafting, and then finalizing reports that were widely disseminated.</p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><strong>Intellectual Merit Outcomes:</strong></span></p> <p>The workshops brought together astronomers and satellite engineers to work together on numerous technical issues. The reports produced by the workshop working groups represent a significant advancement in our understanding of both the effects on astronomical data and some of the operational requirements of the satellite constellations. The efforts of the working groups have resulted in a large network of engaged experts, from both astronomy and industry.</p> <p>&nbsp;As a result of SATCON2, the concept of "SatHub" was born. The need was identified to develop new software tools aimed at partially mitigating the constellation impacts on both optical/infrared and radio astronomy. The tools will aid in determining which observations may be affected and, in conjunction with simulations, will estimate the degradation of science data expected in a particular situation. Additional tools will allow some science to be salvaged from affected datasets.&nbsp; This, in turn, inspired the creation of a&nbsp;Center which will provide a home for several aspects addressing the impact of satellite constellations including SatHub. In short, SatHub will house curated software and links to external software, satellite catalogs and ephemeris access, test data, and documentation.</p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><strong>Broader Impact Outcomes:</strong></span></p> <p>Preservation of the night sky is in everyone's interest: humans and other animals rely on regular periods of darkness for optimum health- many animal species (including important pollinators and some humans) rely on celestial navigation for migration. Recognizing that astronomers and satellite operators aren't the only "stakeholders" in the night sky, the SATCON2 Community Engagement working group brought many new voices and perspectives to the issue, and the Policy working group examined regulatory framework and mitigation approaches from national, international, and industry viewpoints.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/07/2022<br>      Modified by: Charles Mattias&nbsp;Mountain</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Project Overview:  Over the next few years, the projected level of satellite constellations in low earth orbit will seriously impact our ability to conduct ground-based astronomical research. The brightness and sheer numbers of these satellites may actually prohibit some areas of research, like the continuing search for some classes of near-earth asteroids that could represent potential threats to life on Earth.  Two virtual workshops were held to address the impacts of Mega-Constellations on Astronomy. SATCON1 focused on quantifying the impacts on astronomical data and exploring strategies, on behalf of both observatories and satellite operators, to mitigate those impacts. Several recommendations resulted. SATCON2 took up where SATCON1 left off, focusing on paths to implement those recommendations.  Both workshops utilized the talent and energy of Working Group members (4 WGs for each workshop) who spent several weeks prior to and following the actual events, researching, drafting, and then finalizing reports that were widely disseminated.  Intellectual Merit Outcomes:  The workshops brought together astronomers and satellite engineers to work together on numerous technical issues. The reports produced by the workshop working groups represent a significant advancement in our understanding of both the effects on astronomical data and some of the operational requirements of the satellite constellations. The efforts of the working groups have resulted in a large network of engaged experts, from both astronomy and industry.   As a result of SATCON2, the concept of "SatHub" was born. The need was identified to develop new software tools aimed at partially mitigating the constellation impacts on both optical/infrared and radio astronomy. The tools will aid in determining which observations may be affected and, in conjunction with simulations, will estimate the degradation of science data expected in a particular situation. Additional tools will allow some science to be salvaged from affected datasets.  This, in turn, inspired the creation of a Center which will provide a home for several aspects addressing the impact of satellite constellations including SatHub. In short, SatHub will house curated software and links to external software, satellite catalogs and ephemeris access, test data, and documentation.  Broader Impact Outcomes:  Preservation of the night sky is in everyone's interest: humans and other animals rely on regular periods of darkness for optimum health- many animal species (including important pollinators and some humans) rely on celestial navigation for migration. Recognizing that astronomers and satellite operators aren't the only "stakeholders" in the night sky, the SATCON2 Community Engagement working group brought many new voices and perspectives to the issue, and the Policy working group examined regulatory framework and mitigation approaches from national, international, and industry viewpoints.          Last Modified: 01/07/2022       Submitted by: Charles Mattias Mountain]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
