<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[I-Corps:  Multi-Dimensional Electromagnetic Energy Convertor]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jaime A. Camelio</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jcamelio@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032920000</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this I-Corps project is the development of a three-dimensional electromagnetic energy convertor (EMEC) to address the unmet need of many applications for high power output per occupied area. EMEC reaches significantly higher power output than existing commercial solar panels making the EMEC modules particularly suitable for transportation applications.  The reliance of the transportation industry on fossil fuels contributes to ~15% of greenhouse gas emissions worldwide. Electric vehicles (EV) are emission-free, but usually rely on energy generated by fossil fuels for charging. EV’s limited power storage capability and, therefore, limited operational range, remains one of the main challenges to adoption. Solar charging of EVs can increase the vehicles’ operational range while reducing reliance on fossil fuels. Unfortunately, commercial solar panels do not meet the transportation industry requirements because of their low power density and prohibitively large form factor, but EMEC is likely suitable for this application. EMEC has the potential to empower a more sustainable emissions-free transportation industry. The I-Corps project will allow us to test these hypotheses.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project is based on the development of a three-dimensional electromagnetic energy convertor (EMEC) ideal for applications that require high power output such as mobile transportation systems and off-grid power generation. According to the National Renewable Energy Laboratory (NREL), the overall cost of commercial solar panels has declined steadily over the past decade thanks to manufacturing automation and broad adoption. Since the power output of commercial solar panels is directly proportional to their effective light collection area, current commercial solar panels consist of large thin sheets of photovoltaic cells. This solution has been accepted widely, particularly for installation in solar farms and single home rooftops. However, these bulky solar panels have failed generally to deliver enough energy for applications where space is limited, such as in urban environments and transportation vehicles. Flexible solar panels are better for mobile applications, but they also require large areas for energy collection. The proposed technology uses a three-dimensional system whose power density is significantly larger than that of existing commercial solar panels. The compact and modular architecture of this system has the potential to increase the power output and decrease the upfront costs associated with solar panel installations.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/11/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/06/2023</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041, 47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2021419</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nilton</FirstName>
<LastName>Renno</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nilton D Renno</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[nrenno@umich.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000094471</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/11/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate>03/08/2023</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mojtaba</FirstName>
<LastName>Akhavan-Tafti</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mojtaba Akhavan-Tafti</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[akhavant@umich.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000818407</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/08/2023</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Regents of the University of Michigan - Ann Arbor</Name>
<CityName>ANN ARBOR</CityName>
<ZipCode>481091079</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1109 GEDDES AVE, SUITE 3300</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>GNJ7BBP73WE9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MICHIGAN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Michigan Ann Arbor]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>481091340</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~50000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
