<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research: Polynyas in Coastal Antarctica (PICA): Linking Physical Dynamics to Biological Variability]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>52658.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>52658</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06090300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OPP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Polar Programs (OPP)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>David Porter</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dporter@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922930</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[During winter, sea-ice coverage along the Antarctic coast is punctuated by numerous polynyas--isolated openings of tens to hundreds of kilometer wide. These coastal polynyas are hotspots of sea ice production and the primary source regions of the bottom water in the global ocean. They also host high levels of biological activities and are the feeding grounds of Emperor penguins and marine mammals. The polynyas are a key component of the Antarctic coastal system and crucial for the survival of penguins and many other species. These features also differ dramatically from each other in timing of formation, duration, phytoplankton growth season, and overall biological productivity. Yet, the underlying reasons for differences among them are largely unknown.  This project studies the fundamental biophysical processes at a variety of polynyas, examines the connection between the physical environment and the phytoplankton and penguin ecology, and investigates the mechanisms behind polynya variability. The results of this interdisciplinary study will provide a context for interpretation of field measurements in Antarctic coastal polynyas, set a baseline for future polynya studies, and examine how polynya ecosystems may respond to local and large-scale environmental changes. The project will include educational and outreach activities that convey scientific messages to a broad audience. It aims to increase public awareness of the interconnection between large-scale environmental change and Antarctic coastal systems.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The main objectives of this study are to form a comprehensive understanding of the temporal and spatial variability of Antarctic coastal polynyas and the physical controls of polynya ecosystems. The project takes an interdisciplinary approach and seeks to establish a modeling system centered on the Regional Ocean Modeling System.  This system links the ice and ocean conditions to the plankton ecology and penguin population. Applications of the modeling system in representative polynyas, in conjunction with analysis of existing observations, will determine the biophysical influences of individual forcing factors. In particular, this study will test a set of hypothesized effects of winds, offshore water intrusion, ice-shelf melting, sea-ice formation, glacier tongues, and ocean stratification on the timing of polynya phytoplankton bloom and the overall polynya biological productivity. The project will also examine how changing polynya state affects penguin breeding success, adult survival, and population growth. The team will conduct idealized sensitivity analysis to explore implications of forcing variability, including local and large-scale environmental change, on Antarctic coastal ecosystems.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/30/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/30/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.078</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2021245</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yun</FirstName>
<LastName>Li</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Yun Li</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[yunli@udel.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000694723</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/30/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Delaware</Name>
<CityName>NEWARK</CityName>
<ZipCode>197160099</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3028312136</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>220 HULLIHEN HALL</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Delaware</StateName>
<StateCode>DE</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DE00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>T72NHKM259N3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF DELAWARE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Delaware]]></Name>
<CityName>Newark</CityName>
<StateCode>DE</StateCode>
<ZipCode>197160099</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[210 Hullihen Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Delaware</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DE00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5292</Code>
<Text>ANT Integrated System Science</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>02XX</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>0100XXXXDB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~52658</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project was carried out in collaboration with WHOI PIs (NSF Award 1643901) to reveal how physical processes in coastal polynyas around Antarctica affect phytoplankton growth and emperor penguin. To achieve the goal, the team i) simulated the ocean circulation and its interaction with the sea ice and ice shelf, ii) analyzed the influence of physical factors, such as winds, air temperature, shelf depth, ice tongue, and coastline on the formation of sea ice and dense water in the polynyas, iii) investigated the time it takes to break down the water column stratification in the polynyas in winter, iv) analyzed the dispersal pathways of the dense water formed in the polynyas across the Antarctic continental shelf, v) quantified the amount and sources of the freshwater required to establish the polynya stratification in the springtime, vi) analyze the impact of stratification evolution on the timing and intensity of the phytoplankton bloom in the coastal polynyas, and vii) analyzing the impact of ephemeral polynyas and land-fast ice on the emperor penguin ecology.</p> <p>Our team at UD focused on developing and implementing a coupled physical-biological model to address how polynya physics affects biological production. We compiled long-term seasonal climatology of stratification from the World Ocean Database. The results showed that springtime stratification varies by a factor of two among dozens of coastal polynyas around the Antarctica. The level of stratification is related to the satellite-inferred sea ice retreat rate. Additionally, polynya circulation is intrinsically complex and three-dimensional. Polynya flushing time derived from data-assimilative products showed a positive relationship with satellite-derived chlorophyll levels.</p> <p>Our model simulations confirmed the relationship between environmental factors and the observed chlorophyll levels in coastal Antarctica. Besides the influences of stratification, the flushing effects play dual roles in modulating phytoplankton blooms. On the one hand, horizontal flows can modulate the Fe supply for phytoplankton production ? it dilutes local iron-rich meltwater at the beginning of the growing season and later serves as a nutrient subsidy when Fe becomes limited. On the other hand, horizontal flows consistently dilute the phytoplankton population in polynyas. As such, too weak flushing affects Fe sufficiency and thus may hamper phytoplankton from reaching a high concentration, whereas too strong flushing affects phytoplankton aggregation.</p> <p>At UD, this project provided the opportunity to train one graduate student and one undergraduate summer REU student. The results of this project have been published in a number of journal articles and disseminated at various professional conferences and seminars. Outreach talk on the Antarctic food web was presented in K-12 classrooms and to the general public. UD team joined WHOI PIs, an artist, and the WHOI media group in producing a 10-minute animation, which demonstrated the Antarctica polynya biophysical interaction and the research of this project in cartoons. The animation was trimmed into several short clips for easier distribution. The WHOI media office released all animations to the public domain on Youtube, Facebook, and Twitter.</p> <p>The UD team worked with WHOI PIs to gather and organize a variety of historical hydrographic data. Those data were scattered in a variety of online and personal databases. Collecting and organizing them and then sharing them on USAP-DC will help make them easier to access and thus aid future studies of the integrated Antarctic system.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/30/2022<br>      Modified by: Yun&nbsp;Li</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project was carried out in collaboration with WHOI PIs (NSF Award 1643901) to reveal how physical processes in coastal polynyas around Antarctica affect phytoplankton growth and emperor penguin. To achieve the goal, the team i) simulated the ocean circulation and its interaction with the sea ice and ice shelf, ii) analyzed the influence of physical factors, such as winds, air temperature, shelf depth, ice tongue, and coastline on the formation of sea ice and dense water in the polynyas, iii) investigated the time it takes to break down the water column stratification in the polynyas in winter, iv) analyzed the dispersal pathways of the dense water formed in the polynyas across the Antarctic continental shelf, v) quantified the amount and sources of the freshwater required to establish the polynya stratification in the springtime, vi) analyze the impact of stratification evolution on the timing and intensity of the phytoplankton bloom in the coastal polynyas, and vii) analyzing the impact of ephemeral polynyas and land-fast ice on the emperor penguin ecology.  Our team at UD focused on developing and implementing a coupled physical-biological model to address how polynya physics affects biological production. We compiled long-term seasonal climatology of stratification from the World Ocean Database. The results showed that springtime stratification varies by a factor of two among dozens of coastal polynyas around the Antarctica. The level of stratification is related to the satellite-inferred sea ice retreat rate. Additionally, polynya circulation is intrinsically complex and three-dimensional. Polynya flushing time derived from data-assimilative products showed a positive relationship with satellite-derived chlorophyll levels.  Our model simulations confirmed the relationship between environmental factors and the observed chlorophyll levels in coastal Antarctica. Besides the influences of stratification, the flushing effects play dual roles in modulating phytoplankton blooms. On the one hand, horizontal flows can modulate the Fe supply for phytoplankton production ? it dilutes local iron-rich meltwater at the beginning of the growing season and later serves as a nutrient subsidy when Fe becomes limited. On the other hand, horizontal flows consistently dilute the phytoplankton population in polynyas. As such, too weak flushing affects Fe sufficiency and thus may hamper phytoplankton from reaching a high concentration, whereas too strong flushing affects phytoplankton aggregation.  At UD, this project provided the opportunity to train one graduate student and one undergraduate summer REU student. The results of this project have been published in a number of journal articles and disseminated at various professional conferences and seminars. Outreach talk on the Antarctic food web was presented in K-12 classrooms and to the general public. UD team joined WHOI PIs, an artist, and the WHOI media group in producing a 10-minute animation, which demonstrated the Antarctica polynya biophysical interaction and the research of this project in cartoons. The animation was trimmed into several short clips for easier distribution. The WHOI media office released all animations to the public domain on Youtube, Facebook, and Twitter.  The UD team worked with WHOI PIs to gather and organize a variety of historical hydrographic data. Those data were scattered in a variety of online and personal databases. Collecting and organizing them and then sharing them on USAP-DC will help make them easier to access and thus aid future studies of the integrated Antarctic system.       Last Modified: 12/30/2022       Submitted by: Yun Li]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
