<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[International Conference on Quantitative Ethnography]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DRL</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Finbarr Sloane</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>fsloane@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928465</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This project was submitted in response to EHR Core Research (ECR) program announcement NSF 19-508. The ECR program of fundamental research in STEM education provides funding in critical research areas that are essential, broad and enduring. ECR supports projects that help synthesize, build and/or expand research foundations in the following focal areas: STEM learning, STEM learning environments, STEM workforce development, and broadening participation in STEM. The ECR program is distinguished by its emphasis on the accumulation of robust evidence to inform efforts to (a) understand, (b) build theory to explain, and (c) suggest interventions (and innovations) to address persistent challenges in STEM interest, education, learning, and participation. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This conference, to be held at the Pepperdine University campus, will build the capacity of NSF-supported communities to benefit from the highly promising research methodology of quantitative ethnography (QE). This training workshop for young scholars, embedded in conference, supports the goals of the ECR program by developing a community of early career researchers to carefully use quantitative ethnography in the conduct of basic STEM education research. These scholars will be prepared to examine and empirically test new theory consistent with the central goals of the ECR program. The funding will support: a) attendance and training at an international conference on QE for doctoral and early career researchers to be held in the U.S., b) a technical immersion preconference workshop that several of participating researchers would lead for these young scholars, and c) a broader slate of symposium speakers who represent NSF supported disciplines that QE methods can benefit significantly.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The intellectual merit of the conference arises both from the appeal or promise of QE across numerous fields. The proposed activities are organized around broadening the impact of QE’s intellectual merit across new disciplines. The project maintains a consistent emphasis on furnishing next-generation researchers with conceptual and software tools and methodology to address important current and future questions across the spectrum of fields NSF supports in social sciences, basic STEM education research, and the learning sciences.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/21/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/21/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2022709</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Eric</FirstName>
<LastName>Hamilton</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Eric Hamilton</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[eric.hamilton@pepperdine.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000083670</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/21/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Danielle</FirstName>
<LastName>Espino</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Danielle P Espino</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[danielle.espino@pepperdine.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000800500</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/21/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Pepperdine University</Name>
<CityName>MALIBU</CityName>
<ZipCode>902633999</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3105064819</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>24255 PACIFIC COAST HWY</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>33</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA33</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NHBMUW819YE7</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PEPPERDINE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Pepperdine University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>900450001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>36</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA36</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7980</Code>
<Text>ECR-EDU Core Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8817</Code>
<Text>STEM Learning &amp; Learning Environments</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0420</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The primary impact of these program activities has been two-fold: Drawing in a substantial number of new scholars into a form of Quantitative Ethnography (QE) methodology to use it in their respective areas, which in turn expands the fields of study using the QE methodology.&nbsp; Secondly, these activities provide an opportunity for existing scholars to continue to deepen their understanding of QE and push the methodology forward through exploration and questions (e.g. topics such as segmentation and stanzas).&nbsp; Keynotes presented at the conference also helped to get the QE community thinking on considerations to push forward.&nbsp;</p> <p>With the ongoing uncertainties related to the COVID-19 pandemic, a planned in-person experience shifted to a virtual setting.&nbsp; The organizing team took advantage of this shift as an opportunity to appeal to researchers that would otherwise have limited capacity to attend in-person.&nbsp; The close to 200 attendees for ICQE21 was almost double that of the in-person conference in 2019, hailing from over 100 different institutions and 40 countries. Despite the larger numbers and virtual setting, participants commented how the conference felt welcoming, intimate yet intellectually challenging in ways that encouraged them to want to further engage with the QE community to better utilize the methodology.&nbsp;</p> <p>A pre-conference immersive workshop was reimagined as a month long experience leading up to the conference, called the QE Accelerator.&nbsp; Led by four early career researchers and four graduate student facilitators, the QE Accelerator consisted of 22 participants who went through an application and selection process to engage in weekly sessions over the course of one month to learn how to apply QE methodology in their own work.&nbsp; The workshop was well received and beneficial by all parties involved-- the participants were appreciative of the information, the graduate student facilitators were given an opportunity to teach QE, and the early career researchers managing the workshop overall had an opportunity to develop what a month long program might look like.&nbsp; The QE Accelerator successfully provided both support to those new to QE to engage, while also providing professional development experience to early career researchers and graduate students.</p> <p>ICQE21 included 6 workshops, 4 symposia, 4 interest group sessions, 26 papers and 19 posters, with the papers published into proceedings by Springer(https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-030-93859-8).&nbsp;Posters were published via supplement that is also available on the ICQE21 website (https://icqe21.org).&nbsp; Preprints of these papers were made available on the Open Science Framework (OSF) repository (https://osf.io/meetings/ICQE21/). Additionally, all keynotes, paper sessions and symposia sessions were recorded and are available on the ICQE21 website and searchable on YouTube for viewing (https://www.icqe21.org/videos/). These resources were also announced and shared through the QE community newsletter (which includes all ICQE21 attendees) and social media outlets.&nbsp; Additionally, institutional press releases and coverage also promoted ICQE21 to further disseminate content and generate interest in the methodology.&nbsp;</p> <p>A special session involving participants from the QE Accelerator reflecting on their experiences drew interest from first-time attendees to further their endeavors to utilize QE methodology.&nbsp;&nbsp;Mentoring groups were reimagined as Expertise Exchanges, to allow for mutual exchange across familiarity and maturity within the QE methodology, rather than solely on institutional position; in some instances, involved graduate students were able to provide insights to professors newer to the methodology. This exemplifies the unique engagement achieved in disseminating QE understanding to a varied audience of both current scholars and newcomers.</p> <p>The program accomplished the intended goals of this grant in significantly deepening the quantitiy, quality, and inclusiveness of participation of researchers in a valuable form of QE methodology and its software tools.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/24/2023<br>      Modified by: Eric&nbsp;Hamilton</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The primary impact of these program activities has been two-fold: Drawing in a substantial number of new scholars into a form of Quantitative Ethnography (QE) methodology to use it in their respective areas, which in turn expands the fields of study using the QE methodology.  Secondly, these activities provide an opportunity for existing scholars to continue to deepen their understanding of QE and push the methodology forward through exploration and questions (e.g. topics such as segmentation and stanzas).  Keynotes presented at the conference also helped to get the QE community thinking on considerations to push forward.   With the ongoing uncertainties related to the COVID-19 pandemic, a planned in-person experience shifted to a virtual setting.  The organizing team took advantage of this shift as an opportunity to appeal to researchers that would otherwise have limited capacity to attend in-person.  The close to 200 attendees for ICQE21 was almost double that of the in-person conference in 2019, hailing from over 100 different institutions and 40 countries. Despite the larger numbers and virtual setting, participants commented how the conference felt welcoming, intimate yet intellectually challenging in ways that encouraged them to want to further engage with the QE community to better utilize the methodology.   A pre-conference immersive workshop was reimagined as a month long experience leading up to the conference, called the QE Accelerator.  Led by four early career researchers and four graduate student facilitators, the QE Accelerator consisted of 22 participants who went through an application and selection process to engage in weekly sessions over the course of one month to learn how to apply QE methodology in their own work.  The workshop was well received and beneficial by all parties involved-- the participants were appreciative of the information, the graduate student facilitators were given an opportunity to teach QE, and the early career researchers managing the workshop overall had an opportunity to develop what a month long program might look like.  The QE Accelerator successfully provided both support to those new to QE to engage, while also providing professional development experience to early career researchers and graduate students.  ICQE21 included 6 workshops, 4 symposia, 4 interest group sessions, 26 papers and 19 posters, with the papers published into proceedings by Springer(https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-030-93859-8). Posters were published via supplement that is also available on the ICQE21 website (https://icqe21.org).  Preprints of these papers were made available on the Open Science Framework (OSF) repository (https://osf.io/meetings/ICQE21/). Additionally, all keynotes, paper sessions and symposia sessions were recorded and are available on the ICQE21 website and searchable on YouTube for viewing (https://www.icqe21.org/videos/). These resources were also announced and shared through the QE community newsletter (which includes all ICQE21 attendees) and social media outlets.  Additionally, institutional press releases and coverage also promoted ICQE21 to further disseminate content and generate interest in the methodology.   A special session involving participants from the QE Accelerator reflecting on their experiences drew interest from first-time attendees to further their endeavors to utilize QE methodology.  Mentoring groups were reimagined as Expertise Exchanges, to allow for mutual exchange across familiarity and maturity within the QE methodology, rather than solely on institutional position; in some instances, involved graduate students were able to provide insights to professors newer to the methodology. This exemplifies the unique engagement achieved in disseminating QE understanding to a varied audience of both current scholars and newcomers.  The program accomplished the intended goals of this grant in significantly deepening the quantitiy, quality, and inclusiveness of participation of researchers in a valuable form of QE methodology and its software tools.       Last Modified: 01/24/2023       Submitted by: Eric Hamilton]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
