<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research: RAPID: Coronavirus persistence, transmission, and circulation in the environment]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>130000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>130000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Mamadou Diallo</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mdiallo@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924257</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The novel coronavirus (2019-nCoV) outbreak has rapidly spread from its beginning in Wuhan China. Currently, people have been infected on all continents except Antarctica. 2019-nCoV has some similarity to two other coronavirus outbreaks (SARS and MERS). Despite intensive study of SARS and MERS, we still lack a fundamental understanding of coronavirus behavior in the environment. Most importantly, we do not know how coronavirus spreads and how long it remains infective when exposed to sunlight. The goal of this RAPID research project is to address these questions to better predict transport. A secondary goal of this research project is to determine whether virus monitoring in wastewater treatment facilities can be used to catch outbreaks early. This will be achieved by monitoring coronavirus dynamics in wastewater treatment plants in the San Francisco Bay Area. The project team includes researchers with complimentary expertise on coronavirus transfer, inactivation, and detection. Successful completion of this research will better prepare scientists, engineers, and public health officials for future coronavirus outbreaks. Societal benefits include understanding coronavirus transmission in communities to decrease the time necessary to identify outbreaks to protect public health and national security.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A novel coronavirus (2019-nCoV) has recently emerged from Wuhan China and its spread is causing international concern. This outbreak follows two other coronavirus outbreaks SARS and MERS. The initial cases of the SARS coronavirus outbreak spread via aerosolized fecal particles through the air ducts of the apartment complex. Early reports of 2019-nCoV suggest it too is excreted in feces. Despite intensive study of these past outbreaks, we still lack a fundamental understanding of enveloped virus particle transport in air and water infrastructure and their inactivation potential from solar radiation exposure. This information is critical to control transmission and predict persistence. A second important question is whether monitoring of viruses in wastewater treatment facilities can be used to catch virus circulation early in community outbreaks. The specific objectives of this project are to characterize how enveloped viruses are transferred from surfaces to skin, how coronaviruses are inactivated by solar and UV radiation, and by monitoring coronavirus dynamics in wastewater treatment plants in the San Francisco Bay Area. The project team includes researchers with complimentary expertise on virus transfer from skin to surfaces, coronavirus detection methods, and viral photoinactivation. The work will be performed at the Codiga Water Resource Recovery Center in Santa Clara County where two of the initial 2019-nCoV cases have been observed in the USA. Results from this research will better prepare scientists, engineers, and public health officials for future coronavirus outbreaks. It will provide critical information on endemic coronavirus circulation and provide a framework for capturing the outbreak dynamics of a novel virus in a community. Further, the enveloped virus transfer study will help scientists understand if and how the transfer of enveloped viruses differs from non-enveloped viruses. Broader benefits to society include understanding when and how transmission may occur in communities; information that is critical to decreasing the time necessary to identify viral disease outbreaks to protect public health and national security.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/17/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/17/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2022877</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Craig</FirstName>
<LastName>Criddle</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Craig S Criddle</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[criddle@stanford.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000426081</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/17/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alexandria</FirstName>
<LastName>Boehm</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alexandria Boehm</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[aboehm@stanford.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000474521</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/17/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Stanford University</Name>
<CityName>STANFORD</CityName>
<ZipCode>943052004</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6507232300</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>450 JANE STANFORD WAY</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>16</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA16</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>HJD6G4D6TJY5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>THE LELAND STANFORD JUNIOR UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Stanford University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>943054020</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>16</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA16</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1440</Code>
<Text>EnvE-Environmental Engineering</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1642</Code>
<Text>Special Initiatives</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~130000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This grant funded research to inform the nation&rsquo;s response to the COVID-19 pandemic. At the start of the pandemic, very little was known about the persistence and occurrence of enveloped human viruses, like SARS-CoV-2.</p> <p>In this project, we generated some of the very first data on the presence of the SARS-CoV-2 virus in wastewater, and we showed that its RNA concentrations in wastewater rose and fell as COVID-19 cases in the population contributing to the wastewater rose and fell. This work served as a basis for a large regional project to measure SARS-CoV-2 in wastewater throughout the Bay Area of California that provided data in real time to public health stakeholders to inform their response to the pandemic.</p> <p>This grant also funded research to understand how enveloped viruses are transferred from surfaces to human fingertips. We used human volunteers who touched surfaces (like glass slides or metal or wood) seeded with a benign enveloped bacteriophage (phi6, a virus that infects bacteria). We examined whether the enveloped bacteriophage was transferred to human skin in a similar manner as non-enveloped bacteriophage (we used a benign bacteriophage MS2, a virus that infects bacteria). We found that both could be transferred to a similar extent (around 20-25% of viruses are transferred to a fingertip on contact with the surface), but that transfer of the non-enveloped phage was slightly greater than the enveloped phage.</p> <p>This grant funded research to document the persistence of enveloped viruses in water illuminated by sunlight. We studied how sunlight inactivated enveloped bacteriophage phi6 and non-enveloped bacteriophage MS2. We found that sunlight was extremely effective at inactivating phi6 and that phi6 was inactivated more quickly than MS2. Phi6 is most sensitive to UVB wavelengths of light and when UVB photons are removed from the light, the phage is more persistent compared to when UVB photons are present. &nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/23/2023<br>      Modified by: Alexandria&nbsp;Boehm</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This grant funded research to inform the nation’s response to the COVID-19 pandemic. At the start of the pandemic, very little was known about the persistence and occurrence of enveloped human viruses, like SARS-CoV-2.  In this project, we generated some of the very first data on the presence of the SARS-CoV-2 virus in wastewater, and we showed that its RNA concentrations in wastewater rose and fell as COVID-19 cases in the population contributing to the wastewater rose and fell. This work served as a basis for a large regional project to measure SARS-CoV-2 in wastewater throughout the Bay Area of California that provided data in real time to public health stakeholders to inform their response to the pandemic.  This grant also funded research to understand how enveloped viruses are transferred from surfaces to human fingertips. We used human volunteers who touched surfaces (like glass slides or metal or wood) seeded with a benign enveloped bacteriophage (phi6, a virus that infects bacteria). We examined whether the enveloped bacteriophage was transferred to human skin in a similar manner as non-enveloped bacteriophage (we used a benign bacteriophage MS2, a virus that infects bacteria). We found that both could be transferred to a similar extent (around 20-25% of viruses are transferred to a fingertip on contact with the surface), but that transfer of the non-enveloped phage was slightly greater than the enveloped phage.  This grant funded research to document the persistence of enveloped viruses in water illuminated by sunlight. We studied how sunlight inactivated enveloped bacteriophage phi6 and non-enveloped bacteriophage MS2. We found that sunlight was extremely effective at inactivating phi6 and that phi6 was inactivated more quickly than MS2. Phi6 is most sensitive to UVB wavelengths of light and when UVB photons are removed from the light, the phage is more persistent compared to when UVB photons are present.            Last Modified: 03/23/2023       Submitted by: Alexandria Boehm]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
