<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Doctoral Dissertation Research: Positioning translational research in the biotech ecosystem: From basic research to more exploitable knowledge]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>11428.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>11428</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SMA</Abbreviation>
<LongName>SBE Off Of Multidisciplinary Activities</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Josie Welkom Miranda</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jwmirand@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927376</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Novel scientific discoveries in the biomedical sector do not become viable clinical treatments or commercial products by themselves. There are numerous steps to go through and obstacles to overcome along the complex biomedical developmental process. Translational research has emerged to increase the speed of the conversion process and improve biomedical productivity. Since 2006, the National Institutes of Health (NIH)’s Clinical and Translational Science Awards (CTSA) program has supported over 60 institutions in order to improve the clinical and translational research environment. While current literature examines the effect of the NIH translational research program, the scope of its analysis is generally restricted to publication at the recipient level. This study analyzes the effect of the NIH CTSA program on biotech entrepreneurship by expanding the scope of analysis to a broader level. In addition, this project attempts to identify the effective combinations of conditions for a high level of biotech entrepreneurship with a specific emphasis on the role of translational research. The results will contribute to a more comprehensive understanding of the effect of translational research in the context of biotech entrepreneurial activity and help us to assess the potential benefit of translational research to the public health.   &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research draws on the entrepreneurial ecosystem approach and the knowledge spillover theory of entrepreneurship to analyze the effects of translational research on biotech entrepreneurship. The overarching analytical framework is that translational research increases biotech entrepreneurship by increasing the commercially exploitable knowledge stock that is available to entrepreneurs. For the empirical testing, the project uses federal innovation programs such as the Small Business Innovation Research as a proxy for biotech entrepreneurship. This study also considers and examines the biomedical patent, among other forms of exploitable knowledge. The empirical methods highlight how having the translational research program makes differences in the outcomes. Data is collected through various sources including federal agencies such as the National Institutes of Health, the National Science Foundation, and the Census Bureau. The findings will be principally disseminated through publication and will contribute to the literature in the translational research and entrepreneurial ecosystem fields. Additionally, federal agencies like the NIH will have access to a careful empirical appraisal of the CTSA program’s contribution to biomedical enterprises.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/30/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/27/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2022218</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nicholas</FirstName>
<LastName>Vonortas</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nicholas S Vonortas</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[vonortas@gwu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000160910</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/30/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sang-Min</FirstName>
<LastName>Park</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sang-Min Park</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[sangminpark@gwmail.gwu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000820988</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/30/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>George Washington University</Name>
<CityName>WASHINGTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>200520042</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2029940728</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1918 F ST NW</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>ECR5E2LU5BL6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GEORGE WASHINGTON UNIVERSITY (THE)</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[George Washington University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>200520042</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>125Y</Code>
<Text>Science of Science</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7626</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE OF SCIENCE POLICY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~11428</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>This project investigated the impact of translational research on biomedical entrepreneurship in the US. Translational research is a type of research that aims to bridge the gap between scientific discoveries and practical applications. We used the National Institutes of Health (NIH) Clinical and Translational Science Awards (CTSA) program as a measure of translational research, and the NIH Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) program as a measure of biomedical entrepreneurship. The study also examined two types of knowledge that link translational research to biomedical entrepreneurship: biomedical patents and clinical trials. We proposed three analytical models based on the knowledge spillover theory of entrepreneurship and the entrepreneurial ecosystem approach. The models were tested using panel data from 381 metropolitan areas over 10 years. The main findings are that the CTSA program has a positive but small effect on regional SBIR grants and biomedical patents. In addition, biomedical patents have a strong correlation with regional SBIR grants, but clinical trials do not. In short, path analysis indicates that the effect of the CTSA program on regional SBIR grants is not strongly conveyed through biomedical patents or clinical trials.</span></p> <p><span>Given that the impact of translational research is small and that different factors may also contribute to the regional biomedical entrepreneurship, we further explored how other factors influence regional biomedical entrepreneurship. In other words, this study looked at how different conditions in a region work together to make these businesses successful. The analysis with the fuzzy-set qualitative comparative analysis shows that there are three configurations that regional conditions can work together to make vibrant biomedical business ecosystem: 1) Public research activity and patents in the biomedical field, and human capital; 2) Public research and patents in the biomedical sector, clinical trials, and venture investment; 3) Private research and patents in the biomedical sector, human capital, per capita income, population density, and venture investment.</span></p> <p><span>The findings of this project suggest that translational research can play a role in promoting biomedical entrepreneurship but the effect size is relatively small. The results also suggest that there are three different configurations of regional conditions that can be conducive to biomedical entrepreneurship. The study concludes by presenting policy recommendations to enhance the effect of translational research on regional entrepreneurship and to improve the regional conditions for biomedical entrepreneurship: Better linking translational researchers and entrepreneurs; Enhancing the local government's role for facilitating the knowledge utilization; Identifying regional characteristics before planning and implementing regional biomedical policies.&nbsp;&nbsp;</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/25/2023<br>      Modified by: Sang-Min&nbsp;Park</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project investigated the impact of translational research on biomedical entrepreneurship in the US. Translational research is a type of research that aims to bridge the gap between scientific discoveries and practical applications. We used the National Institutes of Health (NIH) Clinical and Translational Science Awards (CTSA) program as a measure of translational research, and the NIH Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) program as a measure of biomedical entrepreneurship. The study also examined two types of knowledge that link translational research to biomedical entrepreneurship: biomedical patents and clinical trials. We proposed three analytical models based on the knowledge spillover theory of entrepreneurship and the entrepreneurial ecosystem approach. The models were tested using panel data from 381 metropolitan areas over 10 years. The main findings are that the CTSA program has a positive but small effect on regional SBIR grants and biomedical patents. In addition, biomedical patents have a strong correlation with regional SBIR grants, but clinical trials do not. In short, path analysis indicates that the effect of the CTSA program on regional SBIR grants is not strongly conveyed through biomedical patents or clinical trials.  Given that the impact of translational research is small and that different factors may also contribute to the regional biomedical entrepreneurship, we further explored how other factors influence regional biomedical entrepreneurship. In other words, this study looked at how different conditions in a region work together to make these businesses successful. The analysis with the fuzzy-set qualitative comparative analysis shows that there are three configurations that regional conditions can work together to make vibrant biomedical business ecosystem: 1) Public research activity and patents in the biomedical field, and human capital; 2) Public research and patents in the biomedical sector, clinical trials, and venture investment; 3) Private research and patents in the biomedical sector, human capital, per capita income, population density, and venture investment.  The findings of this project suggest that translational research can play a role in promoting biomedical entrepreneurship but the effect size is relatively small. The results also suggest that there are three different configurations of regional conditions that can be conducive to biomedical entrepreneurship. The study concludes by presenting policy recommendations to enhance the effect of translational research on regional entrepreneurship and to improve the regional conditions for biomedical entrepreneurship: Better linking translational researchers and entrepreneurs; Enhancing the local government's role for facilitating the knowledge utilization; Identifying regional characteristics before planning and implementing regional biomedical policies.            Last Modified: 09/25/2023       Submitted by: Sang-Min Park]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
