<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[EAGER: Development of the Novel Recombinase System for the Intersectional Dissection of Neural Circuitry]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>300000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>300000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08090200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IOS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Evan Balaban</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[A comprehensive understanding of brain cell diversity and cell-to-cell communication (connectivity via specialized junctions between cells called synapses) is essential for understanding the anatomical substrates and cellular mechanisms that underlie brain function. Elucidation of the detailed synaptic organization of specific neural circuits is a necessary component for achieving this goal. Progress in this area of neuroscience has been limited by a lack of tools that can simultaneously reveal multiple cell types with distinct molecular and physiological properties within the same brain areas, as well as highlighting in detail how these cells are connected to each other. This project utilizes a novel molecular-biological strategy for defining multiple cell types and their interconnections in mouse brains, enabling investigators to mark individual cells that express combinations of engineered genetic elements. This technique is combined with an existing method that inserts two incomplete parts of a fluorescent molecule onto the surfaces of different nerve cells. If those cells communicate by forming a connection (synapse) with each other, the fragments of the fluorescent molecule come into close enough contact to become functional again, and synapses are identifiable as colored dots of fluorescent light. Both graduate and undergraduate students will be involved in the development and optimization of these tools, and the genetic constructs will be distributed via a non-profit agency; all protocols and sequence information will be made widely available through the PI's website. These new tools will greatly enhance the speed and precision with which neuroscientists can study the detailed organization of brain circuitry, and the synaptic connections made onto specific neurons. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project introduces novel molecular and viral strategies for defining multiple cell types and their synaptic organization. It is based on a novel viral strategy to achieve the intersectional expression of transgenes among specific neuronal populations in transgenic mouse lines that express Cre, flippase (FLP), and other recombinases. A novel site-specific recombinase system (phiC31 and a phiC31-dependent single inverted open reading frame [pSIO]) is used to acheive virus-mediated, specific-transgene expression without cross-reactivity to other recombinases, both in vitro and in vivo. This phiC31/pSIO recombinase system is then combined with "enhanced Green fluorescent protein Reconstitution Across Synaptic Partners" (eGRASP) to label synaptic contacts made by specific inputs. By providing a novel experimental framework for identifying the cellular constituents of local neural circuits and examining the synaptic organization of multiple presynaptic inputs onto specific neurons, and by optimizing these tools for general use and making them freely available to the scientific community, this project is expected to accelerate discovery about the organizational and functional properties of neural circuitry.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/07/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/07/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2022241</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Byungkook</FirstName>
<LastName>Lim</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Byungkook Lim</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[bklim@ucsd.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000690894</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/07/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-San Diego</Name>
<CityName>LA JOLLA</CityName>
<ZipCode>920930021</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8585344896</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>9500 GILMAN DRIVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>50</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA50</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>UYTTZT6G9DT1</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, SAN DIEGO</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[The Regents of the Univ. of Calif., U.C. San Diego]]></Name>
<CityName>La Jolla</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>920930357</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[9500 Gilman Dr., Mail Code 0934]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>50</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA50</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7712</Code>
<Text>Organization</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7713</Code>
<Text>Activation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7714</Code>
<Text>Modulation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~300000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The complexity of the nervous system is not just because of the large number of neurons but mainly by the enormous synaptic connectivity. The more fascinating aspect of this complexity is the specificity. Each neuron in the brain has a specific input/output pattern; while different connections serve distinct functional roles. Thus, to fully understand the roles of specific circuitry, the elucidation of the relationship between structural and functional organization is essential. Many investigators are working toward this end but have been limited to local circuits and selected populations, due to the lack of tools that can simultaneously define specific cell types with distinct functional properties. Thus, we will introduce several molecular and viral tools useful for defining specific neural populations and studying their functional roles.</p> <p>Various transgenic mouse lines expressing Cre- or Flp-recombinase in specific cell types have been developed and several viral tools for targeting neurons are also introduced. Especially, the recombinase-specific viral-mediated gene delivery using Cre- and Flp recombinase and their counterparts cDIO (Cre-mediated double inverted open reading frame) and fDIO (Flp-mediated double inverted open reading frame) showed a reliable transgene expression in specific cell types.</p> <p>However, the limitation of the number of specific recombinases prevents researchers to define many cell types simultaneously. Especially, with the advent of single cell analysis methods, more information on the molecular profiling of the brain will lead to the identification of more heterogeneity. For example, single-cell RNA-seq results suggest that parvalbumin (PV)-positive interneurons, conventionally regarded as a single type of cortical interneurons, consist of several different subtypes in the cortex. This means that more tools that can define the growing number of individual neuronal populations are needed.</p> <p>Thus, in this project, we developed and validated several molecular and viral tools that can be used to define more specific neuronal types with novel recombinase combinations, PhiC31/pSIO and Bxb1/bSIO. Moreover, using these recombinases, we developed easily applicable viral tools for the robust and efficient intersectional expression of various transgenes, including GCaMPs or ChR2, which provided valuable tools for the anatomical and functional understanding of neural circuitry.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/25/2022<br>      Modified by: Byungkook&nbsp;Lim</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The complexity of the nervous system is not just because of the large number of neurons but mainly by the enormous synaptic connectivity. The more fascinating aspect of this complexity is the specificity. Each neuron in the brain has a specific input/output pattern; while different connections serve distinct functional roles. Thus, to fully understand the roles of specific circuitry, the elucidation of the relationship between structural and functional organization is essential. Many investigators are working toward this end but have been limited to local circuits and selected populations, due to the lack of tools that can simultaneously define specific cell types with distinct functional properties. Thus, we will introduce several molecular and viral tools useful for defining specific neural populations and studying their functional roles.  Various transgenic mouse lines expressing Cre- or Flp-recombinase in specific cell types have been developed and several viral tools for targeting neurons are also introduced. Especially, the recombinase-specific viral-mediated gene delivery using Cre- and Flp recombinase and their counterparts cDIO (Cre-mediated double inverted open reading frame) and fDIO (Flp-mediated double inverted open reading frame) showed a reliable transgene expression in specific cell types.  However, the limitation of the number of specific recombinases prevents researchers to define many cell types simultaneously. Especially, with the advent of single cell analysis methods, more information on the molecular profiling of the brain will lead to the identification of more heterogeneity. For example, single-cell RNA-seq results suggest that parvalbumin (PV)-positive interneurons, conventionally regarded as a single type of cortical interneurons, consist of several different subtypes in the cortex. This means that more tools that can define the growing number of individual neuronal populations are needed.  Thus, in this project, we developed and validated several molecular and viral tools that can be used to define more specific neuronal types with novel recombinase combinations, PhiC31/pSIO and Bxb1/bSIO. Moreover, using these recombinases, we developed easily applicable viral tools for the robust and efficient intersectional expression of various transgenes, including GCaMPs or ChR2, which provided valuable tools for the anatomical and functional understanding of neural circuitry.          Last Modified: 08/25/2022       Submitted by: Byungkook Lim]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
