<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research: Unlocking the secrets of slow slip by drilling at the northern Hikurangi subduction margin, New Zealand: CORK observatory development and installation]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>35367.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>35367</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OCE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Deborah K. Smith</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The Hikurangi subduction zone offshore the eastern North Island of New Zealand has characteristics that provide a globally unique window into a fundamental aspect of how stress builds up and is relieved as an oceanic plate thrusts (or ?subducts?) beneath continental crust. Recently, seismologists have recognized that subduction megathrust faults undergo slip in episodic ?slow slip events?. Prior to the discovery of slow slip events in the last decade, our paradigms of fault slip were focused on seismic slip in major earthquakes. Since the discovery of slow slip, most studies have focused on deep (&gt;20-40 km depth) slow slip events, but we now realize that shallow slow slip events (&lt;5-15 km depth) exist that are much more accessible to near-source investigations. These shallow slow fault slip events are centered beneath the ocean so onshore instruments have not been able to measure how much surface deformation occurs. This study takes advantage of planned International Ocean Discovery Program drilling to install sensors in two boreholes that will measure properties indicative of change in the shallow crust that the episodic fault activity causes.  Senior researchers in borehole instrumentation will mentor mid-early career scientists, passing along extensive knowledge of such complex implementation and research. Japanese, New Zealand, and German collaborators will participate with the US investigators in this international study, and local communities will benefit from scientist outreach associated with cruises off New Zealand. This study is being undertaken as a ?community proposal?, whereby all data will be immediately publicly available.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;The shallowest, well-documented slow slip events on Earth occur at the northern Hikurangi margin, offshore Gisborne, New Zealand, at &lt;5-15 km depth. They recur approximately every 1-2 years, with slip on the plate boundary interface of up to 15-20 cm. The unusually close proximity of the Gisborne slow slip events to the seafloor, the large slow slip event magnitudes (equivalent to an earthquake magnitude Mw ~6.3-6.8), and short recurrence intervals makes this the ideal setting for evaluating the near-source hydrological, geochemical, and thermal response of the offshore subduction margin to large, frequent, well-documented deformation transients. The borehole observatory data will clarify the role that fluid pressures, fluid flow, and temperature play in the occurrence of slow slip events, as well as the influence of slow slip event deformation on fluid and geochemical cycling within the forearc. This project will establish the borehole facility and set-up open data access. Analysis of the first two years of data, recovered by ROV, will evaluate the deformation, hydrological, and geochemical responses near the source of slow slip, as well as document the thermal regime of shallow slow slip. One of the borehole installations will target the region surrounding the shallow portion of the megathrust fault , while sensors in a second borehole will target the over-riding plate ~5 km above the slow slip event source.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/19/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/19/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2022832</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Demian</FirstName>
<LastName>Saffer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Demian M Saffer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[demian@ig.utexas.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000087242</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/19/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Texas at Austin</Name>
<CityName>AUSTIN</CityName>
<ZipCode>787121139</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5124716424</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>110 INNER CAMPUS DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>25</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX25</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>V6AFQPN18437</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT AUSTIN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>X5NKD2NFF2V3</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[The University of Texas at Austin]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>787121139</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>25</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX25</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1620</Code>
<Text>Marine Geology and Geophysics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5720</Code>
<Text>OCEAN DRILLING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01001617DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01001819DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~15370</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~19997</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Subduction zone plate boundaries produce the world's largest and deadliest earthquakes and tsunamis, but we know little about when they will strike because most subduction zone earthquakes occur miles beneath the ocean floor, making these faults difficult to monitor using conventional land-based methods. This project aimed to design, construct, and install a suite of novel sensors into two boreholes drilled beneath deep water and into the Earth's crust offshore of Northern New Zealand. This region is of particular interest because it is the site of frequent "slow slip events", a type of slow motion earthquake that involves centimeters to tens of centimeters of movement along the subduction zone fault over days to years. In some cases, these slow motion earthquakes can precede (and possibly trigger) major earthquake ruptures, such as was observed prior to the magnigtude 9 Tohoku earthquake offshore Japan in 2011. The observation of these enigmatic slow slip events also provides a new window into the physics of earthquake-generating faults.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>The sensors and samplng systems developed in this project were successfully installed,&nbsp;within only a few hundred meters to a few km of the source regions of earthquakes and slow slip events. as part of Integrated Ocean Discovery Program (IODP) Expedition 375 in 2018. The observatory systems include: (1) pressure sensors that monitor the accumulation and release of strain caused by tectonic motion and fault and earthquake slip; (2) temperature sensors to monitor changes in fluid movement and heat transfer that may be associated with fault motions; and (3) chemical sampling devices to provide a record of variations in fluid movement and composition that may also be associated with fault slip.</p> <p>In 2019 and again in 2021, visits to the boreholes using a remotely operated submersible successfully accessed these observatory systems, and acquired long-term records of pressure in the subsurface. These initial data document a large slow slip event in 2019, and provide observations both at high resolution and in the offshore-most reaches of the subduction fault close to its shallow edge at the ocean trench. The new data provide insight into fault motion in unprecedented detail, including the migration of fault slip as the event unfolded, and the observation of multiple smaller slip events far offshore that went undetected by other (land-based) sensor networks. The fluid sampling system and temperature sensors remain in place, and will be recovered, along with data and samples, in the coming years. The pressure data obtained to date provide key new insights into the accumulation and release of stress in the shallowest subduction zone, with key implications for hazards posed by tsunami and shallow earthquake slip.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/23/2021<br>      Modified by: Demian&nbsp;M&nbsp;Saffer</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Subduction zone plate boundaries produce the world's largest and deadliest earthquakes and tsunamis, but we know little about when they will strike because most subduction zone earthquakes occur miles beneath the ocean floor, making these faults difficult to monitor using conventional land-based methods. This project aimed to design, construct, and install a suite of novel sensors into two boreholes drilled beneath deep water and into the Earth's crust offshore of Northern New Zealand. This region is of particular interest because it is the site of frequent "slow slip events", a type of slow motion earthquake that involves centimeters to tens of centimeters of movement along the subduction zone fault over days to years. In some cases, these slow motion earthquakes can precede (and possibly trigger) major earthquake ruptures, such as was observed prior to the magnigtude 9 Tohoku earthquake offshore Japan in 2011. The observation of these enigmatic slow slip events also provides a new window into the physics of earthquake-generating faults.    The sensors and samplng systems developed in this project were successfully installed, within only a few hundred meters to a few km of the source regions of earthquakes and slow slip events. as part of Integrated Ocean Discovery Program (IODP) Expedition 375 in 2018. The observatory systems include: (1) pressure sensors that monitor the accumulation and release of strain caused by tectonic motion and fault and earthquake slip; (2) temperature sensors to monitor changes in fluid movement and heat transfer that may be associated with fault motions; and (3) chemical sampling devices to provide a record of variations in fluid movement and composition that may also be associated with fault slip.  In 2019 and again in 2021, visits to the boreholes using a remotely operated submersible successfully accessed these observatory systems, and acquired long-term records of pressure in the subsurface. These initial data document a large slow slip event in 2019, and provide observations both at high resolution and in the offshore-most reaches of the subduction fault close to its shallow edge at the ocean trench. The new data provide insight into fault motion in unprecedented detail, including the migration of fault slip as the event unfolded, and the observation of multiple smaller slip events far offshore that went undetected by other (land-based) sensor networks. The fluid sampling system and temperature sensors remain in place, and will be recovered, along with data and samples, in the coming years. The pressure data obtained to date provide key new insights into the accumulation and release of stress in the shallowest subduction zone, with key implications for hazards posed by tsunami and shallow earthquake slip.           Last Modified: 10/23/2021       Submitted by: Demian M Saffer]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
