<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research FSML: PhytoChop: An estuarine phytoplankton observatory]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>228316.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>228316</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DBI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Peter McCartney</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Phytoplankton form the base of aquatic foodwebs and play a fundamental role in the transformation of energy, carbon, and nutrients in aquatic ecosystems. Phytoplankton biomass and species composition can fluctuate rapidly, with ecological and even toxicological consequences, yet the factors that govern these dynamics in coastal and estuarine environments remains poorly constrained. This project establishes the PhytoChop Coastal Observatory, an autonomous instrument array designed to continuously monitor the composition and photosynthetic activity of the phytoplankton community. The observatory, located at Horn Point Laboratory’s research pier situated on a tidal sub-estuary of Chesapeake Bay, the Choptank River, will provide images and quantitative data describing phytoplankton composition and activity on a public-facing data portal. The project will provide data that will enable a deeper understanding of the factors that govern phytoplankton dynamics at time scales ranging from cellular division to seasonal succession and eventually to interannual scales. Engagement with end-users will take several forms, including the development of computer scripts for scientists, course modules for students, image libraries for everyone including the general public, and an internship to specifically engage with the oyster aquaculture community. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This proposal seeks to establish a state-of-the-art coastal observatory, PhytoChop, to support research and education on the community composition and ecophysiology of phytoplankton, including photosynthetic and mixotrophic protists and cyanobacteria. The PhytoChop Coastal Observatory will be housed at Horn Point Laboratory’s research pier drawing water from a mesohaline tidal sub-estuary of Chesapeake Bay, the Choptank River. The observatory will provide high frequency taxonomic and physiological data by combining an Imaging FlowCytobot (IFCB), a Fast-Repetition Rate Fluorometer (FRRF), and instrumentation to measure environmental parameters that constrain phytoplankton growth (temperature, light, nutrients). Data collection frequency will enable examination of the phytoplankton community from time scales spanning from cell division to seasonal succession, and eventually to interannual scales. The data stream resulting from the PhytoChop Coastal Observatory will be made publicly available in near-real time to be readily available to the scientific community at (https://hplmonitoring.umces.edu/). To help streamline data analysis in the classroom and beyond, we will deposit scripts (R, Python) that import and query PhytoChop Coastal Observatory data into a GitHub repository. Data resulting from this project is anticipated to benefit a broad scientific audience including phytoplankton ecologists and physiologists and coastal and estuarine ecosystem ecologists.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/23/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/23/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2022994</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Matthew</FirstName>
<LastName>Gray</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Matthew W Gray</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mgray@umces.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000736430</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/23/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sairah</FirstName>
<LastName>Malkin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sairah Malkin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[smalkin@umces.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000715891</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/23/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Pierson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>James J Pierson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jpierson@umces.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000190722</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/23/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Greg</FirstName>
<LastName>Silsbe</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Greg Silsbe</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[gsilsbe@umces.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000763601</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/23/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Maryland Center for Environmental Sciences</Name>
<CityName>CAMBRIDGE</CityName>
<ZipCode>216133368</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4102212014</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2020 HORNS POINT RD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MD01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>JHTYTGKYWLL9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MARYLAND CENTER FOR ENVIRONMENTAL SCIENCE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Maryland Center for Environmental Sciences]]></Name>
<CityName>Cambridge MD</CityName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>216130775</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2020 Horns Point Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MD01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7593</Code>
<Text>FIELD STATIONS AND MARINE LABS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1104</Code>
<Text>FIELD STATIONS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~228316</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="Default">Phytoplankton form the base of aquatic foodwebs and are fundamental players in the transformation of energy, carbon, and nutrients in aquatic ecosystems, as well as being a principal determinant of water quality. Decades of experimental and observational research have yielded a broad understanding of phytoplankton biogeography. Yet the factors that govern phytoplankton community assembly, activity, and dynamics over both shorter (daily to sub-seasonal) and longer (interannual) time scales remain poorly understood. The community composition and activity of phytoplankton can fluctuate rapidly, particularly in coastal and estuarine environments, with ecological and even toxicological consequences.</p> <p class="Default">This project established the PhytoChop Coastal Observatory, an advanced autonomous instrument array designed to monitor the composition and photosynthetic activity of the phytoplankton community, together with water column nutrient and temperature and salinity data, over long durations at high frequency. This integrated array will enable a deeper understanding of the ecological factors that govern phytoplankton community assembly and activity within a subtropical and strongly seasonal system, at time scales ranging from cellular division to seasonal succession, and ultimately interannual variability.</p> <p>The observatory is housed at Horn Point Laboratory's research pier situated on the Choptank River, a mesohaline tidal sub-estuary of the Chesapeake Bay (Figure 1). Water is continuously pumped from the Choptank River into the enclosure where it is then passed to a series of instruments. <em>PhytoChop </em>includes an Imaging FlowCytobot (IFCB), a rugged and waterproof flow cytometer that captures high resolution images (~3.4 pixels/micron) of individual phytoplankton (Figure 2). Our research team includes an algal taxonomist with expertise on IFCB imagery who is employing machine learning image recognition software to identify and enumerate phytoplankton taxa. To complement the IFCB and to gain a better understanding of water quality dynamics, the enclosure also features instrumentation that measures water temperature, salinity, nutrient concentrations and phytoplankton biomass and physiology (active fluorometry).</p> <p>We have developed a public-facing website that allows the general public to view and access PhytoChop data (<a href="http://www.umces.edu/phytochop">www.umces.edu/phytochop</a>) and have developed learning tools to incorporate observatory data into undergraduate curriculum. Moreover, PhytoChop data is being used for a variety of applied research projects, including water quality impacts on aquaculture. The core instrumentation is also serving as a nexus for a suite of additional data streams through extramural funding. In the summer of 2022 researchers deployed a series of hyperspectral radiometers that emulate future earth-observing satellite missions that measure water color (Figure 3), and beginning in 2023 researchers will be taking weekly water samples for environmental DNA analysis.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/29/2022<br>      Modified by: Greg&nbsp;Silsbe</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2022994/2022994_10688569_1669737896672_figure2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2022994/2022994_10688569_1669737896672_figure2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 2"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2022994/2022994_10688569_1669737896672_figure2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 2"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Example images from IFCB, from a sampled collected from PhytoChop between March and November 2022. A. Ceratulina sp.; B. Centric diatom; C. Ceratulina pelagica; D. Akashiwo sp.; E. Strombidium oculatum; F. Gyrodinoid dinoflagellate; G. Thallasiosira sp.; H. Cryptophyceae; I. Euglena sp.; J. Mesodini</div> <div class="imageCredit">Emily Brownlee</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Greg&nbsp;Silsbe</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 2</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2022994/2022994_10688569_1669737721317_Figure1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2022994/2022994_10688569_1669737721317_Figure1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 1"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2022994/2022994_10688569_1669737721317_Figure1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 1"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The PhytoChop Coastal Observatory Enclosure situated on the Choptank River.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Greg Silsbe</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Greg&nbsp;Silsbe</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 1</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2022994/2022994_10688569_1669738126384_figure3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2022994/2022994_10688569_1669738126384_figure3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 3"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2022994/2022994_10688569_1669738126384_figure3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 3"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Shifting changes in water color measured across a 50 day period</div> <div class="imageCredit">Greg Silsbe</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Greg&nbsp;Silsbe</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 3</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[Phytoplankton form the base of aquatic foodwebs and are fundamental players in the transformation of energy, carbon, and nutrients in aquatic ecosystems, as well as being a principal determinant of water quality. Decades of experimental and observational research have yielded a broad understanding of phytoplankton biogeography. Yet the factors that govern phytoplankton community assembly, activity, and dynamics over both shorter (daily to sub-seasonal) and longer (interannual) time scales remain poorly understood. The community composition and activity of phytoplankton can fluctuate rapidly, particularly in coastal and estuarine environments, with ecological and even toxicological consequences. This project established the PhytoChop Coastal Observatory, an advanced autonomous instrument array designed to monitor the composition and photosynthetic activity of the phytoplankton community, together with water column nutrient and temperature and salinity data, over long durations at high frequency. This integrated array will enable a deeper understanding of the ecological factors that govern phytoplankton community assembly and activity within a subtropical and strongly seasonal system, at time scales ranging from cellular division to seasonal succession, and ultimately interannual variability.  The observatory is housed at Horn Point Laboratory's research pier situated on the Choptank River, a mesohaline tidal sub-estuary of the Chesapeake Bay (Figure 1). Water is continuously pumped from the Choptank River into the enclosure where it is then passed to a series of instruments. PhytoChop includes an Imaging FlowCytobot (IFCB), a rugged and waterproof flow cytometer that captures high resolution images (~3.4 pixels/micron) of individual phytoplankton (Figure 2). Our research team includes an algal taxonomist with expertise on IFCB imagery who is employing machine learning image recognition software to identify and enumerate phytoplankton taxa. To complement the IFCB and to gain a better understanding of water quality dynamics, the enclosure also features instrumentation that measures water temperature, salinity, nutrient concentrations and phytoplankton biomass and physiology (active fluorometry).  We have developed a public-facing website that allows the general public to view and access PhytoChop data (www.umces.edu/phytochop) and have developed learning tools to incorporate observatory data into undergraduate curriculum. Moreover, PhytoChop data is being used for a variety of applied research projects, including water quality impacts on aquaculture. The core instrumentation is also serving as a nexus for a suite of additional data streams through extramural funding. In the summer of 2022 researchers deployed a series of hyperspectral radiometers that emulate future earth-observing satellite missions that measure water color (Figure 3), and beginning in 2023 researchers will be taking weekly water samples for environmental DNA analysis.       Last Modified: 11/29/2022       Submitted by: Greg Silsbe]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
