<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[BII-Design: Evolution of Oxygenic Photosynthesis]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>79534.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>79534</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DBI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Stephen DiFazio</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sdifazio@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924517</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The evolution of oxygenic photosynthesis changed the trajectory of life on Earth. By about 2.4 billion years ago, photosynthesis began to cause accumulation of oxygen in Earth’s atmosphere. This oxygen eventually allowed multicellular animals to evolve. However, scientists do not know when or how oxygenic photosynthesis evolved. Understanding its origin requires integrating data and ideas from biochemistry, microbiology, evolutionary biology, and Earth history. This project will bring together individual scientists with the breadth of knowledge and diversity of skills to identify and address the key questions for understanding oxygenic photosynthesis. Specifically, researchers will design a cross-disciplinary Biology Integration Institute on The Evolution of Oxygenic Photosynthesis. The team will include university students and early career scientists who will learn cross-disciplinary techniques through participation in project-related activities and as part of a graduate level course that integrates appropriate sciences. Public outreach and education projects will show others how scientists work together on complicated problems. The researchers are committed to diversity, inclusivity, and academic excellence, and they will apply best practices for broadening participation and integrating educational components into the project.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;The researchers will establish a cross-disciplinary collaboration at UC Davis to investigate the evolution of oxygenic photosynthesis. Through a series of workshops, they will: 1) assess current knowledge and hypotheses; 2) articulate outstanding questions that transcend subdisciplines and can be productively addressed by an interdisciplinary team; 3) identify additional key collaborators to address research questions; 4) build an interdisciplinary and interinstitutional research team to answer the target questions; and 5) host a writing workshop for all collaborators to construct an Implementation proposal with active participation from the full Implementation team. This project advances the mission of the Biology Integration Institute and NSF by linking researchers across biological and geological disciplines.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/27/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/13/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2022126</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ralph</FirstName>
<LastName>Britt</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ralph D Britt</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[rdbritt@ucdavis.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000243309</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/27/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Patrick</FirstName>
<LastName>Shih</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Patrick M Shih</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[pmshih@lbl.gov]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000782160</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/27/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dawn</FirstName>
<LastName>Sumner</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>Y</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Dawn Y Sumner</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[dysumner@ucdavis.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000417193</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/27/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Charles</FirstName>
<LastName>Brown</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>T</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Charles T Brown</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ctbrown@ucdavis.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000497272</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/27/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Christen</FirstName>
<LastName>Grettenberger</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Christen Grettenberger</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[clgrettenberger@ucdavis.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000744530</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/27/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Davis</Name>
<CityName>DAVIS</CityName>
<ZipCode>956186153</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5307547700</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1850 RESEARCH PARK DR, STE 300</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>TX2DAGQPENZ5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, DAVIS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>NUDGYLBB4S99</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Davis]]></Name>
<CityName>Davis</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>956186134</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1 Shields Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7275</Code>
<Text>Cross-BIO Activities</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~79534</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project was designed to create a large-scale research proposal aimed at discovering the origin and evolutionary history of photosynthesis. This work requires scientists from multiple disciplines that often do not work together. To bring researchers together and generate the proposal, the team proceeded through eight key goals:</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <ol> <li><strong>Assessing the Current Knowledge Regarding the Origin and Evolution of Oxygenic Photosynthesis</strong>: The design team met regularly during fall 2020 and winter 2021 to determine the state of knowledge in the field for each of our sub-disciplines. They identified gaps in the knowledge within their sub-disciplines and other sub-disciplines. This allowed the team to identify potential areas for further research.</li> <li><strong>Articulating Outstanding Questions That Can Be Productively Addressed by an Interdisciplinary Team:</strong>&nbsp;The team identified six promising research themes that can be addressed by members of the team and additional members of an implementation team. They used those research themes as the basis for a 2022 BII Implementation proposal, which was submitted and edited for a 2023 resubmission.</li> <li><strong>Assembling a Research Team</strong>: For each of the themes, the team identified potential roles for design team members and began to identify other researchers that could be part of the implementation team. The team also hosted a mini-symposium in spring 2021, which spurred engaging discussion of potential research areas.</li> <li><strong>Building an Interdisciplinary and Interinstitutional Research</strong>: Based on the outcomes from objectives 1-3, the team has begun to plan their interdisciplinary and interinstitutional research plan. The team successfully worked together to design, write and submit a BII Implementation proposal in 2022 and are working to resubmit it in 2023.</li> <li><strong>Hosting a Writing Workshop for All Collaborators to Construct an Implementation Proposal</strong>: The team planned to host an in-person writing workshop but had to move it to an online or hybrid format due to the COVID-19 pandemic. They used their experiences with online learning and meetings over the last year to facilitate an online writing workshop. The team successfully worked together to design, write and submit a BII Implementation proposal in 2022 and are working to resubmit it in 2023.</li> <li><strong>Generating Preliminary Data to Guide the Research in the Implementation Proposal:</strong>&nbsp;The team generated preliminary data to guide the research in the Implementation proposal. Some of this work was published in the journal MSphere.</li> <li><strong>Design and Teach a Graduate Course.</strong>&nbsp;&nbsp;As part of this work, the team trained 6 graduate students in a graduate seminar class. These students learned how to do DNA based work in the field and lab and how to analyze the data.</li> <li><strong>Invest in pilot education and outreach projects.</strong>&nbsp;A graduate student funded by this grant provided a summer research opportunity for 6 undergraduate students during which they devised their own research projects and did laboratory and computational analyses. The team also brought on an expert in education and outreach who helped them to design an effective outreach plan that integrated well into the research project and who was a co-PI on the Implementation proposal in 2022 and will be in 2023.&nbsp;</li> </ol> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/25/2023<br>      Modified by: Christen&nbsp;Grettenberger</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project was designed to create a large-scale research proposal aimed at discovering the origin and evolutionary history of photosynthesis. This work requires scientists from multiple disciplines that often do not work together. To bring researchers together and generate the proposal, the team proceeded through eight key goals:     Assessing the Current Knowledge Regarding the Origin and Evolution of Oxygenic Photosynthesis: The design team met regularly during fall 2020 and winter 2021 to determine the state of knowledge in the field for each of our sub-disciplines. They identified gaps in the knowledge within their sub-disciplines and other sub-disciplines. This allowed the team to identify potential areas for further research. Articulating Outstanding Questions That Can Be Productively Addressed by an Interdisciplinary Team: The team identified six promising research themes that can be addressed by members of the team and additional members of an implementation team. They used those research themes as the basis for a 2022 BII Implementation proposal, which was submitted and edited for a 2023 resubmission. Assembling a Research Team: For each of the themes, the team identified potential roles for design team members and began to identify other researchers that could be part of the implementation team. The team also hosted a mini-symposium in spring 2021, which spurred engaging discussion of potential research areas. Building an Interdisciplinary and Interinstitutional Research: Based on the outcomes from objectives 1-3, the team has begun to plan their interdisciplinary and interinstitutional research plan. The team successfully worked together to design, write and submit a BII Implementation proposal in 2022 and are working to resubmit it in 2023. Hosting a Writing Workshop for All Collaborators to Construct an Implementation Proposal: The team planned to host an in-person writing workshop but had to move it to an online or hybrid format due to the COVID-19 pandemic. They used their experiences with online learning and meetings over the last year to facilitate an online writing workshop. The team successfully worked together to design, write and submit a BII Implementation proposal in 2022 and are working to resubmit it in 2023. Generating Preliminary Data to Guide the Research in the Implementation Proposal: The team generated preliminary data to guide the research in the Implementation proposal. Some of this work was published in the journal MSphere. Design and Teach a Graduate Course.  As part of this work, the team trained 6 graduate students in a graduate seminar class. These students learned how to do DNA based work in the field and lab and how to analyze the data. Invest in pilot education and outreach projects. A graduate student funded by this grant provided a summer research opportunity for 6 undergraduate students during which they devised their own research projects and did laboratory and computational analyses. The team also brought on an expert in education and outreach who helped them to design an effective outreach plan that integrated well into the research project and who was a co-PI on the Implementation proposal in 2022 and will be in 2023.            Last Modified: 04/25/2023       Submitted by: Christen Grettenberger]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
