<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research FSML: PhytoChop: An estuarine phytoplankton observatory]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>21840.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>21840</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DBI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Peter McCartney</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Phytoplankton form the base of aquatic foodwebs and play a fundamental role in the transformation of energy, carbon, and nutrients in aquatic ecosystems. Phytoplankton biomass and species composition can fluctuate rapidly, with ecological and even toxicological consequences, yet the factors that govern these dynamics in coastal and estuarine environments remains poorly constrained. This project establishes the PhytoChop Coastal Observatory, an autonomous instrument array designed to continuously monitor the composition and photosynthetic activity of the phytoplankton community. The observatory, located at Horn Point Laboratory’s research pier situated on a tidal sub-estuary of Chesapeake Bay, the Choptank River, will provide images and quantitative data describing phytoplankton composition and activity on a public-facing data portal. The project will provide data that will enable a deeper understanding of the factors that govern phytoplankton dynamics at time scales ranging from cellular division to seasonal succession and eventually to interannual scales. Engagement with end-users will take several forms, including the development of computer scripts for scientists, course modules for students, image libraries for everyone including the general public, and an internship to specifically engage with the oyster aquaculture community. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This proposal seeks to establish a state-of-the-art coastal observatory, PhytoChop, to support research and education on the community composition and ecophysiology of phytoplankton, including photosynthetic and mixotrophic protists and cyanobacteria. The PhytoChop Coastal Observatory will be housed at Horn Point Laboratory’s research pier drawing water from a mesohaline tidal sub-estuary of Chesapeake Bay, the Choptank River. The observatory will provide high frequency taxonomic and physiological data by combining an Imaging FlowCytobot (IFCB), a Fast-Repetition Rate Fluorometer (FRRF), and instrumentation to measure environmental parameters that constrain phytoplankton growth (temperature, light, nutrients). Data collection frequency will enable examination of the phytoplankton community from time scales spanning from cell division to seasonal succession, and eventually to interannual scales. The data stream resulting from the PhytoChop Coastal Observatory will be made publicly available in near-real time to be readily available to the scientific community at (https://hplmonitoring.umces.edu/). To help streamline data analysis in the classroom and beyond, we will deposit scripts (R, Python) that import and query PhytoChop Coastal Observatory data into a GitHub repository. Data resulting from this project is anticipated to benefit a broad scientific audience including phytoplankton ecologists and physiologists and coastal and estuarine ecosystem ecologists.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/23/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/23/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2022966</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Emily</FirstName>
<LastName>Brownlee</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>F</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Emily F Brownlee</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[efbrownlee@smcm.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000821665</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/23/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>St Mary's College of Maryland</Name>
<CityName>SAINT MARYS CITY</CityName>
<ZipCode>206863002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2408954192</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>18952 E FISHER RD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MD05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>UFQ5LT1SLK61</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>EDUCATION, MARYLAND DEPARTMENT OF</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>EJEEH8S7HW17</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[St Mary's College of Maryland]]></Name>
<CityName>St. Mary's City</CityName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>206863001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[18952 E. Fisher Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MD05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7593</Code>
<Text>FIELD STATIONS AND MARINE LABS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1104</Code>
<Text>FIELD STATIONS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~21840</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-a029751b-7fff-cbd1-2eaf-a9fdea4951da"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The major goal of this project was to establish a coastal observatory, PhytoChop, at the research pier of the University of Maryland Center for Environmental Science- Horn Point Laboratory (UMCES HPL) on the Choptank River. The specialized instrumentation housed at the observatory are an Imaging FlowCytobot (IFCB), a fast repetition rate fluorometer (FRRF), and nutrient and water quality analyzers. The IFCB is essentially an underwater microscope, which takes high resolution images of phytoplankton and the microzooplankton that feed upon them. It can provide data on what types of phytoplankton are present and their abundance. The FRRF provides data on the photosynthetic efficiency of phytoplankton. The nutrient and water quality analyzers provide complementary environmental data for the biological instrumentation. This suite of automated instrumentation continuously samples the Choptank River to provide long-term, high frequency measurements of phytoplankton composition, abundance, and photosynthetic activity.&nbsp;</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Co-PI Emily Brownlee's contribution to the major goals of the project related to the optimization and field deployment of the IFCB. Additionally, she implemented data analysis of IFCB phytoplankton images to create a training set that will allow for automated classification of images. Currently, the consistent generation of data by the IFCB is underway and publicly available (</span><a href="https://ifcb.hpl.umces.edu/timeline?dataset=hpl-ifcb-data"><span>https://ifcb.hpl.umces.edu/timeline?dataset=hpl-ifcb-data</span></a><span>). During this time, Brownlee worked with UMCES scientists and graduate students to integrate the IFCB into the observatory and train them on how to optimize and field deploy the instrument. During the final stages of the project, Brownlee trained an undergraduate student on IFCB data analysis and image classification. Beyond the technical aspects, Brownlee developed a curriculum</span><span> that implements IFCB images into a course-based undergraduate research experience for an upper division undergraduate Biological Oceanography course. Students will learn plankton taxonomy of major plankton groups of the Chesapeake Bay and design questions on how the major groups will respond to environmental changes.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>This integrated array will enable a deeper understanding of the ecological factors</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>that govern phytoplankton community assembly and activity in the Chesapeake Bay. Furthermore, high temporal resolution abundance and identification data can also be instrumental in real-time detection and early notification of harmful algal blooms (HABs), which can lead to timely shellfish closings.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/22/2022<br>      Modified by: Emily&nbsp;F&nbsp;Brownlee</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   The major goal of this project was to establish a coastal observatory, PhytoChop, at the research pier of the University of Maryland Center for Environmental Science- Horn Point Laboratory (UMCES HPL) on the Choptank River. The specialized instrumentation housed at the observatory are an Imaging FlowCytobot (IFCB), a fast repetition rate fluorometer (FRRF), and nutrient and water quality analyzers. The IFCB is essentially an underwater microscope, which takes high resolution images of phytoplankton and the microzooplankton that feed upon them. It can provide data on what types of phytoplankton are present and their abundance. The FRRF provides data on the photosynthetic efficiency of phytoplankton. The nutrient and water quality analyzers provide complementary environmental data for the biological instrumentation. This suite of automated instrumentation continuously samples the Choptank River to provide long-term, high frequency measurements of phytoplankton composition, abundance, and photosynthetic activity.     Co-PI Emily Brownlee's contribution to the major goals of the project related to the optimization and field deployment of the IFCB. Additionally, she implemented data analysis of IFCB phytoplankton images to create a training set that will allow for automated classification of images. Currently, the consistent generation of data by the IFCB is underway and publicly available (https://ifcb.hpl.umces.edu/timeline?dataset=hpl-ifcb-data). During this time, Brownlee worked with UMCES scientists and graduate students to integrate the IFCB into the observatory and train them on how to optimize and field deploy the instrument. During the final stages of the project, Brownlee trained an undergraduate student on IFCB data analysis and image classification. Beyond the technical aspects, Brownlee developed a curriculum that implements IFCB images into a course-based undergraduate research experience for an upper division undergraduate Biological Oceanography course. Students will learn plankton taxonomy of major plankton groups of the Chesapeake Bay and design questions on how the major groups will respond to environmental changes.    This integrated array will enable a deeper understanding of the ecological factors that govern phytoplankton community assembly and activity in the Chesapeake Bay. Furthermore, high temporal resolution abundance and identification data can also be instrumental in real-time detection and early notification of harmful algal blooms (HABs), which can lead to timely shellfish closings.          Last Modified: 11/22/2022       Submitted by: Emily F Brownlee]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
