<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Symposium: Research Frontiers in Animal Behavior and Parasitism 2020]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>19900.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>19900</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Katharina Dittmar</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kdittmar@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927799</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Host behavior and parasitism are inextricably linked. Behavior frequently defines parasite transmission dynamics; at the same time, parasites can shape complex host behaviors in ecological and evolutionary time. This award supports participation in a conference on Research Frontiers in Animal Behavior and Parasitism, to be held in May 2020 in Athens, GA, USA. The conference brings together experts in infectious disease ecology and animal behavior for a two-day event that will define new frontiers of research at the interface of these important areas of study. Four major conference themes are: (i) links between social behavior and pathogen infection; (ii) host movement behavior and pathogen spread; (iii) pathogen-driven changes to host and vector behavior; and (iv) mechanisms and evolution of behavioral defenses.  Each of these sessions will feature keynote talks from invited speakers, together with short contributed presentations from conference attendees.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This conference provides a platform for professional development and future collaboration between established researchers and early career scientists. Organizers will administer a science networking event, where more senior conference attendees will meet with junior researchers to discuss research and professional development questions. The conference especially encourages student participation by keeping registration fees low, thus allowing early career researchers to participate and meet leading scientists in the field. Early career researchers will play an active role in shaping emerging perspectives that develop from the conference, to map out frontiers of research in the field. The conference will also include early career researchers who are members of the Weaving the Future of Animal Behavior (WFAB) community which will help foster the integration of ideas from animal behavior with infectious disease ecology and evolution. Finally, ideas emerging from discussion at the symposium will feature as short contributions to an upcoming edited volume on animal behavior and parasites.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is being jointly funded by the Ecology and Evolution of Infectious Diseases Program (Division of Environmental Biology) and the Behavioral Systems Program (Division of Integrative Organismal Systems).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/31/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/31/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2022897</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
<LastName>Hall</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Richard J Hall</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[rjhall@uga.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000608916</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/31/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Vanessa</FirstName>
<LastName>Ezenwa</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>O</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Vanessa O Ezenwa</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[vezenwa@uga.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000398870</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/31/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sonia</FirstName>
<LastName>Altizer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sonia M Altizer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[saltizer@uga.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000208966</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/31/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Georgia Research Foundation Inc</Name>
<CityName>ATHENS</CityName>
<ZipCode>306021589</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7065425939</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>310 E CAMPUS RD RM 409</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NMJHD63STRC5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF GEORGIA RESEARCH FOUNDATION, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Georgia]]></Name>
<CityName>Athens</CityName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>306021589</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[310 East Campus Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7374</Code>
<Text>Systematics &amp; Biodiversity Sci</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7659</Code>
<Text>Animal Behavior</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~19900</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Many animal and human behaviors, including social interactions, and decisions about when and where to gather, nest, and forage are shaped by interactions with parasites and perceived infection risk. In turn, behaviors like social distancing and mate choice can alter the trajectories of parasite transmission and evolution, as vividly illustrated by the ongoing COVID-19 pandemic. The many connections between animal behavior and parasitism have been the subject of growing research interest, and this project aimed to synthesize existing knowledge and identify new research frontiers at the interface of animal behavior and parasitism by organizing a virtual symposium and producing an associated book.</p> <p>We organized a two-day virtual symposium on animal behavior and parasitism which brought together 120 early-career and senior researchers from across the globe for a mixture of short research talks and posters, an early-career networking event, and synthesis discussion. The presentations resulting from this event are publicly available at the symposium website: <a href="https://www.ceid.uga.edu/symposium2021/">https://www.ceid.uga.edu/symposium2021/</a>. Following the symposium, we edited a book entitled Animal Behavior and Parasitism, to be published in October 2022. The book features 19 chapters focusing on fundamental topics at the interface of parasitism and animal behavior, including social, movement and mating behavior, parasite modification of host behavior and host behavioral defenses against parasitism. Additionally, two &lsquo;emerging frontiers&rsquo; chapters motivated, in part, by discussion at the symposium, were led by early-career researchers.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/31/2022<br>      Modified by: Richard&nbsp;J&nbsp;Hall</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Many animal and human behaviors, including social interactions, and decisions about when and where to gather, nest, and forage are shaped by interactions with parasites and perceived infection risk. In turn, behaviors like social distancing and mate choice can alter the trajectories of parasite transmission and evolution, as vividly illustrated by the ongoing COVID-19 pandemic. The many connections between animal behavior and parasitism have been the subject of growing research interest, and this project aimed to synthesize existing knowledge and identify new research frontiers at the interface of animal behavior and parasitism by organizing a virtual symposium and producing an associated book.  We organized a two-day virtual symposium on animal behavior and parasitism which brought together 120 early-career and senior researchers from across the globe for a mixture of short research talks and posters, an early-career networking event, and synthesis discussion. The presentations resulting from this event are publicly available at the symposium website: https://www.ceid.uga.edu/symposium2021/. Following the symposium, we edited a book entitled Animal Behavior and Parasitism, to be published in October 2022. The book features 19 chapters focusing on fundamental topics at the interface of parasitism and animal behavior, including social, movement and mating behavior, parasite modification of host behavior and host behavioral defenses against parasitism. Additionally, two ‘emerging frontiers’ chapters motivated, in part, by discussion at the symposium, were led by early-career researchers.          Last Modified: 07/31/2022       Submitted by: Richard J Hall]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
