<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[CAREER: INTEGRATED WATER, ENERGY, AND EMISSIONS DECISION MAKING FOR A LOW CARBON FUTURE WITH COAL-FIRED POWER PLANTS]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>424106.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>424106</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Mamadou Diallo</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mdiallo@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924257</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[1554117&lt;br/&gt;Mauter&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Cost-effectively reducing the human health and environmental externalities of electricity generation is a defining sustainability challenge of the 21st century. Solutions to this complex problem will necessarily span multiple spatial scales, time scales, and disciplines. Integrated decision models can aid researchers, engineering practitioners, and policy makers in moving away from short-term fixes toward holistic sustainability solutions. The proposed research develops an integrated decision model for coal-fired power plants that investigates the effects of market conditions, regulatory policy, power plant emission control processes, and materials performance on the cost of sustainable electricity generation.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The most significant barriers to performing integrated assessment of coal-fired power plants are uncertainties in: 1) the cost and efficacy of wastewater treatment technologies for compliance with proposed effluent limitation guidelines issued by the EPA; 2) the interaction effects between air and water emission control technologies during phased implementation of emission regulations at coal-fired power plants; 3) the viability of alternative wastewater treatment processes that circumvent auxiliary power consumption by using waste heat from coal-fired power plants processes; and, 4) the role that new membrane materials might play in enabling these alternative water treatment processes in the future. The proposed work will fill these fundamental knowledge gaps and integrate the findings into an aqueous emissions control decision model that guides policy, directs compliance pathways, motivates technology development, and enables the reliable prediction of future emissions. The most significant barrier to stakeholders using integrated decision-making tools to inform compliance pathways at coal-fired power plants is that these academically-derived tools rarely evolve with stakeholder needs. The proposed stakeholder engagement process, beginning with a research prioritization workshop, continuing through yearly meetings, and culminating in a simple and adaptive decision tool, will increase the probability that this model is widely adopted. Additional outreach and educational tasks are integrated into the model development process and span the K-12, undergraduate, and doctoral research communities. The principal investigator (PI) will engage high-school students in documenting aqueous emissions from Ohio River Valley coal-fired power plants. The PI will also develop a formal mentorship program for undergraduate researchers and doctoral student mentors in the PI's laboratory that will promote targeted goal setting, improve skill development, and enhance retention of undergraduate researchers in STEM fields.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/06/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/06/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2023841</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Meagan</FirstName>
<LastName>Mauter</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Meagan S Mauter</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mauter@stanford.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000619520</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/06/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Stanford University</Name>
<CityName>STANFORD</CityName>
<ZipCode>943052004</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6507232300</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>450 JANE STANFORD WAY</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>16</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA16</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>HJD6G4D6TJY5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>THE LELAND STANFORD JUNIOR UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Stanford University]]></Name>
<CityName>Stanford</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>943052004</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[450 Jane Stanford Way]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>16</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA16</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1440</Code>
<Text>EnvE-Environmental Engineering</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01001617DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~424105</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Coal fired power plants (CFPPs) continue to be largest emitters of air toxics,&nbsp;aqueous contaminants,&nbsp;and greenhouse gasses&nbsp;in the US. Though market conditions and regulatory pressure have reduced the fraction of electricity generation by CFPPs significantly,&nbsp;some regions are still highly dependent on coal.&nbsp; Most atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub>&nbsp;stabilization scenarios assume that the US will cut &gt;80% of electricity sector CO<sub>2</sub>&nbsp;emissions by 2050, but transitioning away from high-carbon intensity CFPP generation will be a 20-25 year process.<sup><br /></sup></p> <p>To encourage this transition process, the US Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) has proposed or promulgated a number of rules that systematically ratchet down the emissions from CFPPs in order to reduce human health damages and limit the profitability of old CFPP facilities. Some combination of SO<sub>2,</sub>&nbsp;NO<sub>x,</sub><sub>&nbsp;</sub>mercury,&nbsp;ozone,&nbsp;CO<sub>2</sub>,&nbsp;and wastewater effluent pollution control&nbsp;regulations are likely to affect every CFPP over the next decade. While work is underway to evaluate cost-effective compliance options for criteria air pollutant reduction and CO<sub>2</sub>&nbsp;capture/storage at CFPPs,&nbsp;there is a critical gap in the development and analysis of wastewater management options for compliance with proposed effluent limitation guidelines (ELGs) issued by the EPA.<sup><br /></sup></p> <p>In addition, policy makers lack a comprehensive understanding of the interactions between air and water regulatory standards.&nbsp; Air emission control technologies generate additional wastewater loads, while energy intensive wastewater treatment processes consume auxiliary power and may lead to additional air emissions.&nbsp; Integrated assessment of air and water control technologies are critical to guiding policy, directing compliance pathways, motivating technology development, and predicting future emissions.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>This project developed a series of integrated decision support tools that consider interactions between air and water pollution control technologies, compare the costs and performance of wastewater management processes, and direct the development and valuation of novel membrane materials that enable high recovery wastewater treatment are critical for the affordable transition to sustainable electricity generation.&nbsp; We also integrated research and education to advance the policies, processes, and materials associated with wastewater management at coal-fired power plants (CFPPs).&nbsp;</p> <p>Key scientific, policy, and educational outcomes included: 1) developing an aqueous emissions control technology decision model to assess how regulatory&nbsp;policy&nbsp;will influence wastewater quantity and composition, auxiliary power consumption and air emissions, and the cost of electricity generation at US CFPPs. 2) Evaluated the techno-economic feasibility and avoided auxiliary power consumption of emerging wastewater treatment&nbsp;processes&nbsp;that are powered by waste heat from CFPPs, including forward osmosis (FO) and membrane distillation (MD).&nbsp; 3) Elucidated structure-function relationships for MD&nbsp;materials&nbsp;and estimated the wastewater treatment cost and energy savings conferred by enhanced membrane permeability. 4) Disseminated model results to assist regulators and operators of CFPPs cost-effectively manage wastewater treatment during the transition to sustainable electricity generation.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/01/2023<br>      Modified by: Meagan&nbsp;S&nbsp;Mauter</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Coal fired power plants (CFPPs) continue to be largest emitters of air toxics, aqueous contaminants, and greenhouse gasses in the US. Though market conditions and regulatory pressure have reduced the fraction of electricity generation by CFPPs significantly, some regions are still highly dependent on coal.  Most atmospheric CO2 stabilization scenarios assume that the US will cut &gt;80% of electricity sector CO2 emissions by 2050, but transitioning away from high-carbon intensity CFPP generation will be a 20-25 year process.   To encourage this transition process, the US Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) has proposed or promulgated a number of rules that systematically ratchet down the emissions from CFPPs in order to reduce human health damages and limit the profitability of old CFPP facilities. Some combination of SO2, NOx, mercury, ozone, CO2, and wastewater effluent pollution control regulations are likely to affect every CFPP over the next decade. While work is underway to evaluate cost-effective compliance options for criteria air pollutant reduction and CO2 capture/storage at CFPPs, there is a critical gap in the development and analysis of wastewater management options for compliance with proposed effluent limitation guidelines (ELGs) issued by the EPA.   In addition, policy makers lack a comprehensive understanding of the interactions between air and water regulatory standards.  Air emission control technologies generate additional wastewater loads, while energy intensive wastewater treatment processes consume auxiliary power and may lead to additional air emissions.  Integrated assessment of air and water control technologies are critical to guiding policy, directing compliance pathways, motivating technology development, and predicting future emissions.    This project developed a series of integrated decision support tools that consider interactions between air and water pollution control technologies, compare the costs and performance of wastewater management processes, and direct the development and valuation of novel membrane materials that enable high recovery wastewater treatment are critical for the affordable transition to sustainable electricity generation.  We also integrated research and education to advance the policies, processes, and materials associated with wastewater management at coal-fired power plants (CFPPs).   Key scientific, policy, and educational outcomes included: 1) developing an aqueous emissions control technology decision model to assess how regulatory policy will influence wastewater quantity and composition, auxiliary power consumption and air emissions, and the cost of electricity generation at US CFPPs. 2) Evaluated the techno-economic feasibility and avoided auxiliary power consumption of emerging wastewater treatment processes that are powered by waste heat from CFPPs, including forward osmosis (FO) and membrane distillation (MD).  3) Elucidated structure-function relationships for MD materials and estimated the wastewater treatment cost and energy savings conferred by enhanced membrane permeability. 4) Disseminated model results to assist regulators and operators of CFPPs cost-effectively manage wastewater treatment during the transition to sustainable electricity generation.          Last Modified: 06/01/2023       Submitted by: Meagan S Mauter]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
