<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[CHS: Small: Computational Modeling of Human Rhythms to Improve Health and Quality of Life]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/17/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>448237.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>480237</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Dan Cosley</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dcosley@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928832</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[According to recent research, balance is a significant contributor to health and well-being. Health challenges are associated with work and personal imbalances, in the form of overload, that exceed human capability to manage their own natural pace. Part of these overloads are due to the imposition of activities and mis-timed or incompatible demands on biological and psychological needs, or lack of attention to synchronization or receptivity of mental and physical states when meeting work and life demands. Advice about life management and health is often generic (for example, have 8 hours sleep a day) rather than tailored to individual lifestyles. This research proposes to improve health and wellbeing in individuals through awareness of their personal rhythms, which are repeated cycles of internal and external events including biological, mental, social, and environmental. The investigators seek to design and evaluate a data analytic and modeling method to make people aware of what they could be doing at any given time to align with their biological clock and to achieve high performance in daily life and work without burning out or developing stress-related disorders. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research provides an intelligent platform for collecting longitudinal data and modeling human rhythms to enable detection of current, and prediction of future states in each rhythm to provide optimal action recommendations and interventions. The work leverages advances in wearable devices, sensing technology, and online sources to proactively collect and analyze physiological, psychological, behavioral, social, and environmental data to identify personal rhythms, to explore their relationship to positive physical, mental, and behavioral outcomes, and to provide people with tools to reason about these relationships and to improve outcomes. In addition to advancing the state of the art in modeling rhythmic patterns, the research will demonstrate the impact of rhythm-aware technology in changing people?s perceptions and behavior and directing them towards a more balanced and successful life. Integration of personal rhythms in daily lives of individuals will transform societal activities and the overall performance of people and contributes to creating a healthier society.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/15/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/23/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2023762</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Afsaneh</FirstName>
<LastName>Doryab</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Afsaneh Doryab</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ad4ks@virginia.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000704586</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/15/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Virginia Main Campus</Name>
<CityName>CHARLOTTESVILLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>229034833</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4349244270</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1001 EMMET ST N</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>VA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>JJG6HU8PA4S5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RECTOR &amp; VISITORS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[The Rector & Visitors of the University of Virginia]]></Name>
<CityName>Charlottesville</CityName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>229034833</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1001 N. Emmet St.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>VA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7367</Code>
<Text>HCC-Human-Centered Computing</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7367</Code>
<Text>Cyber-Human Systems</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7923</Code>
<Text>SMALL PROJECT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01001819DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01001920DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~448237</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~16000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~16000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-3246295a-7fff-3094-16ff-ebc1d00c26ac"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span><strong>Project Overview</strong>: <span id="docs-internal-guid-9ba3aafb-7fff-cda7-70d7-03636480ebc0"><span>The project aimed to enhance individuals' health and wellbeing by increasing their awareness of biobehavioral rhythms, encompassing biological, mental, social, and environmental cycles. This research leveraged mobile and wearable devices, as well as sensing technology, to collect, model, and analyze various data streams. The ultimate goal was to gain a deeper understanding of human rhythms and their impact on health, wellness, and performance.</span></span></span></p> <p dir="ltr"><strong>Key Objectives and Achievements:</strong></p> <p dir="ltr"><span><strong>Objective 1 -&nbsp;<span id="docs-internal-guid-51c76757-7fff-244e-4bfb-eb422ed2db53"><span>Develop an Intelligent Platform for Analyzing Rhythms:&nbsp;</span></span></strong></span>A computational framework (CoRhythmo) was created to process diverse sensor data streams, identify periodic characteristics, and build micro machine learning models for sensor features<span style="font-size: 10px;"><sup>1</sup></span>. CoRhythmo demonstrated its capability to process vast data streams and shed light on the relationships between biobehavioral rhythms and mental health and productivity. An extensive multimodal dataset on biobehavioral rhythms was also generated, enabling the examination of various cyclic patterns. CoRhythmo software and dataset are accessible on GitHub<span style="font-size: 10px;"><sup>2</sup></span>.</p> <p><strong>Objective 2 - Advance the understanding of human rhythms:&nbsp;</strong>The research went beyond circadian rhythms, showcasing the existence of different cyclic behaviors and their impact on human health and performance. Innovative methods for measuring rhythm stability were introduced, revealing correlations between regular behavioral patterns and resilience<span style="font-size: 10px;"><sup>3</sup></span>. The research identified significant disruptions in biobehavioral rhythms in cancer patients, and machine learning models built with rhythm features outperformed traditional medical measures in predicting readmission rates<span style="font-size: 10px;"><sup>4</sup></span>. Furthermore, the project made significant strides in mental health prediction, identifying distinct repeating behavior patterns among college students with depression, loneliness, and social isolation<span style="font-size: 10px;"><sup>1,5</sup></span>. These findings underscore the potential of mobile and wearable technology to model complex and longitudinal human behavior.</p> <p><strong>Objective 3 - Integrate rhythm-awareness into technology for behavior improvement:&nbsp;</strong>Personalized music melodies were developed based on sensor data to communicate biobehavioral patterns, leading to positive behavior changes<span style="font-size: 10px;"><sup>6</sup></span>. We also explored circadian-based scheduling approaches, which resulted in improved wellbeing when participants adhered to circadian schedules<span style="font-size: 10px;"><sup>7</sup></span>.</p> <p><strong>Disciplinary Imapct:&nbsp;</strong>The project introduced a flexible computational framework within the Ubiquitous Computing community. This framework enables the processing of massive sensor data at various time granularities, allowing the observation of short- and long-term cyclic behaviors, stability modeling, and impact assessment. Additionally, the project generated the first-ever longitudinal mobile and wearable dataset focused on biobehavioral rhythms, benefiting research not only in Human-Centered Computing but also in related fields.</p> <p><span id="docs-internal-guid-f4933c3c-7fff-befe-ac2b-fe59571e9e91"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Both the software and dataset resulting from the project are shared with the research community, promoting collaboration and further advancements in the study of biobehavioral rhythms.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span><strong>Impact on Other Disciplines:</strong>&nbsp;<span id="docs-internal-guid-c5ad160d-7fff-55a8-4790-bb1968978ca5"><span>The developed computational framework and methods have implications for psychology, behavioral science, and medicine. For example, research on biobehavioral rhythms in cancer patients revealed disruptions during treatment, especially in hospitals, and their association with readmission after discharge. These findings could significantly influence hospital environments to reduce readmissions.</span></span></span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span><strong>Impact on Human Resources:</strong> The project provided valuable training to more than 30 graduate and undergraduate students (17 female), enhancing their skills in critical thinking, research design, data analysis, and collaboration. These skills are essential for their future careers in academia and industry.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span id="docs-internal-guid-3555ec1e-7fff-80d4-10db-36eddca6ce2f"><strong>Impact on Technology Transfer</strong>:&nbsp;<span id="docs-internal-guid-3507c060-7fff-a44a-fe4e-8413c9b5c180">The research advanced the understanding of human rhythms and their impact on health and wellbeing. It also paved the way for technology transfer<span style="font-size: 10px;"><sup>8&nbsp;</sup></span>and interdisciplinary collaboration, demonstrating the potential for real-world applications to improve lives through rhythm-aware technology.</span></span></p> <p dir="ltr"><strong>Selected Publications and products:</strong></p> <p dir="ltr">1.&nbsp;Yan, R., Liu, X., Dutcher, J., Tumminia, M., Villalba, D., Cohen, S., ... &amp; Doryab, A. (2022). A computational framework for modeling biobehavioral rhythms from mobile and wearable data streams.&nbsp;<em>ACM Transactions on Intelligent Systems and Technology (TIST)</em>,&nbsp;<em>13</em>(3), 1-27.</p> <p dir="ltr">2.&nbsp;https://github.com/HAI-lab-UVA</p> <p dir="ltr">3.&nbsp;<span id="docs-internal-guid-4db677b0-7fff-09ee-89e8-38d538b2cef6">Gao, J., Yan, R. &amp; Doryab A. (2023). Modeling Regularity and Predictability in Human Behavior from Multidimensional Sensing Signals and Personal Characteristics. Proceedings of 22nd International Conference in Machine Learning and Applications.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr">4. Doryab, A., Dey, A. K., Kao, G., &amp; Low, C. (2019). Modeling biobehavioral rhythms with passive sensing in the wild: a case study to predict readmission risk after pancreatic surgery.&nbsp;<em>Proceedings of the ACM on Interactive, Mobile, Wearable and Ubiquitous Technologies</em>,&nbsp;<em>3</em>(1), 1-21.</p> <p dir="ltr">5. Doryab, A., Villalba, D. K., Chikersal, P., Dutcher, J. M., Tumminia, M., Liu, X., ... &amp; Dey, A. K. (2019). Identifying behavioral phenotypes of loneliness and social isolation with passive sensing: statistical analysis, data mining and machine learning of smartphone and fitbit data.&nbsp;<em>JMIR mHealth and uHealth</em>,&nbsp;<em>7</em>(7), e13209.</p> <p dir="ltr">6. Clark, M., &amp; Doryab, A. (2023). Sounds of Health: Using Personalized Sonification Models to Communicate Health Information.&nbsp;<em>Proceedings of the ACM on Interactive, Mobile, Wearable and Ubiquitous Technologies</em>,&nbsp;<em>6</em>(4), 1-31.</p> <p dir="ltr">7. Sadekar, P., Baitinger, J., Conway, S., Clark, M., &amp; Doryab, A. (2023). Personalization in Circadian Rhythm-Based Event Scheduling. In&nbsp;<em>2023 Systems and Information Engineering Design Symposium (SIEDS)</em>&nbsp;(pp. 55-60). IEEE.</p> <p>8.&nbsp;Doryab, A., Yan, R., &amp; Liu, X. (2022).&nbsp;<em>U.S. Patent Application No. 17/398,097</em>.</p> <p dir="ltr">&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/04/2023<br>      Modified by: Afsaneh&nbsp;Doryab</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   Project Overview: The project aimed to enhance individuals' health and wellbeing by increasing their awareness of biobehavioral rhythms, encompassing biological, mental, social, and environmental cycles. This research leveraged mobile and wearable devices, as well as sensing technology, to collect, model, and analyze various data streams. The ultimate goal was to gain a deeper understanding of human rhythms and their impact on health, wellness, and performance. Key Objectives and Achievements: Objective 1 - Develop an Intelligent Platform for Analyzing Rhythms: A computational framework (CoRhythmo) was created to process diverse sensor data streams, identify periodic characteristics, and build micro machine learning models for sensor features1. CoRhythmo demonstrated its capability to process vast data streams and shed light on the relationships between biobehavioral rhythms and mental health and productivity. An extensive multimodal dataset on biobehavioral rhythms was also generated, enabling the examination of various cyclic patterns. CoRhythmo software and dataset are accessible on GitHub2.  Objective 2 - Advance the understanding of human rhythms: The research went beyond circadian rhythms, showcasing the existence of different cyclic behaviors and their impact on human health and performance. Innovative methods for measuring rhythm stability were introduced, revealing correlations between regular behavioral patterns and resilience3. The research identified significant disruptions in biobehavioral rhythms in cancer patients, and machine learning models built with rhythm features outperformed traditional medical measures in predicting readmission rates4. Furthermore, the project made significant strides in mental health prediction, identifying distinct repeating behavior patterns among college students with depression, loneliness, and social isolation1,5. These findings underscore the potential of mobile and wearable technology to model complex and longitudinal human behavior.  Objective 3 - Integrate rhythm-awareness into technology for behavior improvement: Personalized music melodies were developed based on sensor data to communicate biobehavioral patterns, leading to positive behavior changes6. We also explored circadian-based scheduling approaches, which resulted in improved wellbeing when participants adhered to circadian schedules7.  Disciplinary Imapct: The project introduced a flexible computational framework within the Ubiquitous Computing community. This framework enables the processing of massive sensor data at various time granularities, allowing the observation of short- and long-term cyclic behaviors, stability modeling, and impact assessment. Additionally, the project generated the first-ever longitudinal mobile and wearable dataset focused on biobehavioral rhythms, benefiting research not only in Human-Centered Computing but also in related fields.    Both the software and dataset resulting from the project are shared with the research community, promoting collaboration and further advancements in the study of biobehavioral rhythms. Impact on Other Disciplines: The developed computational framework and methods have implications for psychology, behavioral science, and medicine. For example, research on biobehavioral rhythms in cancer patients revealed disruptions during treatment, especially in hospitals, and their association with readmission after discharge. These findings could significantly influence hospital environments to reduce readmissions. Impact on Human Resources: The project provided valuable training to more than 30 graduate and undergraduate students (17 female), enhancing their skills in critical thinking, research design, data analysis, and collaboration. These skills are essential for their future careers in academia and industry.  Impact on Technology Transfer: The research advanced the understanding of human rhythms and their impact on health and wellbeing. It also paved the way for technology transfer8 and interdisciplinary collaboration, demonstrating the potential for real-world applications to improve lives through rhythm-aware technology. Selected Publications and products: 1. Yan, R., Liu, X., Dutcher, J., Tumminia, M., Villalba, D., Cohen, S., ... &amp; Doryab, A. (2022). A computational framework for modeling biobehavioral rhythms from mobile and wearable data streams. ACM Transactions on Intelligent Systems and Technology (TIST), 13(3), 1-27. 2. https://github.com/HAI-lab-UVA 3. Gao, J., Yan, R. &amp; Doryab A. (2023). Modeling Regularity and Predictability in Human Behavior from Multidimensional Sensing Signals and Personal Characteristics. Proceedings of 22nd International Conference in Machine Learning and Applications.  4. Doryab, A., Dey, A. K., Kao, G., &amp; Low, C. (2019). Modeling biobehavioral rhythms with passive sensing in the wild: a case study to predict readmission risk after pancreatic surgery. Proceedings of the ACM on Interactive, Mobile, Wearable and Ubiquitous Technologies, 3(1), 1-21. 5. Doryab, A., Villalba, D. K., Chikersal, P., Dutcher, J. M., Tumminia, M., Liu, X., ... &amp; Dey, A. K. (2019). Identifying behavioral phenotypes of loneliness and social isolation with passive sensing: statistical analysis, data mining and machine learning of smartphone and fitbit data. JMIR mHealth and uHealth, 7(7), e13209. 6. Clark, M., &amp; Doryab, A. (2023). Sounds of Health: Using Personalized Sonification Models to Communicate Health Information. Proceedings of the ACM on Interactive, Mobile, Wearable and Ubiquitous Technologies, 6(4), 1-31. 7. Sadekar, P., Baitinger, J., Conway, S., Clark, M., &amp; Doryab, A. (2023). Personalization in Circadian Rhythm-Based Event Scheduling. In 2023 Systems and Information Engineering Design Symposium (SIEDS) (pp. 55-60). IEEE.  8. Doryab, A., Yan, R., &amp; Liu, X. (2022). U.S. Patent Application No. 17/398,097.         Last Modified: 09/04/2023       Submitted by: Afsaneh Doryab]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
