<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Support for Student Participation in the 64th International Conference on Electron, Ion, and Photon Beam Technology and Nanofabrication; New Orleans, Louisiana; May 26-29, 2020]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>18000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>18000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Andrew Wells</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>awells@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927225</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This award supports the student attendance at the International Conference on Electron, Ion and Photon Beam Technology and Nanofabrication (EIPBN) to be held May 26 to 29, 2020, in New Orleans, Louisiana. The EIPBN meeting is an important annual lithography and nanofabrication gathering and attracts participants and presenters from academia, industry, and government laboratories. This forum is instrumental in the generation and incubation of breakthrough and transformative ideas in many scientific areas including nanotechnology and nanomanufacturing. This international conference is a key mechanism for linking basic science with engineering towards the development of useful nano-enabled products, which are significant to the US and world economies. This conference offers a forum for the open exchange of new and previously unpublished scientific research and ideas. This award will partially support the participation of undergraduate and graduate students, to train the next generation of researchers in nanotechnology and nanomanufacturing and to broaden participation by students who would otherwise not be able to attend. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;EIPBN is a major international meeting and will provide a single forum for discussion of the latest developments in directed energy-enabled synthesis, fabrication, imaging, measurement and characterization of nanoscale structures, multi-layered devices and multi-scale systems. NSF funding will be used to support about 36 students financially so that students may participate in short courses, the commercial session, the technical program, and other social events. There are also a number of key student programs, including a Career Mentoring Session with academic and industry leaders, Student Breakfast with the organization committee, and Women in Nanofabrication (WIN) Luncheon to discuss diversity challenges faced by nanotechnology researchers and scientists. The conference organization committee will reach out to local universities and underrepresented groups to recruit student presenters and participants.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/19/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/19/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2023337</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Chih-Hao</FirstName>
<LastName>Chang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Chih-Hao Chang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[chichang@utexas.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000602410</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/19/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Texas at Austin</Name>
<CityName>AUSTIN</CityName>
<ZipCode>787121139</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5124716424</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>110 INNER CAMPUS DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>25</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX25</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>V6AFQPN18437</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT AUSTIN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>X5NKD2NFF2V3</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Texas at Austin]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>787595316</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>37</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX37</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>088Y</Code>
<Text>AM-Advanced Manufacturing</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>081E</Code>
<Text>NANO SCALE ASSEMBLY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>082E</Code>
<Text>MFG MACHINES &amp; METROLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>083E</Code>
<Text>MATERIAL TRANSFORMATION PROC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>084E</Code>
<Text>NANOMANUFACTURING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~18000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The goal of this project was to enable student participation in the 64<sup>th</sup>&nbsp;International Conference on Electron, Ion, and Photon Beam Technologies and Nanofabrication (EIPBN). The EIPBN meeting is the premier symposium focused on nanolithography and attracts academic, industry, and government laboratory participants and presenters. The meeting was held virtually from June 1-4, 2021. The goal of the meeting is to advance knowledge by enabling the exchange of information concerning advanced and emerging nanofabrication and nanomanufacturing topics and how they enable traditional and novel applications. The conference encompassed a short-course workshop session, a commercial exhibit session, a plenary session, an Industrial Highlights session, 18 oral sessions organized in 3 parallel tracks, and 2 poster sessions. The oral and poster sections included 14 invited speakers, 88 contributed oral presentations, and 69 poster presentations. In addition to technical sessions, there are multiple special sessions designed to allow for professional development. These include the Industrial Highlight, Exhibitor Quick Pitch, and the Start-Up Competition to foster collaboration between academia and industry. The Women in Nanofabrication (WIN) luncheon provided a good opportunity for women scientist to find mentors and collaborators. For students, the short-course workshop, Career Mentor Lunch, Student Breakfast, and virtual job fair provided avenues to learn about career paths and job advice.&nbsp;The EIPBN 2021 conference supported free registration and short course attendance for all 335 student attendees, 69 of whom were presenters.&nbsp;A variety of universities, countries, and topics were represented among the students receiving support.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/15/2022<br>      Modified by: Chih-Hao&nbsp;Chang</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The goal of this project was to enable student participation in the 64th International Conference on Electron, Ion, and Photon Beam Technologies and Nanofabrication (EIPBN). The EIPBN meeting is the premier symposium focused on nanolithography and attracts academic, industry, and government laboratory participants and presenters. The meeting was held virtually from June 1-4, 2021. The goal of the meeting is to advance knowledge by enabling the exchange of information concerning advanced and emerging nanofabrication and nanomanufacturing topics and how they enable traditional and novel applications. The conference encompassed a short-course workshop session, a commercial exhibit session, a plenary session, an Industrial Highlights session, 18 oral sessions organized in 3 parallel tracks, and 2 poster sessions. The oral and poster sections included 14 invited speakers, 88 contributed oral presentations, and 69 poster presentations. In addition to technical sessions, there are multiple special sessions designed to allow for professional development. These include the Industrial Highlight, Exhibitor Quick Pitch, and the Start-Up Competition to foster collaboration between academia and industry. The Women in Nanofabrication (WIN) luncheon provided a good opportunity for women scientist to find mentors and collaborators. For students, the short-course workshop, Career Mentor Lunch, Student Breakfast, and virtual job fair provided avenues to learn about career paths and job advice. The EIPBN 2021 conference supported free registration and short course attendance for all 335 student attendees, 69 of whom were presenters. A variety of universities, countries, and topics were represented among the students receiving support.           Last Modified: 01/15/2022       Submitted by: Chih-Hao Chang]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
