<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Midwest Numerical Analysis Day 2020]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>5000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>5000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Yuliya Gorb</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ygorb@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922113</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This award supports participation of early-career researchers in the annual conference "The Midwest Numerical Analysis Day" held at the campus of Missouri University of Science and Technology, Rolla, MO, on September 25-26, 2020. The Midwest Numerical Analysis Day has provided a forum since the 1990s for computational mathematicians in the Midwest area to share their research on numerical methods and their analysis. Since many engineers will participate in the Midwest Numerical Analysis Day 2020, this conference will provide an important platform for computational scientists and engineers to communicate with each other on recent development, analysis, and applications of various numerical methods, and find common interests for future collaborations. The Midwest Numerical Analysis Day has also served as a yearly regional conference to provide an opportunity for graduate students and postdocs to present their research on numerical methods. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The topics of this conference focus on the algorithm development, analysis, and applications of efficient, accurate, and stable numerical methods, especially those for solving multi-physics and multi-scale problems. In recent years, the inherent multi-physics and multi-scale features of many sophisticated and challenging real-world problems accentuate the importance to develop more efficient, accurate, and stable numerical methods for the relevant partial differential equations. In order to address these needs, the Midwest Numerical Analysis Day 2020 intends to create a forum for early-career and senior researchers from different fields, including computational mathematics, computer science, physics, and various engineering fields, to discuss recent advances on relevant numerical methods with the corresponding numerical analysis and applications.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/26/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/26/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2023264</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jue</FirstName>
<LastName>Yan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jue Yan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jyan@iastate.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000110021</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/26/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Xiaoming</FirstName>
<LastName>He</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Xiaoming He</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[hex@mst.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000582591</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/26/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Missouri University of Science and Technology</Name>
<CityName>ROLLA</CityName>
<ZipCode>654091330</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5733414134</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>300 W. 12TH STREET</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[202 CENTENNIAL HALL]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MO08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>Y6MGH342N169</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MISSOURI SYSTEM</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Missouri University of Science and Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>Rolla</CityName>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>654096506</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Department of Math & Stat]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MO08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1271</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL MATHEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9263</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL SCIENCE &amp; ENGING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~5000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Midwest Numerical Analysis Day 2021 was hosted at Havener center of Missouri University of Science and Technology from October 29-30, 2021. This NSF grant was used to provide travel support to 11 graduate students and 1 postdoc for attending the conference and giving presentations. This conference is featured with 4 plenary presentations, 50 parallel presentations in 12 parallel sessions, and 116 participants.</p> <p>The Midwest Numerical Analysis Day conference series brings together young mathematicians, mathematics graduate students, recent PhDs, women and underrepresented groups into contact with a community of active researchers. The conference places an emphasis on helping junior researchers in the research areas of computational and applied mathematics to grow and develop, with a low-cost high-efficiency forum for the computational and applied mathematicians in the Midwest area.</p> <p>Compared with the previous Midwest Numerical Analysis Day meetings, more engineers attended this meeting. In order to provide a forum for the scientists and engineers to communicate with each other for possible future collaborations, we have two engineers (one in academia and one in industrial) in the local organizing committee and invite many engineers to present their numerical works and applications.</p> <p class="float-left">A special issue for this conference will be published on International Journal of Numerical Analysis and Modeling for this conference. Missouri Institute for Computational and Applied Mathematical Sciences is being expanded at Missouri University of Science and Technology.&nbsp; Funding for this project supported the growth of this institute and enhanced the relatively small amount of computational mathematics research activities in the state of Missouri.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/01/2022<br>      Modified by: Xiaoming&nbsp;He</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Midwest Numerical Analysis Day 2021 was hosted at Havener center of Missouri University of Science and Technology from October 29-30, 2021. This NSF grant was used to provide travel support to 11 graduate students and 1 postdoc for attending the conference and giving presentations. This conference is featured with 4 plenary presentations, 50 parallel presentations in 12 parallel sessions, and 116 participants.  The Midwest Numerical Analysis Day conference series brings together young mathematicians, mathematics graduate students, recent PhDs, women and underrepresented groups into contact with a community of active researchers. The conference places an emphasis on helping junior researchers in the research areas of computational and applied mathematics to grow and develop, with a low-cost high-efficiency forum for the computational and applied mathematicians in the Midwest area.  Compared with the previous Midwest Numerical Analysis Day meetings, more engineers attended this meeting. In order to provide a forum for the scientists and engineers to communicate with each other for possible future collaborations, we have two engineers (one in academia and one in industrial) in the local organizing committee and invite many engineers to present their numerical works and applications. A special issue for this conference will be published on International Journal of Numerical Analysis and Modeling for this conference. Missouri Institute for Computational and Applied Mathematical Sciences is being expanded at Missouri University of Science and Technology.  Funding for this project supported the growth of this institute and enhanced the relatively small amount of computational mathematics research activities in the state of Missouri.       Last Modified: 04/01/2022       Submitted by: Xiaoming He]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
