<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[GRC Defects in Semiconductors: Defect Formation, Characterization, Control and Utilization]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>5000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>5000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Robert Forrey</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rforrey@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925199</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This award will provide partial support for students, early career researchers and under-represented sectors of the scientific community that are engaged in research related to defects in semiconductors, to attend the 2020 Defects in Semiconductors Gordon Research Conference and Gordon Research Seminar. The Conference and Seminar will take place August 15 to 21, 2020, at Colby-Sawyer College, New London, New Hampshire. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Defects in semiconductors are playing an increasingly important role in quantum sensing and quantum information science, and the conference program shows ample evidence of this, with sessions devoted to. e.g., single photon sources and  magnetometry in diamond devices using NV centers. In addition to the conference itself, graduate students and postdoctoral researchers can benefit from the two-day Gordon Research Seminar, designed by and for their peers. Attendance at both the GRS and GRC can provide young scientists with a unique opportunity to actively engage in this important area of research for the development of present and future quantum technologies. The training of a future quantum workforce has been recently recognized as an important strategic goal for U.S. science policy.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/25/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/25/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2023837</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kai-Mei</FirstName>
<LastName>Fu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kai-Mei Fu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[kaimeifu@uw.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000586827</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/25/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Gordon Research Conferences</Name>
<CityName>EAST GREENWICH</CityName>
<ZipCode>028183454</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4017834011</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5586 POST RD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[UNIT 2]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>RI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>XL5ANMKWN557</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GORDON RESEARCH CONFERENCES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Gordon Research Conferences]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>032577818</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Hampshire</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NH02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7281</Code>
<Text>QIS - Quantum Information Scie</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7203</Code>
<Text>QUANTUM INFORMATION SCIENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~5000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Developing the ability to control and manipulate defects in semiconductor materials and devices has been of fundamental importance to the semiconductor industry from its inception. In nanoscale devices the presence of a single defect can have a profound influence on device performance. In many semiconductor device applications, including the solar industry, to achieve optimal device performance defect minimization within the bulk and at interfaces is of paramount importance. To achieve the exquisite control required, detailed attention needs to be given to the appropriate combination of theory, characterization and control. Not all defects are detrimental to device performance and in some cases defects can be used as the active element of a device or material. That is particularly true in the case of emerging quantum devices where single defects with desirable optical and electronic properties are being used to develop quantum computing, quantum metrology and spintronic technologies. The Gordon Research Conference on Defects in Semiconductors focused on the key issues of defect formation, characterization, control and utilization that need to be addressed for continued development in semiconductor and emerging quantum device technologies.</p> <p>This Gordon Research Conference on Defects in Semiconductors is held biannually and offered a unique opportunity for scientists and technologists to address key questions and opportunities associated with defects across the full spectrum of semiconductor materials and devices. The off-the-record format of the conference allowed an opportunity for full and frank discussion of new discoveries and challenges. The conference blended lecture hall presentation and in-depth discussion with social gatherings to provide an environment in which young scientists and experienced practitioners in the field can actively engage in sharing concerns and advances in semiconductor research. Attendees benefitd from the conference-friendly facilities and relaxed atmosphere of Colby-Sawyer College. The format of the conference and the local environment provided an excellent opportunity to discuss science and to develop networks and new collaborations.</p> <p>The conference addressed theory, characterization, control and utilization of defects in a broad range of semiconductor materials and devices of topical interest. This included defects in wide band-gap nitride, oxide, and carbide semiconductors and novel two-dimensional materials such as transition metal di-chalcogenides and other graphene analogues. Attention also focused on emerging materials for photovoltaics including the perovskites. Technological applications ranged from electronics for power generation, power distribution, and lighting to spintronics and quantum information processing.</p> <p>The Gordon Research Conference was complemented by a highly successful Gordon Research Seminar (GRS) designed by and for graduate students and post-doctoral fellows. The two-day GRS preceded the GRC, acclimatizing young scientists to the unique style of Gordon Conferences and encouraging them to share and present their ideas to their peers. Attendance at both the GRS and GRC provided young scientists with a unique opportunity to actively engage in this area of research that is of fundamental importance to existing and future developments in semiconductor and quantum technologies.</p> <p>The Gordon Research Seminar on Defects in Semiconductors was a unique forum for graduate students, postdoctoral researchers, and early career scientists with comparable levels of experience and education to present and exchange new data and cutting edge ideas.</p> <p>This meeting explored two general themes. First, how experimental and theoretical techniques allow us to characterize defects at the microscopic level and their formation in semiconductor materials. Second, how one can utilize these insights via defect engineering to control the optical, electronic, and thermal properties of a material. Applications included but are not limited to optoelectronic devices, quantum technologies, and photocatalytic materials.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/02/2023<br>      Modified by: Kai-Mei&nbsp;Fu</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Developing the ability to control and manipulate defects in semiconductor materials and devices has been of fundamental importance to the semiconductor industry from its inception. In nanoscale devices the presence of a single defect can have a profound influence on device performance. In many semiconductor device applications, including the solar industry, to achieve optimal device performance defect minimization within the bulk and at interfaces is of paramount importance. To achieve the exquisite control required, detailed attention needs to be given to the appropriate combination of theory, characterization and control. Not all defects are detrimental to device performance and in some cases defects can be used as the active element of a device or material. That is particularly true in the case of emerging quantum devices where single defects with desirable optical and electronic properties are being used to develop quantum computing, quantum metrology and spintronic technologies. The Gordon Research Conference on Defects in Semiconductors focused on the key issues of defect formation, characterization, control and utilization that need to be addressed for continued development in semiconductor and emerging quantum device technologies.  This Gordon Research Conference on Defects in Semiconductors is held biannually and offered a unique opportunity for scientists and technologists to address key questions and opportunities associated with defects across the full spectrum of semiconductor materials and devices. The off-the-record format of the conference allowed an opportunity for full and frank discussion of new discoveries and challenges. The conference blended lecture hall presentation and in-depth discussion with social gatherings to provide an environment in which young scientists and experienced practitioners in the field can actively engage in sharing concerns and advances in semiconductor research. Attendees benefitd from the conference-friendly facilities and relaxed atmosphere of Colby-Sawyer College. The format of the conference and the local environment provided an excellent opportunity to discuss science and to develop networks and new collaborations.  The conference addressed theory, characterization, control and utilization of defects in a broad range of semiconductor materials and devices of topical interest. This included defects in wide band-gap nitride, oxide, and carbide semiconductors and novel two-dimensional materials such as transition metal di-chalcogenides and other graphene analogues. Attention also focused on emerging materials for photovoltaics including the perovskites. Technological applications ranged from electronics for power generation, power distribution, and lighting to spintronics and quantum information processing.  The Gordon Research Conference was complemented by a highly successful Gordon Research Seminar (GRS) designed by and for graduate students and post-doctoral fellows. The two-day GRS preceded the GRC, acclimatizing young scientists to the unique style of Gordon Conferences and encouraging them to share and present their ideas to their peers. Attendance at both the GRS and GRC provided young scientists with a unique opportunity to actively engage in this area of research that is of fundamental importance to existing and future developments in semiconductor and quantum technologies.  The Gordon Research Seminar on Defects in Semiconductors was a unique forum for graduate students, postdoctoral researchers, and early career scientists with comparable levels of experience and education to present and exchange new data and cutting edge ideas.  This meeting explored two general themes. First, how experimental and theoretical techniques allow us to characterize defects at the microscopic level and their formation in semiconductor materials. Second, how one can utilize these insights via defect engineering to control the optical, electronic, and thermal properties of a material. Applications included but are not limited to optoelectronic devices, quantum technologies, and photocatalytic materials.       Last Modified: 05/02/2023       Submitted by: Kai-Mei Fu]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
