<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[STTR Phase I:  Sustainable Glass Raw Materials and Processes for the Upcycling of Waste Concrete into SIlicate Glass]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>256000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>256000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rajesh Mehta</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rmehta@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922174</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact of this Small Business Technology Transfer (STTR) Phase I project is to provide waste concrete as a new raw material source for the glass and other industries.  It is estimated that 2.2 billion tons of waste concrete is generated globally each year.  About 70% of the construction waste generated in the US is concrete, but it is not typically used as a raw material for glass production or other chemical processes.  Using concrete as a raw material reduces its contribution to landfills as well as the need for mining virgin raw materials., and contributes environmental benefits.  This STTR Phase I project will study processes to prepare furnace-ready concrete for glass production.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This STTR Phase I project will study the feasibility of waste concrete as a raw material constituent (feedstock) for calcium-silicate glass and glass-making.  Environmental benefits are possible because concrete contains the same key oxides used in glass making (silicon, calcium, aluminum and iron oxides) as well as sulfur compounds (e.g. gypsum mixed with the cement to regulate setting, and therefore can potentially serve as a candidate raw material in the production of calcium-silicate soda lime and calcium-borosilicate glasses.Research objectives include: 1) characterize variations in chemical composition from industrially relevant sources; 2) determine variation in contaminant concentrations; 3) demonstrate processes and methods to address contaminant variations' 4) characterize the specifications for a furnace-ready waste concrete glass batch; 5) produce pilot batches of calcium-silicate soda lime glass; and 6) characterize variations in produced glasses.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/07/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/22/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041, 47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2023638</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Scott</FirstName>
<LastName>Misture</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Scott Misture</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[misture@alfred.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000160296</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/07/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Bernard</FirstName>
<LastName>Pike</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>G</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Bernard G Pike</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[bernie@conox.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000816550</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/07/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>CONOX, LLC</Name>
<CityName>SPRING</CityName>
<ZipCode>773894021</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8046153939</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>25318 OAK KNOT DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>P5EHQ9J2YEW5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CONOX, LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Conox, LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>Spring</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>773894021</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[25318 Oak Knot Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1505</Code>
<Text>STTR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1238</Code>
<Text>TECH FOR SUSTAINABLE ENVIRONMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8040</Code>
<Text>Energy and Environment</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~256000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>NSF Project Outcomes Report</strong></p> <p><strong>Summary</strong></p> <p>We set about to determine if some portion of the vast amounts of waste Portland cement concrete generated globally each year (nearly 2 billion tons) could be put to a higher economic use by diverting some portion of the waste stream to the manufacture of glass and glass-related products and thereby reduce the need for virgin raw materials, reduce the carbon footprint of glassmaking, and reduce energy consumption in glassmaking.</p> <p>It was hypothesized that waste Portland cement concrete could be successfully used to make soda lime glass and other types of glass due to striking similarities in chemical composition and phase composition of their raw materials.&nbsp; It was also hypothesized that the burnt lime (calcium oxide) content of cement would help to reduce CO<sub>2</sub>&nbsp;emissions in glassmaking.&nbsp; To answer these questions, it was necessary to look at the chemical make-up of waste concrete streams, chemical consistency, CO<sub>2</sub>&nbsp;emissions, and glass melting behavior and compare them to traditional soda lime glasses, including the resulting glass properties.</p> <p>The samples were subjected to rigorous examination in the raw material state; melted into glass; and as glass made by mixing waste concrete with conventional glass batch materials in order to understand their ability to replace various levels of virgin raw materials in the glass batch.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Findings</strong></p> <p>Our work confirmed that a variety of waste cement concretes (from a variety of sources) could be used in the formulation of wide range of ordinary and advanced calcium-silicate glasses.&nbsp; The flexibility of waste concrete to serve as a source of primary network formers (from the SiO2) as well as network modifiers and flux (from the CaO and Na2O) was successfully demonstrated.&nbsp; Deficient oxides can easily be formulated in, while excess oxides can be balanced or diluted, often with other recycled materials (like glass cullet), or changing the fractional makeup of the waste concrete (e.g. adding more coarse or more fine grade fractions to the batch composition).&nbsp;</p> <p>Substituting waste concrete (otherwise herein referred to as Furnace Ready Concrete, or FRC) for virgin quartz sand and calcium in typical soda lime glasses reduced CO2 evolution from batch from between 26 and 43 percent, as was expected. However, in using ultra-low and non-carbonate batch materials, CO2 evolution was calculated as having been reduced by over 75%.&nbsp; Not only can waste concrete be used in significant proportions (&gt;10% of batch weight), in many traditional soda lime silicate glasses we have successfully formulated glasses to meet some of the most restrictive environmental objectives, including:</p> <ul> <li>Ultra-low melt temperature (down to 1080 degrees C; 500+ degrees lower than normal)</li> <li>Ultra-low levels of CO2 evolution from glass batch (as low as 2.20% of glass weight)</li> <li>Ultra-high levels of recycled content (up to 100%, in cases eliminating the need for virgin sand)</li> </ul> <p>When used to formulate ultra-low melt temperature glasses, it appears waste concrete has a significant economic advantage over mined materials necessary to achieve such ultra-low melt temperatures (see Table 2).&nbsp; We were able to formulate ultra-low melt temperature glasses for about one half the batch cost of using mined minerals (see Table 2).</p> <p>In one case, CO2 evolution from a container batch formulation was lowered to 4.40% of glass weight, which compares to about 17.77% for ordinary soda lime silicate (SLS) container glass.&nbsp; What's more, it did so at 1080 degrees C versus 1650 degrees C for ordinary SLS container glass, and at about half the batch cost of attaining similar results with virgin mined materials.</p> <p>Waste Portland cement concrete from diverse geographies was used successfully to replace significant volumes (25 to 85 weight percent) of virgin raw materials (quartz, sodium carbonate, and calcium carbonate) in the production of standard soda lime silicate glasses.&nbsp; These more sustainable glass batch mixtures exhibited very similar, if not identical, properties to standard soda lime glass including; specific gravity, chemical composition, glass transition temperature (Tg), and viscosity.</p> <p>The use of waste Portland cement concrete as a major constituent in soda lime glass formulations resulted in meaningful, non-trivial reductions (between 26 and 46 percent) of CO2 emissions over the use of virgin raw materials, and virgin raw materials combined with recycled glass cullet.&nbsp; This technology can go a long way in helping the glass industry meet CO2 targets, and may hold potential for reducing energy consumption through greater levels of glass pull.</p> <p>We have developed glasses using waste concrete that appear suitable for container, float, fiberglass (insulation), and glass bead that can reduce melt temperatures to as low as 1080 degrees C, while cutting CO2 evolution from batch by 75% or more; all while saving on virgin (mined) resources (particularly silica sand), increasing recycled content (for sustainability and circularity), reducing the overall carbon footprint of glass, and reducing landfill burden.</p> <p>We wish to thank the National Science Foundation for its support.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/07/2023<br>      Modified by: Bernard&nbsp;G&nbsp;Pike</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2023638/2023638_10694093_1691450178088_CleartoCobaltBlue--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2023638/2023638_10694093_1691450178088_CleartoCobaltBlue--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Clear to Cobalt Blue"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2023638/2023638_10694093_1691450178088_CleartoCobaltBlue--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Clear to Cobalt Blue"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Soda lime glasses made from using waste concrete.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Scott Trom</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Bernard&nbsp;G&nbsp;Pike</div> <div class="imageTitle">Clear to Cobalt Blue</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2023638/2023638_10694093_1691447259790_Table3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2023638/2023638_10694093_1691447259790_Table3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Table 3"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2023638/2023638_10694093_1691447259790_Table3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Table 3"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Key performance features</div> <div class="imageCredit">Scott Trom</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Bernard&nbsp;G&nbsp;Pike</div> <div class="imageTitle">Table 3</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2023638/2023638_10694093_1691447206571_Table2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2023638/2023638_10694093_1691447206571_Table2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Table 2"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2023638/2023638_10694093_1691447206571_Table2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Table 2"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Environmental and economic factor comparisons</div> <div class="imageCredit">Scott Trom</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Bernard&nbsp;G&nbsp;Pike</div> <div class="imageTitle">Table 2</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2023638/2023638_10694093_1691448223542_Picture1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2023638/2023638_10694093_1691448223542_Picture1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Table 1"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2023638/2023638_10694093_1691448223542_Picture1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Table 1"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Oxide compositions of sample glasses evaluated in this study</div> <div class="imageCredit">Scott Trom</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Bernard&nbsp;G&nbsp;Pike</div> <div class="imageTitle">Table 1</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2023638/2023638_10694093_1691447696986_Picture1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2023638/2023638_10694093_1691447696986_Picture1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Photo 1"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2023638/2023638_10694093_1691447696986_Picture1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Photo 1"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Various examples of soda lime glass obtained from waste concrete.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Alfred Univeristy</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Bernard&nbsp;G&nbsp;Pike</div> <div class="imageTitle">Photo 1</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ NSF Project Outcomes Report  Summary  We set about to determine if some portion of the vast amounts of waste Portland cement concrete generated globally each year (nearly 2 billion tons) could be put to a higher economic use by diverting some portion of the waste stream to the manufacture of glass and glass-related products and thereby reduce the need for virgin raw materials, reduce the carbon footprint of glassmaking, and reduce energy consumption in glassmaking.  It was hypothesized that waste Portland cement concrete could be successfully used to make soda lime glass and other types of glass due to striking similarities in chemical composition and phase composition of their raw materials.  It was also hypothesized that the burnt lime (calcium oxide) content of cement would help to reduce CO2 emissions in glassmaking.  To answer these questions, it was necessary to look at the chemical make-up of waste concrete streams, chemical consistency, CO2 emissions, and glass melting behavior and compare them to traditional soda lime glasses, including the resulting glass properties.  The samples were subjected to rigorous examination in the raw material state; melted into glass; and as glass made by mixing waste concrete with conventional glass batch materials in order to understand their ability to replace various levels of virgin raw materials in the glass batch.    Findings  Our work confirmed that a variety of waste cement concretes (from a variety of sources) could be used in the formulation of wide range of ordinary and advanced calcium-silicate glasses.  The flexibility of waste concrete to serve as a source of primary network formers (from the SiO2) as well as network modifiers and flux (from the CaO and Na2O) was successfully demonstrated.  Deficient oxides can easily be formulated in, while excess oxides can be balanced or diluted, often with other recycled materials (like glass cullet), or changing the fractional makeup of the waste concrete (e.g. adding more coarse or more fine grade fractions to the batch composition).   Substituting waste concrete (otherwise herein referred to as Furnace Ready Concrete, or FRC) for virgin quartz sand and calcium in typical soda lime glasses reduced CO2 evolution from batch from between 26 and 43 percent, as was expected. However, in using ultra-low and non-carbonate batch materials, CO2 evolution was calculated as having been reduced by over 75%.  Not only can waste concrete be used in significant proportions (&gt;10% of batch weight), in many traditional soda lime silicate glasses we have successfully formulated glasses to meet some of the most restrictive environmental objectives, including:  Ultra-low melt temperature (down to 1080 degrees C; 500+ degrees lower than normal) Ultra-low levels of CO2 evolution from glass batch (as low as 2.20% of glass weight) Ultra-high levels of recycled content (up to 100%, in cases eliminating the need for virgin sand)   When used to formulate ultra-low melt temperature glasses, it appears waste concrete has a significant economic advantage over mined materials necessary to achieve such ultra-low melt temperatures (see Table 2).  We were able to formulate ultra-low melt temperature glasses for about one half the batch cost of using mined minerals (see Table 2).  In one case, CO2 evolution from a container batch formulation was lowered to 4.40% of glass weight, which compares to about 17.77% for ordinary soda lime silicate (SLS) container glass.  What's more, it did so at 1080 degrees C versus 1650 degrees C for ordinary SLS container glass, and at about half the batch cost of attaining similar results with virgin mined materials.  Waste Portland cement concrete from diverse geographies was used successfully to replace significant volumes (25 to 85 weight percent) of virgin raw materials (quartz, sodium carbonate, and calcium carbonate) in the production of standard soda lime silicate glasses.  These more sustainable glass batch mixtures exhibited very similar, if not identical, properties to standard soda lime glass including; specific gravity, chemical composition, glass transition temperature (Tg), and viscosity.  The use of waste Portland cement concrete as a major constituent in soda lime glass formulations resulted in meaningful, non-trivial reductions (between 26 and 46 percent) of CO2 emissions over the use of virgin raw materials, and virgin raw materials combined with recycled glass cullet.  This technology can go a long way in helping the glass industry meet CO2 targets, and may hold potential for reducing energy consumption through greater levels of glass pull.  We have developed glasses using waste concrete that appear suitable for container, float, fiberglass (insulation), and glass bead that can reduce melt temperatures to as low as 1080 degrees C, while cutting CO2 evolution from batch by 75% or more; all while saving on virgin (mined) resources (particularly silica sand), increasing recycled content (for sustainability and circularity), reducing the overall carbon footprint of glass, and reducing landfill burden.  We wish to thank the National Science Foundation for its support.             Last Modified: 08/07/2023       Submitted by: Bernard G Pike]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
