<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative: The STARS Aligned: How the STARS Computing Corps Broadens Participation in Computing]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>105104.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>105104</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Allyson Kennedy</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>aykenned@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928905</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This award is a one-year extension of the STARS Computing Corps Alliance for Broadening Participation in Computing (BPC). The primary research aim of extension is to investigate research questions around the impact of the STARS Computing Corps Alliance on its past and current efforts to broaden participation in computing. This longitudinal evaluation has the potential to elucidate successful components of BPC Alliances and their role as national resources on issues of diversity, equity, and inclusion in computing. Further, the results of this study could further extend knowledge about practices designed to increase persistence and support career advancement in computing for undergraduate students, graduate students, and faculty, particularly for those from underrepresented groups. The conferences, communities, and networks supported through STARS will continue to create significant institutional and human resources that could increase the reach of BPC research to a larger audience of researchers, educators, administrators, CS departments, and K-20 students.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In addition to understanding the longitudinal impact of the STARS Computing Corps on computing persistence and career advancement for underrepresented students and faculty, the work also aims to 1) formalize existing STARS efforts for propagating best-practices for BPC; 2) expand STARS online resources designed to build capacity for engaging in BPC evaluation and research; 3) develop a virtual STARS alumni community; and 4) continue to support an academic community for BPC through STARS Celebration and RESPECT.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/10/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/10/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2023399</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Manuel</FirstName>
<LastName>Perez-Quinones</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Manuel A Perez-Quinones</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[Perez.Quinones@uncc.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000478387</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Audrey</FirstName>
<LastName>Rorrer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Audrey S Rorrer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[arorrer@uncc.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000252239</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of North Carolina at Charlotte</Name>
<CityName>CHARLOTTE</CityName>
<ZipCode>282230001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7046871888</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>9201 UNIVERSITY CITY BLVD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>JB33DT84JNA5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF NORTH CAROLINA AT CHARLOTTE, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>N8DMK1K4C2K5</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of North Carolina at Charlotte]]></Name>
<CityName>Charlotte</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>282230001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[9201 University City Blvd]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>055y</Code>
<Text>CISE Education and Workforce</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7482</Code>
<Text>BROADENING PARTIC IN COMPUTING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~105104</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-d41a00e7-7fff-3c69-ec62-6baddea51be6"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Our experience in leading the STARS Computing Corps Alliance for Broadening Participation in Computing (BPC) since 2006 demonstrates the value of a community of practice that engages computing faculty and students at institutions of higher education (IHEs) with a shared commitment to take action to advance diversity, equity, and inclusion in computing. Our flagship STARS Leadership Corps program has engaged over 2600 college students and 100 faculty from 53 colleges and universities in projects designed to promote persistence by connecting computing to community and societal impacts, reinforcing computing knowledge through teaching and practice, and developing professional, entrepreneurial, and creative skills. These student-led STARS Leadership Corps service-learning projects are centered around the goal of broadening participation of underrepresented groups in computing in K-20. Examples include assisting K-12 teachers to introduce computer science (CS) concepts into their courses, designing peer tutoring programs for undergraduates, and designing and implementing CS education outreach events for K-12 students, and engaging in socially relevant computing research. A previous study shows that STARS college student members have positive gains in GPA, self-efficacy, computing identity, and commitment to computing, with enhanced outcomes for students who identify as women, Black, and Hispanic/Latinx (Payton, 2016). STARS has also helped to foster an academic community centered around BPC through its annual STARS Celebration conference, which builds capacity through education and ignites action for adoption of evidence-based BPC practices, and through the annual RESPECT research conference, which advances peer-reviewed scholarship on diversity, equity, and inclusion in computing.</span></p> <p dir="ltr">&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>This project, STARS Aligned supported an extended investigation of the STARS Computing Corps to further develop STARS as a national resource to build capacity for research and practice, ignite action, and foster an academic community for broadening participation of underrepresented groups in computing. Specifically, we expanded the collection of STARS online resources designed to build student and faculty capacity for engaging in BPC evaluation and research by building a BPC Scholarship Toolkit that is available online and being propagated through STARS Celebration. We developed a virtual STARS alumni community to support sustained engagement as well as longitudinal follow-up and we also continue to support an academic community for BPC through the STARS Celebration and RESPECT conferences. Furthermore, this project investigated&nbsp; the longitudinal impact of the STARS Computing Corps on computing persistence and career advancement for undergraduates, graduate students, and faculty, particularly those from underrepresented groups, and has a research manuscript accepted for publication.&nbsp;</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/11/2023<br>      Modified by: Audrey&nbsp;S&nbsp;Rorrer</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   Our experience in leading the STARS Computing Corps Alliance for Broadening Participation in Computing (BPC) since 2006 demonstrates the value of a community of practice that engages computing faculty and students at institutions of higher education (IHEs) with a shared commitment to take action to advance diversity, equity, and inclusion in computing. Our flagship STARS Leadership Corps program has engaged over 2600 college students and 100 faculty from 53 colleges and universities in projects designed to promote persistence by connecting computing to community and societal impacts, reinforcing computing knowledge through teaching and practice, and developing professional, entrepreneurial, and creative skills. These student-led STARS Leadership Corps service-learning projects are centered around the goal of broadening participation of underrepresented groups in computing in K-20. Examples include assisting K-12 teachers to introduce computer science (CS) concepts into their courses, designing peer tutoring programs for undergraduates, and designing and implementing CS education outreach events for K-12 students, and engaging in socially relevant computing research. A previous study shows that STARS college student members have positive gains in GPA, self-efficacy, computing identity, and commitment to computing, with enhanced outcomes for students who identify as women, Black, and Hispanic/Latinx (Payton, 2016). STARS has also helped to foster an academic community centered around BPC through its annual STARS Celebration conference, which builds capacity through education and ignites action for adoption of evidence-based BPC practices, and through the annual RESPECT research conference, which advances peer-reviewed scholarship on diversity, equity, and inclusion in computing.   This project, STARS Aligned supported an extended investigation of the STARS Computing Corps to further develop STARS as a national resource to build capacity for research and practice, ignite action, and foster an academic community for broadening participation of underrepresented groups in computing. Specifically, we expanded the collection of STARS online resources designed to build student and faculty capacity for engaging in BPC evaluation and research by building a BPC Scholarship Toolkit that is available online and being propagated through STARS Celebration. We developed a virtual STARS alumni community to support sustained engagement as well as longitudinal follow-up and we also continue to support an academic community for BPC through the STARS Celebration and RESPECT conferences. Furthermore, this project investigated  the longitudinal impact of the STARS Computing Corps on computing persistence and career advancement for undergraduates, graduate students, and faculty, particularly those from underrepresented groups, and has a research manuscript accepted for publication.              Last Modified: 01/11/2023       Submitted by: Audrey S Rorrer]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
