<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Understanding the Role of Affinity Groups on the Advancement of Women of Color in the Engineering Academy  a Workshop]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>49999.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>49999</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EEC</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Engineering Education and Centers</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Amelia Greer</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>agreer@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922552</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This workshop will study the intersection of professional organizations and affinity groups within those organizations, and the role that they play for women of color (WoC) in engineering academia as they traverse their career pathways. The purpose of the workshop is to discover the reach, structure, and impact of affinity groups, and to learn from successful models from other professional societies.  The dearth of WoC in the engineering academy and their advancement in the profession can be correlated to obstacles faced by this population. In contrast from the environment in the engineering academy for underrepresented groups (URGs), corporate settings have embraced and understood the value that diversity offers. Corporate settings have gone beyond the goal of achieving diversity, but recognize that inclusion is essential for the growth of their diverse environment. To foster an inclusive environment, corporations have learned that affinity groups within the organization are key as they provide a means for individuals to articulate concerns and impart change. The perception by WoC in the engineering academy is that industry offers a more tolerable environment supporting professional career advancement. Therefore, similar efforts as those in corporate settings have been implemented organically by WoC in large professional societies.  This workshop will bring together leaders from government, academia, professional societies and industry to address critical issues around the entry, persistence and advancement of WoC in the engineering academy. Participants from diverse institutions (2-year, 4-year, research intensive, minority serving) will examine this critical element of community support and belonging in broadening participation. Strategic initiatives and cross-sector collaboratives will support the development of future and current faculty to advance through professional engagement in national settings. This work is aligned with the big ideas of NSF such as INCLUDES.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This workshop will assess the effect of the presence of affinity groups within discipline-specific professional organizations on the promotion, tenure, and progression into leadership within the academy for WoC. Due to the limited availability of literature, the proposed workshop is designed to gain an understanding of the current landscape of discipline specific professional organizations, their affinity groups, and their roles leading to assess their reach and impact on the advancement of WoC in the engineering academy.  A motivation driving the conceptualization of this workshop is to contribute towards supporting the career progression of underrepresented groups (URG) females in the engineering academy. &lt;br/&gt; To better understand how affinity groups can support the progression of WoC in the engineering academy this workshop will seek to answer the following research questions: (1) Can the reach that professional organizations and related affinity groups within those organizations have on engaging WoC be quantified? (2) Is there a prescribed structure within affinity groups that is associated with a proportion of its population achieving academic career advancement? (3) Can the impact that professional organizations and related affinity groups have on the advancement of WoC in engineering academia be quantified? (i.e. percentages of WoC promoted to full professor, percentages of WoC in academic leadership, etc.)&lt;br/&gt;This workshop will draw upon Positive Organizational Scholarship (POS) to conceptualize and design best practices for affinity groups of WoC in the engineering academy. This workshop will anchor in the POS research on career development to explore the potential of affinity groups with an emphasis on professional and psychosocial support, communal practices, mutual learning and growth, and network-based model of mentoring.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/02/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/16/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2024569</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tonya</FirstName>
<LastName>Peeples</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Tonya L Peeples</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[tzp225@psu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000253549</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/02/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Margaret</FirstName>
<LastName>Bailey</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Margaret B Bailey</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mbbeme@rit.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000206421</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/02/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Julie</FirstName>
<LastName>Ivy</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Julie E Ivy</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jsivy@ncsu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000318907</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/16/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Iris</FirstName>
<LastName>Rivero</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>V</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Iris V Rivero</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ivreie@rit.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000478377</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/02/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Maria</FirstName>
<LastName>Mayorga</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Maria E Mayorga</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[memayorg@ncsu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000243602</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/16/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Rochester Institute of Tech</Name>
<CityName>ROCHESTER</CityName>
<ZipCode>146235603</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5854757987</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1 LOMB MEMORIAL DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>25</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY25</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>J6TWTRKC1X14</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ROCHESTER INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Rochester Institute of Tech]]></Name>
<CityName>Rochester</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>146235603</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Department of Industrial and Sys]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>25</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY25</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1385</Code>
<Text>SSA-Special Studies &amp; Analysis</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7680</Code>
<Text>EDA-Eng Diversity Activities</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7680</Code>
<Text>ENG DIVERSITY ACTIVITIES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~49999</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Project Summary</span></strong></p> <p>Academic circles, specifically within the United States, are becoming increasingly aware of significant disparities that exist for marginalized groups in higher education. These disparities are especially apparent for women of color (WoC) who serve as faculty members for American colleges and universities, where only 10% of fully tenured faculty are WoC (National Center for Science and Engineering Statistics, 2021). This figure is even lower within the engineering science, where only 3% of fully tenured faculty are WoC.</p> <p>In the academy, it is known that advancement is not solely driven by scholarly work, but by connections, awareness, social networks and resilience. Professional societies have played an important role for WoC engineering faculty to interact in their field and are a necessary connector for support (both formal and informal) in the promotion process. The absence of strong networks, supportive allies and cultures of inclusion can cause faculty, and in this conversation WoC engineering faculty to "fall through the cracks." Therefore, professional societies can provide the necessary platform to support and play pivotal roles in the career trajectory of WoC tenure track faculty in engineering academia. However, there is a scarcity of literature correlating and quantifying their role of backing specifically the career advancement of WoC in engineering academia. To contribute to elucidate whether professional societies play a pivotal role in the success of WoC in engineering academia, this project was designed to gain an understanding of the current landscape of discipline specific professional organizations, their affinity groups, and their roles leading to assess their reach and impact on the advancement of WoC in the engineering academy.</p> <p><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Intellectual Merit</span></strong></p> <p>The perspectives and lived experiences of the Organizing Committee of this project (largely consisting of WoC engineering faculty at the rank of full professor) suggest that the largest opportunities for growth have come from affinity groups or societies. They believe that in the long-term these affinity groups could be utilized as vehicles for improving the advancement of WoC in the academy. While the Organizing Committee members have all benefited from the aforementioned affinity groups, the extent to which these groups exist, how they function, how many faculty engage with them and their impact is not fully known. Therefore, this project aimed to quantify the reach, structure, and impact that professional societies and their affinity groups have on WoC in engineering academia by engaging in a series of workshops with "change agents" within engineering academia and industry. Change agents were defined as engineering professionals who held positions that allowed them to effect organizational change, such as those in administrative, leadership, or research-related positions.</p> <p>Data gathering was performed through the organization and delivery of two workshops. Evaluators used a mixed-method approach that consisted of reviewing project-related materials such as meeting notes, participant surveys, interview transcripts, and data collected during the workshops. Data analysis focused on identifying: 1) the core characteristics of professional organizations and affinity groups that contribute to WoC achieving academic career advancement; 2) the extent that professional organizations and affinity groups have reaching and engaging WoC in engineering academia; and 3) the opportunities that data collected can be leveraged to support WoC in engineering academia. The first workshop was a half-day virtual event aimed at gathering initial data about affinity groups to inform the design of the subsequent in-person workshop.</p> <p>Core characteristics of professional societies and affinity groups, as perceived by survey and interview respondents, related to social-emotional impacts such as a sense of community support, open communication, empathy, and having a shared mind to solve issues pertaining to diversity, equity, and inclusion (DEI). While direct benefits of group affiliations on career advancement for WoC were examined, participant feedback suggested that the breadth of impact that these groups have may be better understood by expanding research questions to include indirect benefits too. Participants also stressed the importance of allyship and financial support from the larger institutions that house or interact with a given professional organization or affinity group.</p> <p>With regards to the extent that professional societies and affinity groups currently reach and engage WoC in engineering academia cumulative findings suggest that many participants, especially those in leadership positions within their groups, find that a high level of engagement and communication from their group is maintained through conferences and smaller group meetings. Others shared a variety of ways WoC could be better reached by professional organizations and affinity groups.</p> <p><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Broader Impacts</span></strong></p> <p>In totality, the collected data can be used to inform subsequent research and related initiatives. In fact, a group of participants in this project submitted an ADVANCE proposal as this grant's funding period was coming to an end. Lastly, data analysis revealed that an additional knowledge gap that needs to be addressed is identifying indirect benefits that professional societies provide which contribute to the career advancement of WoC in engineering academia.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/26/2023<br>      Modified by: Iris&nbsp;V&nbsp;Rivero</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Project Summary  Academic circles, specifically within the United States, are becoming increasingly aware of significant disparities that exist for marginalized groups in higher education. These disparities are especially apparent for women of color (WoC) who serve as faculty members for American colleges and universities, where only 10% of fully tenured faculty are WoC (National Center for Science and Engineering Statistics, 2021). This figure is even lower within the engineering science, where only 3% of fully tenured faculty are WoC.  In the academy, it is known that advancement is not solely driven by scholarly work, but by connections, awareness, social networks and resilience. Professional societies have played an important role for WoC engineering faculty to interact in their field and are a necessary connector for support (both formal and informal) in the promotion process. The absence of strong networks, supportive allies and cultures of inclusion can cause faculty, and in this conversation WoC engineering faculty to "fall through the cracks." Therefore, professional societies can provide the necessary platform to support and play pivotal roles in the career trajectory of WoC tenure track faculty in engineering academia. However, there is a scarcity of literature correlating and quantifying their role of backing specifically the career advancement of WoC in engineering academia. To contribute to elucidate whether professional societies play a pivotal role in the success of WoC in engineering academia, this project was designed to gain an understanding of the current landscape of discipline specific professional organizations, their affinity groups, and their roles leading to assess their reach and impact on the advancement of WoC in the engineering academy.  Intellectual Merit  The perspectives and lived experiences of the Organizing Committee of this project (largely consisting of WoC engineering faculty at the rank of full professor) suggest that the largest opportunities for growth have come from affinity groups or societies. They believe that in the long-term these affinity groups could be utilized as vehicles for improving the advancement of WoC in the academy. While the Organizing Committee members have all benefited from the aforementioned affinity groups, the extent to which these groups exist, how they function, how many faculty engage with them and their impact is not fully known. Therefore, this project aimed to quantify the reach, structure, and impact that professional societies and their affinity groups have on WoC in engineering academia by engaging in a series of workshops with "change agents" within engineering academia and industry. Change agents were defined as engineering professionals who held positions that allowed them to effect organizational change, such as those in administrative, leadership, or research-related positions.  Data gathering was performed through the organization and delivery of two workshops. Evaluators used a mixed-method approach that consisted of reviewing project-related materials such as meeting notes, participant surveys, interview transcripts, and data collected during the workshops. Data analysis focused on identifying: 1) the core characteristics of professional organizations and affinity groups that contribute to WoC achieving academic career advancement; 2) the extent that professional organizations and affinity groups have reaching and engaging WoC in engineering academia; and 3) the opportunities that data collected can be leveraged to support WoC in engineering academia. The first workshop was a half-day virtual event aimed at gathering initial data about affinity groups to inform the design of the subsequent in-person workshop.  Core characteristics of professional societies and affinity groups, as perceived by survey and interview respondents, related to social-emotional impacts such as a sense of community support, open communication, empathy, and having a shared mind to solve issues pertaining to diversity, equity, and inclusion (DEI). While direct benefits of group affiliations on career advancement for WoC were examined, participant feedback suggested that the breadth of impact that these groups have may be better understood by expanding research questions to include indirect benefits too. Participants also stressed the importance of allyship and financial support from the larger institutions that house or interact with a given professional organization or affinity group.  With regards to the extent that professional societies and affinity groups currently reach and engage WoC in engineering academia cumulative findings suggest that many participants, especially those in leadership positions within their groups, find that a high level of engagement and communication from their group is maintained through conferences and smaller group meetings. Others shared a variety of ways WoC could be better reached by professional organizations and affinity groups.  Broader Impacts  In totality, the collected data can be used to inform subsequent research and related initiatives. In fact, a group of participants in this project submitted an ADVANCE proposal as this grant's funding period was coming to an end. Lastly, data analysis revealed that an additional knowledge gap that needs to be addressed is identifying indirect benefits that professional societies provide which contribute to the career advancement of WoC in engineering academia.       Last Modified: 02/26/2023       Submitted by: Iris V Rivero]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
