<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Support for the 2020 Gordon Research Conference/Seminar on Rock Deformation: Combining Laboratory Measurements with Observational Constraints to Understand Tectonic Processes]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>49500.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>49500</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Stephen Harlan</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sharlan@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927707</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The project provides travel and registration costs for graduate students and early career researchers to attend the 2020 Gordon Research Conference and Seminar on Rock Deformation. The conference will be held from August 8th to the 14th, 2020 at Bates College in Lewiston, Maine. The Gordon Research Conferences and Seminars provide an international forum for the presentation and discussion of frontier scientific research, and invited presentations will highlight the latest results in a context that looks towards future scientific avenues. The topics that will be the topic of this activity  include cutting-edge presentations and discussions of a variety of topics pertaining to rock deformation, including lithospheric rheology from small-scale experiments, fundamental frictional processes, earthquake mechanics; fault slip in natural environments, lower crustal dynamics, mantle rheology, and shallow and deep subduction processes. The Gordon Research Conferences and Seminars provide a unique opportunity for early-career scientists to come together in a highly stimulating and non-intimidating environment to discuss current research and build networks that can lead to a lifetime of collaboration and scientific achievement. In addition, the project will contribute to broadening of participation of underrepresented groups in science, technology, and mathematics (STEM) through recruitment of participants from underrepresented groups. The Gordon Research Conference and associated Gordon Research Seminar will foster development of new research directions in rock deformation and will contribute to the development of a diverse and globally competitive STEM workforce. The conference program includes topics of societal relevance that bear on the understanding of geologic hazards, which is of benefit to society.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/17/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/17/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2024104</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Heather</FirstName>
<LastName>Savage</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Heather M Savage</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[hsavage@ucsc.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000569517</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/17/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Santa Cruz</Name>
<CityName>SANTA CRUZ</CityName>
<ZipCode>950641077</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8314595278</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1156 HIGH ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>19</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA19</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>VXUFPE4MCZH5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA SANTA CRUZ</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Bates College]]></Name>
<CityName>Lewiston</CityName>
<StateCode>ME</StateCode>
<ZipCode>042400800</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2 Andrews Rd]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maine</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>ME02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1572</Code>
<Text>Tectonics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1574</Code>
<Text>Geophysics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1580</Code>
<Text>Instrumentation &amp; Facilities</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1620</Code>
<Text>Marine Geology and Geophysics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8076</Code>
<Text>GeoPRISMS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~49500</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This grant provided travel support for the 2022 Gordon Research Conference/Gordon Research Seminar on Rock Deformation at Bates College, Maine, from August 6<sup>th</sup>-August 12<sup>th</sup>. The theme of the conference was &ldquo;Combining Laboratory Measurements with Observational Constraints to Understand Tectonic Processes&rdquo;, which focused on how to scale up observations from laboratory experiments to tectonic processes.&nbsp; Dan Faulkner (Univ. of Liverpool) was the GRC chair and Heather Savage (UC Santa Cruz) was the vice chair. The GRS was run by Carolyn Tewksbury-Christle and Taka Kanaya. The GRS program is designed to provide opportunities for early-career scientists to present research and build community.</p> <p>The Rock Deformation GRC series highlights the latest research and future trends in brittle and ductile rock mechanics and applications, with experimental, field, numerical, and theoretical contributions. The conference assesses our understanding of the nature and controls on rock strength, fracture, friction and ductile flow during induced and natural tectonic loading. The conference goal is to promote multi-disciplinary and multi-scale studies of coupling between thermal, chemical and mechanical forces in minerals, rocks and fluids. The impact of rock deformation research also has far-reaching socio-economic impact through: identification, assessment and mitigation of geohazards (earthquakes, landslides, and volcanic eruptions), effectiveness and environmental integrity of hydrocarbon extraction and geothermal energy resources, and reliability of underground storage facilities.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/26/2023<br>      Modified by: Heather&nbsp;M&nbsp;Savage</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This grant provided travel support for the 2022 Gordon Research Conference/Gordon Research Seminar on Rock Deformation at Bates College, Maine, from August 6th-August 12th. The theme of the conference was "Combining Laboratory Measurements with Observational Constraints to Understand Tectonic Processes", which focused on how to scale up observations from laboratory experiments to tectonic processes.  Dan Faulkner (Univ. of Liverpool) was the GRC chair and Heather Savage (UC Santa Cruz) was the vice chair. The GRS was run by Carolyn Tewksbury-Christle and Taka Kanaya. The GRS program is designed to provide opportunities for early-career scientists to present research and build community.  The Rock Deformation GRC series highlights the latest research and future trends in brittle and ductile rock mechanics and applications, with experimental, field, numerical, and theoretical contributions. The conference assesses our understanding of the nature and controls on rock strength, fracture, friction and ductile flow during induced and natural tectonic loading. The conference goal is to promote multi-disciplinary and multi-scale studies of coupling between thermal, chemical and mechanical forces in minerals, rocks and fluids. The impact of rock deformation research also has far-reaching socio-economic impact through: identification, assessment and mitigation of geohazards (earthquakes, landslides, and volcanic eruptions), effectiveness and environmental integrity of hydrocarbon extraction and geothermal energy resources, and reliability of underground storage facilities.             Last Modified: 06/26/2023       Submitted by: Heather M Savage]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
