<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[I-Corps: Treating Bone Trauma Using a Biodegradable Bone Fixation Device]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ruth Shuman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rshuman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922160</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this I-Corps project is the improvement of bone trauma treatment outcomes through patient-specific biodegradable bone fixation devices. Current modalities of treating patients with bone trauma rely on the use of permanent and stiff bone fixation devices that carry substantial risks and increase the suffering of patients and the total operation cost. The new biodegradable (nonpermanent) devices have superior design and properties that, if adopted, may address these problems and result in a significant clinical breakthrough. No other technology with advantages similar to these has been identified in the US or the global market. The global targeted craniomaxillofacial fixation market is estimated to reach a value of USD $1,500 million by the end of 2020. In addition, the market size of biodegradable bone graft materials in North America only is expected to exceed $690 million by 2020. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project is focused on the development of nonpermanent bone fixation devices made of a patent-pending biodegradable magnesium-based alloy with properties achieved using novel post-fabrication processes. Based on preliminary in-vitro studies, these devices are expected to be both strong enough to bear loads then lose strength and fully resorb following bone healing. It is hypothesized that the team's fixation devices will transfer enough compressive stresses to the healing bone to facilitate continuous bone remodeling. A preliminary proof-of-concept through a series of in vitro studies was successfully achieved. In addition, the biocompatibility of the alloy before and after the post-fabrication processes was assured. The success in developing nonpermanent fixation devices is expected to result in reduced post-surgery complications, reduced overall hospital stays and costs, and elimination of the need for a second surgery for implant removal.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/13/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/13/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2024076</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Hamdy</FirstName>
<LastName>Ibrahim</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Hamdy Ibrahim</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[hamdy-ibrahim@utc.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000819102</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/13/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Tennessee Chattanooga</Name>
<CityName>CHATTANOOGA</CityName>
<ZipCode>374032504</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4234254431</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>615 MCCALLIE AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TN03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>JNZFHMGJN7M3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TENNESSEE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>JBG7T7RXQ2B7</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Tennessee Chattanooga]]></Name>
<CityName>Chattanooga</CityName>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>374032504</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[615 McCallie Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TN03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Project summary:</span></strong> The team assessed the commercialization potential of a patient-specific biodegradable bone fixation device to treat patients with bone trauma. The use of biodegradable bone fixation devices will result in better healing outcomes due to their superior properties. Once commercialized, these devices will be used by orthopedic surgeons to treat bone trauma with faster healing rates, and reduced post-operation complications.</p> <p><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Intellectual Merit:</span></strong> The success in developing non-permanent fixation hardware is expected to result in a clinical breakthrough for treating patients with fractured bones. To this end, our team developed biodegradable bone fixation devices that, based on our studies, are expected to be both strong enough to bear loads and lose strength and fully resorb following bone healing. We also found that our biocompatible bone fixation devices will facilitate continuous bone remodeling. We know that the permanent existence of stiff metallic parts (e.g., Ti-6Al-4V and 316L stainless) in the body after bone healing frequently results in detrimental reactions, including inflammation, possible infection, and bone resorption. This NSF-funded project focused on two main activities: (i) performing a methodical study toward developing a proof of concept and fabricating the prototype of a bone fixation device based on our innovation, and (ii) developing a business model for the resulting bone fixation device through the entrepreneurial immersion and Lean Launchpad methodology. These activities have contributed to the field of biodegradable medical device design and fabrication. This research also helped us to understand the procedure/pathway to fabricate biodegradable bone fixation devices using FDA-approved fabrication methods.</p> <p><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Broader Impact:</span></strong><strong> </strong>The broader impacts of this project on the advancement of a medical device made of biodegradable metals are substantial. Current modalities of treating patients with bone trauma rely on the use of permanent and stiff bone fixation devices that carry substantial risks of inflammation, infection, subsequent bone fracture, and bone resorption. Through this project, the team developed a business model that can enable a start-up company to commercialize biodegradable (nonpermanent) bone fixation devices that can address the problems associated with the currently-in-use permanent bone fixation devices. Some of the most important impacts of this project are: (i) gaining a fundamental understanding of the orthopedic medical device ecosystem through the program customer discovery activities, (ii) gaining the ability to design and fabricate a new class of regenerative skeletal fixation devices based on the market/customer needs. Equally important, this project involved three graduate students and one undergraduate student who participated in the entrepreneurial immersion course and additional local I-Corps program. They led the team's effort, throughout the duration of the project, in developing a final technology-disposition plan for biodegradable bone fixation devices based on our innovation.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/26/2023<br>      Modified by: Hamdy&nbsp;Ibrahim</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Project summary: The team assessed the commercialization potential of a patient-specific biodegradable bone fixation device to treat patients with bone trauma. The use of biodegradable bone fixation devices will result in better healing outcomes due to their superior properties. Once commercialized, these devices will be used by orthopedic surgeons to treat bone trauma with faster healing rates, and reduced post-operation complications.  Intellectual Merit: The success in developing non-permanent fixation hardware is expected to result in a clinical breakthrough for treating patients with fractured bones. To this end, our team developed biodegradable bone fixation devices that, based on our studies, are expected to be both strong enough to bear loads and lose strength and fully resorb following bone healing. We also found that our biocompatible bone fixation devices will facilitate continuous bone remodeling. We know that the permanent existence of stiff metallic parts (e.g., Ti-6Al-4V and 316L stainless) in the body after bone healing frequently results in detrimental reactions, including inflammation, possible infection, and bone resorption. This NSF-funded project focused on two main activities: (i) performing a methodical study toward developing a proof of concept and fabricating the prototype of a bone fixation device based on our innovation, and (ii) developing a business model for the resulting bone fixation device through the entrepreneurial immersion and Lean Launchpad methodology. These activities have contributed to the field of biodegradable medical device design and fabrication. This research also helped us to understand the procedure/pathway to fabricate biodegradable bone fixation devices using FDA-approved fabrication methods.  Broader Impact: The broader impacts of this project on the advancement of a medical device made of biodegradable metals are substantial. Current modalities of treating patients with bone trauma rely on the use of permanent and stiff bone fixation devices that carry substantial risks of inflammation, infection, subsequent bone fracture, and bone resorption. Through this project, the team developed a business model that can enable a start-up company to commercialize biodegradable (nonpermanent) bone fixation devices that can address the problems associated with the currently-in-use permanent bone fixation devices. Some of the most important impacts of this project are: (i) gaining a fundamental understanding of the orthopedic medical device ecosystem through the program customer discovery activities, (ii) gaining the ability to design and fabricate a new class of regenerative skeletal fixation devices based on the market/customer needs. Equally important, this project involved three graduate students and one undergraduate student who participated in the entrepreneurial immersion course and additional local I-Corps program. They led the team's effort, throughout the duration of the project, in developing a final technology-disposition plan for biodegradable bone fixation devices based on our innovation.       Last Modified: 04/26/2023       Submitted by: Hamdy Ibrahim]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
