<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[EAGER: Impact of LEO Satellite Constellations on Optical Astronomy: Measurement, Simulation, Mitigation, and Forecast]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>299871.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>299871</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AST</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Nigel Sharp</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>nsharp@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924905</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The exponential industrialization of space, in the form of tens of thousands of rather large Low Earth Orbit (LEO) communications satellites (LEOsats), has a timescale short compared with normal scientific research projects.  As they are presently configured, LEOsats will have a major deleterious impact on ground based optical astronomy.  This study will assess the science impact of LEOsats, and explore the effectiveness of different mitigation strategies.  There is an urgent need for informed studies that assess the impact realistically, as well as exploratory investigations to choose one, or a few, of the best of various proposed different mitigation strategies.  Since the Vera C. Rubin Observatory (VRO) is most impacted, with a domino effect on all other astronomy which would use VRO data, this project will focus on assessment, laboratory measurements, simulation, and mitigation, specific to the VRO and its initial mission, the Legacy Survey of Space and Time (LSST).  The natural night sky is the universal heritage of everyone, not just professional astronomers, and it is threatened by tens of thousands of bright moving LEOsats.  Finding ways to reduce their impact affects the quality of life of pretty well all of modern society.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/16/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/16/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2024216</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>J. Anthony</FirstName>
<LastName>Tyson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>J. Anthony Tyson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[tyson@physics.ucdavis.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000439210</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/16/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Davis</Name>
<CityName>DAVIS</CityName>
<ZipCode>956186153</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5307547700</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1850 RESEARCH PARK DR, STE 300</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>TX2DAGQPENZ5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, DAVIS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>NUDGYLBB4S99</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California, Davis]]></Name>
<CityName>Davis</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>956165270</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[One Shields Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1798</Code>
<Text/>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~299871</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><div class="page" title="Page 1"> <div class="layoutArea"> <div class="column"> <p>&nbsp;</p> </div> </div> <div class="layoutArea"> <div class="column"> <p><span>PROJECT SUMMARY</span></p> </div> </div> <img src="blob:https:/www.research.gov/679948e5-a32d-4026-90c1-cf26e9b5c58a" alt="page1image1459818464" width="469.000000" height="1.000000" /> <div class="layoutArea"> <div class="column"> <p><span>Humanity is experiencing an exponential industrialization of space, in the form of tens of thousands of large Low Earth Orbit (LEO) communications satellites. This is happening on a timescale short compared with normal scientific research projects. Without mitigation, in the next several years this will transform ground based optical astronomy. We find that there is no combination of mitigations which can alleviate the negative impacts on astronomy science.</span></p> <p><span>Intellectual Merit:</span></p> <p><span>Given that several companies are going ahead with their satellite constellations, our options are limited to assessing the science impact, and exploration of the effectiveness of several mitigation strategies.&nbsp;<span>&nbsp; The Vera C. Rubin Observatory "Legacy Survey of Space and Time" (LSST) is most impacted, because of its wide and rapid survey of the night sky. &nbsp;Negative impacts on LSST science will have a domino effect on all other astronomy which would use Rubin Observatory data, including space telescopes. </span></span></p> <p><span><span>When satellites cross the wide field of view, they leave a trail on the image. These trails can cause so-called "systematic errors" in the science. This is true even if the trails are "masked" in sofware processing. We explored combinations of several mitigation options. During the two years of this grant, this exploration covered: LSST science impact assessment, lab measurements of the effects of satellite trails on the LSST Camera, forward simulation of Rubin Observatory sky survey imaging including synthetic satellite trails, and a number of mitigation options. &nbsp;As an example, we worked with SpaceX on methods to make their satellites in orbit appear less bright. &nbsp;Another example is advanced algorithms for LSST data analysis which may alleviate some of the damaging effects on LSST science due to satellite trails.</span></span></p> <p><span>Broader Impacts:</span></p> <p><span>We addressed the pressing need for more work on this new challenge to astronomy on several broad fronts on a short timescale. This is in addition to the work we continue to undertake supported by Vera Rubin Observatory Project personnel and some students in our group.&nbsp;Our work, reports, and workshops have had an impact on the satellite industry.&nbsp;There is a growing realization among satellite operators that they must pursue novel engineering solutions, and adopt best practices for making their satellites less visible.</span>&nbsp;The postdoctoral scholar suppported by this grant is a hispanic minority.</p> </div> </div> </div> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/13/2023<br>      Modified by: J. Anthony&nbsp;Tyson</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[           PROJECT SUMMARY       Humanity is experiencing an exponential industrialization of space, in the form of tens of thousands of large Low Earth Orbit (LEO) communications satellites. This is happening on a timescale short compared with normal scientific research projects. Without mitigation, in the next several years this will transform ground based optical astronomy. We find that there is no combination of mitigations which can alleviate the negative impacts on astronomy science.  Intellectual Merit:  Given that several companies are going ahead with their satellite constellations, our options are limited to assessing the science impact, and exploration of the effectiveness of several mitigation strategies.   The Vera C. Rubin Observatory "Legacy Survey of Space and Time" (LSST) is most impacted, because of its wide and rapid survey of the night sky.  Negative impacts on LSST science will have a domino effect on all other astronomy which would use Rubin Observatory data, including space telescopes.   When satellites cross the wide field of view, they leave a trail on the image. These trails can cause so-called "systematic errors" in the science. This is true even if the trails are "masked" in sofware processing. We explored combinations of several mitigation options. During the two years of this grant, this exploration covered: LSST science impact assessment, lab measurements of the effects of satellite trails on the LSST Camera, forward simulation of Rubin Observatory sky survey imaging including synthetic satellite trails, and a number of mitigation options.  As an example, we worked with SpaceX on methods to make their satellites in orbit appear less bright.  Another example is advanced algorithms for LSST data analysis which may alleviate some of the damaging effects on LSST science due to satellite trails.  Broader Impacts:  We addressed the pressing need for more work on this new challenge to astronomy on several broad fronts on a short timescale. This is in addition to the work we continue to undertake supported by Vera Rubin Observatory Project personnel and some students in our group. Our work, reports, and workshops have had an impact on the satellite industry. There is a growing realization among satellite operators that they must pursue novel engineering solutions, and adopt best practices for making their satellites less visible. The postdoctoral scholar suppported by this grant is a hispanic minority.             Last Modified: 05/13/2023       Submitted by: J. Anthony Tyson]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
