<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[30th Goldschmidt Conference – Geochemistry and Society Special Sessions]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>12600.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>12600</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>RISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div of Res, Innovation, Synergies, &amp; Edu</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Brandon Jones</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mbjones@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924713</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Part 1&lt;br/&gt;The Earth, environmental and space sciences (EESS) depend on growing international teams, collaboration, diverse research groups, and open, interoperable data. As a celebration of the 30th Goldschmidt conference at Goldschmidt 2020, Theme 15 “Geochemistry and Society” will focus on core topics of interest to all delegates across the disciplines, with emphasis on issues relevant to society and related to the location of the conference (Hawaii and the Pacific Rim). This Theme will explore the future of our science—the major scientific and social challenges, the growing connections with society, human and environmental health, and what workforce is needed to engage and address these opportunities in the future. Career advancement, incentives, and rewards could be better aligned to support workforce needs, as could efforts to enhance diversity, inclusiveness and participation in (and awareness of) EESS in many regions of the world. This travel grant will support key invited experts who would traditionally not participate in the conference.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Part 2&lt;br/&gt;Theme 15 (Geochemistry and Society) at Goldschmidt 2020 is about the future of our planet and how we live on it, the solar system beyond, our science, and our involvement in society, from a geochemical perspective. The Theme will focus on 5 topics of interest (1) Geochemistry and GeoHazards, (2) Origin of Life on Earth and Beyond, (3) Future of Land and Sea in the Face of Climate Change and Biodiversity Loss, (4) Diversity and Inclusion in the Geosciences, and (5) Teaching and Communicating Science in the Age of Social Media. A diverse set of speakers are sought to help address all topics with particular emphasis on topics 1, 4 and 5. These are topics highly relevant to society and early career geoscientists are poised to assist in the solution creation for issues and questions related to these topics. Career advancement, incentives, and rewards could be better aligned to support related geoscience workforce needs, as could efforts to enhance diversity, inclusiveness and participation in (and awareness of) EESS in many regions of the world. The talks will be open to the general public and invitee high school and college students from under represented groups will be invited to participate. The talks will be recorded and available to the public.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/23/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/23/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2024013</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Adina</FirstName>
<LastName>Paytan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Adina Paytan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[apaytan@ucsc.EDU]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000486939</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/23/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Santa Cruz</Name>
<CityName>SANTA CRUZ</CityName>
<ZipCode>950641077</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8314595278</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1156 HIGH ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>VXUFPE4MCZH5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA SANTA CRUZ</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Santa Cruz]]></Name>
<CityName>Santa Cruz</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>950641077</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1156 High Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7699</Code>
<Text>Integrat &amp; Collab Ed &amp; Rsearch</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~12600</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span class="ILfuVd" lang="en"><span class="hgKElc">Indigenous Knowledge  is a body of observations, oral and written knowledge, practices, and  beliefs embeded in <span>the cultural traditions of regional, indigenous, or local communities.</span> Theis knowledge and prectices are based on centuries of observations and interactiosn with the environment and promote environmental sustainability and the responsible  stewardship of natural resources through relationships between humans  and environmental systems. As part of the <a title="Goldschmidt" href="https://conf.goldschmidt.info/goldschmidt/2022/meetingapp.cgi" target="_blank">2022 Goldschmidt Conference</a>, the Geochemical Society organized a special program titled, ?<a title="Theme 15" href="https://conf.goldschmidt.info/goldschmidt/2022/meetingapp.cgi/Program/1084" target="_blank">Geology through a cultural lens</a> - Diverse perspectives on the natural world.? This program, supported by the <a title="Edith Kanakaole Foundation" href="https://edithkanakaolefoundation.org/" target="_blank">Edith Kanaka&#699;ole Foundation</a>, highlighted native Hawaiian and Pacific Islander worldviews as they relate to the natural world. Specifically, it addressed <a title="Papaku Makawalu" href="https://edithkanakaolefoundation.org/papakuMakawalu.php" target="_blank">Papaku&#772; Makawalu</a>, the dynamic Hawaiian understanding of the physical, intellectual, and spiritual foundations from which life cycles emerge. </span></span>The primary objectives of this program were to 1) highlight native Hawaiian culture and knowledge as it relates to our understanding of the natural world and 2) discuss how scientists can help to solve present day environmental challenges in Hawai?i and the Pacific Ocean. The first Goldschmidt Conference to be held in Hawai?i presented a special opportunity to inform geochemists from around the world about these topics. It also presented an opportunity to discuss with members of the Hawaiian community ways to address questions of environmental management in their region. Talkes focused on the connection between <a title="Land and Sea" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=lD9C2ez3tUA" target="_blank">land and sea</a>, the role of <a title="Fire" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BtktA0GtsTI" target="_blank">fire</a> in the environment, marine <a title="Life Cycles" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=tBjBOT3Zbko" target="_blank">sustainability</a> and life cycles, <a title="Water" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=bCo4htygJkI" target="_blank">water </a>resources and the <a title="Sky" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cfMZkXbUSj0" target="_blank">sky</a> above us.&nbsp; The materials were disseminated broadly to both scientists, educators, students of all; ages and local community organizations</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/02/2022<br>      Modified by: Adina&nbsp;Paytan</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Indigenous Knowledge  is a body of observations, oral and written knowledge, practices, and  beliefs embeded in the cultural traditions of regional, indigenous, or local communities. Theis knowledge and prectices are based on centuries of observations and interactiosn with the environment and promote environmental sustainability and the responsible  stewardship of natural resources through relationships between humans  and environmental systems. As part of the 2022 Goldschmidt Conference, the Geochemical Society organized a special program titled, ?Geology through a cultural lens - Diverse perspectives on the natural world.? This program, supported by the Edith Kanaka&#699;ole Foundation, highlighted native Hawaiian and Pacific Islander worldviews as they relate to the natural world. Specifically, it addressed Papaku&#772; Makawalu, the dynamic Hawaiian understanding of the physical, intellectual, and spiritual foundations from which life cycles emerge. The primary objectives of this program were to 1) highlight native Hawaiian culture and knowledge as it relates to our understanding of the natural world and 2) discuss how scientists can help to solve present day environmental challenges in Hawai?i and the Pacific Ocean. The first Goldschmidt Conference to be held in Hawai?i presented a special opportunity to inform geochemists from around the world about these topics. It also presented an opportunity to discuss with members of the Hawaiian community ways to address questions of environmental management in their region. Talkes focused on the connection between land and sea, the role of fire in the environment, marine sustainability and life cycles, water resources and the sky above us.  The materials were disseminated broadly to both scientists, educators, students of all; ages and local community organizations       Last Modified: 11/02/2022       Submitted by: Adina Paytan]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
