<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[NSF Student Travel Grant for 2020 IEEE Radio Frequency Integrated Circuits Symposium (RFIC 2020). To be held August 4-6, 2020.]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>10000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>10000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ECCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Donald Wunsch</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This project helps support the participation of around 40 US-based students to attend the IEEE Radio Frequency Integrated Circuits Symposium (RFIC 2020) originally scheduled for June 21-23, 2020 in Los Angeles and now a virtual symposium due to the COVID-19 pandemic.  The Symposium is part of Microwave Week 2020, the world’s largest RF &amp; microwave technical convention and will now be held from August 4-6, 2020. Over the last three years, the RFIC Symposium has been a three-day long event with over 900 registered attendees, including about 300 students.  The project will  support the selected students that are chosen for their registration fees to the RFIC Symposium.  The RFIC Symposium organizers seek to increase the number of student participants by targeting women, undergraduates, and under-represented groups for participation. The aim is to support young researchers who might not otherwise be able to attend RFIC 2020 due to financial difficulty as well as to encourage the diversity of the field.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The RFIC Symposium is one of the world’s premier events to learn about RFIC design, technology and research. Students are able to obtain feedback on their work (through paper presentations and demos and &lt;br/&gt;competition), talk with senior researchers from government, industry, and academia, and get exposed to &lt;br/&gt;the latest research. RFIC 2020 has a number of events specifically beneficial to student researchers, which &lt;br/&gt;are technical talks, interactive demo session, workshops, tutorials, technical lecture, exhibition, the three-&lt;br/&gt;minute thesis (3MT®) competition program, and other targeted student activities. To summarize, &lt;br/&gt;participation at RFIC 2020 will expose these US-based students to this critical research field of US &lt;br/&gt;national interests (e.g., 5G wireless), enhance the research experiences for students, and provide increased &lt;br/&gt;opportunities for new collaborations to advance knowledge.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/17/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/13/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2024033</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Donald</FirstName>
<LastName>Lie</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>Y</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Donald Y Lie</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[donald.lie@ttu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000545944</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/17/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Texas Tech University</Name>
<CityName>LUBBOCK</CityName>
<ZipCode>79409</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8067423884</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2500 BROADWAY</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>19</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX19</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>EGLKRQ5JBCZ7</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TEXAS TECH UNIVERSITY SYSTEM</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Texas Tech University]]></Name>
<CityName>Lubbock</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>794091035</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2500 Broadway Ave., MS 1035]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>19</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX19</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7607</Code>
<Text>EPCN-Energy-Power-Ctrl-Netwrks</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~10000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The IEEE Radio Frequency Integrated Circuits Symposium (RFIC) is an annual international symposium that serves as a premier forum focused exclusively on presenting the latest state-of-the-art research results in RF, millimeter-wave, and wireless integrated circuits (ICs). The RFIC&rsquo;2020 Symposium is part of Microwave Week 2020, the world&rsquo;s largest RF &amp; microwave technical convention. Over the last three years, RFIC has been a three-day long event with over 900 registered attendees, including about 300 students. We have continued to grow the event. The RFIC Symposium has been an annual IEEE conference that is combined with the International Microwave Symposium (IMS), ARFTG, and the Industry Exhibition to form the &ldquo;Microwave Week&rdquo;, the world&rsquo;s largest RF/microwave technical convention of the year. The 2020 Microwave Week was supposed to be held at the Los Angeles from June 21-26; however, due to the global COVID-19 pandemic, it was held virtually with RFIC Symp. 2020, and RFIC Symp. 2021 was held in a hybrid mode but mostly virtually as well. Therefore, all costs are used for covering the registration fees for the student awardees for attending the IEEE RFIC Symp. 2020 or 2021. The $10,000 covers 21 awardees for RFIC&rsquo;20, and of 15 awardees for RFIC&rsquo;21, respectively.</p> <p>Fig. 1 shows the RFIC&rsquo;20 website picture of this NSF Student Conference Registration Awards info for RFIC&rsquo;20, where we explain &ldquo;As part of NSF's commitment to maintain United States' research competitiveness in important areas of Science and Technology, the organizers of IEEE RFIC&rsquo;20 are pleased to announce the 2020 NSF Student Conference Registration Awards (traditionally names as the NSF Student Travel Awards) to encourage more US-based STEM students both at the graduate and undergraduate levels to attend and participate in the IEEE RFIC Symp. 2020, which has now become a virtual conference. Each award will cover up to $250 USD for the full conference registration fee.&rdquo;</p> <p>The applicants need to download a from RFIC&rsquo;20 website to apply. Our Selection Criteria are listed in Fig. 1.</p> <h1>Intellectual Merit</h1> <p>RFIC Symp. is one of the world&rsquo;s premier events to learn about RFIC design, technology and research. Students are able to obtain feedback on their work (paper presentations and demos), talk with senior researchers from government, industry, and academia, and get exposed to the latest research. RFIC has a number of events targeted, with several specifically aimed towards student researchers. Young students&rsquo; attendance is important because they represent the future of these events. Students also benefit tremendously by attending presentations on the latest research, making new connections, and participating in the various conference events. The NSF travel grant helps us increase student attendance in a significant manner. This is particularly useful to encourage student participation in RFIC Symp. workshops, panels, demos, tutorials, exhibition, and attending papers presentations. The workshops and the technical lectures provide the students the latest updates and direct interactions with world experts from government, industry, and academia, and provide unique training that is not possible at any university program. The RFIC symp. has a long history of successful workshops, while the technical lecture that was introduced since RFIC 2019 was well attended, especially from students (over 250 attended, while estimated ~80+ as students).&nbsp;</p> <h1>Broader Impacts</h1> <p>As one can see from Table 1, and Table 2, we have 5 student authors who took advantage of this NSF Grant for RFIC&rsquo;20, and 2 for RFIC&rsquo;21. For RFIC&rsquo;20, 33.3% of the awardees are US citizens, while 14.3% are undergraduate students, and the majority of awardees are PhD students (i.e., 76.2%), while ~10% are Master students. Also 3 awardees (i.e., 14.3%) are female. The awardees were attending UT Dallas, UC Davis, Case Western Reserve University, Boston University, GaTech, Florida International University, Ohio State U, Texas Tech U, UCLA, Washington State University, Rice U and UCSB; total 12 institutions. Eight countries where the awarded students originally came from are Iran, India, China, Turkey, Pakistani, USA, Haiti, and Egypt.</p> <p>For RFIC&rsquo;21, 20% of the awardees are US citizens, while this time no undergraduate students, and all are PhD students. This is probably because IMS/RFIC&rsquo;21 eventually were held in a hybrid mode at Atlanta and the announcement of this hybrid decision was rather late, which confused most non-PhD students applicants. Two awardees (i.e., 13.3%) are female. The awardees attended UC Davis, Carnegie Mellon University, Arizona State University, Cornell U, Texas Tech U, North Carolina State U, GaTech, Washington State U and Rice U; total 9 institutions. Awardees from 5 countries are represented: Iran, India, China, Turkey, USA, and Egypt.</p> <p>We believe this grant has helped us to improve the participation of US-based minority students, and enhanced the STEM educational experience and proficiencies for US-based students. It also help developing a diverse, globally competitive STEM workforce in the United States, and increase partnerships between academia, industry, and government to increase the economic competitiveness of the US.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/16/2021<br>      Modified by: Donald&nbsp;D&nbsp;Lie</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2024033/2024033_10698217_1639630753986_NSF_RFIC20_Student_Reg_Info_Appl_Website--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2024033/2024033_10698217_1639630753986_NSF_RFIC20_Student_Reg_Info_Appl_Website--rgov-800width.jpg" title="NSF_RFIC20_website"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2024033/2024033_10698217_1639630753986_NSF_RFIC20_Student_Reg_Info_Appl_Website--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="NSF_RFIC20_website"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Fig. 1 A picture of the NSF Student Conference Registration Award application info and form published on IEEE RFIC Symp. 20 website</div> <div class="imageCredit">Donald Y C Lie</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Donald&nbsp;D&nbsp;Lie</div> <div class="imageTitle">NSF_RFIC20_website</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2024033/2024033_10698217_1639630624903_Table2_RFIC21_NSF_awardees_breakdown_DL--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2024033/2024033_10698217_1639630624903_Table2_RFIC21_NSF_awardees_breakdown_DL--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Awardees_Breakdown_NSF_RFIC21"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2024033/2024033_10698217_1639630624903_Table2_RFIC21_NSF_awardees_breakdown_DL--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Awardees_Breakdown_NSF_RFIC21"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Table 2. Breakdown of NSF RFIC'2021 Students Travel Grant Awardees</div> <div class="imageCredit">Donald Y C Lie</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Donald&nbsp;D&nbsp;Lie</div> <div class="imageTitle">Awardees_Breakdown_NSF_RFIC21</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2024033/2024033_10698217_1639630382568_Table1_RFIC20_NSF_awardees_breakdown_DL.emf--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2024033/2024033_10698217_1639630382568_Table1_RFIC20_NSF_awardees_breakdown_DL.emf--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Awardees_Breakdown_NSF_RFIC20"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2024033/2024033_10698217_1639630382568_Table1_RFIC20_NSF_awardees_breakdown_DL.emf--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Awardees_Breakdown_NSF_RFIC20"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Table 1. Breakdown of NSF RFIC'2020 Students Travel Grant Awardees</div> <div class="imageCredit">Donald Y C Lie</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Donald&nbsp;D&nbsp;Lie</div> <div class="imageTitle">Awardees_Breakdown_NSF_RFIC20</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The IEEE Radio Frequency Integrated Circuits Symposium (RFIC) is an annual international symposium that serves as a premier forum focused exclusively on presenting the latest state-of-the-art research results in RF, millimeter-wave, and wireless integrated circuits (ICs). The RFIC’2020 Symposium is part of Microwave Week 2020, the world’s largest RF &amp; microwave technical convention. Over the last three years, RFIC has been a three-day long event with over 900 registered attendees, including about 300 students. We have continued to grow the event. The RFIC Symposium has been an annual IEEE conference that is combined with the International Microwave Symposium (IMS), ARFTG, and the Industry Exhibition to form the "Microwave Week", the world’s largest RF/microwave technical convention of the year. The 2020 Microwave Week was supposed to be held at the Los Angeles from June 21-26; however, due to the global COVID-19 pandemic, it was held virtually with RFIC Symp. 2020, and RFIC Symp. 2021 was held in a hybrid mode but mostly virtually as well. Therefore, all costs are used for covering the registration fees for the student awardees for attending the IEEE RFIC Symp. 2020 or 2021. The $10,000 covers 21 awardees for RFIC’20, and of 15 awardees for RFIC’21, respectively.  Fig. 1 shows the RFIC’20 website picture of this NSF Student Conference Registration Awards info for RFIC’20, where we explain "As part of NSF's commitment to maintain United States' research competitiveness in important areas of Science and Technology, the organizers of IEEE RFIC’20 are pleased to announce the 2020 NSF Student Conference Registration Awards (traditionally names as the NSF Student Travel Awards) to encourage more US-based STEM students both at the graduate and undergraduate levels to attend and participate in the IEEE RFIC Symp. 2020, which has now become a virtual conference. Each award will cover up to $250 USD for the full conference registration fee."  The applicants need to download a from RFIC’20 website to apply. Our Selection Criteria are listed in Fig. 1. Intellectual Merit  RFIC Symp. is one of the world’s premier events to learn about RFIC design, technology and research. Students are able to obtain feedback on their work (paper presentations and demos), talk with senior researchers from government, industry, and academia, and get exposed to the latest research. RFIC has a number of events targeted, with several specifically aimed towards student researchers. Young students’ attendance is important because they represent the future of these events. Students also benefit tremendously by attending presentations on the latest research, making new connections, and participating in the various conference events. The NSF travel grant helps us increase student attendance in a significant manner. This is particularly useful to encourage student participation in RFIC Symp. workshops, panels, demos, tutorials, exhibition, and attending papers presentations. The workshops and the technical lectures provide the students the latest updates and direct interactions with world experts from government, industry, and academia, and provide unique training that is not possible at any university program. The RFIC symp. has a long history of successful workshops, while the technical lecture that was introduced since RFIC 2019 was well attended, especially from students (over 250 attended, while estimated ~80+ as students).  Broader Impacts  As one can see from Table 1, and Table 2, we have 5 student authors who took advantage of this NSF Grant for RFIC’20, and 2 for RFIC’21. For RFIC’20, 33.3% of the awardees are US citizens, while 14.3% are undergraduate students, and the majority of awardees are PhD students (i.e., 76.2%), while ~10% are Master students. Also 3 awardees (i.e., 14.3%) are female. The awardees were attending UT Dallas, UC Davis, Case Western Reserve University, Boston University, GaTech, Florida International University, Ohio State U, Texas Tech U, UCLA, Washington State University, Rice U and UCSB; total 12 institutions. Eight countries where the awarded students originally came from are Iran, India, China, Turkey, Pakistani, USA, Haiti, and Egypt.  For RFIC’21, 20% of the awardees are US citizens, while this time no undergraduate students, and all are PhD students. This is probably because IMS/RFIC’21 eventually were held in a hybrid mode at Atlanta and the announcement of this hybrid decision was rather late, which confused most non-PhD students applicants. Two awardees (i.e., 13.3%) are female. The awardees attended UC Davis, Carnegie Mellon University, Arizona State University, Cornell U, Texas Tech U, North Carolina State U, GaTech, Washington State U and Rice U; total 9 institutions. Awardees from 5 countries are represented: Iran, India, China, Turkey, USA, and Egypt.  We believe this grant has helped us to improve the participation of US-based minority students, and enhanced the STEM educational experience and proficiencies for US-based students. It also help developing a diverse, globally competitive STEM workforce in the United States, and increase partnerships between academia, industry, and government to increase the economic competitiveness of the US.          Last Modified: 12/16/2021       Submitted by: Donald D Lie]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
