<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Impacts, Disruption, and Displacement After Low Attention Disasters: Experiences of Non-owner and Immigrant Households]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>9689.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>9689</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jacqueline Meszaros</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jmeszaro@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927261</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This Rapid Response Research (RAPID) project examines life disruption, recovery resources, and displacement with a focus on non-homeowner and immigrant households in Marshalltown, Iowa after an EF-3 Tornado. The damage from this tornado was concentrated in older low-income neighborhoods with many uninsured houses, limited government assistance, and low capacity to provide replacement housing within the community. This research examines recovery needs resulting from social vulnerability especially tenure and immigration. The results will assist planners, emergency managers, and policymakers to incorporate approaches within recovery programs that better communicate assistance eligibility criteria with immigrants. This scientific research contribution thus supports NSF's mission to promote the progress of science and to advance our national welfare. In this case, the benefits will be insights to assist recovery of our most vulnerable populations after a disaster.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research addresses gaps in the disaster literature with respect to low attention disasters that affect immigrants, renters and contract homeowners. Vulnerable households like immigrants and non-homeowners are at a disadvantage for accessing recovery assistance to complete home repairs and subsequently at a higher risk of long-term displacement. This project collects data to examine recovery experiences of immigrants and non-homeowners in the aftermath of the Marshalltown tornado that did not receive much attention and resources despite causing major damages in low income neighborhoods with a relatively higher percentage of minority, immigrant, and non-homeowner households. Hence, it offers a unique possibility for assessing the complex recovery challenges related to housing tenure and immigration after low attention disasters. Methods of data collection consist of conducting focus groups with households, one on one interviews, and participant observation. Analysis methods include qualitative coding of data through theme identification and constant comparison.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/14/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/14/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2024139</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sara</FirstName>
<LastName>Hamideh</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sara Hamideh</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[sara.hamideh@stonybrook.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000719638</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/14/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>SUNY at Stony Brook</Name>
<CityName>STONY BROOK</CityName>
<ZipCode>117940001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6316329949</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>W5510 FRANKS MELVILLE MEMORIAL L</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>M746VC6XMNH9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>THE RESEARCH FOUNDATION FOR THE STATE UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[SUNY at Stony Brook]]></Name>
<CityName>Stony Brook</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>117940001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1638</Code>
<Text>HDBE-Humans, Disasters, and th</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>041E</Code>
<Text>HAZARD AND DISASTER REDUCTION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>042E</Code>
<Text>HAZARD AND DISASTER RESPONSE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9102</Code>
<Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01001920DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~9689</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span lang="EN">Many towns in the Midwest experience Tornados frequently, sometimes with relatively overwhelming impacts and little attention and aid. Low-attention disasters that affect vulnerable populations create unique recovery challenges. We conducted a qualitative case study of impacts and recovery of housing in Marshalltown, Iowa after an EF3 Tornado in 2018 which affected a large portion of the town, in particular neighborhoods with high concentration of immigrant, low-income households in old and poorly maintained housing.&nbsp;</span>We examined the disparities in access to recovery resources, strategies and resources that vulnerable households use to rebound in the absence of substantial aid, and the effects of living in unrepaired homes and prolonged recovery.</p> <p><span lang="EN">Our case study reveals the complex dynamics of vulnerability that unfold through time before, during, and long after a disaster and calls for a proactive, deliberate, and equity-centered approach to recovery planning, with emphasis on older and lower-income neighborhoods that can become targets of rushed decisions after a disaster. Setting recovery policies in normal times can help ensure more deliberative and inclusive approaches that fulfill the interests of a wider range of residents in a community.</span></p> <p><span lang="EN">Our findings call for federal recovery programs to better support local government agencies and NGOs that are rooted in culturally diverse communities as they are in the frontline of assisting disaster-affected households. L</span>ocal community organizations are in a better position to provide more flexible aid and ensure affected households can feel safe to reach out for assistance and understand the process and eligibility criteria for receiving recovery assistance.</p> <p><span lang="EN">Disaster vulnerability is a process that begins before an event, therefore governmental and non-governmental organizations should address the disaster needs based on the constraints that result from intersectionality of vulnerability factors present long before a disaster.&nbsp;<span lang="EN">Cities like Marshalltown that attract different immigrant groups for economic reasons should provide quality rental and affordable options in their housing market which in turn can reduce housing damages after disasters and reduce prolonged stays and frequent moves during temporary housing stages which are especially harmful for the health fragile and elderly.</span></span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/17/2022<br>      Modified by: Sara&nbsp;Hamideh</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Many towns in the Midwest experience Tornados frequently, sometimes with relatively overwhelming impacts and little attention and aid. Low-attention disasters that affect vulnerable populations create unique recovery challenges. We conducted a qualitative case study of impacts and recovery of housing in Marshalltown, Iowa after an EF3 Tornado in 2018 which affected a large portion of the town, in particular neighborhoods with high concentration of immigrant, low-income households in old and poorly maintained housing. We examined the disparities in access to recovery resources, strategies and resources that vulnerable households use to rebound in the absence of substantial aid, and the effects of living in unrepaired homes and prolonged recovery.  Our case study reveals the complex dynamics of vulnerability that unfold through time before, during, and long after a disaster and calls for a proactive, deliberate, and equity-centered approach to recovery planning, with emphasis on older and lower-income neighborhoods that can become targets of rushed decisions after a disaster. Setting recovery policies in normal times can help ensure more deliberative and inclusive approaches that fulfill the interests of a wider range of residents in a community.  Our findings call for federal recovery programs to better support local government agencies and NGOs that are rooted in culturally diverse communities as they are in the frontline of assisting disaster-affected households. Local community organizations are in a better position to provide more flexible aid and ensure affected households can feel safe to reach out for assistance and understand the process and eligibility criteria for receiving recovery assistance.  Disaster vulnerability is a process that begins before an event, therefore governmental and non-governmental organizations should address the disaster needs based on the constraints that result from intersectionality of vulnerability factors present long before a disaster. Cities like Marshalltown that attract different immigrant groups for economic reasons should provide quality rental and affordable options in their housing market which in turn can reduce housing damages after disasters and reduce prolonged stays and frequent moves during temporary housing stages which are especially harmful for the health fragile and elderly.       Last Modified: 05/17/2022       Submitted by: Sara Hamideh]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
