<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[EAGER: Bioforecasting: understanding and predicting species persistence in ecological communities under changing environments]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>199298.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>199298</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Douglas Levey</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dlevey@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925196</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Biodiversity is defined as the presence of all species of plants, animals and other living things at a given place and time. These species share their environment and interact in complex ways. Scientists know that biodiversity is critical for providing many ecological services necessary for the planet’s health. Examples of these services include nutrient cycling, water purification, and soil formation. Thus, understanding and predicting changes in biodiversity (called "bioforecasting") is important for human wellbeing. However, because of larger and faster environmental changes, knowing whether a species in a given place will persist has become one of the biggest ecological challenges that scientists face. The main problem is that it’s virtually impossible to know how, where, when and which environmental conditions will change. The changes are obvious only in hindsight. This project will create a new way to solve the problem. The goal is to estimate the chance that a species will persist in a given place and how its presence (or absence) can affect the chance of other species persisting there, too. This project will also help launch the careers of a scientist and the students he will mentor as they together craft a new theory.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The main difficulty in understanding and predicting species persistence resides in knowing the exact equations governing the dynamics of ecological communities and the high uncertainty regarding initial conditions, parameter values, intrinsic randomness, and more importantly, how the changing external conditions will affect all of these dynamics. While bioforecasting is already a well-established endeavor in ecological research, current bioforecasting approaches demand extensive amounts of data and their generalization often lacks experimental validation. Thus, it has been emphasized that radically new frameworks are needed. Development of such frameworks involve large risks and many challenges. This project will break new ground by integrating concepts from the ensemble theory of statistical mechanics with the mathematical concepts of structural stability, applied to population dynamics to tackle current limitations in bioforecasting. Specifically, instead of aiming to study the future behavior of a system by inferring the main conditions acting upon it, this project will provide a testable methodology to estimate and interpret the probability of a future behavior based on the fraction of possible conditions compatible with the observability of such behavior. The investigator will develop model-driven and data-driven approaches to estimate such probabilities and validate them with empirical data already compiled in the literature.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/01/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/01/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2024349</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Serguei</FirstName>
<LastName>Saavedra</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Serguei Saavedra</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[sersaa@mit.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000709901</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/01/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Massachusetts Institute of Technology</Name>
<CityName>CAMBRIDGE</CityName>
<ZipCode>021394301</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6172531000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>77 MASSACHUSETTS AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>E2NYLCDML6V1</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MASSACHUSETTS INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>E2NYLCDML6V1</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Massachusetts Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021394301</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1128</Code>
<Text>Population &amp; Community Ecology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~199298</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-37599cab-7fff-0cec-52b8-853df60212a2"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>There is a rapidly increasing interest in explaining and predicting the behavior of natural ecological communities to enhance the presence of beneficial species and ecosystem functions and to suppress the presence of harmful ones. The collection of species in ecological communities regulate key ecosystem services and functions, e.g., water purification, soil formation, CO2 sequestration, crop production, and human-well being. However, the predictions/interventions that work under one context do not always work under a different context. Why, when, and how often shall predictions/interventions work? This project developed and verified model-driven and data-driven tools to study the survival of species in ecological communities under changing environmental contexts. Most of the tractable work in theoretical ecology has been done at the two-species level, considering and assuming one single environmental context at a time. The traditional focus has been on the stability of equilibria of community dynamics (perturbations on state variables), but always assuming feasibility - the existence of a positive equilibrium. Moreover, because the magnitude of environmental perturbations can have different impacts on species abundances within communities, it has been unclear whether the same perturbation can have different impacts as a function of time.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>First, this project introduced a geometric perspective to describe and quantify the possibility and probability of a community's survival by the volume of environmentally-driven parameters compatible with positive solutions (feasibility). Specifically, the project linked the volume of survival possibility to the structural stability of communities (i.e., tolerance of a community to different environmental contexts or formally perturbations on parameter values).</span><span> </span><span>The project demonstrated that the survival of all species in a community does not require pairwise survival and vice versa. It also demonstrated that even under simple models the combination of context-dependent parameters compatible with the survival of a community can change as a function of the number/identity of the interacting species.&nbsp; Then, the project </span><span>estimated the probability of survival proportional to the normalized volume of survival possibilities. </span><span>The project showed that the effect of an invader species (e.g., pathogen) on a resident community can be computed as the ratio of the survival probabilities with and without the invader species. Using experimental data, verified that the addition of a species into a pool can affect positively (resp. negatively) the structural stability of a given collection of species and enhance (resp. inhibit) its survival.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Second, this project proposed to use the volume contraction rate (trace of the Jacobian matrix) of a dynamical system as a measure related to the time-varying sensitivity (inverse of structural stability) of a community to environmental perturbations. To make it practical to real-world data, the project integrated and improved nonparametric attractor reconstruction methods (known as S-map) to infer the state-dependent linearization (Jacobian) of a dynamical from time series under process noise. Results showed that the community sensitivity to perturbations and its prediction depend on the time of perturbation. Additionally, results show that the most sensitive species to perturbations were not always the ones with the most rapidly changing or lowest abundance, which are typical criteria to classify endangered species. Overall, this project established model-driven and data-driven tools as a path towards increasing our&nbsp;</span>understanding of the potential limits and opportunities in the conservation and restoration of ecological communities.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/07/2023<br>      Modified by: Serguei&nbsp;Saavedra</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   There is a rapidly increasing interest in explaining and predicting the behavior of natural ecological communities to enhance the presence of beneficial species and ecosystem functions and to suppress the presence of harmful ones. The collection of species in ecological communities regulate key ecosystem services and functions, e.g., water purification, soil formation, CO2 sequestration, crop production, and human-well being. However, the predictions/interventions that work under one context do not always work under a different context. Why, when, and how often shall predictions/interventions work? This project developed and verified model-driven and data-driven tools to study the survival of species in ecological communities under changing environmental contexts. Most of the tractable work in theoretical ecology has been done at the two-species level, considering and assuming one single environmental context at a time. The traditional focus has been on the stability of equilibria of community dynamics (perturbations on state variables), but always assuming feasibility - the existence of a positive equilibrium. Moreover, because the magnitude of environmental perturbations can have different impacts on species abundances within communities, it has been unclear whether the same perturbation can have different impacts as a function of time. First, this project introduced a geometric perspective to describe and quantify the possibility and probability of a community's survival by the volume of environmentally-driven parameters compatible with positive solutions (feasibility). Specifically, the project linked the volume of survival possibility to the structural stability of communities (i.e., tolerance of a community to different environmental contexts or formally perturbations on parameter values). The project demonstrated that the survival of all species in a community does not require pairwise survival and vice versa. It also demonstrated that even under simple models the combination of context-dependent parameters compatible with the survival of a community can change as a function of the number/identity of the interacting species.  Then, the project estimated the probability of survival proportional to the normalized volume of survival possibilities. The project showed that the effect of an invader species (e.g., pathogen) on a resident community can be computed as the ratio of the survival probabilities with and without the invader species. Using experimental data, verified that the addition of a species into a pool can affect positively (resp. negatively) the structural stability of a given collection of species and enhance (resp. inhibit) its survival.  Second, this project proposed to use the volume contraction rate (trace of the Jacobian matrix) of a dynamical system as a measure related to the time-varying sensitivity (inverse of structural stability) of a community to environmental perturbations. To make it practical to real-world data, the project integrated and improved nonparametric attractor reconstruction methods (known as S-map) to infer the state-dependent linearization (Jacobian) of a dynamical from time series under process noise. Results showed that the community sensitivity to perturbations and its prediction depend on the time of perturbation. Additionally, results show that the most sensitive species to perturbations were not always the ones with the most rapidly changing or lowest abundance, which are typical criteria to classify endangered species. Overall, this project established model-driven and data-driven tools as a path towards increasing our understanding of the potential limits and opportunities in the conservation and restoration of ecological communities.             Last Modified: 03/07/2023       Submitted by: Serguei Saavedra]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
