<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[EAR/IF: Acquisition of Bench Top SEM and Field Equipment for Research and Teaching]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>273136.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>273136</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>David Lambert</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dlambert@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924736</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This project is jointly funded by the Division of Earth Sciences Instrumentation and Facilities and the Established Program to Stimulate Competitive Research (EPSCoR).  The award will support acquisition of a scanning electron microscope (SEM) and ancillary field equipment including a water quality sonde, data logger, and a weather station, to support research and research training at Wichita State University.  The equipment will benefit multiple WSU researchers for studies in geology, biology, chemistry, anthropology, and engineering with relevance to societal interests including reducing and remediating toxic elements introduced into the subsurface,  studies of hydrophobic composite materials to harvest water vapor in arid regions, and studies of mineral-microbe interactions in hypersaline environments.  The instrumentation will support graduate and undergraduate student experiential learning and research training and the investigators intend to conduct instrument-mediated outreach to local K-12 students and educators.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The equipment will be used foremost for investigations of the transport and fate of natural and man-made colloidal materials in groundwaters and soils, with field equipment deployed at a local University managed nature preserve (the Ninnescah Reserve).  The SEM will facilitate micron to sub-micron scale imaging of the interactions between natural and synthetic colloids with mineral surfaces with implications for understanding the subsurface transport and fate of metal contaminants adsorbed to natural organic materials and studies of potential remediation techniques for neutralizing acid mine drainage.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/20/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/20/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2024962</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Andrew</FirstName>
<LastName>Swindle</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Andrew Swindle</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[andrew.swindle@wichita.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000744951</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/20/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Wichita State University</Name>
<CityName>WICHITA</CityName>
<ZipCode>672609700</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3169783285</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1845 FAIRMOUNT ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Kansas</StateName>
<StateCode>KS</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>KS04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>JKKNZLNYLJ19</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WICHITA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>JKKNZLNYLJ19</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Wichita State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Wichita</CityName>
<StateCode>KS</StateCode>
<ZipCode>672600007</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Kansas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>KS04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1580</Code>
<Text>Instrumentation &amp; Facilities</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EPSCoR Co-Funding</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~273136</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This award allowed for the procurement of various scientific equipment that improved the research capabilities at WSU.&nbsp; The equipment procured can be divided in to two categories: on-campus equipment, and field equipment.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The on-campus equipment consisted of a Bench Top SEM and a sputter coater.&nbsp; This equipment allowed for the establishment of the Environmental Mineralogy Imaging Laboratory, which provides imaging services to on- and off-campus researchers.&nbsp; In the Geology Department this equipment has been used in research related to acid mine drainage, the use of nanogoethite and nanoTiO<sub>2 </sub>in groundwater remediation, and the types and occurrence of clays in restored prairies.&nbsp; This equipment is also used by researchers in the Department of Chemistry and the Department of Mechanical Engineering.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The field equipment consists of 10 multiparameter groundwater data loggers that are able to track groundwater level, water temperature, and conductivity at various time intervals.&nbsp; The other piece of equipment is a weather station that also monitoring of temperature, precipitation, humidity, solar radiation, wind speed and direction, and soil moisture.&nbsp; The field equipment is in place at the WSU Biological Field Station: Ninnescah Reserve.&nbsp; On this site the Geology Department has a series of 10 groundwater wells spread out over an area of approximately 10 acres (in roughly a rectangle), and each one of those wells hold a data logger.&nbsp; Situated in the middle of these wells is the weather station.&nbsp; This setup allowed for the study of rainfall and how it relates to recharge in the shallow subsurface.&nbsp; The ability to track conductivity provides clues as the flux of ionic species from the soils to groundwater.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The field equipment has also allowed for more teaching opportunities related to the field of hydrogeology.&nbsp; The loggers can be programmed to take sub-second measurements, which allows students to conduct slug tests and pump tests.&nbsp; These are real-world activities in the field of hydrogeology that students rarely get exposed to.&nbsp; Additionally, as the data loggers are continuously collecting data, the students get experience handling, manipulating, and interpreting massive data sets.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Overall, this equipment has greatly expanded research in the fields of geology, solid-state chemistry, and mechanical engineering, while simultaneously providing educational activities for undergraduate and graduate students.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/29/2023<br>      Modified by: Andrew&nbsp;Swindle</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This award allowed for the procurement of various scientific equipment that improved the research capabilities at WSU.  The equipment procured can be divided in to two categories: on-campus equipment, and field equipment.      The on-campus equipment consisted of a Bench Top SEM and a sputter coater.  This equipment allowed for the establishment of the Environmental Mineralogy Imaging Laboratory, which provides imaging services to on- and off-campus researchers.  In the Geology Department this equipment has been used in research related to acid mine drainage, the use of nanogoethite and nanoTiO2 in groundwater remediation, and the types and occurrence of clays in restored prairies.  This equipment is also used by researchers in the Department of Chemistry and the Department of Mechanical Engineering.      The field equipment consists of 10 multiparameter groundwater data loggers that are able to track groundwater level, water temperature, and conductivity at various time intervals.  The other piece of equipment is a weather station that also monitoring of temperature, precipitation, humidity, solar radiation, wind speed and direction, and soil moisture.  The field equipment is in place at the WSU Biological Field Station: Ninnescah Reserve.  On this site the Geology Department has a series of 10 groundwater wells spread out over an area of approximately 10 acres (in roughly a rectangle), and each one of those wells hold a data logger.  Situated in the middle of these wells is the weather station.  This setup allowed for the study of rainfall and how it relates to recharge in the shallow subsurface.  The ability to track conductivity provides clues as the flux of ionic species from the soils to groundwater.      The field equipment has also allowed for more teaching opportunities related to the field of hydrogeology.  The loggers can be programmed to take sub-second measurements, which allows students to conduct slug tests and pump tests.  These are real-world activities in the field of hydrogeology that students rarely get exposed to.  Additionally, as the data loggers are continuously collecting data, the students get experience handling, manipulating, and interpreting massive data sets.     Overall, this equipment has greatly expanded research in the fields of geology, solid-state chemistry, and mechanical engineering, while simultaneously providing educational activities for undergraduate and graduate students.           Last Modified: 09/29/2023       Submitted by: Andrew Swindle]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
