<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase II:  Synthetic biology platform for production of stabilized high-value proteins]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1000000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1199999</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Cooperative Agreement</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Erik Pierstorff</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>epiersto@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922165</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase II project is to help patients living with diabetes. The disease accounts for 12% of deaths in the US and patients face major lifestyle changes.  Most patients transition to insulin replacement therapy, which carries a complex dosing schedule that, if not followed closely, can leave patients in dangerous states of glucose dysregulation. More than 50 million diabetics currently use basal insulin analogs designed for longer activity than human insulin. The convenience and improved safety of these analogs has led to widespread adoption and a global market surpassing $10B. However, all current basal insulins require daily injections, a dosing burden that leads to poor treatment adherence, leaving patients vulnerable to dangerous fluctuations in blood glucose. The modified insulin described in this Phase II project is intended to provide the stability necessary to achieve once-weekly dosing. Relaxing the injection schedule should dramatically improve compliance and safety for patients; furthermore, the solution can be delivered at lower cost. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project uses a scalable in vivo protein production platform to produce long-acting insulin analogs for the diabetes market. The project utilizes the platform’s unique capability to site-specifically install non-standard amino acids into proteins, and to produce the modified proteins at scale. By replacing key bond-forming amino acids in insulin with non-standard amino acids that form stronger bonds, the modified insulins can achieve the stability necessary to support once-weekly dosing. The research objectives are to: produce sufficient quantities of variants of this insulin analog to support an experimental program, demonstrate improved stability of the variants over wild-type insulin in cell-based assays, and demonstrate sufficiently prolongated pharmacodynamics of the insulin analogs in an animal study to support once-weekly dosing. Potential outcomes include the first insulin analog capable of filling a major clinical and commercial need for affordable, safe insulin analogs with relaxed dosing schedules. Further, the work provides technical validation of a novel protein production platform.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/14/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/21/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>CoopAgrmnt</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2024671</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
<LastName>Mandell</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Daniel J Mandell</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[dan.mandell@grobio.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000779392</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/14/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>GRO BIOSCIENCES INC</Name>
<CityName>CAMBRIDGE</CityName>
<ZipCode>021393544</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4159997625</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>750 MAIN STREET</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>REYUNPCCJMM4</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GRO BIOSCIENCES INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[GRO BIOSCIENCES INC]]></Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021393543</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[700 Main Street North]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5373</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase II</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>144E</Code>
<Text>Synthetic biology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>169E</Code>
<Text>SBIR Tech Enhan Partner (TECP)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8038</Code>
<Text>Biotechnology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~1000000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~199999</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>During our NSF SBIR Phase II work period we produced valuable <em>in vivo </em>data to support bringing stabilized therapeutics into the clinic. The data generated support two high-value product profiles. First, the pharmacokinetic, pharmacodynamic, potency, and safety data support the use of our therapeutics for a long-acting formulation that could increase safety and convenience for patients. This modality is further supported by the resistance to protease degradation observed. Second, the surprisingly rapid pharmacodynamics of one of our variants, combined with the resistance to aggregation discovered during our award, raise the unexpected possibility of using our therapeutics in a fast-acting formulation. Current fast-acting formulations are limited due to their tendency to aggregate, and they limit the granularity of therapeutic control due to the lag time required to return to baseline levels. The data generated during our Phase II SBIR work suggest that our therapeutics could address both these limitations.</p> <p>Our TECP supplemental award also generated valuable data to advance assets for immunotolerization. Specifically, by using TECP funds to synthesize antigenic peptides bearing tolerizing glycans, we demonstrated that our ProGly&trade; approach to immunomodulation can induce antigen-specific T regulatory (Treg) cells and drive a tolerogenic cytokine profile in cell studies using tissue from an animal model of autoimmune disease. We have now begun live animal studies in a well-characterized model of autoimmune disease using this material. The cell-based data has already generated significant interest among pharmaceutical and biotechnology companies, with conversations now underway on using ProGly to reverse autoimmune disease, to eliminate anti-drug antibodies impairing protein-based therapies, and to eliminate neutralizing antibodies currently impeding gene therapies delivered by viral capsids. The latter application can address two critical problems in gene therapy. First, many patients have been pre-exposed to viral vectors, leaving them with neutralizing antibody titers that render them ineligible for reimbursement by insurance (thereby placing these million-dollar therapies beyond the reach of millions of patients). Second, viral delivery vectors typically cannot be redosed due neutralizing antibodies generated from the primary administration. The data generated by our TECP award has advanced our ProGly technology to partnering discussions across all these high-value applications with the potential to improve or initiate therapy for millions of underserved patients. Accordingly, we have filed a provisional patent application on ProGly.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/26/2023<br>      Modified by: Daniel&nbsp;J&nbsp;Mandell</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ During our NSF SBIR Phase II work period we produced valuable in vivo data to support bringing stabilized therapeutics into the clinic. The data generated support two high-value product profiles. First, the pharmacokinetic, pharmacodynamic, potency, and safety data support the use of our therapeutics for a long-acting formulation that could increase safety and convenience for patients. This modality is further supported by the resistance to protease degradation observed. Second, the surprisingly rapid pharmacodynamics of one of our variants, combined with the resistance to aggregation discovered during our award, raise the unexpected possibility of using our therapeutics in a fast-acting formulation. Current fast-acting formulations are limited due to their tendency to aggregate, and they limit the granularity of therapeutic control due to the lag time required to return to baseline levels. The data generated during our Phase II SBIR work suggest that our therapeutics could address both these limitations.  Our TECP supplemental award also generated valuable data to advance assets for immunotolerization. Specifically, by using TECP funds to synthesize antigenic peptides bearing tolerizing glycans, we demonstrated that our ProGly&trade; approach to immunomodulation can induce antigen-specific T regulatory (Treg) cells and drive a tolerogenic cytokine profile in cell studies using tissue from an animal model of autoimmune disease. We have now begun live animal studies in a well-characterized model of autoimmune disease using this material. The cell-based data has already generated significant interest among pharmaceutical and biotechnology companies, with conversations now underway on using ProGly to reverse autoimmune disease, to eliminate anti-drug antibodies impairing protein-based therapies, and to eliminate neutralizing antibodies currently impeding gene therapies delivered by viral capsids. The latter application can address two critical problems in gene therapy. First, many patients have been pre-exposed to viral vectors, leaving them with neutralizing antibody titers that render them ineligible for reimbursement by insurance (thereby placing these million-dollar therapies beyond the reach of millions of patients). Second, viral delivery vectors typically cannot be redosed due neutralizing antibodies generated from the primary administration. The data generated by our TECP award has advanced our ProGly technology to partnering discussions across all these high-value applications with the potential to improve or initiate therapy for millions of underserved patients. Accordingly, we have filed a provisional patent application on ProGly.          Last Modified: 01/26/2023       Submitted by: Daniel J Mandell]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
