<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Plate Boundary Structure and Deformation Workshop]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>64916.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>64916</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OCE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Gail Christeson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>gchriste@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922952</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This project will support a two-day workshop at the University of Hawaii at Manoa related to plate boundary structure and deformation at rifts and subduction zones. The primary goal of the workshop is to present and synthesize research results that have been funded by the NSF-GeoPRISMS (Geodynamic Processes at Rifting and Subducting Margins) Program related to understanding the tectonic processes that underpin movement at convergent and divergent plate boundaries. Approximately 50 scientists will participate in the workshop onsite at UH Manoa, of which at least 23 will be early-career scientists (student, postdoc, of pre-tenure faculty within 10 years of PhD). The program will consist of keynotes, posters, and lighting talks to communicate the breadth of active science conducted by participants, as well as discussion sessions and opportunities for early career development. There will also be a half-day pre-workshop meeting for early-career scientists. The aim is to have participation from an interdisciplinary group of scientists representing all five GeoPRISMS focus sites to encourage novel collaborations. To facilitate synthesizing research results and address data legacy targets, all participants will be required to make their GeoPRISMS datasets open-access and provide a doi indicating their location; these will be cataloged and shared. The workshop organizers will employ specialized video services from Montana State University to create ~ 1 minute outreach videos that capture scientific discoveries of the GeoPRISMS program; these and the keynote talks will be made available on YouTube.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Advancing understanding of plate tectonic theory hinges on investigations of tectonic processes acting at both convergent and divergent plate boundaries. Together, these plate boundaries primarily balance Earth’s rock cycle and shape our planet. The workshop aims to bring a group of scientists together to highlight discoveries determined through NSF GeoPRISMS funded projects encompassing both the Rift Initiation and Evolution (RIE) and Subduction Cycles and Deformation (SCD) initiatives. The workshop will primarily tackle three outstanding questions associated with plate boundary structure and deformation processes: (1) What are the relationships between fault zone rheology and deformation and how are they constrained across a range of temporal and spatial scales in the field and lab? (2) How does the rheology of the crust and mantle influence and/or record deformation at plate boundaries? (3) What feedbacks exist between larger scale lithospheric processes, fault zone rheology, and surface processes? The workshop will facilitate interdisciplinary interactions that cross-cut research expertise (e.g. geochemistry, geology, geodynamics, seismology, geodesy, EM, etc.) and study locations (i.e. encompassing all GeoPRISMS focus sites) to address questions pertaining to fundamental tectonic processes and motivate future research collaborations by encouraging active participation from all participants.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/28/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/28/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2025668</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Helen</FirstName>
<LastName>Janiszewski</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Helen A Janiszewski</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[hajanisz@hawaii.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000822437</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/28/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Hawaii</Name>
<CityName>HONOLULU</CityName>
<ZipCode>968222247</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8089567800</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2425 CAMPUS RD SINCLAIR RM 1</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Hawaii</StateName>
<StateCode>HI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>HI01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NSCKLFSSABF2</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF HAWAII</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Hawaii]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>HI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>968222234</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Hawaii</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>HI01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1620</Code>
<Text>Marine Geology and Geophysics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8076</Code>
<Text>GeoPRISMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~64916</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="Default"><span lang="haw">The primary goal of the project </span><span>was</span><span lang="haw">&nbsp;to hold a two-day Plate Boundary Structure and Deformation Workshop at the University of Hawai&#699;i at M&#257;noa from March 17-18, 2022, with a half day early career session held on March 16. </span><span>We brought 66 scientists to Honolulu to participate at our 2.5 day workshop focusing on scientific </span><span lang="haw">discoveries determined through NSF GeoPRISMS funded projects encompassing both the Rift Initiation and Evolution (RIE) and Subduction Cycles and Deformation (SCD) initiatives</span><span> (an additional 33 registered for a zoom webinar). There were 11 keynote talks (three focused on community science initiatives, and eight research talks), 50 poster presentations, an interdisciplinary networking session, sessions on FAIR data practices and fostering DEI initiatives in research, and three breakout discussion sessions. The early career half-day meeting additionally included a mentoring session, and a session on preparing NSF proposals. The theme of the workshop was to </span><span lang="haw">provide a forum for interdisciplinary discussion that crosscut GeoPRISMS focus sites. Specific topics of interest include</span><span>d</span><span lang="haw"> the role of crustal and mantle rheology in influencing or recording deformation, fault zone rheology and slip behavior, and relationships between tectonic deformation and surface processes.</span>&nbsp;</p> <p class="Default"><span>Nearly 75% of in-person attendees were early career scientists (graduate students, postdocs, or early career faculty/researchers) and almost half of attendees self-identified as part of an underrepresented group in the earth sciences. In response to a question about the most valuable aspects of the workshop in a post-workshop survey, common themes included opportunities for networking and mentoring, fostering a sense of a diverse and inclusive solid earth science research community, and the opportunity to learn about a variety of interdisciplinary research topics. Keynote talks were recorded and made available via a YouTube playlist as well as through the workshop?s website as a legacy product. In addition, four short (&lt; 5 minutes) videos highlighting GeoPRISMS scientists, their research, and their career pathways were produced. This effort was led by two science filmmaking graduate students from Montana State University. Each video interviewed one conference attendee whose career was significantly shaped by the GeoPRISMS program. These videos are publicly accessible on YouTube, and available through the workshop website.</span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/22/2023<br>      Modified by: Helen&nbsp;A&nbsp;Janiszewski</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2025668/2025668_10690258_1674442931026_ScreenShot2023-01-22at4.58.37PM--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2025668/2025668_10690258_1674442931026_ScreenShot2023-01-22at4.58.37PM--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Workshop Participants Group Photo"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2025668/2025668_10690258_1674442931026_ScreenShot2023-01-22at4.58.37PM--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Workshop Participants Group Photo"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Group photo from the workshop at UH Manoa.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Ashley Lobao and Leif Everson</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Helen&nbsp;A&nbsp;Janiszewski</div> <div class="imageTitle">Workshop Participants Group Photo</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[The primary goal of the project was to hold a two-day Plate Boundary Structure and Deformation Workshop at the University of Hawai&#699;i at M&#257;noa from March 17-18, 2022, with a half day early career session held on March 16. We brought 66 scientists to Honolulu to participate at our 2.5 day workshop focusing on scientific discoveries determined through NSF GeoPRISMS funded projects encompassing both the Rift Initiation and Evolution (RIE) and Subduction Cycles and Deformation (SCD) initiatives (an additional 33 registered for a zoom webinar). There were 11 keynote talks (three focused on community science initiatives, and eight research talks), 50 poster presentations, an interdisciplinary networking session, sessions on FAIR data practices and fostering DEI initiatives in research, and three breakout discussion sessions. The early career half-day meeting additionally included a mentoring session, and a session on preparing NSF proposals. The theme of the workshop was to provide a forum for interdisciplinary discussion that crosscut GeoPRISMS focus sites. Specific topics of interest included the role of crustal and mantle rheology in influencing or recording deformation, fault zone rheology and slip behavior, and relationships between tectonic deformation and surface processes.  Nearly 75% of in-person attendees were early career scientists (graduate students, postdocs, or early career faculty/researchers) and almost half of attendees self-identified as part of an underrepresented group in the earth sciences. In response to a question about the most valuable aspects of the workshop in a post-workshop survey, common themes included opportunities for networking and mentoring, fostering a sense of a diverse and inclusive solid earth science research community, and the opportunity to learn about a variety of interdisciplinary research topics. Keynote talks were recorded and made available via a YouTube playlist as well as through the workshop?s website as a legacy product. In addition, four short (&lt; 5 minutes) videos highlighting GeoPRISMS scientists, their research, and their career pathways were produced. This effort was led by two science filmmaking graduate students from Montana State University. Each video interviewed one conference attendee whose career was significantly shaped by the GeoPRISMS program. These videos are publicly accessible on YouTube, and available through the workshop website.       Last Modified: 01/22/2023       Submitted by: Helen A Janiszewski]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
