<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Doctoral Dissertation Research: Global Financial Market Practices in Urban Resilience Planning]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>18000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>18000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jeffrey Mantz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jmantz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927783</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This project investigates how changing financial market practices associated with environmental variability risks impact cities and those who live in them. The research will make significant contributions to an understanding of the financial drivers that shape how cities respond to a changing environment. The work will enhance knowledge of the impact of unaffordable flood insurance, property devaluation, and governmental management in cities impacted by these increased environmental risks. Understanding the impact of these changing practices on urban life is critical for creating equitable and effective urban governance. Findings from this project will be disseminated in open-access articles for public use and the project will support the training of doctoral student. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research uses an integration of expert interviews, ethnographic observation, and documentary analysis to examine the role of changing financial market practices in urban resilience planning. The research will be conducted in coastal cities that are already experiencing the effects of a changing environment and that have put into place resilience bonds. Specific research questions that the investigators will answer include: (1) What kind of problem(s) does environmental variability pose to key financial market actors, and how do they address these problems in their practices?; (2) How do these practices inform governmental action on resilience?; and (3) How might market-driven action impact residents’ ability to make financial claims in the future? This project offers a novel perspective on two increasingly pervasive contemporary problems that face societies around the world: how to finance urban resilience, and how changing risk rating practices create urban inequalities and uneven social and environmental outcomes.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/16/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/16/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2025990</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Stephen</FirstName>
<LastName>Collier</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Stephen J Collier</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[stephenjcollier@berkeley.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000056211</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/16/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Savannah</FirstName>
<LastName>Cox</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Savannah Cox</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[savannah.cox@berkeley.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000822555</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/16/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Berkeley</Name>
<CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
<ZipCode>947101749</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5106433891</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1608 4TH ST STE 201</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>GS3YEVSS12N6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>NUDGYLBB4S99</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Berkeley]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>947201750</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8857</Code>
<Text>Geography &amp; Spatial Sci-DDRI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1352</Code>
<Text>GEOGRAPHY AND SPATIAL SCIENCES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~18000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project investigated how changing financial market practices on climate risk are beginning to impact cities and those who live in them. We conducted this investigation through a 15-month case study of the Miami Forever Bond, a first-of-its-kind general obligation bond meant to pay for a first round of climate-resilient infrastructure projects in the highly climate vulnerable city of Miami, Florida. We selected the Forever Bond for analysis because it brings the practices of global market actors (such as bond rating agencies, investors, and insurers) into relation with local political and environmental concerns (such as housing affordability, flooding, and sea level rise). We hypothesized the following: first, that changing financial practices on climate risk would greatly inform the ways that Miami officials acted on these risks through resilient infrastructure investment. Second, that these investments in resilient infrastructure would become a site of immense political contestation over Miami&rsquo;s future and who has the authority to shape it.&nbsp;</p> <p>Following 53 expert interviews, 65 hours of participant observation, and analysis of over 100 relevant documents, we found the following: first, that changing market practices on climate risk did help frame the ways that Miami officials valued resilient infrastructure investment. In public and private settings, experts couched the value of the Forever Bond in terms of saving on flood insurance premiums, retaining property values, and keeping bond ratings high. As one official told us, the Forever Bond and the resilient infrastructure projects it paid for served as a &ldquo;confidence tool:&rdquo; one way among others that city officials could reassure those with investment interests in Miami that the city is taking appropriate steps to address its climate vulnerability. That this official and many others couched the value of a resilience bond in terms of confidence leads us to another project finding. Since financial actors like rating agencies and investors are only beginning to wrap their minds around the risks that climate change poses to their bottom lines, a city&rsquo;s resilience or vulnerability to climate change is&mdash;at least for now&mdash;an object of negotiation. Contra a scholarly literature which would suggest that extra-local actors like these simply dictate the terms and behavior of city governments, we found that climate change presented novel opportunities for city officials to help set such terms, challenging the conventional wisdom on how investment markets and urban infrastructure work.&nbsp;</p> <p>The issue of climate change, and how to build resilience toward it, also presented novel opportunities for Miami residents to contest existing inequalities within the city. Here, too, we found a similar logic at work. Because there are significant uncertainties regarding the concrete forms and temporalities of resilience, and because resilience has so many competing definitions, local climate justice activists were able to suggest building resilient infrastructure entails the construction of affordable housing and the reform of local decision-making processes: specifically, giving long-marginalized residents the ability to oversee and weigh in on how and where bond dollars are spent. Importantly, because the Forever Bond establishes a route along which local politics can travel to the desks of rating agency analysts (through the rating process), we also observed the ways in which activist understandings of resilient infrastructure became valuable in the eyes of rating agencies. Indeed, affordable housing provision was one reason that rating agency&rsquo;s decided to improve Miami&rsquo;s bond rating after the passage of the Miami Forever Bond.</p> <p>Taken together, the project findings push geographic scholarship on financialization and urban governance in new directions. Where these literatures would anticipate finance-driven adaptation as evacuating politics, we showed how finance-driven adaptation has become a battleground regarding the physical forms, features, and temporalities of the resilient city. We also showed how activists have attached significant sums of bond money to anti-displacement measures, which these literatures would not anticipate. Project outcomes include the following: 3 peer-reviewed journal articles, one chapter in an edited volume, 4 conference presentations, and 1 successful grant proposal to build on project findings.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/01/2022<br>      Modified by: Savannah&nbsp;Cox</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project investigated how changing financial market practices on climate risk are beginning to impact cities and those who live in them. We conducted this investigation through a 15-month case study of the Miami Forever Bond, a first-of-its-kind general obligation bond meant to pay for a first round of climate-resilient infrastructure projects in the highly climate vulnerable city of Miami, Florida. We selected the Forever Bond for analysis because it brings the practices of global market actors (such as bond rating agencies, investors, and insurers) into relation with local political and environmental concerns (such as housing affordability, flooding, and sea level rise). We hypothesized the following: first, that changing financial practices on climate risk would greatly inform the ways that Miami officials acted on these risks through resilient infrastructure investment. Second, that these investments in resilient infrastructure would become a site of immense political contestation over Miami’s future and who has the authority to shape it.   Following 53 expert interviews, 65 hours of participant observation, and analysis of over 100 relevant documents, we found the following: first, that changing market practices on climate risk did help frame the ways that Miami officials valued resilient infrastructure investment. In public and private settings, experts couched the value of the Forever Bond in terms of saving on flood insurance premiums, retaining property values, and keeping bond ratings high. As one official told us, the Forever Bond and the resilient infrastructure projects it paid for served as a "confidence tool:" one way among others that city officials could reassure those with investment interests in Miami that the city is taking appropriate steps to address its climate vulnerability. That this official and many others couched the value of a resilience bond in terms of confidence leads us to another project finding. Since financial actors like rating agencies and investors are only beginning to wrap their minds around the risks that climate change poses to their bottom lines, a city’s resilience or vulnerability to climate change is&mdash;at least for now&mdash;an object of negotiation. Contra a scholarly literature which would suggest that extra-local actors like these simply dictate the terms and behavior of city governments, we found that climate change presented novel opportunities for city officials to help set such terms, challenging the conventional wisdom on how investment markets and urban infrastructure work.   The issue of climate change, and how to build resilience toward it, also presented novel opportunities for Miami residents to contest existing inequalities within the city. Here, too, we found a similar logic at work. Because there are significant uncertainties regarding the concrete forms and temporalities of resilience, and because resilience has so many competing definitions, local climate justice activists were able to suggest building resilient infrastructure entails the construction of affordable housing and the reform of local decision-making processes: specifically, giving long-marginalized residents the ability to oversee and weigh in on how and where bond dollars are spent. Importantly, because the Forever Bond establishes a route along which local politics can travel to the desks of rating agency analysts (through the rating process), we also observed the ways in which activist understandings of resilient infrastructure became valuable in the eyes of rating agencies. Indeed, affordable housing provision was one reason that rating agency’s decided to improve Miami’s bond rating after the passage of the Miami Forever Bond.  Taken together, the project findings push geographic scholarship on financialization and urban governance in new directions. Where these literatures would anticipate finance-driven adaptation as evacuating politics, we showed how finance-driven adaptation has become a battleground regarding the physical forms, features, and temporalities of the resilient city. We also showed how activists have attached significant sums of bond money to anti-displacement measures, which these literatures would not anticipate. Project outcomes include the following: 3 peer-reviewed journal articles, one chapter in an edited volume, 4 conference presentations, and 1 successful grant proposal to build on project findings.          Last Modified: 06/01/2022       Submitted by: Savannah Cox]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
