<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Masking Agents to Promote Ingestion of Organic Pest Ant Bait]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>11/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>210876.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>210876</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Erik Pierstorff</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>epiersto@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922165</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research Phase I project is the development of an environmentally neutral product for control of red imported fire ants (RIFA), aggressive pests that occur in high densities and are specialists of urban, rural, and agricultural habitats, particularly in southern states. The RIFA affects many economic sectors and cause billions of dollars in damage and control costs annually. Their large numbers and potent sting disrupt the quality of life for millions of Americans and 5-10% of these may develop hypersensitivity to their venom, creating significant medical costs. The RIFA reproductive system lead to rapid re-infestation of treated areas; therefore, continuous use of control measures is required, with associated environmental risk. This project will enable commercialization of a new bait that is environmentally neutral and cost competitive. It will be the first new active ingredient for RIFA control in 20 years. Our novel application of masking agents for RIFA control is expected to have a general impact on the discovery of new pest control active ingredients. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This SBIR Phase I project will advance the translation of novel active ingredients for effective RIFA pest mitigation. Prior testing has indicated that additives are needed for this type of pesticide. This project will test additives and optimize formulations for field use  of the new ingredients.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/01/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/25/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041, 47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2025718</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Satya</FirstName>
<LastName>Chinta</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Satya P Chinta</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[chintasatya@gmail.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000820657</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/01/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Foresight Science &amp; Technology Incorporated</Name>
<CityName>HOPKINTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>017481889</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4012734844</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>34 HAYDEN ROWE ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[STE 156]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>GHG2Z3MBLGL6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>FORESIGHT SCIENCE &amp; TECHNOLOGY INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Foresight Science & Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>Gainsville</CityName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>326081067</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1600 SW 23rd Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8038</Code>
<Text>Biotechnology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~210876</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Project Outcomes Report &ndash; NSF Award#&nbsp;2025718</p> <p>Project Title:&nbsp;Masking Agents to Promote Ingestion of Organic Pest Ant Bait</p> <p>Recipient Organization: FORESIGHT SCIENCE &amp; TECHNOLOGY, INC.</p> <p>Grant Period:&nbsp;09/01/2020&ndash;&nbsp;01/31/2023</p> <p>PI:&nbsp;Satya P. Chinta</p> <p>This NSF Phase I project focused on novel bait formulations to control red imported fire ants (RIFA). Prior research discovered novel active ingredients (AIs) for fire ant control that successfully caused mortality of RIFA colony workers and their queen under laboratory conditions.&nbsp;&nbsp;However, it was clear in field trials that foraging worker ants would not ingest the bait due to taste aversion. The main objective of this project was to overcome the negative &ldquo;taste&rdquo; of the AI to RIFA in the field using taste masking agents that are widely used in human and animal medications.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Several techniques for masking the aversive taste of the AIs were evaluated, including taste masking flavors, e.g., fruit juices, sweeteners (nectars); and phagostimulants (oils, non-dairy milks substitutes).&nbsp;These techniques represent the simplest approach to taste masking, especially in the case of liquid formulations. However, this approach was not successful, since field ants rejected the material provided.&nbsp;Therefore, our focus shifted to a class of complex entrapment agents that are currently used as taste masking agents in the pharmaceutical industry but have not been utilized as adjuvants for insect control.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Experimental results treating fresh from the field queen right (QR) colonies containing up to 20k workers, brood and queen with AI in taste masking agent (&alpha;-cyclodextrin) resulted in about 65% worker mortality and the death of all 3 colony queens. Queen deaths occurred&nbsp;&nbsp;during the 6<sup>th</sup>&nbsp;- 7<sup>th</sup>&nbsp;week of feeding which shows the acceptance of the AI and also that the masking agent does not interfere with feeding or queen mortality. The control colony remained healthy with the queen surviving the duration of the experiment. These results support movement of this technology to experiments with larger field collected QR RIFA colonies (80-100k workers), and ultimately field experiments.&nbsp;Preliminary and follow-up research for the first time demonstrated the potential of this novel taste masking approach to overcome the taste sensitivity of a pest insect.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The&nbsp;research establishes proof of concept for the use of&nbsp;taste masking agents used in human and animal medications&nbsp;to mask the negative taste of the new AIs.&nbsp;Our objective for the NSF SBIR Phase 2 period is to apply and expand on the knowledge of the pharmaceutical ingredients in overcoming adverse tasting drugs to control RIFA (including sub species) in laboratory and then followed in the field. The use of taste masking agents for insect control and for RIFA control specifically represents new intellectual property. Standard procedures in screening for new insect toxicants dictate that compounds rejected by the target pest are eliminated from further evaluations. Thus, our proposal is unique, and success will provide a new paradigm for active ingredient screening in general.&nbsp;Practically, this will&nbsp;enable field evaluations with the goal of establishing this approach as a platform technology for a broader range of pest ant control products.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/03/2023<br>      Modified by: Satya&nbsp;P&nbsp;Chinta</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Project Outcomes Report &ndash; NSF Award# 2025718  Project Title: Masking Agents to Promote Ingestion of Organic Pest Ant Bait  Recipient Organization: FORESIGHT SCIENCE &amp; TECHNOLOGY, INC.  Grant Period: 09/01/2020&ndash; 01/31/2023  PI: Satya P. Chinta  This NSF Phase I project focused on novel bait formulations to control red imported fire ants (RIFA). Prior research discovered novel active ingredients (AIs) for fire ant control that successfully caused mortality of RIFA colony workers and their queen under laboratory conditions.  However, it was clear in field trials that foraging worker ants would not ingest the bait due to taste aversion. The main objective of this project was to overcome the negative "taste" of the AI to RIFA in the field using taste masking agents that are widely used in human and animal medications.     Several techniques for masking the aversive taste of the AIs were evaluated, including taste masking flavors, e.g., fruit juices, sweeteners (nectars); and phagostimulants (oils, non-dairy milks substitutes). These techniques represent the simplest approach to taste masking, especially in the case of liquid formulations. However, this approach was not successful, since field ants rejected the material provided. Therefore, our focus shifted to a class of complex entrapment agents that are currently used as taste masking agents in the pharmaceutical industry but have not been utilized as adjuvants for insect control.      Experimental results treating fresh from the field queen right (QR) colonies containing up to 20k workers, brood and queen with AI in taste masking agent (&alpha;-cyclodextrin) resulted in about 65% worker mortality and the death of all 3 colony queens. Queen deaths occurred  during the 6th - 7th week of feeding which shows the acceptance of the AI and also that the masking agent does not interfere with feeding or queen mortality. The control colony remained healthy with the queen surviving the duration of the experiment. These results support movement of this technology to experiments with larger field collected QR RIFA colonies (80-100k workers), and ultimately field experiments. Preliminary and follow-up research for the first time demonstrated the potential of this novel taste masking approach to overcome the taste sensitivity of a pest insect.      The research establishes proof of concept for the use of taste masking agents used in human and animal medications to mask the negative taste of the new AIs. Our objective for the NSF SBIR Phase 2 period is to apply and expand on the knowledge of the pharmaceutical ingredients in overcoming adverse tasting drugs to control RIFA (including sub species) in laboratory and then followed in the field. The use of taste masking agents for insect control and for RIFA control specifically represents new intellectual property. Standard procedures in screening for new insect toxicants dictate that compounds rejected by the target pest are eliminated from further evaluations. Thus, our proposal is unique, and success will provide a new paradigm for active ingredient screening in general. Practically, this will enable field evaluations with the goal of establishing this approach as a platform technology for a broader range of pest ant control products.             Last Modified: 02/03/2023       Submitted by: Satya P Chinta]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
