<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase II:  Innovative software and database tools for targeted genomics]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>999594.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>999594</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Cooperative Agreement</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Erik Pierstorff</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>epiersto@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922165</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase II project is to rectify long-standing issues impeding the promise of genomic data to revolutionize human biomedicine and animal health. The genomic services industry is projected to reach $2.7 billion by 2024 (CAGR 16%) in the USA. The proposed project is a cloud-based platform consisting of a database and a suite of software analytical tools to enable rapid and accurate assessment of the impact of gene variants on biological function or trait, as well as disease. This will enable researchers to advance treatment across a broad spectrum of issues within human biomedicine, such as cancer; diabetes; neurological, cardiac, and developmental diseases, and many others. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This SBIR Phase II project will address long-standing deficiencies in research challenges leading to higher costs, prolonged delays, and failure to advance scientific discovery.  The technical objectives of the SBIR Phase II project include: 1) extend methods to generate, validate, and annotate high-quality DNA sequence data for a precisely organized central database; 2) assemble and implement software content, unique supplemental databases and powerful applications for the end user; 3) engineer the software, architecture and performance of the cloud platform for optimal ease of use and accessibility for the end user.  The solution will transform current applications in targeted genomics through the rapid, accurate assessment of the impact of gene variants on biological function, phenotypic trait or disease.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/16/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/16/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>CoopAgrmnt</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2025936</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jill</FirstName>
<LastName>Pecon-Slattery</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jill Pecon-Slattery</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jill@cornerstonegenomics.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000780390</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/16/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>CORNERSTONE GENOMICS LLC</Name>
<CityName>SHARPSBURG</CityName>
<ZipCode>217821611</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2405665160</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>17590 MILLERS SAWMILL RD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MD06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>SJF6KT88CZX8</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CORNERSTONE GENOMICS INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[CORNERSTONE GENOMICS LLC]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>217821611</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MD06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5373</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase II</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1718</Code>
<Text>BIOINFORMATICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~999594</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p style="text-align: left;"><span style="white-space: pre;"> </span>Supported by the NSF SBIR Phase II award, Cornerstone Genomics Inc successfully developed a unique cloud SaaS platform for genomic researchers consisting of novel databases and analytical software accessed by the user through subscription plans. &nbsp;The product CodeXome transforms targeted genomics, offering unprecedented speed and accuracy for interpreting the impact of gene variants on biological function, phenotypic trait or disease from the millions of neutral mutations that recur over time.&nbsp;<br /><span style="white-space: pre;"> </span>CodeXome overcomes longstanding delays in finding those specific gene alterations that cause changes in biology or inherited diseases. &nbsp;The key databases driving CodeXome innovation are composed of proprietary sequences of ~20,000 genes we share with our extended primate family of Great Apes, Old World Monkeys, New World Monkeys, tarsiers, lemurs, lorises, and bushbabies. &nbsp;Organized and anchored to the human genome, the databases describe natural changes permitted by each gene to maintain normal function; and how these patterns recur over 80 million years of time. &nbsp;Researchers can upload their data, and cross reference with our databases to precisely identify those genetic changes unique to their project. What used to take researchers months, maybe years, can now be done in a matter of minutes.<br /><span style="white-space: pre;"> </span>The larger societal significance is that CodeXome unites formerly disparate fields of human biomedicine and wildlife biodiversity to expand frontiers of scientific exploration. &nbsp;CodeXome is a flexible, intuitive SaaS, offering genome researchers a new dimension to accelerate speed to discovery. Although broad in its scope of potential applications, CodeXome provides exceptional clarity in disease diagnostics and as a foundational resource for precision medicine R&amp;D. &nbsp;Notably, over 50% of the primate lineages present in our study are listed as endangered by the IUCN. &nbsp;Thus, CodeXome is not limited to providing information crucial to human biomedicine, but also offers unprecedented resources for researchers seeking genomic solutions to preserve primate biodiversity, enable conservation management plans, and ensure the health and survival of both wild and managed populations.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/06/2023<br>      Modified by: Jill&nbsp;Pecon-Slattery</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Supported by the NSF SBIR Phase II award, Cornerstone Genomics Inc successfully developed a unique cloud SaaS platform for genomic researchers consisting of novel databases and analytical software accessed by the user through subscription plans.  The product CodeXome transforms targeted genomics, offering unprecedented speed and accuracy for interpreting the impact of gene variants on biological function, phenotypic trait or disease from the millions of neutral mutations that recur over time.   CodeXome overcomes longstanding delays in finding those specific gene alterations that cause changes in biology or inherited diseases.  The key databases driving CodeXome innovation are composed of proprietary sequences of ~20,000 genes we share with our extended primate family of Great Apes, Old World Monkeys, New World Monkeys, tarsiers, lemurs, lorises, and bushbabies.  Organized and anchored to the human genome, the databases describe natural changes permitted by each gene to maintain normal function; and how these patterns recur over 80 million years of time.  Researchers can upload their data, and cross reference with our databases to precisely identify those genetic changes unique to their project. What used to take researchers months, maybe years, can now be done in a matter of minutes.  The larger societal significance is that CodeXome unites formerly disparate fields of human biomedicine and wildlife biodiversity to expand frontiers of scientific exploration.  CodeXome is a flexible, intuitive SaaS, offering genome researchers a new dimension to accelerate speed to discovery. Although broad in its scope of potential applications, CodeXome provides exceptional clarity in disease diagnostics and as a foundational resource for precision medicine R&amp;D.  Notably, over 50% of the primate lineages present in our study are listed as endangered by the IUCN.  Thus, CodeXome is not limited to providing information crucial to human biomedicine, but also offers unprecedented resources for researchers seeking genomic solutions to preserve primate biodiversity, enable conservation management plans, and ensure the health and survival of both wild and managed populations.             Last Modified: 08/06/2023       Submitted by: Jill Pecon-Slattery]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
