<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[FW-HTF-P: Redesigning the Future of Construction Work by Replicating the Master-Apprentice Learning Model in Human-Robot Worker Teams]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>250000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>250000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Alexandra Medina-Borja</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>amedinab@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927557</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The construction industry could benefit significantly from increased productivity, use of modern work processes, improved relationships among stakeholders, and increased attention to safety and health issues of construction workers. In the absence of these improvements, a chronic shortage of skilled construction workers has developed, largely due to a retiring workforce and the reluctance of younger generations or people of different abilities to pursue such careers. More recently, the outbreak of the COVID-19 pandemic has caused serious economic difficulties and schedule delays on construction projects, since it is hard to maintain social-distancing on construction sites. These impacts further emphasize the need for construction techniques that can allow workers to perform tasks remotely, decreasing the number of on-site workers at any one time to ensure worker health and safety. This planning grant will support investigation of the potential of human-robot teams to transform future construction work and the profile of future construction workers.  It is expected that such changes would result in new career opportunities and significant benefits to the industry. The project team envisions that human workers will use technology to teach co-robots to perform construction work tasks remotely, resulting in symbiotic human-robot teams that can be widely deployed in the construction industry. This approach parallels the classical Master-Apprentice vocational model prevalent in today’s construction industry.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The overarching goal of this research planning grant is to explore the feasibility and potential of a human-robot team through engagement with a range of stakeholders. The proposed activities for this planning project include: 1) Fact-finding surveys distributed to representatives of construction firms, current construction workers, and potential future construction workers (high school students); 2) Technology pilot presentation and feedback from representatives of construction firms and workers; and 3) A comprehensive research program development workshop with expert stakeholder participants from academia and industry. These activities will allow the research team to set the foundation for developing a convergent research agenda that reshapes the future of construction work into a human-robot partnership that supports a self-sustaining cycle of lifelong learning, knowledge-transfer, and effective teamwork. Ultimately, the results of this project will inform the opportunities and challenges of incorporating co-robots on construction sites without replacing the current workforce or adversely impacting the construction work process. The success of this planning grant will pave the way for a significant research effort that takes a human-centered approach toward the future of construction work and ensures that it improves accessibility, quality of life, productivity, and job satisfaction. The PIs will recruit a diverse group of students and partners from industry and academia and pursue broad dissemination of the research findings in academic and industry venues.  This project has been funded by the Future of Work at the Human-Technology Frontier cross-directorate program to advance design of intelligent work technologies that operate in harmony with human workers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/12/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/26/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2025805</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Joyce</FirstName>
<LastName>Chai</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>Y</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Joyce Y Chai</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[chaijy@umich.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000477137</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/12/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Vineet</FirstName>
<LastName>Kamat</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Vineet R Kamat</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[vkamat@umich.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000244987</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/12/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Carol</FirstName>
<LastName>Menassa</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Carol C Menassa</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[menassa@umich.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000545592</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/12/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Honglak</FirstName>
<LastName>Lee</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Honglak Lee</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[honglak@eecs.umich.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000583664</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/12/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Xi Jessie</FirstName>
<LastName>Yang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Xi Jessie Yang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[xijyang@umich.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000754053</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/12/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Regents of the University of Michigan - Ann Arbor</Name>
<CityName>ANN ARBOR</CityName>
<ZipCode>481091079</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1109 GEDDES AVE, SUITE 3300</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>GNJ7BBP73WE9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MICHIGAN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Universiy of Michigan]]></Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>481092125</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2350 Hayward Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>103Y</Code>
<Text>FW-HTF Futr Wrk Hum-Tech Frntr</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>063Z</Code>
<Text>FW-HTF Futr Wrk Hum-Tech Frntr</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~250000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The construction industry is ill-famed for its stagnant productivity, use of antiquated work processes, adversarial relationships among stakeholders, and safety and health issues among construction workers. Over time, this has led to a chronic shortage of skilled workers, largely due to an aging and retiring workforce and the reluctance of younger generations or people of different abilities to pursue such careers. This FW-HTF planning grant has engaged with industry and academic partners to investigate whether intelligent human-robot teams have the potential to transform future construction work and the profile of future construction workers resulting in new career opportunities and significant benefits to the industry.</p> <p>The overarching goal of this research planning grant is to explore the feasibility and potential of the outlined vision through engagement with a wide range of stakeholders. The activities undertaken as part of this planning project include: 1) Engagement with academic and industry stakeholders; 2) Construction Worker Survey where we used technology adoption model (TAM) and innovation diffusion theory (IDT) to develop a survey, collect data and develop models to help us better understand the main factors affecting construction worker adoption of human robot collaboration in the industry; 3) Construction Industry Workshop that was conducted charrette style to solicit input from key industry participants on their vision for construction work in 2035; and 4) Detailed review of literature on human-robot collaboration in construction and proposal of a taxonomy that can guide future research initiatives in this area. The main outcomes from each of these activities are summarized below:</p> <p><strong>Construction Worker Survey:</strong>&nbsp;This study proposed an extended TAM&nbsp; with concepts from the IDT and variables about quality of life, aiming to examine factors that affect construction workers&rsquo; behavioral intention (BI) to work in the HRC system. The proposed model verified the effect of Perceived Usefulness (PU) and Perceived Ease of Use (PEU) on BI. The effects of relative advantage (RA), complexity, trialability, and observability of the technology were also important factors. Perceived Effect on Quality of Life (PEQL) had no significant impact on BI, but was found to be influenced by PU.</p> <p>This study contributes to understanding acceptance theories of new technologies in the construction industry by providing empirical evidence. The identified key factors can guide construction companies to develop strategies for workers&rsquo; HRC acceptance.</p> <p><strong>Industry Workshop:</strong> A total of 30 participants atteneded the workshop. The five top benefits for using HRC cited by the participants were enhanced productivity, increased efficiency, improved safety, health, and job opportunities. The top five identified obstacles included technology infancy, inaccuracy, safety risks, low technology, and threats to job security.</p> <p>The workshop discussion started with an emphasis that workers are not afraid of robots as &lsquo;competition&rsquo; as long as the robots have the ability to be useful in assisting people in doing their jobs and robots can improve the safety of construction jobs and make the workers&rsquo; tasks less physically strenuous.</p> <p>All participants acknowledged that research in this area is invaluable. The more we discuss the ways that we envision robots being used in construction, the better we will be at adopting their place in the industry.</p> <p>Upskilling the current workforce is key to integrating robots into daily use on construction sites. Unions and contractors will play a significant role in assisting their long-time members and employees to become comfortable with the technology through training and incentives to learn new technology.</p> <p>Also, there was a focus on how the technology may be used to attract young people into the industry with the promise of operating cutting-edge robotic technology versus performing strenuous manual labor. An eventual goal is to make jobs in the construction industry more accessible to traditionally underrepresented groups of people for whom construction work is currently difficult or inaccessible.</p> <p><strong>3) Taxonomy of Human-Robot Collaboration in Construction:</strong>&nbsp; A taxonomy of collaborative human-robot construction teams is proposed to characterize the existing human-robot collaboration methods in construction by the level of robot autonomy (LoRA) and the human effort in sensing, planning, and acting. We proposed a condensed taxonomy of six distinct groups: Manual, Pre-Programming, Adaptive Manipulation, Imitation Learning, Improvisatory Control, and Full Autonomy, to adequately classify construction work performed by human-robot teams.</p> <p>These activities allowed the research team to set the foundation for developing a convergent research agenda that reshapes the future of construction work into a human-robot partnership that supports a self-sustaining cycle of lifelong learning, knowledge-transfer, and effective teamwork. This planning grant has paved the way for a significant research effort that takes a human-centered approach towards the future of construction work and ensures that it improves accessibility, quality of life, productivity, and job satisfaction. The PIs recruited a diverse group of students and partners from industry and academia and continue to pursue broad dissemination of the research findings in academic and industry venues.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/02/2022<br>      Modified by: Carol&nbsp;C&nbsp;Menassa</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The construction industry is ill-famed for its stagnant productivity, use of antiquated work processes, adversarial relationships among stakeholders, and safety and health issues among construction workers. Over time, this has led to a chronic shortage of skilled workers, largely due to an aging and retiring workforce and the reluctance of younger generations or people of different abilities to pursue such careers. This FW-HTF planning grant has engaged with industry and academic partners to investigate whether intelligent human-robot teams have the potential to transform future construction work and the profile of future construction workers resulting in new career opportunities and significant benefits to the industry.  The overarching goal of this research planning grant is to explore the feasibility and potential of the outlined vision through engagement with a wide range of stakeholders. The activities undertaken as part of this planning project include: 1) Engagement with academic and industry stakeholders; 2) Construction Worker Survey where we used technology adoption model (TAM) and innovation diffusion theory (IDT) to develop a survey, collect data and develop models to help us better understand the main factors affecting construction worker adoption of human robot collaboration in the industry; 3) Construction Industry Workshop that was conducted charrette style to solicit input from key industry participants on their vision for construction work in 2035; and 4) Detailed review of literature on human-robot collaboration in construction and proposal of a taxonomy that can guide future research initiatives in this area. The main outcomes from each of these activities are summarized below:  Construction Worker Survey: This study proposed an extended TAM  with concepts from the IDT and variables about quality of life, aiming to examine factors that affect construction workers’ behavioral intention (BI) to work in the HRC system. The proposed model verified the effect of Perceived Usefulness (PU) and Perceived Ease of Use (PEU) on BI. The effects of relative advantage (RA), complexity, trialability, and observability of the technology were also important factors. Perceived Effect on Quality of Life (PEQL) had no significant impact on BI, but was found to be influenced by PU.  This study contributes to understanding acceptance theories of new technologies in the construction industry by providing empirical evidence. The identified key factors can guide construction companies to develop strategies for workers’ HRC acceptance.  Industry Workshop: A total of 30 participants atteneded the workshop. The five top benefits for using HRC cited by the participants were enhanced productivity, increased efficiency, improved safety, health, and job opportunities. The top five identified obstacles included technology infancy, inaccuracy, safety risks, low technology, and threats to job security.  The workshop discussion started with an emphasis that workers are not afraid of robots as ‘competition’ as long as the robots have the ability to be useful in assisting people in doing their jobs and robots can improve the safety of construction jobs and make the workers’ tasks less physically strenuous.  All participants acknowledged that research in this area is invaluable. The more we discuss the ways that we envision robots being used in construction, the better we will be at adopting their place in the industry.  Upskilling the current workforce is key to integrating robots into daily use on construction sites. Unions and contractors will play a significant role in assisting their long-time members and employees to become comfortable with the technology through training and incentives to learn new technology.  Also, there was a focus on how the technology may be used to attract young people into the industry with the promise of operating cutting-edge robotic technology versus performing strenuous manual labor. An eventual goal is to make jobs in the construction industry more accessible to traditionally underrepresented groups of people for whom construction work is currently difficult or inaccessible.  3) Taxonomy of Human-Robot Collaboration in Construction:  A taxonomy of collaborative human-robot construction teams is proposed to characterize the existing human-robot collaboration methods in construction by the level of robot autonomy (LoRA) and the human effort in sensing, planning, and acting. We proposed a condensed taxonomy of six distinct groups: Manual, Pre-Programming, Adaptive Manipulation, Imitation Learning, Improvisatory Control, and Full Autonomy, to adequately classify construction work performed by human-robot teams.  These activities allowed the research team to set the foundation for developing a convergent research agenda that reshapes the future of construction work into a human-robot partnership that supports a self-sustaining cycle of lifelong learning, knowledge-transfer, and effective teamwork. This planning grant has paved the way for a significant research effort that takes a human-centered approach towards the future of construction work and ensures that it improves accessibility, quality of life, productivity, and job satisfaction. The PIs recruited a diverse group of students and partners from industry and academia and continue to pursue broad dissemination of the research findings in academic and industry venues.          Last Modified: 09/02/2022       Submitted by: Carol C Menassa]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
