<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Development of Safety Accessory for Improving Performance and Minimizing Complications of Manual Ventilation (COVID-19)]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>255999.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>275999</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Henry Ahn</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>hahn@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927069</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project includes improved performance and minimized complications of manual ventilation through the development of a cost-efficient and user-friendly medical device. The bag valve mask (BVM) is used during first-response and emergencies to manually deliver air to patients unable to breathe on their own. Approximately 13.1 million BVMs are used annually in the United States. Due to a lack of feedback mechanisms, providers are unable to judge their compliance with ventilation recommendations, resulting in a high incidence of life-threatening complications. In the intensive care unit, mechanical ventilators are used for safe and precise air delivery, but the quality is different.  This project prevents complications of unsafe manual ventilation, thereby improving the quality of care and providing cost savings for the health system. The project will help bridge the gap between manual and mechanical ventilation, aiding first responders in the COVID-19 pandemic. &lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project will advance the science of emergency airway management. This technology will fit into the existing treatment workflow and supply-chain while addressing the need for safer ventilation during COVID-19. Improper manual ventilation due to delivery of unsafe pressures, volume, or frequency is common and occurs regardless of a provider's training or experience. The prevalence and severity of the problem have been studied extensively, establishing the need for the device. The research and development goal is to develop a device that can achieve performance and safety closer to a ventilator. Studies include characterizing usability, performance, efficacy, and biocompatibility.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/01/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/08/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041, 47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2025203</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Prathamesh</FirstName>
<LastName>Prabhudesai</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Prathamesh P Prabhudesai</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[pprabhudesai09@gmail.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000802857</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/01/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>SAFEBVM CORP.</Name>
<CityName>CHESTERFIELD</CityName>
<ZipCode>630178445</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3149736606</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1120 WEIDMAN RD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>U5AEE4JR6QD9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SAFEBVM CORP</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[SAFEBVM CORP.]]></Name>
<CityName>CHESTERFIELD</CityName>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>630178445</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1120 WEIDMAN RD]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8091</Code>
<Text>SBIR Outreach &amp; Tech. Assist</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5345</Code>
<Text>BIOMEDICAL ENGINEERING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8038</Code>
<Text>Biotechnology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~255999</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~20000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>SafeBVM is an early-stage medical devices startup building a new standard of care for artificial ventilation and airway management of patients suffering from cardiac arrest, respiratory distress or failure, trauma, opioid overdose, and for patients undergoing procedures that require ventilatory support. For patients with inadequate breathing, the use of traditional bag valve masks resuscitators (BVM) in emergency situations and during short transports can result in expensive and life-threatening complications due to improper ventilation technique. In the U.S., about 13.1 million BVMs are used annually. Medical providers frequently deliver unsafe manual ventilation with BVMs, regardless of the qualifications and experience of the provider. Dangerously high pressures, flow rates, and volumes of air flow can result in complications such as gastric insufflation, and less frequently, aspiration pneumonia, acute lung injury (ALI), acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS), barotrauma, volutrauma, and pneumothorax. There is an urgent need for intervention to improve patient safety during manual ventilation with the resuscitator bag.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>We are developing a novel platform of safety technologies for standard BVM resuscitators that minimize dangerously high pressure, flow rates, and volumes of air flow during manual ventilation. The patented flow and pressure regulating device will ensure safe, optimal, and personalized manual ventilation based on the patient&rsquo;s lung status, preventing potentially life-threatening and costly injuries associated with unsafe manual ventilation. After FDA approval, SafeBVM&rsquo;s Sotair series will be the only emergency device that will offer both safe and personalized ventilation while minimizing gastric insufflation. Our products have the potential to greatly reduce the risk of complications caused by standard BVMs and their associated costs to the health care system.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>To address the prevalent issues with the BVM, the Sotair Series devices are designed to regulate air flow and pressure and are compatible with all standard BVMs on the market. With the built-in haptic and audiovisual feedback mechanisms, the devices require little training to use, making them appropriate for use in the National Stockpile and through FEMA. In this Phase I SBIR, we successfully demonstrated statistically significant similarity of airflow patterns generated by mechanical ventilator vs. airflow patterns generated by more than 100 providers using the Sotair Adult device with BVM on standard test lungs. We also evaluated airflow parameters in cadavers and met biocompatibility testing requirements and standards to support a submission with the U.S. Food and Drug Administration. As the only platform of technologies that will offer safe, affordable, and optimized ventilation while minimizing gastric insufflation, SafeBVM&rsquo;s product should have broad application across the entire care continuum, but especially in emergency and battlefield medicine.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/15/2022<br>      Modified by: Prathamesh&nbsp;P&nbsp;Prabhudesai</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ SafeBVM is an early-stage medical devices startup building a new standard of care for artificial ventilation and airway management of patients suffering from cardiac arrest, respiratory distress or failure, trauma, opioid overdose, and for patients undergoing procedures that require ventilatory support. For patients with inadequate breathing, the use of traditional bag valve masks resuscitators (BVM) in emergency situations and during short transports can result in expensive and life-threatening complications due to improper ventilation technique. In the U.S., about 13.1 million BVMs are used annually. Medical providers frequently deliver unsafe manual ventilation with BVMs, regardless of the qualifications and experience of the provider. Dangerously high pressures, flow rates, and volumes of air flow can result in complications such as gastric insufflation, and less frequently, aspiration pneumonia, acute lung injury (ALI), acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS), barotrauma, volutrauma, and pneumothorax. There is an urgent need for intervention to improve patient safety during manual ventilation with the resuscitator bag.     We are developing a novel platform of safety technologies for standard BVM resuscitators that minimize dangerously high pressure, flow rates, and volumes of air flow during manual ventilation. The patented flow and pressure regulating device will ensure safe, optimal, and personalized manual ventilation based on the patient’s lung status, preventing potentially life-threatening and costly injuries associated with unsafe manual ventilation. After FDA approval, SafeBVM’s Sotair series will be the only emergency device that will offer both safe and personalized ventilation while minimizing gastric insufflation. Our products have the potential to greatly reduce the risk of complications caused by standard BVMs and their associated costs to the health care system.     To address the prevalent issues with the BVM, the Sotair Series devices are designed to regulate air flow and pressure and are compatible with all standard BVMs on the market. With the built-in haptic and audiovisual feedback mechanisms, the devices require little training to use, making them appropriate for use in the National Stockpile and through FEMA. In this Phase I SBIR, we successfully demonstrated statistically significant similarity of airflow patterns generated by mechanical ventilator vs. airflow patterns generated by more than 100 providers using the Sotair Adult device with BVM on standard test lungs. We also evaluated airflow parameters in cadavers and met biocompatibility testing requirements and standards to support a submission with the U.S. Food and Drug Administration. As the only platform of technologies that will offer safe, affordable, and optimized ventilation while minimizing gastric insufflation, SafeBVM’s product should have broad application across the entire care continuum, but especially in emergency and battlefield medicine.          Last Modified: 02/15/2022       Submitted by: Prathamesh P Prabhudesai]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
