<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Symposium on Science and Technology Driving the Bioeconomy 2020]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>16000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>16000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Carole Read</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cread@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922418</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This award is partial support of the 2020 Symposium on Stakeholders Perspective on the Bioeconomy as part of the meeting of the USDA S-1075 Multistate Committee. The biobased economy has potential to produce biofuels and bioproducts in an environmentally sustainable way. This consortia of researchers from 35 land grant universities address barriers to a bioeconomy including challenges in feedstock logistics and conversion technologies.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Annual meetings of the S-1045 multistate committee are held to coordinate and share research from land grant universities across the nation. Symposiums are organized with leading researchers and speakers from funding agencies to share the latest research knowledge and coordinate future research. The 2020 S-1075 Multistate Committee annual symposium will be held at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln. The meeting is planned to occur on July 9-10, 2020. The goal of the 2020 symposium is to develop an understanding of the key challenges when trying to commercialize bioenergy and bioproduct technologies. NSF funding will be used to support graduate students to attend this symposium and to meet with member researchers from approximately 35 land grant institutions. This is a meeting where the students can interact with the entire sector of the bioeconomy including researchers, producers, processors, financial sector and government agencies. This will help in orienting the next workforce generation to challenges and opportunities in the bioeconomy. The proceedings from the symposium will be published in both hard and soft copy formats and distributed widely to interested audience by S-1045 members.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/04/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/04/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2025807</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Christopher</FirstName>
<LastName>Saffron</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Christopher M Saffron</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[saffronc@egr.msu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000589568</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/04/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
<LastName>Wilkins</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mark R Wilkins</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mwilkins3@unl.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000291980</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/04/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ajay</FirstName>
<LastName>Kumar</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ajay Kumar</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ajay.kumar@okstate.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000542176</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/04/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Michigan State University</Name>
<CityName>EAST LANSING</CityName>
<ZipCode>488242600</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5173555040</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>426 AUDITORIUM RD RM 2</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>R28EKN92ZTZ9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MICHIGAN STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>VJKZC4D1JN36</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Michigan State University]]></Name>
<CityName>East Lansing</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>488242600</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Office of Sponsored Programs]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1403</Code>
<Text>Proc Sys, Reac Eng &amp; Mol Therm</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1491</Code>
<Text>Cellular &amp; Biochem Engineering</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7643</Code>
<Text>EnvS-Environmtl Sustainability</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7644</Code>
<Text>EchemS-Electrochemical Systems</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8020</Code>
<Text>Green Engineering</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~16000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>The goal of the S1075 2022 Meeting and Symposium was to develop an understanding of the key challenges for commercializing bioenergy and bioproduct technologies.&nbsp; The objectives of this proposal were to 1) present USDA and university technology platforms and technical expertise to graduate students, while 2) these same students share their research at the symposium through poster sessions.&nbsp; This information exchange was used to further develop and coordinate the research agenda for the S-1075 committee and guide future research on biofuels and bioproducts at universities across the nation.&nbsp;&nbsp;</span>NSF support was sought specifically to support graduate students and increase their attendance at this meeting.</p> <p><span>The 2020 S1075 Symposium was postponed twice, until July 15-16 of 2022, owing to the COVID-19 pandemic.&nbsp; As both the USDA S1075 Multistate Meeting and Symposium were held, in person, in Houston, TX, the $16K NSF travel funds were awarded to graduate students who submitted research abstracts to attend the meeting.&nbsp; The request for abstracts was announced to all participating land grant universities on May 19, 2022.&nbsp; On June 17th, all 13 graduate student respondees were notified that they would receive funds to cover all or most of their travel expenses, including local transport, per diem, airfare, and lodging.&nbsp; A total of 12 students attended the Symposium on July 15-16, presenting their research posters during S1075 meeting breaks and in the evening of July 15th.&nbsp; During the poster session, faculty and graduate students from multiple Universities discussed research results extending their professional networks.&nbsp;&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span>Graduate students were provided an opportunity to present posters, in person, to University professors, graduate students from other institutions, and the USDA.&nbsp; On site and in person presentation opportunities were seldomly offered during the COVID-19 pandemic, so this Symposium was greatly needed to reconnect people from different States with one another.&nbsp; Experience presenting posters helps young researchers learn to communicate their findings.</span></p> <p><span><span>Many of the projects that the S1075 group investigates have direct application on our greater society.&nbsp; Future technologies, developed by this group, will lead to new processes that create jobs in the future bioeconomy.&nbsp; The products these processes make also provide services that consumers demand through market forces.&nbsp; As such, adoption of these technologies can have a broad societal impact through profit generation and income taxation that supports national infrastructure.&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;</span><br /></span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/23/2022<br>      Modified by: Christopher&nbsp;M&nbsp;Saffron</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The goal of the S1075 2022 Meeting and Symposium was to develop an understanding of the key challenges for commercializing bioenergy and bioproduct technologies.  The objectives of this proposal were to 1) present USDA and university technology platforms and technical expertise to graduate students, while 2) these same students share their research at the symposium through poster sessions.  This information exchange was used to further develop and coordinate the research agenda for the S-1075 committee and guide future research on biofuels and bioproducts at universities across the nation.  NSF support was sought specifically to support graduate students and increase their attendance at this meeting.  The 2020 S1075 Symposium was postponed twice, until July 15-16 of 2022, owing to the COVID-19 pandemic.  As both the USDA S1075 Multistate Meeting and Symposium were held, in person, in Houston, TX, the $16K NSF travel funds were awarded to graduate students who submitted research abstracts to attend the meeting.  The request for abstracts was announced to all participating land grant universities on May 19, 2022.  On June 17th, all 13 graduate student respondees were notified that they would receive funds to cover all or most of their travel expenses, including local transport, per diem, airfare, and lodging.  A total of 12 students attended the Symposium on July 15-16, presenting their research posters during S1075 meeting breaks and in the evening of July 15th.  During the poster session, faculty and graduate students from multiple Universities discussed research results extending their professional networks.    Graduate students were provided an opportunity to present posters, in person, to University professors, graduate students from other institutions, and the USDA.  On site and in person presentation opportunities were seldomly offered during the COVID-19 pandemic, so this Symposium was greatly needed to reconnect people from different States with one another.  Experience presenting posters helps young researchers learn to communicate their findings.  Many of the projects that the S1075 group investigates have direct application on our greater society.  Future technologies, developed by this group, will lead to new processes that create jobs in the future bioeconomy.  The products these processes make also provide services that consumers demand through market forces.  As such, adoption of these technologies can have a broad societal impact through profit generation and income taxation that supports national infrastructure.             Last Modified: 10/23/2022       Submitted by: Christopher M Saffron]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
