<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research: Understanding the Drivers of Microbial Survival and Autotrophy in a Characteristically Marine and Terrestrial Serpentinizing System–Ney’s Spring]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>208846.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>208846</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Alberto Perez-Huerta</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>aperezhu@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032920000</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Many of the microorganisms on Earth live in environments without access to sunlight and therefore lack the energy from light to power chemical reactions like photosynthesis.  These bacteria live on other types of chemical reactions that use rocks and water instead of light and produce compounds that microorganisms can live on, like hydrogen, methane, or hydrogen sulfide.  One of these interactions, known as serpentinization, occurs principally in the deep sea associated with volcanic activity and mid-ocean rifts, and it can support specialized microbial life. Many questions remain however about specific chemical reactions, diversity of the microbes and metabolic activities, and how the microbes survive in these extreme environments. This project will characterize a natural spring in Northern California, Ney’s spring, which is similar to marine serpentinzing systems, making it uniquely accessible for investigation and allows the use of monitoring techniques not possible in deep marine systems.  Experiments and measurements will be made in the spring and the laboratory to examine microbial activity and chemical environment including microscale profiling.  Laboratory cultures of microbes from the spring and spring muds will be established to understand microbial processes.  Cultivations of microbes from this environment could result in the isolation of novel bacteria and applied biotechnology. The research team will implement outreach and learning activities in local schools and community colleges that benefit a diverse group of young STEM participants.  This project is jointly funded by Earth Sciences and the Established Program to Stimulate Competitive Research (EPSCoR).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The team will approach the overarching goal of understanding microbially-mediated chemical processes that support life in this unique, ‘marine-like’ terrestrial spring by characterizing the microbial and chemical makeup of this spring, with a focus on analyses that support evidence of microbial activities that are thought to support life (utilizing inorganic compounds such as sulfide and methane). A series of field based, and lab-based experiments to support predictions of microbial activities will be performed. Cutting edge electrochemical techniques, including microelectrode profiling of spring’s chemistry, and in situ electrochemical incubations used to test for microbes that can utilize solid phase mineral as energy sources, will be used. Confirmation of microbial activities will be conducted by obtaining isolated cultivars. Significant intellectual merit will therefore be achieved by producing the first cohesive insight into the activity of microbial communities in this ‘marine-like’ spring of unique chemistry. This work will also help develop new experimental approaches in the field through the implementation of novel and cutting-edge experimentation and analytical approaches. Cultivations of microbes form this environment, also has the potential to support development of applied biotechnology. The unique, cross-discipline nature of this work will also allow the Co-Is to implement outreach and learning activities in local schools and community colleges that benefit a diverse group of young STEM participants.  This project supports two early career female investigators and significantly enhances their new research groups.  This project is jointly funded by Earth Sciences and the Established Program to Stimulate Competitive Research (EPSCoR).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/19/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/19/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2025749</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Brittany</FirstName>
<LastName>Kruger</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Brittany Kruger</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[brittany.kruger@dri.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000746075</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/19/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Nevada System of Higher Education, Desert Research Institute</Name>
<CityName>RENO</CityName>
<ZipCode>895121095</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7756737300</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2215 RAGGIO PKWY</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Nevada</StateName>
<StateCode>NV</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NV02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>MV1JFXA4S621</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NEVADA SYSTEM OF HIGHER EDUCATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>E2N7LVJCNCW8</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Board of Regents, NSHE, on behalf of the Desert Research Institu]]></Name>
<CityName>Las Vegas</CityName>
<StateCode>NV</StateCode>
<ZipCode>891197363</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[755 E. Flamingo Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Nevada</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NV01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7295</Code>
<Text>Geobiology &amp; Low-Temp Geochem</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EPSCoR Co-Funding</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~208846</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The main goal of this project was to elucidate the geochemically and microbially-mediated sulfur and carbon cycling in a marine-like, high pH, and high salt terrestrial serpentinizing system, Ney?s Spring.&nbsp;We conducted multi-season time-series sampling of the system over multiple years, quantifying the aqueous geochemistry and microbial community at each sampling event and assessing multi-fraction radiocarbon and stable isotopes at select events. Cyclic voltammetry was used to further characterize sulfur species. We have currently produced two manuscripts from this effort. The first is a primary microbial and geochemical characterization of the system that also provides thermodynamic prediction of feasible microbial metabolisms (Trutschel et al., <em>STOTEN</em>, 2022). The second is a one-year seasonal analysis of the same parameters illustrating that observed geochemical variations occurred independent of impacts from meteoric water inputs to the system, and therefore allowed for correlative analysis between microbial community changes and geochemistry changes (Trutschel et al., <em>Front. Micro</em>., 2023, Fig. 1, Fig. 2). Additional outcomes include cultivation of several hyperalkaliphile isolates (growth at pH &gt; 12.3) for which characterization and assessment of electrochemical activity is ongoing (Table 1). Two additional manuscripts are in preparation. One is focused on elucidation of the sulfur cycle and quantification of sulfur species, including several diverse intermediate species that we have confirmed to be present in the system (tetrathionate, polysulfide, and thiosulfate), and specific characterization and use of these species for microbial growth. A second focuses on the carbon cycle of the system as related to the microbial community, including insights gained from multi-fraction radiocarbon analysis, stable carbon isotope analysis, and lipid analysis in comparison with a second serpentinizing system (The Cedars), which is hypothesized to be connected to the same subduction zone as Ney?s Spring. Together, these outcomes advance our knowledge of seasonality and microbial-geochemical interdependence in marine-like serpentinizing systems, of how sulfur chemistry supports microbial life in high pH systems, and of potential carbon incorporation mechanisms in high pH systems.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/11/2023<br>      Modified by: Brittany&nbsp;Kruger</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The main goal of this project was to elucidate the geochemically and microbially-mediated sulfur and carbon cycling in a marine-like, high pH, and high salt terrestrial serpentinizing system, Ney?s Spring. We conducted multi-season time-series sampling of the system over multiple years, quantifying the aqueous geochemistry and microbial community at each sampling event and assessing multi-fraction radiocarbon and stable isotopes at select events. Cyclic voltammetry was used to further characterize sulfur species. We have currently produced two manuscripts from this effort. The first is a primary microbial and geochemical characterization of the system that also provides thermodynamic prediction of feasible microbial metabolisms (Trutschel et al., STOTEN, 2022). The second is a one-year seasonal analysis of the same parameters illustrating that observed geochemical variations occurred independent of impacts from meteoric water inputs to the system, and therefore allowed for correlative analysis between microbial community changes and geochemistry changes (Trutschel et al., Front. Micro., 2023, Fig. 1, Fig. 2). Additional outcomes include cultivation of several hyperalkaliphile isolates (growth at pH &gt; 12.3) for which characterization and assessment of electrochemical activity is ongoing (Table 1). Two additional manuscripts are in preparation. One is focused on elucidation of the sulfur cycle and quantification of sulfur species, including several diverse intermediate species that we have confirmed to be present in the system (tetrathionate, polysulfide, and thiosulfate), and specific characterization and use of these species for microbial growth. A second focuses on the carbon cycle of the system as related to the microbial community, including insights gained from multi-fraction radiocarbon analysis, stable carbon isotope analysis, and lipid analysis in comparison with a second serpentinizing system (The Cedars), which is hypothesized to be connected to the same subduction zone as Ney?s Spring. Together, these outcomes advance our knowledge of seasonality and microbial-geochemical interdependence in marine-like serpentinizing systems, of how sulfur chemistry supports microbial life in high pH systems, and of potential carbon incorporation mechanisms in high pH systems.          Last Modified: 09/11/2023       Submitted by: Brittany Kruger]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
