<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Research and Development for the A-Pod HAB Trap and Removal Process]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>254504.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>254504</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rajesh Mehta</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rmehta@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922174</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact of this Small Business Innovation Research (Phase I) project is to reduce human and environmental health risks posed by Harmful Algae Bloom (HABs) impacts to water resources.  Communities across the nation allocate substantial financial resources to address HABs in their water bodies as HABs can be extremely toxic. However, this ecological problem can be treated as an eco-mining opportunity because HABs are tiny eco-miners that scour, collect, and concentrate excess nutrients in water bodies. The proposed technology is an eco-sensitive mining technology designed to harvest, trap, and permanently remove these HABs, their toxins, and the often ore-grade concentration of nutrients they contain. This project will advance a technology to permanently and sustainably removing the HABs, their toxins and the excess nutrients they contain. As a fully scalable and rapidly deployable, cost-effective technology, it will rapidly resolve HAB impairments and related health risks.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The intellectual merit of the proposed project is to target HABs, trap them through mechanical filtration, separate them through flotation, and monitor and test the effluent water for toxins. The proposed research is focused on development of remote and automatic operation capabilities to further minimize potential contact with HABs.   The process can be deployed in less than one day to surround and control small or very large areas of HABs, does not require a land-based treatment area, and does not need electricity or high capacity pumping systems to work. It can trap and remove HABs actively or passively.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/04/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/04/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2025679</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jonathan</FirstName>
<LastName>Higgins</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jonathan B Higgins</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[higginsenv@comcast.net]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000821894</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/04/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>HIGGINS ENVIRONMENTAL ASSOCIATES, INC.</Name>
<CityName>AMESBURY</CityName>
<ZipCode>019135410</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9788349000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>19 ELIZABETH ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>KTTGM8DQFLQ4</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>HIGGINS ENVIRONMENTAL ASSOCIATES, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[HIGGINS ENVIRONMENTAL ASSOCIATES, INC.]]></Name>
<CityName>Amesbury</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>019135410</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[19 Elizabeth Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1238</Code>
<Text>TECH FOR SUSTAINABLE ENVIRONMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>125E</Code>
<Text>CENTERS: CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE SYS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~254504</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>NSF's Phase I funding was used to support development and use of a technology call the A-Pod.&nbsp; The A-Pod technology is a recently-patented (August 2020), readily deployable, fully scaleable, floatable device to reduce health risks posed by toxic forms of cyanobacteria also known as harmful algae blooms (HABs) by selectively targeting, concentrating and containing (trapping) HABs, their toxins and excess nutrients for rapid and permanent removal from water bodies<br />&nbsp;&nbsp; &nbsp;<br />Our NSF Phase I objectives focused on improving automation, portability, scalability and use of&nbsp; the A-Pods to mitigate risks and to restore water bodies impacted by HABs. We also researched and evaluated suitable disposal and reuse options for recovered HABs.&nbsp; To accomplish these objectives, the Phase I had three tasks as follows:<br /><br />Task 1 - Automation and HAB Targeting;<br />Task 2 - Scalability, Materials and Method of Construction; and<br />Task 3 - Disposal/Recycling Options for Recovered HABs.<br /><br />A summary of Phase I research and results for each of these tasks follows:<br /><br />&nbsp;&nbsp; &nbsp;Task 1:We were able to rapidly field characterize the full water column (shallow and deep) extent and movement of HABs in small to very large water bodies and use this information to efficiently deploy, scale and utilize A-Pods, attached to shore as well as deployed in open waters away from shore, to trap, concentrate and remove HABs, their toxins and nutrients.&nbsp; We also identified and developed automation processes to more efficiently trap and remove HABs while minimizing user contact time around HABs and negative impacts to other aquatic organisms.<br /><br />&nbsp;&nbsp; &nbsp;Task 2: We identified and field tested various materials and methods of construction for the A-Pods.&nbsp; By prototyping and then completing field trials, we identified a low cost, robust yet light weight and readily scalable materials and method of design for the A-Pod that we are now commercially-using to target, trap, concentrate, and permanently remove HABs and their excess nutrients and toxins from water bodies.<br /><br />&nbsp;&nbsp; &nbsp;Task 3: We researched and coordinated with State agencies to evaluate available local disposal and recycling options for recovered HABs and their toxins. We identified commercially-viable and regulatory-preferred options which included by order of preference: Reuse; Repurposing; Destruction; and, Disposal.&nbsp; We field trialed and documented methods to support reuse and repurposing of HAB biomass and toxins removed from water bodies. We continue to research cost effective, safe and efficient ways to detoxify, reuse and repurpose HABs.<br /><br />We have provided presentations and summaries of our NSF-supported research and findings at technical conferences and public meetings.&nbsp; Importantly, our research and development documented changes in HAB life cycles, occurrence and water body conditions that are not well understood scientifically all while efficiently removing shallow and deep occurrences of HABs, their nutrients and toxins using the A-Pods.<br /><br />In Year 2022, A-Pods were deployed and used to substantially restore a large, historically HAB-impaired water body and to mitigate health risks associated with water contact, use and swimming by the public, pets and wildlife.&nbsp; By using the A-Pods, this was the first year in the past six years that the water body was not closed to swimming by the local health department.&nbsp; During use of the A-Pods, this water body also had significant improvements in water clarity (from 15 feet initially to over 33 feet deep) corresponding to a decrease in overall HAB biomass, HAB biovolume and toxins with documented removal of HABs by A-Pods over time.&nbsp; We achieved similar results at other water bodies. <br /><br />Use of the A-Pods is a science-supported, holistic and cost-effective way to sustainably prevent and reduce health risks posed by HABs and to restore water quality of water bodies by allowing for targeted and ecologically-sensitive removal of excessive HAB biomass, their nutrients and toxins.&nbsp; The A-Pod approach also limits negative impacts to beneficial species of aquatic-dependent algae, animals, insects, plants and zooplankton. &nbsp;<br /><br />With NSF-support, the A-Pod technology has been improved and proven to be a cost-effective and scalable tool for rapidly and sustainably mitigating health risks to people, pets, livestock, aquaculture, wildlife and the environment posed by toxic HAB impacts to water resources and water-dependent uses.&nbsp; We are continuing to research and develop additional supporting aspects and functions for use of A-Pods over a range of HAB types within fresh and estuarine waters.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/28/2022<br>      Modified by: Jonathan&nbsp;B&nbsp;Higgins</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ NSF's Phase I funding was used to support development and use of a technology call the A-Pod.  The A-Pod technology is a recently-patented (August 2020), readily deployable, fully scaleable, floatable device to reduce health risks posed by toxic forms of cyanobacteria also known as harmful algae blooms (HABs) by selectively targeting, concentrating and containing (trapping) HABs, their toxins and excess nutrients for rapid and permanent removal from water bodies      Our NSF Phase I objectives focused on improving automation, portability, scalability and use of  the A-Pods to mitigate risks and to restore water bodies impacted by HABs. We also researched and evaluated suitable disposal and reuse options for recovered HABs.  To accomplish these objectives, the Phase I had three tasks as follows:  Task 1 - Automation and HAB Targeting; Task 2 - Scalability, Materials and Method of Construction; and Task 3 - Disposal/Recycling Options for Recovered HABs.  A summary of Phase I research and results for each of these tasks follows:      Task 1:We were able to rapidly field characterize the full water column (shallow and deep) extent and movement of HABs in small to very large water bodies and use this information to efficiently deploy, scale and utilize A-Pods, attached to shore as well as deployed in open waters away from shore, to trap, concentrate and remove HABs, their toxins and nutrients.  We also identified and developed automation processes to more efficiently trap and remove HABs while minimizing user contact time around HABs and negative impacts to other aquatic organisms.      Task 2: We identified and field tested various materials and methods of construction for the A-Pods.  By prototyping and then completing field trials, we identified a low cost, robust yet light weight and readily scalable materials and method of design for the A-Pod that we are now commercially-using to target, trap, concentrate, and permanently remove HABs and their excess nutrients and toxins from water bodies.      Task 3: We researched and coordinated with State agencies to evaluate available local disposal and recycling options for recovered HABs and their toxins. We identified commercially-viable and regulatory-preferred options which included by order of preference: Reuse; Repurposing; Destruction; and, Disposal.  We field trialed and documented methods to support reuse and repurposing of HAB biomass and toxins removed from water bodies. We continue to research cost effective, safe and efficient ways to detoxify, reuse and repurpose HABs.  We have provided presentations and summaries of our NSF-supported research and findings at technical conferences and public meetings.  Importantly, our research and development documented changes in HAB life cycles, occurrence and water body conditions that are not well understood scientifically all while efficiently removing shallow and deep occurrences of HABs, their nutrients and toxins using the A-Pods.  In Year 2022, A-Pods were deployed and used to substantially restore a large, historically HAB-impaired water body and to mitigate health risks associated with water contact, use and swimming by the public, pets and wildlife.  By using the A-Pods, this was the first year in the past six years that the water body was not closed to swimming by the local health department.  During use of the A-Pods, this water body also had significant improvements in water clarity (from 15 feet initially to over 33 feet deep) corresponding to a decrease in overall HAB biomass, HAB biovolume and toxins with documented removal of HABs by A-Pods over time.  We achieved similar results at other water bodies.   Use of the A-Pods is a science-supported, holistic and cost-effective way to sustainably prevent and reduce health risks posed by HABs and to restore water quality of water bodies by allowing for targeted and ecologically-sensitive removal of excessive HAB biomass, their nutrients and toxins.  The A-Pod approach also limits negative impacts to beneficial species of aquatic-dependent algae, animals, insects, plants and zooplankton.    With NSF-support, the A-Pod technology has been improved and proven to be a cost-effective and scalable tool for rapidly and sustainably mitigating health risks to people, pets, livestock, aquaculture, wildlife and the environment posed by toxic HAB impacts to water resources and water-dependent uses.  We are continuing to research and develop additional supporting aspects and functions for use of A-Pods over a range of HAB types within fresh and estuarine waters.       Last Modified: 10/28/2022       Submitted by: Jonathan B Higgins]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
