<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Workshop on the proposed Network of Mountain Observatories for Composition of the Atmosphere]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>29886.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>29886</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06020104</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AGS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sylvia Edgerton</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sedgerto@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928522</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The Workshop on the proposed Network of Mountain Observatories for Composition of the Atmosphere (MOCA) will bring together atmospheric scientists to develop a long-term plan for coordinating research efforts at multiple high-elevation sites within the continental U.S.  Atmospheric measurements at high altitudes are sparse, and continuous sampling at mountain research observatories provides access to critical information about long-term changes in regional background atmospheric composition, as well as seasonal and diurnal processes and extreme episodes (e.g. wildfires, radionuclide releases, volcanic ash, dust storms, and stratospheric intrusions). The proposed network spans across different climatic zones and ecosystems in the U.S. and includes four internationally recognized atmospheric research observatories, which have been in operation for decades and are well-positioned to observe both atmospheric flow to the continental U.S. from the west and atmospheric flow to the east. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Specific goals of the workshop will be to: (1) further develop and refine the research objectives within each of the proposed science themes (reactive trace gases, greenhouse gases, aerosols and radiation, and clouds and precipitation); (2) identify critical measurements needed to meet these research objectives; (3) identify strategies to leverage measurements within different science themes to address additional research objectives or to better address existing research objectives; (4) identify research objectives that would especially benefit from a common set of measurements across sites; (5) develop metrics to prioritize research objectives; (6) evaluate the measurement infrastructure and data management needs for each site to be incorporated into the Global Atmospheric Watch (GAW) network as a global station; (7) encourage critical discussion about how best to implement and manage such a broad range of research objectives across multiple sites, including a data management plan; (8) develop a timeline for each research objective, following initial instrument integration at each site; (9) identify opportunities for meaningful and productive collaboration with other agencies and local/regional stakeholders; and (10) identify strategies for sustaining long-term, well-calibrated measurements at each site. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Conclusions from the workshop will be disseminated through a workshop summary publication.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/06/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/06/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2025215</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sara</FirstName>
<LastName>Lance</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sara Lance</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[smlance@albany.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000716389</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/06/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>SUNY at Albany</Name>
<CityName>ALBANY</CityName>
<ZipCode>122220100</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5184374974</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1400 WASHINGTON AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NHH3T1Z96H29</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH FOUNDATION FOR THE STATE UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>GMZUKXFDJMA9</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[SUNY at Albany]]></Name>
<CityName>Albany</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>122220100</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1400 Washington Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1524</Code>
<Text>Atmospheric Chemistry</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~29886</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><strong>Intellectual Merit: </strong></span>This grant supported a science workshop dedicated to developing the research objectives and  measurement/ management strategy for a network of high-elevation  observatories across the continental U.S., which we have named Mountain Observatories for Composition of the Atmosphere (MOCA). The objective of the MOCA workshop was to bring together researchers to  develop a long-term plan for coordinating research effort at multiple  high-elevation sites within the continental U.S., with the ultimate goal  of assessing changes in atmospheric composition and developing better  fundamental understanding of atmospheric processes.</p> <p>Combining  measurements with different atmospheric chemistry foci (including the  gas, aerosol, and aqueous phases) at high elevation sites across the  U.S., along with measurements of the relevant photochemical and  meteorological influences, will be key to developing better  understanding of the sources, transformation and fate of atmospheric  pollutants, so as to better understand and predict changes in  atmospheric composition. The primary task of the MOCA workshop was to develop a strong basis for prioritizing measurements to be included or excluded in the final MOCA network design based on scientific value, instrument costs and ease of operation</p> <p>Long-term high-elevation atmospheric measurements over the past several  decades have been used to document and understand chemical changes to  atmospheric composition as a result of human activities (e.g. greenhouse  gases, ozone and particulate pollution, acid rain, and ozone depleting  substances). These examples demonstrate the power of continuous  measurements spanning a decade or more at one location. However, our  understanding of multiphase chemical processes remains incomplete. Human  emissions also continue to evolve, even as ecosystems continue to  respond to previously emitted pollutants. Thus, even while some crises  appear to have been averted due to better understanding and  interventions to reduce emissions of specific pollutants, we must remain  vigilant to emerging threats to human and ecosystem health.<br /><br /><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Broader Impacts</span></strong>: The proposed network of mountaintop research  observatories would elevate atmospheric sciences research in the U.S. by  providing crucial infrastructure and transfer of knowledge that would  advance the science currently being conducted independently by  researchers at separate locations. If successful, this initiative would broaden the  research objectives currently attainable by enabling a more complete set  of measurements at each site and greater cooperation within the broader  atmospheric science community, and provide additional training  opportunities for students and young scientists.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/14/2022<br>      Modified by: Sara&nbsp;Lance</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2025215/2025215_10656399_1644899125015_Clipboard01--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2025215/2025215_10656399_1644899125015_Clipboard01--rgov-800width.jpg" title="MOCA Virtual Workshop"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2025215/2025215_10656399_1644899125015_Clipboard01--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="MOCA Virtual Workshop"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The workshop took place remotely as participants were still under lockdown as a result of the COVID-19 pandemic</div> <div class="imageCredit">Sara Lance</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Sara&nbsp;Lance</div> <div class="imageTitle">MOCA Virtual Workshop</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2025215/2025215_10656399_1644898719111_HDP_2016_2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2025215/2025215_10656399_1644898719111_HDP_2016_2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Hidden Peak, Utah"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2025215/2025215_10656399_1644898719111_HDP_2016_2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Hidden Peak, Utah"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">One of the initially proposed measurement sites in the MOCA network</div> <div class="imageCredit">John Lin</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Sara&nbsp;Lance</div> <div class="imageTitle">Hidden Peak, Utah</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2025215/2025215_10656399_1644898779326_WhiteFace10--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2025215/2025215_10656399_1644898779326_WhiteFace10--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Whiteface Mountain, NY"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2025215/2025215_10656399_1644898779326_WhiteFace10--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Whiteface Mountain, NY"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">One of the measurement sites in the proposed MOCA network</div> <div class="imageCredit">Sara Lance</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Sara&nbsp;Lance</div> <div class="imageTitle">Whiteface Mountain, NY</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Intellectual Merit: This grant supported a science workshop dedicated to developing the research objectives and  measurement/ management strategy for a network of high-elevation  observatories across the continental U.S., which we have named Mountain Observatories for Composition of the Atmosphere (MOCA). The objective of the MOCA workshop was to bring together researchers to  develop a long-term plan for coordinating research effort at multiple  high-elevation sites within the continental U.S., with the ultimate goal  of assessing changes in atmospheric composition and developing better  fundamental understanding of atmospheric processes.  Combining  measurements with different atmospheric chemistry foci (including the  gas, aerosol, and aqueous phases) at high elevation sites across the  U.S., along with measurements of the relevant photochemical and  meteorological influences, will be key to developing better  understanding of the sources, transformation and fate of atmospheric  pollutants, so as to better understand and predict changes in  atmospheric composition. The primary task of the MOCA workshop was to develop a strong basis for prioritizing measurements to be included or excluded in the final MOCA network design based on scientific value, instrument costs and ease of operation  Long-term high-elevation atmospheric measurements over the past several  decades have been used to document and understand chemical changes to  atmospheric composition as a result of human activities (e.g. greenhouse  gases, ozone and particulate pollution, acid rain, and ozone depleting  substances). These examples demonstrate the power of continuous  measurements spanning a decade or more at one location. However, our  understanding of multiphase chemical processes remains incomplete. Human  emissions also continue to evolve, even as ecosystems continue to  respond to previously emitted pollutants. Thus, even while some crises  appear to have been averted due to better understanding and  interventions to reduce emissions of specific pollutants, we must remain  vigilant to emerging threats to human and ecosystem health.  Broader Impacts: The proposed network of mountaintop research  observatories would elevate atmospheric sciences research in the U.S. by  providing crucial infrastructure and transfer of knowledge that would  advance the science currently being conducted independently by  researchers at separate locations. If successful, this initiative would broaden the  research objectives currently attainable by enabling a more complete set  of measurements at each site and greater cooperation within the broader  atmospheric science community, and provide additional training  opportunities for students and young scientists.       Last Modified: 02/14/2022       Submitted by: Sara Lance]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
