<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Workshop: The Role of Geoscience In Environmental Health Through Food Sovereignty]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>48260.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>48260</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>RISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div of Res, Innovation, Synergies, &amp; Edu</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Brandon Jones</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mbjones@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924713</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Part 1&lt;br/&gt;The purpose of this workshop is to bring together Native American/Alaska Native (NA/AN) tribal communities, leaders, elders, and cultural practitioners, faculty, students, geoscience and health professionals who engage in various aspects of geoscience, food sovereignty, and human health to emphasize both the importance geoscience plays in environmental sustainability and monitoring and the interconnectedness of geoscience in food sovereignty and thus human health. The workshop will contribute to empirical knowledge through the creation of a cross cultural geoscience learning community dedicated to respectfully and ethically coupling Traditional Knowledge and geoscience practices thereby expanding both knowledge systems. This workshop will add to the knowledge of collaboratively building upon best practices for engaging in geoscience research with tribal nations. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Part 2&lt;br/&gt;The workshop, which will weave together geoscience research with sustaining traditional nutritional methodologies will address the following questions 1) how does geoscience research impact Indigenous food sovereignty (implications from changing weather patterns)?, 2) what geoscience research is being conducted with tribal nations to monitor environmental health and sustainability? 3) why is geoscience research important for tribal nations? 4) what knowledge needs to be generated or shared regarding the coupling of tribal knowledge (TK) with geoscience? and 5) why is food sovereignty important? Throughout the workshop participants will be prompted to consider these questions to expand interdisciplinary partnerships, promote ethical and culturally aligned geoscience research, and highlight the importance of geoscience in environmental health and the role of geoscience research around issues of food sovereignty.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/24/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/24/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2025156</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Wendy</FirstName>
<LastName>Todd</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Wendy Todd</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[wtodd@d.umn.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000082974</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/24/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rebecca</FirstName>
<LastName>Webster</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Rebecca M Webster</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[rwebster@d.umn.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000818866</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/24/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Minnesota Duluth</Name>
<CityName>DULUTH</CityName>
<ZipCode>558123031</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2187267582</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1035 UNIVERSITY DR RM 133</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MN08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>LPCTM8BS8NF3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MINNESOTA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>CB47L9C9MDX1</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Minnesota Duluth]]></Name>
<CityName>Duluth</CityName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>558123011</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MN08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7699</Code>
<Text>Integrat &amp; Collab Ed &amp; Rsearch</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~48260</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Role of Geoscience In Environmental Health project successfully hosted 4 commuity workshops, one in &nbsp;Wisconsin with the Oneida Nation, two in Hydaburg Alaska with the Haida Nation, and one in Minnesota with the Fond du Lac tribe. The workshop engaged with 175 particpants to discuss goscience impacts on Indigenous food soveriengity and cross-cultural knowledge between tribal nations. The workshop with the Oneida nation focused on reclaiming traditional pottery making for processing of corn using traditional practices led by Oneida cultural practicioners and the imortance of traditional foods with a focus on corn and community health. Workshop one in Hydaburg Alaska focused on environmental impacts on traditional fishery resources and food security for rural tribal nations. Workshop two focused on interviews with Haida elders and matriarchs, hisotry of food security and the importance of a triditional diet. Work shop four was held at the Fond du Lac Tribal Community College in minnesota as a Water Soveriengity workshop in collaboration with the Indigenous Womens Water Sisterhood. The workshop hosted 100 Indigenous scholars and cultuarl practicions from around Minnesota.</p> <p>The project found that while there is a push to reclaim traditional foods and an interest in learning more aobut food security, there is a critial need to incorporate geoscience education and knowledge into reclamation practices to demonstarte the importance of environmental health for helathy foods and human health. The project allowed for the conversion to begin with tribal nations and raised interest in Indigenous students using both Traditional Knowege and Western science for food security issues. &nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/12/2023<br>      Modified by: Wendy&nbsp;Smythe</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2025156/2025156_10660317_1686596324561_mushroom-21-ak--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2025156/2025156_10660317_1686596324561_mushroom-21-ak--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Mushroom harvest"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2025156/2025156_10660317_1686596324561_mushroom-21-ak--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Mushroom harvest"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Image from a cultural food walk identifying traditional foods such as this mushroom that was harvested in Southeast Alaska</div> <div class="imageCredit">Wendy Todd</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Wendy&nbsp;Smythe</div> <div class="imageTitle">Mushroom harvest</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2025156/2025156_10660317_1686596420844_mike_jones_shirmp--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2025156/2025156_10660317_1686596420844_mike_jones_shirmp--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Southeast shrimp harvest"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2025156/2025156_10660317_1686596420844_mike_jones_shirmp--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Southeast shrimp harvest"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Community member Mike Jones is pulling shrimp traps to share with his home community.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Wendy Todd</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Wendy&nbsp;Smythe</div> <div class="imageTitle">Southeast shrimp harvest</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2025156/2025156_10660317_1686597040765_foodworkshopFDLTCC--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2025156/2025156_10660317_1686597040765_foodworkshopFDLTCC--rgov-800width.jpg" title="PI and Co-PI at FDLTCC"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2025156/2025156_10660317_1686597040765_foodworkshopFDLTCC--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="PI and Co-PI at FDLTCC"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">PIs Todd and Webster at Fond du Lac Tribal Community College (FDLTCC) for the Minnesota water and foods workshop.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Wendy Todd</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Wendy&nbsp;Smythe</div> <div class="imageTitle">PI and Co-PI at FDLTCC</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2025156/2025156_10660317_1686597114665_kasaanshrimp--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2025156/2025156_10660317_1686597114665_kasaanshrimp--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Spotted shrimp Southeast Alaska"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2025156/2025156_10660317_1686597114665_kasaanshrimp--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Spotted shrimp Southeast Alaska"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Spotted shrimp harvest in Southeast Alaska.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Wendy Todd</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Wendy&nbsp;Smythe</div> <div class="imageTitle">Spotted shrimp Southeast Alaska</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Role of Geoscience In Environmental Health project successfully hosted 4 commuity workshops, one in  Wisconsin with the Oneida Nation, two in Hydaburg Alaska with the Haida Nation, and one in Minnesota with the Fond du Lac tribe. The workshop engaged with 175 particpants to discuss goscience impacts on Indigenous food soveriengity and cross-cultural knowledge between tribal nations. The workshop with the Oneida nation focused on reclaiming traditional pottery making for processing of corn using traditional practices led by Oneida cultural practicioners and the imortance of traditional foods with a focus on corn and community health. Workshop one in Hydaburg Alaska focused on environmental impacts on traditional fishery resources and food security for rural tribal nations. Workshop two focused on interviews with Haida elders and matriarchs, hisotry of food security and the importance of a triditional diet. Work shop four was held at the Fond du Lac Tribal Community College in minnesota as a Water Soveriengity workshop in collaboration with the Indigenous Womens Water Sisterhood. The workshop hosted 100 Indigenous scholars and cultuarl practicions from around Minnesota.  The project found that while there is a push to reclaim traditional foods and an interest in learning more aobut food security, there is a critial need to incorporate geoscience education and knowledge into reclamation practices to demonstarte the importance of environmental health for helathy foods and human health. The project allowed for the conversion to begin with tribal nations and raised interest in Indigenous students using both Traditional Knowege and Western science for food security issues.         Last Modified: 06/12/2023       Submitted by: Wendy Smythe]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
