<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Fast field detection of trace fluorocarbon compounds in water]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>256000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>256000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rajesh Mehta</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rmehta@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922174</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this SBIR Phase I project is in the development of a low-cost, high sensitivity sensor to measure contaminants in groundwater. These measurements are currently performed using technologies that are relatively expensive ($250-300 per water sample) and have a long turn-around time (10-15 business days). The proposed on-site optical detection technology targets a 10-fold reduction in test price ($20-30 per water sample), and fast detection time (&lt;10 minutes). The proposed sensor will possess the following advanced attributes: high sensitivity, high specificity, fast detection, ease of operation, low power consumption, zero chemical release, low operational cost, remote measurements, and long-term stability without the need for recalibration. Moreover, direct use of the sample water will potentially eliminate uncertainties associated with measurement techniques.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research Phase I project is directed toward development of a powerful on-site detection and monitoring system for trace levels of perfluoroalkyl substances (PFAS) in groundwater. The proposed technology uses fluorescence quenching induced phase shift. A fluorescent material with PFAS molecule binding sites will be fabricated and its PFAS-induced fluorescence quenching will be experimentally evaluated. Using phase fluorometry, the phase shift of quenched emissions against excitation pulses will be recorded and correlated to the concentration of PFAS in water. The key technical risks lie in improving sensitivity by three orders of magnitude for a complex aqueous sample.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/10/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/10/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2025338</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Qingwu</FirstName>
<LastName>Wang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Qingwu Wang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[qwang@2witech.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000697769</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>2WITECH SOLUTIONS LLC</Name>
<CityName>ANDOVER</CityName>
<ZipCode>018103924</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9787991416</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>100 SCHOOL ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>LXK4KCSW35L7</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>2WITECH SOLUTIONS LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[2WITECH SOLUTIONS LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>Lowell</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>018524574</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[110 CANAL ST, 2ND FL]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1084</Code>
<Text>NANOTECHNOLOGY INITIATIVE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1238</Code>
<Text>TECH FOR SUSTAINABLE ENVIRONMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1639</Code>
<Text>SENSORS AND SENSING SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~256000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="a">The project outcomes report details the activities and results achieved during 2Witech Solutions Small Business Innovation Research Phase I program to develop a platform optical sensing technology<strong> </strong>for field trace detection of one of perfluorochemicals (PFCs), perfluorooctanoic acid (PFOA), in water. The proposed sensor is based on core/shell quantum dot-based fluorescent sensing disk where its fluorescence can be quenched when brought in direct contact with PFOA molecules in water. The sensing disk comprises fluorescent quantum dots embedded within a matrix by a wet-chemical process that involves the formation of an inorganic colloidal suspension and gelation of the formed colloidal suspension in a continuous liquid phase to form a three-dimensional network structure. Artificial recognition sites are created in the matrix, which are complementary to the molecule of PFOA in its size, shape and spatial arrangement of the functional groups. During measurement, analyte of interest (PFOA) in water are captured by those artificial recognition sites and stay in direct contact with the quantum dots, leading to quenching of fluorescent emissions and reduction of lifetime. The fluorescence quenching comes from energy transfer from excited quantum dots to PFOA molecules in a non-radioactive way and the degree of quenching is correlated to the concentration of PFOA in water. The average fluorescence lifetime of the quantum dots changes as the PFOA concentration increases. <strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p>Development of PFOA sensor based on fluorescent quenching effect to PFOA was demonstrated by successful completion of all the objectives of Phase I. The sensor was constructed by embedding core/shell quantum dots with artificial recognition sites to a hydrophilic porous and solid membrane, where selected polymer was used to bind the sensing particles onto a porous support. The sensor showed remarkable sensitivity to 10 parts per trillion (ppt) level of PFOA, rapid response (within minutes), great dynamic range ranging from 10 ppt to 1000 ppt and desirable selectivity against isopropyl alcohol and butanol. Feasibility of phase shift measurements using pulsed excitation light and its correlation to concentrations of PFOA in water was successfully assessed. In addition, to simplify the complicated design of sensing device caused by the extremely low life time (~10<sup>-9</sup> second) of the quantum dots, a straightforward alternative method based on ratiometric fluorescent measurement was evaluated. After incorporating dyes that are insensitive to PFOA, fluorescent ratio between the measured peak values of PFOA-sensitive quantum dots and PFOA-insensitive dye clearly showed a strong and reliable correlation to the concentration of target.&nbsp;</p> <p>Perfluorooctanoic acid and perfluorooctane sulphonate (PFOS) are widely spread across the US with different concentrations in drinking water. A 2020 study from the&nbsp;Environmental Working Group found that more than 200 million people in the U.S. could have per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances (PFAS) in their drinking water.<strong> </strong>Recent studies indicate that exposure to PFOA and PFOS over certain levels may result in adverse health effects. Currently measurement of concentration of PFOA and PFOS in water is performed using lab-based mass spectrometry technologies, which are relatively expensive ($250-300 per water sample) and have a longer turn-around time (10-15 business days). The proposed on-site optical detection technology is targeting 10 times reduced test price ($20-30 per water sample) and fast detection time (&lt;10 minutes). The US Air Force identified approximately 200 installations in the U.S. where PFOA and PFOS may have been released. The proposed sensing technology will provide a low cost approach for the Air Force personnel and its contractors to conduct site inspections to confirm if releases occurred. Other potential customers include public water suppliers and wastewater treatment facilities in PFC-contaminated areas. It can be expected that the proposed technology will have a broad customer base because PFC contamination is a global issue due to the broad applications of PFCs in manufacturing. This program will also enable further scientific/technological understanding on nanomaterial synthesis and surface functionalization, molecular imprinting, fluorescence quenching, and instrumentation. <strong></strong></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/06/2022<br>      Modified by: Qingwu&nbsp;Wang</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[The project outcomes report details the activities and results achieved during 2Witech Solutions Small Business Innovation Research Phase I program to develop a platform optical sensing technology for field trace detection of one of perfluorochemicals (PFCs), perfluorooctanoic acid (PFOA), in water. The proposed sensor is based on core/shell quantum dot-based fluorescent sensing disk where its fluorescence can be quenched when brought in direct contact with PFOA molecules in water. The sensing disk comprises fluorescent quantum dots embedded within a matrix by a wet-chemical process that involves the formation of an inorganic colloidal suspension and gelation of the formed colloidal suspension in a continuous liquid phase to form a three-dimensional network structure. Artificial recognition sites are created in the matrix, which are complementary to the molecule of PFOA in its size, shape and spatial arrangement of the functional groups. During measurement, analyte of interest (PFOA) in water are captured by those artificial recognition sites and stay in direct contact with the quantum dots, leading to quenching of fluorescent emissions and reduction of lifetime. The fluorescence quenching comes from energy transfer from excited quantum dots to PFOA molecules in a non-radioactive way and the degree of quenching is correlated to the concentration of PFOA in water. The average fluorescence lifetime of the quantum dots changes as the PFOA concentration increases.    Development of PFOA sensor based on fluorescent quenching effect to PFOA was demonstrated by successful completion of all the objectives of Phase I. The sensor was constructed by embedding core/shell quantum dots with artificial recognition sites to a hydrophilic porous and solid membrane, where selected polymer was used to bind the sensing particles onto a porous support. The sensor showed remarkable sensitivity to 10 parts per trillion (ppt) level of PFOA, rapid response (within minutes), great dynamic range ranging from 10 ppt to 1000 ppt and desirable selectivity against isopropyl alcohol and butanol. Feasibility of phase shift measurements using pulsed excitation light and its correlation to concentrations of PFOA in water was successfully assessed. In addition, to simplify the complicated design of sensing device caused by the extremely low life time (~10-9 second) of the quantum dots, a straightforward alternative method based on ratiometric fluorescent measurement was evaluated. After incorporating dyes that are insensitive to PFOA, fluorescent ratio between the measured peak values of PFOA-sensitive quantum dots and PFOA-insensitive dye clearly showed a strong and reliable correlation to the concentration of target.   Perfluorooctanoic acid and perfluorooctane sulphonate (PFOS) are widely spread across the US with different concentrations in drinking water. A 2020 study from the Environmental Working Group found that more than 200 million people in the U.S. could have per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances (PFAS) in their drinking water. Recent studies indicate that exposure to PFOA and PFOS over certain levels may result in adverse health effects. Currently measurement of concentration of PFOA and PFOS in water is performed using lab-based mass spectrometry technologies, which are relatively expensive ($250-300 per water sample) and have a longer turn-around time (10-15 business days). The proposed on-site optical detection technology is targeting 10 times reduced test price ($20-30 per water sample) and fast detection time (&lt;10 minutes). The US Air Force identified approximately 200 installations in the U.S. where PFOA and PFOS may have been released. The proposed sensing technology will provide a low cost approach for the Air Force personnel and its contractors to conduct site inspections to confirm if releases occurred. Other potential customers include public water suppliers and wastewater treatment facilities in PFC-contaminated areas. It can be expected that the proposed technology will have a broad customer base because PFC contamination is a global issue due to the broad applications of PFCs in manufacturing. This program will also enable further scientific/technological understanding on nanomaterial synthesis and surface functionalization, molecular imprinting, fluorescence quenching, and instrumentation.           Last Modified: 03/06/2022       Submitted by: Qingwu Wang]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
