<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[I-Corps:  High purity metal additive manufacturing]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ruth Shuman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rshuman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922160</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this I-Corps project is to explore translation for novel metal additive manufacturing (AM) for applications such as antennas, filters, biomedical devices, and aerospace devices. While the current prototype has focused on and shown successful results with copper, the process can be expanded to other highly pure metals, such as aluminum. The proposed technology is a new method of additive manufacturing enabling deposition of highly pure metals in an energy-efficient process with less waste. The largest AM adopter thus far, the aerospace industry, utilizes many 3D printed parts.  The proposed project will investigate translational opportunities in  aerospace manufacturing.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project is based on a novel metal additive manufacturing method, where the material is deposited/printed into the prototype, design, or technology. Existing additive manufacturing technologies have limitations in which alloys can be printed, limiting the product's purity.  The proposed technology is a new AM method enabling pure metal printing.  It  can be used to deposit in any direction (i.e. at any orientation onto a wafer or substrate), beneficial for specific prototype strengths. Each nozzle deposits around a rate of 1 cc/hour. This method also allows for control of porosity at the nanoscale level, allowing for new applications and benefits in areas such as biomedical implants and filtration.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/11/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/11/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2025020</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gregory</FirstName>
<LastName>Denbeaux</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gregory Denbeaux</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[gdenbeaux@sunypoly.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000195104</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/11/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>SUNY Polytechnic Institute</Name>
<CityName>ALBANY</CityName>
<ZipCode>122033613</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5184378689</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>257 FULLER RD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>CDAQNZCL6287</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>THE RESEARCH FOUNDATION FOR THE STATE UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[SUNY Polytechnic Institute]]></Name>
<CityName>Albany</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>122033603</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[257 Fuller Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This I-Corps project on additive manufacturing was for doing the customer discovery and learning the entreprenerial process.&nbsp; One graduate student completed the national node I-Corps based on this technology.&nbsp; One undergraduate student completed a local I-Corps node as well.</p> <p>This additive manufacturing method came out of prior industrially funded research on understanding nanoparticle transport for defectivity reduction in semiconductor manufacturing.&nbsp; We were studying under what conditions nanoparticles bounce or stick from surfaces.&nbsp; This method encompasses that research area allowing us to perform controlled deposition of highly pure metals, alloys, and possibly other material classes into sum-mm resolution selected locations.</p> <p>The early demonstration of this approach was demonstrated in 2019 using existing components in our lab at SUNY Polytechnic.&nbsp; The second iteration with improved control of the composition, deposition rate, purity and spatial resolution received internal funding support within SUNY Polytechnic Institute.</p> <p>The field of additive manufacturing is already crowded with many approaches including laser powder bed fusion.&nbsp; What we did not know was how this new technology could fit into that space.</p> <p>Through the customer discovery process and over 50 interviews, we found that there were some niches where the existing additive manufacturing processes were not meeting the needs of the industrical users.&nbsp; One area in particular is the ability to expand the composition of the structures fabricated with additive manufacturing.&nbsp; Based on that customer discovery, our technical approach has shifted to fabricating nanocomposites for improved high temperature structural properties compared with the existing alloys.&nbsp; That technical approach is in development.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/30/2023<br>      Modified by: Gregory&nbsp;Denbeaux</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This I-Corps project on additive manufacturing was for doing the customer discovery and learning the entreprenerial process.  One graduate student completed the national node I-Corps based on this technology.  One undergraduate student completed a local I-Corps node as well.  This additive manufacturing method came out of prior industrially funded research on understanding nanoparticle transport for defectivity reduction in semiconductor manufacturing.  We were studying under what conditions nanoparticles bounce or stick from surfaces.  This method encompasses that research area allowing us to perform controlled deposition of highly pure metals, alloys, and possibly other material classes into sum-mm resolution selected locations.  The early demonstration of this approach was demonstrated in 2019 using existing components in our lab at SUNY Polytechnic.  The second iteration with improved control of the composition, deposition rate, purity and spatial resolution received internal funding support within SUNY Polytechnic Institute.  The field of additive manufacturing is already crowded with many approaches including laser powder bed fusion.  What we did not know was how this new technology could fit into that space.  Through the customer discovery process and over 50 interviews, we found that there were some niches where the existing additive manufacturing processes were not meeting the needs of the industrical users.  One area in particular is the ability to expand the composition of the structures fabricated with additive manufacturing.  Based on that customer discovery, our technical approach has shifted to fabricating nanocomposites for improved high temperature structural properties compared with the existing alloys.  That technical approach is in development.       Last Modified: 03/30/2023       Submitted by: Gregory Denbeaux]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
