<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Non-pharmaceutical, light and ultrasound combination therapy to prevent SSI's and HAI's]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>253670.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>253670</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Henry Ahn</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>hahn@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927069</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial the potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is significant reduction in suffering and healthcare costs from the incidence of Surgical Site Infections (SSIs), Hospital Acquired Infections (HAIs), and Superbugs. This project will provide many societal benefits: improved disaster care prior to hospitalization; better in-field military injury outcomes; improved infection care in underdeveloped nations with limited access to hospitals and clinics, and others. Costs of HAIs and SSIs currently exceed $41B worldwide. A recent estimate indicates that failing to tackle antibiotic resistance could lead to over 10M deaths annually, and millions in cumulative economic damage. The proposed technology is an infection treatment that does not use antibiotics.  As an alternative, this project will offer a non-pharmaceutical solution providing cost-effective treatments that reduce the clinical use of antibiotics. This project will provide a reduction in patient suffering, improved medical outcomes, and reduced overall healthcare costs.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project will develop a non-pharmaceutical therapy that selectively kills bacteria and viruses and prevents SSI’s and HAI’s and does not induce further antimicrobial resistance. The project focuses on combining and simultaneous applying specific wavelengths of light and sound frequency resulting in a novel therapeutic dose to kill bacteria, including Methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus (MRSA). The technology can be used pre-surgery to disinfect body areas where the surgery will be performed, and post-surgery to prevent infections at surgical sites. The innovative combination of specific wavelengths of light and sound frequency activates a unique biochemical mechanism to kill bacteria from within. The research will identify ideal materials that will transmit both light and sound energies efficiently whilst meeting safety, efficacy, and ergonomic configurations for proposed applications. The aim is to also find optimal treatment times to treat different areas of the body for specific bacterial infections.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/17/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/13/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2025728</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Vipula</FirstName>
<LastName>Tailor</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Vipula Tailor</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[vipula.tailor@sonixmedicaldevices.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000822941</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/17/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>SONIX MEDICAL DEVICES INC.</Name>
<CityName>BRASELTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>305174322</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6098517500</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1545 ADAMS AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[STE 1]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>JPXJLC82Z5Y6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SONIX MEDICAL DEVICES INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Sonix Medical Devices, Inc]]></Name>
<CityName>Braselton</CityName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>305174322</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1545 Adams Avenue, Suite #1]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>004E</Code>
<Text>BIOMEDICAL ENG AND DIAGNOSTICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8038</Code>
<Text>Biotechnology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~253670</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Project Outcomes Report for Non-Pharmaceutical Light and Ultrasound Combination Therapy for SSIs and HAIs</p> <p>Surgical Site Infections (SSIs) and Hospital Acquired Infections (HAIs) remain an ongoing challenge for both healthcare providers and their patients. The issue with these bacterial is compounded by the growing threat of Antimicrobial Resistance (AMR). Our research effort addresses these issues with a non-pharmaceutical, blue light and ultrasound combination therapy which selectively kills only bacteria, with the goal of preventing SSI?s and HAI?s, and doing so in a way that does not induce further Antimicrobial Resistance.</p> <p>The novel therapy combines safe levels of blue light with low intensity ultrasound to create a synergistic combination that works far more effectively than either energy alone. The low intensity ultrasound ?activates? the bacteria within the infection site such that they become susceptible to the antimicrobial effects of blue light. The goal of this research program was to adapt this energy combination so that it could be applied to patients with specific Surgical Site Infections. This involved the development of new patient contact materials and energy sources so that the treatment device could be applied to the infection site and used without operator interaction. The research program tested a range of new flexible patient-safe plastic materials that would transmit both blue light and ultrasound efficiently. New compact ultrasound transducers were designed and evaluated, along with novel blue light LED configurations. The combinations were tested both on the bench and in the laboratory, showing that the combination could substantially reduce bacterial levels. Bacteria levels dropped by factors of 100 or more. The designs will next be incorporated into prototype clinical devices for eventual testing on patients, for whom surgical site infections remain a significant cause of morbidity, mortality, hospitalizations, and cost.</p> <p>When the concept is finally brought to market, it will lead to substantial healthcare savings and improved Quality of Life for patients affected by infection. It can also lead to reduced incidence of AMR in the future since the technology has been shown to prevent the development of Antibiotic Resistance in treated bacteria.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/14/2021<br>      Modified by: Vipula&nbsp;Tailor</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2025728/2025728_10697969_1631592491196_Sonix-A8Results_913--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2025728/2025728_10697969_1631592491196_Sonix-A8Results_913--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Efficacy"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2025728/2025728_10697969_1631592491196_Sonix-A8Results_913--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Efficacy"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Test results showing multiple log reduction in bacterial growth post treatment with Sonix - A8 technology.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Vipula Tailor</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Vipula&nbsp;Tailor</div> <div class="imageTitle">Efficacy</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Project Outcomes Report for Non-Pharmaceutical Light and Ultrasound Combination Therapy for SSIs and HAIs  Surgical Site Infections (SSIs) and Hospital Acquired Infections (HAIs) remain an ongoing challenge for both healthcare providers and their patients. The issue with these bacterial is compounded by the growing threat of Antimicrobial Resistance (AMR). Our research effort addresses these issues with a non-pharmaceutical, blue light and ultrasound combination therapy which selectively kills only bacteria, with the goal of preventing SSI?s and HAI?s, and doing so in a way that does not induce further Antimicrobial Resistance.  The novel therapy combines safe levels of blue light with low intensity ultrasound to create a synergistic combination that works far more effectively than either energy alone. The low intensity ultrasound ?activates? the bacteria within the infection site such that they become susceptible to the antimicrobial effects of blue light. The goal of this research program was to adapt this energy combination so that it could be applied to patients with specific Surgical Site Infections. This involved the development of new patient contact materials and energy sources so that the treatment device could be applied to the infection site and used without operator interaction. The research program tested a range of new flexible patient-safe plastic materials that would transmit both blue light and ultrasound efficiently. New compact ultrasound transducers were designed and evaluated, along with novel blue light LED configurations. The combinations were tested both on the bench and in the laboratory, showing that the combination could substantially reduce bacterial levels. Bacteria levels dropped by factors of 100 or more. The designs will next be incorporated into prototype clinical devices for eventual testing on patients, for whom surgical site infections remain a significant cause of morbidity, mortality, hospitalizations, and cost.  When the concept is finally brought to market, it will lead to substantial healthcare savings and improved Quality of Life for patients affected by infection. It can also lead to reduced incidence of AMR in the future since the technology has been shown to prevent the development of Antibiotic Resistance in treated bacteria.           Last Modified: 09/14/2021       Submitted by: Vipula Tailor]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
