<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase II:  Finalized Design, Performance and Safety Testing of SmartOto, A Handheld Device for Detection of Otitis Media]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1000000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1000000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Cooperative Agreement</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Henry Ahn</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>hahn@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927069</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase II project is to improve diagnosis of pediatric otitis media (ear infection).  Otitis media is the leading cause of unnecessary antibiotic use in children and the second most common pediatric physician appointment.  It is estimated that more than 90% of children will suffer at least one case of otitis media before age 5.  Despite its prevalence, there may be less than 60% diagnostic accuracy in primary care where the vast majority of cases are seen.  Current clinical diagnostics have proven inadequate to address over-prescription of antibiotics and unnecessary specialist and surgical referrals. Otitis media is typically diagnosed using an otoscope to view the tympanic membrane (eardrum) and assess visual signs of an infection.  Otoscope designs have changed little since the 1800’s.  This SBIR Phase II project advances a novel device that integrates clinical standard otoscopy with a novel technique to non-invasively assess ear health using light in real time and with 98% accuracy.  This new otoscope has the potential to create a new standard of care in diagnosis and management of otitis media, and stands to save billions in direct healthcare costs through more accurate diagnosis.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase II project will advance translation of a device providing clinicians with an objective, real-time indicator of ear health during standard otoscopy.  At the push of a button, the LED driven measurement will provide an instantaneous, accurate indication of the presence or absence of middle ear effusion (MEE) – the most sensitive and specific indicator of acute otitis media per established clinical guidelines.  This project will meet the desired technical specifications of sufficiently sensitive visualization capabilities and reducing measurement time from 1.4 seconds to less than 300 milliseconds.  This project will also: 1) Optimize manufacturability and assembly; 2) Develop a standard automated calibration system; and 3) Conduct standard electronic, photobiologic, and biocompatibility testing for safety and regulatory purposes.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/14/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/13/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>CoopAgrmnt</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2025870</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Weidling</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John Weidling</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jweidlin@gmail.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000672100</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/14/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>CACTUS MEDICAL,LLC</Name>
<CityName>IRVINE</CityName>
<ZipCode>92614</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9496320393</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2601 MAIN ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[STE 730]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>47</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA47</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>FKNKPAKHVPN6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CACTUS MEDICAL LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>F1N4QMQG87T5</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[CACTUS MEDICAL,LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>Irvine</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>926145264</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2601 Main St Ste 730]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>47</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA47</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5373</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase II</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>004E</Code>
<Text>BIOMEDICAL ENG AND DIAGNOSTICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8038</Code>
<Text>Biotechnology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~1000000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Ear infection mis-diagnosis represents the leading cause for use of unnecessary antibiotics in the pediatric population. In order to address this problem, Cactus Medical, LLC has been developing a novel otoscope to provide a spectral measurement of middle ear effusion (MEE) status (a key indicator of ear infection) during a routine otoscopic examination of the ear. Cactus? successful completion of NSF Phase II objectives has produced a working prototype otoscope which performs the MEE measurement in less than 1 second at the press of a button, and is now in use in clinical studies.</p> <p>During the course of work on this Phase II project, Cactus met the following objectives: 1. Enhancement of visualization capabilities through modification to the light source and optical lens elements to provide a larger field of view at higher magnification with improved flatness of field; 2. Reduction of MEE measurement time through re-design of the light detection circuit for low noise light collection measured in milliseconds; 3. Otoscope designed for manufacturability and assembly through the modularization of component parts with qualification steps for each sub-assembly; 4. Production of a calibration system by designing and building a custom fixture for light calibration of each individual SmartOto unit to a National Institute of Standards and Technology (NIST) standard for brightness across all used wavelengths of light; and 5. A SmartOto design that allows for the use of multiple speculum sizes to fit into ear canals of different sizes.</p> <p>Cactus has achieved the milestone of a finalized first generation SmartOto<sup>TM</sup> Otoscope prototype. This device addresses all identified customer requirements, has highly repeatable measurements, can be factory calibrated, and provides clear actionable results as hypothesized in Cactus? value proposition. All technical problems related to the Phase II project have been successfully solved.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/29/2022<br>      Modified by: John&nbsp;Weidling</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2025870/2025870_10706692_1669733029010_Cactus_Outcomes--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2025870/2025870_10706692_1669733029010_Cactus_Outcomes--rgov-800width.jpg" title="SmartOto Prototype"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2025870/2025870_10706692_1669733029010_Cactus_Outcomes--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="SmartOto Prototype"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Cactus Medical, LLC's SmartOto Otoscope captures spectral information related to ear infection at the press of a button. The results are obtained and displayed within 1 second.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Cactus Medical, LLC</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">John&nbsp;Weidling</div> <div class="imageTitle">SmartOto Prototype</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Ear infection mis-diagnosis represents the leading cause for use of unnecessary antibiotics in the pediatric population. In order to address this problem, Cactus Medical, LLC has been developing a novel otoscope to provide a spectral measurement of middle ear effusion (MEE) status (a key indicator of ear infection) during a routine otoscopic examination of the ear. Cactus? successful completion of NSF Phase II objectives has produced a working prototype otoscope which performs the MEE measurement in less than 1 second at the press of a button, and is now in use in clinical studies.  During the course of work on this Phase II project, Cactus met the following objectives: 1. Enhancement of visualization capabilities through modification to the light source and optical lens elements to provide a larger field of view at higher magnification with improved flatness of field; 2. Reduction of MEE measurement time through re-design of the light detection circuit for low noise light collection measured in milliseconds; 3. Otoscope designed for manufacturability and assembly through the modularization of component parts with qualification steps for each sub-assembly; 4. Production of a calibration system by designing and building a custom fixture for light calibration of each individual SmartOto unit to a National Institute of Standards and Technology (NIST) standard for brightness across all used wavelengths of light; and 5. A SmartOto design that allows for the use of multiple speculum sizes to fit into ear canals of different sizes.  Cactus has achieved the milestone of a finalized first generation SmartOtoTM Otoscope prototype. This device addresses all identified customer requirements, has highly repeatable measurements, can be factory calibrated, and provides clear actionable results as hypothesized in Cactus? value proposition. All technical problems related to the Phase II project have been successfully solved.          Last Modified: 11/29/2022       Submitted by: John Weidling]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
