<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase II:  A New Bio-based Monomer for the Coatings Industry]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>961720.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1654020</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Cooperative Agreement</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Benaiah Schrag</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bschrag@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928323</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase II project is to provide domestic production of renewable, biomass-based alternatives to products currently made from oil.  This SBIR Phase II project will demonstrate the commercial potential of producing 1,5-pentanediol (1,5-PDO), a key chemical used to manufacture coatings, adhesives, and plastics, from agricultural wastes like corn cobs. Biomass-based chemicals can decrease the nation's dependence on oil and reduce greenhouse gas emissions, while providing cost-competitive high-performance chemical products. Creating high-value commodity chemicals using nonfood agricultural materials as feedstock promises to create new markets for bio-based waste products.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase II project will generate the necessary experimental data to design commercial reactors for producing renewable bio-based 1,5-pentanediol. A chemical pathway to produce bio-based 1,5-pentanediol has been demonstrated in laboratory reactors using commercially relevant reactors and catalysts.  In this work a wide range of reactor operating conditions will be explored in the laboratory for scale-up of the process. These operating conditions will be further demonstrated in larger pilot-scale equipment to inform design at commercial scale.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/16/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/10/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>CoopAgrmnt</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2025857</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kevin</FirstName>
<LastName>Barnett</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kevin J Barnett</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[kjbarnett@pyranco.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000710897</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/16/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>PYRAN INC</Name>
<CityName>MADISON</CityName>
<ZipCode>537196006</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6087090290</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>505 S ROSA RD STE 112</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>ETTFUT548XF3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PYRAN INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[PYRAN LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>Madison</CityName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>537196006</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[505 South Rosa Road, Suite 112]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5373</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase II</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>165E</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase IIB</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>169E</Code>
<Text>SBIR Tech Enhan Partner (TECP)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8021</Code>
<Text>Materials Engineering</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002223DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~1461720</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2022~192300</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="CTMSTY">Providing bio-based alternatives to materials currently made from oil is critical to fighting climate change and increasing U.S. energy and economic security. Pyran has developed a new process to manufacture a chemical called 1,5-pentanediol (1,5-PDO) from renewable agricultural wastes (e.g., corn cobs). 1,5-PDO belongs to a class of chemicals called &ldquo;diols&rdquo; which are used in a wide variety of everyday materials such as coatings, adhesives, paints, and plastics. Currently these diols are manufactured from oil using complex, expensive, and hazardous processes. Pyran&rsquo;s proprietary technology can replace these oil-based diols with a renewable alternative while reducing associated greenhouse gas emissions by more than 95%. Pyran&rsquo;s recently completed NSF SBIR Phase II project demonstrates that renewable 1,5-PDO production can be sufficiently scaled to replace oil-based diols at lower costs, providing an opportunity for consumers to access high quality sustainable versions of their favorite products.</p> <p class="CTMSTY">The Phase II project built on developments from Phase I to test Pyran&rsquo;s renewable 1,5-PDO process at larger scale. In Phase I, Pyran&rsquo;s chemical pathway to produce 1,5-PDO was demonstrated in laboratory reactors using commercially relevant reactor configurations and catalysts (materials used to increase the rate of chemical reactions to improve their economic potential). In Phase II, in preparation for scaleup activities, Pyran explored a wider range of reactor operating conditions in the lab, which produced a better understanding of the key conditions that affect reactor performance. Pyran then demonstrated these conditions in larger &ldquo;pilot scale&rdquo; equipment in the Phase II project. &ldquo;Piloting&rdquo; is a crucial step in scaling up a process to learn more about the behavior of the reactions in larger scale equipment while managing the risks and costs compared to even larger commercial assets. Pyran was able to successfully demonstrate its process in reactors 500-1,000x larger than the laboratory and produce multiple tons of renewable 1,5-PDO product to be tested in a variety of products. Data collected during these experiments were implemented in detailed process designs and economic projections for the commercial process.</p> <p class="CTMSTY">The funds that Pyran were able to leverage from the NSF SBIR program have provided a strong groundwork for the commercialization of renewable 1,5-PDO paint ingredient. Over the course of the NSF SBIR Phase II project, Pyran raised &gt;$4M in non-grant funding, secured a commercial product offtake agreement with a large chemical company, and identified strategic investors for our commercial facility, all demonstrating the success the NSF SBIR Phase II program had on leveraging Pyran&rsquo;s technical accomplishments into tangible commercial outcomes.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/14/2023<br>      Modified by: Kevin&nbsp;J&nbsp;Barnett</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[Providing bio-based alternatives to materials currently made from oil is critical to fighting climate change and increasing U.S. energy and economic security. Pyran has developed a new process to manufacture a chemical called 1,5-pentanediol (1,5-PDO) from renewable agricultural wastes (e.g., corn cobs). 1,5-PDO belongs to a class of chemicals called "diols" which are used in a wide variety of everyday materials such as coatings, adhesives, paints, and plastics. Currently these diols are manufactured from oil using complex, expensive, and hazardous processes. Pyran’s proprietary technology can replace these oil-based diols with a renewable alternative while reducing associated greenhouse gas emissions by more than 95%. Pyran’s recently completed NSF SBIR Phase II project demonstrates that renewable 1,5-PDO production can be sufficiently scaled to replace oil-based diols at lower costs, providing an opportunity for consumers to access high quality sustainable versions of their favorite products. The Phase II project built on developments from Phase I to test Pyran’s renewable 1,5-PDO process at larger scale. In Phase I, Pyran’s chemical pathway to produce 1,5-PDO was demonstrated in laboratory reactors using commercially relevant reactor configurations and catalysts (materials used to increase the rate of chemical reactions to improve their economic potential). In Phase II, in preparation for scaleup activities, Pyran explored a wider range of reactor operating conditions in the lab, which produced a better understanding of the key conditions that affect reactor performance. Pyran then demonstrated these conditions in larger "pilot scale" equipment in the Phase II project. "Piloting" is a crucial step in scaling up a process to learn more about the behavior of the reactions in larger scale equipment while managing the risks and costs compared to even larger commercial assets. Pyran was able to successfully demonstrate its process in reactors 500-1,000x larger than the laboratory and produce multiple tons of renewable 1,5-PDO product to be tested in a variety of products. Data collected during these experiments were implemented in detailed process designs and economic projections for the commercial process. The funds that Pyran were able to leverage from the NSF SBIR program have provided a strong groundwork for the commercialization of renewable 1,5-PDO paint ingredient. Over the course of the NSF SBIR Phase II project, Pyran raised &gt;$4M in non-grant funding, secured a commercial product offtake agreement with a large chemical company, and identified strategic investors for our commercial facility, all demonstrating the success the NSF SBIR Phase II program had on leveraging Pyran’s technical accomplishments into tangible commercial outcomes.          Last Modified: 07/14/2023       Submitted by: Kevin J Barnett]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
