<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Travel Support for Hinode-14/IRIS-11 Joint Science Meeting]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>18752.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>18752</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06020203</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AGS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Lisa Winter</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lwinter@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928519</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This 1-year project is to enable the participation of graduate students and early-career researchers at the Hinode-14 / IRIS-11 Joint Science Meeting, which will be held at George Mason University during July 28-31, 2020.  The meeting will highlight the most recent achievements of the Hinode and IRIS space missions together with the latest research advancements on topics related to the missions’ goals.  To date, these two satellites have provided an incredible amount of physical insights regarding the dynamics of the solar atmosphere, in particular how energy is released in the solar corona, how solar flares evolve, how eruptive events occur, and what the sources of the solar wind are.  The  present joint meeting will put special emphasis on the synergies with the Daniel K. Inouye Solar Telescope  (DKIST), which is supported by the NSF.  Furthermore, science topics that include close cooperation and coordination with other ground-based facilities and recent space-based missions, such as the Parker Solar Probe and Solar Orbiter, are also solicited in the invited talks as well as in the call for abstracts.  The following science themes are identified by the Scientific Organization Committee, and the relevant topics will be organized around these themes: (i) connection to inner heliosphere platforms; (ii) photospheric convection and solar magnetic field; (iii) atmospheric heating: chromosphere to corona; (iv) flares, jets, and Coronal Mass Ejections (CMEs); and, (v) DKIST science and workforce development.  The research and EPO agenda of this 1-year project supports the Strategic Goals of the AGS Division in discovery, learning, diversity, and interdisciplinary research.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/19/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/19/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2025986</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jie</FirstName>
<LastName>Zhang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jie Zhang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jzhang7@gmu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000229995</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/19/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>George Mason University</Name>
<CityName>FAIRFAX</CityName>
<ZipCode>220304422</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7039932295</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4400 UNIVERSITY DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>11</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>VA11</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>EADLFP7Z72E5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GEORGE MASON UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>EADLFP7Z72E5</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[George Mason University]]></Name>
<CityName>Fairfax</CityName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>220304422</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4400 University Dr # 3F3]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>11</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>VA11</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1523</Code>
<Text>SOLAR-TERRESTRIAL</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~18752</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>&nbsp;</p> <p><span>The goal of this project is to support the Hinode-14 / IRIS-11 Joint Science Meeting, originally planned as an in-person meeting at the Arlington Campus of George Mason University, Arlington, Virginia, USA.</span> <span>Due to COVID-19 pandemic, the meeting was postponed multiple times from its original planned date of July 28-31, 2020. </span><span>The meeting successfully took place on October 25-29, 2021. It was hosted by George Mason University (Fairfax, VA, USA). The meeting highlighted the most recent achievements of the IRIS and Hinode missions together with the latest research on topics related to the missions? goals. The science program was organized around four themes: (1) Hinode/IRIS connection to inner heliospheric platforms (PSP, SolO and other instrumetnts), (2) photospheric convection and solar magnetic field, (3) atmospheric heating: chromosphere to corona and (4) Flares, jets, CMEs and others. The fifth day was dedicated to a tutorial to the usage of data from EIS, XRT and SOT, and SunPy and IRISpy software packages.</span><span>&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span>There were 350 registrations from 26 countries. &nbsp;There were 138 abstracts submitted, distributing in 50 oral presentations (14 invited) and 88 posters. </span>The meeting acknowledges support from NSF, GMU, NSO, NASA and SCOSTEP/PRESTO. The full meeting information can be accessed at http://hinode14.org</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/13/2022<br>      Modified by: Jie&nbsp;Zhang</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[    The goal of this project is to support the Hinode-14 / IRIS-11 Joint Science Meeting, originally planned as an in-person meeting at the Arlington Campus of George Mason University, Arlington, Virginia, USA. Due to COVID-19 pandemic, the meeting was postponed multiple times from its original planned date of July 28-31, 2020. The meeting successfully took place on October 25-29, 2021. It was hosted by George Mason University (Fairfax, VA, USA). The meeting highlighted the most recent achievements of the IRIS and Hinode missions together with the latest research on topics related to the missions? goals. The science program was organized around four themes: (1) Hinode/IRIS connection to inner heliospheric platforms (PSP, SolO and other instrumetnts), (2) photospheric convection and solar magnetic field, (3) atmospheric heating: chromosphere to corona and (4) Flares, jets, CMEs and others. The fifth day was dedicated to a tutorial to the usage of data from EIS, XRT and SOT, and SunPy and IRISpy software packages.   There were 350 registrations from 26 countries.  There were 138 abstracts submitted, distributing in 50 oral presentations (14 invited) and 88 posters. The meeting acknowledges support from NSF, GMU, NSO, NASA and SCOSTEP/PRESTO. The full meeting information can be accessed at http://hinode14.org          Last Modified: 05/13/2022       Submitted by: Jie Zhang]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
