<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Plant Photomorphogenesis using Adaptive Multispectral LED Arrays in a Rotary Aeroponic Cultivation Chamber (RACC)]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>256000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>256000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rajesh Mehta</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rmehta@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922174</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is to provide a sustainable method to grow healthy produce for individuals at a residential consumer level independent of location, climate, or season of the year.  This project will develop new systems to grow produce in spaces with a small footprint, reducing food waste and consumption of potable water and energy. This can provide the capability to enhance cost-effective production in a small space with limited resources.  &lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;The intellectual merit of this SBIR Phase I project is a new plant cultivation technology, called rotary aeroponics. coupled with a tunable irradiance growth efficiency research light designed to examine how light wavelength and timing can impact plant photomorphogenesis. Rotary aeroponic cultivation is the method of growing plants on a rotating cylindrical tower that is affixed vertically within a controlled environmental chamber. The tower design provides a larger surface area for growing plants in comparison to traditional vertical farming methods, thereby increasing the number of plants grown in a smaller space with less power consumption. The goal of this project is to successfully grow a healthy polyculture assortment of leafy green vegetables in a food-safe environment. The multi-spectra light will be used to learn how to maximize plant yields, minimize food safety risks, and enhance the taste profiles of different plant types.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/04/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/04/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2025920</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ivan</FirstName>
<LastName>Ball</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ivan Ball</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ivan@gropod.io]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000815844</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/04/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>HELIPONIX, LLC</Name>
<CityName>EVANSVILLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>477142437</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8126645092</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>800 S SAINT JAMES BLVD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IN08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>RNHPHCGG4DR6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>HELIPONIX LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[HELIPONIX, LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>Evansville</CityName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>477142437</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[47714-2437]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IN08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1238</Code>
<Text>TECH FOR SUSTAINABLE ENVIRONMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8040</Code>
<Text>Energy and Environment</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~256000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>The revolutionary design of the RACC, protected by an international PCT patent, houses a revolving aeroponic tower which optimizes the square footage used to grow plants with the least amount of power consumption and moving parts.&nbsp;The goal of Phase I research was to evaluate the feasibility of the RACC system, optimize lighting conditions, and operational parameters to maximize production of safe, healthy, and nutritious produce in an resource use efficient manner. After several experiments the Phase I project&nbsp;confirmed the feasibility for plant growth across 8 different varieties of plants, including leafy greens, herbs, and microgreens under residential home conditions.</span></p> <p><span>During the Phase I experiments, several key discoveries were made and will be explored deeper. The first key finding was that full spectrum lighting resulted in superior growth and user experience than Red/Blue lighting. After analyzing the data of the lighting experiments, it was noted that the rotary aeroponic method stimulates plant growth via triggering shade avoidance responses. Additionally, crop growth and nutrition are dependent on the combination of rotation and light spectra after looking at the differences in plant tower rotation speed and light recipe selection. Further experimentation is needed to confirm these findings.&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span>As for the rotary aeroponic chamber design, additional cooling is not necessary when growing under residential environmental conditions. A new improved airflow design will enable an increased light input to further optimize the yield and power use efficiency of the system. The use of computer vision and deep learning allows non-invasive detection of plant traits to continually improve the systems performance over time. This will be important to include in the system design for commercialization to assist residential consumers to grow complex varieties of produce in their homes around the globe.</span></p> <p><span>Supply chain disruptions over the past year have caused shortages and price increases of food. Climate change and soil degradation is creating a challenge for farmers to keep up with the demands of an exponentially increasing population. Food waste from our existing and complex supply chain contributes to large amounts of greenhouse gases. Pesticides and chemical contaminations have compromised the safety of our food system and sustainability of our ecosystem. Decentralization of agriculture in a rotary aeroponic cultivation chamber can eliminate virtually all of these issues when scaled to the masses around the globe. Nonperishable compostable seed pods that contain the required inputs for plant growth can be shipped cheaply and placed directly into the RACC. Technologies such as computer vision plant health monitoring, deep learning system optimization, and blockchain traceability will enable the future of decentralized agriculture.</span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/14/2021<br>      Modified by: Ivan&nbsp;Ball</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The revolutionary design of the RACC, protected by an international PCT patent, houses a revolving aeroponic tower which optimizes the square footage used to grow plants with the least amount of power consumption and moving parts. The goal of Phase I research was to evaluate the feasibility of the RACC system, optimize lighting conditions, and operational parameters to maximize production of safe, healthy, and nutritious produce in an resource use efficient manner. After several experiments the Phase I project confirmed the feasibility for plant growth across 8 different varieties of plants, including leafy greens, herbs, and microgreens under residential home conditions.  During the Phase I experiments, several key discoveries were made and will be explored deeper. The first key finding was that full spectrum lighting resulted in superior growth and user experience than Red/Blue lighting. After analyzing the data of the lighting experiments, it was noted that the rotary aeroponic method stimulates plant growth via triggering shade avoidance responses. Additionally, crop growth and nutrition are dependent on the combination of rotation and light spectra after looking at the differences in plant tower rotation speed and light recipe selection. Further experimentation is needed to confirm these findings.   As for the rotary aeroponic chamber design, additional cooling is not necessary when growing under residential environmental conditions. A new improved airflow design will enable an increased light input to further optimize the yield and power use efficiency of the system. The use of computer vision and deep learning allows non-invasive detection of plant traits to continually improve the systems performance over time. This will be important to include in the system design for commercialization to assist residential consumers to grow complex varieties of produce in their homes around the globe.  Supply chain disruptions over the past year have caused shortages and price increases of food. Climate change and soil degradation is creating a challenge for farmers to keep up with the demands of an exponentially increasing population. Food waste from our existing and complex supply chain contributes to large amounts of greenhouse gases. Pesticides and chemical contaminations have compromised the safety of our food system and sustainability of our ecosystem. Decentralization of agriculture in a rotary aeroponic cultivation chamber can eliminate virtually all of these issues when scaled to the masses around the globe. Nonperishable compostable seed pods that contain the required inputs for plant growth can be shipped cheaply and placed directly into the RACC. Technologies such as computer vision plant health monitoring, deep learning system optimization, and blockchain traceability will enable the future of decentralized agriculture.       Last Modified: 10/14/2021       Submitted by: Ivan Ball]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
