<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[GeoPRISMS Synthesis Workshop: Volatiles from Source to Surface]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>52379.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>54221</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OCE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Gail Christeson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>gchriste@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922952</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Volatiles (e.g., water, carbon dioxide, sulfur, chlorine, fluorine) play important roles in nearly every Earth process, from the makeup of our atmosphere to whether a volcanic eruption will be explosive. The ability to quantify and track the distribution and migration of volatiles through the Earth is fundamental to the understanding of numerous processes but requires diligent and clever methods for measuring volatile concentrations. This project will support a GeoPRISMS synthesis workshop on volatiles. Despite the clear significance of volatiles, challenges remain in understanding their storage within Earth, fluxes, chemical interactions, and roles in processes in and around tectonic plate boundaries. In the last decade, the GeoPRISMS program has led to immense progress towards understanding volatiles, but it remains to synthesize these findings across disciplines. The objectives of the workshop will be to (1) share and synthesize progress within the broad research community; (2) identify outstanding questions and foster solutions with focused working groups; (3) develop and integrate students with early-, mid-, and late-career scientists into new research initiatives; and (4) build collaboration in a multidisciplinary community. This workshop will collect and distribute datasets and education materials, as well as create 1-minute videos that highlight researchers in different stages of their careers that have contributed to the GeoPRISMS program in the last decade.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The influence of volatiles in Earth processes ranges from the structural and compositional evolution of a subducting slab, rift initiation, mantle melting, magmatic differentiation, magma ascent, and volcanic eruption and gas emission. These processes exert fundamental controls over the composition and properties of Earth’s crust, mantle, and atmosphere. The ability to understand and link these processes and track their distribution and migration throughout Earth is a fundamental requirement for linking observation and process. Interdisciplinary research projects allow for topics such as volatile transport to be approached from multiple perspectives and in varied tectonic settings, providing more observations and more robust models than can be achieved by single-discipline studies. To continue advancement in the rich and diverse field of volatiles, a workshop will be held to share discipline and GeoPRISMs site specific findings and interpretations, which will identify regions of spatial and/or scientific overlap, define focused and tractable questions, and identify action items to help address these questions. Fundamental to the success of interdisciplinary projects, however, is a basic understanding of all of the involved methodologies and their limitations. The early career portion of this workshop will serve to help bridge that gap for upcoming scientists that have had less exposure to interdisciplinary projects.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/21/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/11/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2025625</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Madison</FirstName>
<LastName>Myers</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Madison Myers</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[madison.myers@montana.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000796103</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/21/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Montana State University</Name>
<CityName>BOZEMAN</CityName>
<ZipCode>59717</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4069942381</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>216 MONTANA HALL</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Montana</StateName>
<StateCode>MT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MT01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>EJ3UF7TK8RT5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MONTANA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>HD5YDTPGA865</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Montana State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Bozeman</CityName>
<StateCode>MT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>597172470</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Montana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MT01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1573</Code>
<Text>Petrology and Geochemistry</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1620</Code>
<Text>Marine Geology and Geophysics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8076</Code>
<Text>GeoPRISMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002223DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~52379</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2022~1842</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><div class="page" title="Page 3"> <div class="section"> <div class="layoutArea"> <div class="column"> <p><span>The Volatiles from Source to Surface GeoPRISMS Synthesis Workshop took place from May 23 to 26, 2022 at Montana State University (MSU) in Bozeman, MT. Our organizing committee was composed of six early-career scientists with strong ties to volatile measurement and cycling, with half having been either directly or tangentially impacted by the GeoPRISMS program. The workshop had over 90 applicants, with 50 in-person participants accepted based on an anonymous review of their applications.</span></p> <div class="page" title="Page 3"> <div class="section"> <div class="layoutArea"> <div class="column"> <p><span>The main workshop was preceded by a half-day Early Career Session on May 23, 2022, which was open to students and untenured scientists within 5 years of their PhD. This pre-workshop meeting was attended by 27 participants (54% of attendees) and focused around networking, confidence building on anticipated research topics, and exploring future career options. For the&nbsp;</span>main workshop, the meeting was structured around eight keynote talks that were chosen to again represent a mix of career stages, disciplines, genders, and race. These talks covered a wide range of research disciplines (petrology, geochemistry, geodesy, seismology, magnetotellurics, numerical modeling, remote sensing), and focused mostly on the current state and future directions of these fields. Six of eight talks were successfully recorded and now available on the workshop website. Talks were scheduled on two separate days, and interspersed with breakout discussion and poster sessions. All participants were invited to present their research findings in a poster session, which resulted in 38 poster presentations. To facilitate discussion and participation across all attendees, four breakout sessions were held where participants were randomly assigned to one of five groups. A discussion moderator and scribe were assigned for each group (total 20 moderators, and 20 scribes). Broadly, these focused on (i) identifying remaining and new science questions; (ii) data and technology needs and synergies; and (iii) visions for the future. In between these two workshop days we organized a field trip to Yellowstone National Park, where three separate techniques for measuring gases were demonstrated.</p> <div class="page" title="Page 4"> <div class="section"> <div class="layoutArea"> <div class="column"> <p><span>The end results of this project can be found on our website (https://volatilessourcetosurface.weebly.com/) which includes a link to download the workshop report, as well as recorded lectures and outreach videos on the legacy of GeoPRISMS to early-, mid- and late- career scientists.&nbsp;</span></p> </div> </div> </div> </div> </div> </div> </div> </div> </div> </div> </div> </div><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/07/2023<br>      Modified by: Madison&nbsp;Myers</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[     The Volatiles from Source to Surface GeoPRISMS Synthesis Workshop took place from May 23 to 26, 2022 at Montana State University (MSU) in Bozeman, MT. Our organizing committee was composed of six early-career scientists with strong ties to volatile measurement and cycling, with half having been either directly or tangentially impacted by the GeoPRISMS program. The workshop had over 90 applicants, with 50 in-person participants accepted based on an anonymous review of their applications.      The main workshop was preceded by a half-day Early Career Session on May 23, 2022, which was open to students and untenured scientists within 5 years of their PhD. This pre-workshop meeting was attended by 27 participants (54% of attendees) and focused around networking, confidence building on anticipated research topics, and exploring future career options. For the main workshop, the meeting was structured around eight keynote talks that were chosen to again represent a mix of career stages, disciplines, genders, and race. These talks covered a wide range of research disciplines (petrology, geochemistry, geodesy, seismology, magnetotellurics, numerical modeling, remote sensing), and focused mostly on the current state and future directions of these fields. Six of eight talks were successfully recorded and now available on the workshop website. Talks were scheduled on two separate days, and interspersed with breakout discussion and poster sessions. All participants were invited to present their research findings in a poster session, which resulted in 38 poster presentations. To facilitate discussion and participation across all attendees, four breakout sessions were held where participants were randomly assigned to one of five groups. A discussion moderator and scribe were assigned for each group (total 20 moderators, and 20 scribes). Broadly, these focused on (i) identifying remaining and new science questions; (ii) data and technology needs and synergies; and (iii) visions for the future. In between these two workshop days we organized a field trip to Yellowstone National Park, where three separate techniques for measuring gases were demonstrated.      The end results of this project can be found on our website (https://volatilessourcetosurface.weebly.com/) which includes a link to download the workshop report, as well as recorded lectures and outreach videos on the legacy of GeoPRISMS to early-, mid- and late- career scientists.                    Last Modified: 04/07/2023       Submitted by: Madison Myers]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
