<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Glycocalyx engineering to probe the role of mucin structure in coronavirus transmission and infection]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>199276.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>199276</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Abraham Joy</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ajoy@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922913</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Project Non-Technical Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;With this award, the Biomaterials Program in the Division of Materials Research and the Chemistry of Life Processes Program in the Division of Chemistry are funding Dr. Jessica R. Kramer from The University of Utah to study the role of mucus composition in coronavirus (COV) transmission. COV-related diseases have emerged as a serious public health threat. Airborne droplets from an infected person’s cough, sneeze, or even talking are a major source of viral spread. These droplets stem from virus-laden mucosalivary fluid and land on the mucus membranes of the next potential host (mouth, airway, eyes) or on hard surfaces. There, the virus is dispersed for the next infection. Mucus is produced in hundreds of forms that vary between species, and even person-to-person. The forms present could affect how easily the viruses pass through the mucus membrane, especially since some types bind directly to COVs. Mucus forms could also affect the concentration and viability of COVs in airborne droplets. The goal of this project is to identify the forms of mucus that result in increased airborne COV transmission and infection. This will be accomplished by simulation of cough droplets produced from varied mucus and using human cells coated with varied mucus. This knowledge could lead to development of new therapeutics that disrupt COV-mucus binding, or identify populations more vulnerable to COV transmission and infection. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Project Technical Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research project undertakes study of the role of mucin glycoprotein structures in coronavirus (COV) transmission via airborne particles, fomite objects, and in cellular entry through the glycocalyx. Epithelial tissue is coated with protective mucins that are secreted to form mucus and also tethered to the cell surface to form the glycocalyx. COVs must traverse these layers before entry into host cells for replication. Viral transmission through expelled airborne mucosalivary droplets is a major mode of transmission. Mucins are produced with a variety of attached glycans specific to each host. These glycans alter the viscoelasticity of mucosalivary fluid and directly bind to COV spike proteins. These factors could affect virus loading and viability in airborne particles and could affect docking and diffusion at the cell surface. However, such questions have been challenging to answer because native mucin glycosylation is poorly-defined and not tunable by current biological methods. The PI’s lab will synthesize mucin analogs with tunable COV-binding glycan patterns and will use them to engineer the glycocalyx of live cell surfaces. Coughs will be simulated and the role of mucin structure in airborne respiratory droplet COV transmission will be examined by characterization of droplet morphology, and viral loading and viability. Docking and diffusion at the cell surface, as well as replication, will be quantified on live epithelial cells.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/30/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/30/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2026965</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jessica</FirstName>
<LastName>Kramer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jessica Kramer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jessica.kramer@utah.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000761899</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/30/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Utah</Name>
<CityName>SALT LAKE CITY</CityName>
<ZipCode>841129049</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8015816903</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>201 PRESIDENTS CIR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Utah</StateName>
<StateCode>UT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>UT01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>LL8GLEVH6MG3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF UTAH</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Utah]]></Name>
<CityName>SALT LAKE CITY</CityName>
<StateCode>UT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>841125001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[36 s wasatch dr]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Utah</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>UT01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1253</Code>
<Text>OFFICE OF MULTIDISCIPLINARY AC</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1712</Code>
<Text>DMR SHORT TERM SUPPORT</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6883</Code>
<Text>Chemistry of Life Processes</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7623</Code>
<Text>BIOMATERIALS PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7573</Code>
<Text>BIO-RELATED MATERIALS RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8614</Code>
<Text>Nanomaterials</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~199276</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The main outcome of this project was determining that mucins, which are the major protein component of mucus and saliva, reduce the ability of coronaviruses to infect live cells.</p> <p>Prior viral studies largely excluded mucins, despite their clear role in body fluids of transmission. People can have different mucin structures dues to their genetics, diet, health, and environment. We found that some mucin structures are more protective than others, due to attached sugars. We studied direct contact transmission (i.e. sharing body fluids or a sneeze in the face) as well as fomite transmission, which is where the virus is picked up off of a surface. In the fomite scenario, the virus and the mucin-containing bodily fluid dry up together. We tested glass, plastic, steel, and surgical masks as common touch surfaces. In all cases, mucins with specific sugars attached could inhibt infection of live cells. The effect was stronger when the virus and mucin dried together. If we removed the sugars from the mucin, it was no longer protective.</p> <p>We believe the data obtained in this project will be useful in identifying populations at higher risk of infection due to altered mucin structure, or for development of therapeutics that mimic mucins' inhibitory action.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/27/2022<br>      Modified by: Jessica&nbsp;Kramer</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2026965/2026965_10661437_1658947147277_toc--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2026965/2026965_10661437_1658947147277_toc--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Mucins inhibit coronavirus infection"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2026965/2026965_10661437_1658947147277_toc--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Mucins inhibit coronavirus infection"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Mucins inhibit coronavirus infection</div> <div class="imageCredit">ACS Central Science, Kramer Lab</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jessica&nbsp;Kramer</div> <div class="imageTitle">Mucins inhibit coronavirus infection</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The main outcome of this project was determining that mucins, which are the major protein component of mucus and saliva, reduce the ability of coronaviruses to infect live cells.  Prior viral studies largely excluded mucins, despite their clear role in body fluids of transmission. People can have different mucin structures dues to their genetics, diet, health, and environment. We found that some mucin structures are more protective than others, due to attached sugars. We studied direct contact transmission (i.e. sharing body fluids or a sneeze in the face) as well as fomite transmission, which is where the virus is picked up off of a surface. In the fomite scenario, the virus and the mucin-containing bodily fluid dry up together. We tested glass, plastic, steel, and surgical masks as common touch surfaces. In all cases, mucins with specific sugars attached could inhibt infection of live cells. The effect was stronger when the virus and mucin dried together. If we removed the sugars from the mucin, it was no longer protective.  We believe the data obtained in this project will be useful in identifying populations at higher risk of infection due to altered mucin structure, or for development of therapeutics that mimic mucins' inhibitory action.         Last Modified: 07/27/2022       Submitted by: Jessica Kramer]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
