<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Heap leaching and slope saturation monitoring with muon detectors]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>255945.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>255945</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Benaiah Schrag</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bschrag@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928323</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This Small Business Innovation Research Phase I (SBIR) project focuses on the development of a broad-scope technology for advanced geophysical density measurements and the monitoring of fluid fronts based on the passive detection of naturally occurring cosmic rays. The primary application area is in the mining sector where the technology is expected to be able to drive significant efficiency improvements (up to 10%) in the recovery of copper and other metals. These efficiencies could potentially result in a commercial value of close to $1 billion per year in the United States alone. The technology can also be applied to monitoring the stability of dams and levees, a widely recognized ongoing concern, where it can provide significant safety and environmental benefits.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The intellectual merit of this project is the development of field-ready instrumentation, and in particular an innovative fit-for-purpose network of cosmic ray detectors that can be easily scaled and reconfigured to cover large or small investigation areas with a customizable spatial resolution at a minimal cost. This project will also demonstrate original data inversion methodologies and function of such methods in the feasibility study.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/01/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/13/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2026042</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tancredi</FirstName>
<LastName>Botto</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Tancredi Botto</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[tbotto@muonvision.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000822736</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/01/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>MUON VISION INC.</Name>
<CityName>CAMBRIDGE</CityName>
<ZipCode>021391631</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8579980402</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>404 BROADWAY</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>VJB9AWHVFHQ5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MUON VISION INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[MUON VISION INC.]]></Name>
<CityName>cambridge</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021391631</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[404 broadway]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>100E</Code>
<Text>Novel devices &amp; vacuum electronics</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5187</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8616</Code>
<Text>Instr Rsrch,Metro&amp;Std NanTech</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~255945</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>In this work we studied the feasibility of using muon radiography as a novel technique for improving the efficiency of various mining activities and built a suitable field-read sensor ready for field testing.</p> <p>Muons are naturally occurring, deeply penetrating subatomic particles originating in the upper layers of the earth atmosphere and reaching everywhere on the surface of the earth. In close analogy to a medical X-ray, muon radiography is a technique for developing images or 3D maps of the distribution of matter density inside even very large objects. In the past, this technique has been applied to imaging the inside of volcanoes, pyramids, and even nuclear reactors.</p> <p>Our detailed simulation results show that muon radiography is also very well suited for determining the density distribution inside heaps of mineral ore undergoing metal extraction via the leaching process. In addition, we also showed that the technique is sensitive to density changes over time, such as those that may occur when the leaching fluids are percolating through the heap. This has significant economic value as knowledge of this fluid distribution can be used to ultimately increase the efficiency for metal recovery and extraction, as well as optimize water consumption and the safety of the overall operation in terms of preventing significant landslides.</p> <p>Similarly, our results also show that muon radiography could be used also in monitoring the stability of levees or earthen dams, such as those built around mine tailings storage facilities. This could also have significant impact as tailing dam failures are often catastrophic for both the environment and nearby communities. Our work suggests that with the help of muon radiography, technical experts could build a better model of a dam leading to a more confident analysis of its structural stability.</p> <p>In addition to the above work, we also built a prototype sensor ready for field tests and demonstration work. A necessary requirement for a muon radiography sensor is the ability to detect individual muons and for each, determine their arrival direction. This has been realized by a combination of segmented detector elements coupled with high-sensitivity front-end electronics. Our muon sensor is low-cost, lightweight, low-power and can be entirely operated remotely. It also features a novel conveyance mechanism that allows it to be moved to various locations under the asset under investigation. We anticipate field testing this sensor in an actual mine environment in the coming months. &nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/22/2021<br>      Modified by: Tancredi&nbsp;Botto</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ In this work we studied the feasibility of using muon radiography as a novel technique for improving the efficiency of various mining activities and built a suitable field-read sensor ready for field testing.  Muons are naturally occurring, deeply penetrating subatomic particles originating in the upper layers of the earth atmosphere and reaching everywhere on the surface of the earth. In close analogy to a medical X-ray, muon radiography is a technique for developing images or 3D maps of the distribution of matter density inside even very large objects. In the past, this technique has been applied to imaging the inside of volcanoes, pyramids, and even nuclear reactors.  Our detailed simulation results show that muon radiography is also very well suited for determining the density distribution inside heaps of mineral ore undergoing metal extraction via the leaching process. In addition, we also showed that the technique is sensitive to density changes over time, such as those that may occur when the leaching fluids are percolating through the heap. This has significant economic value as knowledge of this fluid distribution can be used to ultimately increase the efficiency for metal recovery and extraction, as well as optimize water consumption and the safety of the overall operation in terms of preventing significant landslides.  Similarly, our results also show that muon radiography could be used also in monitoring the stability of levees or earthen dams, such as those built around mine tailings storage facilities. This could also have significant impact as tailing dam failures are often catastrophic for both the environment and nearby communities. Our work suggests that with the help of muon radiography, technical experts could build a better model of a dam leading to a more confident analysis of its structural stability.  In addition to the above work, we also built a prototype sensor ready for field tests and demonstration work. A necessary requirement for a muon radiography sensor is the ability to detect individual muons and for each, determine their arrival direction. This has been realized by a combination of segmented detector elements coupled with high-sensitivity front-end electronics. Our muon sensor is low-cost, lightweight, low-power and can be entirely operated remotely. It also features a novel conveyance mechanism that allows it to be moved to various locations under the asset under investigation. We anticipate field testing this sensor in an actual mine environment in the coming months.            Last Modified: 11/22/2021       Submitted by: Tancredi Botto]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
