<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Stabilization of the desired epitopes of hRSV-F protein for efficient absorption through the gut]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>256000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>276000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Erik Pierstorff</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>epiersto@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922165</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project will be to provide global populations with a safe, affordable and viable edible vaccine against the human respiratory syncytial virus (hRSV). hRSV is a critical global health problem, annually affecting 64 million people and causing over 160,000 death, motivating a vaccine. Natural food-derived vaccines offer advantages over traditional injections by providing a safe, affordable, non-invasive, non-egg-based (reduced allergenic risk), vegan-friendly, effective and efficient antigen-delivery system. The project addresses this need by developing a cherry-tomato-based oral vaccine that can be administered painlessly in a chewable gummy-like pill formulation or in oral drops.  The proposed fruit-vaccines will minimize the global incidence of hRSV through scalable production and distribution, increasing global accessibility and vaccination rates. Furthermore, with fewer disposables it is more environmentally friendly. This method could apply broadly to other oral-delivery platforms.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Phase I project will advance peptide-based oral-delivery platforms.  The project will improve the yield and consistent expression of the immunogenic antigen (hRSV-F protein) in the plant, both pre- and post-harvest, as well as before and after delivery into the body. The approach involves bioengineering the plant-optimized gene for the hRSV-F protein to improve its stability by blocking undesirable cleavage sites while retaining the desirable protective epitopes of the hRSV-F immunogen. Transgenic plants expressing the stabilized hRSV-F in the tomato fruits will be grown in a greenhouse. The hRSV-F-containing cherry-tomatoes will be harvested, homogenized (pureed), and then lyophilized (freeze-dried) to formulate innovative vaccine purees or pills, respectively. Tasks include conducting qualitative and quantitative analyses, such as color, consistency, pH, concentration of intact hRSV-F protein, its potential degradation products and desired epitope/s, analyzed using enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA), western-blot and high-performance liquid chromatography.  These tests will help characterize the persistence and effectiveness of the proposed changes on hRSV-F protein expression, yield, and stability in fresh-fruits, tomato-puree and in the freeze-dried fruit-pills. Similar assessments will be performed also post-ingestion, in the gut contents and in blood of mice.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/23/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/06/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2026281</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Swarnamali</FirstName>
<LastName>Rupassara</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>I</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Swarnamali I Rupassara</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[indurupassara@gmail.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000748970</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/23/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>FruitVaccine Incorporation</Name>
<CityName>CHAMPAIGN</CityName>
<ZipCode>618207460</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2173690605</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>60 HAZELWOOD DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>Q6NEUVB7V6S3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>FRUITVACCINE INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[FruitVaccine Inc.]]></Name>
<CityName>Champaign</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>618207460</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[60 Hazelwood Dr.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8091</Code>
<Text>SBIR Outreach &amp; Tech. Assist</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>008E</Code>
<Text>Gene and Drug Delivery</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8038</Code>
<Text>Biotechnology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~276000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The infectious respiratory disease caused by human respiratory syncytial virus (hRSV) is a critical global health problem that annually affects 64 million people and causes 160,000 deaths. The need for a preventive vaccine against hRSV is urgent, yet none is available on the market. FruitVaccine Inc. (<a href="http://www.fruitvaccine.org/">http://www.fruitvaccine.org/</a>), in this NSF-SBIR funded project, addresses that dire and urgent need by developing a fruit-based low-cost, orally-administered subunit vaccine against hRSV that increases the availability of vaccinations to global populations.&nbsp; By producing vaccines at low-cost in an easily scalable manner, this project can promote new trends in the vaccine industry that will increase the number of global vaccinations. The ultimate goal of our efforts is to develop a universal respiratory vaccine by also targeting other globally problematic respiratory diseases such as Covid-19 and Influenza.</p> <p>FruitVaccine Research Team has created six improved gene constructs from our plant-optimized parent-gene coding for the hRSV immunogenic F-protein (hRSV-F), to achieve sufficient and consistent expression of the immunogen in the plant, both pre- and post-harvest, as well as before- and after-delivery into the body (<strong>Fig 1</strong>). &nbsp;The approach involved bioengineering the plant-optimized hRSV-F gene to improve its stability by blocking undesirable cleavage sites within protective desirable epitopes of hRSV-F immunogen, then incorporating the stabilized hRSV-F gene into cherry-tomatoes, growing those transgenic plants in a greenhouse, harvesting the hRSV-F-containing fruits, homogenizing (pureeing), and then lyophilizing (freeze-drying) those fruits to formulate innovative pills. &nbsp;Genetic engineering of the hRSV-F immunogen were conducted to 1) maximize its plant-expression levels, and 2) stabilize the desired epitopes of plant-optimized viral immunogen incorporated into and expressed in fruits, during processing, formulation and after ingestion. We are finalizing our in-vivo experiments in preparation for our NSF-SBIR Phase II application.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The NSF-SBIR Phase 1 Award also qualified us to take part in two of NSF?s entrepreneurial customer discovery training programs, each lasted approximately two months, in the aim to validate/invalidate our hypotheses regarding product-market fit between our company?s value proposition and our anticipated customer segment(s): <strong>1) Boot Camp (completed</strong> in early 2021), and our Successful completion of that qualified us for NSF?s more comprehensive <strong>2)</strong> <strong>All-SBIR Innovation Corps (<a href="https://www.nsf.gov/news/special_reports/i-corps/index.jsp">I-Corps</a>) Program</strong>, which we completed in summer 2021.&nbsp; FruitVaccine team conducted comprehensive interviews with 135 healthcare and vaccine providers and professionals across the US to learn about their experiences, practices, and challenges in providing routine vaccinations to learn about their current jobs, workflow, and experience with existing solutions to discover those customers? needs, pain points, and decision criteria. We spoke with a diverse set of individuals who fill separate roles within independent pharmacies, hospitals, public health departments, university clinics, pharmaceutical companies, NGOs, and other organizations. We recorded these interviews and later analyzed the transcripts using text mining and informatics to see if strategically meaningful patterns could be derived from the questions we asked.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>We discovered that the greatest challenge many healthcare providers face is the need to improve workflow efficiency, as the current injectable-vaccination process takes an average of 23 minutes per patient (<strong>Fig 2</strong>). In the pharmacy space, this is being driven by shrinking reimbursement rates from pharmacy benefit managers, necessitating that a higher volume of services be provided to patients. As margins continue to tighten, pharmacists could be forced to discontinue relatively time-intensive services such as intramuscular vaccine administration, having to spend additional times with average of 24% of their patients who express needle-fear (<strong>Fig 3</strong>). Oral vaccine pills, which take only about 5 minutes to serve, would provide them relief as a time-saving measure and improve the patient/provider experience (<strong>Rupassara et al 2022</strong>).&nbsp;</p> <p>NSF also organized <strong>Dawnbreaker</strong> to guide us with our Commercial Plan. We estimated our Serviceable Obtainable Market (SOM), Serviceable Available Market (SAM), and Total Available Market (TAM). The global vaccine market can be segmented by region, patient type, disease indication, technology, route of administration, and distribution channel. Our initial target will be immunosuppressed children and adults, as well as elderly (&ge;65 years) in the United States who are at high risk for severe hRSV infection. Assuming similar compliance rates as the pneumonia vaccine, our SOM in 2027 is $225millon by serving estimated 5% of vaccine providers (e.g., clinics, pharmacies, health depts.) in US market (2.5M people x $ 150/dose initial price). SAM is $7.5 billion with estimated 70% elderly and 25% immunosuppressed individuals aged 6 months to 64 years in the US (50M people ? $150/dose).&nbsp; Our TAM is $18.8 billion in a bottom-up estimate of global hRSV market by applying SAM assumptions to historical and forecasted regional market shares ($7.5B/0.4, with the assumption that the US vaccine market is approximately 40% of the global market) (<strong>Fig 4</strong>).</p> <p>References:</p> <p>Rupassara SI, Kindt JW, Kazi N, Kahanda I (2022). &nbsp;"Challenges and Opportunities in Current Vaccine Technology and Administration: A Comprehensive Survey." Journal of the American Medical Informatics Association (submitted).</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/02/2022<br>      Modified by: Swarnamali&nbsp;I&nbsp;Rupassara</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2026281/2026281_10709569_1646203138869_FruitVaccineInc_EngineeredGeneConstruct--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2026281/2026281_10709569_1646203138869_FruitVaccineInc_EngineeredGeneConstruct--rgov-800width.jpg" title="An engineered gene construct"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2026281/2026281_10709569_1646203138869_FruitVaccineInc_EngineeredGeneConstruct--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="An engineered gene construct"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 1: An engineered gene construct</div> <div class="imageCredit">FruitVaccine Inc.</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Swarnamali&nbsp;I&nbsp;Rupassara</div> <div class="imageTitle">An engineered gene construct</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2026281/2026281_10709569_1646202989961_FruitVaccineInc_LengthVaccinationProcess--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2026281/2026281_10709569_1646202989961_FruitVaccineInc_LengthVaccinationProcess--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Length of vaccination process"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2026281/2026281_10709569_1646202989961_FruitVaccineInc_LengthVaccinationProcess--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Length of vaccination process"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 2: Total length of vaccination process per patient</div> <div class="imageCredit">FruitVaccine Inc.</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Swarnamali&nbsp;I&nbsp;Rupassara</div> <div class="imageTitle">Length of vaccination process</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2026281/2026281_10709569_1646203336535_FruitVaccineInc_PatientNeedleFear--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2026281/2026281_10709569_1646203336535_FruitVaccineInc_PatientNeedleFear--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Patient needle-fear"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2026281/2026281_10709569_1646203336535_FruitVaccineInc_PatientNeedleFear--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Patient needle-fear"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 3: Percentage of patients afraid of needles as estimated by the interviewees</div> <div class="imageCredit">FruitVaccine Inc.</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Swarnamali&nbsp;I&nbsp;Rupassara</div> <div class="imageTitle">Patient needle-fear</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2026281/2026281_10709569_1646203597678_FruitVaccineInc_SOM_SAM_TAM--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2026281/2026281_10709569_1646203597678_FruitVaccineInc_SOM_SAM_TAM--rgov-800width.jpg" title="SOM, SAM, and TAM"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2026281/2026281_10709569_1646203597678_FruitVaccineInc_SOM_SAM_TAM--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="SOM, SAM, and TAM"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 4: Market opportunity for FruitVaccine's Annual Vaccine: SOM, SAM, and TAM estimates for 2027</div> <div class="imageCredit">FruitVaccine Inc.</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Swarnamali&nbsp;I&nbsp;Rupassara</div> <div class="imageTitle">SOM, SAM, and TAM</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The infectious respiratory disease caused by human respiratory syncytial virus (hRSV) is a critical global health problem that annually affects 64 million people and causes 160,000 deaths. The need for a preventive vaccine against hRSV is urgent, yet none is available on the market. FruitVaccine Inc. (http://www.fruitvaccine.org/), in this NSF-SBIR funded project, addresses that dire and urgent need by developing a fruit-based low-cost, orally-administered subunit vaccine against hRSV that increases the availability of vaccinations to global populations.  By producing vaccines at low-cost in an easily scalable manner, this project can promote new trends in the vaccine industry that will increase the number of global vaccinations. The ultimate goal of our efforts is to develop a universal respiratory vaccine by also targeting other globally problematic respiratory diseases such as Covid-19 and Influenza.  FruitVaccine Research Team has created six improved gene constructs from our plant-optimized parent-gene coding for the hRSV immunogenic F-protein (hRSV-F), to achieve sufficient and consistent expression of the immunogen in the plant, both pre- and post-harvest, as well as before- and after-delivery into the body (Fig 1).  The approach involved bioengineering the plant-optimized hRSV-F gene to improve its stability by blocking undesirable cleavage sites within protective desirable epitopes of hRSV-F immunogen, then incorporating the stabilized hRSV-F gene into cherry-tomatoes, growing those transgenic plants in a greenhouse, harvesting the hRSV-F-containing fruits, homogenizing (pureeing), and then lyophilizing (freeze-drying) those fruits to formulate innovative pills.  Genetic engineering of the hRSV-F immunogen were conducted to 1) maximize its plant-expression levels, and 2) stabilize the desired epitopes of plant-optimized viral immunogen incorporated into and expressed in fruits, during processing, formulation and after ingestion. We are finalizing our in-vivo experiments in preparation for our NSF-SBIR Phase II application.     The NSF-SBIR Phase 1 Award also qualified us to take part in two of NSF?s entrepreneurial customer discovery training programs, each lasted approximately two months, in the aim to validate/invalidate our hypotheses regarding product-market fit between our company?s value proposition and our anticipated customer segment(s): 1) Boot Camp (completed in early 2021), and our Successful completion of that qualified us for NSF?s more comprehensive 2) All-SBIR Innovation Corps (I-Corps) Program, which we completed in summer 2021.  FruitVaccine team conducted comprehensive interviews with 135 healthcare and vaccine providers and professionals across the US to learn about their experiences, practices, and challenges in providing routine vaccinations to learn about their current jobs, workflow, and experience with existing solutions to discover those customers? needs, pain points, and decision criteria. We spoke with a diverse set of individuals who fill separate roles within independent pharmacies, hospitals, public health departments, university clinics, pharmaceutical companies, NGOs, and other organizations. We recorded these interviews and later analyzed the transcripts using text mining and informatics to see if strategically meaningful patterns could be derived from the questions we asked.      We discovered that the greatest challenge many healthcare providers face is the need to improve workflow efficiency, as the current injectable-vaccination process takes an average of 23 minutes per patient (Fig 2). In the pharmacy space, this is being driven by shrinking reimbursement rates from pharmacy benefit managers, necessitating that a higher volume of services be provided to patients. As margins continue to tighten, pharmacists could be forced to discontinue relatively time-intensive services such as intramuscular vaccine administration, having to spend additional times with average of 24% of their patients who express needle-fear (Fig 3). Oral vaccine pills, which take only about 5 minutes to serve, would provide them relief as a time-saving measure and improve the patient/provider experience (Rupassara et al 2022).   NSF also organized Dawnbreaker to guide us with our Commercial Plan. We estimated our Serviceable Obtainable Market (SOM), Serviceable Available Market (SAM), and Total Available Market (TAM). The global vaccine market can be segmented by region, patient type, disease indication, technology, route of administration, and distribution channel. Our initial target will be immunosuppressed children and adults, as well as elderly (&ge;65 years) in the United States who are at high risk for severe hRSV infection. Assuming similar compliance rates as the pneumonia vaccine, our SOM in 2027 is $225millon by serving estimated 5% of vaccine providers (e.g., clinics, pharmacies, health depts.) in US market (2.5M people x $ 150/dose initial price). SAM is $7.5 billion with estimated 70% elderly and 25% immunosuppressed individuals aged 6 months to 64 years in the US (50M people ? $150/dose).  Our TAM is $18.8 billion in a bottom-up estimate of global hRSV market by applying SAM assumptions to historical and forecasted regional market shares ($7.5B/0.4, with the assumption that the US vaccine market is approximately 40% of the global market) (Fig 4).  References:  Rupassara SI, Kindt JW, Kazi N, Kahanda I (2022).  "Challenges and Opportunities in Current Vaccine Technology and Administration: A Comprehensive Survey." Journal of the American Medical Informatics Association (submitted).       Last Modified: 03/02/2022       Submitted by: Swarnamali I Rupassara]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
