<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Using Immersive Virtual Reality For High-Quality Training to Caregivers Working With Seniors]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>255901.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>275901</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Diane Hickey</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project will be significant for helping senior caregivers optimally understand and respond to cognitive changes in older adults through a new Virtual Reality (VR) The project will result in a high-quality, effective training module for helping senior caregivers optimally understand and respond to cognitive changes in older adults. This will enhance the competence, confidence, and motivation of their nursing staff, and help reduce staff turnover. The solution will empower caregivers to effectively attend to the needs of the elderly in a way that enhances seniors’ quality-of-life and facilitates ‘aging in place,’ hence contributing towards increasing well-being among the elderly population and alleviating the societal costs of aging.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project addresses the technical challenge of developing VR content that effectively promotes caregiver knowledge acquisition, skill development, and motivation increases, while keeping the training experience relatively brief and efficient. Unlike simple memorization of information, positive psychological outcomes like enhanced motivation are challenging to generate. This project will strategically employ cinematic directing techniques at key points in the VR training - a new  approach to VR training. The solution leverages principles from the cognitive neuroscience of learning to deliver innovations in VR content design, analysis and delivery. Research objectives include: (1) building an engaging VR training module centered around teaching empathy and communication skills, which is enhanced with cinematic directing elements, (2) assessing the usability and feasibility of the developed content for achieving the desired outcomes in the short- and long-term, (3) building and assessing a VR training module centered around teaching observation and behavioral skills to senior caregivers, which includes embedded interactive testing elements.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/25/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/09/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2026134</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>William</FirstName>
<LastName>Maddox</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>T</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>William T Maddox</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ikonahealth_grants@outlook.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000807642</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/25/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate>10/09/2020</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tim</FirstName>
<LastName>Fitzpatrick</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Tim Fitzpatrick</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ikonahealth_grants2@outlook.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000800200</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>10/09/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>IKONA, INC.</Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<ZipCode>100166759</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7745733432</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>135 MADISON AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[FL 5]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>VFHNQA5CMAR5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>IKONA INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[IKONA, INC.]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>100013089</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8091</Code>
<Text>SBIR Outreach &amp; Tech. Assist</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>079E</Code>
<Text>VISUALIZATION &amp; VIRTUAL DESIGN</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1707</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED LEARNING TECHNOLOGIES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8018</Code>
<Text>Smart and Connected Health</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>Health Care Enterprise Systems</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8032</Code>
<Text>Software Services and Applications</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8033</Code>
<Text>Hardware Software Integration</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01001920DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~255901</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~20000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The goal of the proposed research project was three-fold: 1. to build and evaluate virtual reality-based content for home dialysis familiarization; 2. to build and evaluate an online learning platform to support kidney education for patients and their families; and 3. to identify potential segments and settings within kidney care that could serve as initial segments for commercialization through rigorous customer discovery and market validation. During this Phase I project we leveraged experiences in VR development and film production, project management, software development, clinical education, rapid prototyping, data analysis and customer discovery to support our research efforts.</p> <p>We encountered technical hurdles along the way on several fronts, including all three of our research objectives. From high-level architecture considerations and pandemic-related safety protocols to hundreds of user experience (UX) and user interface (UI) improvements, we had to make difficult, deliberate decisions to reach our research goals despite having to make adjustments that were not part of our planning process. Our knowledge of the current product, its capabilities and role in the end-user's environment is stronger now because we faced these technical hurdles.</p> <p>As we conclude our Phase I project, we feel confident in our potential to bring a solution to market that will address critical gaps and challenges in the kidney care ecosystem today. From home dialysis familiarization to individualized education pathways for every person affected by kidney disease, the reach and scale of effective learning are significant. Based on our extensive customer discovery efforts we believe care settings from primary care and nephrology practices to dialysis clinics and patients at home will be able to access the value of our personalized learning solutions. We also believe our commercial efforts will unlock several existing barriers to access for many earlier stage patients who need more effective learning tools to slow the progression of their disease and avoid high cost, adverse events where most care and spend are focused today.</p> <p>The outcomes of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project are significant for helping people with kidney disease better understand their health and treatment options in ways that lead to higher confidence, lower anxiety, better transitions and health outcomes. The project resulted in the creation of novel virtual reality (VR)- and online-based learning tools to help patients on dialysis, their care partners, frontline health professionals, and people affected by earlier stages of chronic kidney disease (CKD). We evaluated these tools within our target user populations and found high usability and feasibility, as well as improvements in confidence and anxiety, and increased demand for additional VR-based content throughout the dialysis patient journey. This will help more patients understand home-based treatment options, assist dialysis providers with transitioning patients to home-based modalities, and ultimately support successful transitions for patients in terms of preparation, training, and support while receiving dialysis at home. The solution will empower health professionals to effectively educate their patient populations in ways that also enhance personalized learning pathways, improve learning and retention, and help alleviate the costs of inadequate education often caused by staffing shortages, highly variable education, and traditional education methods that fall short of patients' needs and expectations.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/03/2021<br>      Modified by: Tim&nbsp;Fitzpatrick</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The goal of the proposed research project was three-fold: 1. to build and evaluate virtual reality-based content for home dialysis familiarization; 2. to build and evaluate an online learning platform to support kidney education for patients and their families; and 3. to identify potential segments and settings within kidney care that could serve as initial segments for commercialization through rigorous customer discovery and market validation. During this Phase I project we leveraged experiences in VR development and film production, project management, software development, clinical education, rapid prototyping, data analysis and customer discovery to support our research efforts.  We encountered technical hurdles along the way on several fronts, including all three of our research objectives. From high-level architecture considerations and pandemic-related safety protocols to hundreds of user experience (UX) and user interface (UI) improvements, we had to make difficult, deliberate decisions to reach our research goals despite having to make adjustments that were not part of our planning process. Our knowledge of the current product, its capabilities and role in the end-user's environment is stronger now because we faced these technical hurdles.  As we conclude our Phase I project, we feel confident in our potential to bring a solution to market that will address critical gaps and challenges in the kidney care ecosystem today. From home dialysis familiarization to individualized education pathways for every person affected by kidney disease, the reach and scale of effective learning are significant. Based on our extensive customer discovery efforts we believe care settings from primary care and nephrology practices to dialysis clinics and patients at home will be able to access the value of our personalized learning solutions. We also believe our commercial efforts will unlock several existing barriers to access for many earlier stage patients who need more effective learning tools to slow the progression of their disease and avoid high cost, adverse events where most care and spend are focused today.  The outcomes of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project are significant for helping people with kidney disease better understand their health and treatment options in ways that lead to higher confidence, lower anxiety, better transitions and health outcomes. The project resulted in the creation of novel virtual reality (VR)- and online-based learning tools to help patients on dialysis, their care partners, frontline health professionals, and people affected by earlier stages of chronic kidney disease (CKD). We evaluated these tools within our target user populations and found high usability and feasibility, as well as improvements in confidence and anxiety, and increased demand for additional VR-based content throughout the dialysis patient journey. This will help more patients understand home-based treatment options, assist dialysis providers with transitioning patients to home-based modalities, and ultimately support successful transitions for patients in terms of preparation, training, and support while receiving dialysis at home. The solution will empower health professionals to effectively educate their patient populations in ways that also enhance personalized learning pathways, improve learning and retention, and help alleviate the costs of inadequate education often caused by staffing shortages, highly variable education, and traditional education methods that fall short of patients' needs and expectations.       Last Modified: 10/03/2021       Submitted by: Tim Fitzpatrick]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
