<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase II:  Developing suspended microchannel resonators as a platform for personalized medicine in cancer]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1000000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1500000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Cooperative Agreement</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Henry Ahn</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>hahn@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927069</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase II project is to identify potential therapies for a multiple myeloma (MM) patients. Newly diagnosed MM is typically sensitive to a variety of therapies, but relapse is common in later stages.  Personalized analysis would improve treatment decisions.  This project will develop new testing for personalized medicine. Although the initial target is MM, this can potentially be applied to other cancers or diseases.  Personalized medicine can lead to reduced healthcare costs, optimized drug development, and improved patient care.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase II project will help develop methods and techniques that will be used to offer new tests for guiding the treatment of multiple myeloma (MM) patients. The test relies on resolving changes of cancer cells collected from patients upon exposure to various drug options by measuring the mass of individual cells. Today MM is the second most common hematologic malignancy in the world. Unfortunately, today there are no biomarkers to define therapeutic susceptibility of MM patients to identify a personalized treatment regimen. This project aims to address this problem by developing a high-throughput single-cell mass measurement platform based on suspended microchannel resonators (SMR) to resolve the effects of the drugs on the cancer cells. In this project a new generation of SMR chips with linked single-cell imaging, image processing and cell classification will be developed to analyze a 20-drug panel in three hours.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/11/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/13/2023</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>CoopAgrmnt</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041, 47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2026060</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Selim</FirstName>
<LastName>Olcum</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Selim A Olcum</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[solcum@travera.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000755447</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/11/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>TRAVERA, INC.</Name>
<CityName>MEDFORD</CityName>
<ZipCode>021554247</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6505767738</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>200 BOSTON AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[STE 1500]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>U8A5ACZ33ZJ8</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRAVERA, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Travera LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021394534</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[99a Erie Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5373</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase II</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>008E</Code>
<Text>Gene and Drug Delivery</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>165E</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase IIB</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>6883</Code>
<Text>CHEMISTRY OF LIFE PROCESSES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8038</Code>
<Text>Biotechnology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002223DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~1000000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2022~500000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Travera aims to improve personalized medicine strategies in cancer by introducing a rapid therapy guidance test based on measuring how cancer cells change their mass&nbsp;<em>in vitro</em>&nbsp;in response to therapies. This new approach is enabled by the suspended microchannel resonator (SMR), which is an extremely sensitive microfluidic mass sensor developed originally at MIT.&nbsp;SMR can measure the mass of single cells with exquisite precision as they flow through a microfluidic channel.</p> <p>Throughout the Phase II award period, Travera has developed a CLIA compliant rapid therapy guidance test (Travera-RTG) that can measure how cancer cells in a patient's tumor biopsy respond to a selected panel of drugs, to guide physicians to select the best therapy option for their patients. During the Phase II award we have streamlined the sample collection and shipment procedures, developed cell isolation and cell dosing techniques for different tissue types (including malignant fluids, bone marrow, blood, fine and core needle biopsies and resections), designed and fabricated new generation SMR sensors for rapid and automated single cell mass measurements, introduced linked single-cell imaging capabilities for identifying tumor cells of interest in the flow of cells to improve assay fidelity, implemented quality control and quality management protocols to the entirety of our pre-analytical, analytical and post-analytical platform.&nbsp;Furthermore, using samples from ~50 patients in various clinical studies with a range of partner oncologists, we have shown that Travera's approach is more than 80% accurate predicting the patient outcome for a given therapy. &nbsp;</p> <p>The technological advancements we achieved during the Phase II project enabled Travera to perform its test and return results within 48 hours after sample collection. Combined with the high predictive accuracy we achieved, the fast turn-around-time, helps physicians to make quick therapeutic decisions for their already frail patients, improving patient&rsquo;s quality of life.&nbsp;</p> <p>Currently, Travera is pursuing to expand its clinical validation data through multiple studies established with partnering institutions and practicing physicians before Travera-RTG test can seek reimbursement through Centers for Medicare &amp; Medicaid Services (CMS).</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/13/2023<br>      Modified by: Selim&nbsp;A&nbsp;Olcum</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2026060/2026060_10706474_1673641669113_Figure1_v2_HD--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2026060/2026060_10706474_1673641669113_Figure1_v2_HD--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Travera testing pipeline"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2026060/2026060_10706474_1673641669113_Figure1_v2_HD--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Travera testing pipeline"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Schematic overview of the full testing pipeline including sample collection and shipment, tumor cell isolation and overnight drug incubation, single-cell mass data collection using SMR-based instruments with linked imaging, downstream classification, statistical analysis, and results reporting.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Travera</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Selim&nbsp;A&nbsp;Olcum</div> <div class="imageTitle">Travera testing pipeline</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Travera aims to improve personalized medicine strategies in cancer by introducing a rapid therapy guidance test based on measuring how cancer cells change their mass in vitro in response to therapies. This new approach is enabled by the suspended microchannel resonator (SMR), which is an extremely sensitive microfluidic mass sensor developed originally at MIT. SMR can measure the mass of single cells with exquisite precision as they flow through a microfluidic channel.  Throughout the Phase II award period, Travera has developed a CLIA compliant rapid therapy guidance test (Travera-RTG) that can measure how cancer cells in a patient's tumor biopsy respond to a selected panel of drugs, to guide physicians to select the best therapy option for their patients. During the Phase II award we have streamlined the sample collection and shipment procedures, developed cell isolation and cell dosing techniques for different tissue types (including malignant fluids, bone marrow, blood, fine and core needle biopsies and resections), designed and fabricated new generation SMR sensors for rapid and automated single cell mass measurements, introduced linked single-cell imaging capabilities for identifying tumor cells of interest in the flow of cells to improve assay fidelity, implemented quality control and quality management protocols to the entirety of our pre-analytical, analytical and post-analytical platform. Furthermore, using samples from ~50 patients in various clinical studies with a range of partner oncologists, we have shown that Travera's approach is more than 80% accurate predicting the patient outcome for a given therapy.    The technological advancements we achieved during the Phase II project enabled Travera to perform its test and return results within 48 hours after sample collection. Combined with the high predictive accuracy we achieved, the fast turn-around-time, helps physicians to make quick therapeutic decisions for their already frail patients, improving patient’s quality of life.   Currently, Travera is pursuing to expand its clinical validation data through multiple studies established with partnering institutions and practicing physicians before Travera-RTG test can seek reimbursement through Centers for Medicare &amp; Medicaid Services (CMS).          Last Modified: 01/13/2023       Submitted by: Selim A Olcum]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
