<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Novel Laparoscopic Device for treatment of Varicocele]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>256000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>256000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Henry Ahn</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>hahn@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927069</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is to advance translation of a new procedure to address varicocele, the most common cause of male infertility. Varicocele affects approximately 30 million men in the US alone and is the direct cause of over 1.5 million involuntary infertile couples. It is also associated with testicular pain, erectile disfunction, and low free testosterone. Current treatments have varying success, with only 50% of patients noticing &gt;50% improvement in sperm parameters and up to 37% of patients showing no change. The treatment for varicocele has not changed since 1929 and consists of ligation or occlusion of the internal spermatic vein, the primary route of drainage for the testis. This project will advance a new method of treatment. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project aims at leveraging a highly effective procedure proposed to treat Varicocele. Even though surgical ligation procedures have shown promising clinical efficacy, the technical difficulty and low success rates motivate other treatment modalities. This procedure was proposed in the 1980s based on an advanced understanding of hemodynamics responsible for the pathophysiology of varicocele. Preliminary tests suggest lower complication rates and complete elimination of hydrocele formation, recurrence rate of up to 0.2%, and faster recovery times. This project will advance a technology to simplify the procedure.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/26/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/07/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041, 47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2026272</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tushar</FirstName>
<LastName>Sharma</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Tushar Sharma</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[tushar@vivifimedical.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000821167</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/26/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>VIVIFI MEDICAL LLC</Name>
<CityName>ROSHARON</CityName>
<ZipCode>775831955</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9713346157</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>10018 TESLA DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>14</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX14</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>GT2FKG1Z3GM3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>VIVIFI MEDICAL, INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[VIVIFI MEDICAL LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>Houston</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>770073371</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5000 Schuler St]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5345</Code>
<Text>BIOMEDICAL ENGINEERING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8038</Code>
<Text>Biotechnology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~256000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Vivifi Medical, LLC, has developed the first device-based treatment for varicocele. Varicocele is the most common cause of male infertility and, if untreated, can also lead to testicular pain, erectile disfunction, low systemic testosterone, and benign prostate hyperplasia. Varicocele affects approximately 30 million men in the US alone and is the direct cause of over 1.5 million involuntary infertile couples. Current methods of treatment have significantly low success rates, with only 50% of patients noticing &gt;50% improvement in sperm parameters and up to 37% of patients showing no change. The treatment for varicocele has not changed since 1929 and consists of ligation of the internal spermatic vein, the primary route of drainage of the testis. Vivifi Medical&rsquo;s technology is disrupting the current standard of care by providing surgeons with a simple-to-use tool to create a fluid shunt between the internal spermatic vein and an adjacent vein. In 1984, a shunting/anastomosis procedure was proposed as alternative treatment for varicocele and was based on an advanced understanding of hemodynamics responsible for pathophysiology of Varicocele. Through initial studies, this procedure showed groundbreaking results. Since then, this procedure has been used in multiple independent studies to treat patients with close to 100% success rates. Additionally, the complication rates are significantly lower, with complete elimination of hydrocele formation, recurrence rate of up to 0.2% and faster recovery times. However, this procedure has not caught widespread adoption due to the high skill required to perform this procedure.</p> <p>This SBIR project resulted in development of a minimally viable product of laparoscopic technology that will lower the barrier for urologists to perform this highly challenging procedure, thereby making this procedure a reality for patients of varicocele and infertility. In total, the resulting device will afford patients the benefits of surgery, without the risk, ultimately reducing overall cost of care associated with patients of infertility.Vivifi Medical believes its technological innovation will enable clinicians to better serve the 30 million Americans who suffer from the effects of varicocele.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Blood vessel shunting is rapidly gaining popularity due to improved understanding of physiological hemodynamics. However, shunting using currently available devices has not been feasibly demonstrated in laparoscopic procedures due to the need to access the intravascular space. Vivifi Medical has developed a novel technology, the Calexis-Lap device, that allows for laparoscopic anastomosis of blood vessels. This device will enable clinicians to safely and easily perform a procedure that has shown superior efficacy in treating varicocele. Repair of varicocele for the treatment of male infertility &ndash; the initial target patient population for Vivifi Medical &ndash; has shown superior efficacy in achieving conception over other more expensive techniques. Other clinical applications for the Vivifi technology will be explored as well.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/28/2022<br>      Modified by: Tushar&nbsp;Sharma</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Vivifi Medical, LLC, has developed the first device-based treatment for varicocele. Varicocele is the most common cause of male infertility and, if untreated, can also lead to testicular pain, erectile disfunction, low systemic testosterone, and benign prostate hyperplasia. Varicocele affects approximately 30 million men in the US alone and is the direct cause of over 1.5 million involuntary infertile couples. Current methods of treatment have significantly low success rates, with only 50% of patients noticing &gt;50% improvement in sperm parameters and up to 37% of patients showing no change. The treatment for varicocele has not changed since 1929 and consists of ligation of the internal spermatic vein, the primary route of drainage of the testis. Vivifi Medical’s technology is disrupting the current standard of care by providing surgeons with a simple-to-use tool to create a fluid shunt between the internal spermatic vein and an adjacent vein. In 1984, a shunting/anastomosis procedure was proposed as alternative treatment for varicocele and was based on an advanced understanding of hemodynamics responsible for pathophysiology of Varicocele. Through initial studies, this procedure showed groundbreaking results. Since then, this procedure has been used in multiple independent studies to treat patients with close to 100% success rates. Additionally, the complication rates are significantly lower, with complete elimination of hydrocele formation, recurrence rate of up to 0.2% and faster recovery times. However, this procedure has not caught widespread adoption due to the high skill required to perform this procedure.  This SBIR project resulted in development of a minimally viable product of laparoscopic technology that will lower the barrier for urologists to perform this highly challenging procedure, thereby making this procedure a reality for patients of varicocele and infertility. In total, the resulting device will afford patients the benefits of surgery, without the risk, ultimately reducing overall cost of care associated with patients of infertility.Vivifi Medical believes its technological innovation will enable clinicians to better serve the 30 million Americans who suffer from the effects of varicocele.     Blood vessel shunting is rapidly gaining popularity due to improved understanding of physiological hemodynamics. However, shunting using currently available devices has not been feasibly demonstrated in laparoscopic procedures due to the need to access the intravascular space. Vivifi Medical has developed a novel technology, the Calexis-Lap device, that allows for laparoscopic anastomosis of blood vessels. This device will enable clinicians to safely and easily perform a procedure that has shown superior efficacy in treating varicocele. Repair of varicocele for the treatment of male infertility &ndash; the initial target patient population for Vivifi Medical &ndash; has shown superior efficacy in achieving conception over other more expensive techniques. Other clinical applications for the Vivifi technology will be explored as well.          Last Modified: 05/28/2022       Submitted by: Tushar Sharma]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
