<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase II:  3D Printing of Thermally Stable Composites for Injection Mold Tooling]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>996150.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>996150</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Cooperative Agreement</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rajesh Mehta</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rmehta@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922174</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this SBIR Phase II project is to lower costs for injection molding, a common method of manufacturing plastic goods. Unfortunately, injection molding can be a lengthy and wasteful process because molds are designed, machined from metal, and then shipped to an injection molder. The proposed project will develop new tooling for low-volume injection molding applications at strengths and resolutions comparable with machined aluminum at a fraction of the current cost and lead time, providing extra resilience to the supply chain.  This will be used for applications in industries across automotive, aerospace, consumer product goods, and medical devices.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Phase II SBIR will apply advancements in 3D printing of fiber-reinforced photopolymers to the injection molding application.  This project will apply advancements in fiber-filled photopolymers (such as ceramic and polymer particle reinforced resins) in combination with magnetically aligned structures to injection mold tools. Tooling inserts will be tested across the most common and challenging injection molding plastics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/16/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/16/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>CoopAgrmnt</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2026079</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Joshua</FirstName>
<LastName>Martin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Joshua Martin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[josh@3dfortify.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000754365</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/16/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>3DFortify Inc.</Name>
<CityName>CHARLESTOWN</CityName>
<ZipCode>021291002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7322454321</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>75 HOOD PARK DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[FL 1]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>T163FF5M62E4</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>3D FORTIFY INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[3DFortify INC]]></Name>
<CityName>Boston</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021292856</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[510 Rutherford Ave.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5373</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase II</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8037</Code>
<Text>Advanced Manufacturing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~996150</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>3DFortify Inc. (<strong>Fortify</strong>) is a Boston-based advanced manufacturing company that is creating innovative additive technology in the form of digital light processing (DLP) 3D printing that can incorporate functional &#64257;llers to bring value and performance to photoresins. Fortify has excelled at tackling the photokinetic and rheological challenges associated with incorporating &#64257;ller into photoresins through hardware, software and materials innovations. Speci&#64257;c to this Phase II grant work, Fortify has brought the next generation of 3D printing injection mold tooling to the market.</p> <p>Intellectual merit has been demonstrated through the successful development and commericalization of new high-performance resins. The advanced materials available on the Fortify platform have best-in-class thermomechanical properties (as measured by UTS, Youngs Modulus, and HDT) and have demonstrated the ability to mold higher-temperature and filled resins that drive conventional solutions to failure. Over 1,000 polypropylene parts have been manufactured using a Fortify printed mold tool, as well as over 100 glass-filled ultem components. Innovations across materials science (rheology, photokinetics, surface chemistry), hardware (materials handling of viscous, filled resins) and software (advanced image processing for high-resolution light-cured composites) have made this work possible and have advanced the state of the art in this field.</p> <p>Broader impacts of this work are demonstrated through the success of our customers and partners. For example, Empire Group manufacturing, a local Massachusetts design and prototyping shop, has installed and used a Fortify Flux One system to service over two dozen customers. This service has made it possible for medical device OEM's to bring key products to market faster, all while using domestic suppliers. Fortify now has multiple contract manufacturers that are leveraging the outcomes of this work to bring supply chain robustness to the US while providing advantages in cost, lead-time, and design freedom for their product teams.&nbsp;</p> <p>In an effort to expand the broader impacts of this work, Fortify has engaged in learning and development content as a thought leader in the space. Webinars and white papers can be found on our website, detailing the in's and out's of additive tooling. In addition, Fortify is continuing to engage with top manufacturing universities across the US as a means of investing in the future generation of design and manufacturing talent.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/20/2022<br>      Modified by: Joshua&nbsp;Martin</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2026079/2026079_10711084_1671553141375_printer2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2026079/2026079_10711084_1671553141375_printer2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Fortify Flux One System"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2026079/2026079_10711084_1671553141375_printer2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Fortify Flux One System"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Fortify additive manufacturing system used for printed tooling.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Fortify</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Joshua&nbsp;Martin</div> <div class="imageTitle">Fortify Flux One System</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2026079/2026079_10711084_1671553471691_FortifyDemoDay-Tooling--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2026079/2026079_10711084_1671553471691_FortifyDemoDay-Tooling--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Fortify Public Demo Day"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2026079/2026079_10711084_1671553471691_FortifyDemoDay-Tooling--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Fortify Public Demo Day"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Fortify has put on a series of public training for the industry to learn about printed tooling.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Fortify</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Joshua&nbsp;Martin</div> <div class="imageTitle">Fortify Public Demo Day</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2026079/2026079_10711084_1671553549753_ImagefromiOS(22)--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2026079/2026079_10711084_1671553549753_ImagefromiOS(22)--rgov-800width.jpg" title="LCP Demo part"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2026079/2026079_10711084_1671553549753_ImagefromiOS(22)--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="LCP Demo part"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">LCP components can be made on printed tooling for the first time. This material molds at high heat and is used in electrical and medical applications.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Fortify</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Joshua&nbsp;Martin</div> <div class="imageTitle">LCP Demo part</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2026079/2026079_10711084_1671553630105_20221215_142518--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2026079/2026079_10711084_1671553630105_20221215_142518--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Demo part - Connector"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2026079/2026079_10711084_1671553630105_20221215_142518--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Demo part - Connector"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">This part demonstrates the ability to make snap-fit connectors using Fortify tooling. The material is a recycled nylon made of old fish nets.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Fortify</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Joshua&nbsp;Martin</div> <div class="imageTitle">Demo part - Connector</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ 3DFortify Inc. (Fortify) is a Boston-based advanced manufacturing company that is creating innovative additive technology in the form of digital light processing (DLP) 3D printing that can incorporate functional &#64257;llers to bring value and performance to photoresins. Fortify has excelled at tackling the photokinetic and rheological challenges associated with incorporating &#64257;ller into photoresins through hardware, software and materials innovations. Speci&#64257;c to this Phase II grant work, Fortify has brought the next generation of 3D printing injection mold tooling to the market.  Intellectual merit has been demonstrated through the successful development and commericalization of new high-performance resins. The advanced materials available on the Fortify platform have best-in-class thermomechanical properties (as measured by UTS, Youngs Modulus, and HDT) and have demonstrated the ability to mold higher-temperature and filled resins that drive conventional solutions to failure. Over 1,000 polypropylene parts have been manufactured using a Fortify printed mold tool, as well as over 100 glass-filled ultem components. Innovations across materials science (rheology, photokinetics, surface chemistry), hardware (materials handling of viscous, filled resins) and software (advanced image processing for high-resolution light-cured composites) have made this work possible and have advanced the state of the art in this field.  Broader impacts of this work are demonstrated through the success of our customers and partners. For example, Empire Group manufacturing, a local Massachusetts design and prototyping shop, has installed and used a Fortify Flux One system to service over two dozen customers. This service has made it possible for medical device OEM's to bring key products to market faster, all while using domestic suppliers. Fortify now has multiple contract manufacturers that are leveraging the outcomes of this work to bring supply chain robustness to the US while providing advantages in cost, lead-time, and design freedom for their product teams.   In an effort to expand the broader impacts of this work, Fortify has engaged in learning and development content as a thought leader in the space. Webinars and white papers can be found on our website, detailing the in's and out's of additive tooling. In addition, Fortify is continuing to engage with top manufacturing universities across the US as a means of investing in the future generation of design and manufacturing talent.       Last Modified: 12/20/2022       Submitted by: Joshua Martin]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
