<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Electrochemical Flow Reactor for Uniform Deposition of Li Metal Anodes]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>255737.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>255737</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anna Brady</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>abrady@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927077</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project advances battery technologies for electric vehicles and related applications.  The proposed project advances beyond the current Lithium-ion (Li-ion batteries by demonstrating a cost-effective and scalable process to manufacture high-purity, defect-free Lithium (Li) metal electrodes with superior cycle life. Lithium metal batteries promise substantially higher energy density than Li-ion batteries, and have a compelling value proposition for electric vehicles and portable electronics applications. The proposed technology addresses so-called "range anxiety" in electric vehicles, enabling use of these batteries for ranges exceeding 300 miles. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This SBIR Phase I project proposes to investigate large area Li-metal thin films deposition with high microstructural and compositional uniformity by overcoming Li-ion concentration gradients in the electrolyte. The project proposes to develop superior Li-metal anodes with the aid of an electrochemical flow reactor to overcome the electrolyte-phase mass transfer limitations. Though reproducibility and uniformity of the thin film anodes is not a concern at electrode areas less than 3-cm2, scaling up to areas exceeding 25 cm2 for commercial pouch cell format can lead to non-uniform and dendritic/mossy morphology, resulting in capacity loss and poor cycling life. A large-area electrochemical flow reactor will be assembled and the process parameters for high-performance Li thin film anodes will be established, producing films with high purity (&gt; 99.99%) and controllable thickness (5-50 micron) with a form factor greater than 25 cm2. The key innovation is an electrochemical flow reactor to produce high-performance lithium metal electrodes using low-cost water-based mineral feedstocks at a commercially viable scale.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/23/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/16/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041, 47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2026097</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Vedasri</FirstName>
<LastName>Vedharathinam</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Vedasri Vedharathinam</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[veda@alpha-encorp.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000820404</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/23/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate>12/21/2021</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
<LastName>Lyons</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Daniel J Lyons</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[dlyons@alpha-encorp.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000866425</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/21/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate>09/16/2022</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Landon</FirstName>
<LastName>Oakes</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Landon Oakes</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[Loakes@alpha-encorp.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000892466</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/16/2022</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>alpha-En Corporation</Name>
<CityName>HOPEWELL JUNCTION</CityName>
<ZipCode>125334021</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6039787053</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>200 NORTH DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>P7B1G41EYZB9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ALPHA-EN CORPORATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Alpha-En corporation]]></Name>
<CityName>Yonkers</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>107012788</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[28 wells avenue, Building 3]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>16</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY16</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8399</Code>
<Text>Energy Storage or Transmission</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~255737</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Complexity in the lithium supply chain has resulted in a severe shortage of the lithium required to electrify our transportation sector and energy grid. This program investigated the use of Alpha-En&rsquo;s novel electrolytic process to extract battery grade lithium metal from an aqueous solution as a means to replace the energy intensive, high-pollution electrowinning process of lithium metal manufacturing used today. This program successfully demonstrated the ability to directly extract lithium from an aqueous solution of lithium salt into a thin film of lithium metal which performed well as an anode in a lithium ion battery.</p> <p>Three of the primary tasks from this award were accomplished. Task 1 of this project produced a benchtop electrochemical flow reactor capable of extracting thin film lithium metal directly from an aqueous source. Task 2 optimized the coating process to produce a uniform lithium coating during the extraction. Task 3 characterized the structure and morphology of the lithium metal while quantifying the battery performance obtained with this material. The main conclusions from this work include: (1) Alpha-En&rsquo;s process enables the direct extraction of cell-ready lithium metal electrodes from an aqueous solution of lithium salt at room temperature, (2) lithium metal produced by this process performs well as a lithium metal anode when paired with a traditional lithium-ion battery cathode in a full cell battery, (3) the electrodeposition process offers a high degree of control over the morphology of the deposited lithium metal.</p> <p>The implications of this technology are substantial with regards to the impending climate crisis and the sensitive geopolitics surrounding lithium metal refining. This process promises to replace the current method for lithium metal manufacturing while providing a pathway to enable the full capture of the lithium value chain domestically as much of the lithium raw material in the United States exists within an aqueous source. Continued development and commercialization of this technology will enhance the leadership of the United States in clean energy technology through the training of a qualified workforce and improved manufacturing efficiency.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/03/2023<br>      Modified by: Landon&nbsp;Oakes</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Complexity in the lithium supply chain has resulted in a severe shortage of the lithium required to electrify our transportation sector and energy grid. This program investigated the use of Alpha-En’s novel electrolytic process to extract battery grade lithium metal from an aqueous solution as a means to replace the energy intensive, high-pollution electrowinning process of lithium metal manufacturing used today. This program successfully demonstrated the ability to directly extract lithium from an aqueous solution of lithium salt into a thin film of lithium metal which performed well as an anode in a lithium ion battery.  Three of the primary tasks from this award were accomplished. Task 1 of this project produced a benchtop electrochemical flow reactor capable of extracting thin film lithium metal directly from an aqueous source. Task 2 optimized the coating process to produce a uniform lithium coating during the extraction. Task 3 characterized the structure and morphology of the lithium metal while quantifying the battery performance obtained with this material. The main conclusions from this work include: (1) Alpha-En’s process enables the direct extraction of cell-ready lithium metal electrodes from an aqueous solution of lithium salt at room temperature, (2) lithium metal produced by this process performs well as a lithium metal anode when paired with a traditional lithium-ion battery cathode in a full cell battery, (3) the electrodeposition process offers a high degree of control over the morphology of the deposited lithium metal.  The implications of this technology are substantial with regards to the impending climate crisis and the sensitive geopolitics surrounding lithium metal refining. This process promises to replace the current method for lithium metal manufacturing while providing a pathway to enable the full capture of the lithium value chain domestically as much of the lithium raw material in the United States exists within an aqueous source. Continued development and commercialization of this technology will enhance the leadership of the United States in clean energy technology through the training of a qualified workforce and improved manufacturing efficiency.             Last Modified: 04/03/2023       Submitted by: Landon Oakes]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
