<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[STTR Phase I:  Haptics in Telerobotics for Improved Remote Dexterity]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>256000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>256000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Muralidharan Nair</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Technology Transfer (STTR) Phase I project is to advance haptics - electromechanical systems that operate through the sense of touch. This technology may improve the performance of telemanipulation systems, making the operation similar to that of bare hands, and advance a new generation of robotic tools allowing humans to remotely feel and interact with environments at a distance. Early applications include scenarios where humans would be placed in dangerous (e.g., nuclear, chemical, deep sea, mining, and space), complicated (clean rooms and surgeries), or remote locations (remote maintenance). This technology may reduce the costs of telework (including improved access for those with disabilities), travel, and specialized, local healthcare workers. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Technology Transfer (STTR) Phase I project will evaluate the contributions of realistic tactile and force feedback as well as biologically-inspired haptic reflexes in telemanipulation. Because experimental psychologists and physiologists have demonstrated that the absence of tactile sensory information is detrimental to the speed and dexterity of human hands, telerobot systems will seek to build these systems.  This work seeks to advance haptics for improved telerobotics performance by making them robust to distraction and latency. Several technologies for force and tactile feedback, intelligent haptic reflexes, and control schemes will be developed and tested in a range of telerobotic tasks to evaluate their merits and suitability in candidate applications.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/21/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/28/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2026203</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>William</FirstName>
<LastName>Cortez</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>William Cortez</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[will@tangible-research.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000848649</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/28/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jeremy</FirstName>
<LastName>Fishel</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jeremy Fishel</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jeremy@tangible-research.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000765388</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/28/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jeremy</FirstName>
<LastName>Fishel</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jeremy Fishel</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jeremy@tangible-research.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000765388</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/21/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate>01/28/2021</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Tangible Research Inc.</Name>
<CityName>CHICO</CityName>
<ZipCode>959285355</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5627263181</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>341 BROADWAY ST STE 204</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>JKAHMCTDD5X6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TANGIBLE RESEARCH INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Tangible Research Inc.]]></Name>
<CityName>Chico</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>959285485</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[539 Flume St. #206]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1505</Code>
<Text>STTR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>6840</Code>
<Text>ROBOTICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7632</Code>
<Text>HUMAN-ROBOT INTERACTION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8034</Code>
<Text>Hardware Components</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~256000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The goal of this research was to develop and validate telemanipulation technologies incorporating haptics to allow human operators to intuitively manipulate remote environments. Such technologies are expected to be beneficial when human intelligence and dexterity are required to perform manual tasks, but physically placing a human operator in the workspace would be dangerous, impractical due to distance, or otherwise difficult or expensive. While the sense of touch has been known to be essential in human dexterity, it has been notoriously challenging, expensive, and difficult to achieve robustly in robotics. The aims of this Phase I research were to develop and evaluate the performance gains and limitations of several proposed technologies that could offer benefits in performance, cost, and robustness in telemanipulation.&nbsp;</p> <p>To accomplish the research objectives, a planar grasping leader/follower telerobot system with four degrees of freedom was developed and used as a testbed to evaluate the performance of various force-reflection, tactile sensing, haptic display technologies in a set of timed experiments. The four degrees of freedom allowed for in-plane translation, rotation, and grasping, resulting in a reasonable degree of dexterity while reducing the experimental complexity and system cost. Custom linkages were developed to produce a working area roughly 15cm in diameter, motors were sized to deliver a minimum of 5N of force over the working area. To control the system, custom electronics, firmware, and software were developed to allow for teleoperation between a pair of telerobotic graspers with identical kinematics and hardware. The system could also be reconfigured to disable software controls and mechanically couple the leader and follower robotic graspers to create high-fidelity force and position coupling.</p> <p>&nbsp;Several combinations of tactile sensing, haptic feedback, and force reflection were evaluated in three subjects in three different experiments that involved picking and placing unstable objects, inserting objects into a slot, and operating various switches and knobs. In all tasks, direct manipulation performance (i.e. without the robotic system) was evaluated to baseline ideal human performance, while ideal system performance was established under direct mechanical coupling - neither of which are practical for remote teleoperation in the circumstances described above. Results of preliminary experiments showed great promise for the contributions of both tactile and force reflection on performance; however, tactile feedback has notable advantages due to challenges with stability encountered with force reflection that has been well-documented in research. In all scenarios (direct mechanical coupling, bilateral impedance control, or unilateral impedance control), the addition of tactile feedback resulted in performance gains. Due to budgetary and time constraints imposed from the COVID pandemic it was not possible to explore the components of delay or distraction in teleoperation performance in greater detail, but these preliminary findings show significant promise. Tactile-driven reflexes were also explored, but no gains in performance were seen when the system was operating without delay. Future research is planned to investigate the impacts of delay on performance, where such telerobotic reflexes are anticipated to provide benefit.&nbsp;</p> <p>Through this project we were able to demonstrate the benefits of tactile feedback in telerobotics and will be preparing technical publications documenting these findings to the academic and scientific communities. The development of the experimental testbed and methods will serve as a strong foundation for future research into this subject and development and evaluation of new technologies to enhance dexterity and performance in telerobots with these much-needed capabilities. Furthermore, participation in the NSF Beat-the-Odds Boot Camp has permitted for synchronizing the development of novel technologies with industry needs, which inspired many aspects of the experimental scenarios. This research is a first step towards understanding the role of high-fidelity haptics in telerobotics in greater detail and an essential step in bringing these systems to market.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/09/2022<br>      Modified by: Jeremy&nbsp;Fishel</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The goal of this research was to develop and validate telemanipulation technologies incorporating haptics to allow human operators to intuitively manipulate remote environments. Such technologies are expected to be beneficial when human intelligence and dexterity are required to perform manual tasks, but physically placing a human operator in the workspace would be dangerous, impractical due to distance, or otherwise difficult or expensive. While the sense of touch has been known to be essential in human dexterity, it has been notoriously challenging, expensive, and difficult to achieve robustly in robotics. The aims of this Phase I research were to develop and evaluate the performance gains and limitations of several proposed technologies that could offer benefits in performance, cost, and robustness in telemanipulation.   To accomplish the research objectives, a planar grasping leader/follower telerobot system with four degrees of freedom was developed and used as a testbed to evaluate the performance of various force-reflection, tactile sensing, haptic display technologies in a set of timed experiments. The four degrees of freedom allowed for in-plane translation, rotation, and grasping, resulting in a reasonable degree of dexterity while reducing the experimental complexity and system cost. Custom linkages were developed to produce a working area roughly 15cm in diameter, motors were sized to deliver a minimum of 5N of force over the working area. To control the system, custom electronics, firmware, and software were developed to allow for teleoperation between a pair of telerobotic graspers with identical kinematics and hardware. The system could also be reconfigured to disable software controls and mechanically couple the leader and follower robotic graspers to create high-fidelity force and position coupling.   Several combinations of tactile sensing, haptic feedback, and force reflection were evaluated in three subjects in three different experiments that involved picking and placing unstable objects, inserting objects into a slot, and operating various switches and knobs. In all tasks, direct manipulation performance (i.e. without the robotic system) was evaluated to baseline ideal human performance, while ideal system performance was established under direct mechanical coupling - neither of which are practical for remote teleoperation in the circumstances described above. Results of preliminary experiments showed great promise for the contributions of both tactile and force reflection on performance; however, tactile feedback has notable advantages due to challenges with stability encountered with force reflection that has been well-documented in research. In all scenarios (direct mechanical coupling, bilateral impedance control, or unilateral impedance control), the addition of tactile feedback resulted in performance gains. Due to budgetary and time constraints imposed from the COVID pandemic it was not possible to explore the components of delay or distraction in teleoperation performance in greater detail, but these preliminary findings show significant promise. Tactile-driven reflexes were also explored, but no gains in performance were seen when the system was operating without delay. Future research is planned to investigate the impacts of delay on performance, where such telerobotic reflexes are anticipated to provide benefit.   Through this project we were able to demonstrate the benefits of tactile feedback in telerobotics and will be preparing technical publications documenting these findings to the academic and scientific communities. The development of the experimental testbed and methods will serve as a strong foundation for future research into this subject and development and evaluation of new technologies to enhance dexterity and performance in telerobots with these much-needed capabilities. Furthermore, participation in the NSF Beat-the-Odds Boot Camp has permitted for synchronizing the development of novel technologies with industry needs, which inspired many aspects of the experimental scenarios. This research is a first step towards understanding the role of high-fidelity haptics in telerobotics in greater detail and an essential step in bringing these systems to market.       Last Modified: 02/09/2022       Submitted by: Jeremy Fishel]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
