<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase II:  Performance and Feasibility Evaluation of Electrochemical Advanced Oxidation Technology for Water Purification]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1000000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1000000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Cooperative Agreement</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anna Brady</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>abrady@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927077</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase II project is a cost-efficient and comprehensive water treatment solution that destroys water contaminants on contact, enabling on-site advanced water treatment in many industries with the potential for zero-liquid discharge/reuse operations. The proposed technology uses an innovative electrochemical design for water treatment. This practice reduces costs (e.g., transport, treatment, permitting) associated with hazardous waste and fresh water supplies, while safeguarding communities and the environment from potential contamination through accidental release, incomplete treatment, or non-secure storage. Industries adopting zero-liquid discharge can reduce freshwater demand and redirect it for other critical uses, such as agriculture.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research Phase II project will advance the development of an electrochemical oxidation and reduction destruction technology for industrial and municipal water treatment.  The proposed technology destroys contaminants in a single step using a reactive electrochemical membrane easily customized to the appropriate voltage and amperage to efficiently oxidize or reduce target contaminants in the water. This project will address the following objectives: 1) optimize efficacy and efficiency to destroy PFAS, 1,4-dioxane, nitrate, and perchlorate, 2) finalize large-scale device design, 3) develop a pilot system and explore the performance-cost trade space, and 4) iterate on system design.  The impact of process conditions on treatment efficacy will be explored to optimize for low cost and energy efficiency. Verification and validation will take place with on-site brine treatment pilot testing, while characterizing performance relative to state-of-practice and exploring potential economies of scale.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/20/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/13/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>CoopAgrmnt</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2026035</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Julie</FirstName>
<LastName>Mullen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Julie B Mullen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[info@aclaritywater.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000764346</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/20/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>ACLARITY INC.</Name>
<CityName>NORTH OXFORD</CityName>
<ZipCode>015371103</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7745516213</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>10 CHESTNUT HILL RD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NPBMHZYBNDK8</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ACLARITY INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>NPBMHZYBNDK8</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Aclarity, LLC]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>015371103</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5373</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase II</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1064</Code>
<Text>URBAN INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8030</Code>
<Text>Chemical Technology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~1000000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>For this Phase II award, Aclarity performed additional testing, validation, and design changes needed to establish our proposed technology as an effective water treatment solution and supported the transition to commercial manufacture. Aclarity has completed all four objectives. Objectives included expanding upon contaminant testing, finalizing a large-scale reactor design, testing the large-scale pilot system and evaluating the economics of the larger system, and preparing the finalized large-scale system for manufacturing.</p> <p><br /><span><span> </span>Testing for the destruction of poly- and per-fluorinated alkyl substances (PFAS) at concentrations found in industrial waste has been completed. The effects of type of electrolyte, concentration of electrolyte, and power settings were studied to understand the feasibility of full-scale treatment. Testing of 1,4-dioxane was completed to the best of our ability before changing course to focus more on PFAS destruction applications. The procurement of a reduction reactor for the process of degrading nitrate and perchlorate as well as a hybrid reactor for the process of degrading all compounds, has been accomplished. Testing was halted to direct efforts to PFAS destruction applications. The data obtained from the contaminant testing was pertinent for the completion of Objective 2, sizing a power supply for the needs of the large scale reactor and creating a design package for the pilot scale system. Objective 1 was also critical for completion of Objective 3, piloting of the pilot-scale system and economic analysis thereafter. Because of small scale contaminant testing, we developed the optimal power setting at which the pilot scale system should be operated to achieve the greatest destruction. The first full-scale reactor and pilot-scale system design were completed and built to pass factory acceptance testing. Another pilot scale system was built while the first underwent major design improvements. All systems were deployed to client sites for pilot testing ranging from one to six weeks per pilot. Objective 4, the development and manufacture of full-scale systems, was contingent upon the completion of Objective 3. Full scale sites have been identified and Aclarity is working with partners to close a sale, or offer a service model.</span><span> </span></p> <p><span>&nbsp;</span><span><span> </span>The advancement of each objective has positioned Aclarity to expand a robust sales pipeline, continue fundraising, and commercialize our first multi-reactor full-scale system for an end-user. PFAS destruction has become a major customer focus and our largest vertical.&nbsp; We are clearer on performance and economics through the testing made possible by the Phase II program and are now working with multiple industry leaders to provide full scale solutions for PFAS destruction, excelling in industries like centralized waste treatment and industrial zero-liquid discharge.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/30/2023<br>      Modified by: Julie&nbsp;B&nbsp;Mullen</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ For this Phase II award, Aclarity performed additional testing, validation, and design changes needed to establish our proposed technology as an effective water treatment solution and supported the transition to commercial manufacture. Aclarity has completed all four objectives. Objectives included expanding upon contaminant testing, finalizing a large-scale reactor design, testing the large-scale pilot system and evaluating the economics of the larger system, and preparing the finalized large-scale system for manufacturing.    Testing for the destruction of poly- and per-fluorinated alkyl substances (PFAS) at concentrations found in industrial waste has been completed. The effects of type of electrolyte, concentration of electrolyte, and power settings were studied to understand the feasibility of full-scale treatment. Testing of 1,4-dioxane was completed to the best of our ability before changing course to focus more on PFAS destruction applications. The procurement of a reduction reactor for the process of degrading nitrate and perchlorate as well as a hybrid reactor for the process of degrading all compounds, has been accomplished. Testing was halted to direct efforts to PFAS destruction applications. The data obtained from the contaminant testing was pertinent for the completion of Objective 2, sizing a power supply for the needs of the large scale reactor and creating a design package for the pilot scale system. Objective 1 was also critical for completion of Objective 3, piloting of the pilot-scale system and economic analysis thereafter. Because of small scale contaminant testing, we developed the optimal power setting at which the pilot scale system should be operated to achieve the greatest destruction. The first full-scale reactor and pilot-scale system design were completed and built to pass factory acceptance testing. Another pilot scale system was built while the first underwent major design improvements. All systems were deployed to client sites for pilot testing ranging from one to six weeks per pilot. Objective 4, the development and manufacture of full-scale systems, was contingent upon the completion of Objective 3. Full scale sites have been identified and Aclarity is working with partners to close a sale, or offer a service model.     The advancement of each objective has positioned Aclarity to expand a robust sales pipeline, continue fundraising, and commercialize our first multi-reactor full-scale system for an end-user. PFAS destruction has become a major customer focus and our largest vertical.  We are clearer on performance and economics through the testing made possible by the Phase II program and are now working with multiple industry leaders to provide full scale solutions for PFAS destruction, excelling in industries like centralized waste treatment and industrial zero-liquid discharge.                Last Modified: 06/30/2023       Submitted by: Julie B Mullen]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
