<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  The Development of Signal Sensing, Processing and Mapping Technology to Enable Curative, Patient-Specific Treatment of Atrial Fibrillation]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>251134.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>251134</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Henry Ahn</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>hahn@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927069</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is the development of a diagnostic technology capable of identifying the drivers of Atrial Fibrillation (AF), which promises to enable new therapeutic options for a large population of under-served patients. AF is the most common and complex cardiac arrythmia. AF patients are at severe risk of complications including stroke, heart attack and death. AF patients have limited treatment options and medications are only effective approximately half of the time. Ablation is highly effective at treating other arrythmias, but current diagnostic mapping technologies are limited in the ability to provide customized treatment for chronic AF. This project will test concepts of a new device to measure AF.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project will validate the ability of a novel micro-electrode array to accurately measure AF in an animal. This is important because conventional intra-cardiac catheters lack the spatial resolution to adequately resolve discrete, closely spaced activations. Accurate resolution of cardiac tissue activations is essential to deduce the properties of diseased tissue and to plan effective patient-specific ablation therapy. Optical mapping is a gold standard for measuring electrical activation of tissue and therefore provides a trusted platform for comparative validation. The expected results are to observe complex activation patterns on an ovine heart model using the novel micro-electrode array, and for those electrical patterns to be corroborated by optical mapping data.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/26/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/13/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2026029</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sarah</FirstName>
<LastName>Kalil</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>O</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sarah O Kalil</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[skalil@coremapmedical.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000763910</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/26/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>CoreMap, Inc.</Name>
<CityName>COLCHESTER</CityName>
<ZipCode>054467797</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9787904074</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>197 MOONLIGHT RIDGE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Vermont</StateName>
<StateCode>VT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>VT00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>JDZNFANAM313</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>COREMAP, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[CoreMap, Inc.]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>VT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>054467797</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Vermont</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>VT00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5345</Code>
<Text>BIOMEDICAL ENGINEERING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8032</Code>
<Text>Software Services and Applications</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8038</Code>
<Text>Biotechnology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~251134</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-268d40a6-7fff-7308-a68d-786752d4f360">&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Atrial fibrillation (AF) is the most common and difficult to treat cardiac arrhythmia. The US AF patient </span><span>population is projected to reach 12 million by the end of the decade and the CDC has labeled AF as an </span><span>epidemic. Patients with AF have a higher risk of </span><span>stroke and death, yet treatment options are limited. </span><span>Medications work in only about half of patients and catheter ablation, a procedure that creates scar </span><span>tissue in the heart to alter the spread of electricity, is only attempted in about 1% of the AF patien</span><span>t </span><span>population.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The clinical research conducted in this Phase 1 SBIR project tested various features of a novel </span><span>electrode design aimed at improving the clarity and information content in electrical recordings from </span><span>patients with advanced AF. CoreMap is d</span><span>eveloping a catheter and mapping system to allow physicians to </span><span>identify the cardiac sites responsible for perpetuating AF, thereby directing doctors as to where ablation </span><span>should be delivered to cure fibrillation. The Phase 1 project tested various features </span><span>of electrode </span><span>geometry and spacing, and provided information about the range of electrical activity seen in human </span><span>chronic AF over time and at various locations on the heart. We were able to determine the ideal </span><span>electrode size for our catheter which will be t</span><span>ested next. We also demonstrated that the electrodes </span><span>performed as hypothesized, delivering sharp, organized signals despite the complex and chaotic spread </span><span>of electricity that occurs in human AF. This study was a critical step towards the design, testing an</span><span>d use </span><span>of a transvenous catheter. The next phase of the project will entail transvenous cardiac mapping </span><span>followed by map</span><span>-</span><span>guided ablation for chronic AF. Our aim is to provide a treatment option for the many </span><span>millions of patients suffering from AF who are curr</span><span>ently not&nbsp; considered to be candidates for ablation due to the&nbsp;</span><span>inability to identify AF drivers in individual patients.</span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/30/2022<br>      Modified by: Sarah&nbsp;O&nbsp;Kalil</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   Atrial fibrillation (AF) is the most common and difficult to treat cardiac arrhythmia. The US AF patient population is projected to reach 12 million by the end of the decade and the CDC has labeled AF as an epidemic. Patients with AF have a higher risk of stroke and death, yet treatment options are limited. Medications work in only about half of patients and catheter ablation, a procedure that creates scar tissue in the heart to alter the spread of electricity, is only attempted in about 1% of the AF patient population. The clinical research conducted in this Phase 1 SBIR project tested various features of a novel electrode design aimed at improving the clarity and information content in electrical recordings from patients with advanced AF. CoreMap is developing a catheter and mapping system to allow physicians to identify the cardiac sites responsible for perpetuating AF, thereby directing doctors as to where ablation should be delivered to cure fibrillation. The Phase 1 project tested various features of electrode geometry and spacing, and provided information about the range of electrical activity seen in human chronic AF over time and at various locations on the heart. We were able to determine the ideal electrode size for our catheter which will be tested next. We also demonstrated that the electrodes performed as hypothesized, delivering sharp, organized signals despite the complex and chaotic spread of electricity that occurs in human AF. This study was a critical step towards the design, testing and use of a transvenous catheter. The next phase of the project will entail transvenous cardiac mapping followed by map-guided ablation for chronic AF. Our aim is to provide a treatment option for the many millions of patients suffering from AF who are currently not  considered to be candidates for ablation due to the inability to identify AF drivers in individual patients.       Last Modified: 01/30/2022       Submitted by: Sarah O Kalil]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
