<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Wear and Corrosion Resistant Engineered Surfaces for Lightweight Metals]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>256000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>256000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rajesh Mehta</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rmehta@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922174</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is the ability to improve fuel efficiency and reduce carbon dioxide emissions in transportation. Lightweight metals, such as aluminum, magnesium, and titanium, are particularly desirable for alloys used in automotive and aerospace components, as they could reduce the weight of components by 30%-70%. However, it is difficult to coat these materials because the high temperatures required for the coating processes weaken the alloys. This project will develop a new process to conduct the coating process at lower temperatures, offering high load capacity and enhanced wear and corrosion resistance.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project utilizes a high-pressure gas nitriding medium to enable surface reactions for coating lightweight metals, allowing for lower treatment temperatures at or below 450C. Traditional engineered surfaces are often incompatible with lightweight metals because of cracking that destroys the functional properties. Furthermore, coating these alloys presents challenges because they distort at relatively low temperatures.  This novel approach of nitriding at high pressures provides a chemically converted surface layer that prepares the surface for a secondary surface treatment, such as diamond-like carbon coatings or metal oxides, that typically fail on lightweight metals. The multi-layer approach also provides enhanced corrosion resistance by disrupting diffusion pathways of corrosive media. Combining a hard and stiff sublayer with a softer top layer with lower elastic modulus provides a multi-layer surface for lightweight metals.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/10/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/10/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2026026</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Brandon</FirstName>
<LastName>Strahin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Brandon L Strahin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[bstrahin@precisionsurfacescience.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000805275</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>PRECISION SURFACE SCIENCE, LLC</Name>
<CityName>AKRON</CityName>
<ZipCode>443111028</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3305318466</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>411 WOLF LEDGES PKWY STE 208B</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OH13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>FP3APMPLSNE1</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PRECISION SURFACE SCIENCE, LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[The University of Akron]]></Name>
<CityName>Akron</CityName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>443250002</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[264 Wolf Ledges Pkwy]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>11</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OH11</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>123E</Code>
<Text>CENTERS: ADVANCED MATERIALS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8021</Code>
<Text>Materials Engineering</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~256000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Lightweight metals are desirable for use in many applications such as sporting goods, bicycles, automobile drivetrain components and casings, aerospace components, and firearms. Aluminum (Al) and magnesium (Mg) alloys are more desirable than titanium (Ti) in many applications due to the lower cost and availability of raw materials, lightweight, and relative ease of forming and machining.</p> <p>Adoption of Al and Mg alloys by many applications has been limited by low melting points, low elastic moduli, and poor tribological properties. Traditional coating solutions do not work well for lightweight materials due to the oxide layers that form on the surface preventing adhesion and the low elastic moduli of the lightweight materials not providing adequate support for the coating causing what is known as the "eggshell effect." In addition to these problems, Mg alloys also suffer from corrosion problems when exposed to many environments including water.</p> <p>The original approach of using high-pressure nitrogen in the super critical region was not successful. To replace this approach, a method of laser alloying the surface with ceramic particles to create the reinforcement needed to support tribological coatings was used. Although some improvement was seen in both the B<sub>4</sub>C and SiN doping of aluminum alloys, the results were inconsistent and did not meet the customer requirement of having a wear rate lower than 1 x 10<sup>-</sup><sup>6</sup> mm<sup>3</sup>/J. Laser modification was not successful on the magnesium alloys tested. In addition, the effect on corrosion resistance was negative, with the exception of Al 7075 with SiN and TiMoS2 which showed an improvement of 5x, half of that required by the customer.</p> <p>Due to the inability to meet customer requirements, no product could be commercialized from this research.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/01/2022<br>      Modified by: Brandon&nbsp;L&nbsp;Strahin</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Lightweight metals are desirable for use in many applications such as sporting goods, bicycles, automobile drivetrain components and casings, aerospace components, and firearms. Aluminum (Al) and magnesium (Mg) alloys are more desirable than titanium (Ti) in many applications due to the lower cost and availability of raw materials, lightweight, and relative ease of forming and machining.  Adoption of Al and Mg alloys by many applications has been limited by low melting points, low elastic moduli, and poor tribological properties. Traditional coating solutions do not work well for lightweight materials due to the oxide layers that form on the surface preventing adhesion and the low elastic moduli of the lightweight materials not providing adequate support for the coating causing what is known as the "eggshell effect." In addition to these problems, Mg alloys also suffer from corrosion problems when exposed to many environments including water.  The original approach of using high-pressure nitrogen in the super critical region was not successful. To replace this approach, a method of laser alloying the surface with ceramic particles to create the reinforcement needed to support tribological coatings was used. Although some improvement was seen in both the B4C and SiN doping of aluminum alloys, the results were inconsistent and did not meet the customer requirement of having a wear rate lower than 1 x 10-6 mm3/J. Laser modification was not successful on the magnesium alloys tested. In addition, the effect on corrosion resistance was negative, with the exception of Al 7075 with SiN and TiMoS2 which showed an improvement of 5x, half of that required by the customer.  Due to the inability to meet customer requirements, no product could be commercialized from this research.       Last Modified: 04/01/2022       Submitted by: Brandon L Strahin]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
