<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[FW-HTF-P: Collaborative Research: Wearable Safety and Health Assistive Robot Collaboration for Skilled Construction Workers]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>90000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>90000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Balakrishnan Prabhakaran</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The research objective of this FW-HTF planning project is to build a synergistic team and provide symbiotic solutions to develop and deploy wearable safety and health assistive robots for skilled construction workers. Currently, construction workers suffer intense physical effort, and serious safety and health risk in hazardous working environments. As a result, construction industry becomes one of the highest-risk private sectors in the US. Shortage of skilled workers brings additional challenges and pressures to construction industry to improve workers' safety and health. Wearable robotic technology provides promising potentials to prevent work-related musculoskeletal disorders, assess and assist physical and fatigue, and learn and train worker skills in construction trades. The project will enable the development and deployment of personalized wearable assistive robot collaboration for skilled construction workers. The researchers will also develop a number of integrated research and education programs to attract students from underrepresented groups into engineering and involve undergraduate students into research.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Although robotics technologies have been increasingly used in construction applications, most focus on the use of robots to help conduct construction tasks and few discusses the use of industrial exoskeletons for improving workers' safety and health. In this planning project, the team of researchers plan to build a synergistic team and identify potential topics and symbiotic solutions to achieve the above research goal. Specifically, this project will emphasize on: (1) develop light-weight, flexible, high-performance, personalized wearable exoskeletons for construction workers; (2) develop machine learning-based human skill modeling and training in construction, and (3) initiate new cross-disciplinary collaboration and foster engagement with industry partners and stakeholders. The proposed robotic development and pilot study will provide deep understanding of technical and socio-economic challenges for integrating robotic technologies into existing socio-technical ecosystems of work. The planning grant will also study the effects of the significant shifts in human work on individual, organization and industries with a focus specifically on construction work. The ultimate goal of this project is to develop the necessary research personnel, research infrastructure, and foundational work to expand the opportunities for studying future technology, future workers, and future work at the level of a FW-HTF full research proposal.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/24/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/14/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2026613</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jingang</FirstName>
<LastName>Yi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jingang Yi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jgyi@rutgers.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000246666</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/24/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jie</FirstName>
<LastName>Gong</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jie Gong</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jg931@soe.rutgers.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000574651</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/24/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Rutgers University New Brunswick</Name>
<CityName>NEW BRUNSWICK</CityName>
<ZipCode>089018559</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8489320150</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3 RUTGERS PLZ</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NJ12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>M1LVPE5GLSD9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RUTGERS, THE STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Rutgers, The State University of New Jersey]]></Name>
<CityName>Piscataway</CityName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>088548058</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[98 Brett Road, Dept of Mechanica]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NJ06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>103Y</Code>
<Text>FW-HTF Futr Wrk Hum-Tech Frntr</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>063Z</Code>
<Text>FW-HTF Futr Wrk Hum-Tech Frntr</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~90000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Construction workers exert intense physical effort, and they can experience serious safety and health risks in hazardous, dynamic working environments. As a result, the construction industry is one of the highest-risk sectors in the U.S. A shortage of skilled workers brings additional challenges and pressures to the construction industry and amplifies the need to improve workers' safety and health. Emerging technologies such as wearable sensors and robots (i.e., exoskeletons) provide the potential to prevent work-related musculoskeletal disorders, assist physical demands, and expand employment opportunities for women and aging workers in construction. The main goal of this planning project is to build a synergistic team and provide symbiotic solutions to develop and deploy wearable safety and health assistive robot collaboration for skilled construction workers.</p> <p>Over the past year, the PIs have accomplished a various research tasks to build a synergistic team and identify potential topics and symbiotic solutions to develop effective and efficient wearable safety and health assistive robot collaboration for skilled construction workers. The main outcomes of the project lie in several aspects: (1) a single wearable inertial sensor-based gait detection and pose estimation design for human walking on flat and sloped surfaces in construction; (2) a lightweight, wearable sensing and knee assistive device for construction workers during kneeling and squatting tasks; (3) a human postural balance study on quiet standing and kneeling gaits on inclined and high elevated surfaces for construction workers; and (4) a synergistic team with cross-disciplinary collaboration and engagement with industry partners and stakeholders. More than 3 journal and conference publications and 2 PhD thesis work have been produced and partially supported by the project. A number of research activities were integrated into the education programs to attract students from underrepresented groups into engineering fields, such as participating the Rutgers LSAMP and SUPER programs and hosting multiple high-school and freshmen female students, and supporting senior design projects.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/29/2022<br>      Modified by: Jingang&nbsp;Yi</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2026613/2026613_10701256_1643495371989_Exoskeleton--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2026613/2026613_10701256_1643495371989_Exoskeleton--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Assistive knee exoskeleton for construction workers"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2026613/2026613_10701256_1643495371989_Exoskeleton--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Assistive knee exoskeleton for construction workers"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">A developed lightweight, wearable sensing and assistive knee device for construction workers</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jingang Yi</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jingang&nbsp;Yi</div> <div class="imageTitle">Assistive knee exoskeleton for construction workers</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2026613/2026613_10701256_1643495529061_IMUwalk--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2026613/2026613_10701256_1643495529061_IMUwalk--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Wearable inertial sensor-based experiments"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2026613/2026613_10701256_1643495529061_IMUwalk--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Wearable inertial sensor-based experiments"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">A single wearable sensor-based walking gait activity recognition and pose estimation experiment</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jingang Yi</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jingang&nbsp;Yi</div> <div class="imageTitle">Wearable inertial sensor-based experiments</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Construction workers exert intense physical effort, and they can experience serious safety and health risks in hazardous, dynamic working environments. As a result, the construction industry is one of the highest-risk sectors in the U.S. A shortage of skilled workers brings additional challenges and pressures to the construction industry and amplifies the need to improve workers' safety and health. Emerging technologies such as wearable sensors and robots (i.e., exoskeletons) provide the potential to prevent work-related musculoskeletal disorders, assist physical demands, and expand employment opportunities for women and aging workers in construction. The main goal of this planning project is to build a synergistic team and provide symbiotic solutions to develop and deploy wearable safety and health assistive robot collaboration for skilled construction workers.  Over the past year, the PIs have accomplished a various research tasks to build a synergistic team and identify potential topics and symbiotic solutions to develop effective and efficient wearable safety and health assistive robot collaboration for skilled construction workers. The main outcomes of the project lie in several aspects: (1) a single wearable inertial sensor-based gait detection and pose estimation design for human walking on flat and sloped surfaces in construction; (2) a lightweight, wearable sensing and knee assistive device for construction workers during kneeling and squatting tasks; (3) a human postural balance study on quiet standing and kneeling gaits on inclined and high elevated surfaces for construction workers; and (4) a synergistic team with cross-disciplinary collaboration and engagement with industry partners and stakeholders. More than 3 journal and conference publications and 2 PhD thesis work have been produced and partially supported by the project. A number of research activities were integrated into the education programs to attract students from underrepresented groups into engineering fields, such as participating the Rutgers LSAMP and SUPER programs and hosting multiple high-school and freshmen female students, and supporting senior design projects.          Last Modified: 01/29/2022       Submitted by: Jingang Yi]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
