<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[FW-HTF-P: Building a Skilled Technological Workforce in the Hospitality Service Industry of the Future]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>130000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>146000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Dan Cosley</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dcosley@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928832</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This Future of Work at the Human-Technology frontier planning grant focuses on creating new ways for hospitality workers to shape how automation will affect their industry and their jobs.  It has been widely predicted that the hospitality industry will experience significant job shifts in the coming decades. Automation plays a key role in causing these shifts, with examples including self-service kiosks, various applications of robotics, customer-facing AI, automated operations, and food preparation technologies. Such automation is already displacing many jobs in the hospitality industry. Although new jobs will be developed in the future, many others will be eliminated, and the need for new skill sets is rising. In the hospitality and service industries, automation has already affected hotel room check-in, cashiering, cleaning processes, bartending, and food service. This situation is changing even more rapidly as the work shifts in response to new standards around COVID-19 safety. Nearly 90% of hospitality workers lost work at least temporarily during the pandemic and they lack ways to envision and reap the positive impacts of technology innovation. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research team of experts in robotics, policy, economics, human-computer interaction, and organizational dynamics seeks to mitigate this growing problem by allowing hospitality workers to partner with and benefit from the future of automation and to maximize opportunities and positive outcomes for all of its stakeholders.  The project will create generalizable knowledge through a series of workshops that bring together researchers, policy experts, union leaders and members, and stakeholders from leading hospitality schools. Specifically, the research team will assess the current state of hospitality services through a broad literature review, conduct workshops with key stakeholders, collectively explore technology innovations, and develop a strategic roadmap for future collaboration around automation technologies in the hospitality industry. This project has been funded by the NSF Future of Work at the Human-Technology Frontier cross-directorate program to promote deeper basic understanding of the interdependent human-technology partnership in work contexts by advancing design of intelligent work technologies that operate in harmony with human workers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/19/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/19/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2026537</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
<LastName>Kamlet</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mark S Kamlet</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[kamlet@cmu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000419757</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/19/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate>07/14/2021</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Howard</FirstName>
<LastName>Choset</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Howard M Choset</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[choset@cs.cmu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000167332</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/19/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Howard</FirstName>
<LastName>Choset</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Howard M Choset</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[choset@cs.cmu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000167332</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/19/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate>07/14/2021</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jodi</FirstName>
<LastName>Forlizzi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jodi Forlizzi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[forlizzi@cs.cmu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000226685</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/19/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>George</FirstName>
<LastName>Kantor</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>George Kantor</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[kantor@ri.cmu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000281381</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/19/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>George</FirstName>
<LastName>Kantor</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>George Kantor</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[kantor@ri.cmu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000281381</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/19/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate>07/14/2021</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Chinmay</FirstName>
<LastName>Kulkarni</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Chinmay Kulkarni</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[chinmay.kulkarni@emory.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000705638</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/19/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sarah</FirstName>
<LastName>Fox</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sarah E Fox</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[sarahf@andrew.cmu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000792151</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/19/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Carnegie-Mellon University</Name>
<CityName>PITTSBURGH</CityName>
<ZipCode>152133815</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4122688746</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5000 FORBES AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>U3NKNFLNQ613</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CARNEGIE MELLON UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>U3NKNFLNQ613</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Carnegie Mellon University]]></Name>
<CityName>Pittsburgh</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>152133890</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5000 Forbes Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>103Y</Code>
<Text>FW-HTF Futr Wrk Hum-Tech Frntr</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>063Z</Code>
<Text>FW-HTF Futr Wrk Hum-Tech Frntr</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~130000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~16000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-ff76a8b5-7fff-08e6-6133-56ba3218c1d6"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>This planning grant was used to build a team, along with UNITE HERE!, the largest hospitality union in the US and part of the AFL-CIO, to produce insightful research on how AI should be designed, developed, and deployed in the hospitality industry.&nbsp;</span></p> <p>Housekeeping is a physically demanding job, largely performed by middle-aged women of color and immigrants. Many do not speak English, or possess much digital literacy. However, they take pride in the work that they do and the face-to-face interactions they have with their customers. Many have been doing their jobs for two or three decades.</p> <p>When a guest stays in a union hotel, the service staff are members of UNITE HERE. Workers at many of these properties, which can be owned, managed, and branded by up to three different organizations, are increasingly encountering AI in their day to day work. For example, algorithmic managers assist housekeepers and managers to manage operations and assist in the workflow of cleaning rooms. They also allow for customized room assignments, to deal with issues like getting ready for conference attendees and prioritizing the cleaning of rooms where guests have checked out.</p> <p>However, AI can be problematic in this space, because the needs of workers, customers, and managers are prioritized differently. And workers are at the bottom of this list.&nbsp; For housekeepers, algorithmic managers (AMs) increase work, increase job requirements, and decrease worker autonomy. Instead of letting housekeepers clean rooms in the order&nbsp; that makes the most sense to them based on their ability to complete their room quotas with a minimum of wear and tear on their bodies, AMs send them back and forth and up and down in hallways and elevators, while they push 200-300 pound carts. We have heard again and again from housekeepers that the AM ?wastes my time.? AMs increase wear on the worker by assigning several check-out rooms, which require heavy cleaning, back to back as opposed to alternating them with the lighter physical requirements of rooms in which only sheets and towels need changing. Housekeeping is also an entry level job that traditionally did not require technology skills or even fluent English. This, combined with typical connectivity issues, has altered&nbsp; the job of the housekeeper greatly, with little to no increased training or increased compensation.&nbsp;</p> <p>Our work emerged from a broader engagement with the AFL-CIO?s Technology Institute, which is committed to supporting technology innovation by engaging workers in the innovation process. This grant enabled us to create a team and secure additional funding to surface worker voice in designing, developing, procuring, deploying, and training future technologies in the hospitality industry. This work reflects the charge included in the CHIPs Act for NSF?s Technology, Innovation, and Partnerships directorate to help support mutually beneficial partnerships with labor organizations that can support use-inspired translational research.</p> <div></div> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/25/2023<br>      Modified by: Jodi&nbsp;Forlizzi</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   This planning grant was used to build a team, along with UNITE HERE!, the largest hospitality union in the US and part of the AFL-CIO, to produce insightful research on how AI should be designed, developed, and deployed in the hospitality industry.   Housekeeping is a physically demanding job, largely performed by middle-aged women of color and immigrants. Many do not speak English, or possess much digital literacy. However, they take pride in the work that they do and the face-to-face interactions they have with their customers. Many have been doing their jobs for two or three decades.  When a guest stays in a union hotel, the service staff are members of UNITE HERE. Workers at many of these properties, which can be owned, managed, and branded by up to three different organizations, are increasingly encountering AI in their day to day work. For example, algorithmic managers assist housekeepers and managers to manage operations and assist in the workflow of cleaning rooms. They also allow for customized room assignments, to deal with issues like getting ready for conference attendees and prioritizing the cleaning of rooms where guests have checked out.  However, AI can be problematic in this space, because the needs of workers, customers, and managers are prioritized differently. And workers are at the bottom of this list.  For housekeepers, algorithmic managers (AMs) increase work, increase job requirements, and decrease worker autonomy. Instead of letting housekeepers clean rooms in the order  that makes the most sense to them based on their ability to complete their room quotas with a minimum of wear and tear on their bodies, AMs send them back and forth and up and down in hallways and elevators, while they push 200-300 pound carts. We have heard again and again from housekeepers that the AM ?wastes my time.? AMs increase wear on the worker by assigning several check-out rooms, which require heavy cleaning, back to back as opposed to alternating them with the lighter physical requirements of rooms in which only sheets and towels need changing. Housekeeping is also an entry level job that traditionally did not require technology skills or even fluent English. This, combined with typical connectivity issues, has altered  the job of the housekeeper greatly, with little to no increased training or increased compensation.   Our work emerged from a broader engagement with the AFL-CIO?s Technology Institute, which is committed to supporting technology innovation by engaging workers in the innovation process. This grant enabled us to create a team and secure additional funding to surface worker voice in designing, developing, procuring, deploying, and training future technologies in the hospitality industry. This work reflects the charge included in the CHIPs Act for NSF?s Technology, Innovation, and Partnerships directorate to help support mutually beneficial partnerships with labor organizations that can support use-inspired translational research.              Last Modified: 10/25/2023       Submitted by: Jodi Forlizzi]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
