<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[FW-HTF-P: Essential Decision-Making Skills for the Future Workforce in Smart Manufacturing]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>134190.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>134190</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sara Kiesler</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>skiesler@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928643</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[In 2019, there were over 15.7 million workers in manufacturing, making it the fourth largest industry in the United States. In the next decade, many workers in manufacturing could see their jobs eliminated or reconfigured. Nearly 10 percent of the jobs in manufacturing will be entirely new. Manufacturing is increasingly relying on smart technologies such as artificial intelligence, the internet of things, robots, cobots, and more. Preparing workers for this so-called fourth industrial revolution is not simply about training the workforce to push different buttons or monitor screens. Such an approach would only prepare workers for the machines of today and would fail to address decision-making skills needed for interacting with the smart-technology enabled workplace. This Future of Work at the Human-Technology Frontier (FW-HTF) Planning Grant project is identifying the specific decision-making skills that will be needed for the current workforce to be successful in smart manufacturing facilities of the future. The results from the project will help local and regional agencies create plans and prepare the workforce to ride the tide of technological change as manufacturing facilities adopt smart technologies. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This one-year planning project is gathering information on worker decision-making in established smart factories from different countries to identify decision-making competencies. These case studies, along with an experimental psychology project, and multiple, advisory group meetings, are being used to develop a smart factory worker readiness survey to identify individual strengths and gaps in essential decision-making skills. The project end result will be the development of training modules to assist current and future workers in the manufacturing industry work be more effective decision-makers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/02/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/31/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2026283</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Theresa</FirstName>
<LastName>Castor</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Theresa Castor</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[castor@uwp.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000676070</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/02/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Peggy</FirstName>
<LastName>James</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Peggy A James</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[james@uwp.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000799037</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/02/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Melissa</FirstName>
<LastName>Gregg</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Melissa Gregg</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[greggm@uwp.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000798792</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/02/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Wisconsin-Parkside</Name>
<CityName>KENOSHA</CityName>
<ZipCode>531441133</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2625952364</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>900 WOOD RD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WI01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>F31GEXBJVL57</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF WISCONSIN PARKSIDE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Wisconsin-Parkside]]></Name>
<CityName>Kenosha</CityName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>531412000</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[900 Wood Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WI01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>082Y</Code>
<Text>FW-HTF-Adv Cogn &amp; Phys Capblty</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>063Z</Code>
<Text>FW-HTF Futr Wrk Hum-Tech Frntr</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9102</Code>
<Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~134190</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><div class="OutlineElement Ltr SCXW202037109 BCX0"> <p class="Paragraph SCXW202037109 BCX0"><span class="TextRun SCXW202037109 BCX0" lang="EN-US" xml:lang="EN-US"><span class="NormalTextRun SCXW202037109 BCX0">In 2019, there were over 15.7 million workers in manufacturing, making it the fourth largest industry in the United States. In the next decade, many workers in manufacturing will be displaced; others will see their jobs eliminated. Nearly 10% of the jobs in manufacturing will be entirely new. Manufacturing is increasingly relying on smart technologies such as artificial intelligence, the Internet of things, robots, </span><span class="NormalTextRun SpellingErrorV2Themed SCXW202037109 BCX0">cobots</span><span class="NormalTextRun SCXW202037109 BCX0">, and more. Preparing workers for this fourth industrial revolution is not simply about training the workforce to push different buttons or monitor screens. Such an approach would only prepare workers for the machines of today and would fail to address decision-making skills needed to be adaptable to the new smart-technology enabled workplace. </span><span class="NormalTextRun SCXW202037109 BCX0">The main goal of the project was to identify essential decision-making skills for workers in smart manufacturing and ho</span><span class="NormalTextRun SCXW202037109 BCX0">w best to train workers in applying those decision-making skills in human-machine and human-human interactions in the smart manufacturing context.&nbsp;</span></span><span class="EOP SCXW202037109 BCX0">&nbsp;</span></p> </div> <div class="OutlineElement Ltr SCXW202037109 BCX0"> <p class="Paragraph SCXW202037109 BCX0"><span class="NormalTextRun SCXW202037109 BCX0">This one-year planning project </span><span class="NormalTextRun SCXW202037109 BCX0">applied</span><span class="NormalTextRun SCXW202037109 BCX0"> an integrative and multi-layered approach to understanding worker decision-making in smart manufacturing. </span><span class="NormalTextRun SCXW202037109 BCX0">A comparative analysis of US and German smart manufacturing sites was conducted through site visits and interviews. A cognitive </span><span class="NormalTextRun SCXW202037109 BCX0">psychology experiment was conducted to examine how best to augment human cognition during training to assemble and use novel devices. The experimental results indicated that augmenting human memory results in significantly better performance on an assessment of the novel device than augmenting human perception or no augmentation.</span><span class="NormalTextRun SCXW202037109 BCX0"> </span><span class="NormalTextRun SCXW202037109 BCX0">An advisory board consisting of regional representatives in smart manufacturing and workforce development was also convened.</span><span class="NormalTextRun SCXW202037109 BCX0"> <span class="TextRun Highlight SCXW67171184 BCX0" lang="EN-US" xml:lang="EN-US"><span class="NormalTextRun SCXW67171184 BCX0">Through the website and social media platforms, industry representatives on the advisory board were able to share challenges, and determine commonalties, thus enabling a more informed </span><span class="NormalTextRun ContextualSpellingAndGrammarErrorV2Themed SCXW67171184 BCX0">decision making</span><span class="NormalTextRun SCXW67171184 BCX0"> approach to the industry 4.0 transition</span></span><span class="TextRun SCXW67171184 BCX0" lang="EN-US" xml:lang="EN-US">.&nbsp;</span>A matrix table that identifies essential decision-making characteristics for workers and organ</span><span class="NormalTextRun SCXW202037109 BCX0">izations was developed with the goal of developing a tool that can be used for skill assessment and development.&nbsp;<span class="NormalTextRun SCXW67171184 BCX0">Preliminary analysis of the site matrix indicates</span><span class="NormalTextRun ContextualSpellingAndGrammarErrorV2Themed SCXW67171184 BCX0">: (</span><span class="NormalTextRun ContextualSpellingAndGrammarErrorV2Themed SCXW67171184 BCX0">1)</span><span class="NormalTextRun SCXW67171184 BCX0">&nbsp;Predictive Analytics were more likely to be used towards the final stages of transitioning to Industry 4.0; (2) Hiring difficulties tended to emerge later in the transition process to Industry 4.0; and, (3) Skill training seemed typically focused on machine operation rather than decision making in a human machine interactive environment; years of operation appeared to have little effect on patterns of transition to smart manufacturing.&nbsp;</span></span></p> <p class="Paragraph SCXW202037109 BCX0"><span class="NormalTextRun SCXW202037109 BCX0"><span class="NormalTextRun SCXW67171184 BCX0"><span class="TextRun Highlight SCXW58422310 BCX0" lang="EN-US" xml:lang="EN-US"><span class="NormalTextRun SCXW58422310 BCX0">Operationalization of variables to distinguish traditional from optimized decision-making was developed.&nbsp;</span></span></span></span>Future work is planned to apply the assessment decision-making instrument and to develop training modules to support effective decision-making skills for workers in smart manufacturing.</p> </div> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/20/2022<br>      Modified by: Theresa&nbsp;Castor</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ In 2019, there were over 15.7 million workers in manufacturing, making it the fourth largest industry in the United States. In the next decade, many workers in manufacturing will be displaced; others will see their jobs eliminated. Nearly 10% of the jobs in manufacturing will be entirely new. Manufacturing is increasingly relying on smart technologies such as artificial intelligence, the Internet of things, robots, cobots, and more. Preparing workers for this fourth industrial revolution is not simply about training the workforce to push different buttons or monitor screens. Such an approach would only prepare workers for the machines of today and would fail to address decision-making skills needed to be adaptable to the new smart-technology enabled workplace. The main goal of the project was to identify essential decision-making skills for workers in smart manufacturing and how best to train workers in applying those decision-making skills in human-machine and human-human interactions in the smart manufacturing context.     This one-year planning project applied an integrative and multi-layered approach to understanding worker decision-making in smart manufacturing. A comparative analysis of US and German smart manufacturing sites was conducted through site visits and interviews. A cognitive psychology experiment was conducted to examine how best to augment human cognition during training to assemble and use novel devices. The experimental results indicated that augmenting human memory results in significantly better performance on an assessment of the novel device than augmenting human perception or no augmentation. An advisory board consisting of regional representatives in smart manufacturing and workforce development was also convened. Through the website and social media platforms, industry representatives on the advisory board were able to share challenges, and determine commonalties, thus enabling a more informed decision making approach to the industry 4.0 transition. A matrix table that identifies essential decision-making characteristics for workers and organizations was developed with the goal of developing a tool that can be used for skill assessment and development. Preliminary analysis of the site matrix indicates: (1) Predictive Analytics were more likely to be used towards the final stages of transitioning to Industry 4.0; (2) Hiring difficulties tended to emerge later in the transition process to Industry 4.0; and, (3) Skill training seemed typically focused on machine operation rather than decision making in a human machine interactive environment; years of operation appeared to have little effect on patterns of transition to smart manufacturing.  Operationalization of variables to distinguish traditional from optimized decision-making was developed. Future work is planned to apply the assessment decision-making instrument and to develop training modules to support effective decision-making skills for workers in smart manufacturing.           Last Modified: 06/20/2022       Submitted by: Theresa Castor]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
