<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Urban Resilience to Health Emergencies: Revealing Latent Epidemic Spread Risks from Population Activity Fluctuations and Collective Sense-making]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>200000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>200000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Robert O'Connor</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>roconnor@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927263</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[COVID-19 outbreaks have had dire societal and economic impacts across the globe, and its spread has become a major societal threat in the United States. The majority of epidemic spread models, however, do not fully consider the tremendous uncertainty associated with human response behaviors (both populations and individual actors) and perturbations in urban system supply chains during an epidemic outbreak. For this project, the research team collects and analyzes time-bound data to better understand and predict and to more effectively respond to the risk of infection disease outbreaks in urban areas. These data can be used to help identify the underlying processes that influence urban-scale population response behaviors, collective sense-making in online social media, disruptions in urban system supply chains, and collective information processing and coordination among actors across different urban sectors. These finding can advance the fundamental understanding of the complexities of epidemic outbreak threats, which would extend beyond standard outbreak models and purely clinical research. The outcomes suggest new ways for better prediction and offer novel insights regarding ways to conduct urban-scale surveillance of epidemic spread risks. The findings inform strategies and possible data-driven tools and methods to prevent, help contain, and mitigate the effects of future epidemics and pandemics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The specific project tasks are threefold. First, the project will identify and collect data that could provide weak signals about population response behaviors in response to epidemic threats. For example, anomalies in traffic patterns can suggest reduction in demand due to telecommuting. Mobility data, which informs about patterns of population fluxes, facilitates monitoring of the effectiveness of social distancing measures. Second, the project collects social media posts, such those in as Twitter, to examine how epidemic risk is processed and encoded in online social networks. Third, through organizational interviews and surveys, the project uncovers collective information processing and coordination actions among different actors across various urban sectors responding to epidemic spread risks and urban system perturbations. The data are analyzed through spatial modeling, network analysis, and data analytics techniques. In analysis of these datasets, a particular attention are given to population activity patterns in neighborhoods with vulnerable populations (e.g., elderly, low income, and racial minorities).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/01/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/01/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2026814</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ali</FirstName>
<LastName>Mostafavi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ali Mostafavi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mostafavi@tamu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000654058</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/01/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Texas A&amp;M Engineering Experiment Station</Name>
<CityName>COLLEGE STATION</CityName>
<ZipCode>778433124</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9798626777</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3124 TAMU</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>QD1MX6N5YTN4</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TEXAS A&amp;M ENGINEERING EXPERIMENT STATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>QD1MX6N5YTN4</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Texas Engineering Experiment Station]]></Name>
<CityName>College Station</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>778433136</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3136 TAMU]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1321</Code>
<Text>Decision, Risk &amp; Mgmt Sci</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1321</Code>
<Text>DECISION RISK &amp; MANAGEMENT SCI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~200000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project has resulted in the creation of new data-driven methods and computational models for proactive monitoring of pandemics at local and national scales. The main objective of this project was to develop innovative approaches to detect, track and predict the spread of pandemics using data-driven techniques. The project team focused on developing measures based on fluctuations in population activities and mobility, which have been found to be key indicators of pandemic spread risks. These new measures were created and tested to provide early warning signals, as well as indicators for evaluating population response to public health policies during the COVID-19 pandemic.</p> <p>In addition to the development of new measures, the project team also created and tested several new computational and machine learning-based models for proactive pandemic monitoring. These models were based on heterogeneous features related to sociodemographics, population activities, mobility, and disease characteristics. The objective of these models was to identify patterns and relationships between these features and the spread trajectory of pandemics, in order to develop reliable and explainable predictions to inform policies.</p> <p>The outcomes of this project provided new insights into the connection between human activities and mobility and pandemic spread risk. The data-driven and computational models and measures developed by the project team were found to be effective in examining pandemic spread risk based on the features of population activities and mobility. This information would be valuable for decision-makers, emergency managers, and public health officials, as it provides them with tools and insights to better respond to future pandemics.</p> <p>This project has significantly contributed to the field of urban resilience to health emergencies by developing new data-driven methods and computational models that can effectively analyze the pandemic spread risks based on several heterogenous features.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/28/2023<br>      Modified by: Ali&nbsp;Mostafavi</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project has resulted in the creation of new data-driven methods and computational models for proactive monitoring of pandemics at local and national scales. The main objective of this project was to develop innovative approaches to detect, track and predict the spread of pandemics using data-driven techniques. The project team focused on developing measures based on fluctuations in population activities and mobility, which have been found to be key indicators of pandemic spread risks. These new measures were created and tested to provide early warning signals, as well as indicators for evaluating population response to public health policies during the COVID-19 pandemic.  In addition to the development of new measures, the project team also created and tested several new computational and machine learning-based models for proactive pandemic monitoring. These models were based on heterogeneous features related to sociodemographics, population activities, mobility, and disease characteristics. The objective of these models was to identify patterns and relationships between these features and the spread trajectory of pandemics, in order to develop reliable and explainable predictions to inform policies.  The outcomes of this project provided new insights into the connection between human activities and mobility and pandemic spread risk. The data-driven and computational models and measures developed by the project team were found to be effective in examining pandemic spread risk based on the features of population activities and mobility. This information would be valuable for decision-makers, emergency managers, and public health officials, as it provides them with tools and insights to better respond to future pandemics.  This project has significantly contributed to the field of urban resilience to health emergencies by developing new data-driven methods and computational models that can effectively analyze the pandemic spread risks based on several heterogenous features.        Last Modified: 01/28/2023       Submitted by: Ali Mostafavi]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
