<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase II:  Smartphone Automated External Defibrillator]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>998441.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>998441</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Cooperative Agreement</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Henry Ahn</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>hahn@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927069</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase II project is to save lives through the miniaturization of automated external defibrillators (AED) integrated with smartphones. Sudden cardiac arrest (SCA) kills more than 320,000 Americans a year outside of the hospital. An SCA can cause death if it is not treated in minutes. If an AED is available, it can save a person's life. Unfortunately, today’s AEDs are often not available outside of buildings or large population centers and are too big to easily transport outside of an emergency situation, and thus they often arrive too late for a victim.  This research creates a new type of AED designed to function as a personal device, small enough to be carried everywhere and securely connected to the Internet through smartphone integration.  These next-generation AEDs will save lives by making them available when and where they are needed. These units will be a lightweight addition to an EMT, soldier’s, or park ranger’s emergency kit as a simple and lifesaving addition to everyone’s smartphone. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research Phase II project will advance translation of a novel AED.  Specific activities include methods to develop language support; creation of new channels for ECG transmission to emergency rooms and catheter labs prior to patient arrival; and integration with telecommunication systems used by emergency response personnel (e.g., 911).  This project will optimize the trade space between form factor and performance, using systems engineering methodologies for verification and validation of the proposed solution.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/23/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/29/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>CoopAgrmnt</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2026090</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
<LastName>Fleck</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Daniel Fleck</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[dan.fleck@altrixmedical.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000765230</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/23/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Altrix Medical, Inc.</Name>
<CityName>CENTREVILLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>201203750</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7039893061</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>15504 VINE COTTAGE DRIVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>VA10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>CN6BE8CGLZS7</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ALTRIX MEDICAL INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Altrix Medical, LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>Centreville</CityName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>201203750</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[15504 Vine Cottage Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>VA10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5373</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase II</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5345</Code>
<Text>BIOMEDICAL ENGINEERING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8038</Code>
<Text>Biotechnology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~904739</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~93702</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>In September 2020 Altrix Medical was awarded a Phase 2 SBIR cooperative agreement from the National Science Foundation to continue development of the SmartAED with the overarching objective of creating the smallest automated external defibrillator (AED) in the world that is capable of the same therapies as traditional large format AEDs.&nbsp; Additionally, the work aspired to connect the SmartAED to a smartphone and provide Internet of Things (IoT) features that are not present in current AEDs. Three fundamental goals were accomplished in the SBIR Phase 2 period of performance:&nbsp;</p> <ol> <li>Evolve the prototype developed in Phase 1 to a regulatory compliant AED sized for daily carrying. To do this, our team created a new circuit board design and integrated it with a simple-to-use case.</li> <li>Development of firmware and software to support core AED and ancillary communication features.&nbsp; To accomplish this goal the team hardened the software and firmware to tolerate multiple failure modes, integrated the SmartAED with cloud service features, and ensured the design is compliant as an FDA class 3 device.</li> <li>Validation of the prototype requirements and design with identified user groups that represent the SmartAED markets. To do this, Altrix Medical Inc. met with many different professional and consumer customers and iterated the design and requirements based on their feedback.</li> </ol> <p>The results of the SBIR Phase 2 work significantly advanced knowledge in methods of AED miniaturization.&nbsp; Moreover, completion of a bifurcated architecture to support clinical and communication features significantly reduced the risk profile of this Class 3 medical device. Mechanical designs that were developed under separate funding to increase the usability profile of the SBIR Phase 1 case also underwent usability testing and the resulting findings have been scheduled for additional refinements.</p> <p>This Phase 2 work has positioned the product well for completing the productization and certification of the AED and moving on to production.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/09/2023<br>      Modified by: Daniel&nbsp;Fleck</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2026090/2026090_10707348_1683649455535_smartAED_scene2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2026090/2026090_10707348_1683649455535_smartAED_scene2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Altrix Medical SmartAED"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2026090/2026090_10707348_1683649455535_smartAED_scene2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Altrix Medical SmartAED"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Version One of The Altrix Medical SmartAED</div> <div class="imageCredit">Altrix Medical</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Daniel&nbsp;Fleck</div> <div class="imageTitle">Altrix Medical SmartAED</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ In September 2020 Altrix Medical was awarded a Phase 2 SBIR cooperative agreement from the National Science Foundation to continue development of the SmartAED with the overarching objective of creating the smallest automated external defibrillator (AED) in the world that is capable of the same therapies as traditional large format AEDs.  Additionally, the work aspired to connect the SmartAED to a smartphone and provide Internet of Things (IoT) features that are not present in current AEDs. Three fundamental goals were accomplished in the SBIR Phase 2 period of performance:   Evolve the prototype developed in Phase 1 to a regulatory compliant AED sized for daily carrying. To do this, our team created a new circuit board design and integrated it with a simple-to-use case. Development of firmware and software to support core AED and ancillary communication features.  To accomplish this goal the team hardened the software and firmware to tolerate multiple failure modes, integrated the SmartAED with cloud service features, and ensured the design is compliant as an FDA class 3 device. Validation of the prototype requirements and design with identified user groups that represent the SmartAED markets. To do this, Altrix Medical Inc. met with many different professional and consumer customers and iterated the design and requirements based on their feedback.   The results of the SBIR Phase 2 work significantly advanced knowledge in methods of AED miniaturization.  Moreover, completion of a bifurcated architecture to support clinical and communication features significantly reduced the risk profile of this Class 3 medical device. Mechanical designs that were developed under separate funding to increase the usability profile of the SBIR Phase 1 case also underwent usability testing and the resulting findings have been scheduled for additional refinements.  This Phase 2 work has positioned the product well for completing the productization and certification of the AED and moving on to production.       Last Modified: 05/09/2023       Submitted by: Daniel Fleck]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
