<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Gordon Research Conference on Collective Behavior]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>30000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>30000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>MCB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>David Rockcliffe</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>drockcli@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927123</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Nontechnical Description&lt;br/&gt;Collective behaviors occur on all scales of living systems, from organism to tissue to cell to molecules.  While various scientific groups work on these phenomena across many disciplines (evolution, biology, physics, engineering, etc.), research on collective behaviors is not well coordinated.   The goal of the conference is to bring together and build a community of researchers working in the field of collective behavior across scales and across disciplines.    The award will provide travel and registration support to facilitate participation in the Gordon Research Conference on Collective Behavior, to be held June 6-11, 2021 at Salve Regina University in Newport, RI.  The requested support would enable graduate students and postdocs to participate in the conference, as such promoting the mentoring and inclusion of early stage scientists in the formation of the collective behavior community.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical Description&lt;br/&gt;The Gordon Research Conference on Collective Behavior will bring together scientists, engineers, and mathematical scientists, and consists of nine sessions, with formal morning and evening sessions, and interactive afternoon poster sessions to enable personal interactions designed to initiate trans-disciplinary collaborations. Through the interactive program, the conference will contribute towards the establishment of an enduring inclusive trans-disciplinary community and encourage the participation of women and underrepresented researchers in the area of collective behavior.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/10/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/10/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2026268</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jonathan</FirstName>
<LastName>Arnold</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jonathan Arnold</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[arnold@uga.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000117855</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Gordon Research Conferences</Name>
<CityName>EAST GREENWICH</CityName>
<ZipCode>028183454</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4017834011</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5586 POST RD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[UNIT 2]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>RI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>XL5ANMKWN557</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GORDON RESEARCH CONFERENCES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Gordon Research Conferences]]></Name>
<CityName>Kingston</CityName>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>028921502</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[512 Liberty Lane]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>RI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8011</Code>
<Text>Systems and Synthetic Biology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7465</Code>
<Text>NANOSCALE BIO CORE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~30000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>On August 13-18, 2023 the first Gordon Research Conference on Collective Behavior was held at Grand Summit, Sunday River, Maine. The conference brought together life scientists, mathematicians, bioinformaticians, chemists, physicists, and engineers to understand flocks of birds, schools of fish, and armies of insects as well as collective behavior on other scales stretching from collective attack of viruses on cells to participants in whole ecosystems.&nbsp; The meeting allowed the identification of common problems in collective behavior, common models, and common approaches. This meeting provided the opportunity for researchers from a variety of disciplines to engage on common problems not before described in the literature.&nbsp; The result of the meeting was fostering a new inclusive community of scientists engaging in collective behavior and the realization that the collective behavior community impinged on many fundamental problems ranging from wound healing and herding cells to the cycling of green house gases by microbial communities.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Applications discussed at the meeting included controlling marching locusts as an agricultural plague, how cancer cells move, how synthetic microbial communities can be used in manufacturing, the electronic control of networks in cells, and how trees communicate their disease state. All of these problems required.</p> <p>The meeting had 74 participants from all over the world.&nbsp; The keynote speaker was Professor Deborah Gordon, who provided unifying themes for the meeting on collective behavior. The 74 participants included 19 postdoctoral fellows and 24 graduate students.&nbsp; The rest of the participants were senior scientists. 36 posters were presented in addition to 21 invited talks. A Gordon Research Conference Power Hour was led by Professor Graciela Lorca to promote inclusiveness in the community.&nbsp; Also Dr. Daniel Cohen led an hour on storytelling to increase the communication skills of young scientists.</p> <p>The meeting marked the the beginning of a new discipline called Collective Behavior.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/15/2023<br>      Modified by: Jonathan&nbsp;Arnold</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2026268/2026268_10694936_1694804360201_photo_105279e4-d52b-464b-aab1-29cde48b733c_Page_2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2026268/2026268_10694936_1694804360201_photo_105279e4-d52b-464b-aab1-29cde48b733c_Page_2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Gordon Research Participants 2023"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2026268/2026268_10694936_1694804360201_photo_105279e4-d52b-464b-aab1-29cde48b733c_Page_2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Gordon Research Participants 2023"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Gordon Research Participants 2023 on Collective Behavior in all kingdoms</div> <div class="imageCredit">Gordon Research Conference</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jonathan&nbsp;Arnold</div> <div class="imageTitle">Gordon Research Participants 2023</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ On August 13-18, 2023 the first Gordon Research Conference on Collective Behavior was held at Grand Summit, Sunday River, Maine. The conference brought together life scientists, mathematicians, bioinformaticians, chemists, physicists, and engineers to understand flocks of birds, schools of fish, and armies of insects as well as collective behavior on other scales stretching from collective attack of viruses on cells to participants in whole ecosystems.  The meeting allowed the identification of common problems in collective behavior, common models, and common approaches. This meeting provided the opportunity for researchers from a variety of disciplines to engage on common problems not before described in the literature.  The result of the meeting was fostering a new inclusive community of scientists engaging in collective behavior and the realization that the collective behavior community impinged on many fundamental problems ranging from wound healing and herding cells to the cycling of green house gases by microbial communities.     Applications discussed at the meeting included controlling marching locusts as an agricultural plague, how cancer cells move, how synthetic microbial communities can be used in manufacturing, the electronic control of networks in cells, and how trees communicate their disease state. All of these problems required.  The meeting had 74 participants from all over the world.  The keynote speaker was Professor Deborah Gordon, who provided unifying themes for the meeting on collective behavior. The 74 participants included 19 postdoctoral fellows and 24 graduate students.  The rest of the participants were senior scientists. 36 posters were presented in addition to 21 invited talks. A Gordon Research Conference Power Hour was led by Professor Graciela Lorca to promote inclusiveness in the community.  Also Dr. Daniel Cohen led an hour on storytelling to increase the communication skills of young scientists.  The meeting marked the the beginning of a new discipline called Collective Behavior.       Last Modified: 09/15/2023       Submitted by: Jonathan Arnold]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
