<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  An Injectable Treatment for the Repair of Damaged Tendons and Ligaments]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>255947.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>255947</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Erik Pierstorff</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>epiersto@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922165</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project will be improvement of quality of life and reduction of healthcare costs associated with tendon and ligament injuries which are notoriously difficult and slow to heal, depriving millions of Americans years of productivity. Tendon and ligament injuries are especially debilitating for the aged, the active or those with physically demanding professions. Injured ligaments (e.g. anterior cruciate ligament)  or tendons (e.g. Achilles) require months of rehabilitation and can take up to a year to heal. In the elderly, rotator cuff injuries are pernicious, prevalent and refractory to treatment. Every year in the US, $130 billion is spent on musculoskeletal injury-related medical visits, 60% of which are tendon and ligament injuries. Tendon and ligament injuries result in 288 million lost work days costing the US economy $50 billion annually. In spite of decades of effort, there has been very little improvement in either the rate or the quality of healing for these injuries. The injectable repair system proposed could reduce healing time and improve repair quality. The proposed plan to drastically reduce the cost of the raw materials through human cell engineering will make the treatment solution universally affordable.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed project will determine the feasibility of an entirely new approach to tendon and ligament repair based upon the in vivo delivery and assembly of collagen monomers into the path of force. The approach is derivative of two recent innovations that will be combined in four objectives to produce an injectable collagen-based solution designed to accelerate the repair of damaged connective tissues (i.e. ligaments and tendons) the healing of which presents a significant medical challenge. The first innovation is the use of CRISPR/CAS9 technology which will be used to accelerate the production of collagen by human fibroblasts. Objective 1 will to optimize the CRISPR process and scale it up through isolation and expansion of cells receptive to enhanced collagen production. Objective 2 will leverage the second major innovation, liquid crystal collagen processing technology, to develop a shelf stable injectable solution of highly-dense particulates that is expected to donate large amounts of collagen to injured connective tissue. Objective 3 will demonstrate that the injectable repair solution will deliver collagen to repair damage in vitro and Objective 4 will apply the approach in vivo, to demonstrate that exogenous collagen delivery can speed the repair of damaged, living tendon.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/14/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/13/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2026007</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Adam</FirstName>
<LastName>Hacking</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Adam S Hacking</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[adam.hacking@regenxus.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000749057</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/14/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>RegenX LLC</Name>
<CityName>NASHUA</CityName>
<ZipCode>030623067</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6179973862</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>57 LANGHOLM DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Hampshire</StateName>
<StateCode>NH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NH02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>Y6JZS2H1LF57</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENX LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[RegenX]]></Name>
<CityName>Lowell</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>018524574</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[110 Canal St]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>008E</Code>
<Text>Gene and Drug Delivery</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8038</Code>
<Text>Biotechnology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~255947</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Collagen is the most abundant protein in the human body and is present at high quantity in tissues like skin, tendon and ligament. Collagen forms load bearing structures in tissues that enable motion and resistance to mechanical force. Injury to tissues generally involves a disruption or damage to collagen. As we age, our propensity towards injury increases and our capacity to produce collagen declines. With a decline in collagen production, the rate and extent of tissue repair decreases. As a result, the production and use of collagen for tissue repair, tissue regenerative approaches and other therapeutic approaches is of great interest. To enable the use of collagen in a therapeutic capacity, collagen must first be produced. Production of collagen from cells is costly. One approach to make collagen production commercially feasible is to maximize cellular output of collagen. &nbsp;This SBIR Phase 1 proposal evaluated the feasibility of the production of human collagen from human cells using genetic manipulations to enhance cell activity. This work advanced our understanding of collagen production and determined serval approaches by which it could be enhanced. This proposal also evaluated the reparative effect of collagen materials. Collagen was applied to several injury models and determined that the application of collagen accelerated tissue repair.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/09/2022<br>      Modified by: Adam&nbsp;S&nbsp;Hacking</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Collagen is the most abundant protein in the human body and is present at high quantity in tissues like skin, tendon and ligament. Collagen forms load bearing structures in tissues that enable motion and resistance to mechanical force. Injury to tissues generally involves a disruption or damage to collagen. As we age, our propensity towards injury increases and our capacity to produce collagen declines. With a decline in collagen production, the rate and extent of tissue repair decreases. As a result, the production and use of collagen for tissue repair, tissue regenerative approaches and other therapeutic approaches is of great interest. To enable the use of collagen in a therapeutic capacity, collagen must first be produced. Production of collagen from cells is costly. One approach to make collagen production commercially feasible is to maximize cellular output of collagen.  This SBIR Phase 1 proposal evaluated the feasibility of the production of human collagen from human cells using genetic manipulations to enhance cell activity. This work advanced our understanding of collagen production and determined serval approaches by which it could be enhanced. This proposal also evaluated the reparative effect of collagen materials. Collagen was applied to several injury models and determined that the application of collagen accelerated tissue repair.           Last Modified: 06/09/2022       Submitted by: Adam S Hacking]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
