<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[FW-HTF-P: Understanding the Social and Ethical Implications of Algorithmic Decision Making by Nurses Using the Rothman Index in a Large-Scale Hospital Setting]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>150000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>150000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Balakrishnan Prabhakaran</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[With a shift towards value-based care, healthcare organizations are seeking innovative ways to improve the quality of care while reducing costs. The next several decades will see a rise in algorithm-driven patient care and the widespread use of data-driven warning systems such as the Rothman Index. The Rothman Index is an algorithmic system that uses patient information, lab results, and other health-related data to predict health deterioration. Algorithmic systems such as the Rothman will undoubtedly change what it means to daily work in the field of healthcare, demanding new kinds of expertise and communication from an already over-extended workforce. While such systems may reduce staffing needs, they do not eliminate the need for human oversight and intervention. Understanding how traditionally trained healthcare practitioners interact with such systems is, therefore, vital for the successful implementation of algorithmic patient care. To accomplish this goal, this project seeks to expand our understanding of how nurses in the Virtual Intensive Care Unit (VICU) make algorithmically informed workplace decisions using the Rothman Index. More broadly, the project examines how healthcare workers mediate between algorithms and patient interaction. Consequently, it informs future training protocols, system redesign and revision, and overall optimization of similar futuristic algorithmic tools.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;This project will employ a participatory and worker-centered design process for implementing algorithmic patient care through close collaborations with healthcare workers to advance the technical design of the Rothman Index. It will focus on the experiences of the virtual nurses, the providers who currently mediate between the Rothman Index alerts and health practitioners on the floor, in making actual algorithmic decisions. The project’s foundation is relationship-building with relevant hospital stakeholders followed by collecting and analyzing preliminary data about experiences with the Rothman Index in the VICU work environment, including observations and interviews with virtual nursing staff and deidentified quantitative usage data extracted from the Rothman Index system. Drawing on preliminary findings, hospital stakeholders will be engaged in participatory design to improve workplace protocols and practices around algorithmic decision making. Subsequently, this project will inform three fundamental research challenges: (1) technical communication research on how cognition and memory facilitate workplace writing processes and the impacts of electronic systems on patient-provider and provider-provider communication; (2) organizational research on the synergistic mechanisms that successfully enable VICU; and (3) computer science research on the social and ethical implications of algorithmic interventions such as the Rothman Index. Furthermore, this research will open door to studying many related problems: (a) feasibility of algorithmic patient care for preventative population outreach programs; (b) predictions of job displacements caused by algorithmic patient care implementation and anticipatory workforce training; (c) future algorithmic design for healthcare workplaces.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/25/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/14/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2026607</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Shion</FirstName>
<LastName>Guha</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Shion Guha</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[Shion.guha@marquette.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000731907</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/25/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Amrita</FirstName>
<LastName>George</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Amrita George</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ageorge12@gsu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000823204</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/25/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lillian</FirstName>
<LastName>Campbell</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lillian Campbell</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[lillian.campbell@marquette.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000823219</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/25/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Marquette University</Name>
<CityName>MILWAUKEE</CityName>
<ZipCode>532332310</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4142887200</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>915 W WISCONSIN AVE RM 175</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WI04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>HKJCKTFJNBM7</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MARQUETTE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>YHYDXPLZHLW3</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Marquette University]]></Name>
<CityName>Milwaukee</CityName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>532011881</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[PO Box 1881]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WI04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>103Y</Code>
<Text>FW-HTF Futr Wrk Hum-Tech Frntr</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>063Z</Code>
<Text>FW-HTF Futr Wrk Hum-Tech Frntr</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~150000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project resulted in several distinct outcomes for both Intellectual Merits and Broader Impacts that are presented as follows:<br /><br /><strong>Intellectual Merit: </strong>This project examined how nursing staff in a virtual intensive care unit at Froedtert Hospital, an urban academic hospital system, mediated between algorithmic alerts and practitioners on the hospital floor. Researchers ultimately expanded the scope of the grant by partnering with Parkview Health and recruiting health practitioners who work with dashboard systems for interviews. We found that those directly in contact with algorithms tended to value their relational benefits, but administrators and physicians were highly skeptical. This points to the need for more communication between providers and administrators about day-to-day experiences with algorithmic systems, as well as the need for more qualitative research to gain a complete picture of the potential benefits of early warning systems and strategies to support successful implementation (Campbell, George, and Guha, ProComm 2021b). Overall, healthcare workers are more willing to accept the use of technology in their workplace when they see tangible benefits to themselves. Our analysis of interviews with healthcare practitioners revealed that the organizational digital divide was impeding the efficacy of enabling superior operational capabilities when using algorithm-enabled systems in provisioning patient care. While algorithm-enabled systems improved sensing capabilities, response effectiveness and stakeholder satisfaction were impacted due to the observed organizational digital divide (George, Campbell, Guha, Informs 2021). <br /><br />We also identified a transition away from deterioration indexes like Rothman and towards algorithm-enabled wellness technologies (Campbell, George, and Guha, Sigdoc 2021a). However, these responses varied in relation to the hospital context. At Parkview Health, a non-profit community owned healthcare system mainly serving rural and exurban areas around Northeastern Indiana and Northwestern Ohio, administrators were still invested in the improvement of their algorithmic monitoring systems. Thus, researchers were able to conduct algorithmic revisions to improve their behavioral health intake algorithm and account for current developments in research on cyberbullying (Nova et al., 2022). Overall, community hospitals and similarly under-resourced clinical sites, which have limited access to a highly educated workforce, will likely continue to value and benefit from the use of algorithmic decision making tools like Rothman; thus, the evaluation and improvement of algorithmic tools for such contexts remains vital.<br /><br /><strong>Broader Impacts: </strong>As the general population ages and life expectancy increases in the United States demand for health care providers is also on the rise. The next several decades will see a rise in automated patient care and the widespread use of data-driven warning systems like the Rothman Index. These shifts will undoubtedly change what it means to work day-to-day in the field of healthcare, demanding new kinds of expertise and communication from an already over-extended workforce. While such systems may reduce staffing needs, they do not eliminate the need for human oversight and intervention. Understanding how traditionally trained healthcare practitioners interact with predictive analytics is vital for their successful implementation in the future. Our findings point towards a shift towards algorithms for ambulatory patient care in well-resourced hospital contexts that is indicative of broader trends in healthcare technology integration. Understanding how different professional subgroups respond to implementation of patient-facing wellness technologies will be critical going forward. The next stage of our project will work to better understand how algorithmic bias and communication are functioning in relation to AI enabled health technologies. In addition, we will account for differing attitudes and behaviors towards technology integration as a result of varying professional subcultures among health workers. At the same time, algorithms that track patient deterioration and stream-line patient intake will continue to have a vital role particularly in under-resourced healthcare contexts that provide care to some of the most vulnerable patient populations. Thus, continuing to assess and improve these algorithms to reduce algorithmic and practitioner bias will remain an ongoing priority, especially to keep these programs in line with developing research findings.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/23/2022<br>      Modified by: Shion&nbsp;Guha</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2026607/2026607_10701681_1648048655039_ScreenShot2022-01-05at11.43.16AM(1)--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2026607/2026607_10701681_1648048655039_ScreenShot2022-01-05at11.43.16AM(1)--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Cyberbullying Algorithmic Assessment at Parkview Health"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2026607/2026607_10701681_1648048655039_ScreenShot2022-01-05at11.43.16AM(1)--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Cyberbullying Algorithmic Assessment at Parkview Health"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">A Deconstruction of Cyberbullying Assessment Algorithm at Parkview Health</div> <div class="imageCredit">Fayika Farhat Nova, Jessica Pater, Shion Guha</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Shion&nbsp;Guha</div> <div class="imageTitle">Cyberbullying Algorithmic Assessment at Parkview Health</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2026607/2026607_10701681_1648048550063_sigdoc21--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2026607/2026607_10701681_1648048550063_sigdoc21--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Communication and Algorithmic Decision Making in a Virtual Healthcare Context"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2026607/2026607_10701681_1648048550063_sigdoc21--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Communication and Algorithmic Decision Making in a Virtual Healthcare Context"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Image of Poster Published at SIGDOC 2021</div> <div class="imageCredit">Lillian Campbell, Amrita George, and Shion Guha</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Shion&nbsp;Guha</div> <div class="imageTitle">Communication and Algorithmic Decision Making in a Virtual Healthcare Context</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project resulted in several distinct outcomes for both Intellectual Merits and Broader Impacts that are presented as follows:  Intellectual Merit: This project examined how nursing staff in a virtual intensive care unit at Froedtert Hospital, an urban academic hospital system, mediated between algorithmic alerts and practitioners on the hospital floor. Researchers ultimately expanded the scope of the grant by partnering with Parkview Health and recruiting health practitioners who work with dashboard systems for interviews. We found that those directly in contact with algorithms tended to value their relational benefits, but administrators and physicians were highly skeptical. This points to the need for more communication between providers and administrators about day-to-day experiences with algorithmic systems, as well as the need for more qualitative research to gain a complete picture of the potential benefits of early warning systems and strategies to support successful implementation (Campbell, George, and Guha, ProComm 2021b). Overall, healthcare workers are more willing to accept the use of technology in their workplace when they see tangible benefits to themselves. Our analysis of interviews with healthcare practitioners revealed that the organizational digital divide was impeding the efficacy of enabling superior operational capabilities when using algorithm-enabled systems in provisioning patient care. While algorithm-enabled systems improved sensing capabilities, response effectiveness and stakeholder satisfaction were impacted due to the observed organizational digital divide (George, Campbell, Guha, Informs 2021).   We also identified a transition away from deterioration indexes like Rothman and towards algorithm-enabled wellness technologies (Campbell, George, and Guha, Sigdoc 2021a). However, these responses varied in relation to the hospital context. At Parkview Health, a non-profit community owned healthcare system mainly serving rural and exurban areas around Northeastern Indiana and Northwestern Ohio, administrators were still invested in the improvement of their algorithmic monitoring systems. Thus, researchers were able to conduct algorithmic revisions to improve their behavioral health intake algorithm and account for current developments in research on cyberbullying (Nova et al., 2022). Overall, community hospitals and similarly under-resourced clinical sites, which have limited access to a highly educated workforce, will likely continue to value and benefit from the use of algorithmic decision making tools like Rothman; thus, the evaluation and improvement of algorithmic tools for such contexts remains vital.  Broader Impacts: As the general population ages and life expectancy increases in the United States demand for health care providers is also on the rise. The next several decades will see a rise in automated patient care and the widespread use of data-driven warning systems like the Rothman Index. These shifts will undoubtedly change what it means to work day-to-day in the field of healthcare, demanding new kinds of expertise and communication from an already over-extended workforce. While such systems may reduce staffing needs, they do not eliminate the need for human oversight and intervention. Understanding how traditionally trained healthcare practitioners interact with predictive analytics is vital for their successful implementation in the future. Our findings point towards a shift towards algorithms for ambulatory patient care in well-resourced hospital contexts that is indicative of broader trends in healthcare technology integration. Understanding how different professional subgroups respond to implementation of patient-facing wellness technologies will be critical going forward. The next stage of our project will work to better understand how algorithmic bias and communication are functioning in relation to AI enabled health technologies. In addition, we will account for differing attitudes and behaviors towards technology integration as a result of varying professional subcultures among health workers. At the same time, algorithms that track patient deterioration and stream-line patient intake will continue to have a vital role particularly in under-resourced healthcare contexts that provide care to some of the most vulnerable patient populations. Thus, continuing to assess and improve these algorithms to reduce algorithmic and practitioner bias will remain an ongoing priority, especially to keep these programs in line with developing research findings.       Last Modified: 03/23/2022       Submitted by: Shion Guha]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
