<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  A Powerful Clinical Aid in the Diagnosis of Vaginitis to Prevent PTB and Stop STI Transmission]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>249726.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>249726</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Henry Ahn</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>hahn@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927069</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is to provide fast, accurate diagnosis of vaginal infections.  Vaginitis results in 10 million office visits a year representing 10% of all US women’s health visits, is known to dramatically increase susceptibility to sexually transmitted infections. External testing is expensive and can take from a day to weeks for results. For current in-office tests, 40% of all yeast infections and 30% of bacterial infections are misdiagnosed and require further visits.  More importantly, vaginitis can lead to a large fraction of spontaneous preterm births - a major cause of neonatal mortality, emotional distress and lifelong disability worldwide. In the US, PTB results in healthcare costs of $26 B/year, motivating a fast and accurate test.  This project will develop an advanced test that uses artificial intelligence (AI) to study samples quickly and accurately in the doctor's office.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research Phase I project advances a novel test for vaginitis upon clinical presentation.  This project leverages Artificial Intelligence (AI) image analysis with a high-quality fluorescence microscope to rapidly scan specimens in the doctor's office for fast diagnosis. This project will validate preliminary studies suggesting higher image accuracy compared to viewing similar samples under a microscope. Phase 1 of this project will examine prepared samples from diverse patient populations of up to 500 women to optimize analysis and characterization of VHA automated digital pathology system. All samples will be compared to manual assessment currently used clinically. Additionally, user testing in multiple types of clinical research environments, such as medical schools and health networks, will be undertaken to diversify patient sample populations.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/26/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/14/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2026102</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Peggy</FirstName>
<LastName>Robinson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Peggy S Robinson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[peggy.robinson@cazahealth.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000804452</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/26/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>CAZA HEALTH LLC</Name>
<CityName>EARLYSVILLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>229362407</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5402390668</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>379 REAS FORD RD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[STE 1]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>VA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>DPJMXF121964</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CAZA HEALTH LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[CAZA HEALTH LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>Earlysville</CityName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>229362407</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[379 Reas Ford Rd Ste 1]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>VA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5345</Code>
<Text>BIOMEDICAL ENGINEERING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8009</Code>
<Text>Scientifc Software Integration</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8032</Code>
<Text>Software Services and Applications</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8038</Code>
<Text>Biotechnology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~249726</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="Default">Ten percent of all doctor visits from women are for vaginitis in the United States (&gt;10 million physician office visits) which equates to a greater than $3Billion market opportunity.&nbsp; &nbsp;The current diagnostic tools that physician have access to are either wet mount microscopy or send-out molecular tests which take days to weeks to get results and carry significant costs.&nbsp; Some of these tests can exhibit low sensitivity or specificity.&nbsp; Most physicians are faced with making diagnostic decisions based on clinical symptoms and/or results from brightfield microscopy.&nbsp; This results in about 40% of all yeast infections being misdiagnosed and 30% of bacterial vaginosis requiring a second office visit to resolve.&nbsp; Excellent point-of-care (POC) diagnostic tools for women's health conditions such as vaginitis continue to be lacking.</p> <p class="Default">&nbsp;</p> <p class="Default">Caza Health developed an automated vaginosis system (DayZ(TM) System) that utilizes a POC immunofluorescence (IF) assay coupled with an advanced optical detection platform and Artificial Intelligence (AI) algorithms to assist physicians quickly and effectively in the diagnosis of vaginitis. The software accurately searches scanned images for the targets of interest, then displays the status in an user-intuitive interface.</p> <p class="Default">&nbsp;</p> <p class="Default">The test called the DayZ(TM) Vaginal Health Assay (VHA) test provides the physician (Obstetricians, Gynecologists, In-vitro Fertilization Specialists, and Family Practitioners) with the critical information to aid in the diagnosis of bacterial vaginosis (BV), Candidal vaginosis (CV) and Trichomonaisis from one sample and can be performed while the patient is still in the office.&nbsp;</p> <p class="Default">&nbsp;</p> <p class="Default">This Phase 1 SBIR program provided feasibility data and a path to commercialization of the DayZ(TM) System. The Caza Health team was able to deliver a test that is greater in sensitivity and accuracy than current standard of care, wet mount microscopy for BV, CV and TV.&nbsp;</p> <p class="Default">&nbsp;</p> <p class="Default">Key Phase 1 Accomplishments:</p> <ol> <li>Artificial Intelligence (AI) Algorithms that detect and quantify the specific targets indicative of bacterial, yeast infections and/or trichomoniasis.</li> <li>AI algorithms have been optimized to work with specific staining reagents to enhance organism detection.</li> <li>Sensitivity, Specificity and Accuracy using the AI algorithms that exceeds current standard of care, wet mount microscopy.&nbsp; See table below.</li> </ol> <p class="Default">&nbsp;</p> <table border="1" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="0"> <tbody> <tr> <td width="522" valign="top"> <p>&nbsp;</p> <table border="1" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="0" width="597"> <tbody> <tr> <td valign="top"> <p><strong>Organism</strong></p> </td> <td valign="top"> <p><strong>Wet mount</strong></p> </td> <td valign="top"> <p><strong>Culture</strong></p> </td> <td valign="top"> <p><strong>Antigen detection</strong></p> </td> <td valign="top"> <p><strong>DNA</strong></p> </td> <td valign="top"> <p><strong>Day Z? Test</strong></p> </td> </tr> <tr> <td valign="top"> <p>Bacterial vaginosis/ Clue     Cells</p> </td> <td valign="top"> <p>81% / 94%</p> </td> <td valign="top"> <p>89% / 93%</p> </td> <td valign="top"> <p>93% / 93%</p> </td> <td valign="top"> <p>94% / 81%</p> </td> <td valign="top"> <p>100%/96%</p> </td> </tr> <tr> <td valign="top"> <p>Candidiasis</p> </td> <td valign="top"> <p>35-45% / 99%</p> </td> <td valign="top"> <p>67% / 66%</p> </td> <td valign="top"> <p>61-81 % / 97%</p> </td> <td valign="top"> <p>80% / 98%</p> </td> <td valign="top"> <p>100%/94%</p> </td> </tr> <tr> <td valign="top"> <p>Trichomoniasis</p> </td> <td valign="top"> <p>38-82% / 100%</p> </td> <td valign="top"> <p>98% / 100%</p> </td> <td valign="top"> <p>86% / 99%</p> </td> <td valign="top"> <p>88-91% / 100%</p> </td> <td valign="top"> <p>100%/94%</p> </td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <p class="Default">&nbsp;</p> </td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <p style="padding-left: 30px;">4.&nbsp; Scale up and manufacturing of pilot lot of reagents by Randox Biosciences (collaborator on Phase 1 SBIR program).</p> <p style="padding-left: 30px;">5.&nbsp; Verifying of AI algorithms and staining reagents in clinical samples from a study performed by Edward Via College of Osteopathic Medicine (VCOM).</p> <p class="Default" style="padding-left: 30px;">&nbsp;</p> <p class="Default">In summary, the Phase 1 SBIR program developed and evaluated the DayZ(TM) System (Minimum Viable Product) for vaginosis for future validation.&nbsp; The system is able to use the current collection method of patient samples on the slides traditionally used by physicians.&nbsp; The system measures over 50 million pixels at two magnifications, stores data, so the AI Algorithms can select the targets of interest and present the high priority images to the physician for verification.&nbsp; The AI algorithms were finalized to be used in validation studies, one currently in process with VCOM.</p> <p class="Default">&nbsp;</p> <p class="Default">Additionally, the process for reagent manufacturing scale up was established and verified with partner, Randox Biosciences.&nbsp; &nbsp;Pilot lots were established with stability of two years.</p> <p class="Default">&nbsp;</p> <p class="Default">The improved accuracy of the DayZ(TM) test; reduction of physician hands-on-time; availability of results at the point of care, and cost-effectiveness will directly result in better patient outcomes.</p> <p class="Default">&nbsp;</p> <p>The team will use this assay and the learnings from the product development to commercialize the DayZ(TM) VHA Test as well as expand applications into other sexually transmitted infections such as gonorrhea and chlamydia.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/17/2021<br>      Modified by: Peggy&nbsp;S&nbsp;Robinson</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2026102/2026102_10702291_1631915332032_DayZSystem--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2026102/2026102_10702291_1631915332032_DayZSystem--rgov-800width.jpg" title="DayZ(TM) System"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2026102/2026102_10702291_1631915332032_DayZSystem--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="DayZ(TM) System"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The DayZ? System. Caza Health?s compact scanning fluorescence microscope (see yellow arrow) sitting next to a computer. Sample slide is inserted for diagnostic evaluation and read automatically for targets of interest.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Caza Health</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Peggy&nbsp;S&nbsp;Robinson</div> <div class="imageTitle">DayZ(TM) System</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2026102/2026102_10702291_1631915521973_CH130_CH129-6_pic3_WR--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2026102/2026102_10702291_1631915521973_CH130_CH129-6_pic3_WR--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Clue Cells"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2026102/2026102_10702291_1631915521973_CH130_CH129-6_pic3_WR--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Clue Cells"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Clue Cells indicative of bacterial vaginosis identified by the DayZ(TM) AI Algorithms</div> <div class="imageCredit">Caza Health</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Peggy&nbsp;S&nbsp;Robinson</div> <div class="imageTitle">Clue Cells</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2026102/2026102_10702291_1631915687735_CH114_pic1_BGRW--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2026102/2026102_10702291_1631915687735_CH114_pic1_BGRW--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Yeast Pseudohyphae"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2026102/2026102_10702291_1631915687735_CH114_pic1_BGRW--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Yeast Pseudohyphae"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Yeast pseudohayphae detected by DayZ(TM) System</div> <div class="imageCredit">Caza Health</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Peggy&nbsp;S&nbsp;Robinson</div> <div class="imageTitle">Yeast Pseudohyphae</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2026102/2026102_10702291_1631915957206_pic25_40X_WGRB--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2026102/2026102_10702291_1631915957206_pic25_40X_WGRB--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Yeast and Trich"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2026102/2026102_10702291_1631915957206_pic25_40X_WGRB--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Yeast and Trich"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Images of yeast pseudohyphae and swarm of trich identified by the DayZ(TM) System</div> <div class="imageCredit">Caza Health</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Peggy&nbsp;S&nbsp;Robinson</div> <div class="imageTitle">Yeast and Trich</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[Ten percent of all doctor visits from women are for vaginitis in the United States (&gt;10 million physician office visits) which equates to a greater than $3Billion market opportunity.   The current diagnostic tools that physician have access to are either wet mount microscopy or send-out molecular tests which take days to weeks to get results and carry significant costs.  Some of these tests can exhibit low sensitivity or specificity.  Most physicians are faced with making diagnostic decisions based on clinical symptoms and/or results from brightfield microscopy.  This results in about 40% of all yeast infections being misdiagnosed and 30% of bacterial vaginosis requiring a second office visit to resolve.  Excellent point-of-care (POC) diagnostic tools for women's health conditions such as vaginitis continue to be lacking.   Caza Health developed an automated vaginosis system (DayZ(TM) System) that utilizes a POC immunofluorescence (IF) assay coupled with an advanced optical detection platform and Artificial Intelligence (AI) algorithms to assist physicians quickly and effectively in the diagnosis of vaginitis. The software accurately searches scanned images for the targets of interest, then displays the status in an user-intuitive interface.   The test called the DayZ(TM) Vaginal Health Assay (VHA) test provides the physician (Obstetricians, Gynecologists, In-vitro Fertilization Specialists, and Family Practitioners) with the critical information to aid in the diagnosis of bacterial vaginosis (BV), Candidal vaginosis (CV) and Trichomonaisis from one sample and can be performed while the patient is still in the office.    This Phase 1 SBIR program provided feasibility data and a path to commercialization of the DayZ(TM) System. The Caza Health team was able to deliver a test that is greater in sensitivity and accuracy than current standard of care, wet mount microscopy for BV, CV and TV.    Key Phase 1 Accomplishments:  Artificial Intelligence (AI) Algorithms that detect and quantify the specific targets indicative of bacterial, yeast infections and/or trichomoniasis. AI algorithms have been optimized to work with specific staining reagents to enhance organism detection. Sensitivity, Specificity and Accuracy using the AI algorithms that exceeds current standard of care, wet mount microscopy.  See table below.                Organism    Wet mount    Culture    Antigen detection    DNA    Day Z? Test      Bacterial vaginosis/ Clue     Cells    81% / 94%    89% / 93%    93% / 93%    94% / 81%    100%/96%      Candidiasis    35-45% / 99%    67% / 66%    61-81 % / 97%    80% / 98%    100%/94%      Trichomoniasis    38-82% / 100%    98% / 100%    86% / 99%    88-91% / 100%    100%/94%           4.  Scale up and manufacturing of pilot lot of reagents by Randox Biosciences (collaborator on Phase 1 SBIR program). 5.  Verifying of AI algorithms and staining reagents in clinical samples from a study performed by Edward Via College of Osteopathic Medicine (VCOM).   In summary, the Phase 1 SBIR program developed and evaluated the DayZ(TM) System (Minimum Viable Product) for vaginosis for future validation.  The system is able to use the current collection method of patient samples on the slides traditionally used by physicians.  The system measures over 50 million pixels at two magnifications, stores data, so the AI Algorithms can select the targets of interest and present the high priority images to the physician for verification.  The AI algorithms were finalized to be used in validation studies, one currently in process with VCOM.   Additionally, the process for reagent manufacturing scale up was established and verified with partner, Randox Biosciences.   Pilot lots were established with stability of two years.   The improved accuracy of the DayZ(TM) test; reduction of physician hands-on-time; availability of results at the point of care, and cost-effectiveness will directly result in better patient outcomes.    The team will use this assay and the learnings from the product development to commercialize the DayZ(TM) VHA Test as well as expand applications into other sexually transmitted infections such as gonorrhea and chlamydia.        Last Modified: 09/17/2021       Submitted by: Peggy S Robinson]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
