<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAISE-SitS: Designing models to forecast how biogeochemical fluctuations in soil systems govern soil development, terrestrial water storage and ecosystem nutrient fluxes]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>648574.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>648574</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jonathan G Wynn</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jwynn@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924725</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Managing water resources requires a full understanding of the water cycle. The current understanding may, however, be missing a fundamental factor of the water cycle-soil structure. Soil structure, the arrangement of soil particles and pores, was recently discovered to be changing faster than previously thought - over a few decades - in response to shifts in precipitation patterns. Fluctuations in soil structure alter the amount of water that can be stored near the surface and the ease with which water moves through the soil. Although plants, animals, and microbes may have dominant roles in altering soil structure, it is unclear how these processes work together or are modified by soil properties. New mathematical models are needed to study the causes of these observed alterations in soil structure and to examine plant-soil-water responses to varying environmental conditions. The research may fill this need by developing the next generation of models to include biological, physical, and chemical interactions from local soils in the US. Through the development of these models, five faculty from minority groups underrepresented in STEM fields, four postdoctoral scholars, and ten undergraduate researchers will be trained.   The discoveries will be disseminated to the community through webinars, online tools, and local presentations as well as integrated into current curricula across four universities. The models will allow the effects of soil structure fluctuations on ecosystem processes to be evaluated at diverse spatial and time scales.  The research may improve forecasting of future availability and quality of water resources, soils, and associated ecosystem services. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Soil ecosystem models (empirical and process-based) will be developed at multiple spatial scales to link soil structure and function in order to enhance the prediction of water and biogeochemical fluxes on timescales of decades to centuries. These models will be parameterized using soil, plant, and aquatic microbiome data collected across a strong precipitation gradient in the central USA (part of NSF Kansas Established Program to Stimulate Competitive Research, EPSCoR) and continental-scale soil databases (e.g., the National Cooperative Soil Survey Soil Characterization Database, United States Department of Agriculture). Structural equation, 2-D pedon, watershed and continental scale models will be developed to examine and account for the interaction between soil hydraulic properties (e.g., macropores and Ksat) and terrestrial biogeochemical fluxes. Products from this work will include: a mechanistic understanding of macropore evolution with climate; development of climate-dependent pedotransfer functions for pedon, watershed, and continental-scale models; predictive capabilities for soil microbial community responses to changing soil structure; a mechanistic understanding of soil macropore-topography-hillslope structure-climate interactions; and quantification of climate-induced macropore changes to biogeochemistry and water cycles from the pedon to the continental scale. The modeling tools proposed here are expected to address environmental sustainability over time and enhance the ability to predict land-atmosphere dynamics, subsurface water storage, water table fluctuations, and flood events. These models will provide community-accessible tools to examine how soil, hydrologic and biogeochemical feedbacks govern nutrient fluxes, and will ultimately be useful toward alleviating nationwide problems such as managing the nitrogen cycle and the Gulf of Mexico dead zone. Finally, this work will test a new Rule of Life (RoL): Life's responses to climate driven changes in the soil fabric which prompt the emergence of integrated terrestrial responses that are more rapid than typically considered.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/16/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/21/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2026874</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Pamela</FirstName>
<LastName>Sullivan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Pamela Sullivan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[pamela.sullivan@oregonstate.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000683290</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/16/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Oregon State University</Name>
<CityName>CORVALLIS</CityName>
<ZipCode>973318655</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5417374933</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1500 SW JEFFERSON AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OR04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>MZ4DYXE1SL98</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OREGON STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Oregon State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Corvallis</CityName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<ZipCode>973318507</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OR04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1139</Code>
<Text>RSCH EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD SITES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7222</Code>
<Text>XC-Crosscutting Activities Pro</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7275</Code>
<Text>Cross-BIO Activities</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>068Z</Code>
<Text>URoL-Understanding Rules of Life</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01001819DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~648572</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-5c565bfa-7fff-c226-9e91-a1d5eb415f17"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Our work probes the hypothesis that life's rapid responses to climate drive changes in the soil fabric, prompting emergence of integrated terrestrial responses that are more rapid than typically considered. We demonstrate the interactive effects of water availability and root and microbial activities on soil structure and associated fluid flows. For example, we demonstrated that land cover and land management can influence soil structural attributes deep (i.e., &gt;2 m) beneath the surface. Where roots are scarce, vegetative cover is periodically removed by harvesting, and soils possess meaningful shrink-swell characteristics, soil can exhibit unexpectedly large water-stable aggregates at depth in more mesic regions. In drier conditions, deep SOC has a much greater propensity to promote aggregation. These trends are largely reversed in native, perennial systems, suggesting that modifying the surface soil structure and reducing deep root abundance in agricultural fields can promote SOC preservation deep in the regolith regardless of rainfall, but via different mechanisms in mesic vs drier conditions.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Several recent discoveries also point to the effects of climate change on soil aggregate structure which affects the voids between aggregates (macropores) and, ultimately, the rate at which water flows through the land surface. We showed that climate effects on soil pore space are linked to SOC through soil aggregate formation and stability and that this link can be represented by the complexation of SOC and clay mineral surfaces. We also demonstrated the primary control of soil structure near the surface for water exchange between the land and atmosphere at a continental scale.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>To better understand the role of roots and subsurface structure, we developed 1- and 2-D reactive transport models. Outcomes of the models suggest that </span><span>deepening roots can enhance carbonate weathering by promoting recharge and CO</span><span><span>2</span></span><span>&ndash;carbonate contact in the deep subsurface and the hydrological impacts of rooting characteristics can be more influential than those of soil CO</span><span><span>2</span></span><span> distribution in modulating weathering rates. At the broader scale, we also found that differences in climate (wet vs. dry) plays a more important role in solute generation and soil organic carbon decomposition than permeability contrasts in the subsurface. </span><span>&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>We developed a new theory to merge measured properties of the soil (e.g., presence of aggregates, macropores between the aggregates, and shrink-swell potential) with continuous soil moisture data from field sensors. This theory allows soil hydraulic properties&mdash;which control water flow in the soil&mdash;to be dynamically updated at each time step of the sensor data. By incorporating quantified soil structural and shrink-swell potential information into traditional models of soil hydraulic properties our work opens the door to more accurate predictions of water and carbon cycling.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>We also developed a novel way of incorporating soil hydraulic properties into broad-scale land surface models (LSMs) that incorporated soil depth. This method opens the door for prediction of deep soil hydraulic properties from remotely-sensed imagery using airborne or satellite data.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Our work resulted in two new large databases that merged soil laboratory data with field recorded soil and site descriptions. The first is the Pedogenic and Environmental DataSet (PEDS) that was compiled using USDA-Natural Resources Conservation Service National (NRCS) Cooperative Soil Survey (NCSS) data that have been collected from hundreds of thousands of soil samples largely within the US stretching as far back as the late 1920s. The second merges lab and field data for all the megapit and distributed sites within the National Ecological Observatory Network (NEON). These two continental-scale datasets are the first of their kind to be made available in a form that allows field-scale properties to be analyzed with soil lab data ultimately improving our understanding and prediction of global-scale changes to soil carbon and hydrology.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Finally, we developed an emulator that captures the response of the Community Land Model (CLM) to variations in climate, soil, and vegetation parameters. This emulator requires a fraction of the computational cost of the model. Applications of emulators include both improving estimation of soil parameters as well as testing hypotheses related to future structure and function of soils in a warmer climate.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/02/2023<br>      Modified by: Pamela&nbsp;Sullivan</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   Our work probes the hypothesis that life's rapid responses to climate drive changes in the soil fabric, prompting emergence of integrated terrestrial responses that are more rapid than typically considered. We demonstrate the interactive effects of water availability and root and microbial activities on soil structure and associated fluid flows. For example, we demonstrated that land cover and land management can influence soil structural attributes deep (i.e., &gt;2 m) beneath the surface. Where roots are scarce, vegetative cover is periodically removed by harvesting, and soils possess meaningful shrink-swell characteristics, soil can exhibit unexpectedly large water-stable aggregates at depth in more mesic regions. In drier conditions, deep SOC has a much greater propensity to promote aggregation. These trends are largely reversed in native, perennial systems, suggesting that modifying the surface soil structure and reducing deep root abundance in agricultural fields can promote SOC preservation deep in the regolith regardless of rainfall, but via different mechanisms in mesic vs drier conditions.  Several recent discoveries also point to the effects of climate change on soil aggregate structure which affects the voids between aggregates (macropores) and, ultimately, the rate at which water flows through the land surface. We showed that climate effects on soil pore space are linked to SOC through soil aggregate formation and stability and that this link can be represented by the complexation of SOC and clay mineral surfaces. We also demonstrated the primary control of soil structure near the surface for water exchange between the land and atmosphere at a continental scale. To better understand the role of roots and subsurface structure, we developed 1- and 2-D reactive transport models. Outcomes of the models suggest that deepening roots can enhance carbonate weathering by promoting recharge and CO2&ndash;carbonate contact in the deep subsurface and the hydrological impacts of rooting characteristics can be more influential than those of soil CO2 distribution in modulating weathering rates. At the broader scale, we also found that differences in climate (wet vs. dry) plays a more important role in solute generation and soil organic carbon decomposition than permeability contrasts in the subsurface.   We developed a new theory to merge measured properties of the soil (e.g., presence of aggregates, macropores between the aggregates, and shrink-swell potential) with continuous soil moisture data from field sensors. This theory allows soil hydraulic properties&mdash;which control water flow in the soil&mdash;to be dynamically updated at each time step of the sensor data. By incorporating quantified soil structural and shrink-swell potential information into traditional models of soil hydraulic properties our work opens the door to more accurate predictions of water and carbon cycling. We also developed a novel way of incorporating soil hydraulic properties into broad-scale land surface models (LSMs) that incorporated soil depth. This method opens the door for prediction of deep soil hydraulic properties from remotely-sensed imagery using airborne or satellite data. Our work resulted in two new large databases that merged soil laboratory data with field recorded soil and site descriptions. The first is the Pedogenic and Environmental DataSet (PEDS) that was compiled using USDA-Natural Resources Conservation Service National (NRCS) Cooperative Soil Survey (NCSS) data that have been collected from hundreds of thousands of soil samples largely within the US stretching as far back as the late 1920s. The second merges lab and field data for all the megapit and distributed sites within the National Ecological Observatory Network (NEON). These two continental-scale datasets are the first of their kind to be made available in a form that allows field-scale properties to be analyzed with soil lab data ultimately improving our understanding and prediction of global-scale changes to soil carbon and hydrology. Finally, we developed an emulator that captures the response of the Community Land Model (CLM) to variations in climate, soil, and vegetation parameters. This emulator requires a fraction of the computational cost of the model. Applications of emulators include both improving estimation of soil parameters as well as testing hypotheses related to future structure and function of soils in a warmer climate.          Last Modified: 05/02/2023       Submitted by: Pamela Sullivan]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
