<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[FW-HTF-P: Exploring Creative Design at the Human-technology Frontier Through the Emerging Artist-technologist Occupation]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>149674.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>149674</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sara Kiesler</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>skiesler@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928643</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Creative skills have been identified as most valuable for future workers across domains, given the expectation that intelligent machines will increasingly replace routine tasks currently performed by people.  The creative design process also is changing due to advances in technology, in particular, artificial intelligence (AI) and augmented and virtual reality (AR/VR).  What are the creative skills needed for the future workforce, and how can these be best developed and nurtured? This project addresses this question by exploring how advances in AI and AR/VR technology are changing the emerging occupation of artist-technologist.  As experts in both arts and technology who see no barriers between these two fields, artist-technologists are in a unique position to design previously inconceivable media products with relevance and applications not only for the arts and entertainment, but many other fields such as education, health care, marketing and new product development. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project involves a diverse group of researchers and practitioners with relevant expertise in the arts, AI, AR/VR, engineering, learning sciences, education, business, entrepreneurship, career education, ethics, and disability in an exploratory study of how specific applications of AR/VR and AI may affect artist-technologists’ creative process, professional identity, overall work experience, preparation, and related equity and inclusion issues. The initial focus of the project is on musicians and composers, and will expand to other artistic endeavors. At the core of the study are exploratory conversations with key stakeholders (conducted in the tradition of customer discovery interviews promoted by NSF's Innovation Corps program), followed by three task forces drawing implications and identifying issues worthy of further research for enhancing future artist-technologists’ design process at the human-technology frontier (future technology focus), effectively preparing future artist-technologists to make best use of AI and AR/VR in their work (future workers focus), and increasing access to this occupation by underrepresented populations (future work focus), respectively.  A series of team learning experiences and touch-point events informs this collaborative work, while also supporting the project team in developing the needed cross-disciplinary expertise and strategies.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/28/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/04/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2026439</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
<LastName>Bocko</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>F</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mark F Bocko</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[bocko@ece.rochester.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000172582</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/28/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rachel</FirstName>
<LastName>Roberts</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Rachel Roberts</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[rroberts@esm.rochester.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000860178</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/04/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Zhiyao</FirstName>
<LastName>Duan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Zhiyao Duan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[zhiyao.duan@rochester.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000662423</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/28/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Raffaella</FirstName>
<LastName>Borasi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Raffaella Borasi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[rborasi@warner.rochester.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000119317</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/28/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Doser</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>James C Doser</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jdoser@esm.rochester.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000822519</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/28/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate>08/04/2021</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Joseph</FirstName>
<LastName>Testani</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Joseph A Testani</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jtestani@ur.rochester.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000822544</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/28/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Rochester</Name>
<CityName>ROCHESTER</CityName>
<ZipCode>146113847</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5852754031</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>910 GENESEE ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[STE 200]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>25</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY25</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>F27KDXZMF9Y8</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ROCHESTER</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Rochester]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>146270140</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>25</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY25</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>103Y</Code>
<Text>FW-HTF Futr Wrk Hum-Tech Frntr</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>063Z</Code>
<Text>FW-HTF Futr Wrk Hum-Tech Frntr</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~149674</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This Future of Work planning grant focused on <em>Exploring Creative Design at the Human-Technology Frontier through the Emerging Artist-technologist Occupation</em>.&nbsp; At the core of this project were interviews with 41 individuals working at the intersection of art and technology to better understand how they used technology in their work, their career paths, how they learned the technical and artistic skills needed for their work, what challenges they encountered on the way, and which of their current needs could potentially be addressed with applications of artificial intelligence and/or virtual/augmented reality.<em></em></p> <p>The following insights generated by this project could inform new applications of artificial intelligence and/or virtual/augmented reality for artists as well as educational programs to prepare the next generation of artist-technologists:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Artificial intelligence and virtual/augmented reality</strong><strong> have great potential to increase both audience engagement with art and access to artistic creation -&nbsp;</strong>as these technologies can help <em>engage</em>&nbsp;audiences with art rather than just <em>observe</em>&nbsp;it, as well as enable artists to engage on their own in artistic creations that in the past would have required much bigger infrastructure and dedicated staff time (and, thus, funding). &nbsp;Applications of Artificial Intelligence that <em>enable</em> rather than <em>substitute</em> for artistic creation, in particular, have great potential to increase access and <em>democratize art</em>.<strong></strong></li> <li><strong>Most artists are not making use of existing technologies</strong> because they lack the necessary technical knowledge and skills.&nbsp;New interfaces as well as educational interventions for artists that facilitate their use of existing as well as new technologies in their everyday work are needed.<strong></strong></li> <li><strong>Future career paths at the intersection of art and technology are still unclear. </strong>&nbsp;Most of the artist-technologists we interviewed had unusual and non-linear paths leading to their current jobs and they shared the challenge of finding a paying job involving art and technology; many ended up <em>creating</em>&nbsp;their own job as free-lancers or entrepreneurs.&nbsp; <strong></strong></li> <li><strong>Interdisciplinary work is necessary - yet challenging. </strong>Most of the artist-technologists we interviewed reported collaborating with people with different expertise.&nbsp; They recognized the critical need for such teamwork (especially since technology changes so rapidly), yet they also identified great communication challenges between artists and technologists due to their different cultures/ worldviews and lack of a common <em>professional language</em>.<strong></strong></li> <li><strong>Future artists need to develop a different skillset in order to fully capitalize on technology. </strong>The following competencies seem especially important: (a) being aware of possible integrations of art and technology in their field - in terms of both products and career opportunities; (b) having deep expertise in their artistic field PLUS enough understanding of potentially-related fields and technologies to collaborate with experts in those fields; (c) being able to effectively communicate and work with people in other fields; (d) being able to learn things on their own (especially new technologies).<em></em></li> <li><strong>Non-traditional learning experiences are needed to prepare future artist-technologists.&nbsp;</strong> The competencies identified above are currently not part of traditional programs that prepare artists. Most of the artist-technologists we interviewed learned these competencies on their own, through non-traditional learning experiences that included learning new technologies/fields by trying out things, making mistakes and learning from those mistakes - what is often referred to as <em>tinkering</em>.<em></em></li> </ul> <p>An elaboration of these insights, along with information about some representative products, profiles, and career paths at the intersection of art and technology, has been made publicly available on the project website. This is intended to provide a set of resources to support the preparation of future artist-technologists.</p> <p>Another outcome of the project was the development and submission of a proposal for a Future of Work research grant, entitled <em>Toward an Ecosystem of Artificial-intelligence-powered Music Production (TEAMuP)</em>, building on the insights gained from our interviews to enable musicians to become more independent in the production of their music products.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/01/2022<br>      Modified by: Raffaella&nbsp;Borasi</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This Future of Work planning grant focused on Exploring Creative Design at the Human-Technology Frontier through the Emerging Artist-technologist Occupation.  At the core of this project were interviews with 41 individuals working at the intersection of art and technology to better understand how they used technology in their work, their career paths, how they learned the technical and artistic skills needed for their work, what challenges they encountered on the way, and which of their current needs could potentially be addressed with applications of artificial intelligence and/or virtual/augmented reality.  The following insights generated by this project could inform new applications of artificial intelligence and/or virtual/augmented reality for artists as well as educational programs to prepare the next generation of artist-technologists:  Artificial intelligence and virtual/augmented reality have great potential to increase both audience engagement with art and access to artistic creation - as these technologies can help engage audiences with art rather than just observe it, as well as enable artists to engage on their own in artistic creations that in the past would have required much bigger infrastructure and dedicated staff time (and, thus, funding).  Applications of Artificial Intelligence that enable rather than substitute for artistic creation, in particular, have great potential to increase access and democratize art. Most artists are not making use of existing technologies because they lack the necessary technical knowledge and skills. New interfaces as well as educational interventions for artists that facilitate their use of existing as well as new technologies in their everyday work are needed. Future career paths at the intersection of art and technology are still unclear.  Most of the artist-technologists we interviewed had unusual and non-linear paths leading to their current jobs and they shared the challenge of finding a paying job involving art and technology; many ended up creating their own job as free-lancers or entrepreneurs.   Interdisciplinary work is necessary - yet challenging. Most of the artist-technologists we interviewed reported collaborating with people with different expertise.  They recognized the critical need for such teamwork (especially since technology changes so rapidly), yet they also identified great communication challenges between artists and technologists due to their different cultures/ worldviews and lack of a common professional language. Future artists need to develop a different skillset in order to fully capitalize on technology. The following competencies seem especially important: (a) being aware of possible integrations of art and technology in their field - in terms of both products and career opportunities; (b) having deep expertise in their artistic field PLUS enough understanding of potentially-related fields and technologies to collaborate with experts in those fields; (c) being able to effectively communicate and work with people in other fields; (d) being able to learn things on their own (especially new technologies). Non-traditional learning experiences are needed to prepare future artist-technologists.  The competencies identified above are currently not part of traditional programs that prepare artists. Most of the artist-technologists we interviewed learned these competencies on their own, through non-traditional learning experiences that included learning new technologies/fields by trying out things, making mistakes and learning from those mistakes - what is often referred to as tinkering.   An elaboration of these insights, along with information about some representative products, profiles, and career paths at the intersection of art and technology, has been made publicly available on the project website. This is intended to provide a set of resources to support the preparation of future artist-technologists.  Another outcome of the project was the development and submission of a proposal for a Future of Work research grant, entitled Toward an Ecosystem of Artificial-intelligence-powered Music Production (TEAMuP), building on the insights gained from our interviews to enable musicians to become more independent in the production of their music products.       Last Modified: 08/01/2022       Submitted by: Raffaella Borasi]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
