<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[I-Corps:  Acoustic Filters for Next Generation Wireless Handsets]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ruth Shuman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rshuman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922160</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this I-Corps project is the development of technologies to improve bandwidth in the wireless infrastructure. Regulatory agencies world-wide are allocating new wireless spectrum to support increasing throughput demands. Radio systems will require wide bandwidth with low loss to meet the demanded data throughout. Currently available handset filter technology is not able to achieve such wide bandwidth with acceptable loss, resulting in sub-optimum system throughput. The proposed technology triples the bandwidth available in a radio’s front-end to serve the needs of the 5G filter market space. The thin-film technology enables a system that achieves wide bandwidths, low loss, may be manufactured with high yields in a cost-efficient manner at external foundries, and can be used in a form factor consistent with industry standards. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project is based on the development of a radio frequency filter technology that uses thin-films of lithium niobate (LN) resonators. Of particular interest are the LTE 77-79 bands defined as part of the 5th generation cellular network deployment plan (5G), which serves the 3.3 GHz - 5 GHz spectrum. The proposed technology explores translation of a microfabrication process capable of manufacturing acoustic resonators using thin-films of LN. The main challenge for the LN technology is ensuring operation at the frequency of interest for 5G bands (3-6 GHz) in a low-cost manufacturing process.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/28/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/28/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2026275</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Philip</FirstName>
<LastName>Marzolf</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Philip R Marzolf</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[Phil@MarzolfAdvisors.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000805990</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/28/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gianluca</FirstName>
<LastName>Piazza</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gianluca Piazza</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[piazza@ece.cmu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000491421</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/28/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gabriel</FirstName>
<LastName>Vidal</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gabriel Vidal</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[gvidal@andrew.cmu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000804987</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/28/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Carnegie-Mellon University</Name>
<CityName>PITTSBURGH</CityName>
<ZipCode>152133815</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4122688746</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5000 FORBES AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>U3NKNFLNQ613</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CARNEGIE MELLON UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>U3NKNFLNQ613</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Carnegie Mellon University]]></Name>
<CityName>Pittsburgh</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>152133890</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5000 Forbes Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The I-CORPS program was extremely valuable for evaluating the opportunity for technology commercialization as well as for enabling the professional training and growth of the personnel involved in the project. Interactions with more than 100 potential customers were made possible. It was particularly rewarding to engage with potential customers, supply chain managers and experts in technology commercialization.</p> <p>Learning about the importance of pivoting and searching for a broader spectrum of market opportunities was particularly helpful. The personnel learned about the relevance of formulating a clear plan for product insertion into the marketplace and obtained extremely valuable insights in the supply chain and marketing strategies typical of semiconductor products. The team also learned about the barrier to entry into the specific product business and was able to identify new market trends and technological opportunities. The personnel grew professionally by understanding the best methods to interact with customers and how to present to non-technical people.</p> <p>Customer engagement confirmed the value of the technology platform but suggested that greater commercial opportunities would be available if the technology could operate at much higher frequencies around 30 GHz or beyond. In this frequency range, the technology would be unrivaled and the market dynamics not already established. As a result of this analysis, the team looked into technical challenges associated with the development of the technology in this market space. Innovations and investments in fundamental research are required in order to bridge the gap and ensure the proposed product can operate at 30 GHz and beyond. Therefore, future activities will be focused on developing the technology and intellectual property for this new market space. <strong></strong></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/25/2022<br>      Modified by: Gianluca&nbsp;Piazza</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The I-CORPS program was extremely valuable for evaluating the opportunity for technology commercialization as well as for enabling the professional training and growth of the personnel involved in the project. Interactions with more than 100 potential customers were made possible. It was particularly rewarding to engage with potential customers, supply chain managers and experts in technology commercialization.  Learning about the importance of pivoting and searching for a broader spectrum of market opportunities was particularly helpful. The personnel learned about the relevance of formulating a clear plan for product insertion into the marketplace and obtained extremely valuable insights in the supply chain and marketing strategies typical of semiconductor products. The team also learned about the barrier to entry into the specific product business and was able to identify new market trends and technological opportunities. The personnel grew professionally by understanding the best methods to interact with customers and how to present to non-technical people.  Customer engagement confirmed the value of the technology platform but suggested that greater commercial opportunities would be available if the technology could operate at much higher frequencies around 30 GHz or beyond. In this frequency range, the technology would be unrivaled and the market dynamics not already established. As a result of this analysis, the team looked into technical challenges associated with the development of the technology in this market space. Innovations and investments in fundamental research are required in order to bridge the gap and ensure the proposed product can operate at 30 GHz and beyond. Therefore, future activities will be focused on developing the technology and intellectual property for this new market space.        Last Modified: 03/25/2022       Submitted by: Gianluca Piazza]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
