<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Rapid, Additive Manufacturing of Batteries (RAMB)]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>256000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>276000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anna Brady</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>abrady@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927077</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) project will develop a new process to reshape batteries through rapid, custom manufacturing. The battery industry’s manufacturing process has remained relatively unchanged over the past 40 years, impacting applications such as Digital Health and the Internet of Things (IoT). This project will develop a novel platform for battery manufacturing using a cure-on-command technology, which will expedite the components curing process from hours to seconds. The cure-on-command technology will provide added multiple benefits to battery manufacturing through elimination of certain processing steps, such as cost savings, capital equipment savings of 3x, and environmental friendliness.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The aims of this project are to benchmark the benefits of cure-on-command technology for rapid manufacturing of battery components, demonstrate its application for ultra-thin, flexible batteries, and highlight its technical and economic benefits to battery manufacturing. The biggest hurdle to new methods in battery manufacturing has been the thermal evaporation process, which is a slow (&lt;67 m2/min) and toxic process. This project will advance a faster (&gt;500 m2/min) curing process.  The key objectives of this proposal will be: (1) formulate zinc-silver oxide battery materials with cure-on-command technology, (2) test performance and durability of batteries in comparison with the state-of-the-art battery manufacturing process and materials, and (3) integrate and test a small prototype battery (20-220 mAh) to replace bulky, rigid coin cells in devices for Digital Health and IoT applications.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/10/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/03/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2026059</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rajan</FirstName>
<LastName>Kumar</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Rajan Kumar</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[rkumar@ateios.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000761198</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Ocella Inc</Name>
<CityName>NEWBERRY</CityName>
<ZipCode>474497128</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8458428185</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>7970 S ENERGY DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IN08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>PNM7TGPF9V62</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OCELLA INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Ocella Inc]]></Name>
<CityName>Newberry</CityName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>474497128</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[7970 South Energy Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IN08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8091</Code>
<Text>SBIR Outreach &amp; Tech. Assist</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8040</Code>
<Text>Energy and Environment</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8396</Code>
<Text>Clean Energy Technology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~256000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~20000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-60137c85-7fff-e613-1858-e896f5704be7"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The proposal on rapid additive manufacturing of batteries focuses on demonstrating the manufacturing and performance benefits of using radiation-curable polymers and treating them with electron beam (e-beam) radiation to create active electrodes in batteries against the industry standard for electrode processing (thermal curing). The report demonstrates the use of this technique to create lithium-carbon monofluoride (CFx) batteries with an energy density of ~800 mAh/g and a power density of ~2400 mWh/g compared to the traditional thermal curing process. This report also demonstrates preliminary data of the use of this process on lithium-ion batteries with a nickel-manganese-cobalt (NMC532) cathode, demonstrating the process? ability to be chemistry agnostic. Importantly, we demonstrate the process can manufacturing batteries 10x faster roll to roll and 1/5th of the cost compared to traditional battery manufacturing without any loss in performance.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The first objective is focused on the formulation of e-beam curable polymers, active materials, conductive additives, and additional chemicals to form a composite-colloidal ink to be cast into a film and cured using e-beam radiation. The formulation demonstrated good coating ability and high quality of crosslinking through e-beam curing, to yield high-performance e-beam curable battery components to be tested in the second objective.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The purpose of the second objective is to create and compare e-beam cured batteries of varying weight loadings to similar ones formulated using traditional PVDF and NMP formulations. Batteries were assembled at three different weight loads 12.5, 26, and 53 mg/cm2 with a target of achieving &gt;18 mAh/cm2 and tested at different currents to form a Ragone plot demonstrating the energy/power trade-offs. The results of this objective demonstrated e-beam curable batteries can achieve over 800 mAh/g at 250 uA, and only experience a small drop to 700 mAh/g at 1 mA. Generally, the e-beam curable batteries had demonstrated nearly 10% energy density improvement over traditional battery manufacturing.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The third objective was focused on real-time field testing for customers who are developing electronics for IoT and wearables. Most of these applications operate with low current draws followed by a series of high pulse current drains during wireless communication events. Based on customer discovery exercises associated with the NSF iCorp program we determined that the most common energy density in the market of IoT and wearables was 18 mAh/cm2. After formulations of these batteries using e-beam polymers were fabricated, they were tested under current profiles replicating a medical device with a Bluetooth module (Nordic nRF52832). During initial testing, experiments showed that e-beam formulation and battery design in the previous objective had a poor performance during high pulse currents. However, with improvements to the formulation, the e-beam curable battery had achieved a leading energy density compared to the existing thin-film batteries for IoT and wearable applications where it provides nearly 50% more energy per area and a more stable discharge profile under BLE protocols. As the first three objectives focus on performance to attract potential customers, the final objective analyzes the cost of the final battery product and compared with existing solutions.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The final objective leverages the NSF-cost model along with Ateios? custom battery calculator to predict the battery performance and cost. In comparison to existing thin-film batteries, alkaline, and lithium-manganese oxide, our unit economics demonstrated that a battery of the same size using our technology would provide our potential customers with over 65% more nominal capacity at price parity. In summary our report demonstrates that e-beam curable batteries can manufacture any type and size of high-performance batteries at better unit economics compared to traditional battery manufacturing based on thermal curing processing and toxic chemicals.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/29/2021<br>      Modified by: Rajan&nbsp;Kumar</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2026059/2026059_10694924_1635483604630_RAMB_UltraThinBattery--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2026059/2026059_10694924_1635483604630_RAMB_UltraThinBattery--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Ultra Thin Battery Manufactured using Proposed Technology"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2026059/2026059_10694924_1635483604630_RAMB_UltraThinBattery--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Ultra Thin Battery Manufactured using Proposed Technology"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Ultra thin battery manufacturing by the proposed process and mounted onto a flexible board</div> <div class="imageCredit">Ocella Inc</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Rajan&nbsp;Kumar</div> <div class="imageTitle">Ultra Thin Battery Manufactured using Proposed Technology</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2026059/2026059_10694924_1635483510654_BatteryPerformanceRAMB--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2026059/2026059_10694924_1635483510654_BatteryPerformanceRAMB--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Battery Performance C/60 and BLE Protocols"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2026059/2026059_10694924_1635483510654_BatteryPerformanceRAMB--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Battery Performance C/60 and BLE Protocols"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Performance of RAMB battery under constant discharge of 1 mA and under BLE pulsing.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Ocella Inc</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Rajan&nbsp;Kumar</div> <div class="imageTitle">Battery Performance C/60 and BLE Protocols</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   The proposal on rapid additive manufacturing of batteries focuses on demonstrating the manufacturing and performance benefits of using radiation-curable polymers and treating them with electron beam (e-beam) radiation to create active electrodes in batteries against the industry standard for electrode processing (thermal curing). The report demonstrates the use of this technique to create lithium-carbon monofluoride (CFx) batteries with an energy density of ~800 mAh/g and a power density of ~2400 mWh/g compared to the traditional thermal curing process. This report also demonstrates preliminary data of the use of this process on lithium-ion batteries with a nickel-manganese-cobalt (NMC532) cathode, demonstrating the process? ability to be chemistry agnostic. Importantly, we demonstrate the process can manufacturing batteries 10x faster roll to roll and 1/5th of the cost compared to traditional battery manufacturing without any loss in performance. The first objective is focused on the formulation of e-beam curable polymers, active materials, conductive additives, and additional chemicals to form a composite-colloidal ink to be cast into a film and cured using e-beam radiation. The formulation demonstrated good coating ability and high quality of crosslinking through e-beam curing, to yield high-performance e-beam curable battery components to be tested in the second objective. The purpose of the second objective is to create and compare e-beam cured batteries of varying weight loadings to similar ones formulated using traditional PVDF and NMP formulations. Batteries were assembled at three different weight loads 12.5, 26, and 53 mg/cm2 with a target of achieving &gt;18 mAh/cm2 and tested at different currents to form a Ragone plot demonstrating the energy/power trade-offs. The results of this objective demonstrated e-beam curable batteries can achieve over 800 mAh/g at 250 uA, and only experience a small drop to 700 mAh/g at 1 mA. Generally, the e-beam curable batteries had demonstrated nearly 10% energy density improvement over traditional battery manufacturing. The third objective was focused on real-time field testing for customers who are developing electronics for IoT and wearables. Most of these applications operate with low current draws followed by a series of high pulse current drains during wireless communication events. Based on customer discovery exercises associated with the NSF iCorp program we determined that the most common energy density in the market of IoT and wearables was 18 mAh/cm2. After formulations of these batteries using e-beam polymers were fabricated, they were tested under current profiles replicating a medical device with a Bluetooth module (Nordic nRF52832). During initial testing, experiments showed that e-beam formulation and battery design in the previous objective had a poor performance during high pulse currents. However, with improvements to the formulation, the e-beam curable battery had achieved a leading energy density compared to the existing thin-film batteries for IoT and wearable applications where it provides nearly 50% more energy per area and a more stable discharge profile under BLE protocols. As the first three objectives focus on performance to attract potential customers, the final objective analyzes the cost of the final battery product and compared with existing solutions. The final objective leverages the NSF-cost model along with Ateios? custom battery calculator to predict the battery performance and cost. In comparison to existing thin-film batteries, alkaline, and lithium-manganese oxide, our unit economics demonstrated that a battery of the same size using our technology would provide our potential customers with over 65% more nominal capacity at price parity. In summary our report demonstrates that e-beam curable batteries can manufacture any type and size of high-performance batteries at better unit economics compared to traditional battery manufacturing based on thermal curing processing and toxic chemicals.             Last Modified: 10/29/2021       Submitted by: Rajan Kumar]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
