<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[FW-HTF-P: Planning to study automation and the future of news production]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>130854.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>130854</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Andruid Kerne</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This planning grant supports multidisciplinary teambuilding and the refinement of a research plan for convergent research on the future of work involving humans and technology. The specific focus is the work of journalists who create articles, videos and other content to inform the public. Journalism has long been affected by new technologies, including printing, internet distribution, and automated curation, in the form of social media news feeds. Emerging artificial intelligence technologies capable of creating texts, statistics, videos, diagrams and data-driven animations are anticipated to further impact the profession. Understanding these impacts is important because journalists perform the socially important function of informing the public about events and activities that affect their decision making. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project convenes an interdisciplinary team of scholars to a develop a proposal for sustained research addressing the future of news production, considering technologies such as natural language processing, crowdsourcing, information visualization, and artificial intelligence, taken broadly. The team members’ backgrounds span a range of disciplinary areas, including information science, computer science, economics, sociology, communications, and design. The planned work includes refining the project vision and theoretical framework, recruiting field sites and an advisory board, conducting pilot research to identify relevant technologies and impacts and planning of convergent research activities. Pilot research will include observation, interviews and focus groups with journalists to understand the impact of current technologies and possibilities for future technologies.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/04/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/14/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2026583</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kevin</FirstName>
<LastName>Crowston</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kevin Crowston</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[crowston@syr.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000106314</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/04/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jeffrey</FirstName>
<LastName>Nickerson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>V</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jeffrey V Nickerson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jnickerson@stevens.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000108449</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/04/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lydia</FirstName>
<LastName>Chilton</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lydia B Chilton</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[chilton@cs.columbia.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000776634</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/04/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Keren</FirstName>
<LastName>Henderson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Keren Henderson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[khenders@syr.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000823463</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/04/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Syracuse University</Name>
<CityName>SYRACUSE</CityName>
<ZipCode>132440001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3154432807</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>900 S CROUSE AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>22</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY22</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>C4BXLBC11LC6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SYRACUSE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Syracuse University]]></Name>
<CityName>Syracuse</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>132444100</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Hinds Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>22</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY22</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>103Y</Code>
<Text>FW-HTF Futr Wrk Hum-Tech Frntr</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>063Z</Code>
<Text>FW-HTF Futr Wrk Hum-Tech Frntr</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~130854</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This planning grant supported multidisciplinary team-building, pilot field work and refinement of a research plan for convergent research on the future of work that involves humans and technology jointly synthesizing and documenting knowledge. The planned project would investigate the human-technology frontier specifically for the work of news journalists who synthesize knowledge and create documents in the form of articles to inform the public. By knowledge synthesis and documentation (or just documentation for short), we include the various processes for gathering information, organizing it, making sense of it, filtering or prioritizing it, adding context to it and presenting it intelligible ways in the form of documents, that is, artifacts that carry meaning to inform work in other contexts.</p> <p>The intellectual merit of the project was to create a solid research framework and plan, with the goal of developing a project that will make a significant contribution to our knowledge about human and technology collaborations. The planned project will be a collaboration between investigators who collectively span different disciplinary areas that can be brought to bear on this topic: computer science, information science, information systems and journalism.</p> <p>The broader impact of the project is the potential to benefit society by addressing problems faced by journalists. Journalists and news work are important to study because, even in the face of numerous challenges, news organizations remain a powerful force for keeping communities safe and healthy by providing information about events and trends to help people make better decisions about their lives. Journalism, as an information-based industry and profession, has always been impacted by new technologies, most recently by the rise of the Internet and loss of advertising revenue, as well as the long-standing tension between journalistic values and business interests. These pressures take a toll on journalistic processes and products. Some important stories are not getting told: they take too much time to discover, research, and craft into narratives, and time is increasingly in short supply. The project planned seeks to address this problem by identifying points where computer-support could improve the efficiency and effectiveness of journalistic work. As well, the project included a doctoral student who developed skills in literature review, interviewing, qualitative data analysis and paper writing, thus contributing to training and education.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/06/2022<br>      Modified by: Kevin&nbsp;Crowston</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This planning grant supported multidisciplinary team-building, pilot field work and refinement of a research plan for convergent research on the future of work that involves humans and technology jointly synthesizing and documenting knowledge. The planned project would investigate the human-technology frontier specifically for the work of news journalists who synthesize knowledge and create documents in the form of articles to inform the public. By knowledge synthesis and documentation (or just documentation for short), we include the various processes for gathering information, organizing it, making sense of it, filtering or prioritizing it, adding context to it and presenting it intelligible ways in the form of documents, that is, artifacts that carry meaning to inform work in other contexts.  The intellectual merit of the project was to create a solid research framework and plan, with the goal of developing a project that will make a significant contribution to our knowledge about human and technology collaborations. The planned project will be a collaboration between investigators who collectively span different disciplinary areas that can be brought to bear on this topic: computer science, information science, information systems and journalism.  The broader impact of the project is the potential to benefit society by addressing problems faced by journalists. Journalists and news work are important to study because, even in the face of numerous challenges, news organizations remain a powerful force for keeping communities safe and healthy by providing information about events and trends to help people make better decisions about their lives. Journalism, as an information-based industry and profession, has always been impacted by new technologies, most recently by the rise of the Internet and loss of advertising revenue, as well as the long-standing tension between journalistic values and business interests. These pressures take a toll on journalistic processes and products. Some important stories are not getting told: they take too much time to discover, research, and craft into narratives, and time is increasingly in short supply. The project planned seeks to address this problem by identifying points where computer-support could improve the efficiency and effectiveness of journalistic work. As well, the project included a doctoral student who developed skills in literature review, interviewing, qualitative data analysis and paper writing, thus contributing to training and education.       Last Modified: 01/06/2022       Submitted by: Kevin Crowston]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
