<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[I-Corps:  MAGNETIC NANO PARTICLE GYROSCOPE]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ruth Shuman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rshuman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922160</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this I-Corps project is the development of a new magnetic-based nanoparticle gyroscopic sensor. Inertia sensors accurately indicate change in orientation by detecting angular acceleration. Presently, gyroscopic sensors are available in many technology forms, but the most widely used are pressure-based micro-electromechanical sensors (MEMs). This project proposes a new sensor in a relatively simple, rugged design that is low cost and uses less power.  It is designed for use in challenging or dangerous environments, such as deep sea and high altitude. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project is based on the development of a new gyroscopic sensor with the ability to sense inertia due to the ability of the magnetic nanoparticles to resist being tilted from their original space positions. Magnetic nanoparticles in fluids, rotating magnetic field, and gyroscopic technologies and methods provide a method and system for a gyroscopic sensor. The next step is to understand performance requirements for parameters such as particular bias and scale factor stability, environmental sensitivity, repeatability, signal/noise ratio, minimum g-sensitivity (spinning frequency resulting from an acceleration force); and identify ways improve accuracy/performance, bandwidth, and size.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/08/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/08/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2026981</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Johnson</FirstName>
<LastName>Asumadu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Johnson A Asumadu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[johnson.asumadu@wmich.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000397941</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/08/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Western Michigan University</Name>
<CityName>KALAMAZOO</CityName>
<ZipCode>490085200</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2693878298</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1903 W MICHIGAN AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>J7WULLYGFRH1</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WESTERN MICHIGAN UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>MSBPLPK9YJW4</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Western Michigan University]]></Name>
<CityName>Kalamazoo</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>490085200</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1903 W. Michigan Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>NSF-ICorps Outcomes</strong></p> <p>Customer discovery Techniques:</p> <p>The key application of the technology would be in inertia measurment units (IMUs), which are the main units in autonomous and unmanned aerial systems such as unmanned autonomous vehicles (UAVs) and drones.</p> <ul> <li>Depending on the end customer use the key parameters; scale factor/size stability, G^2 sensitivity, bias stability, bandwidth, and bias repeatability would vary somewhat.</li> </ul> <p>The Key Value Propositions:</p> <ul> <li>Sensitivity and stability over standard temperature ranges were what the customer really cared about<a href="file:///F:/CAREER%202021/NSF%20I-CORPS%20REPORT/FINAL5%20-%20OUTCOMES/OUTCOMES/FINAL3/NSF_outcomes.docx#_msocom_1">[kh1]</a>&nbsp;<a href="file:///F:/CAREER%202021/NSF%20I-CORPS%20REPORT/FINAL5%20-%20OUTCOMES/OUTCOMES/FINAL3/NSF_outcomes.docx#_msocom_2">[WU2]</a>&nbsp;</li> <li>Expected: Ease of configurability of sensor outputs, alignment, and precision</li> <li>Simple packaging to help reduce the size of circuit boards that the sensors</li> <li>Shorter time to apply in applications compared to similar sensors such as MEMs</li> <li>It is robust and cannot be destroyed easily and will survive very harsh environment</li> <li>Nano gyroscope preforms steadily under magnetic interference (up to 65000nT)</li> <li>-0.5 G ? 16G Vibration tolerant</li> <li>Shorter time from research to manufacturing compared to similar sensors such as MEMs</li> </ul> <p>Customer Segemented Exploration:</p> <p>(oil drilling, agriculture, military/law enforcement, and other security applications)</p> <ul> <li>The demand for Agricultural drones are increasing. The total addressable market (TAM) is about $1.2 billions in 2020. The agricultural drone market is expected to grow at a CAGR of 31.1% from 2019 to 2025 to reach $5.19 billion by 2025.</li> <li>The military and defense total addressable market (TAM ) is $21.74 billion US in 2020. The serviced addressable market (SAM) for this technology is an $7.24 million US mid-grade and basic UAVs market. The Serviceable Obtainable Market (SOM) is $700 Million. The Military UAVs are broadly classified with different payloads and subcomponents and their manufacturers.</li> <li>Additional findings: there is a large market for positioning sensor in oil and gas drilling market (TAM $11.9 billion US for Measurement-While-Drilling (MWD)).</li> <li>  <ul> </ul> </li> </ul> <p>Customer ecosystem:</p> <ul> <li>&nbsp;Equipment manufacturers (OEMS) are important in the chain supply as distributors of the sensors and/or manufacturers of the drone parts and drones. </li> <li>The OEMs will obtain the necessary industry certification.</li> <li>Customer pricing of sensors are different depending on the market</li> <li>Federal Aviation Administration (FAA) regulatory board is the certifier who renders the protocols of a safe and confined design for the drones to fly considering the weight, operation and design</li> <li>Within the OEM, the CEO and the product innovation manager are the decision makers, the finance manager is the economic buyer, and the sales representatives are the influencers.</li> </ul> <ul> </ul> <p>The NSF I-Corps program allowed the NanoGyro team to develop a business canvas model that can take a lab-based prototype, find a viable market, and provided the buidling blocks to commerialize the technology.</p> <div> <hr size="1" /> <div> <div> <p>&nbsp;<a href="file:///F:/CAREER%202021/NSF%20I-CORPS%20REPORT/FINAL5%20-%20OUTCOMES/OUTCOMES/FINAL3/NSF_outcomes.docx#_msoanchor_1">[kh1]</a>Provide more specific information. How much better sensitivity, stability. How much wider of a temp range do you need to meet? Why is it important?</p> </div> </div> <div> <div> <p>&nbsp;<a href="file:///F:/CAREER%202021/NSF%20I-CORPS%20REPORT/FINAL5%20-%20OUTCOMES/OUTCOMES/FINAL3/NSF_outcomes.docx#_msoanchor_2">[WU2]</a></p> </div> </div> </div> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/11/2021<br>      Modified by: Johnson&nbsp;A&nbsp;Asumadu</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2026981/2026981_10683586_1631400084333_johnson_asumadu_image3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2026981/2026981_10683586_1631400084333_johnson_asumadu_image3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Important Insights"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2026981/2026981_10683586_1631400084333_johnson_asumadu_image3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Important Insights"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Drones should be robust, stable, and with minimum vibrations</div> <div class="imageCredit">NanoGyro Team</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Johnson&nbsp;A&nbsp;Asumadu</div> <div class="imageTitle">Important Insights</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2026981/2026981_10683586_1631399526247_johnson_asumadu_image1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2026981/2026981_10683586_1631399526247_johnson_asumadu_image1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Where NanoGyro Should Be?"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2026981/2026981_10683586_1631399526247_johnson_asumadu_image1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Where NanoGyro Should Be?"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">OEM Parts for IMU</div> <div class="imageCredit">NanoGyro Team</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Johnson&nbsp;A&nbsp;Asumadu</div> <div class="imageTitle">Where NanoGyro Should Be?</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2026981/2026981_10683586_1631399851498_johnson_asumadu_image2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2026981/2026981_10683586_1631399851498_johnson_asumadu_image2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Application Grades"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2026981/2026981_10683586_1631399851498_johnson_asumadu_image2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Application Grades"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Customer Segmentation</div> <div class="imageCredit">NanoGyro Team</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Johnson&nbsp;A&nbsp;Asumadu</div> <div class="imageTitle">Application Grades</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ NSF-ICorps Outcomes  Customer discovery Techniques:  The key application of the technology would be in inertia measurment units (IMUs), which are the main units in autonomous and unmanned aerial systems such as unmanned autonomous vehicles (UAVs) and drones.  Depending on the end customer use the key parameters; scale factor/size stability, G^2 sensitivity, bias stability, bandwidth, and bias repeatability would vary somewhat.   The Key Value Propositions:  Sensitivity and stability over standard temperature ranges were what the customer really cared about[kh1] [WU2]  Expected: Ease of configurability of sensor outputs, alignment, and precision Simple packaging to help reduce the size of circuit boards that the sensors Shorter time to apply in applications compared to similar sensors such as MEMs It is robust and cannot be destroyed easily and will survive very harsh environment Nano gyroscope preforms steadily under magnetic interference (up to 65000nT) -0.5 G ? 16G Vibration tolerant Shorter time from research to manufacturing compared to similar sensors such as MEMs   Customer Segemented Exploration:  (oil drilling, agriculture, military/law enforcement, and other security applications)  The demand for Agricultural drones are increasing. The total addressable market (TAM) is about $1.2 billions in 2020. The agricultural drone market is expected to grow at a CAGR of 31.1% from 2019 to 2025 to reach $5.19 billion by 2025. The military and defense total addressable market (TAM ) is $21.74 billion US in 2020. The serviced addressable market (SAM) for this technology is an $7.24 million US mid-grade and basic UAVs market. The Serviceable Obtainable Market (SOM) is $700 Million. The Military UAVs are broadly classified with different payloads and subcomponents and their manufacturers. Additional findings: there is a large market for positioning sensor in oil and gas drilling market (TAM $11.9 billion US for Measurement-While-Drilling (MWD)).        Customer ecosystem:   Equipment manufacturers (OEMS) are important in the chain supply as distributors of the sensors and/or manufacturers of the drone parts and drones.  The OEMs will obtain the necessary industry certification. Customer pricing of sensors are different depending on the market Federal Aviation Administration (FAA) regulatory board is the certifier who renders the protocols of a safe and confined design for the drones to fly considering the weight, operation and design Within the OEM, the CEO and the product innovation manager are the decision makers, the finance manager is the economic buyer, and the sales representatives are the influencers.     The NSF I-Corps program allowed the NanoGyro team to develop a business canvas model that can take a lab-based prototype, find a viable market, and provided the buidling blocks to commerialize the technology.       [kh1]Provide more specific information. How much better sensitivity, stability. How much wider of a temp range do you need to meet? Why is it important?       [WU2]             Last Modified: 09/11/2021       Submitted by: Johnson A Asumadu]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
