<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Revealing the intermolecular interactions between the SARS-CoV-2/COVID-19 fusion peptide and the host cell membrane that underlie its flexibility in host tropism]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>200000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>200000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>MCB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Matt Buechner</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mbuechne@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924675</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Coronavirus is a membrane-enveloped package decorated with “spikes” that protrude from its surface. These spikes interact with the host cell to initiate infection of that cell. The ability of coronavirus to spread to other cells depends on how well the spike interacts with its target host membrane. The part of the spike that controls this interaction is called the “fusion peptide” and its job is to insert into the host membrane to initiate the delivery its genetic cargo into the cell. However, the specifics of how the fusion peptide interacts with the membrane is still not known.   In this project, various interactions between the fusion peptide with membrane surfaces that mimic different kinds of host cells will be studied.  This information will provide insight into the characteristics of both the fusion peptide and the host cell that promotes their interaction, and ultimately, infection and viral transmission to new hosts.  With a better understanding of the science behind this critical interaction for virus adaptation to new hosts, we will be better informed about how this virus spreads and ultimately equipped to develop strategies to stop it. This fundamental information has the potential to enable fresh approaches to the design of antiviral drugs that target the fusion peptide. Given that the fusion peptide is highly conserved across the coronavirus family, these studies will be directly applicable to all coronaviruses, including the coronavirus that causes COVID-19.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A key determinant of the ability of coronavirus to spread is how it interacts with its target host membrane. For coronavirus, entry into a host cell is mediated by a single glycoprotein protruding from its membrane envelope, called spike (S). Within S, the region that directly interacts with the membrane is called the fusion peptide, FP. It is the physico-chemical interactions of the FP with the host membrane that anchors it, thus enabling the necessary deformations of the membrane that lead to delivery of the viral genome into the cell. Thus, understanding FP interactions at the most fundamental level will facilitate the development of strategies to limit those interactions to stop the spread of infections.  This information is expected to be helpful in predicting the characteristics of emerging strains that could post a threat to humans in the future. The objective of this project is to measure and identify the specific intermolecular interactions responsible for insertion of FP into membranes. Specifically, this project will: 1) elucidate the factors that control hydrophobic interactions of FP using single molecule force measurements with atomic force microscopy and models of biological membranes, and 2) characterize the structure-function relationship of the FP using circular dichroism and isothermal calorimetry to correlate specific interactions with amino acid sequence and host surface properties. The intellectual merit of this project is discovering how changes in host membrane chemistry or amino acid sequence of the FP modulates the hydrophobic interaction and ultimately influences activity critical to the spread of infection. The broader impact of this project is providing information that will enable fresh approaches to the design of antiviral drugs, as well as to identify basic design rules that inform how the FP promotes the interaction with membranes of specific chemistry to predict host susceptibility to infection. Given that the FP is highly conserved across the CoV family, these studies will be directly applicable to all CoVs, including those yet to emerge.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/31/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/31/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2027070</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Susan</FirstName>
<LastName>Daniel</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Susan Daniel</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[sd386@cornell.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000498757</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/31/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gary</FirstName>
<LastName>Whittaker</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gary R Whittaker</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[grw7@cornell.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000114267</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/31/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nicholas</FirstName>
<LastName>Abbott</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nicholas L Abbott</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[nabbott@cornell.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000097716</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/31/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Cornell University</Name>
<CityName>ITHACA</CityName>
<ZipCode>148502820</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6072555014</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>341 PINE TREE RD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>19</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY19</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>G56PUALJ3KT5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CORNELL UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Cornell University]]></Name>
<CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>148535201</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[113 Ho Plaza, 256 Olin Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>19</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY19</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1114</Code>
<Text>Cellular Dynamics and Function</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7465</Code>
<Text>NANOSCALE BIO CORE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~200000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Coronavirus (CoV) is a serious public health concern because it infects a wide range of animals and has no readily available countermeasures when it emerges in humans and causes serious disease. The outbreak of SARS-CoV-2/COVID-19 highlighted our lack of readiness at the national level to deal with such pandemics. A broader understanding of the aspects of the virus that can be leveraged to reduce or eliminate infection is needed. One key determinant of the ability of the virus to spread is how it interacts with its target host membrane. This interaction is mediated by the viral coat protein, called spike (S). S contains a specific domain, called the fusion peptide (FP), that facilitates fusion of the viral membrane with the host membrane to deliver the viral genome into the host cell. This domain must anchor itself into the host membrane for the fusion process to proceed successfully. This anchoring step is triggered by specific environmental cues that prompt the conformational changes in S that lead to the insertion of the FP into the host membrane. Thus, understanding how the FP interacts with cell membrane surfaces, and how that is changed, either by the host cell chemistry or the FP amino acid sequence, is valuable information that informs our understanding of the science behind virus transmission and adaptation to new hosts.<strong> </strong>Understanding FP interactions at the most fundamental level has the potential, in the long term, to enable the development of strategies to <em>stop</em> the spread of infection and also to <em>predict</em> the characteristics of emerging strains that could post a threat to humans in the future.</p> <p>This objective of this project was to characterize the structure-function relationship of the FP in the post-fusion state using biophysical approaches to correlate specific interactions with amino acid sequence, environmental conditions, and host surface properties. During this work, we successfully adapted our supported bilayer platform and single-molecule force measurement techniques to obtain critical measurements of the FP with surfaces of varying chemistry and complexity. The simple model surfaces used in our study provided facile control over composition and properties, and allowed us to decouple forces and understand the fundamental nature of the interactions encoded by the FP.&nbsp; The knowledge emerging from those studies was then used to interpret results obtained using more complex, but more relevant, cell membrane surfaces. We also examined changes in the interactions of wildtype FP subjected to different environmental conditions (ionic and pH). In the final part of the project, we selectively substituted amino acids at specific positions of the FP to gain further insight into how these key residues ultimately impact membrane interactions and the structure of the peptide.</p> <p><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Intellectual Merit.</span></strong> This project provided fundamental insight into the intermolecular interactions, specifically, the interplay of ionic and hydrophobic interactions that underlie the function of FP from coronaviruses. We elucidated how changes in amino acid sequence of the FP modulates the hydrophobic interaction, a key step in the anchoring of the FP in the host membrane. This project provided the first single-molecule biophysical characterization of hydrophobic interactions mediated by FPs in the context of virus entry. While these types of interactions are straightforward to characterize in model systems, this work is significant because elucidation of these interactions in the viral entry context is difficult because they occur after the fusion trigger and rearrangement of S to expose the FP. As such, this research provides much needed insight into this post-trigger state and ultimately informs our understanding of fusion activity critical to the spread of infection.</p> <p><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Broader Impact.</span></strong> The fundamental knowledge on FP-host membrane interactions emerging from this study enables fresh approaches to the design of antiviral drugs, such as those that target the fusion function, as well as learning basic design rules that inform how the FP promotes the interaction with membranes of specific chemistry to predict host susceptibility to infection. Given that the FP is highly conserved across the CoV family, these studies are directly applicable to all CoVs, including those yet to emerge, and thus serve to better prepare our national response to future pandemic situations.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/01/2022<br>      Modified by: Susan&nbsp;Daniel</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Coronavirus (CoV) is a serious public health concern because it infects a wide range of animals and has no readily available countermeasures when it emerges in humans and causes serious disease. The outbreak of SARS-CoV-2/COVID-19 highlighted our lack of readiness at the national level to deal with such pandemics. A broader understanding of the aspects of the virus that can be leveraged to reduce or eliminate infection is needed. One key determinant of the ability of the virus to spread is how it interacts with its target host membrane. This interaction is mediated by the viral coat protein, called spike (S). S contains a specific domain, called the fusion peptide (FP), that facilitates fusion of the viral membrane with the host membrane to deliver the viral genome into the host cell. This domain must anchor itself into the host membrane for the fusion process to proceed successfully. This anchoring step is triggered by specific environmental cues that prompt the conformational changes in S that lead to the insertion of the FP into the host membrane. Thus, understanding how the FP interacts with cell membrane surfaces, and how that is changed, either by the host cell chemistry or the FP amino acid sequence, is valuable information that informs our understanding of the science behind virus transmission and adaptation to new hosts. Understanding FP interactions at the most fundamental level has the potential, in the long term, to enable the development of strategies to stop the spread of infection and also to predict the characteristics of emerging strains that could post a threat to humans in the future.  This objective of this project was to characterize the structure-function relationship of the FP in the post-fusion state using biophysical approaches to correlate specific interactions with amino acid sequence, environmental conditions, and host surface properties. During this work, we successfully adapted our supported bilayer platform and single-molecule force measurement techniques to obtain critical measurements of the FP with surfaces of varying chemistry and complexity. The simple model surfaces used in our study provided facile control over composition and properties, and allowed us to decouple forces and understand the fundamental nature of the interactions encoded by the FP.  The knowledge emerging from those studies was then used to interpret results obtained using more complex, but more relevant, cell membrane surfaces. We also examined changes in the interactions of wildtype FP subjected to different environmental conditions (ionic and pH). In the final part of the project, we selectively substituted amino acids at specific positions of the FP to gain further insight into how these key residues ultimately impact membrane interactions and the structure of the peptide.  Intellectual Merit. This project provided fundamental insight into the intermolecular interactions, specifically, the interplay of ionic and hydrophobic interactions that underlie the function of FP from coronaviruses. We elucidated how changes in amino acid sequence of the FP modulates the hydrophobic interaction, a key step in the anchoring of the FP in the host membrane. This project provided the first single-molecule biophysical characterization of hydrophobic interactions mediated by FPs in the context of virus entry. While these types of interactions are straightforward to characterize in model systems, this work is significant because elucidation of these interactions in the viral entry context is difficult because they occur after the fusion trigger and rearrangement of S to expose the FP. As such, this research provides much needed insight into this post-trigger state and ultimately informs our understanding of fusion activity critical to the spread of infection.  Broader Impact. The fundamental knowledge on FP-host membrane interactions emerging from this study enables fresh approaches to the design of antiviral drugs, such as those that target the fusion function, as well as learning basic design rules that inform how the FP promotes the interaction with membranes of specific chemistry to predict host susceptibility to infection. Given that the FP is highly conserved across the CoV family, these studies are directly applicable to all CoVs, including those yet to emerge, and thus serve to better prepare our national response to future pandemic situations.          Last Modified: 08/01/2022       Submitted by: Susan Daniel]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
