<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: A Novel Detector for Mitigating the Covid-19 Pandemic based on Phase Interrogated Ultra-sensitive Microwave Resonance]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>200000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>200000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ECCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Aranya Chakrabortty</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>achakrab@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928113</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This project will conduct research to develop a rapid and powerful electronic probe that can detect biochemical attributes of COVID-19 from exhaled breath in real-time and on-demand. Our approach is an alternative and complementary solution to rRT-PCR for large-scale COVID-19 testing. The proposed sensor is a novel biohazard aerosol analyzer probe, which is based on phase interrogated ultra-sensitive microwave resonance. The probe can detect physicochemical attributes of human lung capacities and compositions of breath aerosols. We hypothesize that the compositions of the breath aerosols (water, virus, bacterial) will correlate to permittivity signatures of specific pulmonary diseases, which can be extracted using machine learning algorithms. The probe will separate sick from healthy individuals through a rapid and definitive test of an individual's breath. The proposal focuses on defining the theoretical and experimental sensitivity and selectivity of the probe and addresses the following: Is it possible to detect signatures from COVID-19 and other diseases from exhaled breath in real-time? Computer simulations will be employed to investigate the fundamental electromagnetic parameters of a prototype probe to determine the theoretical limit of detection. Probes will be fabricated and used to identify size distributions and chemical compositions of innocuous aerosols and those containing materials simulating viruses and respiratory tract secretions to detect COVID-19. Machine learning will be employed to analyze aerosol data and identify diseased individuals.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: This work will advance the state-of-the-art of non-invasive point-of-care probes in the health care arena. The integration of machine learning data analysis with real-time and on-demand medical diagnostics is a novel contribution which will permit real-time evaluation of large-scale probe data and the concomitant detection of vectors of disease propagation.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: This work will inspire engineers to quickly advance the proposed strategy for identifying COVID-19 and other pulmonary disease signatures from human breath in real-time so that testing of human breath will soon become standard medical practice worldwide. The work is multidisciplinary, involving optics, electronics, chemistry, physics, virology, and machine learning. Testing has been identified as a scarce and essential resource. This research will permanently and dramatically enhance the containment of pandemics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/03/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/06/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2027571</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Donald</FirstName>
<LastName>Wunsch</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Donald C Wunsch</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[dwunsch@mst.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000420285</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/03/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate>01/06/2021</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jie</FirstName>
<LastName>Huang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jie Huang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jieh@mst.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000703678</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/03/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yang</FirstName>
<LastName>Wang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Yang Wang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[yangwang@miami.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000823403</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/03/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Missouri University of Science and Technology</Name>
<CityName>ROLLA</CityName>
<ZipCode>654091330</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5733414134</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>300 W. 12TH STREET</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[202 CENTENNIAL HALL]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MO08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>Y6MGH342N169</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MISSOURI SYSTEM</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Missouri University of Science and Technology]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>654096506</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MO08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7607</Code>
<Text>EPCN-Energy-Power-Ctrl-Netwrks</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1653</Code>
<Text>Adaptive &amp; intelligent systems</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~200000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>We are pleased to share the outcomes of our National Science Foundation (NSF) funded project, "RAPID: A Novel Detector for Mitigating the Covid-19 Pandemic based on Phase Interrogated Ultra-sensitive Microwave Resonance." This project aimed to develop an innovative breath analyzer, known as the Open-Ended Hollow Coaxial Cable Resonator (OE-HCCR), to revolutionize pulmonary function testing. Our work addresses both the intellectual merit and broader impacts of scientific research, with implications for healthcare and diagnostics.</p> <p><span>Project Overview:</span> Our research centered on the development of a noninvasive, real-time breath analyzer capable of distinguishing between healthy and compromised lung functions. Traditional pulmonary function tests can be expensive and complex, limiting their accessibility. To overcome these challenges, we introduced the OE-HCCR breath analyzer, a breakthrough in exhaled breath condensate analysis.</p> <p><span>Key Findings and Outcomes:</span></p> <ol> <li> <p><span>Innovation in Diagnostics:</span> The OE-HCCR breath analyzer leverages electromagnetic analysis of exhaled breath components to detect subtle abnormalities. We successfully demonstrated its heightened sensitivity to nonvolatile particulate matter, such as virus particles, indicative of compromised lung function.</p> </li> <li> <p><span>Cost-Effective Healthcare Tool:</span> Our research yielded a cost-effective and reliable diagnostic tool that holds great promise for widespread adoption in diverse healthcare settings. The OE-HCCR analyzer is designed to enhance the accessibility of pulmonary assessments.</p> </li> <li> <p><span>Mathematical Model:</span> We developed a comprehensive mathematical model to support the functionality of the breath analyzer, which was corroborated by experimental results. This model serves as a foundation for the technology's precision and accuracy.</p> </li> <li> <p><span>Experimental Validation:</span> Our experiments involved five key studies, including the sensitivity of phase signals to various substances, material variations within the active cavity, and the influence of different breathing techniques. These experiments demonstrated the OE-HCCR analyzer's ability to distinguish between exhaled breath and ambient air, as well as its sensitivity to breath content.</p> </li> <li> <p><span>Breath Signal Analysis:</span> We identified distinct patterns in breath signal profiles, with elongated signal tails indicating higher concentrations of nonvolatile materials. This observation has significant implications for the diagnosis of respiratory conditions.</p> </li> </ol> <p><span>Broader Impacts:</span> The outcomes of our project extend beyond scientific merit. The development of the OE-HCCR breath analyzer has the potential to:</p> <ul> <li> <p><span>Improve Healthcare Accessibility:</span> By offering a cost-effective and noninvasive method for preliminary lung function assessment, this technology can make healthcare more accessible, particularly in resource-limited or remote areas.</p> </li> <li> <p><span>Early Disease Detection:</span> The OE-HCCR analyzer's ability to detect compromised lung function early could aid in the early diagnosis of respiratory diseases and conditions, facilitating timely interventions.</p> </li> <li> <p><span>Research Advancements:</span> Our project contributes to the advancement of respiratory research, providing a valuable tool for researchers to study breath content in greater detail.</p> </li> </ul> <p><span>Future Directions:</span> While our current focus has been on nonvolatile components in exhaled breath, we are actively exploring the analysis of volatile components. Future research endeavors include incorporating thin-film metal organic framework (MOF) structures within the active cavity to achieve specificity for specific volatile organic compounds. This could enable disease diagnosis and contagion determination.</p> <p><span>Conclusion:</span> The NSF-funded project, "RAPID: A Novel Detector for Mitigating the Covid-19 Pandemic based on Phase Interrogated Ultra-sensitive Microwave Resonance," has resulted in the development of a groundbreaking breath analyzer with far-reaching implications for healthcare and diagnostics. The OE-HCCR breath analyzer offers a cost-effective and accessible solution for preliminary lung function assessment, with the potential to improve healthcare outcomes and advance our understanding of respiratory health.</p> <p>We are grateful to the NSF for their support throughout this project, and we look forward to further developments and applications of our innovative technology in the field of healthcare and beyond.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/29/2023<br>      Modified by: Jie&nbsp;Huang</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2027571/2027571_10674606_1696015304967_Picture1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2027571/2027571_10674606_1696015304967_Picture1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Actual prototype and 3D model of the OE-HCCR Breath Analyzer Probe"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2027571/2027571_10674606_1696015304967_Picture1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Actual prototype and 3D model of the OE-HCCR Breath Analyzer Probe"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Actual prototype and 3D model of the OE-HCCR Breath Analyzer Probe. (a) Actual prototype of the 6mm inner conductor OE-HCCR Breath Analyzer Probe, complete with coaxial cable and vacuum tubing. (b) A 3D cutaway view of a model of the 6mm inner conductor Breath Analyzer Probe, highlighting the first</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jie Huang</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jie&nbsp;Huang</div> <div class="imageTitle">Actual prototype and 3D model of the OE-HCCR Breath Analyzer Probe</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ We are pleased to share the outcomes of our National Science Foundation (NSF) funded project, "RAPID: A Novel Detector for Mitigating the Covid-19 Pandemic based on Phase Interrogated Ultra-sensitive Microwave Resonance." This project aimed to develop an innovative breath analyzer, known as the Open-Ended Hollow Coaxial Cable Resonator (OE-HCCR), to revolutionize pulmonary function testing. Our work addresses both the intellectual merit and broader impacts of scientific research, with implications for healthcare and diagnostics.  Project Overview: Our research centered on the development of a noninvasive, real-time breath analyzer capable of distinguishing between healthy and compromised lung functions. Traditional pulmonary function tests can be expensive and complex, limiting their accessibility. To overcome these challenges, we introduced the OE-HCCR breath analyzer, a breakthrough in exhaled breath condensate analysis.  Key Findings and Outcomes:    Innovation in Diagnostics: The OE-HCCR breath analyzer leverages electromagnetic analysis of exhaled breath components to detect subtle abnormalities. We successfully demonstrated its heightened sensitivity to nonvolatile particulate matter, such as virus particles, indicative of compromised lung function.    Cost-Effective Healthcare Tool: Our research yielded a cost-effective and reliable diagnostic tool that holds great promise for widespread adoption in diverse healthcare settings. The OE-HCCR analyzer is designed to enhance the accessibility of pulmonary assessments.    Mathematical Model: We developed a comprehensive mathematical model to support the functionality of the breath analyzer, which was corroborated by experimental results. This model serves as a foundation for the technology's precision and accuracy.    Experimental Validation: Our experiments involved five key studies, including the sensitivity of phase signals to various substances, material variations within the active cavity, and the influence of different breathing techniques. These experiments demonstrated the OE-HCCR analyzer's ability to distinguish between exhaled breath and ambient air, as well as its sensitivity to breath content.    Breath Signal Analysis: We identified distinct patterns in breath signal profiles, with elongated signal tails indicating higher concentrations of nonvolatile materials. This observation has significant implications for the diagnosis of respiratory conditions.    Broader Impacts: The outcomes of our project extend beyond scientific merit. The development of the OE-HCCR breath analyzer has the potential to:    Improve Healthcare Accessibility: By offering a cost-effective and noninvasive method for preliminary lung function assessment, this technology can make healthcare more accessible, particularly in resource-limited or remote areas.    Early Disease Detection: The OE-HCCR analyzer's ability to detect compromised lung function early could aid in the early diagnosis of respiratory diseases and conditions, facilitating timely interventions.    Research Advancements: Our project contributes to the advancement of respiratory research, providing a valuable tool for researchers to study breath content in greater detail.    Future Directions: While our current focus has been on nonvolatile components in exhaled breath, we are actively exploring the analysis of volatile components. Future research endeavors include incorporating thin-film metal organic framework (MOF) structures within the active cavity to achieve specificity for specific volatile organic compounds. This could enable disease diagnosis and contagion determination.  Conclusion: The NSF-funded project, "RAPID: A Novel Detector for Mitigating the Covid-19 Pandemic based on Phase Interrogated Ultra-sensitive Microwave Resonance," has resulted in the development of a groundbreaking breath analyzer with far-reaching implications for healthcare and diagnostics. The OE-HCCR breath analyzer offers a cost-effective and accessible solution for preliminary lung function assessment, with the potential to improve healthcare outcomes and advance our understanding of respiratory health.  We are grateful to the NSF for their support throughout this project, and we look forward to further developments and applications of our innovative technology in the field of healthcare and beyond.          Last Modified: 09/29/2023       Submitted by: Jie Huang]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
