<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Infer and Control Global Spread of Corona-Virus with Graphical Models]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>100000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>100000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sylvia Spengler</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sspengle@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927347</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Graphs are ubiquitous in modeling statistical data-driven phenomena in physical, biological and societal systems. The spread of COVID-19, and other corona-viruses, between people, communities, cities, states and countries can be described in terms of a graph, which we refer to as the Corona Graph. Generally, the Corona Graphs we aim to utilize will be able to describe a specific region, level of spatio-temporal resolution, related geographical, transportation and social interaction details - for example, the city of Tucson, Arizona, during the summer of 2020, with a house-hold as an elementary unit, and accounting for businesses and their current state of isolation. This project goal is to build novel methodology which allows, given spatio-temporal specification and data, to (machine) learn the Corona Graph and underlying Corona Graphical Model, which will then be capable of interpolating, i.e. making societally important inference predictions about the virus spread. The essence of the RAPID proposal is in developing and transferring technology from the state-of-the-art in the foundational computer science, applied mathematics and statistics to the network modelling of COVID-19 spread. The technology developed under auspices of the project will allow to mix epidemiological inputs, such as these expressed in terms of the compartmental models of the epidemiology, with the state of the art approaches in AI and Data Science, such as Graphical Models and Deep Learning. The Corona Graphical Models will be flexible in dealing with heterogenous data sources, becoming available as the World recovers from the “hammer” stage of global self-isolation and transitions to the multi-month “dance” of balancing the conflicting objectives of keeping the reproduction rate of the virus under control while also minimizing the economic and societal costs. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The technical aims of the project are divided into three thrusts, focused on the formulation, inference and learning, respectively, of the Corona Graphical Models. The formulation thrust pivots construction of a class of Graphical Models analyzed in the two other follow up thrusts by integrating epidemiology, transportation and other relevant considerations, variables and constraints. The, second, inference thrust strives to combine existing methodologies with novel methods and algorithms to answer questions such as, what is the complexity of computing marginal probabilities of observing a geographical area, including many nodes of the Corona Graph, to have density of immune population to be 10%? Selection of the Corona Graph and epidemiology-meaningful factors, such as frequency of inter-node interactions and efficiency of a node quarantine, will be learned in the third trust from available data,  such as samples of the virus exposure collected at multiple nodes of the Corona Graph  throughout a period of interest. On the technical level the project approach to modeling, learning and inference with Graphical Models will open doors to combining under one umbrella location- and time-specific data and information from epidemiology, transportation and social sciences. The project will also result in the dissemination of Graphical Model ideas, algorithms, data and benchmarks to the broader foundational AI community and also to multiple other research communities interested in adapting the novel application-informed Graphical Model methodology.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/20/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/20/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2027072</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Chertkov</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael Chertkov</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[chertkov@math.arizona.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000189014</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/20/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Arizona</Name>
<CityName>TUCSON</CityName>
<ZipCode>85721</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5206266000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>845 N PARK AVE RM 538</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AZ03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>ED44Y3W6P7B9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ARIZONA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Arizona]]></Name>
<CityName>Tucson</CityName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>857210089</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[617 N. Santa Rita Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AZ07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>158Y</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7364</Code>
<Text>INFO INTEGRATION &amp; INFORMATICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>1N20</Code>
<Name>R&amp;RA CARES Act DEFC N</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>010N2021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[R&RA CARES Act DEFC N]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~100000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p style="text-align: left;">Both COVID-19 and novel pandemics challenge those of us within the modeling community, specifically in establishing suitable relations between lifecycles, scales, and existing methods.&nbsp;</p> <p style="text-align: left;">&nbsp;</p> <p style="text-align: left;">In this project we aimed to leverage in this project publicly available data to compose a chain of Graphical Models (GMs) for predicting infection rates across communities, space, and time. We attempted to anchor our GMs against the more expensive yet state-of-the-art Agent-Based Models (ABMs). Insight obtained from designing novel GMs calibrated to ABMs furnishes reduced, yet reliable surrogates for the end-to-end public health challenge of community contact tracing and transmission.</p> <p style="text-align: left;">&nbsp;</p> <p style="text-align: left;">In our first sub-project, we have focused &nbsp;on developing GM methodology. Specifically, we introduced static GM of the Ising model type which emerges from a dynamic GM of the Independent Cascade type, introduced and studied in Computer and Networks sciences mainly in the context of the spread of social influences. We posed the challenge of computing Conditional A-posteriori Level of Infection (CALI), which provides a quantitative answer to the questions: What is the probability that a given node in the GM (given census tract within the city) becomes infected in the result of injection of the infection at another node? We developed approximate inference techniques, of the variational and variable elimination types. &nbsp;We built a 123-node model of Seattle, as well as its 10-node and 20-node coarsegrained variants, and then conduct the proof of principles experimental studies. The experiments on the coarse-grained models have helped us to validate the approximate inference by juxtaposing it to the exact inference. We concluded&nbsp; this first study with an extensive discussion of how the methodology should be developed further, both at the level of devising realistic GMs from observational data &nbsp;and also regarding utilization of the GM inference methodology for more complex problems of the pandemic mitigation and control.</p> <p style="text-align: left;">In our second sub-project, we have focused on applying the Graphical Model methodology to predicting and preventing pandemics. We have provided algorithmic answers to the following two inter-related public health challenges. (1) Inference Challenge: assuming that there are N census blocks (nodes) in the city, and given an initial infection at any set of nodes, what is the probability for a subset of census blocks to become infected by the time the spread of the infection burst is stabilized? (2) Prevention Challenge: What is the minimal control action one can take to minimize the infected part of the stabilized state footprint? To answer the challenges, we built a Graphical Model of pandemic of the attractive Ising type, where each node represents a census track and each edge factor represents the strength of the pairwise interaction between a pair of nodes. We showed that almost all attractive Ising Models on dense graphs result in either of the two modes for the most probable state: either all nodes which were not infected initially became infected, or all the initially uninfected nodes remain uninfected. This bi-modal solution of the Inference Challenge allowed us to re-state the Prevention Challenge as the following tractable convex programming: for the bare Ising Model with pair-wise and bias factors representing the system without prevention measures, such that the most probable state is fully infected for at least one of the initial infection patterns, find the closest set of factors resulting in all the most probable states of the Ising model, with the optimal prevention measures applied, to become safe.</p> <p style="text-align: left;">In our third sub-project, we have focused on designing an agent based model of pandemic of new generation which we call "Agent-in-the cell" model.&nbsp;We argue that to understand, model and prevent the spread of pandemic, it is useful to partition (tessellate) the entire spatial domain of interest, for&nbsp;example one associated with the city of Seattle, into small enough geographic regions (or cells), in particular because the tessellations&nbsp;may be tuned to reflect the population?s mobility patterns. One&nbsp;natural tessellation is the Voronoi Tessellation (VT) where each cell has a center at the geographical location of the Census Block&nbsp;Groups (CBGs) and all spots within the cell are reachable faster&nbsp;by automobile, subway, or foot from the cell center than from the enter of any other VT cell. We may also associate another VT with&nbsp;the Points of Interest (POI) of a certain type, for example super-markets, schools, etc. Which of the VTs, or a combination of them, should be used when developing an ABM&nbsp;that accurately represents realistic movement patterns in an urban&nbsp;environment? We address this question by building a new methodology, coined&nbsp;Agent-In-Cell (AIC), that allowed morphing VTs associated with&nbsp;different POIs into the original VT associated with CBs. We provided theoretical arguments and verify these in simulations to show that the VTs are advantageous for epidemiological&nbsp;monitoring and decisions.</p> <p style="text-align: left;">&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/26/2022<br>      Modified by: Michael&nbsp;Chertkov</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[Both COVID-19 and novel pandemics challenge those of us within the modeling community, specifically in establishing suitable relations between lifecycles, scales, and existing methods.    In this project we aimed to leverage in this project publicly available data to compose a chain of Graphical Models (GMs) for predicting infection rates across communities, space, and time. We attempted to anchor our GMs against the more expensive yet state-of-the-art Agent-Based Models (ABMs). Insight obtained from designing novel GMs calibrated to ABMs furnishes reduced, yet reliable surrogates for the end-to-end public health challenge of community contact tracing and transmission.   In our first sub-project, we have focused  on developing GM methodology. Specifically, we introduced static GM of the Ising model type which emerges from a dynamic GM of the Independent Cascade type, introduced and studied in Computer and Networks sciences mainly in the context of the spread of social influences. We posed the challenge of computing Conditional A-posteriori Level of Infection (CALI), which provides a quantitative answer to the questions: What is the probability that a given node in the GM (given census tract within the city) becomes infected in the result of injection of the infection at another node? We developed approximate inference techniques, of the variational and variable elimination types.  We built a 123-node model of Seattle, as well as its 10-node and 20-node coarsegrained variants, and then conduct the proof of principles experimental studies. The experiments on the coarse-grained models have helped us to validate the approximate inference by juxtaposing it to the exact inference. We concluded  this first study with an extensive discussion of how the methodology should be developed further, both at the level of devising realistic GMs from observational data  and also regarding utilization of the GM inference methodology for more complex problems of the pandemic mitigation and control. In our second sub-project, we have focused on applying the Graphical Model methodology to predicting and preventing pandemics. We have provided algorithmic answers to the following two inter-related public health challenges. (1) Inference Challenge: assuming that there are N census blocks (nodes) in the city, and given an initial infection at any set of nodes, what is the probability for a subset of census blocks to become infected by the time the spread of the infection burst is stabilized? (2) Prevention Challenge: What is the minimal control action one can take to minimize the infected part of the stabilized state footprint? To answer the challenges, we built a Graphical Model of pandemic of the attractive Ising type, where each node represents a census track and each edge factor represents the strength of the pairwise interaction between a pair of nodes. We showed that almost all attractive Ising Models on dense graphs result in either of the two modes for the most probable state: either all nodes which were not infected initially became infected, or all the initially uninfected nodes remain uninfected. This bi-modal solution of the Inference Challenge allowed us to re-state the Prevention Challenge as the following tractable convex programming: for the bare Ising Model with pair-wise and bias factors representing the system without prevention measures, such that the most probable state is fully infected for at least one of the initial infection patterns, find the closest set of factors resulting in all the most probable states of the Ising model, with the optimal prevention measures applied, to become safe. In our third sub-project, we have focused on designing an agent based model of pandemic of new generation which we call "Agent-in-the cell" model. We argue that to understand, model and prevent the spread of pandemic, it is useful to partition (tessellate) the entire spatial domain of interest, for example one associated with the city of Seattle, into small enough geographic regions (or cells), in particular because the tessellations may be tuned to reflect the population?s mobility patterns. One natural tessellation is the Voronoi Tessellation (VT) where each cell has a center at the geographical location of the Census Block Groups (CBGs) and all spots within the cell are reachable faster by automobile, subway, or foot from the cell center than from the enter of any other VT cell. We may also associate another VT with the Points of Interest (POI) of a certain type, for example super-markets, schools, etc. Which of the VTs, or a combination of them, should be used when developing an ABM that accurately represents realistic movement patterns in an urban environment? We address this question by building a new methodology, coined Agent-In-Cell (AIC), that allowed morphing VTs associated with different POIs into the original VT associated with CBs. We provided theoretical arguments and verify these in simulations to show that the VTs are advantageous for epidemiological monitoring and decisions.         Last Modified: 07/26/2022       Submitted by: Michael Chertkov]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
