<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Changes in risk perceptions and COVID-19]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>200000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>200000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Robert O'Connor</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>roconnor@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927263</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[More needs to be learned about how people throughout the world respond to government actions during an infectious disease outbreak. At the beginning of 2020, a novel coronavirus (COVID-19) quickly spread across countries. Governments worldwide encouraged people to stay inside and be more hygienic. After a vaccine is available, governments will encourage people to get this vaccine. However, during 21st century outbreaks of Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome (SARS), H1N1 influenza, and Middle East Respiratory Syndrome (MERS), people did not always follow government recommendations. People grow more apathetic towards government recommendations over time.  This project looks at how behaviors and acceptance of a COVID-19 vaccine change over time and how they are related to risk perceptions and the number of cases and deaths in a region. The research takes place in the United States and four other nations. This international focus identifies what characteristics are associated with sustained adherence to public health recommendations and why they vary globally. Public health officials can use this information in the future to promote vaccines and healthy behaviors. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The rapid spread of the novel coronavirus (COVID-19) throughout the world at the beginning of 2020 is a testament to the need for sustained global responses to emerging infectious diseases. In response to COVID-19, governments worldwide have instituted a variety of countermeasures and encouraged citizens to practice certain hygienic behaviors. This research assesses changes in behaviors and attitudes related to the novel coronavirus (COVID-19). With the understanding that behaviors and vaccine decision making throughout the world can contribute to global spread of infectious diseases, this study collects several waves of Internet-based surveys from individuals in the United States and four other countries. The survey asks participants about their adherence towards countermeasures, risk perceptions, and acceptance of a hypothetical vaccine for COVID-19. The survey is conducted at multiple time points (eight times in the United States and four times in other locations) through on-line surveys. Changes in the adherence to countermeasures are linked to changes in the epidemiology of disease in each country and globally. The aims of this study are (1) to characterize the relationship between the epidemiology of disease and changes over time in risk perceptions, knowledge, and attitudes towards hygienic behaviors, (2) to examine if risk perceptions affect acceptance of vaccines, and (3) to contrast adherence to public health recommendations across countries which have had different governmental responses to the outbreak. This information can be used to better understand how to sustain compliance with public health recommendations and how to promote a COVID-19 vaccine.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/07/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/07/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2027836</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Abram</FirstName>
<LastName>Wagner</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Abram L Wagner</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[awag@umich.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000814874</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/07/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Shu-Fang</FirstName>
<LastName>Shih</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Shu-Fang Shih</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[sfshih@umich.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000823867</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/07/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Regents of the University of Michigan - Ann Arbor</Name>
<CityName>ANN ARBOR</CityName>
<ZipCode>481091079</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1109 GEDDES AVE, SUITE 3300</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>GNJ7BBP73WE9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MICHIGAN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Michigan Ann Arbor]]></Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>481092029</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1415 Washington Heights]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1321</Code>
<Text>Decision, Risk &amp; Mgmt Sci</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~200000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Fewer adult vaccines are available globally compared to childhood vaccines. Less is known about how adults make decisions to get vaccinated, especially considering seasonal influenza vaccination uptake has historically hovered around 50% in the US, and the vaccine may be largely unavailable to adults in other countries. With the SARS-CoV-2 pandemic, and the arrival of COVID-19 vaccines, there was an opportunity to understand how individuals make decisions about a new adult vaccine.</p> <p>The purpose of this grant was to assess changes in behaviors and attitudes related to COVID-19. Between June 2020 and June 2021, 28 cross-sectional surveys were conducted in 6 countries/areas: 8 in the US and 4 each in mainland China, Taiwan, Malaysia, Indonesia, and India. In total, 22,870 adults responded across these surveys.</p> <p>As part of this project, we developed and validated an adult Vaccine Hesitancy Scale. Previously, most questionnaires about vaccine hesitancy were limited to asking parents about childhood vaccines. We modified questions to be about adult vaccines, and we tested this survey in the US and in China to examine its validity. Beyond the English and Simplified Chinese version of this questionnaire, we also translated it into Bahasa Malaysia and Bahasa Indonesia, and provided a localization with Traditional Chinese for Taiwan.</p> <p>The major outcomes of this study are intention towards vaccination and vaccination behavior. In 2020, we asked study participants questions about a hypothetical COVID-19 vaccine. Regarding a hypothetical vaccine, we designed questions for four profiles of hypothetical vaccines based on different effectiveness (95% &amp; 50%) and safety (5% and 20% of getting fever) levels. When administering the survey, we randomized people into receiving different sets of effectiveness and safety information for the vaccine. Our study showed that across our survey locations and time periods, people had stronger preferences for a more effective vaccine, with less preference tied to changes in safety of the vaccine profile.</p> <p>Starting in 2021, we asked about actual vaccine uptake among study participants, and we were able to explore the relationship between mask wearing recommendations and people&rsquo;s vaccine behaviors. In spring 2021, the US CDC also issued guidance that individuals who were vaccinated did not need to wear a mask. We compared mask wearing between those vaccinated and unvaccinated before and after this change in guidance, and found that mask wearing dropped more in those unvaccinated than those vaccinated. The policy implications of our study are that messaging from CDC should be carefully designed as it could have unintended consequences that might counter official efforts to prevent transmission of diseases.</p> <p>Our work has also compared vaccine decision-making among parents for their children vs themselves. In general, parents in the US and Taiwan had reduced preferences for pediatric vaccines compared to those in mainland China, India, Indonesia, and Malaysia. In the US and Malaysia, individuals identified as being vaccine hesitant also were more likely to be accepting of a vaccine for a child than for themselves. Essentially, our findings reveal complexity in vaccine decision-making for oneself vs a child.</p> <p>We have shared the questions and data collected from this grant publicly. Over the grant period, we worked with consultants in four countries, and presented our results during media appearances and at conferences and disseminate the findings through academic publications and outlook articles through a professional association.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/01/2022<br>      Modified by: Abram&nbsp;L&nbsp;Wagner</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[    Fewer adult vaccines are available globally compared to childhood vaccines. Less is known about how adults make decisions to get vaccinated, especially considering seasonal influenza vaccination uptake has historically hovered around 50% in the US, and the vaccine may be largely unavailable to adults in other countries. With the SARS-CoV-2 pandemic, and the arrival of COVID-19 vaccines, there was an opportunity to understand how individuals make decisions about a new adult vaccine.  The purpose of this grant was to assess changes in behaviors and attitudes related to COVID-19. Between June 2020 and June 2021, 28 cross-sectional surveys were conducted in 6 countries/areas: 8 in the US and 4 each in mainland China, Taiwan, Malaysia, Indonesia, and India. In total, 22,870 adults responded across these surveys.  As part of this project, we developed and validated an adult Vaccine Hesitancy Scale. Previously, most questionnaires about vaccine hesitancy were limited to asking parents about childhood vaccines. We modified questions to be about adult vaccines, and we tested this survey in the US and in China to examine its validity. Beyond the English and Simplified Chinese version of this questionnaire, we also translated it into Bahasa Malaysia and Bahasa Indonesia, and provided a localization with Traditional Chinese for Taiwan.  The major outcomes of this study are intention towards vaccination and vaccination behavior. In 2020, we asked study participants questions about a hypothetical COVID-19 vaccine. Regarding a hypothetical vaccine, we designed questions for four profiles of hypothetical vaccines based on different effectiveness (95% &amp; 50%) and safety (5% and 20% of getting fever) levels. When administering the survey, we randomized people into receiving different sets of effectiveness and safety information for the vaccine. Our study showed that across our survey locations and time periods, people had stronger preferences for a more effective vaccine, with less preference tied to changes in safety of the vaccine profile.  Starting in 2021, we asked about actual vaccine uptake among study participants, and we were able to explore the relationship between mask wearing recommendations and people’s vaccine behaviors. In spring 2021, the US CDC also issued guidance that individuals who were vaccinated did not need to wear a mask. We compared mask wearing between those vaccinated and unvaccinated before and after this change in guidance, and found that mask wearing dropped more in those unvaccinated than those vaccinated. The policy implications of our study are that messaging from CDC should be carefully designed as it could have unintended consequences that might counter official efforts to prevent transmission of diseases.  Our work has also compared vaccine decision-making among parents for their children vs themselves. In general, parents in the US and Taiwan had reduced preferences for pediatric vaccines compared to those in mainland China, India, Indonesia, and Malaysia. In the US and Malaysia, individuals identified as being vaccine hesitant also were more likely to be accepting of a vaccine for a child than for themselves. Essentially, our findings reveal complexity in vaccine decision-making for oneself vs a child.  We have shared the questions and data collected from this grant publicly. Over the grant period, we worked with consultants in four countries, and presented our results during media appearances and at conferences and disseminate the findings through academic publications and outlook articles through a professional association.          Last Modified: 07/01/2022       Submitted by: Abram L Wagner]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
