<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Tuskegee University COVID Aware Program]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>199479.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>199479</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sara Kiesler</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>skiesler@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928643</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Because of the ever-evolving nature of COVID-19 information and need for a nationwide response to prevention and containment methods recommended by public health experts, there is an urgent need for all communities including underrepresented minorities to trust and implement these prevention and containment methods. This project is focused on understanding how minority communities’ access and attend to these disease prevention messages during the COVID-19 pandemic outbreak, with potential for understanding their responses to future pandemics and disasters as well. This project will design and test culturally-sensitive tools and materials that promote disease prevention. Based on the successful outcome of this research project, the disease prevention strategies developed can be institutionalized by federal, state, and local agencies. The data may bear on the trustworthiness of communications to minority communities in the deep south. The findings have the capacity to positively affect the diversity of materials, and reduce the levels of mistrust that do exist within minority communities across the deep south. Results from this project will be disseminated in journals and at conferences. Materials produced by the project will be made available to practitioners and other researchers. Students will be trained as part of this project.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This proposal is for research to mitigate the negative impacts of COVID-19 on public health, society, and the economy. The objective of this proposal is to determine the best ways of disseminating disease prevention messages to rural African Americans and other vulnerable populations. The central hypotheses are that minorities have doubts regarding the trustworthiness of these messages and that mistrust can delay the effectiveness of, and innovations in, disease prevention methods. Magnifying and/or delaying disease prevention interventions can lead to increased morbidity and mortality in the this population. The research is non-clinical in nature and involves a multi-state (Georgia, Florida, Alabama, Mississippi, and Louisiana) data collection effort using a newly constructed instrument to assess residents’ level of trust and fear related to disease transmission and where and how they prefer to receive information regarding prevention and treatment strategies. The project will provide health and other organizations with unique information and data on how minority communities access and attend to disease prevention messages and pandemic outbreaks.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/01/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/01/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2027923</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Crystal</FirstName>
<LastName>James</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Crystal M James</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[cjames@tuskegee.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000824261</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/01/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Tuskegee University</Name>
<CityName>TUSKEGEE INSTITUTE</CityName>
<ZipCode>360881923</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3347278970</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1200 W MONTGOMERY RD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Alabama</StateName>
<StateCode>AL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AL03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>U9JCYEXFEEU4</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TUSKEGEE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Tuskegee University]]></Name>
<CityName>Tuskegee Institute</CityName>
<StateCode>AL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>360881609</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1200 W. Montgomery Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Alabama</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AL03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>070Y</Code>
<Text>HBCU-EiR - HBCU-Excellence in</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>025Z</Code>
<Text>SaTC: Secure and Trustworthy Cyberspace</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1594</Code>
<Text>HIST BLACK COLLEGES AND UNIV</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7434</Code>
<Text>CNCI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9102</Code>
<Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>1N20</Code>
<Name>R&amp;RA CARES Act DEFC N</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>010N2021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[R&RA CARES Act DEFC N]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~199479</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project had five overall objectives:</p> <ul> <li>Understanding the effects of disease prevention messages during epidemic and pandemic outbreaks in the African American community</li> <li>Develop a better understanding of how minority communities? access and attend to health messages during a pandemic.</li> <li>Gather data on trust and trustworthiness in minority communities regionally.</li> <li>Implement culturally sensitive tools and materials that promote disease prevention.</li> <li>Develop disease prevention strategies developed that may be institutionalized by federal, state, and local agencies</li> </ul> <p>The major activities of the project included development, validation and dissemination of a novel survey instrument as well as 10 focus group sessions to ascertain more information regarding attitudes and behaviors of participants.</p> <ul> <li>Deployed a 57-question national survey focused on 5 southern states wherein the snowball methodology for participation was implemented.</li> <li>There were 679 recorded responses to the survey   <ul> <li>87% Black/African American</li> <li>87% Female</li> <li>Age range   <ul> <li>26% 35-44</li> <li>28% 45-54</li> <li>18% 25-34</li> </ul> </li> </ul> </li> <li>Income   <ul> <li>24.8% Above 107K annual salary</li> <li>21% $43K-64K</li> </ul> </li> </ul> <p class="Default">The six questions asked of each focus group participants were as follows:&nbsp;</p> <ul> <li>Where do you get information about health?&nbsp;</li> <li>Do you think information that you receive is a trusted source?&nbsp;</li> <li>Who do you most likely follow, social media, a person, or an organization?&nbsp;</li> <li>Which age group do you think receives more false information?&nbsp;</li> <li>What are some doubts and fears that you have regarding COVID?&nbsp;</li> <li>What are strategies that you feel are working and what do you think should be changed?&nbsp;</li> </ul> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Information gathered from the study show that African American women utilize several informational outlets for health messages and verify said information through formal and informal networks.&nbsp;&nbsp;Two community-based organizations were consulted to assist in getting participants to complete the survey and to also participate in focus group sessions to better understand attitudes and behaviors related to COVID-19 messaging and vaccines when made available.&nbsp;&nbsp;Salient themes from the focus groups emphasized the following:</p> <ul> <li>The largest articulated person/organization/person to follow was the local scientist and&nbsp;&nbsp;medical professionals, community organizations and medical professionals who spoke with candor and who appear to lack prejudice. The most untrusted information to follow was social media.</li> </ul> <p>&nbsp;</p> <ul> <li>The age group which appeared to be the most vulnerable for receiving misinformation are: First ? senior citizens, Second- parents of elementary children, and third, ages 16 -25 years because they utilize social media more often.&nbsp;</li> </ul> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The preliminary findings were disseminated in several community sessions to increase awareness about the survey and increase response thereto.&nbsp;&nbsp;The data has been analyzed and presented in regional conferences in the State of Florida and at the time of the report have been submitted for presentation at the American Public Health Association annual meeting.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Outcomes: A COVID19 community task force was initiated in 2020 anchored by the President of Tuskegee University, Former Mayor of Tuskegee, Director of the Macon County Healthcare Authority, and President of the Macon County Ministerial Alliance serving as facilitators of the weekly meeting.&nbsp;&nbsp;This meeting brings together weekly community leaders, elected officials, university faculty and leadership as well as frequently hosts partners from other states.&nbsp;&nbsp;A website has been developed to capture the weekly updates on COVID-19 and other community related matters (https://maconcares.org/).&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/27/2022<br>      Modified by: Crystal&nbsp;M&nbsp;James</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project had five overall objectives:  Understanding the effects of disease prevention messages during epidemic and pandemic outbreaks in the African American community Develop a better understanding of how minority communities? access and attend to health messages during a pandemic. Gather data on trust and trustworthiness in minority communities regionally. Implement culturally sensitive tools and materials that promote disease prevention. Develop disease prevention strategies developed that may be institutionalized by federal, state, and local agencies   The major activities of the project included development, validation and dissemination of a novel survey instrument as well as 10 focus group sessions to ascertain more information regarding attitudes and behaviors of participants.  Deployed a 57-question national survey focused on 5 southern states wherein the snowball methodology for participation was implemented. There were 679 recorded responses to the survey    87% Black/African American 87% Female Age range    26% 35-44 28% 45-54 18% 25-34     Income    24.8% Above 107K annual salary 21% $43K-64K    The six questions asked of each focus group participants were as follows:   Where do you get information about health?  Do you think information that you receive is a trusted source?  Who do you most likely follow, social media, a person, or an organization?  Which age group do you think receives more false information?  What are some doubts and fears that you have regarding COVID?  What are strategies that you feel are working and what do you think should be changed?          Information gathered from the study show that African American women utilize several informational outlets for health messages and verify said information through formal and informal networks.  Two community-based organizations were consulted to assist in getting participants to complete the survey and to also participate in focus group sessions to better understand attitudes and behaviors related to COVID-19 messaging and vaccines when made available.  Salient themes from the focus groups emphasized the following:  The largest articulated person/organization/person to follow was the local scientist and  medical professionals, community organizations and medical professionals who spoke with candor and who appear to lack prejudice. The most untrusted information to follow was social media.      The age group which appeared to be the most vulnerable for receiving misinformation are: First ? senior citizens, Second- parents of elementary children, and third, ages 16 -25 years because they utilize social media more often.       The preliminary findings were disseminated in several community sessions to increase awareness about the survey and increase response thereto.  The data has been analyzed and presented in regional conferences in the State of Florida and at the time of the report have been submitted for presentation at the American Public Health Association annual meeting.     Outcomes: A COVID19 community task force was initiated in 2020 anchored by the President of Tuskegee University, Former Mayor of Tuskegee, Director of the Macon County Healthcare Authority, and President of the Macon County Ministerial Alliance serving as facilitators of the weekly meeting.  This meeting brings together weekly community leaders, elected officials, university faculty and leadership as well as frequently hosts partners from other states.  A website has been developed to capture the weekly updates on COVID-19 and other community related matters (https://maconcares.org/).            Last Modified: 10/27/2022       Submitted by: Crystal M James]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
