<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Large Scale Production of Antiviral Interferons for the Treatment of COVID-19]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>256000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>256000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Erik Pierstorff</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>epiersto@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922165</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project will be to advance the development of production for COVID-19 treatments.  The COVID-19 pandemic is placing great strain on the supply chain for protein and antibody therapeutics and research products.  Interferons represent a specific class of protein released in response to viral infections; they are currently being tested as important therapies to combat COVID-19 infections and to regulate the immune system.   This project will develop a new system to produce and purify interferons using a new platform based on a plant system.  No plant system has been utilized commercially to produce human interferons, due to product loss during purification from plant tissue.  This system overcomes this challenge by secreting the proteins to leaf surfaces where they will easily be recovered.  The rapid scalability of this plant-based system can allow fast production of COVID-19 therapeutics at high levels and lower cost than current protein expression systems.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed Phase I project will develop a photosynthetic platform for the production of COVID-19 therapeutics, as current production strategies are expensive to scale and limited in production capacity.  Plants will be generated that produce and secrete interferons for the purposes of large-scale production.  Further research efforts will be performed to determine if newly-identified trichome-specific promoters, intron-mediated expression elements, and unique protein secretion signals that are cleaved during protein maturation can optimize and enhance the system for interferon production.  Plant-made interferons will be tested for activity and compared against interferons generated in other biomanufacturing systems.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/21/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/21/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2027985</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ryan</FirstName>
<LastName>Shepherd</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ryan W Shepherd</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ryan.shepherd@phyllotech.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000307287</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/21/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>PhylloTech Inc.</Name>
<CityName>BELOIT</CityName>
<ZipCode>535119769</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6083320389</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2636 E STATE LINE RD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WI01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>QC6KNEVDQ7V7</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PHYLLOTECH INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[PhylloTech Inc.]]></Name>
<CityName>Beloit</CityName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>535119769</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2636 E State Line Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WI01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8038</Code>
<Text>Biotechnology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>1N20</Code>
<Name>R&amp;RA CARES Act DEFC N</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>010N2021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[R&RA CARES Act DEFC N]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~256000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Therapeutic proteins can be used as medicines for COVID-19 and in scientific research, but such proteins are often difficult to produce and expensive to purify when using bacterial or mammalian cell based manufacturing systems.&nbsp; Furthermore, the COVID-19 pandemic has placed an unprecedented strain on the nation&rsquo;s supply chain for protein and antibody therapeutics and research products.&nbsp; Interferons are a specific class of protein released in response to viral infections and are being tested as therapies to combat COVID-19 infections but have restrictively high costs of production.&nbsp; Plants are ideal production systems for interferons because they only require soil, light, and water to generate products at low cost and can address an urgent and impending need for the manufacture of interferons as critical COVID-19 research products and treatments.&nbsp; In this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project, PhylloTech has developed a technology to enable the production of antiviral interferons in plants without the need for expensive purification steps.&nbsp; This system, termed OnleafEX, utilizes leaf surface structures called glandular secreting trichomes to produce and secrete bioactive interferons to leaf surfaces where they can be easily recovered. &nbsp;&nbsp;The scalability of this photosynthetic system allows the production of COVID-19 therapeutics at high levels and much lower cost than current protein expression systems.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/30/2021<br>      Modified by: Ryan&nbsp;W&nbsp;Shepherd</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Therapeutic proteins can be used as medicines for COVID-19 and in scientific research, but such proteins are often difficult to produce and expensive to purify when using bacterial or mammalian cell based manufacturing systems.  Furthermore, the COVID-19 pandemic has placed an unprecedented strain on the nation’s supply chain for protein and antibody therapeutics and research products.  Interferons are a specific class of protein released in response to viral infections and are being tested as therapies to combat COVID-19 infections but have restrictively high costs of production.  Plants are ideal production systems for interferons because they only require soil, light, and water to generate products at low cost and can address an urgent and impending need for the manufacture of interferons as critical COVID-19 research products and treatments.  In this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project, PhylloTech has developed a technology to enable the production of antiviral interferons in plants without the need for expensive purification steps.  This system, termed OnleafEX, utilizes leaf surface structures called glandular secreting trichomes to produce and secrete bioactive interferons to leaf surfaces where they can be easily recovered.   The scalability of this photosynthetic system allows the production of COVID-19 therapeutics at high levels and much lower cost than current protein expression systems.              Last Modified: 11/30/2021       Submitted by: Ryan W Shepherd]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
