<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[EAGER: Nanostructure-Enabled Solution Catalysis with Concentration Gradients]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>239823.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>239823</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kenneth Moloy</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kmoloy@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928441</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[With this award, the Chemical Catalysis Program of the NSF Division of Chemistry is funding Dr. Chong Liu of the University of California, Los Angeles to explore new chemistry and reactivity in solution catalysis where the concentrations of reactants and catalysts are controlled in space. Chemical transformations ranging from fundamental investigations to industrial manufacturing are often conducted in solution. It is usually true that the various chemical species are uniformly dispersed throughout the solution. While this often simplifies chemical processes it can also be a limitation. For example, some reactants may not be compatible with each other, with their reactions leading to undesirable side reactions and waste. In these cases it is advantageous to keep these species separated.  Dr. Liu is accomplishing this challenge with electrochemistry using arrays of nanometer scale wires. Successful implementation of the proposed work would potentially offer a new paradigm in chemical synthesis with a multifaceted approach involving nanoscience, electrochemistry, and catalysis. Dr. Liu's research team, including women and students from underrepresented groups, will be engaged in highly interdisciplinary research in this project. &lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;Dr. Liu and his team hypothesize that the electrochemistry of nanowire arrays yields controllable local O2 gradient microscopically, which enables O2-sensitive organometallic catalysts to perform oxidative reactions such as direct methane (CH4) to methanol (CH3OH) conversion. Dr. Liu’s research group will design and characterize concentration gradients generated by wire array electrodes, establish a selective CH4-to-CH3OH conversion of O2-deactivating catalysts with O2 oxidant at ambient condition, and explore additional scenarios of solution catalysis that benefits from concentration gradients. This project establishes the design principle of homogenous catalysis with concentration heterogeneity, by addressing two important questions: (1) How can one use electric potential to control and generate a pre-designed concentration profile at microscopic scale? (2) What improvements can be attained for solution catalysis via the establishment of microscopic concentration gradients? The integration of nanoscience and homogenous catalysis provides a unique and potentially powerful approach to control reactions at both molecular and microscopic length scales&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/18/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/14/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2027330</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Chong</FirstName>
<LastName>Liu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Chong Liu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[chongliu@chem.ucla.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000754881</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/18/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Los Angeles</Name>
<CityName>LOS ANGELES</CityName>
<ZipCode>900244201</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3107940102</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>10889 WILSHIRE BLVD STE 700</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>36</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA36</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>RN64EPNH8JC6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, LOS ANGELES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>NUDGYLBB4S99</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Los Angeles]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>900951406</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>36</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA36</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6884</Code>
<Text>Chemical Catalysis</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8037</Code>
<Text>Advanced Manufacturing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8396</Code>
<Text>Clean Energy Technology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8398</Code>
<Text>Hydrocarbon Conversion</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~239823</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This NSF EAGER project aims to develop new solution catalytic systems enabled by nanomaterials and the concurrently generated concentration gradients. One major outcome of this project is the discovery and detailed mechanistic investigation of a new solution catalytic process that facilitates ambient oxidation of methane to methanol with oxygen (O<sub>2</sub>) as the terminal oxidant. Our study affirms the feasibility of developing new organometallic catalysis with the use of nanomaterial electrodes and electrochemically generated concentration gradients. Furthermore, we developed a generalized kinetic model that not only explains our discovered catalytic system but also offer a guide of designing new catalytic systems with concentration gradients in the future. Another major outcome of this project resides on the training and mentoring of graduate and undergraduate researchers for the next-generation workforce. In collaboration with UCLA Center for Advancement of Teaching (CAT), we developed a machine-learning algorithm that assists teachers to better assess course teaching evaluation comments. Such an outcome will aid the undergraduate instructions across the country in the future.</p> <p>The intellectual merits of this project include the discovery of a new catalytic system of methane-to-methanol conversion, the generalized design principle for catalytic reactions under concentration gradients, as well as the developed machine-learning algorithm for undergraduate teaching evaluation comments. Such achievements yield significant broader impacts in the long run, by offering an alternative design philosophy for solution catalysis and alleviating the challenges faced in our current undergraduate education.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/29/2023<br>      Modified by: Chong&nbsp;Liu</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This NSF EAGER project aims to develop new solution catalytic systems enabled by nanomaterials and the concurrently generated concentration gradients. One major outcome of this project is the discovery and detailed mechanistic investigation of a new solution catalytic process that facilitates ambient oxidation of methane to methanol with oxygen (O2) as the terminal oxidant. Our study affirms the feasibility of developing new organometallic catalysis with the use of nanomaterial electrodes and electrochemically generated concentration gradients. Furthermore, we developed a generalized kinetic model that not only explains our discovered catalytic system but also offer a guide of designing new catalytic systems with concentration gradients in the future. Another major outcome of this project resides on the training and mentoring of graduate and undergraduate researchers for the next-generation workforce. In collaboration with UCLA Center for Advancement of Teaching (CAT), we developed a machine-learning algorithm that assists teachers to better assess course teaching evaluation comments. Such an outcome will aid the undergraduate instructions across the country in the future.  The intellectual merits of this project include the discovery of a new catalytic system of methane-to-methanol conversion, the generalized design principle for catalytic reactions under concentration gradients, as well as the developed machine-learning algorithm for undergraduate teaching evaluation comments. Such achievements yield significant broader impacts in the long run, by offering an alternative design philosophy for solution catalysis and alleviating the challenges faced in our current undergraduate education.           Last Modified: 01/29/2023       Submitted by: Chong Liu]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
