<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: THE PSYCHOLOGICAL UNDERPINNINGS OF PANIC BUYING DURING THE COVID-19 OUTBREAK AND HOW TO MITIGATE THEM]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>135825.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>135825</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Robert O'Connor</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>roconnor@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927263</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The coronavirus pandemic has influenced people’s marketplace behaviors. Panic buying has been evident among consumers all over the world, incurring substantial costs to the buyer, the society, and the marketplace. Hoarding and stockpiling creates shortage of supplies for necessities, depriving others who might be needing them the most in the situation (e.g., health care providers, older individuals), and artificially hikes price levels. For the panic buyer, this behavior creates inventory management problems. This research focuses on the consumer psychology of panic buying and how the media, policy makers, government officials and retailers can frame their communication with the general public at times of such unprecedented events, aiming to mitigate the psychological triggers of this behavior. The current research illuminates the psychological remedies of panic buying, and prescribes actions that may protect the supply chain, ensure equal distribution of necessities among the population, control price hikes of necessities, and extend consumers’ financial well-being in pandemic like situations.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;This research is two interrelated studies aimed at tackling the problem of panic buying owing to the COVID-19 pandemic. The first study explores the underlying psychological processes of panic buying during the ongoing crisis. Through an online survey, a U.S. national pool of 2750 respondents provides measures of relevant psychological factors and proneness to panic buying. The second study uses findings from the first study to develop communication frames and materials. The researcher then randomly assigns respondents to different conditions and evaluates the efficacy of the different conditions to reducing panic buying and hoarding.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is jointly funded by DRMS and the Established Program to Stimulate Competitive Research (EPSCoR).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/01/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/01/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2027620</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mehdi</FirstName>
<LastName>Hossain</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>T</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mehdi T Hossain</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[hossainm@uri.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000800809</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/01/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Rhode Island</Name>
<CityName>KINGSTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>028811974</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4018742635</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>75 LOWER COLLEGE RD RM 103</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>RI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>CJDNG9D14MW7</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF RHODE ISLAND</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Rhode Island]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>028811967</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>RI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1321</Code>
<Text>Decision, Risk &amp; Mgmt Sci</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EPSCoR Co-Funding</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>1N20</Code>
<Name>R&amp;RA CARES Act DEFC N</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>010N2021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[R&RA CARES Act DEFC N]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~135825</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The objectives of this research were to first understand the psychological underpinnings of consumer panic buying during the COVID-19 pandemic, and second, based on such insights, develop communication materials that potentially mitigates the panic factor.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; It was hypothesized that state level anxiety is the central root of panic buying while lack of situational control, being a root of the effect, operates through anxiety in influencing stockpiling. The psychological antecedents, influencing stockpiling, through the roots were, cognitive factors (need-for-cognition, long-term orientation and need for structure), and emotional factors (anticipated regret, uncertainty avoidance, and impulsivity). &nbsp;</p> <p>The effort for this introspection (in phase 1) involved first an online survey among a national pool of respondents, followed by a replication attempt. The replication attempt was essential given the recent critics of replication failure of a large number of social science research, published even (and notably) in prestigious journals (see Diener and Biswas-Diener 2022).</p> <p>A subset of the respondents participating in the replication study were surveyed twice more in June 2020 and December 2020 to gather insights on the effects of the psychological roots and antecedents of consumer stockpiling at various stages of the pandemic.</p> <p>The most consistent finding from the first round of studies was the direct effect of anxiety on consumer stockpiling and the indirect effect of situational control through the effect of anxiety. Among the psychological antecedents, most notable was the direct and indirect effects of anticipated regret on stockpiling. The direct and indirect effects of impulsivity on stockpiling were also consistent.</p> <p>Based on the findings on the psychological roots of panic buying three sets of communication materials were developed. For these materials, while the content of communication remained the same, their framings changed. The framing for the three sets of communication were hope, situational control and benchmark (protection framed). Of particular interest was the hope-framed communication. This framing was developed since research shows that hope is most effective in reducing state anxiety. The goal for this communication is to mitigate the experience of state anxiety and consequently reduce consumer stockpiling.</p> <p>These communication materials were utilized in a 4-weeks longitudinal randomized controlled trial applying real consumption-like scenarios. Results showed that, among three communication framings being studied, the hope-framed intervention was most effective in reducing consumer stockpiling over time for both household essentials and food items.</p> <p>The next study was another longitudinal study being conducted over the course of 8 weeks where consumer stockpiling of the same items was studied. The main difference between the 8-weeks study and the 4-weeks study was that, while in the 4-weeks study the interventions were educational and detailed prescriptions for pandemic related behaviors, in the 8-weeks study the interventions were nudges targeting subconscious behavioral change. Similar to the 4 weeks study, respondents were randomly assigned to hope framed versus situational control framed versus benchmark nudges, that were provided to them at the end of every week&rsquo;s survey.</p> <p>Outcomes from the 8-weeks study suggests that the situational control framed nudges were most effective in reducing consumer stockpiling over time. Also, this set of nudges were most effective in reducing state level anxiety over the course of the study. These findings from the two longitudinal studies not only provide powerful insights into identifying communication framings that reduce stockpiling, but also the effectiveness of the nature of communication in influencing consumer stockpiling (educational vs. nudging). The findings suggest that the hope framed communication is effective is reducing consumer stockpiling when delivered in a detailed, in-depth, manner that appeals to the rational system 2 (thoughtful) mind of the consumers. Apparently, for the effect of hope to emerge, it is essential that the communication materials be delivered in a way that helps consumers effectively reason how adhering to the COVID-19 guidelines puts them on a path for a hopeful future. The nudges on the other hand operate through influencing a more automatic, system 1, path of decision making.</p> <p>A cross sectional experiment was conducted next, with the purpose of experimentally manipulating certain psychological antecedents of panic buying identified based on findings from the first round of the surveys. The experiment validated the role of anticipated regret in influencing consumer stockpiling which operated through the psychological effects of state level anxiety.</p> <p>An additional outcome from this research suggest that, similar to stockpiling, hope framed communication was effective in reducing vaccine hesitancy over time. Also, people&rsquo;s perceived loneliness, as induced by the pandemic related social isolation, was a significant predictor of their willingness to vaccinate, an effect that operated through COVID-19 related fear and vaccine efficacy perception.</p> <p>Based on findings from our research our specific recommendations are the following:</p> <ol> <li>CDC should deliver hope-framed education communication and situational control framed nudges through pandemics to reduce panic in the marketplace. Also effective would be regret-aversive communication.</li> <li>Deliver hope-framed educational communication to reduce vaccine hesitancy. </li> </ol> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/20/2023<br>      Modified by: Mehdi&nbsp;T&nbsp;Hossain</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The objectives of this research were to first understand the psychological underpinnings of consumer panic buying during the COVID-19 pandemic, and second, based on such insights, develop communication materials that potentially mitigates the panic factor.              It was hypothesized that state level anxiety is the central root of panic buying while lack of situational control, being a root of the effect, operates through anxiety in influencing stockpiling. The psychological antecedents, influencing stockpiling, through the roots were, cognitive factors (need-for-cognition, long-term orientation and need for structure), and emotional factors (anticipated regret, uncertainty avoidance, and impulsivity).    The effort for this introspection (in phase 1) involved first an online survey among a national pool of respondents, followed by a replication attempt. The replication attempt was essential given the recent critics of replication failure of a large number of social science research, published even (and notably) in prestigious journals (see Diener and Biswas-Diener 2022).  A subset of the respondents participating in the replication study were surveyed twice more in June 2020 and December 2020 to gather insights on the effects of the psychological roots and antecedents of consumer stockpiling at various stages of the pandemic.  The most consistent finding from the first round of studies was the direct effect of anxiety on consumer stockpiling and the indirect effect of situational control through the effect of anxiety. Among the psychological antecedents, most notable was the direct and indirect effects of anticipated regret on stockpiling. The direct and indirect effects of impulsivity on stockpiling were also consistent.  Based on the findings on the psychological roots of panic buying three sets of communication materials were developed. For these materials, while the content of communication remained the same, their framings changed. The framing for the three sets of communication were hope, situational control and benchmark (protection framed). Of particular interest was the hope-framed communication. This framing was developed since research shows that hope is most effective in reducing state anxiety. The goal for this communication is to mitigate the experience of state anxiety and consequently reduce consumer stockpiling.  These communication materials were utilized in a 4-weeks longitudinal randomized controlled trial applying real consumption-like scenarios. Results showed that, among three communication framings being studied, the hope-framed intervention was most effective in reducing consumer stockpiling over time for both household essentials and food items.  The next study was another longitudinal study being conducted over the course of 8 weeks where consumer stockpiling of the same items was studied. The main difference between the 8-weeks study and the 4-weeks study was that, while in the 4-weeks study the interventions were educational and detailed prescriptions for pandemic related behaviors, in the 8-weeks study the interventions were nudges targeting subconscious behavioral change. Similar to the 4 weeks study, respondents were randomly assigned to hope framed versus situational control framed versus benchmark nudges, that were provided to them at the end of every week’s survey.  Outcomes from the 8-weeks study suggests that the situational control framed nudges were most effective in reducing consumer stockpiling over time. Also, this set of nudges were most effective in reducing state level anxiety over the course of the study. These findings from the two longitudinal studies not only provide powerful insights into identifying communication framings that reduce stockpiling, but also the effectiveness of the nature of communication in influencing consumer stockpiling (educational vs. nudging). The findings suggest that the hope framed communication is effective is reducing consumer stockpiling when delivered in a detailed, in-depth, manner that appeals to the rational system 2 (thoughtful) mind of the consumers. Apparently, for the effect of hope to emerge, it is essential that the communication materials be delivered in a way that helps consumers effectively reason how adhering to the COVID-19 guidelines puts them on a path for a hopeful future. The nudges on the other hand operate through influencing a more automatic, system 1, path of decision making.  A cross sectional experiment was conducted next, with the purpose of experimentally manipulating certain psychological antecedents of panic buying identified based on findings from the first round of the surveys. The experiment validated the role of anticipated regret in influencing consumer stockpiling which operated through the psychological effects of state level anxiety.  An additional outcome from this research suggest that, similar to stockpiling, hope framed communication was effective in reducing vaccine hesitancy over time. Also, people’s perceived loneliness, as induced by the pandemic related social isolation, was a significant predictor of their willingness to vaccinate, an effect that operated through COVID-19 related fear and vaccine efficacy perception.  Based on findings from our research our specific recommendations are the following:  CDC should deliver hope-framed education communication and situational control framed nudges through pandemics to reduce panic in the marketplace. Also effective would be regret-aversive communication. Deliver hope-framed educational communication to reduce vaccine hesitancy.                  Last Modified: 08/20/2023       Submitted by: Mehdi T Hossain]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
