<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Developing and Piloting a Game Design-Based Computer Science Curriculum]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>299895.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>299895</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DRL</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Wu He</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>wuhe@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032920000</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Centered on teaching game-design and computer programming using industry-standard game-development software (Unity 3D), the project aims to create and implement a middle school computer science (CS) curriculum. The project will involve teacher professional development (PD), a collaboration between teachers and researchers to co-develop a curriculum, and research and evaluation to understand the outcomes from the design and implementation efforts. The project will take place in low socioeconomic status and underserved middle schools, which are fraught with issues when it comes to teaching CS (e.g., lack of high-quality PD and teachers) in addition to serving high-need students underrepresented in the CS workforce. Building on the appeal of game design as an attractive CS context for diverse populations, and the pedagogical approaches guiding the curriculum design, the project will address the needs of the underserved students in learning CS, helping overcome representation issues in CS.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Research and evaluation will be conducted on the (a) curriculum development, (b) teacher PD and professional learning communities (PLC), and (c) curriculum implementation processes. First, the curriculum will be built on previously established theoretical and practical frameworks and will be co-created with teachers. Unique to this project, however, game-design software used in industry will be used instead of block-based tools. This will help establish direct real-life relevance and reusable (syntactic) knowledge. The knowledge gained from this design and implementation will inform future game-design efforts in using more advanced software with industry and real-life acceptance and transferability. Second, data will be collected to examine the effectiveness of the hybrid, ongoing PD, and PLC efforts, and inform future CS professional learning opportunities that are similarly extensive, structured, and job-embedded. Third, data will be collected from students and teachers to understand the interaction among the design, teacher PD, and curriculum implementation toward creating an understanding of how the theories and design lead to CS and pedagogical content knowledge of CS during the implementation of the curriculum. Factors contributing to (or limiting) the curriculum’s use, and participation of underserved populations in CS activities will be the core of the analyses. Data will be collected to examine CS knowledge and motivation development of teachers and students by analyzing data from surveys, interviews, student games, reflections, student-student conversations, and classroom videos on teacher-student interactions. This project is funded by the CS for All program.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/05/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/05/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2027948</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Charles</FirstName>
<LastName>Hodges</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Charles B Hodges</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[chodges@georgiasouthern.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000552937</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/05/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Andrew</FirstName>
<LastName>Allen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Andrew A Allen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[andrewallen@georgiasouthern.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000661456</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/05/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mete</FirstName>
<LastName>Akcaoglu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mete Akcaoglu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[makcaoglu@georgiasouthern.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000694445</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/05/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Selcuk</FirstName>
<LastName>Dogan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Selcuk Dogan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[sdogan@georgiasouthern.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000823712</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/05/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Georgia Southern University Research and Service Foundation, Inc</Name>
<CityName>STATESBORO</CityName>
<ZipCode>304586724</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9124785465</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>261 FOREST DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[STE 3000]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>FL4AUYLFP7E8</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GEORGIA SOUTHERN UNIVERSITY RESEARCH &amp; SERVICE FOUNDATION INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Georgia Southern University Research and Service Foundation, Inc]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>304588005</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>134Y</Code>
<Text>CSforAll-Computer Sci for All</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>023Z</Code>
<Text>Computer Science for All (CS for All)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8817</Code>
<Text>STEM Learning &amp; Learning Environments</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0420</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~299895</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Project Game, funded by the CS for All program, embarked on a mission to transform middle school computer science education in underserved, rural settings through the innovative teaching of game-design and programming using industry-standard software Unity 3D. The project spanned two years and aimed to enhance both the substance and appeal of computer science education.</p> <p>Six teachers underwent a year-long professional development (PD) process, which was adapted to an online/hybrid model in response to COVID-19 restrictions in 2021. This adaptation offered the project team an opportunity to identify and learn about best practices for the hybrid approach to teaching. Interest development among the teachers emerged as a significant factor, with variations observed in how this interest influenced their teaching performance.</p> <p>The curriculum was implemented in two schools, reaching approximately 60 students in its first pilot year. A key finding from the pilot was the effectiveness of having teachers use the same lessons in their classrooms that they had learned during their PD for Unity 3D and C#. The students were able to navigate the complexities of learning a text-based language (C#) and industry-standard game-design software with considerable success. The approach not only proved effective but also increased students' motivation to learn computer science.</p> <p>A highlight of the project was the students' presentation of their games at the end of each semester at their schools. These presentations became popular events, showcasing the tangible outcomes of the curriculum and fostering a sense of accomplishment and engagement among students and the broader school community. The courses have become a popular addition to the district curricula and an effective way to teach computer programming and game-design.</p> <p>By focusing on underserved populations and emphasizing the engaging context of game design, Project Game addressed significant representation issues in the computer science workforce. The project's unique approach of integrating industry-standard tools with teacher PD and the co-creation of curriculum established a model with real-life relevance and transferable knowledge. These contributions hold intellectual merit by advancing the field of computer science education. The curriculum materials are publicly available at&nbsp;https://www.projectgame.org/</p> <p>The broader impacts of Project Game extend beyond immediate educational outcomes. The students who learned coding and Unity 3D in these rural settings may possibly start thinking about computer science-related future jobs. This potential shift in career considerations represents a promising impact, contributing to the understanding of effective hybrid teaching methodologies and the potential to inform future computer science education initiatives. The insights gained through this two-year endeavor resonate beyond the immediate context, providing valuable lessons for educators, policymakers, and stakeholders committed to reducing disparities and enhancing quality in the field of computer science.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/21/2023<br>      Modified by: Mete&nbsp;Akcaoglu</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2027948/2027948_10693209_1692109460411_Game_logo_SM--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2027948/2027948_10693209_1692109460411_Game_logo_SM--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Project Game Logo"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2027948/2027948_10693209_1692109460411_Game_logo_SM--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Project Game Logo"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Project Game Logo</div> <div class="imageCredit">Mete Akcaoglu</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Mete&nbsp;Akcaoglu</div> <div class="imageTitle">Project Game Logo</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Project Game, funded by the CS for All program, embarked on a mission to transform middle school computer science education in underserved, rural settings through the innovative teaching of game-design and programming using industry-standard software Unity 3D. The project spanned two years and aimed to enhance both the substance and appeal of computer science education.  Six teachers underwent a year-long professional development (PD) process, which was adapted to an online/hybrid model in response to COVID-19 restrictions in 2021. This adaptation offered the project team an opportunity to identify and learn about best practices for the hybrid approach to teaching. Interest development among the teachers emerged as a significant factor, with variations observed in how this interest influenced their teaching performance.  The curriculum was implemented in two schools, reaching approximately 60 students in its first pilot year. A key finding from the pilot was the effectiveness of having teachers use the same lessons in their classrooms that they had learned during their PD for Unity 3D and C#. The students were able to navigate the complexities of learning a text-based language (C#) and industry-standard game-design software with considerable success. The approach not only proved effective but also increased students' motivation to learn computer science.  A highlight of the project was the students' presentation of their games at the end of each semester at their schools. These presentations became popular events, showcasing the tangible outcomes of the curriculum and fostering a sense of accomplishment and engagement among students and the broader school community. The courses have become a popular addition to the district curricula and an effective way to teach computer programming and game-design.  By focusing on underserved populations and emphasizing the engaging context of game design, Project Game addressed significant representation issues in the computer science workforce. The project's unique approach of integrating industry-standard tools with teacher PD and the co-creation of curriculum established a model with real-life relevance and transferable knowledge. These contributions hold intellectual merit by advancing the field of computer science education. The curriculum materials are publicly available at https://www.projectgame.org/  The broader impacts of Project Game extend beyond immediate educational outcomes. The students who learned coding and Unity 3D in these rural settings may possibly start thinking about computer science-related future jobs. This potential shift in career considerations represents a promising impact, contributing to the understanding of effective hybrid teaching methodologies and the potential to inform future computer science education initiatives. The insights gained through this two-year endeavor resonate beyond the immediate context, providing valuable lessons for educators, policymakers, and stakeholders committed to reducing disparities and enhancing quality in the field of computer science.       Last Modified: 08/21/2023       Submitted by: Mete Akcaoglu]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
