<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Impacts of COVID-19 Out-of-School Stressors on Executive Function and E- Learning]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>200000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>200000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Soo-Siang Lim</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>slim@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927878</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[In the midst of COVID-19 pandemic, students are not only facing health concerns, but also other stressors tied to mandated changes in their environments.  These include a near-complete reliance on technology for college participation and learning, changes in access to peers and social support networks, changes in works-spaces and possible financial uncertainties.  At this juncture of many upheavals, this project will collect data to understand how U.S. undergraduates’ experiences of stress may be impacting their ability to learn as universities switch to on-line instruction. High quality learning through online instruction is known to be challenging in the best of times; these difficulties are likely to be exacerbated by the myriad stresses that undergraduates are experiencing now. Focusing on the experiences of undergraduates at a diverse, minority-serving public four-year college, the data collected will assess the relationships between types of stressors, and student learning using e-learning techniques. Gathering this information immediately will be crucial to supporting students as the pandemic continues. Results will have broad impact on improving instructional infrastructure and practices to better support student learning in these stressful times.  Moreover, this knowledge will be useful to colleges and universities in the development of effective strategies to meet their students’ needs.   &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Executive Functions (EFs) are crucial to successful learning; these are cognitive resources that control attention, allow students to grapple with complex ideas and hold information in mind.  EFs are taxed when students are under stress, leading to increased load on verbal working memory from external concerns or environmental vigilance. The implication is that students experiencing high levels of stress will have fewer EF resources to extend to their learning, potentially made more challenging by lack of familiarity with e-learning.  Two time-sensitive field studies will be conducted to gather information about the types of stressors that U.S. undergraduates in a minority-serving public four-year college are facing during the pandemic. The goal is to assess the relative impacts of different stressors (or their combinations) on learning, in order to best design interventions to mitigate damaging effects. Two theory-driven approaches will be assessed as means to counter potential adverse stress impacts: 1) management of attention as a key aspect of executive function, and 2) management and regulation of emotions during learning.  In addition to advances in our understanding of how stress affects student learning, findings of this project will help inform institutional responses and instructional design for e-learning courses offered during the ongoing COVID-19 pandemic.  More generally, the work will inform the field’s ability to improve e-learning in future applications.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/15/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/15/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2027447</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Justin</FirstName>
<LastName>Richland</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Justin Richland</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jbrich@uci.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000511068</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/15/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lindsey</FirstName>
<LastName>Richland</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lindsey E Richland</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[lerich@uci.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000489434</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/15/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Irvine</Name>
<CityName>IRVINE</CityName>
<ZipCode>926970001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9498247295</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>160 ALDRICH HALL</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>47</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA47</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>MJC5FCYQTPE6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA IRVINE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Irvine]]></Name>
<CityName>Irvine</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>926175500</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3200 Education]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>47</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA47</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>127y</Code>
<Text>Sci of Lrng &amp; Augmented Intel</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>059Z</Code>
<Text>Science of Learning</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>1N20</Code>
<Name>R&amp;RA CARES Act DEFC N</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>010N2021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[R&RA CARES Act DEFC N]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~200000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Part 1. In the midst of COVID-19 pandemic, students are not only facing health concerns, but other stressors tied to their environments.&nbsp; At the outset of the pandemic, there was a very rapid mandated shift that required a near-complete reliance on technology for college participation and learning. This reliance on online course taking has also continued despite many undergraduate institutions returning to in-person coursework as an option.&nbsp; Health concerns, economic uncertainty, changes in their access to peers and social support networks, and changes in their works-spaces were all part of this pandemic's impact on undergraduates. This project gathered data of critical importance to understanding how U.S. undergraduates&rsquo; experiences of stress can impact their ability to learn, as universities switched to on-line instruction. High quality learning through online instruction is known to be challenging in the best of times; these difficulties were likely to be further exacerbated by the ways that undergraduates are experiencing stress due to the pandemic. This study collected data on the experiences of undergraduates at a diverse, minority-serving public four-year college, and assessed the relationships between types of stressors and e-learning techniques (including resources and support systems).&nbsp;</p> <p>Part 2. Executive Functions (EFs), the cognitive resources that control attention, allow students to grapple with complex ideas, and hold information in mind, are crucial to successful learning. &nbsp;They are also often engaged when students are under stress, leading to verbal working memory load in the form of worries or environmental vigilance or monitoring. The implication is that students feeling the highest levels of stress will have fewer EF resources to extend to their learning, potentially made more challenging by unfamiliarity with e-learning. &nbsp;Time-sensitive field studies have been conducted to gather information about the types of stressors that U.S. undergraduates in a minority-serving public four-year college faced during the immediate onset of the pandemic, as well as during its continuing presence. &nbsp;The goals were to assess the relative impacts of different stressors (or their combinations) on learning, in order to best design interventions to mitigate damaging effects. This project also tested two theory-driven strategies to counter potential adverse impacts by educating undergraduates about how to 1) manage their attention, and 2) manage and regulate their emotions during learning.&nbsp;The intellectual merit of the project derives from its ability to provide novel insights into students&rsquo; stress and anxiety during the unique COVID-19 pandemic context, as well as to test theory-driven strategies for improving student learning when under stress. This knowledge will help inform institutional responses and instructional design for e-learning courses offered during the ongoing COVID-19 pandemic. &nbsp;More generally, the work has informed the field&rsquo;s ability to improve e-learning in future applications.&nbsp;</p> <p>Project Outcomes.&nbsp;This project revealed that students were under high stress and anxiety related to the pandemic in 2020 and 2021, many scoring at the levels of clinical importance.&nbsp; This was also distributed unequally, such that those of Latinx descent, first-generation college students, female, and especially those who identified with all of these characteristics, were feeling higher stress than the broader college population. These levels of stress were directly related to how much students learned from online instruction.&nbsp; These could be explained by mind wandering during the lesson, such that higher distress led to higher levels of mind wandering.&nbsp; Knowing this mechanism is important to developing interventions to reduce these effects.&nbsp; For example, a short mindfulness intervention before instruction was able to reduce levels of mind wandering reported by students, suggesting that this may be an effective tool for supporting equity in online learning. Such interventions are important to ensuring that students who are societally more likely to be stressed are not challenged additionally in pandemic circumstances and also during online learning.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/30/2022<br>      Modified by: Lindsey&nbsp;E&nbsp;Richland</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Part 1. In the midst of COVID-19 pandemic, students are not only facing health concerns, but other stressors tied to their environments.  At the outset of the pandemic, there was a very rapid mandated shift that required a near-complete reliance on technology for college participation and learning. This reliance on online course taking has also continued despite many undergraduate institutions returning to in-person coursework as an option.  Health concerns, economic uncertainty, changes in their access to peers and social support networks, and changes in their works-spaces were all part of this pandemic's impact on undergraduates. This project gathered data of critical importance to understanding how U.S. undergraduates’ experiences of stress can impact their ability to learn, as universities switched to on-line instruction. High quality learning through online instruction is known to be challenging in the best of times; these difficulties were likely to be further exacerbated by the ways that undergraduates are experiencing stress due to the pandemic. This study collected data on the experiences of undergraduates at a diverse, minority-serving public four-year college, and assessed the relationships between types of stressors and e-learning techniques (including resources and support systems).   Part 2. Executive Functions (EFs), the cognitive resources that control attention, allow students to grapple with complex ideas, and hold information in mind, are crucial to successful learning.  They are also often engaged when students are under stress, leading to verbal working memory load in the form of worries or environmental vigilance or monitoring. The implication is that students feeling the highest levels of stress will have fewer EF resources to extend to their learning, potentially made more challenging by unfamiliarity with e-learning.  Time-sensitive field studies have been conducted to gather information about the types of stressors that U.S. undergraduates in a minority-serving public four-year college faced during the immediate onset of the pandemic, as well as during its continuing presence.  The goals were to assess the relative impacts of different stressors (or their combinations) on learning, in order to best design interventions to mitigate damaging effects. This project also tested two theory-driven strategies to counter potential adverse impacts by educating undergraduates about how to 1) manage their attention, and 2) manage and regulate their emotions during learning. The intellectual merit of the project derives from its ability to provide novel insights into students’ stress and anxiety during the unique COVID-19 pandemic context, as well as to test theory-driven strategies for improving student learning when under stress. This knowledge will help inform institutional responses and instructional design for e-learning courses offered during the ongoing COVID-19 pandemic.  More generally, the work has informed the field’s ability to improve e-learning in future applications.   Project Outcomes. This project revealed that students were under high stress and anxiety related to the pandemic in 2020 and 2021, many scoring at the levels of clinical importance.  This was also distributed unequally, such that those of Latinx descent, first-generation college students, female, and especially those who identified with all of these characteristics, were feeling higher stress than the broader college population. These levels of stress were directly related to how much students learned from online instruction.  These could be explained by mind wandering during the lesson, such that higher distress led to higher levels of mind wandering.  Knowing this mechanism is important to developing interventions to reduce these effects.  For example, a short mindfulness intervention before instruction was able to reduce levels of mind wandering reported by students, suggesting that this may be an effective tool for supporting equity in online learning. Such interventions are important to ensuring that students who are societally more likely to be stressed are not challenged additionally in pandemic circumstances and also during online learning.           Last Modified: 05/30/2022       Submitted by: Lindsey E Richland]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
