<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[EAGER: Management and Organizational Issues in Technology Transfer at Federal Laboratories: Data Collection and Analysis to Advance Commercialization of Federally-funded Research]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>150000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>150000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SMA</Abbreviation>
<LongName>SBE Off Of Multidisciplinary Activities</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Georgia Kosmopoulou</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>gkosmopo@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928760</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[It is well known that there is less technology transfer from federal labs to the private sector, as compared to technology transfer from universities. That is unfortunate since federal labs receive more government funding for research than universities (e.g., the R&amp;D expenditures of the federal labs in California consistently exceed those for all 10 University of California campuses).  The federal labs also have a technology transfer component, which arguably is not currently being realized to its potential. Accordingly, the overall purpose of this project is to collect data from scientists and managers at federal labs in order to determine how we can advance commercialization of federally-funded research.  Our project has important policy and managerial implications for those who govern and manage technology transfer at federal labs. It is also quite timely, given that the technology transfer gap between universities and federal labs has attracted considerable attention.  Also, the Department of Energy, which runs 17 major national labs (e.g., Sandia, Livermore, Brookhaven, Berkeley, Los Alamos) is presently reviewing technology transfer policies and procedures at its federal labs.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The data we collect will be used to study three potential mechanisms for advancing the commercialization of research at federal labs: (1) assessing the “entrepreneurial orientation” of individual scientists, labs, and organizations; (2) exploring the role of foreign-born status of scientists on entrepreneurial identity, role conflict, and the propensity to engage in technology transfer; and (3) managerial and organizational issues, such as the role of incentives, organizational justice (workplace fairness and equity), championing, leadership, work-life balance, and organizational culture in technology transfer, and strategy formulation.  Specifically, the data that we collect on individual scientists and those who manage these scientists, as well as the technology transfer process more generally at the federal labs, will help identify managerial practices that enhance commercialization and the design of more effective entrepreneurial programs and initiatives. Our findings will also improve our understanding of the potential roadblocks that exist for scientists at federal labs who wish to pursue commercialization of their research. The project will be of great interest not only to scholars of science and innovation policy and technology transfer, but also to the broader community of “micro,” or organizational behavior scholars in the fields of management and organizational psychology. Moreover, this research will yield clear policy implications for managers of federal labs, as well as legislators.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/12/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/09/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2027440</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Waldman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David A Waldman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[waldman@asu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000344307</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/12/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Donald</FirstName>
<LastName>Siegel</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Donald S Siegel</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[donald.siegel.1@asu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000069955</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/12/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Arizona State University</Name>
<CityName>TEMPE</CityName>
<ZipCode>852813670</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4809655479</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>660 S MILL AVENUE STE 204</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AZ04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NTLHJXM55KZ6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ARIZONA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Arizona State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Tempe</CityName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>852876011</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[PO Box876011]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AZ04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>125Y</Code>
<Text>Science of Science</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~150000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>With all of these issues in mind, we are pleased to report the following activities and outcomes associated with our EAGER grant:</p> <p>1)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; <strong>Workshop</strong>-Organization of a major virtual workshop on April 20, 2021 on ?Advancing the Commercialization of Research at Federal Laboratories: Management and Organizational Issues in Technology Transfer.? The agenda for this workshop is shown in Appendix A of this report. Workshop presenters include leading scholars of technology transfer, organizational behavior, human resource management, and intellectual property, journal editors, policy makers, and technology transfer managers and officials at federal labs and federal agencies.</p> <p>2)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; <strong>Presentations</strong>- Presentation of our initial qualitative findings at the Federal Laboratory Consortium Annual Conference in 2021, the National Center for Advancing Translational Sciences (NCATS) Workshop on ?Federal Technology Transfer: Measuring Impact, Innovation, and Efficiencies? in May 2021 (see <a href="https://sites.google.com/ncats.nih.gov/osa-metrics-workshop">https://sites.google.com/ncats.nih.gov/osa-metrics-workshop</a>), and the Academy of Management Meetings in 2021 (virtual) and 2022 in Seattle, WA. Professor Siegel also presented research related to this project at the following universities: University of Illinois-Urbana Champaign, Baylor, Rutgers, and the University of Ottawa. Professor Waldman presented findings at the Rotterdam School of Management, Erasmus University; and the Technical University of Munich.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>3)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; <strong>Article-</strong>Published article: Qualitative findings were published in a paper titled ?<a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0048733321002481">Assessing Differences between University and Federal Laboratory Postdoctoral Scientists in Technology Transfer</a>,? which is in press &nbsp;in the leading journal in the field of innovation studies, <em>Research Policy</em> (2021 SSCI Impact Factor: 9.473). Working paper: We are currently preparing a working paper based on the surveys we conducted at three federal labs (one NIH and two DOD labs).&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>4)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; <strong>Surveying</strong>-We have made considerable progress on surveying individual scientists at three federal labs: 1) The Center for Cancer Research (CCR), which is part of the National Cancer Institute of the NIH; 2) Naval Surface Warfare Center-Crane Division (NWSC-Crane); 3) Air Force Research Laboratory (AFRL) in Albuquerque.&nbsp; We have completed our surveying at CCR and NWSC-Crane).&nbsp;</p> <p>5)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; <strong>Reports on Surveys</strong>-We have completed survey reports for CCR and NWSC-Crane.&nbsp; The CCR report is presented in Appendix B. These reports will be used as the basis for establishing further credibility within the federal lab system for the purpose of broader survey administration and subsequent publication in top management journals.&nbsp;</p> <p>6)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; <strong>Three Special Issues: </strong></p> <p><strong>2024-2026&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; (with Miriam Erez, Maribel Guerrero, Mirjam Knockaert, and Phil Phan)-Special Issue on ?Re-thinking Academic Entrepreneurship: Micro, Macro, and Meso Perspectives? Strategic Entrepreneurship Journal</strong></p> <p><strong>2022-2023 (with Maryann Feldman, Maribel Guerrero, Andy Lockett, and Siri Terjesen)- Special Issue on ?Assessing the Impact of University Innovation and Entrepreneurial Ecosystems: Managerial and Policy Implications?&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Academy of Management Perspectives</strong></p> <p><strong>2021-2023&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; (with Miriam Erez, Zhaoli Song, and Ute Stephan) Special Issue on ?Organizational Behavior and Human Resource Management Perspectives on&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Entrepreneurship? Personnel Psychology</strong></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/03/2022<br>      Modified by: Donald&nbsp;S&nbsp;Siegel</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ With all of these issues in mind, we are pleased to report the following activities and outcomes associated with our EAGER grant:  1)      Workshop-Organization of a major virtual workshop on April 20, 2021 on ?Advancing the Commercialization of Research at Federal Laboratories: Management and Organizational Issues in Technology Transfer.? The agenda for this workshop is shown in Appendix A of this report. Workshop presenters include leading scholars of technology transfer, organizational behavior, human resource management, and intellectual property, journal editors, policy makers, and technology transfer managers and officials at federal labs and federal agencies.  2)      Presentations- Presentation of our initial qualitative findings at the Federal Laboratory Consortium Annual Conference in 2021, the National Center for Advancing Translational Sciences (NCATS) Workshop on ?Federal Technology Transfer: Measuring Impact, Innovation, and Efficiencies? in May 2021 (see https://sites.google.com/ncats.nih.gov/osa-metrics-workshop), and the Academy of Management Meetings in 2021 (virtual) and 2022 in Seattle, WA. Professor Siegel also presented research related to this project at the following universities: University of Illinois-Urbana Champaign, Baylor, Rutgers, and the University of Ottawa. Professor Waldman presented findings at the Rotterdam School of Management, Erasmus University; and the Technical University of Munich.     3)      Article-Published article: Qualitative findings were published in a paper titled ?Assessing Differences between University and Federal Laboratory Postdoctoral Scientists in Technology Transfer,? which is in press  in the leading journal in the field of innovation studies, Research Policy (2021 SSCI Impact Factor: 9.473). Working paper: We are currently preparing a working paper based on the surveys we conducted at three federal labs (one NIH and two DOD labs).    4)      Surveying-We have made considerable progress on surveying individual scientists at three federal labs: 1) The Center for Cancer Research (CCR), which is part of the National Cancer Institute of the NIH; 2) Naval Surface Warfare Center-Crane Division (NWSC-Crane); 3) Air Force Research Laboratory (AFRL) in Albuquerque.  We have completed our surveying at CCR and NWSC-Crane).   5)      Reports on Surveys-We have completed survey reports for CCR and NWSC-Crane.  The CCR report is presented in Appendix B. These reports will be used as the basis for establishing further credibility within the federal lab system for the purpose of broader survey administration and subsequent publication in top management journals.   6)      Three Special Issues:   2024-2026    (with Miriam Erez, Maribel Guerrero, Mirjam Knockaert, and Phil Phan)-Special Issue on ?Re-thinking Academic Entrepreneurship: Micro, Macro, and Meso Perspectives? Strategic Entrepreneurship Journal  2022-2023 (with Maryann Feldman, Maribel Guerrero, Andy Lockett, and Siri Terjesen)- Special Issue on ?Assessing the Impact of University Innovation and Entrepreneurial Ecosystems: Managerial and Policy Implications?                    Academy of Management Perspectives  2021-2023    (with Miriam Erez, Zhaoli Song, and Ute Stephan) Special Issue on ?Organizational Behavior and Human Resource Management Perspectives on                             Entrepreneurship? Personnel Psychology          Last Modified: 09/03/2022       Submitted by: Donald S Siegel]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
