<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Coronavirus-Driven Aerosol Reductions in East Asia and the Effect on Atmospheric Dynamics]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>128339.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>128339</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06020105</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AGS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Chungu Lu</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>clu@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927110</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The goal of this project is to determine how China’s government-mandated COVID-19 quarantine during February 2020 altered the meteorological conditions in which the disease was being transmitted. During the height of the COVID-19 outbreak in East Asia, the Chinese government authorized closure of many industrial facilities, temporarily and dramatically reducing air pollution in East China. The swift reduction of particulate emissions, which can weaken the intensity of incoming solar energy, would have likely allowed more sunlight to pass through the atmosphere, thereby increasing surface air temperature during the quarantine. Because pathogen transmission can be retarded in warmer and more humid conditions, increased surface air temperatures concurrent with quarantine-reduced aerosols may represent another, yet unintentional, mechanism by which large-scale lockdowns can slow the spread of COVID-19. This project will employ satellite imagery and weather model simulations to determine the extent to which reduced air pollution altered air temperature, as well as several other meteorological conditions, during February 2020 in East China. The findings of this project will also reveal additional important information about how atmospheric particulates influence regional weather patterns on a normal, non-quarantine basis.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will mine daily satellite images of NO2, aerosol optical depth (AOD), and air temperature as well as in-situ data from the World Meteorological Organization and Aerosol Robotic Network (AERONET) to assess the co-evolution of pollution decreases and air temperature increases. Additionally, the project will employ the Weather Research and Forecasting (WRF) model coupled with chemistry (WRF-Chem) in a numerical modeling experiment for February 2020 over East China, whereby one simulation is initialized with normal emissions and the second simulation reduces emissions commensurate with the satellite observations collected during February 2020.  This project will yield three key products: (1) Daily database of NO2, AOD, and surface, 925-, and 850-hPa temperature over East China, both absolute values and departure from climatology; (2) Two one-month weather simulations for typical emissions and COVID-19-reduced emissions over China; (3) The net impact of aerosol radiative effects on air temperature, as well as a summary of any changes to circulation, cloud cover, and precipitation. These products are valuable for the COVID-19 pandemic, as well as future disease outbreaks, because they can inform how quarantines and lockdowns potentially impede pathogen transmission via aerosol reductions and associated meteorological feedbacks.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/26/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/26/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2027199</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
<LastName>Miller</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Paul W Miller</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[pmiller1@lsu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000809352</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/26/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Louisiana State University</Name>
<CityName>BATON ROUGE</CityName>
<ZipCode>708030001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2255782760</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>202 HIMES HALL</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
<StateCode>LA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>LA06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>ECQEYCHRNKJ4</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>LOUISIANA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>Z7ZNZH7LJ778</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Louisiana State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Baton Rouge</CityName>
<StateCode>LA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>708032701</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>LA06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1525</Code>
<Text>Physical &amp; Dynamic Meteorology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~128339</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Intellectual Merit</strong></p> <p>Because particulate emissions weaken the intensity of incoming solar radiation, their prompt and dramatic reduction would logically increase surface air temperature. China's COVID-19 quarantine in early 2020 offers a unique opportunity to observe weather patterns as they would otherwise occur without the heavy anthropogenic aerosol contributions that normally characterize the region. This project used (1) temperature and aerosol observations to track the co-evolution of surface warming and pollution reduction during the lockdown, (2) determine the lockdown's role in any observed temperature changes, and (3) examine the cascading effects of surface warming upon atmospheric penomena that may be sensitive to changes in temperature.</p> <p>A simple comparison of pre-quarantine (PRE) versus during-quarantine (C19Q) satellite-based surface air temperatures anomalies and aerosol concentrations revealed a striking correspondence between the locations of greatest C19Q warming and sharpest aerosol reductions (Figure 1) during the lockdowns.</p> <p>However, not all particulate changes can be assumed to arise from the lockdown, nor can all temperature increases be reflexively attributed to reduction in particulate levels. Consequently, newly available satellite observations from the Visible Infrared Imaging Radiometer Suite (VIIRS) aboard the NOAA-20 platform was used to infer the reduction in urban-specific aerosol species (Figure 2). During C19Q, the percentage of aerosols associated with urban activity declined from 27.1% of all particulates to 17.5%, a -34.1% decrease. Near Wuhan urban aerosol fraction declined by -38.2%.</p> <p>The spatial pattern of pollution decreases in Figure 2 was used to initialize an atmospheric modeling experiment composed of two simulations of the Weather Research and Forecasting model coupled with chemistry (WRF-Chem). One simulation contained normal levels of anthropogenic particulate emissions (BASE) and in a second simulation, anthropogenic particulates emissions were adjusted using the percent changes in Figure 2 (REDUX). The WRF-Chem experiment resolved warmer surface temperatures over parts of China that witnessed the most substantial decreases in urban aerosols (Figure 3). For instance, C19Q warming was +0.19?C in Wuhan with temperature increases surrounding Wuhan ranging between +0.2-0.3?C. However, the modeled C19Q increases are only one tenth as large as the PRE vs C19Q warming shown in Figure 1 as well as measured by surface weather stations in China (Figure 3). Thus, while the pollution reductions were contributing factors to the C19Q warming, they were nonetheless secondary to larger-scale synoptic factors (not shown).</p> <p>Given the small, yet widespread, tenths-of-degree warming arising from the lockdowns, additional analysis engaged changes to other meteorological conditions (e.g., wind, precipitation) that may be sensitive to small temperature shifts. Figure 4 shows the difference in accumulated precipitation between the REDUX and BASE simulations. While both scenarios generally underestimate precipitation domain-wide, they are most distinguished by a corridor of positive precipitation error in the BASE case versus near-zero error in the C19Q scenario over southeast China. This feature largely develops from their differing representations of a rainfall event during 28 February - 1 March 2020. The BASE scenario produces a near-continuous band of heavy southwest-to-northeast oriented precipitation (Figure 4c), whereas the C19Q scenario resolves a smaller pocket of heavy rain and moderate rainfall spread across a larger area (Figure 4d), which aligns more closely with satellite observations from NASA's Global Precipitation Measurement Mission (GPM) (Figure 4e).</p> <p>The quarantine-driven differences between these two events are shown in Figure 5, where a cold front is stretched across southwest China. By 0600 UTC (2 PM local time) on 29 February 2020, the pre-frontal warm sector of the C19Q scenario responds more strongly to diurnal heating (Figure 5a, d), possibly driven by incoming shortwave radiation more efficiently reaching the surface with fewer particulates. The control simulation erroneously resolves an area of convection near the cold front (Figure 5c) that is not reproduced in the C19Q simulation (Figure 5f) nor the GPM observations (Figure 5g). The simulated radar reflectivities at this time also reveal relatively significant differences in the distribution of convection (Figure 5b, e), especially considering microphysical aerosol effects were not represented in either simulation.</p> <p>The stronger temperature gradient on 29 February may have also yielded a stronger kinematic profile evident in the 850-hPa wind field. Figure 6 shows that the 850-hPa winds were stronger in the quarantine scenario in the area where the observed precipitation was more accurately resolved. Thus, the aerosol radiative warming may have played an important role influencing the mesoscale circulations that modulate convection initiation and organization such as convergence and low-level wind shear.</p> <p>Overall, reductions in particulate emissions during China's 2020 COVID-19 lockdown resulted in widespread tenths-of-degree warming during February 2020. Though the temperature increases were minor, they did appear to, at least circumstantially, affect the development of larger weather events such as the heavy rainfall event on 29 February 2020.</p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts</strong></p> <p>RAPID projects are not assessed for broader impacts. Regardless, this project partially supported two graduate students, produced one peer-reviewed paper, one publically available dataset, and three conferenence presentations.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/27/2022<br>      Modified by: Paul&nbsp;W&nbsp;Miller</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2027199/2027199_10660904_1658967715200_Figure1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2027199/2027199_10660904_1658967715200_Figure1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 1"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2027199/2027199_10660904_1658967715200_Figure1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 1"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 1. PRE versus C19Q changes in air temperature anomaly (left) and aerosol concentration as measured by the aerosol optical depth (AOD) anomaly (right).</div> <div class="imageCredit">Miller, P. W., C. Reesman, M. K. Grossman, S. A. Nelson, V. Liu, and P. Wang, 2021: Marginal warming associated with a COVID-19 quarantine and the implications for disease transmission. Science of The Total Environment, 780, 146579, doi:https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2021.146579.</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Paul&nbsp;W&nbsp;Miller</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 1</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2027199/2027199_10660904_1658966683400_Figure2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2027199/2027199_10660904_1658966683400_Figure2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 2"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2027199/2027199_10660904_1658966683400_Figure2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 2"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Changes in urban aerosol fraction from NOAA-20 VIIRS.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Miller, P. W., C. Reesman, M. K. Grossman, S. A. Nelson, V. Liu, and P. Wang, 2021: Marginal warming associated with a COVID-19 quarantine and the implications for disease transmission. Science of The Total Environment, 780, 146579, doi:https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2021.146579.</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Paul&nbsp;W&nbsp;Miller</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 2</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2027199/2027199_10660904_1658966973783_Figure4--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2027199/2027199_10660904_1658966973783_Figure4--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 4"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2027199/2027199_10660904_1658966973783_Figure4--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 4"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 4. Percent difference between (A) BASE minus GPM-observed precipitation and (B) REDUX minus GPM-observed. Precipitation for 28 February - 1 March only from (C) BASE, (D) REDUX, and (E) GPM observed.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Paul Miller</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Paul&nbsp;W&nbsp;Miller</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 4</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2027199/2027199_10660904_1658967060114_Figure5--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2027199/2027199_10660904_1658967060114_Figure5--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 5"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2027199/2027199_10660904_1658967060114_Figure5--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 5"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 5. Air temperature at 2 m (left), maximum reflectivity (center), and WRF-Chem accumulated precipitation (right) from the BASE scenario (top) and the REDUX scenario (bottom) during 0600 UTC on 29 February 2020. The GPM observations are shown to the far right for comparison.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Paul Miller</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Paul&nbsp;W&nbsp;Miller</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 5</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2027199/2027199_10660904_1658967171959_Figure6--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2027199/2027199_10660904_1658967171959_Figure6--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 6"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2027199/2027199_10660904_1658967171959_Figure6--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 6"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Mean wind speed (kt) at 850-hPa on 29 February 2020 for the (A) BASE and (B) REDUX scenarios.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Paul Miller</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Paul&nbsp;W&nbsp;Miller</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 6</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2027199/2027199_10660904_1658966894571_Figure3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2027199/2027199_10660904_1658966894571_Figure3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 3"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2027199/2027199_10660904_1658966894571_Figure3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 3"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 3. Difference in air temperature between REDUX and BASE during the COVID-19 lockdown. Observed C19Q temperature increases from 153 stations in the Global Historical Climatology Network (GHCN) are also plotted.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Miller, P. W., C. Reesman, M. K. Grossman, S. A. Nelson, V. Liu, and P. Wang, 2021: Marginal warming associated with a COVID-19 quarantine and the implications for disease transmission. Science of The Total Environment, 780, 146579, doi:https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2021.146579.</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Paul&nbsp;W&nbsp;Miller</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 3</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Intellectual Merit  Because particulate emissions weaken the intensity of incoming solar radiation, their prompt and dramatic reduction would logically increase surface air temperature. China's COVID-19 quarantine in early 2020 offers a unique opportunity to observe weather patterns as they would otherwise occur without the heavy anthropogenic aerosol contributions that normally characterize the region. This project used (1) temperature and aerosol observations to track the co-evolution of surface warming and pollution reduction during the lockdown, (2) determine the lockdown's role in any observed temperature changes, and (3) examine the cascading effects of surface warming upon atmospheric penomena that may be sensitive to changes in temperature.  A simple comparison of pre-quarantine (PRE) versus during-quarantine (C19Q) satellite-based surface air temperatures anomalies and aerosol concentrations revealed a striking correspondence between the locations of greatest C19Q warming and sharpest aerosol reductions (Figure 1) during the lockdowns.  However, not all particulate changes can be assumed to arise from the lockdown, nor can all temperature increases be reflexively attributed to reduction in particulate levels. Consequently, newly available satellite observations from the Visible Infrared Imaging Radiometer Suite (VIIRS) aboard the NOAA-20 platform was used to infer the reduction in urban-specific aerosol species (Figure 2). During C19Q, the percentage of aerosols associated with urban activity declined from 27.1% of all particulates to 17.5%, a -34.1% decrease. Near Wuhan urban aerosol fraction declined by -38.2%.  The spatial pattern of pollution decreases in Figure 2 was used to initialize an atmospheric modeling experiment composed of two simulations of the Weather Research and Forecasting model coupled with chemistry (WRF-Chem). One simulation contained normal levels of anthropogenic particulate emissions (BASE) and in a second simulation, anthropogenic particulates emissions were adjusted using the percent changes in Figure 2 (REDUX). The WRF-Chem experiment resolved warmer surface temperatures over parts of China that witnessed the most substantial decreases in urban aerosols (Figure 3). For instance, C19Q warming was +0.19?C in Wuhan with temperature increases surrounding Wuhan ranging between +0.2-0.3?C. However, the modeled C19Q increases are only one tenth as large as the PRE vs C19Q warming shown in Figure 1 as well as measured by surface weather stations in China (Figure 3). Thus, while the pollution reductions were contributing factors to the C19Q warming, they were nonetheless secondary to larger-scale synoptic factors (not shown).  Given the small, yet widespread, tenths-of-degree warming arising from the lockdowns, additional analysis engaged changes to other meteorological conditions (e.g., wind, precipitation) that may be sensitive to small temperature shifts. Figure 4 shows the difference in accumulated precipitation between the REDUX and BASE simulations. While both scenarios generally underestimate precipitation domain-wide, they are most distinguished by a corridor of positive precipitation error in the BASE case versus near-zero error in the C19Q scenario over southeast China. This feature largely develops from their differing representations of a rainfall event during 28 February - 1 March 2020. The BASE scenario produces a near-continuous band of heavy southwest-to-northeast oriented precipitation (Figure 4c), whereas the C19Q scenario resolves a smaller pocket of heavy rain and moderate rainfall spread across a larger area (Figure 4d), which aligns more closely with satellite observations from NASA's Global Precipitation Measurement Mission (GPM) (Figure 4e).  The quarantine-driven differences between these two events are shown in Figure 5, where a cold front is stretched across southwest China. By 0600 UTC (2 PM local time) on 29 February 2020, the pre-frontal warm sector of the C19Q scenario responds more strongly to diurnal heating (Figure 5a, d), possibly driven by incoming shortwave radiation more efficiently reaching the surface with fewer particulates. The control simulation erroneously resolves an area of convection near the cold front (Figure 5c) that is not reproduced in the C19Q simulation (Figure 5f) nor the GPM observations (Figure 5g). The simulated radar reflectivities at this time also reveal relatively significant differences in the distribution of convection (Figure 5b, e), especially considering microphysical aerosol effects were not represented in either simulation.  The stronger temperature gradient on 29 February may have also yielded a stronger kinematic profile evident in the 850-hPa wind field. Figure 6 shows that the 850-hPa winds were stronger in the quarantine scenario in the area where the observed precipitation was more accurately resolved. Thus, the aerosol radiative warming may have played an important role influencing the mesoscale circulations that modulate convection initiation and organization such as convergence and low-level wind shear.  Overall, reductions in particulate emissions during China's 2020 COVID-19 lockdown resulted in widespread tenths-of-degree warming during February 2020. Though the temperature increases were minor, they did appear to, at least circumstantially, affect the development of larger weather events such as the heavy rainfall event on 29 February 2020.  Broader Impacts  RAPID projects are not assessed for broader impacts. Regardless, this project partially supported two graduate students, produced one peer-reviewed paper, one publically available dataset, and three conferenence presentations.       Last Modified: 07/27/2022       Submitted by: Paul W Miller]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
