<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research: RAPID: Wastewater Informed Epidemiological Monitoring of SARS-CoV-2]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>45503.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>45503</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Mamadou Diallo</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mdiallo@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924257</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The global COVID-19 pandemic causing considerable human health and economic impacts presents the research community with a unique set of challenges that must be addressed in real time. Critical to managing any pandemic is the accurate estimation of how many people are infected within communities. SARS-CoV-2, the virus causing COVID-19, is excreted in the stool of infected individuals, eventually ending up in the wastewater treatment plant. The presence of SARS-CoV-2 in human waste presents the opportunity to potentially monitor wastewater for SARS-CoV-2 to estimate the number of infections in the community and provide an ‘early warning system’ for future SARS-CoV-2 outbreaks. The goal of this research is to develop methods to monitor for SARS-CoV-2 in wastewater and to connect these measurements to epidemiology models. In addition, the project team will coordinate wastewater monitoring efforts for SARS-CoV-2 globally. If successful, this research could lead to other similar monitoring efforts for other viral outbreaks and protect the health of the Nation. &lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;SARS-CoV-2 (i.e., 2019-nCoV) is identified as the cause of an outbreak of respiratory illness that is now a global  pandemic causing significant disruption to medical services and commerce. Significant uncertainties about the prevalence of this virus remain. This information which is vital to inform control recommendations and determine the case fatality rate. The recent detection of SARS-CoV-2 in stool raises the possibility of using wastewater-based epidemiological approaches to estimate the community prevalence of SARS-CoV-2. In this approach, molecular quantification of SARS-CoV-2 will be combined with epidemiological data to model outbreak dynamics and estimate the overall prevalence of the virus in the community over time. These data will be integrated into epidemiological models using data from public health surveillance. Data from wastewater could inform epidemiological estimates on finer spatial scales than epidemiological data and could provide indications of continued community transmission following the initial wave of the pandemic. The potential for this virus to become a seasonally transmitted endemic pathogen like influenza and other coronaviruses would make this type of analysis increasingly informative. Technical developments resulting from this research include improved sample handling methods, molecular quantification approaches, integration of the resulting data into epidemiological models, as well as coordination with domestic and international collaborators to standardize methodology. There is significant scientific interest in using wastewater to monitor for SARS-CoV-2 beyond the current outbreak. This research will inform such efforts and help respond to future outbreaks.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/21/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/21/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2027758</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Joe</FirstName>
<LastName>Brown</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Joe Brown</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[joebrown@email.unc.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000684110</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/21/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Georgia Tech Research Corporation</Name>
<CityName>ATLANTA</CityName>
<ZipCode>30332</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4048944819</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>926 DALNEY ST NW</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>EMW9FC8J3HN4</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GEORGIA TECH RESEARCH CORPORATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>EMW9FC8J3HN4</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Georgia Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>303320002</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[225 North Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>158Y</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>1N20</Code>
<Name>R&amp;RA CARES Act DEFC N</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>010N2021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[R&RA CARES Act DEFC N]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~45503</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Intellectual Merit. In this project, we aimed to establish SARS-CoV-2 levels in wastewater as a predictor of case data. We sampled from 4 different municipal wastewater treatment plants in the Atlanta metro region over the course of March, 2020 to November, 2020. Influent flows for these plants varied from 13 to 80 millions of gallons per day or 49.2 to 302.8 millions of liters per day. We collected 1 liter of primary influent from each plant, transporting on ice and freezing at -80&deg;C within 2 hours of collection. Following difficulty in maintaining a quantitative approach using polyethylene glycol (PEG) precipitation as our concentration method, we used vacuum filtration through 0.45 &mu;m mixed cellulose esters. Prior to filtering, we dosed each sample with MgCl<sub>2</sub>&nbsp;to a final concentration of 25 mM and Bovine respiratory syncytial virus vaccine as a sample processing control. We filtered between 150 to 200 mL of sample onto duplicate filters, storing the filters at -80&deg;C until DNA/RNA extraction, using the Qiagen AllPrep PowerViral. For analysis, we used Bio-Rad&rsquo;s One-Step RT-ddPCR workflow with the CDC N1 assay. Our data revealed a positive but weak correlation between SARS-CoV-2 RNA loadings and 7-day moving averages of reported cases for the sewershed; the observed associations were less strong than for other, similar studies, for unknown reasons.</p> <p>We built on this model to implement SARS-CoV-2 sampling in residence halls on the Georgia Tech campus, work during fall semster 2020 before taking a hiatus (this monitoring program has since resumed). We established a Moore swab passive sampling technique, again with a goal of establishing a predictive tool. We further found that for residence halls, data on SARS-CoV-2 in wastewater was correlated with clinical case data from testing, but the degree of this association was not strong or consistent.</p> <p>Broader Impacts. We have widely deployed the passive sampling method we piloted in residence hall monitoring in other studies, including an ongoing wastewater analysis project in Maputo, Mozambique.&nbsp;</p> <p>In a final phase of the work, we further examined archived samples preserved at -80C using a variety of concentration and analysis steps, comparing recovery of SARS-CoV-2 RNA, other markers like human mitochondrial DNA, and a wide range of other pathogens. We observed that while SARS-CoV-2 recovery was lower than expected for the time period we captured in these samples, we detected many other important enteric pathogens including <em>Giardia</em>, <em>Shigella</em>, Enterotoxigenic <em>E. coli </em>(ETEC), <em>C. difficile</em>, norovirus, and others. This work was made possible through a multiplex Taqman Array Card (TAC) assay we developed. We conclude that wastewater can and should be considered for monitoring across a broad range of microbial targets using this and similar methods, potentially revealing spatial and temporal dynamics of infections in populations.&nbsp;</p> <p>In addition to insights on passive sampling, concentration methods, and molecular analytical methods, this project supported work by 5 graduate students, providing a mechanism for training junior researchers in applied environmental microbiology during the pandemic. The skills they have developed are useful in a wide range of other work they are now doing and contributing to their development as scientists.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/01/2022<br>      Modified by: Joe&nbsp;Brown</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2027758/2027758_10665436_1648667369504_Picture3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2027758/2027758_10665436_1648667369504_Picture3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Multiplex pathogen data from Atlanta metro region wastewater samples"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2027758/2027758_10665436_1648667369504_Picture3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Multiplex pathogen data from Atlanta metro region wastewater samples"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Log10 concentrations of enteric pathogens per liter of wastewater influent (Atlanta metro region) using the skim milk flocculation method.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Joe Brown</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Joe&nbsp;Brown</div> <div class="imageTitle">Multiplex pathogen data from Atlanta metro region wastewater samples</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2027758/2027758_10665436_1648667159190_Picture1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2027758/2027758_10665436_1648667159190_Picture1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Correlation of SARS-CoV-2 signal with case data, Atlanta metro area"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2027758/2027758_10665436_1648667159190_Picture1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Correlation of SARS-CoV-2 signal with case data, Atlanta metro area"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Log10 loadings of SARS-CoV-2 RNA copies per day for one plant plotted against 7-day moving averages of reported cases for the county. As of 2020, the plant service area population was 606,263.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Joe Brown</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Joe&nbsp;Brown</div> <div class="imageTitle">Correlation of SARS-CoV-2 signal with case data, Atlanta metro area</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2027758/2027758_10665436_1648667258154_Picture2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2027758/2027758_10665436_1648667258154_Picture2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Correlation of SARS-CoV-2 signal with case data, university campus residence halls"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2027758/2027758_10665436_1648667258154_Picture2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Correlation of SARS-CoV-2 signal with case data, university campus residence halls"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Cross correlations of detection of SARS-CoV-2 RNA in wastewater with reported cases of COVID-19 with lag in units of days. Negative lag values (along the x-axis) indicate the wastewater signal is leading the reported cases and positive lag indicates the wastewater signal following the reported cases</div> <div class="imageCredit">Joe Brown</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Joe&nbsp;Brown</div> <div class="imageTitle">Correlation of SARS-CoV-2 signal with case data, university campus residence halls</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2027758/2027758_10665436_1648667523500_Picture4--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2027758/2027758_10665436_1648667523500_Picture4--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Relative concentration of SARS-CoV-2 (N1 gene) in Atlanta metro region wastewater, March 2020 - October 2020"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2027758/2027758_10665436_1648667523500_Picture4--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Relative concentration of SARS-CoV-2 (N1 gene) in Atlanta metro region wastewater, March 2020 - October 2020"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Log10 gene copies of selected molecular targets per liter of wastewater influent (Atlanta metro region) using the Concentrating Pipette (CP) method combined with dPCR. The dashed line represents the limit of detection when calculated as 3 partitions out of the total valid partitions.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Joe Brown</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Joe&nbsp;Brown</div> <div class="imageTitle">Relative concentration of SARS-CoV-2 (N1 gene) in Atlanta metro region wastewater, March 2020 - October 2020</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Intellectual Merit. In this project, we aimed to establish SARS-CoV-2 levels in wastewater as a predictor of case data. We sampled from 4 different municipal wastewater treatment plants in the Atlanta metro region over the course of March, 2020 to November, 2020. Influent flows for these plants varied from 13 to 80 millions of gallons per day or 49.2 to 302.8 millions of liters per day. We collected 1 liter of primary influent from each plant, transporting on ice and freezing at -80&deg;C within 2 hours of collection. Following difficulty in maintaining a quantitative approach using polyethylene glycol (PEG) precipitation as our concentration method, we used vacuum filtration through 0.45 &mu;m mixed cellulose esters. Prior to filtering, we dosed each sample with MgCl2 to a final concentration of 25 mM and Bovine respiratory syncytial virus vaccine as a sample processing control. We filtered between 150 to 200 mL of sample onto duplicate filters, storing the filters at -80&deg;C until DNA/RNA extraction, using the Qiagen AllPrep PowerViral. For analysis, we used Bio-Rad’s One-Step RT-ddPCR workflow with the CDC N1 assay. Our data revealed a positive but weak correlation between SARS-CoV-2 RNA loadings and 7-day moving averages of reported cases for the sewershed; the observed associations were less strong than for other, similar studies, for unknown reasons.  We built on this model to implement SARS-CoV-2 sampling in residence halls on the Georgia Tech campus, work during fall semster 2020 before taking a hiatus (this monitoring program has since resumed). We established a Moore swab passive sampling technique, again with a goal of establishing a predictive tool. We further found that for residence halls, data on SARS-CoV-2 in wastewater was correlated with clinical case data from testing, but the degree of this association was not strong or consistent.  Broader Impacts. We have widely deployed the passive sampling method we piloted in residence hall monitoring in other studies, including an ongoing wastewater analysis project in Maputo, Mozambique.   In a final phase of the work, we further examined archived samples preserved at -80C using a variety of concentration and analysis steps, comparing recovery of SARS-CoV-2 RNA, other markers like human mitochondrial DNA, and a wide range of other pathogens. We observed that while SARS-CoV-2 recovery was lower than expected for the time period we captured in these samples, we detected many other important enteric pathogens including Giardia, Shigella, Enterotoxigenic E. coli (ETEC), C. difficile, norovirus, and others. This work was made possible through a multiplex Taqman Array Card (TAC) assay we developed. We conclude that wastewater can and should be considered for monitoring across a broad range of microbial targets using this and similar methods, potentially revealing spatial and temporal dynamics of infections in populations.   In addition to insights on passive sampling, concentration methods, and molecular analytical methods, this project supported work by 5 graduate students, providing a mechanism for training junior researchers in applied environmental microbiology during the pandemic. The skills they have developed are useful in a wide range of other work they are now doing and contributing to their development as scientists.           Last Modified: 04/01/2022       Submitted by: Joe Brown]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
