<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Symposium on Undergraduate Research - 2020]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>10000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>10000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>John D. Gillaspy</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jgillasp@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927173</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This award provides travel support for undergraduate student participation in the Symposium on Undergraduate Research. This Symposium will be held at the annual meeting of the American Physical Society Division of Laser Science (DLS), in conjunction with the annual Frontiers in Optics (FiO) meeting of the Optical Society of America. The conference program includes many of the research topics central to Atomic, Molecular, and Optical Physics. The support of students through this award makes a substantial contribution to the education and training of future scientists. Students who graduate with a background in laser science acquire a broad range of knowledge and skills that enable them to contribute to progress in many areas of science and technology. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The meeting is scheduled to be held Washington DC on September 14, 2020. It offers an opportunity for undergraduate students to present their research results and to interact with senior scientists primarily from the United States, but also the broader international community. Support is provided only for US students (students enrolled in US universities).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/21/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/21/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2027733</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Harold</FirstName>
<LastName>Metcalf</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Harold Metcalf</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[harold.metcalf@stonybrook.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000105073</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/21/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>SUNY at Stony Brook</Name>
<CityName>STONY BROOK</CityName>
<ZipCode>117940001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6316329949</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>W5510 FRANKS MELVILLE MEMORIAL L</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>M746VC6XMNH9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>THE RESEARCH FOUNDATION FOR THE STATE UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Marriott Wardman Hotel]]></Name>
<CityName>Washington DC</CityName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>200080001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2660 Woodley Rd   NW]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1241</Code>
<Text>AMO Experiment/Atomic, Molecul</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1284</Code>
<Text>AMO Theory/Atomic, Molecular &amp;</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~10000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The twenty-second annual DLS Symposium on Undergraduate Research at LS-XXXVIII was held on Monday, 17 October, 2022. The meeting was held in person for the first time since 2019, and the schedule was similar to those of previous in person meetings.&nbsp; It was quite different from previous years because it was in the huge Lilac Ballroom of the Rochester Riverside Convention Center instead of the smaller rooms in the Highland suites.&nbsp; Even though&nbsp;&nbsp; there was no preceding plenary session as there usually has been, the schedule was pretty similar.&nbsp;&nbsp; All the technical details, as well as management of our sessions, were again handled by the Optica (formerly OSA) meetings department, and everything worked out with no major snags or glitches, even though there were several personnel changes.&nbsp;</p> <p>Our Symposium events began at noon with a very special event.&nbsp; Optica was launching a new program called ?Amplify Optics Immersion? that seeks to bring together Black physics and engineering undergraduate or graduate students to explore the research and career opportunities within optics and photonics at our annual meeting. It was run by Marcia Lesky from Optica and she suggested that there is common ground between that program and our symposium.&nbsp; After considering several ways to join the groups, it was decided to bring them together at lunch on Monday, 17 October.&nbsp;</p> <p>It was a buffet lunch in the Lilac Ballroom, and it was a big success.&nbsp; The students mixed up their tables and even met with a delegation from Nigeria as well as many different states. &nbsp;There were plenty of sandwiches and fruits, and everything was fresh. The students were addressed by Marcia Lesky and also by Prof.&nbsp;Jennifer Kruschwitz who runs the Masters program at the Institute of Optics, along with several others. They had extended, lively conversations among themselves and we?re confident that many useful connections were formed.&nbsp; We were introduced to Sarah Moore from Optica who also joined us for dinner that evening.&nbsp;</p> <p>The scientific events began with the poster session, also in the Lilac Ballroom.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>It was gratifying that these very young scientists could give their first presentations at a professional meeting, and it was clearly a memorable event for them. Eighteen of this year's presenters were female, an impressive representation of 33 %.&nbsp; Many of the students remained at the meeting one or more extra days to hear talks or visit exhibits. Some were thrilled to meet famous and/or highly visible scientists, including the authors of some of their textbooks.&nbsp; Judging from the enthusiastic notes that accompanied their final expense reports, the student participants will surely remember this opportunity throughout their professional lives.&nbsp;&nbsp; Some of the comments were:</p> <ul> <li>?.the greatest benefit for me was to get some practice presenting my work in person in front of an audience of students and professionals&nbsp;close to my particular area of interest. It was also great to get to meet some physicists from industry and academia at the conference in general, and I met some people&nbsp;I'll definitely be contacting in the future about internships or opportunities. I also met a lot of students that I'm guessing I'll run into over and over for at least the next few years, so it was great to get to know some of them. </li> <li>I truly enjoyed meeting different people there, from professionals to all the other great students that went?especially the latter. I thought that everyone was super nice and open to meeting others. </li> <li>I thoroughly enjoyed&nbsp;the split between poster and oral presentations, as I was able to follow both without either dragging on for too long. I think we should encourage as many students as possible to attend, as this will only allow us to meet more people and get a feel for the work going on at even more Universities. </li> <li>Thank you all so much for yet another Symposium. The two undergraduates I helped attend had a marvelous time.&nbsp;And&nbsp;combining with another student group sounds like it was extra fun!&nbsp;This event means the world to me and it's incredible how many young scientists it has impacted. Thank you all for making it happen!!&nbsp;</li> <li>On a professional level I got to meet professors from schools whose graduate&nbsp;programs I am applying to and discuss my research with academics that&nbsp;were interested in my work. I really enjoyed it (poster session) as I got to explain on a more personal level what my research was about and answer more questions in comparison to a talk. Also, I am glad I got to talk for the whole two hours and&nbsp;there&nbsp;were no moments of just standing there! </li> </ul> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/12/2023<br>      Modified by: Harold&nbsp;Metcalf</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2027733/2027733_10672243_1686595588882_OSA-3231-cropped--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2027733/2027733_10672243_1686595588882_OSA-3231-cropped--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Group photo"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2027733/2027733_10672243_1686595588882_OSA-3231-cropped--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Group photo"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Participating Students</div> <div class="imageCredit">Optica</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Harold&nbsp;Metcalf</div> <div class="imageTitle">Group photo</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The twenty-second annual DLS Symposium on Undergraduate Research at LS-XXXVIII was held on Monday, 17 October, 2022. The meeting was held in person for the first time since 2019, and the schedule was similar to those of previous in person meetings.  It was quite different from previous years because it was in the huge Lilac Ballroom of the Rochester Riverside Convention Center instead of the smaller rooms in the Highland suites.  Even though   there was no preceding plenary session as there usually has been, the schedule was pretty similar.   All the technical details, as well as management of our sessions, were again handled by the Optica (formerly OSA) meetings department, and everything worked out with no major snags or glitches, even though there were several personnel changes.   Our Symposium events began at noon with a very special event.  Optica was launching a new program called ?Amplify Optics Immersion? that seeks to bring together Black physics and engineering undergraduate or graduate students to explore the research and career opportunities within optics and photonics at our annual meeting. It was run by Marcia Lesky from Optica and she suggested that there is common ground between that program and our symposium.  After considering several ways to join the groups, it was decided to bring them together at lunch on Monday, 17 October.   It was a buffet lunch in the Lilac Ballroom, and it was a big success.  The students mixed up their tables and even met with a delegation from Nigeria as well as many different states.  There were plenty of sandwiches and fruits, and everything was fresh. The students were addressed by Marcia Lesky and also by Prof. Jennifer Kruschwitz who runs the Masters program at the Institute of Optics, along with several others. They had extended, lively conversations among themselves and we?re confident that many useful connections were formed.  We were introduced to Sarah Moore from Optica who also joined us for dinner that evening.   The scientific events began with the poster session, also in the Lilac Ballroom.                                 It was gratifying that these very young scientists could give their first presentations at a professional meeting, and it was clearly a memorable event for them. Eighteen of this year's presenters were female, an impressive representation of 33 %.  Many of the students remained at the meeting one or more extra days to hear talks or visit exhibits. Some were thrilled to meet famous and/or highly visible scientists, including the authors of some of their textbooks.  Judging from the enthusiastic notes that accompanied their final expense reports, the student participants will surely remember this opportunity throughout their professional lives.   Some of the comments were:  ?.the greatest benefit for me was to get some practice presenting my work in person in front of an audience of students and professionals close to my particular area of interest. It was also great to get to meet some physicists from industry and academia at the conference in general, and I met some people I'll definitely be contacting in the future about internships or opportunities. I also met a lot of students that I'm guessing I'll run into over and over for at least the next few years, so it was great to get to know some of them.  I truly enjoyed meeting different people there, from professionals to all the other great students that went?especially the latter. I thought that everyone was super nice and open to meeting others.  I thoroughly enjoyed the split between poster and oral presentations, as I was able to follow both without either dragging on for too long. I think we should encourage as many students as possible to attend, as this will only allow us to meet more people and get a feel for the work going on at even more Universities.  Thank you all so much for yet another Symposium. The two undergraduates I helped attend had a marvelous time. And combining with another student group sounds like it was extra fun! This event means the world to me and it's incredible how many young scientists it has impacted. Thank you all for making it happen!!  On a professional level I got to meet professors from schools whose graduate programs I am applying to and discuss my research with academics that were interested in my work. I really enjoyed it (poster session) as I got to explain on a more personal level what my research was about and answer more questions in comparison to a talk. Also, I am glad I got to talk for the whole two hours and there were no moments of just standing there!               Last Modified: 06/12/2023       Submitted by: Harold Metcalf]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
