<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Plasmonically-enhanced Detection of Corona Virus Disease (COVID-19)]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>100008.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>100008</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Aleksandr Simonian</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>asimonia@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922191</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID-19) is a highly contagious, pandemic disease that has rapidly spread to several hundred thousand people worldwide and caused many deaths. To facilitate the surveillance and control of the spread of the virus, Prof. Singamaneni of Washington University at St. Louis aims to develop a rapid and low-cost diagnostic method that can detect infection in individuals that are asymptomatic or exhibiting mild symptoms.  The sensitive biosensing method is designed to rapidly assess the immune response to the coronavirus across a large population in a high-throughput manner and to enable understanding of the epidemiology of the highly contagious disease. The novel biosensor is suitable for point-of-care and resource-limited settings and can be easily adapted to a broad range of public health threats. This research project provides opportunities to graduate students to be trained in sensor design and the study of sensor performance. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The aim of this project is to design and realize a dual-modal lateral flow assay for highly sensitive and specific detection of IgG and IgM antibodies to coronavirus (SARS-CoV-2) using plasmon-enhanced fluorescence.  Specifically, the dual-modal lateral flow assay relies on plasmonic-fluor, an ultrabright fluorescent nanostructure, to achieve high sensitivity and low detection limit. In addition to ultrabright fluorescence signal, plasmonic-fluors exhibit large absorption and scattering cross-section, making them attractive labels that can be directly visualized by naked eye at high target concentrations.  This dual-modal lateral flow assay enables simultaneous detection of relatively high concentrations of the antibodies as a simple colorimetric signal and low concentrations of the antibodies through highly sensitive fluorescence signal.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/07/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/07/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2027145</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Srikanth</FirstName>
<LastName>Singamaneni</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Srikanth Singamaneni</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[singamaneni@seas.wustl.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000573646</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/07/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Washington University</Name>
<CityName>SAINT LOUIS</CityName>
<ZipCode>63110</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3147474134</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>ONE BROOKINGS DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MO01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>L6NFUM28LQM5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WASHINGTON UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Washington University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>631304862</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MO01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1642</Code>
<Text>Special Initiatives</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7909</Code>
<Text>BIOSENS-Biosensing</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~100008</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The COVID-19 pandemic highlights the need for improved lateral flow assays (LFAs) for precise and rapid clinical diagnoses, mass screenings and epidemiological studies. &nbsp;Real-time reverse transcription polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR) and direct antigen tests have been the mainstay for diagnosis of COVID-19, and serological assays are important for determination of infection stage and vaccine efficacy, and epidemiological studies. These diagnostic platforms are available only in qualified microbiology laboratories and remain expert-dependent, labor-intensive, and time-intensive, limitations that have precluded conduction of the millions of tests per day needed during epidemiological surges. In this project, we demonstrated plasmonic-fluors as a bimodal (colorimetric+fluorescent) reporter element for overcoming long-standing limitations of lateral flow assays: limited sensitivity, low accuracy and small dynamic range compared to laboratory tests, and limited quantitation ability. Plasmonic-fluors produced a discernable fluorescence signal at densities 10000-fold lower than those needed in conventional colorimetric Au nanoparticles (<strong>Figure 1</strong>). Plasmon-enhanced LFAs (p-LFAs) for various analytes (SARS-CoV-2 S1 antibodies, and SARS-CoV-2 antigen) exhibited ~1000-fold improvement in bioanalytical parameters (LOD, LOQ and dynamic range) compared to conventional LFAs with Au nanoparticles as colorimetric nanolabels (<strong>Figure 2</strong>). p-LFAs offered standard-free quantitative detection and the sensitivity of gold standard ELISA, but with a much lower sample-to-answer time (20 min versus 4-6 hours). p-LFAs for detection of SARS-CoV-2 antibodies and antigens present in plasma and nasopharyngeal swab samples, respectively, achieved &gt;95% sensitivity and 100% specificity, demonstrating its clinical applicability.</p> <p>Conventional single-plex serology assays employ pristine SARS-CoV-2 spike (S) protein, the receptor binding domain (RBD) of the spike protein or nucleocapsid (N) protein as recognition elements (<em>i.e.</em> as antigen baits) to capture target antibodies. Despite its simplicity and low cost, conventional serological tests only provide coarse information about viral exposure history, infection stage and are variable in predicting neutralizing activity. This limitation primarily stems from the use of whole proteins or even regions of proteins such as the 223 amino acid RBD or the 301 amino acid N-terminal domain (NTD) of the S protein as baits, where the results only demonstrate overall antibody reaction, which are prone to interference from other coronaviruses owing to the cross reactivity and lack details about informative antibody subclass. &nbsp;Detection and quantification of antibodies that bind to specific epitopes within a whole protein or a domain requires highly sensitive detection modalities. With deeper understanding of humoral response, recent studies have discovered that antibodies towards different epitopes may exhibit polarized functions, while part of them will neutralize the interactions between virus and host cells, others may inversely exacerbate patient outcome due to the antibody-dependent enhancement (ADE) effect, correlating with the severity of COVID-19. In this project, we have demonstrated an ultrasensitive SARS-CoV-2 epitope-specific serological test in a spatially-multiplexed manner through plasmonically-enhanced fluoroimmunoassay.&nbsp; Plasmonic-fluor, serving as the ultrabright fluorescence reporter, significantly improved the detection sensitivity compared to conventional fluorophores and enzyme-driven colorimetric assay.&nbsp; Specifically, the LOD of the antibody p-FLISA for SARS-CoV-2 is nearly 100-fold better compared to ELISA, completed in 20 minutes (<strong>Figure 3</strong>).&nbsp; The ultrasensitive detection of various antibody isotypes and epitope-specific antibodies provides more insightful and detailed information about the immune response after infection.&nbsp;</p> <p>We believe p-LFAs are highly attractive for point-of-care settings with better accuracy than conventional colorimetric LFAs, and with faster sample-to-answer time and lower cost than molecular tests. The platform technology demonstrated here can be readily adapted for the detection of other infectious pathogens and disease biomarkers, and can be employed as an alternative to laboratory-based test for the diagnosis of clinically relevant pathogenic infections and possible future pandemics. &nbsp;Owing to its high sensitivity and specificity, plasmonically-enhanced epitope specific serology assay demonstrated here will be highly attractive to determine the ability of vaccines to cover potential immune epitopes, duration of the immunity, and epidemiological investigation of symptomatic patients and discover asymptomatic individuals. The ultrasensitive serology platform developed in this project can be easily adapted to other infectious diseases by simply replacing the biodetection elements.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/17/2022<br>      Modified by: Srikanth&nbsp;Singamaneni</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2027145/2027145_10663217_1642458591309_Figure1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2027145/2027145_10663217_1642458591309_Figure1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Plasmonic-fluor vs. gold nanoparticle as nanolabels"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2027145/2027145_10663217_1642458591309_Figure1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Plasmonic-fluor vs. gold nanoparticle as nanolabels"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 1: (A) Schematic illustration of plasmonic-fluor. (B) Mean grey value obtained from nitrocellulose membrane drop-casted with different concentrations of AuNPs. (C) Fluorescence intensity obtained from nitrocellulose membrane drop-casted with different concentrations of plasmonic-fluors.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Rohit Gupta</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Srikanth&nbsp;Singamaneni</div> <div class="imageTitle">Plasmonic-fluor vs. gold nanoparticle as nanolabels</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2027145/2027145_10663217_1642458658577_Figure2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2027145/2027145_10663217_1642458658577_Figure2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Detection of SARS-CoV-2 antibodies"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2027145/2027145_10663217_1642458658577_Figure2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Detection of SARS-CoV-2 antibodies"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 2: (A) Schematic illustration of the SARS-CoV-2 S1 antibody LFA strips. Schematic illustration of (B) AuNP-based SARS-CoV-2 S1 antibody LFA and (C) p-LFA. Dose-dependent response of (D) conventional LFA and (E) p-LFA.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Rohit Gupta</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Srikanth&nbsp;Singamaneni</div> <div class="imageTitle">Detection of SARS-CoV-2 antibodies</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2027145/2027145_10663217_1642458739380_Figure3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2027145/2027145_10663217_1642458739380_Figure3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="ELISA vs. p-FLISA for SARS-CoV-2 antibody detection"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2027145/2027145_10663217_1642458739380_Figure3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="ELISA vs. p-FLISA for SARS-CoV-2 antibody detection"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 3: Dose-dependent fluorescence intensity anti SARS-CoV-2 Nucleocapsid (N) protein IgG on microtiter plate by conventional ELISA (black dots) and p-FLISA (red dots) performed in 20 minutes. Bottom image: Fluorescence intensity maps at various analytes concentration.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Zheyu Wang</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Srikanth&nbsp;Singamaneni</div> <div class="imageTitle">ELISA vs. p-FLISA for SARS-CoV-2 antibody detection</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The COVID-19 pandemic highlights the need for improved lateral flow assays (LFAs) for precise and rapid clinical diagnoses, mass screenings and epidemiological studies.  Real-time reverse transcription polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR) and direct antigen tests have been the mainstay for diagnosis of COVID-19, and serological assays are important for determination of infection stage and vaccine efficacy, and epidemiological studies. These diagnostic platforms are available only in qualified microbiology laboratories and remain expert-dependent, labor-intensive, and time-intensive, limitations that have precluded conduction of the millions of tests per day needed during epidemiological surges. In this project, we demonstrated plasmonic-fluors as a bimodal (colorimetric+fluorescent) reporter element for overcoming long-standing limitations of lateral flow assays: limited sensitivity, low accuracy and small dynamic range compared to laboratory tests, and limited quantitation ability. Plasmonic-fluors produced a discernable fluorescence signal at densities 10000-fold lower than those needed in conventional colorimetric Au nanoparticles (Figure 1). Plasmon-enhanced LFAs (p-LFAs) for various analytes (SARS-CoV-2 S1 antibodies, and SARS-CoV-2 antigen) exhibited ~1000-fold improvement in bioanalytical parameters (LOD, LOQ and dynamic range) compared to conventional LFAs with Au nanoparticles as colorimetric nanolabels (Figure 2). p-LFAs offered standard-free quantitative detection and the sensitivity of gold standard ELISA, but with a much lower sample-to-answer time (20 min versus 4-6 hours). p-LFAs for detection of SARS-CoV-2 antibodies and antigens present in plasma and nasopharyngeal swab samples, respectively, achieved &gt;95% sensitivity and 100% specificity, demonstrating its clinical applicability.  Conventional single-plex serology assays employ pristine SARS-CoV-2 spike (S) protein, the receptor binding domain (RBD) of the spike protein or nucleocapsid (N) protein as recognition elements (i.e. as antigen baits) to capture target antibodies. Despite its simplicity and low cost, conventional serological tests only provide coarse information about viral exposure history, infection stage and are variable in predicting neutralizing activity. This limitation primarily stems from the use of whole proteins or even regions of proteins such as the 223 amino acid RBD or the 301 amino acid N-terminal domain (NTD) of the S protein as baits, where the results only demonstrate overall antibody reaction, which are prone to interference from other coronaviruses owing to the cross reactivity and lack details about informative antibody subclass.  Detection and quantification of antibodies that bind to specific epitopes within a whole protein or a domain requires highly sensitive detection modalities. With deeper understanding of humoral response, recent studies have discovered that antibodies towards different epitopes may exhibit polarized functions, while part of them will neutralize the interactions between virus and host cells, others may inversely exacerbate patient outcome due to the antibody-dependent enhancement (ADE) effect, correlating with the severity of COVID-19. In this project, we have demonstrated an ultrasensitive SARS-CoV-2 epitope-specific serological test in a spatially-multiplexed manner through plasmonically-enhanced fluoroimmunoassay.  Plasmonic-fluor, serving as the ultrabright fluorescence reporter, significantly improved the detection sensitivity compared to conventional fluorophores and enzyme-driven colorimetric assay.  Specifically, the LOD of the antibody p-FLISA for SARS-CoV-2 is nearly 100-fold better compared to ELISA, completed in 20 minutes (Figure 3).  The ultrasensitive detection of various antibody isotypes and epitope-specific antibodies provides more insightful and detailed information about the immune response after infection.   We believe p-LFAs are highly attractive for point-of-care settings with better accuracy than conventional colorimetric LFAs, and with faster sample-to-answer time and lower cost than molecular tests. The platform technology demonstrated here can be readily adapted for the detection of other infectious pathogens and disease biomarkers, and can be employed as an alternative to laboratory-based test for the diagnosis of clinically relevant pathogenic infections and possible future pandemics.  Owing to its high sensitivity and specificity, plasmonically-enhanced epitope specific serology assay demonstrated here will be highly attractive to determine the ability of vaccines to cover potential immune epitopes, duration of the immunity, and epidemiological investigation of symptomatic patients and discover asymptomatic individuals. The ultrasensitive serology platform developed in this project can be easily adapted to other infectious diseases by simply replacing the biodetection elements.       Last Modified: 01/17/2022       Submitted by: Srikanth Singamaneni]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
