<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[TCU Cyberinfrastructure Partnership Meeting]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>99547.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>99547</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div. of Equity for Excellence in STEM</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jody Chase</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lchase@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925173</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[A goal of the Tribal Colleges and Universities Program (TCUP) is to increase the science, technology, engineering and mathematics (STEM) instructional and research capacities of specific institutions of higher education that serve the Nation's indigenous students. Expanding the research capacity at these institutions expands the opportunities for students to pursue challenging, rewarding careers in STEM fields, provides for research studies in areas that may be locally relevant, and encourages a faculty community to look beyond the traditional classroom for intellectual and professional growth. This project aligns directly with that goal, and moreover will increase the efficacy of partnerships between TCUP institutions and their mainstream university or private sector partners.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The American Indian Higher Education Consortium (AIHEC) will organize and convene a group of TCU STEM research and education stakeholders and national CI program representatives for a 2-day meeting hosted by the Texas Advanced Computing Center (TACC). The meeting will provide opportunities for participants to share and explore leading practices and innovative approaches to developing and sustaining research and education partnerships employing national CI resources. The aim is to foster the collaboration needed to support and strengthen TCU STEM research and education programs. A primary purpose of the meeting is to form a TCU Cyberinfrastructure Working group to advance CI capabilities among the schools through cross-TCU partnerships and also partnerships with leading members of the national CI Ecosystem.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/04/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/27/2023</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2027898</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Bottum</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>James R Bottum</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jb@clemson.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000151698</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/06/2022</StartDate>
<EndDate>06/12/2023</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Carrie</FirstName>
<LastName>Billy</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Carrie L Billy</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[cbilly@aihec.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000422727</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/12/2023</StartDate>
<EndDate>10/27/2023</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Carrie</FirstName>
<LastName>Billy</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Carrie L Billy</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[cbilly@aihec.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000422727</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/11/2022</StartDate>
<EndDate>09/06/2022</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Carrie</FirstName>
<LastName>Billy</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Carrie L Billy</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[cbilly@aihec.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000422727</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/06/2022</StartDate>
<EndDate>06/12/2023</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gwendolyn</FirstName>
<LastName>Huntoon</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gwendolyn L Huntoon</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ghuntoon@aihec.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000937352</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>10/27/2023</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Algirdas</FirstName>
<LastName>Kuslikis</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Algirdas S Kuslikis</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[akuslikis@aihec.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000329454</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/04/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate>05/11/2022</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>American Indian Higher Education Consortium</Name>
<CityName>ALEXANDRIA</CityName>
<ZipCode>223142015</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7038380400</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>121 ORONOCO ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>VA08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>EGTJJJPLRT11</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>AMERICAN INDIAN HIGHER EDUCATION CONSORTIUM</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>EGTJJJPLRT11</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[American Indian Higher Education Consortium]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>223142015</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>VA08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1744</Code>
<Text>Tribal College &amp; Univers Prog</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0420</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~99547</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="Default">a) Internet 2: While the relationship between AIHEC and Internet2 was developing prior to the meeting, the discussions helped to facilitate progress to a broader initiative to engage TCUs and other MSIs in CI-enabled research.</p> <p class="Default">b) University of Wisconsin/HTCondor: AIHEC and HTCondor staff partnered to provide TCU faculty and students access to GIS software and computing resources to offer courses and conduct geospatial research without relying on on-campus computing resources. Southwestern Indian Polytechnic Institute (SIPI) is the primary partner in the current stage.</p> <p class="Default">c) TCU Cybersecurity Community of Practice. The AIHEC Cyberinfrastructure (CI) Team organized a Cybersecurity COP with an initial focus on remediation from ransomware attacks and basic cybersecurity assessments.</p> <p class="Default">d) The meeting spun off working groups of TCU faculty in STEM education and climate change &amp; resiliency.</p> <p class="Default">e) Sovereign Data Network.&nbsp; UCAR developed a partnership with Navajo Technical University, Southwestern Indian Polytechnic Institute and Tohono O&rsquo;odham Community College focusing on establishing the Sovereign Data Network, a secure federated data center to support data management needs that incorporate data sovereignty protocols.&nbsp; AIHEC worked with this group to support scaling the network to all interested TCUs.</p> <p class="Default">f) Environmental data science (EDS) working group.&nbsp; A group of approximately 18 TCU faculty members have been organized into the EDS working group, comprising faculty interested in participating in environmental data science research and in supplementing their environmental science academic programs with data science courses and applications. They met on a monthly basis. The EDS working group developed plans for putting on data science workshops for TCU students, and creating a data science course series that would be shared with all TCUs.</p> <p class="Default">g) AIM-AHEAD. AIHEC worked with the NIH-funded AIM AHEAD program to engage TCUs in health sciences-focused artificial intelligence/machine learning education and research programming. The project involved the development of AI/ML courses involving applications relevant to AIAN health issues, internship opportunities for TCU students, and a TCU faculty development program.</p> <p class="Default">h) CyVerse: Open Science Workspace for Collaborative Data-driven Discovery. AIHEC and several TCUs, explored access to Cyverse data and compute resources to develop TCU environmental data science capacity.</p> <p class="Default">AIHEC worked with ESIIL, NEON, CyVerse, to establish a common data infrastructure to support research that addresses Tribal priorities involving environmental, health, economic and agricultural application areas. This infrastructure provided a foundation for activities under all of the partnerships that have been facilitated under this project.</p> <p class="Default">&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/27/2023<br>      Modified by: Gwendolyn&nbsp;L&nbsp;Huntoon</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[a) Internet 2: While the relationship between AIHEC and Internet2 was developing prior to the meeting, the discussions helped to facilitate progress to a broader initiative to engage TCUs and other MSIs in CI-enabled research. b) University of Wisconsin/HTCondor: AIHEC and HTCondor staff partnered to provide TCU faculty and students access to GIS software and computing resources to offer courses and conduct geospatial research without relying on on-campus computing resources. Southwestern Indian Polytechnic Institute (SIPI) is the primary partner in the current stage. c) TCU Cybersecurity Community of Practice. The AIHEC Cyberinfrastructure (CI) Team organized a Cybersecurity COP with an initial focus on remediation from ransomware attacks and basic cybersecurity assessments. d) The meeting spun off working groups of TCU faculty in STEM education and climate change &amp; resiliency. e) Sovereign Data Network.  UCAR developed a partnership with Navajo Technical University, Southwestern Indian Polytechnic Institute and Tohono O’odham Community College focusing on establishing the Sovereign Data Network, a secure federated data center to support data management needs that incorporate data sovereignty protocols.  AIHEC worked with this group to support scaling the network to all interested TCUs. f) Environmental data science (EDS) working group.  A group of approximately 18 TCU faculty members have been organized into the EDS working group, comprising faculty interested in participating in environmental data science research and in supplementing their environmental science academic programs with data science courses and applications. They met on a monthly basis. The EDS working group developed plans for putting on data science workshops for TCU students, and creating a data science course series that would be shared with all TCUs. g) AIM-AHEAD. AIHEC worked with the NIH-funded AIM AHEAD program to engage TCUs in health sciences-focused artificial intelligence/machine learning education and research programming. The project involved the development of AI/ML courses involving applications relevant to AIAN health issues, internship opportunities for TCU students, and a TCU faculty development program. h) CyVerse: Open Science Workspace for Collaborative Data-driven Discovery. AIHEC and several TCUs, explored access to Cyverse data and compute resources to develop TCU environmental data science capacity. AIHEC worked with ESIIL, NEON, CyVerse, to establish a common data infrastructure to support research that addresses Tribal priorities involving environmental, health, economic and agricultural application areas. This infrastructure provided a foundation for activities under all of the partnerships that have been facilitated under this project.         Last Modified: 10/27/2023       Submitted by: Gwendolyn L Huntoon]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
