<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Rapidly building a collaborative network of informal educators to address extended school closures related to the 2020 COVID-19 pandemic]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>199416.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>199416</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DRL</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Toni Dancstep</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tdancste@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927922</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This RAPID award is made by the AISL program in the Division of Research on Learning in the Directorate for Education and Human Resources, using funds from the Coronavirus Aid, Relief, and Economic Security (CARES) Act. COVID-19 presents a national threat to the health of children and families, presenting serious implications for the mental and physical health of children. This project addresses two critical aspects of the impact on COVID-19 on families: (a) the large-scale shift to at-home learning based on nationwide school closures and (b) the critical need for families to understand the basic science of virus transmission and prevention. To address these needs, the project team will develop a series of STEM activities for families with children in grades K-6 that make use of items readily available in most households. The activities help children and their families learn about viruses, virus transmission, and virus prevention while also developing other STEM-skills, particularly related to engineering design. Importantly, the project team also considers the emotional well-being of children and families during the disruption of the COVID-19 pandemic. Led by researchers from Indiana University and Binghamton University, and experts in educational resource development from Science Friday (a non-profit organization dedicated to increasing the public’s access to science and scientific information through podcasts, digital videos, original web articles, and educational resources for teachers and informal educators) the project is further supported by partnerships with the New York Hall of Science, Amazeum (AR), the Gulf of Maine Research Institute (ME), The Tech Museum of Innovation (CA), the Indiana State Museum, and Kopernik Observatory Science Center (NY). The activities will be shared with families through live-streamed web sessions that introduce the activity, give tips to adults for facilitation, share a bit on related STEM careers and engage the audience in dialog about the activity and their current experiences. Versions of the sessions that are recorded will be edited and include closed-captioning and subtitles in multiple languages before being posted on platforms such as YouTube. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project uses a design-based research approach to investigate strategies for enabling families to actively engage with STEM while home and away from their traditional institutions during a period of crisis.   The research components focus on: 1) Engagement: How do families engage in the activity tasks, in terms of processes, practices, and use of resources? Who participated, why did they choose to participate and how did they engage (including modification of activities)? What barriers prevented interested families from completing activities?   2) Impact: How did the activities change participants’ feelings of: a) efficacy around STEM and b) connectedness/ isolation, during extended school closures? and 3) the Activities: Which activities had the greatest uptake? How many activity ideas were submitted by those outside of the team? What was the age/content focus of each of these activities? The researchers will analyze social media data (including data on resource downloads and use of tracked links, YouTube and Facebook views, comment threads during livestreams and Likes/Shares/Follows across social media sites) to refine and improve the activities and programming as well as learn about the ways families are engaging in the activities. The researchers will solicit survey responses from website visitors to gather more information on participants, why they participated, how they engaged and how the activities impacted participants’ efficacy around STEM and their feelings of connectedness or isolation. The researchers will also ask participants to submit images, videos and text that describes what they are making and their process along the way. Analysis of this data would lead to insights on how children and families use STEM language and practices; how children and families ask questions and use COVID-19-related and other information as part of their design work; and how ideas are formed, shaped and refined as families engage in design and making. While the project focuses on a unique opportunity to collect data on family STEM engagement as families respond to disruptions from the COVID-19 pandemic, this project and its findings will provide a knowledge base that can be utilized to inform future responses to national emergencies, other work aimed at promoting family learning at home, and approaches to supporting children in open-ended problem solving.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/29/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/29/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2027368</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Adam</FirstName>
<LastName>Maltese</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>V</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Adam V Maltese</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[amaltese@indiana.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000533075</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/29/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ariel</FirstName>
<LastName>Zych</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ariel Zych</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[azych@sciencefriday.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000674051</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/29/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Amber</FirstName>
<LastName>Simpson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Amber M Simpson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[asimpson@binghamton.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000710083</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/29/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Indiana University</Name>
<CityName>BLOOMINGTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>474057000</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3172783473</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>107 S INDIANA AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IN09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>YH86RTW2YVJ4</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF INDIANA UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>YH86RTW2YVJ4</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Indiana University]]></Name>
<CityName>Bloomington</CityName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>474051005</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[201 N. Rose Ave.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IN09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7259</Code>
<Text>AISL</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>4N20</Code>
<Name>EHR CARES Act DEFC N</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>040N2021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[EHR CARES Act DEFC N]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~199416</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>In early March 2019 we sensed that the pandemic would close schools for at least a few weeks and that caregivers would be left trying to figure out how to fill the days. To address this need and opportunity, we gathered a team of educators with expertise in making and STEM education. We planned to create and share activity ideas with caregivers through an associated Facebook group (CoBuild19), which we started on March 13. Membership in the group grew rapidly and leveled off at approximately 5000 members by June 2020. Members are primarily from the United States, Mexico, India, UK and Japan. In the US, members most commonly hail from Indiana, California and Iowa. Facebook reports that 86% of the group members are female and over 40% of the group falls in the 35-44 age range.&nbsp;From March through June 2020, we produced and shared videos and activity guides, averaging a handful of new activities per week. Generally, each activity (~60) we created involved a video and/or a user sheet. These resources were meant to be more like an activity starter than they were intended to be a complete lesson plan and guide.</span></p> <p><span>The research aim of the project was to investigate strategies for enabling families to actively engage with STEM while at home during the pandemic. Our plan was to collect and analyze social media data to refine and improve the activities and programming and learn about the ways families engaged in the activities. We soon found that our videos got many views, &ldquo;Likes&rdquo; and other positive metrics. To date, 23 of our videos have more than 1000 views, with the highest garnering 23K+ views. However, we received very few submissions of videos, images, or text about what families were creating. There was some participation and contributions by members of the group when we started out but as the group grew in size, substantive evidence of participation, in the form of posted pictures of kids&rsquo; projects, comments and questions from the participants, faded. We polled members of the Facebook group about their use of the activities. The responses (n=101) were dominated by the option "<em><span>We are glad to know the ideas are available, but we are not using much</span></em>" (49%), followed by "<em><span>We occasionally do activities</span></em>" (35%). With this happening, we had no data about home participation, so we decided to experiment with different approaches.</span></p> <p><span>By late May 2020 we also realized we could not sustain the pace of producing five activities each week. We decided to shift our focus and try new strategies. Once we finished the original planned content, we focused efforts on conducting virtual maker/STEM camps where we hoped for greater participation. One approach was to reformat the content produced in the first few months of CoBuild19 for camps. Another approach was to create a club/camp that focused on coding. Finally, we also held open challenges to get input from youth related to making and about their experiences during the pandemic.</span></p> <p><span>Related to both intellectual merit and broader impacts, we think there are a few relevant outcomes beyond the artifacts of materials we created.</span></p> <p><span>First, we found that general participation patterns emerged. When we initially announced an activity like a camp, there was often excitement that led to a certain number of initial people indicating interest. Then when set up more formal registration this led to about half of those from the first group taking steps to register. Then when it came to initial participation, the group was about half the size of those registered. Finally, when we made it to the end of the activity, the group winnowed to between half and two thirds of the group that started the activity phase. We think it is important for organizations to understand these types of enrollment and participation patterns as it is important when it comes to planning instruction and other logistics.</span></p> <p><span>Second, we attempted to figure out how to get materials to kids who are most in need. We did not have a strong grasp on the socioeconomic profile of our CoBuild19 users but suspect they are from middle and upper-income settings. We grappled with how we could get materials out to kids - what could we expect them to have and what they needed. Also, in what ways could they consume our content - what options were available and what their preferences were. To address this issue, we gathered some data from traditionally underserved families to understand more about what they have available and how they might connect to the information and activities that we created. We distributed solicitation cards in English and Spanish through various channels, including food banks, across a few states. Based on responses, we saw that there was interest in STEM activities but a need for common maker materials.&nbsp;</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/03/2022<br>      Modified by: Adam&nbsp;V&nbsp;Maltese</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2027368/2027368_10667039_1659529991616_ScreenShot2022-08-03at8.31.16AM--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2027368/2027368_10667039_1659529991616_ScreenShot2022-08-03at8.31.16AM--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Cover of Hindsight 20/21 Book"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2027368/2027368_10667039_1659529991616_ScreenShot2022-08-03at8.31.16AM--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Cover of Hindsight 20/21 Book"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">This is student artwork that we chose for the cover of our Hindsight 20/21 book of student submissions related to the COVID-19 Pandemic</div> <div class="imageCredit">Anonymous</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Adam&nbsp;V&nbsp;Maltese</div> <div class="imageTitle">Cover of Hindsight 20/21 Book</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2027368/2027368_10667039_1659530087274_ScreenShot2022-08-03at8.28.27AM--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2027368/2027368_10667039_1659530087274_ScreenShot2022-08-03at8.28.27AM--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Front page of CoBuildathome.com"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2027368/2027368_10667039_1659530087274_ScreenShot2022-08-03at8.28.27AM--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Front page of CoBuildathome.com"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">We created the CoBuild website to house the project ideas created as part of the CoBuild19 project.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Adam Maltese</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Adam&nbsp;V&nbsp;Maltese</div> <div class="imageTitle">Front page of CoBuildathome.com</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ In early March 2019 we sensed that the pandemic would close schools for at least a few weeks and that caregivers would be left trying to figure out how to fill the days. To address this need and opportunity, we gathered a team of educators with expertise in making and STEM education. We planned to create and share activity ideas with caregivers through an associated Facebook group (CoBuild19), which we started on March 13. Membership in the group grew rapidly and leveled off at approximately 5000 members by June 2020. Members are primarily from the United States, Mexico, India, UK and Japan. In the US, members most commonly hail from Indiana, California and Iowa. Facebook reports that 86% of the group members are female and over 40% of the group falls in the 35-44 age range. From March through June 2020, we produced and shared videos and activity guides, averaging a handful of new activities per week. Generally, each activity (~60) we created involved a video and/or a user sheet. These resources were meant to be more like an activity starter than they were intended to be a complete lesson plan and guide.  The research aim of the project was to investigate strategies for enabling families to actively engage with STEM while at home during the pandemic. Our plan was to collect and analyze social media data to refine and improve the activities and programming and learn about the ways families engaged in the activities. We soon found that our videos got many views, "Likes" and other positive metrics. To date, 23 of our videos have more than 1000 views, with the highest garnering 23K+ views. However, we received very few submissions of videos, images, or text about what families were creating. There was some participation and contributions by members of the group when we started out but as the group grew in size, substantive evidence of participation, in the form of posted pictures of kids’ projects, comments and questions from the participants, faded. We polled members of the Facebook group about their use of the activities. The responses (n=101) were dominated by the option "We are glad to know the ideas are available, but we are not using much" (49%), followed by "We occasionally do activities" (35%). With this happening, we had no data about home participation, so we decided to experiment with different approaches.  By late May 2020 we also realized we could not sustain the pace of producing five activities each week. We decided to shift our focus and try new strategies. Once we finished the original planned content, we focused efforts on conducting virtual maker/STEM camps where we hoped for greater participation. One approach was to reformat the content produced in the first few months of CoBuild19 for camps. Another approach was to create a club/camp that focused on coding. Finally, we also held open challenges to get input from youth related to making and about their experiences during the pandemic.  Related to both intellectual merit and broader impacts, we think there are a few relevant outcomes beyond the artifacts of materials we created.  First, we found that general participation patterns emerged. When we initially announced an activity like a camp, there was often excitement that led to a certain number of initial people indicating interest. Then when set up more formal registration this led to about half of those from the first group taking steps to register. Then when it came to initial participation, the group was about half the size of those registered. Finally, when we made it to the end of the activity, the group winnowed to between half and two thirds of the group that started the activity phase. We think it is important for organizations to understand these types of enrollment and participation patterns as it is important when it comes to planning instruction and other logistics.  Second, we attempted to figure out how to get materials to kids who are most in need. We did not have a strong grasp on the socioeconomic profile of our CoBuild19 users but suspect they are from middle and upper-income settings. We grappled with how we could get materials out to kids - what could we expect them to have and what they needed. Also, in what ways could they consume our content - what options were available and what their preferences were. To address this issue, we gathered some data from traditionally underserved families to understand more about what they have available and how they might connect to the information and activities that we created. We distributed solicitation cards in English and Spanish through various channels, including food banks, across a few states. Based on responses, we saw that there was interest in STEM activities but a need for common maker materials.           Last Modified: 08/03/2022       Submitted by: Adam V Maltese]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
