<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: COVID-19’s Impact on the Urban Environment, Behavior, and Wellbeing]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>199998.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>199998</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Mamadou Diallo</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mdiallo@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924257</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[SARS CoV2, the coronavirus responsible for the global severe acute respiratory syndrome pandemic (COVID-19) represents a major threat to the health and welfare of the public. Currently the US death toll is nearing 30,000 and estimates exceeding a hundred thousand fatalities if the spread of the virus continues unchecked. Public health interventions including strict shelter in place rules have been put in place across the US and globally to limit the spread of the virus through communities. This has had a dramatic impact on the economy, with millions of people becoming unemployed in the immediate aftermath of the interventions. The goal of this RAPID project is to develop the science for rapid assessment of how public health interventions in response to the COVID-19 pandemic are impacting the environment, human behavior, and the wellbeing of the public. This goal will be achieved through detailed characterization of various biomarkers of environmental health and wellbeing in wastewater collected in the service area of people living in Tempe, Arizona. The information collected will be available to city officials, other community stakeholders, and the public using an online platform for emergency response. The resources developed in this project will inform the Nation of the impacts of shelter in place and assist crisis management and decision makers in managing these interventions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of this project is to employ detailed high-resolution analysis of wastewater together with geospatial modeling to develop a rapid assessment of environmental health at the community level during the mandated health interventions in response to the global COVID-19 pandemic. The study will take place in Tempe, Arizona, a city of 185,000 people. Baseline data on environmental quality and human behavior and health have been collected by the research team for the past two years leading up to the pandemic. A transdisciplinary team consisting of an environmental engineer, a virologist, and a bioinformatician will study environmental and human health impacts associated with the global pandemic and the public health interventions implemented in the city in response to the outbreak using this unique data resource. Urban wastewater will be sampled daily during the shelter in place intervention for analysis of a broad spectrum of compounds and biomarkers using liquid chromatography tandem mass spectrometry. Analyses include the types and quantities of air pollutants, medications taken as a result of fever and viral infections (e.g., ibuprofen), allergy suppressants, stimulants and depressants (such as nicotine and alcohol), drugs of abuse, dietary markers (indicating potential food shortages), and general biomarkers suggestive of human wellbeing and health status (e.g., antidepressants). US census data will enable an interpretation of study findings using demographics and population-size data relevant for crisis management and evidence-based decision making by scientists, city planners, mayors, health agencies, healthcare providers, and policy makers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/28/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/28/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2028564</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Arvind</FirstName>
<LastName>Varsani</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Arvind Varsani</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[Arvind.Varsani@asu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000743918</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/28/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Matthew</FirstName>
<LastName>Scotch</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Matthew L Scotch</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[Matthew.Scotch@asu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000690031</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/28/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rolf</FirstName>
<LastName>Halden</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>U</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Rolf U Halden</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[halden@asu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000384207</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/28/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Arizona State University</Name>
<CityName>TEMPE</CityName>
<ZipCode>852813670</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4809655479</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>660 S MILL AVENUE STE 204</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AZ04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NTLHJXM55KZ6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ARIZONA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Arizona State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Tempe</CityName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>852876011</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[P.O. Box 876011]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AZ04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>158Y</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>1N20</Code>
<Name>R&amp;RA CARES Act DEFC N</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>010N2021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[R&RA CARES Act DEFC N]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~199998</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>We monitored a wide range of biomarkers, including SARS-CoV-2, illicit drugs, opioids, drugs related to mental health, including antidepressants, benzodiazepine, Z-drugs, stress hormones, and the antidiabetic drug metformin in municipal wastewater of the city of Tempe during the COVID-19 pandemic. Z-drugs are the class of drugs that act similar to benzodiazepines and are used to treat anxiety and insomnia. Use of substances like this may provide insights into overall population stress and health status. In addition to pandemic samples, archived wastewater samples from the Human Health Observatory (HHO) at Arizona State University also were analyzed to deduce changes in usage patterns of Z-drugs and antidepressants during the COVID-19 pandemic, using pre-pandemic levels as a baseline. Antidepressants including ketamine, temazepam, and the Z-drug zolpidem were detected across all sampling locations during the pandemic. Interestingly, lorazepam was the only antidepressant drug found in wastewater samples above the detection limit before the pandemic. Overall, results indicate a profound impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on mental health and substance use. This study supports findings from the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) survey that documented increased mental health problems, particularly in younger adults, minorities communities, and the working class during the COVID-19 pandemic. Similarly, cocaine and its metabolite benzoylecgonine and metabolites of opioids were also detected in most of the sampling locations.&nbsp; Our location-specific findings from Tempe, AZ contribute to nationwide data collected by the CDC&rsquo;s Drug Overdose Surveillance and Epidemiology (DOSE) system that reported overdoses of opioids and stimulants during the pandemic across the U.S. states. Consumption of the antidiabetic drug metformin ranged from &lt;20,000 mg to &gt;60,000 mg per day per 1000 people across various communities. The study approach taken here also may supplement health survey data on the prevalence of diabetes in the state by tracking the consumption of antidiabetic drugs in communities in near real-time via municipal wastewater analysis.</p> <p>Results from this project suggest that the public health response to this and future pandemics should include prevention and intervention measures to address mental health conditions and substance use in society. Collected data will contribute to an understanding of the public health status and behavioral changes during the U.S. COVID-19 epidemic. Results obtained in this work have been shared with city council members, healthcare agencies, and policymakers to inform the public health response to the COVID-19 epidemic in Arizona.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/27/2021<br>      Modified by: Rolf&nbsp;U&nbsp;Halden</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2028564/2028564_10666673_1630098438158_PORFigurepng--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2028564/2028564_10666673_1630098438158_PORFigurepng--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Tempe COVID-19 WBE Dashboard."><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2028564/2028564_10666673_1630098438158_PORFigurepng--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Tempe COVID-19 WBE Dashboard."></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">This project helped to obtain real-time information on the occurrence of SARS-CoV-2 in wastewater from the city of Tempe, AZ, information that was used by city officials to mount a public health response to the pandemic locally.</div> <div class="imageCredit">City of Tempe & Arizona State University</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Rolf&nbsp;U&nbsp;Halden</div> <div class="imageTitle">Tempe COVID-19 WBE Dashboard.</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ We monitored a wide range of biomarkers, including SARS-CoV-2, illicit drugs, opioids, drugs related to mental health, including antidepressants, benzodiazepine, Z-drugs, stress hormones, and the antidiabetic drug metformin in municipal wastewater of the city of Tempe during the COVID-19 pandemic. Z-drugs are the class of drugs that act similar to benzodiazepines and are used to treat anxiety and insomnia. Use of substances like this may provide insights into overall population stress and health status. In addition to pandemic samples, archived wastewater samples from the Human Health Observatory (HHO) at Arizona State University also were analyzed to deduce changes in usage patterns of Z-drugs and antidepressants during the COVID-19 pandemic, using pre-pandemic levels as a baseline. Antidepressants including ketamine, temazepam, and the Z-drug zolpidem were detected across all sampling locations during the pandemic. Interestingly, lorazepam was the only antidepressant drug found in wastewater samples above the detection limit before the pandemic. Overall, results indicate a profound impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on mental health and substance use. This study supports findings from the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) survey that documented increased mental health problems, particularly in younger adults, minorities communities, and the working class during the COVID-19 pandemic. Similarly, cocaine and its metabolite benzoylecgonine and metabolites of opioids were also detected in most of the sampling locations.  Our location-specific findings from Tempe, AZ contribute to nationwide data collected by the CDC’s Drug Overdose Surveillance and Epidemiology (DOSE) system that reported overdoses of opioids and stimulants during the pandemic across the U.S. states. Consumption of the antidiabetic drug metformin ranged from &lt;20,000 mg to &gt;60,000 mg per day per 1000 people across various communities. The study approach taken here also may supplement health survey data on the prevalence of diabetes in the state by tracking the consumption of antidiabetic drugs in communities in near real-time via municipal wastewater analysis.  Results from this project suggest that the public health response to this and future pandemics should include prevention and intervention measures to address mental health conditions and substance use in society. Collected data will contribute to an understanding of the public health status and behavioral changes during the U.S. COVID-19 epidemic. Results obtained in this work have been shared with city council members, healthcare agencies, and policymakers to inform the public health response to the COVID-19 epidemic in Arizona.       Last Modified: 08/27/2021       Submitted by: Rolf U Halden]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
