<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[AGS-PRF: Novel Analyses of Total Solar Eclipse Data as a Tool for Coronal Physics]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>190000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>190000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06020203</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AGS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Lisa Winter</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lwinter@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928519</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[A total solar eclipse (TSE) is a rare event where the shadow of the moon blocks out the surface of the Sun on the Earth. This enables scientists to study the very hot, tenuous outer layer of the Sun, known as the corona. This project will enable a postdoctoral research fellow to study TSE observations to understand the solar wind and corona – which is important in predicting space weather effects. The project also supports outreach activities with the local Hawaiian community, through a high school scholars’ program and additional outreach and mentoring activities.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The work includes four distinct sub-projects on coronal physics based on existing white-light and narrowband emission line data from TSE observations: (i) An investigation of solar wind source regions in the corona using freeze-in distance and temperature diagnostics; (ii) A Differential Emission Measure (DEM) analysis using multiple Fe lines; (iii) Absolute calibrations of the imaging data to determine the density and structure of both the K corona (electron scattering), F corona (dust scattering) and absolute line emission; and (iv) Compare the TSE results with cutting edge coronal and solar wind models which make explicit predictions that can be tested with TSE observations.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/20/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/16/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2028173</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Benjamin</FirstName>
<LastName>Boe</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Benjamin R Boe</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<NSF_ID>000823751</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/20/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Boe, Benjamin R</Name>
<CityName>Honolulu</CityName>
<ZipCode>96822</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Hawaii</StateName>
<StateCode>HI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>HI01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Institute for Astronomy, University of Hawaii]]></Name>
<CityName>Honolulu</CityName>
<StateCode>HI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>968221839</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Hawaii</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>HI01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7137</Code>
<Text>Postdoctoral Fellowships</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1523</Code>
<Text>SOLAR-TERRESTRIAL</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7137</Code>
<Text>POSTDOCTORAL FELLOWSHIPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~94000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~96000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The solar corona is the outer atmosphere of the Sun, which flows outward into interplanetary space as the solar wind. The solar wind and dynamic eruptions from the Sun that pass through the corona, called Coronal Mass Ejections (CMEs), can have an impact on the Earth and spacecraft. These effects are often referred to as space weather. Studying the entire development of space weather and the solar wind, from the surface of the Sun, through the corona, and into the solar system is an essential endeavor for protecting our society and space-based assets. <br /><br />One key missing element in our understanding of these processes is the state and dynamics of the solar corona. The corona is much fainter than the solar surface, but it is so close to the Sun that it is very challenging to obtain high-quality observations, particularly between about 1.5 and 6 solar radii from the center of the Sun. This research focused on using observations made during total solar eclipses, when the Moon perfectly blocks out the Sun, to analyze the corona from just above the solar surface out to 3.4 solar radii.<br /><br />The work resulted in a number of studies, including a new way to measure the F corona (dust in the solar system) and K corona (electrons in the corona), and the electron temperature distribution in the corona. The analysis resulted in new findings pointing to possible issues with previous methods used to measure the K and F corona that could be improved in the future. The electron distribution was found to be surprisingly constant beyond 1.35 Rs, which provides strong constraints for future models of the corona and solar wind. These observations were compared with predictions from a leading super-computer model, which demonstrated the accuracy of the simulation. There was also a study of a new type of CME interaction with a nearby coronal structure that has implications for how CMEs evolve as they leave the corona.<br /><br />Using the unique eclipse observations, it was established that line emission from ions in the corona (which are used to infer the temperature and other physical properties) can be measured as far as 3.4 Rs, with indications that it could be observed even farther away from the Sun. This finding informs how future space-based observations could measure the line emission at larger heights than has been previously attempted. A summary of these findings was included in a White Paper for the 2024 Heliophysics decadal survey, which will guide future research in this field for the next ten years.<br /><br />The funding of this fellowship also supported the mentorship of five undergraduate student projects, as well as the collaboration of a graduate student in the research.<br /><br />The outcomes of this work were presented at multiple conferences and a press release for the public: https://www.hawaii.edu/news/2021/07/13/double-bubble-solar-eruption/<br /><br />The calibrated data products from this work are available here: https://www2.ifa.hawaii.edu/SolarEclipseData/</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/21/2023<br>      Modified by: Benjamin&nbsp;R&nbsp;Boe</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2028173/2028173_10700327_1679453499237_ScreenShot2023-03-21at4.34.13PM--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2028173/2028173_10700327_1679453499237_ScreenShot2023-03-21at4.34.13PM--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Double-bubble Coronal Mass Ejection"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2028173/2028173_10700327_1679453499237_ScreenShot2023-03-21at4.34.13PM--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Double-bubble Coronal Mass Ejection"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">White-light image of the 2020 December 14 total solar eclipse. The bubble feature on the left is a unique interaction between a coronal mass ejection and a nearby coronal streamer</div> <div class="imageCredit">https://doi.org/10.3847/2041-8213/ac05ca</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Benjamin&nbsp;R&nbsp;Boe</div> <div class="imageTitle">Double-bubble Coronal Mass Ejection</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2028173/2028173_10700327_1679453249238_ScreenShot2023-03-21at4.34.47PM--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2028173/2028173_10700327_1679453249238_ScreenShot2023-03-21at4.34.47PM--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Line Emission in the Corona"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2028173/2028173_10700327_1679453249238_ScreenShot2023-03-21at4.34.47PM--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Line Emission in the Corona"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Line Emission of three ions, Fe X, Fe XI, and Fe XIV, which are three different ions of Iron. The left panels are the eclipse data, the right panels are predictions from a leading model.</div> <div class="imageCredit">https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/1538-4357/ac8101</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Benjamin&nbsp;R&nbsp;Boe</div> <div class="imageTitle">Line Emission in the Corona</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2028173/2028173_10700327_1679453096479_ScreenShot2023-03-21at4.34.29PM--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2028173/2028173_10700327_1679453096479_ScreenShot2023-03-21at4.34.29PM--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Electron Temperature of the Corona"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2028173/2028173_10700327_1679453096479_ScreenShot2023-03-21at4.34.29PM--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Electron Temperature of the Corona"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Electron temperature maps inferred from two line ratios with both the eclipse data and a cutting-edge model.</div> <div class="imageCredit">https://doi.org/10.3847/1538-4357/ac8101</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Benjamin&nbsp;R&nbsp;Boe</div> <div class="imageTitle">Electron Temperature of the Corona</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The solar corona is the outer atmosphere of the Sun, which flows outward into interplanetary space as the solar wind. The solar wind and dynamic eruptions from the Sun that pass through the corona, called Coronal Mass Ejections (CMEs), can have an impact on the Earth and spacecraft. These effects are often referred to as space weather. Studying the entire development of space weather and the solar wind, from the surface of the Sun, through the corona, and into the solar system is an essential endeavor for protecting our society and space-based assets.   One key missing element in our understanding of these processes is the state and dynamics of the solar corona. The corona is much fainter than the solar surface, but it is so close to the Sun that it is very challenging to obtain high-quality observations, particularly between about 1.5 and 6 solar radii from the center of the Sun. This research focused on using observations made during total solar eclipses, when the Moon perfectly blocks out the Sun, to analyze the corona from just above the solar surface out to 3.4 solar radii.  The work resulted in a number of studies, including a new way to measure the F corona (dust in the solar system) and K corona (electrons in the corona), and the electron temperature distribution in the corona. The analysis resulted in new findings pointing to possible issues with previous methods used to measure the K and F corona that could be improved in the future. The electron distribution was found to be surprisingly constant beyond 1.35 Rs, which provides strong constraints for future models of the corona and solar wind. These observations were compared with predictions from a leading super-computer model, which demonstrated the accuracy of the simulation. There was also a study of a new type of CME interaction with a nearby coronal structure that has implications for how CMEs evolve as they leave the corona.  Using the unique eclipse observations, it was established that line emission from ions in the corona (which are used to infer the temperature and other physical properties) can be measured as far as 3.4 Rs, with indications that it could be observed even farther away from the Sun. This finding informs how future space-based observations could measure the line emission at larger heights than has been previously attempted. A summary of these findings was included in a White Paper for the 2024 Heliophysics decadal survey, which will guide future research in this field for the next ten years.  The funding of this fellowship also supported the mentorship of five undergraduate student projects, as well as the collaboration of a graduate student in the research.  The outcomes of this work were presented at multiple conferences and a press release for the public: https://www.hawaii.edu/news/2021/07/13/double-bubble-solar-eruption/  The calibrated data products from this work are available here: https://www2.ifa.hawaii.edu/SolarEclipseData/       Last Modified: 03/21/2023       Submitted by: Benjamin R Boe]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
