<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[NSF Travel Support for 2020 Visualization Early Career Faculty Workshop]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>16053.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>16053</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Hector Munoz-Avila</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>hmunoz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924481</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The Visualization Early Career Faculty Workshop offers specialized mentoring to junior faculty whose research spans broad areas in information visualization. Its goal is to develop the next generation of faculty in data science and visualization research so as to strengthen and diversify this field. This workshop provides a forum where junior faculty can interact with each other in a setting that promotes positive career growth and contributes to sharing knowledge. This event addresses both an important and timely need, as researchers in this field come from a wide array of demographic and technical backgrounds. Many departments have at most one researcher in visualization, and thus the mentoring the junior faculty receive from their home institution cannot address the unique challenges of building an academic career in this field. Junior faculty from underrepresented groups will be encouraged to participate. The workshop experience will support and retain this interdisciplinary workforce of researchers and educators in the important area visualization that enables decision making and knowledge discovery.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Specifically, this workshop complements traditional academic mentoring by offering a peer support and mentoring group for junior faculty so as to exchange information with peers. Faculty recently transitioning from junior to mid-career stages also participate to help structure the content of the workshop and provide guidance. This event fosters the growth and development of new faculty as they begin their careers in academia. Its unique, small group format produces an intensive workshop that helps build identity as well as to bridge newcomers to the larger ecosystem of academics in visualization across the country. The group of attendees is curated so as to offer diverse perspectives that might not appear in each attendee's home department. Since visualization research is broad in scope, our attendees hail from multiple universities that serve a wide range of students as well as departments in multiple fields (such as Computer Science, Information Science, Computational Media, and Digital Humanities). Therefore, workshop topics span numerous cross-cutting concerns such as developing a visualization research program, recruiting and managing a research group, handling the academic responsibilities of teaching and service, and strategies for collaboration, achieving visibility, and work-life balance.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/27/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/27/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2028384</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Remco</FirstName>
<LastName>Chang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Remco Chang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[remco@cs.tufts.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000238906</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/27/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Tufts University</Name>
<CityName>SOMERVILLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>021442401</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6176273696</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>169 HOLLAND ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>WL9FLBRVPJJ7</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF TUFTS COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>S6ZWCYHRQQB3</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Tufts University School of Engineering]]></Name>
<CityName>Medford</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021555530</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[200 College Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7364</Code>
<Text>Info Integration &amp; Informatics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7364</Code>
<Text>INFO INTEGRATION &amp; INFORMATICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~16053</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Visualization Early Career Faculty Workshop, known as the VIS Summer Camp, aimed to provide peer support and mentoring to junior tenure-track faculty in the United States whose research focused on data visualization. These annual workshops played a crucial role in assisting faculty members as they transitioned from graduate school or postdoctoral positions to the multifaceted responsibilities of an academic career in visualization.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The workshops addressed a wide range of crucial aspects related to the faculty role, encompassing the design of visualization research programs, securing funding, managing research groups, handling teaching commitments, developing innovative pedagogical approaches, fostering research collaborations, navigating service responsibilities and departmental politics, attaining visibility and recognition, and maintaining a healthy work-life balance. By comprehensively addressing these diverse responsibilities, the workshops aimed to empower the next generation of visualization leaders and facilitate their success in the field.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Over the course of the project, three mentoring workshops were successfully organized. The first workshop took place in August 2021 in Minneapolis, MN, followed by the second workshop in June 2022 in Atlantic City, NJ, and the third in June 2023 in Charleston, SC. The initial workshop had a total of 15 participants, while the second workshop had 11 participants due to the withdrawal of four attendees because of COVID-19 considerations. The third workshop saw the participation of 12 individuals. Detailed information about the participants and schedules for each workshop can be accessed through the workshop websites: https://vissummercamp.github.io/2021/, https://vissummercamp.github.io/2022/, and https://vissummercamp.github.io/2023/.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>These workshops provided an invaluable platform for pre-tenure faculty members from across the United States to connect, collaborate, and foster relationships. The opportunity to meet in person allowed for reflection, feedback exchange, and sharing of lessons learned. The workshops established a supportive environment that facilitated mentorship and peer learning, creating a strong network of early-career visualization faculty members.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>One of the remarkable outcomes of the workshops was the extensive sharing of teaching experiences and classroom materials among the participants. These faculty members engaged in fruitful discussions, where they openly addressed the successes and shortcomings of their existing courses, as well as shared innovative teaching strategies aimed at enhancing students' educational experiences. By leveraging the collective wisdom and experiences of the participants, the workshops contributed to the improvement of future visualization courses at their respective institutions, potentially leading to enhanced educational outcomes for students.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The impact of the workshops extended beyond intangible peer-mentoring benefits. Several tangible outcomes emerged as a result of the workshops, including publications and proposal submissions. For instance, three participants collaborated on a journal article based on their discussions during the 2021 workshop, resulting in its publication in the prestigious IEEE Computer Graphics and Applications (CG&amp;A) journal. Furthermore, four participants submitted their CAREER proposals to the National Science Foundation (NSF) following the feedback they received from the workshops. Two of these proposals were accepted for funding. Additionally, three participants submitted a proposal to the Department of Energy, with their initial two-page white paper being accepted. The participants utilized the second workshop to refine and finalize the full proposal.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>These outcomes demonstrated the substantial impact and tangible results generated by the workshops. By fostering collaboration, sharing of experiences, and mentorship, the workshops supported the professional growth of participants and facilitated the translation of ideas into concrete scholarly outputs. The workshops played a pivotal role in advancing the careers of early-career faculty members in the visualization community.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>In conclusion, the Visualization Early Career Faculty Workshops served as a vital platform for supporting and mentoring junior tenure-track faculty members in the United States specializing in data visualization. The workshops effectively addressed the multifaceted responsibilities of faculty roles, fostering collaboration, sharing of teaching experiences, and classroom materials. The outcomes included publications and proposals that highlighted the progress and success of participants. By empowering and guiding the next generation of visualization leaders, the workshops contributed to the growth and development of the participants and made a lasting impact on the field of visualization education.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/10/2023<br>      Modified by: Remco&nbsp;Chang</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Visualization Early Career Faculty Workshop, known as the VIS Summer Camp, aimed to provide peer support and mentoring to junior tenure-track faculty in the United States whose research focused on data visualization. These annual workshops played a crucial role in assisting faculty members as they transitioned from graduate school or postdoctoral positions to the multifaceted responsibilities of an academic career in visualization.     The workshops addressed a wide range of crucial aspects related to the faculty role, encompassing the design of visualization research programs, securing funding, managing research groups, handling teaching commitments, developing innovative pedagogical approaches, fostering research collaborations, navigating service responsibilities and departmental politics, attaining visibility and recognition, and maintaining a healthy work-life balance. By comprehensively addressing these diverse responsibilities, the workshops aimed to empower the next generation of visualization leaders and facilitate their success in the field.     Over the course of the project, three mentoring workshops were successfully organized. The first workshop took place in August 2021 in Minneapolis, MN, followed by the second workshop in June 2022 in Atlantic City, NJ, and the third in June 2023 in Charleston, SC. The initial workshop had a total of 15 participants, while the second workshop had 11 participants due to the withdrawal of four attendees because of COVID-19 considerations. The third workshop saw the participation of 12 individuals. Detailed information about the participants and schedules for each workshop can be accessed through the workshop websites: https://vissummercamp.github.io/2021/, https://vissummercamp.github.io/2022/, and https://vissummercamp.github.io/2023/.     These workshops provided an invaluable platform for pre-tenure faculty members from across the United States to connect, collaborate, and foster relationships. The opportunity to meet in person allowed for reflection, feedback exchange, and sharing of lessons learned. The workshops established a supportive environment that facilitated mentorship and peer learning, creating a strong network of early-career visualization faculty members.     One of the remarkable outcomes of the workshops was the extensive sharing of teaching experiences and classroom materials among the participants. These faculty members engaged in fruitful discussions, where they openly addressed the successes and shortcomings of their existing courses, as well as shared innovative teaching strategies aimed at enhancing students' educational experiences. By leveraging the collective wisdom and experiences of the participants, the workshops contributed to the improvement of future visualization courses at their respective institutions, potentially leading to enhanced educational outcomes for students.     The impact of the workshops extended beyond intangible peer-mentoring benefits. Several tangible outcomes emerged as a result of the workshops, including publications and proposal submissions. For instance, three participants collaborated on a journal article based on their discussions during the 2021 workshop, resulting in its publication in the prestigious IEEE Computer Graphics and Applications (CG&amp;A) journal. Furthermore, four participants submitted their CAREER proposals to the National Science Foundation (NSF) following the feedback they received from the workshops. Two of these proposals were accepted for funding. Additionally, three participants submitted a proposal to the Department of Energy, with their initial two-page white paper being accepted. The participants utilized the second workshop to refine and finalize the full proposal.     These outcomes demonstrated the substantial impact and tangible results generated by the workshops. By fostering collaboration, sharing of experiences, and mentorship, the workshops supported the professional growth of participants and facilitated the translation of ideas into concrete scholarly outputs. The workshops played a pivotal role in advancing the careers of early-career faculty members in the visualization community.     In conclusion, the Visualization Early Career Faculty Workshops served as a vital platform for supporting and mentoring junior tenure-track faculty members in the United States specializing in data visualization. The workshops effectively addressed the multifaceted responsibilities of faculty roles, fostering collaboration, sharing of teaching experiences, and classroom materials. The outcomes included publications and proposals that highlighted the progress and success of participants. By empowering and guiding the next generation of visualization leaders, the workshops contributed to the growth and development of the participants and made a lasting impact on the field of visualization education.          Last Modified: 07/10/2023       Submitted by: Remco Chang]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
