<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Measuring the Impact of the COVID-19 Pandemic on STEM Student Engagement and Learning in Online Learning Environments]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>199943.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>199943</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>John Jackman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jjackman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924816</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The COVID-19 pandemic has caused a sudden and unprecedented shift of undergraduate education to online learning.  Instructors and students, many of whom have limited experience teaching and learning online, have suddenly been immersed in an exclusively virtual learning experience.  This shift has been accompanied by drastic limitations in students’ daily activities, social interactions, and job opportunities.  Given that the current disruption in the system is transient in nature, it is urgent to collect and analyze the data needed to understand the impact of the pandemic on undergraduate students.  To this end, this project will examine the immediate and long-term impacts of the pandemic on undergraduate students’ emotional well-being, day-to-day functioning, and learning.  The study aims to provide insights on how disruptions can affect learners’ stress, engagement, and learning outcomes both during the online learning experience and during the return to learning conditions that are similar to those prior to the disruption.  Results from this project will help inform higher-education institutions and policymakers as they develop strategies to mitigate the effects on student learning resulting from the current pandemic and to plan responses for future disruptions.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of this project is to understand the longitudinal and dynamic impact of the pandemic on undergraduate STEM students’ emotional states (such as stress, anxiety, depressive symptoms, and frustration), day-to-day life (such as social isolation, sedentariness, access to outdoor environments, and proximity to outbreak hotspots), and learning engagement and outcomes.  Fluctuations in students’ day-to-day functions and emotional states will be evaluated during and after the pandemic, using information from psychological surveys, interviews, computer vision-based analytics, and wearable sensors.  Learning outcomes will be assessed using grades and self-evaluation of learning.  Quantitative and qualitative analysis of the resulting data will be used to understand the effects of the disruptions in daily life on students’ emotional states and learning outcomes.  This project aims to advance the STEM education community’s understanding of the relationship between disruptions in the education system and student learning, and potentially reveal characteristics that promote resilience of students during and following the acute stages of a crisis.  This RAPID award is made by the Improving Undergraduate STEM Education program in the Division of Undergraduate Education (Education and Human Resources Directorate), using funds from the Coronavirus Aid, Relief, and Economic Security (CARES) Act.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/28/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/28/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2028224</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Steven</FirstName>
<LastName>Van Dessel</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Steven Van Dessel</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[svandessel@wpi.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000706071</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/28/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jacob</FirstName>
<LastName>Whitehill</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jacob Whitehill</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jrwhitehill@wpi.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000709937</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/28/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Shichao</FirstName>
<LastName>Liu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Shichao Liu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[sliu8@wpi.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000770683</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/28/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Angela</FirstName>
<LastName>Rodriguez</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Angela C Rodriguez</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[acrodriguez@wpi.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000810140</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/28/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Soroush</FirstName>
<LastName>Farzin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Soroush Farzin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[sfarzin2@wpi.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000824316</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/28/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Worcester Polytechnic Institute</Name>
<CityName>WORCESTER</CityName>
<ZipCode>016092247</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5088315000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>100 INSTITUTE RD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>HJNQME41NBU4</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WORCESTER POLYTECHNIC INSTITUTE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Worcester Polytechnic Institute]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>016092280</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1998</Code>
<Text>IUSE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8209</Code>
<Text>Improv Undergrad STEM Ed(IUSE)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>4N20</Code>
<Name>EHR CARES Act DEFC N</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>040N2021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[EHR CARES Act DEFC N]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~199943</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-1c9ecd15-7fff-3a16-7edd-37b81f4b4936"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The 2020 SARS-CoV-2 (coronavirus) crisis is disrupting almost every aspect of daily life across the world, including undergraduate education. Suddenly, both instructors and students with little prior experience teaching or learning online are immersed in an exclusively online learning environment. In addition to the severe personal and medical challenges caused by the pandemic, students must also adapt to a different mode of academic instruction as well as a primarily home-based learning environment where they lack the recreational and social activities that had been an integral part of their college lives. These factors will likely increase students? stress and may impair their learning.&nbsp;</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The primary goal of the proposal is to measure the longitudinal and dynamic impacts of SARS-CoV-2 on undergraduate STEM students? emotional states and their associated relationships with learning outcomes during the pandemic.&nbsp; The research team has enrolled 180 undergraduate students from Worcester Polytechnic Institute to monitor their stress, learning, and physical environment in dorms or houses through surveys, interviews, facial expressions recorded during online class taking, heart rate, and course grade of each academic term. Each student participated in the study for approximately three months at different stages of the pandemic from Summer 2020 to Spring 2021.&nbsp;</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The project has revealed that 54% of the males and 38% of females were consistently depressed during the participation. Only approximately 21-23% of the student participants did not experience either consistent or unstable depression. The results found that depression is significantly associated with poor self-reported learning performance, while perceived stress level and loneliness show mere associations. In addition, self-reported learning performance is significantly associated with students? satisfaction with temperature, indoor air quality, amount of light, visual comfort, acoustics, and indoor environment as a whole.&nbsp;</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The severity of the number of daily COVID cases reported in students? residence state was not relevant to learning performance, as there were no significant differences in performance between terms despite a varying average number of daily COVID cases and daily case number gradient between terms. There exists some limited evidence that people tend to be more stressed when the number of Covid cases rises.&nbsp; This trend exists during Summer 2020 which is around the peak time that Covid cases grow rapidly across the country. As time goes on, the participants tend to be less stressed. This relationship disappears in Fall 2020 and Spring 2021 (no evidence showing the significant effects between the covid count and stress level). Additionally, The action units (AUs) do not seem to be statistically significantly related to the stress value itself. When we analyzed whether any AU is related to a student being at the beginning vs. the end of the semester, there exists one action unit (AU9) that is significantly related in both the Fall and Spring datasets. Moreover, the AU9 also shows some relationship to depression.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The project helps understand the association between students? stress and learning during COVID when learning remotely. The impact of the indoor physical environment on learning has been investigated, suggesting the importance of promoting the indoor environment for effective learning outcomes. The results can suggest further research on indoor environmental design in terms of mental health. Furthermore, the analysis on the relationship between COVID case numbers in the home state on depression and learning implies that COVID case numbers might not be a trigger for stress or poor learning. In addition, there is limited evidence that students? facial expressions can be associated with stress. Also, the findings on facial expressions indicate that teachers/instructors should not rely purely on students? videos to determine their stress levels.&nbsp; All these results can help educators, school administrators, and policymakers to best respond to students? learning and mental health for future possible pandemics.&nbsp; Moreover, the knowledge gained from the project can support the transformation of indoor environmental design by not only looking at energy but also people?s well-being.&nbsp;</span></p> <div><span><br /></span></div> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/05/2022<br>      Modified by: Shichao&nbsp;Liu</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2028224/2028224_10666577_1641402568237_graphicabstract-01--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2028224/2028224_10666577_1641402568237_graphicabstract-01--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Project abstract"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2028224/2028224_10666577_1641402568237_graphicabstract-01--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Project abstract"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">research questions and methods</div> <div class="imageCredit">Shichao Liu</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Shichao&nbsp;Liu</div> <div class="imageTitle">Project abstract</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   The 2020 SARS-CoV-2 (coronavirus) crisis is disrupting almost every aspect of daily life across the world, including undergraduate education. Suddenly, both instructors and students with little prior experience teaching or learning online are immersed in an exclusively online learning environment. In addition to the severe personal and medical challenges caused by the pandemic, students must also adapt to a different mode of academic instruction as well as a primarily home-based learning environment where they lack the recreational and social activities that had been an integral part of their college lives. These factors will likely increase students? stress and may impair their learning.     The primary goal of the proposal is to measure the longitudinal and dynamic impacts of SARS-CoV-2 on undergraduate STEM students? emotional states and their associated relationships with learning outcomes during the pandemic.  The research team has enrolled 180 undergraduate students from Worcester Polytechnic Institute to monitor their stress, learning, and physical environment in dorms or houses through surveys, interviews, facial expressions recorded during online class taking, heart rate, and course grade of each academic term. Each student participated in the study for approximately three months at different stages of the pandemic from Summer 2020 to Spring 2021.     The project has revealed that 54% of the males and 38% of females were consistently depressed during the participation. Only approximately 21-23% of the student participants did not experience either consistent or unstable depression. The results found that depression is significantly associated with poor self-reported learning performance, while perceived stress level and loneliness show mere associations. In addition, self-reported learning performance is significantly associated with students? satisfaction with temperature, indoor air quality, amount of light, visual comfort, acoustics, and indoor environment as a whole.     The severity of the number of daily COVID cases reported in students? residence state was not relevant to learning performance, as there were no significant differences in performance between terms despite a varying average number of daily COVID cases and daily case number gradient between terms. There exists some limited evidence that people tend to be more stressed when the number of Covid cases rises.  This trend exists during Summer 2020 which is around the peak time that Covid cases grow rapidly across the country. As time goes on, the participants tend to be less stressed. This relationship disappears in Fall 2020 and Spring 2021 (no evidence showing the significant effects between the covid count and stress level). Additionally, The action units (AUs) do not seem to be statistically significantly related to the stress value itself. When we analyzed whether any AU is related to a student being at the beginning vs. the end of the semester, there exists one action unit (AU9) that is significantly related in both the Fall and Spring datasets. Moreover, the AU9 also shows some relationship to depression.    The project helps understand the association between students? stress and learning during COVID when learning remotely. The impact of the indoor physical environment on learning has been investigated, suggesting the importance of promoting the indoor environment for effective learning outcomes. The results can suggest further research on indoor environmental design in terms of mental health. Furthermore, the analysis on the relationship between COVID case numbers in the home state on depression and learning implies that COVID case numbers might not be a trigger for stress or poor learning. In addition, there is limited evidence that students? facial expressions can be associated with stress. Also, the findings on facial expressions indicate that teachers/instructors should not rely purely on students? videos to determine their stress levels.  All these results can help educators, school administrators, and policymakers to best respond to students? learning and mental health for future possible pandemics.  Moreover, the knowledge gained from the project can support the transformation of indoor environmental design by not only looking at energy but also people?s well-being.                Last Modified: 01/05/2022       Submitted by: Shichao Liu]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
