<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID:  Collaborative Research:  Optimizing non-pharmaceutical and pharmaceutical interventions for controlling COVID-19 at the community-level]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>87492.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>87492</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Katharina Dittmar</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kdittmar@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927799</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[During emerging infectious disease outbreaks, such as the current novel coronavirus (COVID-19) pandemic, mathematical models are important tools to help inform public health recommendations and best utilization of limited resources. This research will develop and analyze data-driven mathematical models to predict the spread and evaluate the success of various public health intervention strategies to control COVID-19 in the US and abroad. The models will account for the characteristics of the pathogen, the variation of transmission that occur within community and in hospital settings, and geographical difference in transmission. The broader impacts from these models will provide real-time information to assist public health officials and decision-makers in making critical decisions on COVID-19 control policies and resource allocation.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Standard modeling approach such as compartmental population-based approach may not be suitable for modeling the spread of COVID-19, due to the high-level of heterogeneity of such systems, disease pathways, population makeup, host interactions on different levels of organization (household, workplace/school, social activities), and adaptive features of human behavior. The investigators will employ an individual-based modeling approach (IBM) that will accommodate such local heterogeneities. The investigators will use social, demographic, and epidemiological data of COVID-19 cases in the US and Korea, as well as hospital-level and city-level contact tracing data of COVID-19 in Wuhan, China, to parameterize their models. First, they will develop an IBM hospital-based model to explore different hospital-based interventions for mitigating the risk of nosocomial transmission of COVID-19 between patients and healthcare workers. Second, they will develop an IBM community-based model to evaluate and identify optimal non-pharmaceutical and potential pharmaceutical interventions for COVID-19 control in different local communities (city-county scale). The non-pharmaceutical interventions will include, amongst others: case isolation at home or hospitals, voluntary self-quarantine, stopping mass gathering, closure of schools, universities, or workplaces, and social distancing such as reduction of contacts, wearing of protective masks, and reduction of individuals' movements. Pharmaceutical interventions will include novel vaccines and antiviral therapies.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This RAPID award is made by the Ecology and Evolution of Infectious Diseases Program in the Division of Environmental Biology, using funds from the Coronavirus Aid, Relief, and Economic Security (CARES) Act&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/05/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/05/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2028632</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Martial</FirstName>
<LastName>Ndeffo Mbah</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Martial L Ndeffo Mbah</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mndeffo@cvm.tamu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000824121</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/05/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Texas A&amp;M University</Name>
<CityName>COLLEGE STATION</CityName>
<ZipCode>778454375</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9798626777</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>400 HARVEY MITCHELL PKY S STE 30</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>JF6XLNB4CDJ5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TEXAS A &amp; M UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>HH6VX5XDL284</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Texas A&M University]]></Name>
<CityName>College Station</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>778434458</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4458 TAMU]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>158Y</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>1N20</Code>
<Name>R&amp;RA CARES Act DEFC N</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>010N2021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[R&RA CARES Act DEFC N]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~87492</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-a7ca1066-7fff-6189-25e6-d384dbf124c4">&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span id="docs-internal-guid-44b21450-7fff-f107-0fe9-69a7c613254f"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Emerging infectious disease outbreaks, such as the current novel coronavirus (COVID-19) pandemic, call for new approaches, mathematical models and computational tools to help improve our understanding of disease spread and burden and inform public health policies. Studying disease transmission and the means of their control should be explored on different levels and scales, ranging from large (country / regional) scales, down to local communities (counties, cities/neighborhoods) or individual enterprises (schools/colleges, hospitals, or workplaces). Standard population-based modeling approaches may not be suitable for modeling disease spread at local scales, due to multiple heterogeneities: disease pathways, population makeup and social interactions on different levels of organization.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Our research project has developed a series of novel computational modeling frameworks to investigate disease spread and control across different scales. These frameworks&nbsp; include an individual based modeling (IBM) approach, and semi-empirical modeling framework, and a state-space modeling framework. Our IBM approach expands conventional IBM, which assumes random or social network-like mixing, by accounting for&nbsp; more realistic patterns of human behavior, social interaction and structures. Our semi-empirical modeling framework provides a novel simple model for estimating COID-19 prevalence and seroprevalence at different geographical scales using only reported cases and test positivity data. The state-space spatial model provides a new modeling framework for more accurate estimation of COVID-19 epidemiological parameters and transmission dynamics from partial and noisy data.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>We used these models to estimate the effectiveness of different non-pharmaceutical intervention measures (testing, quarantine, social distancing, lockdowns) to control the spread of COVID-19 at different geographical scales in the US. Our college campus model was used to examine a wide range of college transmission environments, and intervention strategies, including class/dorm arrangement and social activities, test screening and isolation, vaccination and monitoring. We developed free web-based interactive applications of our models which can be used by public health officials or the general public to explore different scenarios of COVID-19 spread and control at different scales. Results of our research were presented at different national conferences and published in several high profile open access academic journals. In addition, the project supported the professional development of a minority faculty and the training of three students.</span></p> <div><span><br /></span></div> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr">&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/16/2021<br>      Modified by: Martial&nbsp;L&nbsp;Ndeffo Mbah</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[      Emerging infectious disease outbreaks, such as the current novel coronavirus (COVID-19) pandemic, call for new approaches, mathematical models and computational tools to help improve our understanding of disease spread and burden and inform public health policies. Studying disease transmission and the means of their control should be explored on different levels and scales, ranging from large (country / regional) scales, down to local communities (counties, cities/neighborhoods) or individual enterprises (schools/colleges, hospitals, or workplaces). Standard population-based modeling approaches may not be suitable for modeling disease spread at local scales, due to multiple heterogeneities: disease pathways, population makeup and social interactions on different levels of organization.    Our research project has developed a series of novel computational modeling frameworks to investigate disease spread and control across different scales. These frameworks  include an individual based modeling (IBM) approach, and semi-empirical modeling framework, and a state-space modeling framework. Our IBM approach expands conventional IBM, which assumes random or social network-like mixing, by accounting for  more realistic patterns of human behavior, social interaction and structures. Our semi-empirical modeling framework provides a novel simple model for estimating COID-19 prevalence and seroprevalence at different geographical scales using only reported cases and test positivity data. The state-space spatial model provides a new modeling framework for more accurate estimation of COVID-19 epidemiological parameters and transmission dynamics from partial and noisy data.    We used these models to estimate the effectiveness of different non-pharmaceutical intervention measures (testing, quarantine, social distancing, lockdowns) to control the spread of COVID-19 at different geographical scales in the US. Our college campus model was used to examine a wide range of college transmission environments, and intervention strategies, including class/dorm arrangement and social activities, test screening and isolation, vaccination and monitoring. We developed free web-based interactive applications of our models which can be used by public health officials or the general public to explore different scenarios of COVID-19 spread and control at different scales. Results of our research were presented at different national conferences and published in several high profile open access academic journals. In addition, the project supported the professional development of a minority faculty and the training of three students.              Last Modified: 09/16/2021       Submitted by: Martial L Ndeffo Mbah]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
