<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Collaborative Research: Transforming passive protective face masks toward active capture and inactivation of coronavirus with nano-assisted surfactant modification]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>92402.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>92402</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ashley Pierce</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>apierce@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924493</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Novel coronavirus disease is caused by SARS-CoV-2, an extremely virulent strain of coronavirus that is responsible for an increasing number of illnesses and deaths, globally. According to the World Health Organization, “SARS-CoV-2 is transmitted via droplets and fomites during close unprotected contact between an infector and an infectee”.  A recent study has shown that these virions can be airborne for at least 30 minutes and be active on the aerosol droplets up to three hours.  Non-pharmaceutical protection is essential to stunt the spread of this virus. As of March 19, 2020, the Center for Disease Control’s official guidelines include non-optimal reuse of surgical masks for extended periods of time.  Then, on March 27, 2020, the World Health Organization declared a critical emergency on personal protection equipment.  The reuse of masks puts healthcare workers, first line responders, patients, and the community at risk. The aim of this research project between the University of Texas-Austin and the University of Florida Health Shands Hospital is to develop and implement a rapid protocol for extended use of surgical and N95 masks.  The researchers will develop a fast, simple procedure for turning passive masks into active protective gear.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This proposal addresses a critical need to improve personal protection equipment during the coronavirus crisis. A new extended use protocol for masks will render immediate benefits to the healthcare community.  An enhanced mechanistic understanding of virion capture and inactivation at nano-bio interfaces will have wide applicability in the design of personal protective equipment. This research project has the following objectives: (i) obtain masks from the Shands hospital, treat them with surfactants, ultraviolet-C ray, and steam, and then characterize the efficacy of each treatment using viability tests, (ii) modify mask surfaces with surfactant-modified (sodium lauryl sulfate, butadines, or stearoyl lactylate) carbon particles (activated carbon, carbon quantum dots, or nano-diamond) at different ratios and moisture content and then test their efficacy in attaching and inactivating coronaviruses, (iii) understand the mechanisms of virus attachment and inactivation, and (iv) implement a rapid extended mask-use program. The outcomes from this project should have critical and widespread scientific and public health impacts.  The modified masks could provide needed support to the depleted mask-inventory of health care providers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/21/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/21/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2028521</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Navid</FirstName>
<LastName>Saleh</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Navid Saleh</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[navidsaleh@gmail.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000526079</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/21/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Texas at Austin</Name>
<CityName>AUSTIN</CityName>
<ZipCode>787121139</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5124716424</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>110 INNER CAMPUS DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>25</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX25</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>V6AFQPN18437</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT AUSTIN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>X5NKD2NFF2V3</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Texas at Austin]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>787121532</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>25</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX25</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>158Y</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>1N20</Code>
<Name>R&amp;RA CARES Act DEFC N</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>010N2021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[R&RA CARES Act DEFC N]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~92402</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Overview.&nbsp;</strong>The COVID-19 pandemic caused novel and severe respiratory infections that were responsible for significant morbidity and mortality on a global scale. Airborne transmission has been identified earlyon and the use of personal protective equipment (PPE) became essential. Furthermore, the virus was shown to be viable (active) for up to 3-h on droplets. This suggests that SARS-CoV-2 can remain infectious on surfaces, including facemasks, that were being highly re-used during the pandemic when supplies were critically low. &nbsp;For example, in &nbsp;March 2020, the Center for Disease Control&rsquo;s (CDC) official guidelines included non-optimal reuse of surgical masks for extended periods of time but a few weeks later, the WHO declared a critical emergency on PPE, leaving mask re-use the only option. Such reuse of masks, the only available option, put healthcare workers, first-line responders, patients, and the community at high risk.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Facemasks can offer effective protection against direct viral infections by sequestering virus particles. However, most facemasks do not inactivate viruses. During long-term use or re-use of masks could lead to transmission through re-aerosolization or surface transfer which leads to infection. To address this challenge, this<strong>&nbsp;</strong>project aimed to develop and implement a rapid protocol for extended use of surgical facemasks turning passive masks into active protective gear. The study leveraged the decade-long collaborative research between the PIs at University of Texas at Austin (UT) and University of Florida (UF) on virus-nanomaterial interactions, the unique capability of materials design (at UT) and the advantage of virus strains (at UF) and approved BSL2 and BSL3 capabilities. We tested the ability of various surfactants (soap molecules) and nanoparticles (carbon, metal oxides) to inactivate aerosolized respiratory viruses (influenza, coronavirus) that were deposited on mask surfaces in a custom chamber exposure system. The goal was to test a potential platform that can be readily implemented in mask disinfection post-use.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Intellectual Merit</strong></p> <p>Several major outcomes of this project advanced our understanding of the use of nanoparticles and surfactants may kill viruses on facemask materials. These outcomes include the following.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <ul> <li>Live virus particles are present on mask surfaces for up to 3 hours. Carbon nanoparticles (pristine of amine modified) alone do not effectively kill virus particles (influenza, coronavirus) on masks but the addition of surfactants seem to contribute to viral killing.</li> </ul> <ul> <li>Metal oxide nanoparticles&nbsp;alone do not effectively kill virus particles on masks but the addition of surfactants seem to contribute to viral killing.</li> <li>Some common soap molecules, e.g., sodium laurel sulphate (SLS or SDS) is superior at virus killing compared to other commonly used surfactants. This can be problematic from a safety standpoint and also confounds viral viability results (in the lab setting).</li> <li>Three graduate students have been trained in mask surface coating, characterization of the masks, and public health implications of viruses as well as importance of PPE during this process.</li> </ul> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts.&nbsp;</strong>The outcomes from this project can have profound and widespread scientific and public health impacts. It is important to understand whether viruses remain infectious on mask materials, especially during times of extended wear and re-use. So far, we have determined that viruses can remain viable on facemasks and are best deactivated with surfactants. Using nanoparticles as a support, we intend to design masks that effectively de-activate virus particles directly on the mask &ndash; improving technology and safety &ndash; for health care workers and the public. We expect this technology to be applicable to many respiratory viruses. Multiple graduate students have been trained during this grant administration and the results have been disseminated to a wider audience through an interactive workshop with 60 participants from across the nation.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/31/2023<br>      Modified by: Navid&nbsp;Saleh</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Overview. The COVID-19 pandemic caused novel and severe respiratory infections that were responsible for significant morbidity and mortality on a global scale. Airborne transmission has been identified earlyon and the use of personal protective equipment (PPE) became essential. Furthermore, the virus was shown to be viable (active) for up to 3-h on droplets. This suggests that SARS-CoV-2 can remain infectious on surfaces, including facemasks, that were being highly re-used during the pandemic when supplies were critically low.  For example, in  March 2020, the Center for Disease Control’s (CDC) official guidelines included non-optimal reuse of surgical masks for extended periods of time but a few weeks later, the WHO declared a critical emergency on PPE, leaving mask re-use the only option. Such reuse of masks, the only available option, put healthcare workers, first-line responders, patients, and the community at high risk.     Facemasks can offer effective protection against direct viral infections by sequestering virus particles. However, most facemasks do not inactivate viruses. During long-term use or re-use of masks could lead to transmission through re-aerosolization or surface transfer which leads to infection. To address this challenge, this project aimed to develop and implement a rapid protocol for extended use of surgical facemasks turning passive masks into active protective gear. The study leveraged the decade-long collaborative research between the PIs at University of Texas at Austin (UT) and University of Florida (UF) on virus-nanomaterial interactions, the unique capability of materials design (at UT) and the advantage of virus strains (at UF) and approved BSL2 and BSL3 capabilities. We tested the ability of various surfactants (soap molecules) and nanoparticles (carbon, metal oxides) to inactivate aerosolized respiratory viruses (influenza, coronavirus) that were deposited on mask surfaces in a custom chamber exposure system. The goal was to test a potential platform that can be readily implemented in mask disinfection post-use.     Intellectual Merit  Several major outcomes of this project advanced our understanding of the use of nanoparticles and surfactants may kill viruses on facemask materials. These outcomes include the following.     Live virus particles are present on mask surfaces for up to 3 hours. Carbon nanoparticles (pristine of amine modified) alone do not effectively kill virus particles (influenza, coronavirus) on masks but the addition of surfactants seem to contribute to viral killing.   Metal oxide nanoparticles alone do not effectively kill virus particles on masks but the addition of surfactants seem to contribute to viral killing. Some common soap molecules, e.g., sodium laurel sulphate (SLS or SDS) is superior at virus killing compared to other commonly used surfactants. This can be problematic from a safety standpoint and also confounds viral viability results (in the lab setting). Three graduate students have been trained in mask surface coating, characterization of the masks, and public health implications of viruses as well as importance of PPE during this process.      Broader Impacts. The outcomes from this project can have profound and widespread scientific and public health impacts. It is important to understand whether viruses remain infectious on mask materials, especially during times of extended wear and re-use. So far, we have determined that viruses can remain viable on facemasks and are best deactivated with surfactants. Using nanoparticles as a support, we intend to design masks that effectively de-activate virus particles directly on the mask &ndash; improving technology and safety &ndash; for health care workers and the public. We expect this technology to be applicable to many respiratory viruses. Multiple graduate students have been trained during this grant administration and the results have been disseminated to a wider audience through an interactive workshop with 60 participants from across the nation.                Last Modified: 07/31/2023       Submitted by: Navid Saleh]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
