<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: How People Learn Rapidly: COVID-19 as a Crisis of Socioscientific Understanding and Educational Equity]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>199744.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>199744</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DRL</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jolene Jesse</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jjesse@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927303</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The primary objective of this study is to document how people learn the science of the COVID-19 pandemic in real time, how they activate this scientific knowledge towards informed decision making, and how these processes change over time. This study is intended to produce additional insights on how such learning is shaped by equity concerns and contextual factors. For example, researchers will document how the ways in which people learn the science of COVID-19 are mediated by the sources of information they have access to and leverage, as well as what supports them in doing so. The research will further document how people leverage their understandings of COVID-19, alongside other forms of knowledge and concerns in their decision-making. This study may serve a crucial role in aiding the public understanding of where structural points of informational failure might occur. It may also reveal where and how the public engages or resists community action strategies to mitigate spread and suffering through when, how and why they gather, share, and make sense of scientific data. This RAPID was submitted in response to the NSF Dear Colleague letter related to the COVID-19 pandemic. This award is made by the AISL and ECR programs in the Division of Research on Learning, using funds from the Coronavirus Aid, Relief, and Economic Security (CARES) Act. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research will draw upon a conceptual framework of consequential learning and a methodological framework of narrative inquiry. Sixty participants in Lansing, Michigan and Seattle, Washington will participate over the course of one year in cyclical interviews, focus group conversations and experience sampling approaches. Documents and resources named and used by the participants in their learning will be collected and analyzed. Attention will be paid to science learning in the following areas as the primary focus: a) the science of SARS-CoV-2 and the relationship between virus and disease, b) viral transmission, and c) origination, replication and spread. A key focus will also be how people use scientific data and evidence-based explanations when developing understandings and making decisions with respect to the pandemic. This research is urgent and timely because the COVID-19 pandemic is projected to occur in multiple waves over approximately 18 months. Insights may produce basic understanding about rapid science learning, policy strategies, school-based practices and resources for use within current and future waves. Socioscientific crises differentially impact people, with effects felt more significantly by vulnerable people. Thus, this study will address the urgent call for investigation into factors and experiences of low-income individuals and families who are trying to educate themselves on continually changing data during an international health crisis.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/29/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/29/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2028370</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Elizabeth</FirstName>
<LastName>Davis</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Elizabeth A Davis</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[betsyd@umich.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000365880</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/29/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Leslie</FirstName>
<LastName>Herrenkohl</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Leslie R Herrenkohl</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[leslierh@umich.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000180654</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/29/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Angela</FirstName>
<LastName>Calabrese Barton</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Angela Calabrese Barton</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[angieCB@umich.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000100970</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/29/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Regents of the University of Michigan - Ann Arbor</Name>
<CityName>ANN ARBOR</CityName>
<ZipCode>481091079</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1109 GEDDES AVE, SUITE 3300</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>GNJ7BBP73WE9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MICHIGAN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Michigan-Ann Arbor]]></Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3003 S. State St.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7259</Code>
<Text>AISL</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>4N20</Code>
<Name>EHR CARES Act DEFC N</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>040N2021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[EHR CARES Act DEFC N]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~199744</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-0de5e448-7fff-4c81-2022-f358e53a80a0">&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>In long-term research-practice partnerships in the midwestern and western US, we sought to understand what/how community partners learn about and take action on COVID-19 and justice-related concerns. Our overarching research questions included:&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>&#9679;</span><span>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; </span><span>How and what science do people learn about COVID-19?&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>&#9679;</span><span>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; </span><span>How do people activate and apply the science they learn to make (or revise) personal and family decisions?&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>&#9679;</span><span>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; </span><span>How is youths&rsquo; and adults&rsquo; learning about COVID-19 shaped by their critical consciousness around racial, educational, and economic justice?&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>As we sought to answer these questions, we further considered the political and ethical dimensions of doing research </span><span>through</span><span> remote methods.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>We draw upon theories of consequential learning, focusing on what counts as valued learning, and how the processes of learning involve disrupting or transforming normative patterns of participation towards new forms of expertise and social relations</span><span> </span><span>that counter ahistorical and universalist notions of knowing.</span><span> </span><span>Consequential learning reveals how learning matters to people here-and-now and towards imagined social futures, and power dynamics in how actors are positioned across time, place and scales-of-activity. To attend to power in our remote methods, we further drew upon critical witnessing and being with -- practices toward conscientization, social transformation and the public good of communities historically marginalized by systemic inequities.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>This larger study involves 62 participants across two metropolitan areas representing different geographic regions of the US.&nbsp; We used both remote participatory interviewing and informal conversations with experience sampling methods. Methods took shape interactively as we partnered with participants to cogenerate data over time through a multimodal and dynamic data cogeneration design. </span><span>Our deep and long-term relationships framed and mediated our data cogeneration</span><span>.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Key insights include:</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>First, participants came together to co-create new data-constructing and data-sharing infrastructures that could better serve their needs as they continued to learn the science of COVID-19 and its equity-related complexities. </span><span>By c</span><span>ommunity infrastructuring</span><span> we mean justice-oriented acts of necessity for community protection and well-being to share and re-organize resources in-the-moment and with an eye towards the urgent near-future. </span><span>Participants highlighted conflicts between sources and messaging, where and how they saw their own experiences mirrored/challenged in them, and the extent to which these data could possibly inform/transform their decisions and actions. Using multimodal forms of information sharing with us, participants pointed out how misinformation campaigns fostered deepening racial and socioeconomic injustices, and what that meant for their own practices.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Second,</span><span> participants&rsquo; enactment of critical data practices changed how they negotiated between coming-to-know and coming-to-act. </span><span>C</span><span>ommunity-engaged critical practices</span><span> are what people do in socially-mediated and culturally-embedded ways with, in relation to, and oriented around data and data infrastructures in support of more equitable everyday living and communities. These practices arose from tensions in participants&rsquo; engagement with data as they mobilized big and small data from different epistemological and social origins towards meaning-making, action-taking and co</span><span>mmunicating. These tensions shaped how and why youth re-mixed data practices and authored new hybrid ones for navigating, understanding data, critiqued and recontextualized data and data narratives for re-imagining data about their worlds and hoped-for-futures; and re-positioned themselves and their world into data.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Third, </span><span>participants&rsquo; coming-to-know and coming-to-act in the datafied pandemic is always embodied and racialized.&nbsp; Early in the pandemic, we found that Asian or Asian American identifying participants who brought prior knowledge/experience with other pandemics and the practice of mask wearing quickly understood that the practice of mask wearing as helpful for preventing community viral spread in the community.&nbsp; Yet, some participants reported not wearing masks because early in the pandemic mask wearing was interpreted as an indication that &ldquo;I am sick&rdquo; rather than &ldquo;I am being responsible community member..&rdquo;&nbsp; We found that although participants built scientific understanding from trusted sources and experiences, they did not trust the general public and feared racism, intimidation, and violence.&nbsp;&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span>Implications: </span><span>Across findings, youths&rsquo; learning about and decision-making related to COVID-19 is deeply tied to how, when and why they access data and data infrastructures in relation to their lives and communities, and how trust mediates these processes. </span><span>Advancing justice-oriented work with community partners in remote research required attention to political and ethical dimensions of learning, and to how tools get leveraged, re-mixed and co-opted in the crucial work of critical witnessing and being with. Findings suggest that we need new models of learning and action that recognize cultural contexts, practices, and systemic injustices.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/09/2022<br>      Modified by: Angela&nbsp;Calabrese Barton</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   In long-term research-practice partnerships in the midwestern and western US, we sought to understand what/how community partners learn about and take action on COVID-19 and justice-related concerns. Our overarching research questions included:  &#9679;      How and what science do people learn about COVID-19?  &#9679;      How do people activate and apply the science they learn to make (or revise) personal and family decisions?  &#9679;      How is youths’ and adults’ learning about COVID-19 shaped by their critical consciousness around racial, educational, and economic justice?  As we sought to answer these questions, we further considered the political and ethical dimensions of doing research through remote methods.    We draw upon theories of consequential learning, focusing on what counts as valued learning, and how the processes of learning involve disrupting or transforming normative patterns of participation towards new forms of expertise and social relations that counter ahistorical and universalist notions of knowing. Consequential learning reveals how learning matters to people here-and-now and towards imagined social futures, and power dynamics in how actors are positioned across time, place and scales-of-activity. To attend to power in our remote methods, we further drew upon critical witnessing and being with -- practices toward conscientization, social transformation and the public good of communities historically marginalized by systemic inequities.    This larger study involves 62 participants across two metropolitan areas representing different geographic regions of the US.  We used both remote participatory interviewing and informal conversations with experience sampling methods. Methods took shape interactively as we partnered with participants to cogenerate data over time through a multimodal and dynamic data cogeneration design. Our deep and long-term relationships framed and mediated our data cogeneration.      Key insights include: First, participants came together to co-create new data-constructing and data-sharing infrastructures that could better serve their needs as they continued to learn the science of COVID-19 and its equity-related complexities. By community infrastructuring we mean justice-oriented acts of necessity for community protection and well-being to share and re-organize resources in-the-moment and with an eye towards the urgent near-future. Participants highlighted conflicts between sources and messaging, where and how they saw their own experiences mirrored/challenged in them, and the extent to which these data could possibly inform/transform their decisions and actions. Using multimodal forms of information sharing with us, participants pointed out how misinformation campaigns fostered deepening racial and socioeconomic injustices, and what that meant for their own practices.    Second, participants’ enactment of critical data practices changed how they negotiated between coming-to-know and coming-to-act. Community-engaged critical practices are what people do in socially-mediated and culturally-embedded ways with, in relation to, and oriented around data and data infrastructures in support of more equitable everyday living and communities. These practices arose from tensions in participants’ engagement with data as they mobilized big and small data from different epistemological and social origins towards meaning-making, action-taking and communicating. These tensions shaped how and why youth re-mixed data practices and authored new hybrid ones for navigating, understanding data, critiqued and recontextualized data and data narratives for re-imagining data about their worlds and hoped-for-futures; and re-positioned themselves and their world into data.    Third, participants’ coming-to-know and coming-to-act in the datafied pandemic is always embodied and racialized.  Early in the pandemic, we found that Asian or Asian American identifying participants who brought prior knowledge/experience with other pandemics and the practice of mask wearing quickly understood that the practice of mask wearing as helpful for preventing community viral spread in the community.  Yet, some participants reported not wearing masks because early in the pandemic mask wearing was interpreted as an indication that "I am sick" rather than "I am being responsible community member.."  We found that although participants built scientific understanding from trusted sources and experiences, they did not trust the general public and feared racism, intimidation, and violence.      Implications: Across findings, youths’ learning about and decision-making related to COVID-19 is deeply tied to how, when and why they access data and data infrastructures in relation to their lives and communities, and how trust mediates these processes. Advancing justice-oriented work with community partners in remote research required attention to political and ethical dimensions of learning, and to how tools get leveraged, re-mixed and co-opted in the crucial work of critical witnessing and being with. Findings suggest that we need new models of learning and action that recognize cultural contexts, practices, and systemic injustices.             Last Modified: 08/09/2022       Submitted by: Angela Calabrese Barton]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
