<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID Collaborative proposal: Spatial dynamics of COVID-19]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>73034.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>73034</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Samuel Scheiner</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sscheine@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927175</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This project will develop a set of mathematical models of the spread of SARS-CoV-2, the cause of COVID-19. The 2019-2020 global corona virus pandemic is ongoing and poses an unprecedented challenge to the normal movement of people within and between countries. The models developed by this research will provide the means to determine how the risk of transmission varies over time between specific locations and can be combined with other data sources to help determine the primary routes of transmission and the actions that are successful in slowing or halting the spread. These methods are designed to provide initial models with limited data, while allowing for the integration of more robust datasets as they become available. The proposed project will produce information directly applicable to managing the geographic spread of SARS-CoV-2, will inform CDC decisions and responses to the pandemic, and will provide a way to assess changes to importation risk in close to real-time. In addition,the proposed project will contribute to the training of a graduate student and an undergraduate student. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Stochastic spatial models provide the means for determining the time-varying risk of pathogen transmission between specific locations. This project will develop extensions of these models that will be more effective at analyzing and forecasting spatial spread of emerging disease. The project will develop a spatial model that incorporates time-varying cases in each location, including a reliable method for parameterization. It will use those models to estimate the effects of travel restrictions and quarantines on the spread globally and within the U.S. By closely studying the spread at the source of the outbreak it will assess how travel patterns and interventions altered the pandemic trajectory. The models will also assist in identifying areas at greatest risk of importation of new cases when local transmission is controlled. These aims will be accomplished by using publicly available data sources and compiling new information on the timeline of interventions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/31/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/14/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2028136</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Drake</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John M Drake</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jdrake@uga.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000231870</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/31/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Georgia Research Foundation Inc</Name>
<CityName>ATHENS</CityName>
<ZipCode>306021589</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7065425939</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>310 E CAMPUS RD RM 409</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NMJHD63STRC5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF GEORGIA RESEARCH FOUNDATION, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Georgia]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>306021589</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[310 East Campus Rd.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>U323</Code>
<Text/>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021RB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~73034</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-21bcfe40-7fff-17a7-85d6-41e3ccecf2a8"> <p dir="ltr"><span>This project sought to develop new models to understand the spatial spread of COVID-19 at the county scale in China and the United States. Although infectious disease models have been around for over one hundred years, most models focus only on local transmission, not the way in which a disease moves through a highly interconnected landscape. An important innovation in this study is the ability to measure the effectiveness of non-pharmaceutical interventions such as bar closures, stay-at-home orders, mask requirements, and gathering size restrictions. In addition to curtailing local transmission, such measures also have the potential to reduce the rate of spread from and to neighboring communities, thereby giving policymakers and officials sufficient time to develop and deploy plans for risk mitigation and damage control. Our model showed that mask orders and stay-at-home orders significantly decreased the rate of spread of Covid-19 in the US. In contrast, we failed to detect an effect of gathering size restrictions and bar closures on rate of spread, perhaps because these measures primarily affect local transmission and not movement. The US importation model showed that the identity of the ports of entry of highest risk changed very little over the course of the epidemic, but the sources of that risk changed significantly as SARS-CoV-2 swept around the world.</span></p> <div><span><br /></span></div> </span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/27/2021<br>      Modified by: John&nbsp;M&nbsp;Drake</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  This project sought to develop new models to understand the spatial spread of COVID-19 at the county scale in China and the United States. Although infectious disease models have been around for over one hundred years, most models focus only on local transmission, not the way in which a disease moves through a highly interconnected landscape. An important innovation in this study is the ability to measure the effectiveness of non-pharmaceutical interventions such as bar closures, stay-at-home orders, mask requirements, and gathering size restrictions. In addition to curtailing local transmission, such measures also have the potential to reduce the rate of spread from and to neighboring communities, thereby giving policymakers and officials sufficient time to develop and deploy plans for risk mitigation and damage control. Our model showed that mask orders and stay-at-home orders significantly decreased the rate of spread of Covid-19 in the US. In contrast, we failed to detect an effect of gathering size restrictions and bar closures on rate of spread, perhaps because these measures primarily affect local transmission and not movement. The US importation model showed that the identity of the ports of entry of highest risk changed very little over the course of the epidemic, but the sources of that risk changed significantly as SARS-CoV-2 swept around the world.             Last Modified: 12/27/2021       Submitted by: John M Drake]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
