<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Bioengineering in Microgravity Workshop; International Space Station US National Laboratory Virtual Symposium]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>30000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>30000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Laurel Kuxhaus</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lkuxhaus@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924465</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This award will support research that will contribute new knowledge related to bioengineering in Space. The International Space Station US National Laboratory will host a Virtual Symposium to strategically partner with approximately 50 diverse scientists, engineers, and clinicians. This collaboration will leverage their translational expertise to accelerate the understanding of fundamental science that could lead to biomedical breakthroughs by studying biological phenomena in Low Earth Orbit. The goals of the Symposium are:  1) to leverage translational expertise from scientists, engineers, and clinicians to accelerate our understanding of how biomedical breakthroughs can be developed or tested in space (low earth orbit); 2) produce a written document detailing the results of the discussions.  Specifically, this document will identify research areas and findings to propel thought leadership of the low earth orbit environment, and how this work could ultimately lead to clinical translation. This is work for the betterment of humankind and could have significant benefits to the US economy. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The ability to perform research in a microgravity environment provides unprecedented opportunities for fundamental research. Under the umbrella of Regenerative Medicine, four focus areas for the Symposium have been identified: Stem cells; Biofabrication and 3D bioprinting; Organoids/microphysiological systems; Artificial intelligence (AI) and Robotics.  Removing the effects of gravity has contributed significantly to the collective fundamental knowledge of cellular behavior, cell-cell interactions, tissue development and regeneration, as well as the aggregate interactions in the context of a whole organism. Pioneering bioengineering experiments on the International Space Station coupled with ground-based studies have demonstrated that microgravity enables the study of novel features not attainable under unit gravity conditions. These include changes to stem cell proliferation rates and differentiation. Printing biological tissues in microgravity also promises advantages in the use of lower-viscosity biomaterials or bioinks and the ability to fabricate diaphanous, intricate structures. These processes are heavily reliant on biomechanical and mechanobiological cues that are affected by the gravitational field. In this way, the International Space Station provides an unprecedented opportunity to advance fundamental research in biomechanics and mechanobiology. The participants of this interdisciplinary workshop will be tasked with determining and then publicly disseminating the roadmap for future advances in microgravity bioengineering. The results will be critical for funders that currently sponsor bioengineering research which relies on reduced microgravity environments. The results will enable these agencies and the researchers they support to appropriately plan for future programs and studies.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/17/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/17/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2028635</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Marcello</FirstName>
<LastName>Giulianotti</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Marcello Giulianotti</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mgiulianotti@issnationallab.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000823559</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/17/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Center for the Advancement of Science in Space, Inc.</Name>
<CityName>MELBOURNE</CityName>
<ZipCode>329407553</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3217576134</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>6905 N WICKHAM RD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[STE 500]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>YDQLHSMTBZ24</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CENTER FOR THE ADVANCEMENT OF SCIENCE IN SPACE, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Center for the Advancement of Science in Space, Inc.]]></Name>
<CityName>Melbourne</CityName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>329407553</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[6905 N. Wickham Road, Suite 500]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7479</Code>
<Text>BMMB-Biomech &amp; Mechanobiology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>028E</Code>
<Text>BIOMECHANICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>036E</Code>
<Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~30000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Center for the Advancement of Science in Space, Inc. (CASIS), manager of the International Space Station (ISS) National Laboratory, and the University of Pittsburgh&rsquo;s McGowan Institute for Regenerative Medicine hosted a Biomanufacturing in Space Symposium. In a series of virtual working sessions, the symposium gathered subject matter experts in the areas of tissue engineering, regenerative medicine, and space-based research to identify the most promising opportunities to leverage the ISS for research and development (R&amp;D) to advance space-based biomanufacturing. The symposium was meant to serve as the first step in developing a roadmap to establish a robust and sustainable market for biomanufacturing in space.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Through the symposium, multiple opportunities for space-based biomanufacturing R&amp;D were identified and prioritized. These opportunities fall in three key areas: (1) disease modeling through the use of microphysiological systems (also called tissue chips) and organoids, (2) stem cells and stem-cell-derived products, and (3) biofabrication.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Symposium participants also noted the critical need for additional data to validate and de-risk the opportunities and underscored the importance of utilizing approaches such as automation, artificial intelligence, and machine learning to produce and capture this data. Additionally, symposium participants concluded that public-private partnership and funding will be crucial in advancing the opportunities toward a biomanufacturing marketplace in LEO.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>As of the end of 2021 the work from the Symposium has led to two open-access publications (<a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.stemcr.2021.12.001">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.stemcr.2021.12.001</a> and <a href="https://doi.org/10.20944/preprints202108.0044">https://doi.org/10.20944/preprints202108.0044</a>) and has been utilized to inform the scope for two research solicitations (<a href="https://www.issnationallab.org/research-on-the-iss/solicitations/rfp2022-2/">https://www.issnationallab.org/research-on-the-iss/solicitations/rfp2022-2/</a> and <a href="https://www.issnationallab.org/research-on-the-iss/solicitations/nlra2021-6/">https://www.issnationallab.org/research-on-the-iss/solicitations/nlra2021-6/</a>).</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/01/2022<br>      Modified by: Marcello&nbsp;Giulianotti</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Center for the Advancement of Science in Space, Inc. (CASIS), manager of the International Space Station (ISS) National Laboratory, and the University of Pittsburgh’s McGowan Institute for Regenerative Medicine hosted a Biomanufacturing in Space Symposium. In a series of virtual working sessions, the symposium gathered subject matter experts in the areas of tissue engineering, regenerative medicine, and space-based research to identify the most promising opportunities to leverage the ISS for research and development (R&amp;D) to advance space-based biomanufacturing. The symposium was meant to serve as the first step in developing a roadmap to establish a robust and sustainable market for biomanufacturing in space.     Through the symposium, multiple opportunities for space-based biomanufacturing R&amp;D were identified and prioritized. These opportunities fall in three key areas: (1) disease modeling through the use of microphysiological systems (also called tissue chips) and organoids, (2) stem cells and stem-cell-derived products, and (3) biofabrication.     Symposium participants also noted the critical need for additional data to validate and de-risk the opportunities and underscored the importance of utilizing approaches such as automation, artificial intelligence, and machine learning to produce and capture this data. Additionally, symposium participants concluded that public-private partnership and funding will be crucial in advancing the opportunities toward a biomanufacturing marketplace in LEO.     As of the end of 2021 the work from the Symposium has led to two open-access publications (https://doi.org/10.1016/j.stemcr.2021.12.001 and https://doi.org/10.20944/preprints202108.0044) and has been utilized to inform the scope for two research solicitations (https://www.issnationallab.org/research-on-the-iss/solicitations/rfp2022-2/ and https://www.issnationallab.org/research-on-the-iss/solicitations/nlra2021-6/).          Last Modified: 02/01/2022       Submitted by: Marcello Giulianotti]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
