<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Collaborative Research: Designing an Educational Intervention to Address Intuitive Misconceptions about COVID-19]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>99155.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>191704</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DRL</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Gregg Solomon</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>gesolomo@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928333</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Misconceptions about the transmission of COVID-19 can lead to noncompliance with preventive public health recommendations. The first goal of this project, led by researchers at Boston University and Northeastern University, is to understand the deeper conceptual nature of these biological misconceptions. The research will explore whether these ideas are specific to COVID-19 or whether they reflect intuitive reasoning patterns of reasoning about biological phenomena more generally, and how prevalent they are in early elementary school children. A further focus of this research will be on caregivers and teachers–adults who are important sources of information to children. Prior NSF-funded research has shown that misconceptions about biological phenomena emerge early in development and can become entrenched. Therefore, the second major goal of this research is the rapid design and testing of a pilot educational intervention that addresses children’s and adults’ reasoning about COVID-19 and also incorporates more general information about the causal mechanisms that underlie biological contagion. The intervention will be modeled on earlier interventions by the investigators that used animated narratives to teach complex biological concepts successfully to children and adults. This RAPID award is made by the EHR Core Research (ECR) program in DRL, using funds from the Coronavirus Aid, Relief, and Economic Security (CARES) Act. ECR supports work that advances the fundamental research literature on STEM learning.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Humans possess powerful intuitive explanatory and inferential tendencies that provide fast and efficient – but sometimes fallible – guidelines for making sense of complex phenomena in the biological world. Prior NSF-funded work has shown how these tendencies–for example, intuitive teleological, essentialist, and anthropocentric modes of reasoning–emerge early and act as filters on the learning of biological information at all ages. Sometimes these intuitions are consistent with formal biological reasoning and can be leveraged in the classroom to support learning, but sometimes they are not and lead to systematic and entrenched biological misconceptions across development. Information about COVID-19 is no exception. In this project, the researchers will: (1) investigate intuitive reasoning about the causal mechanisms of COVID-19 transmission and infection–along with reasoning about illness more generally–among teachers and caregivers of 1st - 2nd grade students; (2) conduct parallel investigations with the 1st - 2nd grade students themselves; and (3) rapidly design and pilot test a cognitively-informed educational intervention on COVID-19, and related illnesses, for elementary children, caregivers, and teachers based on the evidence that will be gleaned from these investigations. In order to understand the influence on children of adults’ reasoning about COVID-19–and disease more generally–this project will develop child and adult versions of a survey instrument consisting of: (a) an open-ended interview on the causality, treatment, and prevention of COVID-19; (b) a risky behavior detection task to assess knowledge and beliefs about the risks of common behaviors; (c) a causal knowledge assessment that asks more generally about the mechanisms of illness transmission and infection. These measures will be administered via online research. Insights gained from these measures will be quickly used to develop a pilot intervention that will use an animated narrative video to supported children's and adults’ mechanistic understanding of COVID-19 and related disease transmission and prevention. Pre- and post-testing will determine the effectiveness of this pilot intervention and lay the foundation for future research and intervention. This research will shed light on children’s and adults’ understandings about COVID-19, and the degree to which children’s ideas are shaped by intuitive explanatory tendencies and that misconceptions can be exacerbated by specific misinformation from caregivers and teachers. It will also illuminate cognitively-informed ways to educate adults about complex biological phenomena as a way of addressing misconceptions in the children with whom they interact.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/08/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/11/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2028140</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Samuel</FirstName>
<LastName>Ronfard</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Samuel Ronfard</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[samuel.ronfard@utoronto.ca]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000824318</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/08/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Deborah</FirstName>
<LastName>Kelemen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Deborah Kelemen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[dkelemen@bu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000485977</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/08/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Trustees of Boston University</Name>
<CityName>BOSTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>022151703</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6173534365</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1 SILBER WAY</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>THL6A6JLE1S7</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF BOSTON UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Trustees of Boston University]]></Name>
<CityName>Boston</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>022151300</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[881 Commonwealth Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7980</Code>
<Text>ECR-EDU Core Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>102Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-Disproportionate Impcts Inst-Indiv</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8817</Code>
<Text>STEM Learning &amp; Learning Environments</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0421</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>4N20</Code>
<Name>EHR CARES Act DEFC N</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>040N2021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[EHR CARES Act DEFC N]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~99155</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~92549</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><div class="WordSection1"> <p>Humans possess powerful intuitive ways of understanding important domains of experience, which provide us with fast and efficient, but ultimately fallible guidelines for dealing with the complex world around us. We filter new information through these intuitive ways of understanding, which can lead to systematic misconceptions.</p> <p>Understanding information about COVID-19 is no exception. Beliefs like <em>asymptomatic individuals cannot transmit infection</em>, and <em>antibiotic medications are effective against viral infections </em>are but two examples of widespread misconceptions about viral disease held by large sections of the US public.</p> <p>Our goals in this collaborative study were to respond to the COVID- 19 pandemic by learning how intuitive understanding might give rise to misconceptions about viral illness like COVID-19 among parents and 6-9-year-old children, and to develop effective ways of overcoming those misconceptions. Funding from the NSF allowed us to gather an international interdisciplinary team that includes specialists in cognitive and developmental psychology, immunology, and science education. Together we developed and conducted in- depth interviews investigating understanding of the mechanisms of COVID-19 infection and transmission among elementary school children and parents.</p> <p>These interviews revealed that parents of 6-to-9-year-olds had relatively accurate knowledge of how COVID-19 was transmitted, but also had misconceptions about COVID infection processes and susceptibilities, and especially about the role of the immune system. We also found that most parents limited their discussions of COVID with their children to brief, basic factual information about transmission and preventative behaviors, rarely discussing underlying mechanisms that might allow children to think beyond the immediate pandemic situation. Specficially, interviews with children revealed that they knew basic facts about COVID-19 transmission but very little about the reasons for preventative behaviors (e.g. vaccination) even if they were from pro-vaccination families. In general, children often held the misconception that vaccines are like <em>medicine </em>(i.e. they directly fight an infectious disease agent) rather than that vaccines are like <em>teachers </em>(i.e. train a body how to recognize and fight an infection disease agent for the longer-term).</p> <p>Despite COVID vaccination options becoming available during the course of our data collection, we found parents tended not to explain immunity or discuss vaccination information or attitudes with children. Because misconceptions about the immune system and immunity were widespread among people we interviewed, and could impact vaccination decisions, we decided to refocus our child research on children's understanding and learning about immunity and vaccination, so that our findings could be useful beyond COVID.</p> <p>Based on what we learned about parents&rsquo; and childrens&rsquo; understanding of and misconceptions about the immune system from our interviews, we designed a picture book-based intervention for 5- to 8-year-old children meant to teach about the components and role of the immune system in fighting illness, and how vaccines work to bolster this system.</p> <p>Although such information might seem too complicated for young children, because the intuitive conceptual frameworks that give rise to misconceptions become increasingly entrenched with development, the ideal time to intervene is early elementary school, when children have acquired rudimentary ideas about the mechanisms of illness transmission, but are still actively constructing this understanding. By teaching about how viral illness actually works, we hope to give children the tools to make informed decisions about their own health-related behaviors that will generalize to a variety of health contexts.</p> </div> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/18/2023<br>      Modified by: Deborah&nbsp;Kelemen</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Humans possess powerful intuitive ways of understanding important domains of experience, which provide us with fast and efficient, but ultimately fallible guidelines for dealing with the complex world around us. We filter new information through these intuitive ways of understanding, which can lead to systematic misconceptions.  Understanding information about COVID-19 is no exception. Beliefs like asymptomatic individuals cannot transmit infection, and antibiotic medications are effective against viral infections are but two examples of widespread misconceptions about viral disease held by large sections of the US public.  Our goals in this collaborative study were to respond to the COVID- 19 pandemic by learning how intuitive understanding might give rise to misconceptions about viral illness like COVID-19 among parents and 6-9-year-old children, and to develop effective ways of overcoming those misconceptions. Funding from the NSF allowed us to gather an international interdisciplinary team that includes specialists in cognitive and developmental psychology, immunology, and science education. Together we developed and conducted in- depth interviews investigating understanding of the mechanisms of COVID-19 infection and transmission among elementary school children and parents.  These interviews revealed that parents of 6-to-9-year-olds had relatively accurate knowledge of how COVID-19 was transmitted, but also had misconceptions about COVID infection processes and susceptibilities, and especially about the role of the immune system. We also found that most parents limited their discussions of COVID with their children to brief, basic factual information about transmission and preventative behaviors, rarely discussing underlying mechanisms that might allow children to think beyond the immediate pandemic situation. Specficially, interviews with children revealed that they knew basic facts about COVID-19 transmission but very little about the reasons for preventative behaviors (e.g. vaccination) even if they were from pro-vaccination families. In general, children often held the misconception that vaccines are like medicine (i.e. they directly fight an infectious disease agent) rather than that vaccines are like teachers (i.e. train a body how to recognize and fight an infection disease agent for the longer-term).  Despite COVID vaccination options becoming available during the course of our data collection, we found parents tended not to explain immunity or discuss vaccination information or attitudes with children. Because misconceptions about the immune system and immunity were widespread among people we interviewed, and could impact vaccination decisions, we decided to refocus our child research on children's understanding and learning about immunity and vaccination, so that our findings could be useful beyond COVID.  Based on what we learned about parents’ and childrens’ understanding of and misconceptions about the immune system from our interviews, we designed a picture book-based intervention for 5- to 8-year-old children meant to teach about the components and role of the immune system in fighting illness, and how vaccines work to bolster this system.  Although such information might seem too complicated for young children, because the intuitive conceptual frameworks that give rise to misconceptions become increasingly entrenched with development, the ideal time to intervene is early elementary school, when children have acquired rudimentary ideas about the mechanisms of illness transmission, but are still actively constructing this understanding. By teaching about how viral illness actually works, we hope to give children the tools to make informed decisions about their own health-related behaviors that will generalize to a variety of health contexts.                 Last Modified: 07/18/2023       Submitted by: Deborah Kelemen]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
