<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Using Popular Media to Educate Youth About the Biology of Viruses and the Current COVID-19 Pandemic]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>200000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>200000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DRL</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Robert Russell</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rlrussel@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922995</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[As part of its overall strategy to enhance learning in informal environments, the Advancing Informal STEM Learning (AISL) program funds innovative research, approaches, and resources for use in a variety of settings. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This RAPID was submitted in response to the NSF Dear Colleague letter related to the COVID-19 pandemic. This award is made by the AISL program in the Division of Research on Learning, using funds from the Coronavirus Aid, Relief, and Economic Security (CARES) Act. The project will develop and research an integrated package of high-quality, widely accessible media and other outreach materials designed to engage middle school youth, educators, and libraries in learning about viruses in relation to COVID-19. There is an immediate need to provide youth with accurate, engaging, and accessible materials to help them understand the basic biology underlying the COVID-19 pandemic, including the routes of COVID-19 transmission and mechanisms to prevent its spread.  This is particularly important for those without science backgrounds or interests so that the rumors, hearsay, and gossip circulating among youth can be replaced with research-based information. Since 2007, the project team and partners have focused on developing and studying new ways of educating youth and the public about biology, virology, and infectious disease. The project will develop a web-accessible package of customizable graphics, illustrated stories, and essays—all of which can be easily incorporated into free-choice and directed on-line learning as well standards-based lesson plans for Grades 6-8. These resources will be disseminated broadly and at no cost to youth and educators of all kinds, including schools, libraries, museums, and other established networks for formal and informal science education. The project web package will be linked to multiple websites that serve as important educational resources on science and virology for youth, the general public, and educators. A prominent university press will publish and promote the illustrated stories and support distribution of 7,000 free copies. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will conduct research examining how richly-illustrated science narratives impact youth understanding of and curiosity about science. The research will help develop the foundation for better understanding how to educate youth about COVID-19 (and future pandemics) while generating new knowledge about effective methods for public science outreach during a major unanticipated natural event. For formative evaluation, the project will use an innovative rapid response feedback method.  Youth will be invited to provide timely, specific comments on the serialized stories through a curated portal. As new excerpts are related online, different questions will be posed to youth who are selected because of specific characteristics (e.g., low or high initial science interest). These data will guide story development in real time and provide a mechanism to gauge the story appeal, comprehensibility, and initial impacts. The project will address two research questions: “How effective are illustrated stories in having positive impacts among participants on COVID-19 knowledge, science identity, attitudes, and interest in science careers?” and “How do story lines and characters have differential impacts on virus knowledge, epidemiology, and youth attitudes towards science and science careers?” To conduct this research, the project will conduct online surveys using adapted items from prior research conducted by the project team.  Additional items will assess COVID-19 knowledge, attitudes, personal experiences with the virus, well-being, and exposure to public health messaging about the virus. Research findings will be shared widely to inform the field about new ways delivering science education content during the advent of rapidly evolving global and educational challenges.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/08/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/08/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2028026</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Judy</FirstName>
<LastName>Diamond</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Judy Diamond</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jdiamond1@unl.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000446856</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/08/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Julia</FirstName>
<LastName>McQuillan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Julia McQuillan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jmcquillan2@unl.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000113341</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/08/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Patricia</FirstName>
<LastName>Wonch Hill</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Patricia Wonch Hill</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[phill3@unl.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000629773</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/08/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Elizabeth</FirstName>
<LastName>VanWormer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Elizabeth VanWormer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[liz.vanwormer@unl.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000676940</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/08/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</Name>
<CityName>LINCOLN</CityName>
<ZipCode>685032427</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4024723171</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2200 VINE ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Nebraska</StateName>
<StateCode>NE</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NE01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>HTQ6K6NJFHA6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>BOARD OF REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF NEBRASKA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Nebraska-Lincoln]]></Name>
<CityName>Lincoln</CityName>
<StateCode>NE</StateCode>
<ZipCode>685880374</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[MORR 308]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Nebraska</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NE01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7259</Code>
<Text>AISL</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>4N20</Code>
<Name>EHR CARES Act DEFC N</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>040N2021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[EHR CARES Act DEFC N]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~200000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><em></em>The goal of the RAPID, <em>Using Popular Media to Educate Youth About the Biology of Viruses and the Current COVID-19 Pandemic</em>, was to establish a research foundation for better understanding how to educate youth about COVID-19 while generating new knowledge about effective methods for public science outreach during a major global challenge.</p> <p>In collaboration with virologists, artists, and the NE Commission Indian Affairs, the project developed 20 comics about COVID-19 during the pandemic and posted them weekly from June through December of 2020 on the website: <strong>worldofviruses.unl.edu</strong>. Each fictional narrative addressed fundamental issues in biology, virology, and public health to help readers understand the complexities of living through a viral pandemic. The stories focus on three themes: the biology of SARS-CoV-2; the relationship of animals, particularly bats, to the COVID-19 pandemic; and the impact of the pandemic on Tribal communities. The comics were disseminated in various ways. Individuals downloaded and printed the comics, and libraries embedded them in their website teen pages. We printed the comics as posters that were displayed in the Nebraska State Capitol for three weeks in May 2021, the NE State Office Building for Minority Health month of April 2021, and the McGoogan Library at the University of NE Medical Center during fall 2021. A book of our COVID-19 comics with essays for youth written by scientists was published by the University of Nebraska Press and distributed to 10,000 middle school students.</p> <p>Throughout the course of the project, we gathered feedback from youth and adult audiences. The Lincoln Public School district gave permission for us to survey 4<sup>th</sup> through 9<sup>th</sup> grade students. A total of 264 students completed the survey of 25 knowledge items about COVID-19, health prevention behaviors, viruses, vaccines, the immune system, and animals in public health. Students who received each comic set answered more questions correctly about that set than those who did not read that comic, and the results were statistically significant for all groups. Reading the comics was associated with 7 to 29% higher accuracy about COVID-19, varying by specific topics.</p> <p>Our surveys also examined how youth obtained information about COVID-19, the sources they used, and whether there was a relationship between the number of kinds of pandemic information sources and the accuracy of knowledge. The students relied on mainstream media, parents, school, and medical professionals. The idea that youth primarily learn most of what they know from social media was not supported by the present study. Multivariate models adjusting for relevant control variables showed a positive association between number of sources of information and COVID-19 relevant knowledge.</p> <p>Three manuscripts resulted from the project:</p> <p>Diamond, J., Spiegel, A., Hill, T.W., VanWormer, E., gaiashkibos, J., Hall, B., Sutherlen, A. and McQuillan, J. 2021. Developing pandemic comics for youth audiences. <em>Journal of STEM Outreach</em> 4(2): 1-10.</p> <p>Diamond, J., Hall, B., Sutherlen, A. (In Press) Viruses. In L. Diedrich and B. L. Martino (eds.) <em>Keywords and Keyimages in Graphic Medicine</em>. University Park: Penn State University Press.</p> <p>Wonch Hill, P., Diamond, J., McQuillan, J., Spiegel, A.N., VanWormer, E., Leadabrand, M. Accuracy of COVID-19 relevant knowledge among youth: Do sources of information matter? (Submitted to <em>PLOS ONE</em>).</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/01/2022<br>      Modified by: Judy&nbsp;Diamond</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The goal of the RAPID, Using Popular Media to Educate Youth About the Biology of Viruses and the Current COVID-19 Pandemic, was to establish a research foundation for better understanding how to educate youth about COVID-19 while generating new knowledge about effective methods for public science outreach during a major global challenge.  In collaboration with virologists, artists, and the NE Commission Indian Affairs, the project developed 20 comics about COVID-19 during the pandemic and posted them weekly from June through December of 2020 on the website: worldofviruses.unl.edu. Each fictional narrative addressed fundamental issues in biology, virology, and public health to help readers understand the complexities of living through a viral pandemic. The stories focus on three themes: the biology of SARS-CoV-2; the relationship of animals, particularly bats, to the COVID-19 pandemic; and the impact of the pandemic on Tribal communities. The comics were disseminated in various ways. Individuals downloaded and printed the comics, and libraries embedded them in their website teen pages. We printed the comics as posters that were displayed in the Nebraska State Capitol for three weeks in May 2021, the NE State Office Building for Minority Health month of April 2021, and the McGoogan Library at the University of NE Medical Center during fall 2021. A book of our COVID-19 comics with essays for youth written by scientists was published by the University of Nebraska Press and distributed to 10,000 middle school students.  Throughout the course of the project, we gathered feedback from youth and adult audiences. The Lincoln Public School district gave permission for us to survey 4th through 9th grade students. A total of 264 students completed the survey of 25 knowledge items about COVID-19, health prevention behaviors, viruses, vaccines, the immune system, and animals in public health. Students who received each comic set answered more questions correctly about that set than those who did not read that comic, and the results were statistically significant for all groups. Reading the comics was associated with 7 to 29% higher accuracy about COVID-19, varying by specific topics.  Our surveys also examined how youth obtained information about COVID-19, the sources they used, and whether there was a relationship between the number of kinds of pandemic information sources and the accuracy of knowledge. The students relied on mainstream media, parents, school, and medical professionals. The idea that youth primarily learn most of what they know from social media was not supported by the present study. Multivariate models adjusting for relevant control variables showed a positive association between number of sources of information and COVID-19 relevant knowledge.  Three manuscripts resulted from the project:  Diamond, J., Spiegel, A., Hill, T.W., VanWormer, E., gaiashkibos, J., Hall, B., Sutherlen, A. and McQuillan, J. 2021. Developing pandemic comics for youth audiences. Journal of STEM Outreach 4(2): 1-10.  Diamond, J., Hall, B., Sutherlen, A. (In Press) Viruses. In L. Diedrich and B. L. Martino (eds.) Keywords and Keyimages in Graphic Medicine. University Park: Penn State University Press.  Wonch Hill, P., Diamond, J., McQuillan, J., Spiegel, A.N., VanWormer, E., Leadabrand, M. Accuracy of COVID-19 relevant knowledge among youth: Do sources of information matter? (Submitted to PLOS ONE).       Last Modified: 08/01/2022       Submitted by: Judy Diamond]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
