<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Emerging Adults’ Daily Well-Being, Social Experiences, and Academic Persistence in the Context of the COVID-19 Pandemic]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>131978.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>131978</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anna V. Fisher</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>avfisher@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928451</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Rapid societal shifts associated with the COVID-19 pandemic have necessitated that education move online. Such shifts also increase students’ exposure to online discrimination, which can in turn negatively impact students’ academic performance and development. Prior research suggests that discrimination can push students away from pursuing STEM careers at a moment when a diverse, interdisciplinary STEM workforce is critical to confronting complex scientific challenges. In traditional in-person educational settings, positive interactions with diverse classmates and instructors can facilitate the maintenance of cognitive performance, educational attainment, and STEM participation despite negative experiences. Whether these positive interactions transfer to an online context, and whether they similarly buffer the effects of discrimination, is less understood. This study captures important daily variations in students’ well-being and academic outcomes that can inform future university practices regarding education and student wellness during crises. The findings may be of particular interest to educational institutions that have been forced to quickly shift to online instruction. As the COVID-19 pandemic demonstrates, there is a need for novel ideas and excellent leadership in STEM fields. This study will identify factors that may protect and promote STEM career outcomes.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project capitalizes on an existing ethnically diverse sample of college STEM majors who previously (pre-pandemic) reported on their daily in-class experiences, well-being, and academic outcomes. The present study collects additional data, using nearly identical methods, across two 7-day cycles. The project aims to: (1) Describe the frequency of daily discrimination experienced by college-aged ethnically diverse STEM majors; (2) Assess the extent to which rates of discrimination differ from their pre-pandemic levels; (3) Examine whether daily discrimination is correlated with STEM students’ day-to-day well-being, academic efficacy, and outcome expectations for their future STEM careers; and (4) Explore digital peer and university social supports as moderators of associations between daily discrimination and outcomes in a context of limited in-person interaction. Exploratory open-ended questions will identify participants’ educational experiences related to COVID-19.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/11/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/11/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2028034</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alysha</FirstName>
<LastName>Hall</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alysha R Hall</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[alysha.r.hall@asu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000703221</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/11/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Medina</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael A Medina</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mame@ucdavis.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000824367</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/11/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Adrienne</FirstName>
<LastName>Nishina</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Adrienne Nishina</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[anishina@ucdavis.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000535101</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/11/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Diana</FirstName>
<LastName>Meter</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Diana J Meter</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[diana.meter@usu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000824365</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/11/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Davis</Name>
<CityName>DAVIS</CityName>
<ZipCode>956186153</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5307547700</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1850 RESEARCH PARK DR, STE 300</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>TX2DAGQPENZ5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, DAVIS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>NUDGYLBB4S99</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Davis]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>956186134</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1698</Code>
<Text>DS -Developmental Sciences</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1698</Code>
<Text>DS-Developmental Sciences</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>1N20</Code>
<Name>R&amp;RA CARES Act DEFC N</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>010N2021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[R&RA CARES Act DEFC N]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~131978</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="Default">With the country still reeling from of the devastating COVID-19 pandemic, including its long-term impact on national education and healthcare, young people need ample academic and socioemotional support. However, there is growing evidence that ethnic-racial minority youth and adults alike are instead being subjected to discrimination and unequal treatment, both interpersonally and via media. In this study, a diverse college-aged sample of STEM majors relayed their academic and personal experiences during this crisis. Furthermore, the longitudinal nature of our data allowed us to cross-reference these findings with students&rsquo; past reports of these factors prior to the COVID-19 pandemic. This work also uniquely provided the ability to study day-to-day stability and change in young people&rsquo;s experiences across the pandemic and contexts.</p> <p>To address this topic, we sought to examine a series of pointed and timely questions. First, what is the frequency of daily environmental and proximal microaggressions experienced by college-aged STEM students, including Asian American students and students who may have been vicariously or directly impacted by discrimination experiences during the pandemic? Second, how might these experiences impact minority youth&rsquo;s stress day-to-day during and after student learning was shifted exclusively online. Third, what might be the mental and physical health impacts of environmental microaggressions among these students as compared to data collected from the same participants prior to the COVID-19 pandemic?</p> <p class="Default">We assessed these questions through a variety of methods. We gathered an ethnically diverse sample of college students and administered to them daily electronic surveys. These surveys, containing quantitative and qualitative measures, inquired about students&rsquo; daily personal and academic experiences, and specifically how they might have changed since the beginning of the COVID-19 pandemic. Student surveys also included measures assessing their daily experiences during the pandemic of microaggressions, ethnic identity beliefs, diversity exposure, and other race- and discrimination-related perceptions and experiences.</p> <p class="Default">Our initial findings indicate that most of the young people in our study reported experiencing some form of vicarious ethnic-racial discrimination at some point across the data collection waves. In addition, some study participants reported experiencing some form of direct ethnic-racial discrimination. However, in general these experiences were fairly low infrequency. Furthermore, we have begun to examine the qualitative data related to students online learning experiences during the pandemic. Both stressors and factors that were helpful in the learning process largely centered around social relationships with instructors and with peers. For example, eliciting social support from others and experiencing empathy and concern from instructors were particularly helpful to students.</p> <p class="Default">These and a number of additional threads of research have been, and will continue to be, disseminated through presentations, writings, and our newly informed work with schools and student-supporting communities. Specifically, our planned and future manuscripts will be useful in fields such as education (e.g., STEM; higher ed), psychology, human development, and sociology. In addition, findings from our sample of college-aged STEM majors could directly relate to how institutions of higher education conduct their human resources practices in relation to student success and well-being. Moreover, the context of online education during the pandemic can provide additional insight as to how to best support ethnically/racially diverse STEM students who may engage in online learning. This project&rsquo;s provided insights into students&rsquo; life experiences in relation to social ethnic-racial biases, and the outcomes thereof, will speak to each of these and other domains.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/29/2023<br>      Modified by: Michael&nbsp;A&nbsp;Medina</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[With the country still reeling from of the devastating COVID-19 pandemic, including its long-term impact on national education and healthcare, young people need ample academic and socioemotional support. However, there is growing evidence that ethnic-racial minority youth and adults alike are instead being subjected to discrimination and unequal treatment, both interpersonally and via media. In this study, a diverse college-aged sample of STEM majors relayed their academic and personal experiences during this crisis. Furthermore, the longitudinal nature of our data allowed us to cross-reference these findings with students’ past reports of these factors prior to the COVID-19 pandemic. This work also uniquely provided the ability to study day-to-day stability and change in young people’s experiences across the pandemic and contexts.  To address this topic, we sought to examine a series of pointed and timely questions. First, what is the frequency of daily environmental and proximal microaggressions experienced by college-aged STEM students, including Asian American students and students who may have been vicariously or directly impacted by discrimination experiences during the pandemic? Second, how might these experiences impact minority youth’s stress day-to-day during and after student learning was shifted exclusively online. Third, what might be the mental and physical health impacts of environmental microaggressions among these students as compared to data collected from the same participants prior to the COVID-19 pandemic? We assessed these questions through a variety of methods. We gathered an ethnically diverse sample of college students and administered to them daily electronic surveys. These surveys, containing quantitative and qualitative measures, inquired about students’ daily personal and academic experiences, and specifically how they might have changed since the beginning of the COVID-19 pandemic. Student surveys also included measures assessing their daily experiences during the pandemic of microaggressions, ethnic identity beliefs, diversity exposure, and other race- and discrimination-related perceptions and experiences. Our initial findings indicate that most of the young people in our study reported experiencing some form of vicarious ethnic-racial discrimination at some point across the data collection waves. In addition, some study participants reported experiencing some form of direct ethnic-racial discrimination. However, in general these experiences were fairly low infrequency. Furthermore, we have begun to examine the qualitative data related to students online learning experiences during the pandemic. Both stressors and factors that were helpful in the learning process largely centered around social relationships with instructors and with peers. For example, eliciting social support from others and experiencing empathy and concern from instructors were particularly helpful to students. These and a number of additional threads of research have been, and will continue to be, disseminated through presentations, writings, and our newly informed work with schools and student-supporting communities. Specifically, our planned and future manuscripts will be useful in fields such as education (e.g., STEM; higher ed), psychology, human development, and sociology. In addition, findings from our sample of college-aged STEM majors could directly relate to how institutions of higher education conduct their human resources practices in relation to student success and well-being. Moreover, the context of online education during the pandemic can provide additional insight as to how to best support ethnically/racially diverse STEM students who may engage in online learning. This project’s provided insights into students’ life experiences in relation to social ethnic-racial biases, and the outcomes thereof, will speak to each of these and other domains.       Last Modified: 09/29/2023       Submitted by: Michael A Medina]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
