<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome Coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2)-Prevention: Multiple-Site Binding with Fusing Aptamers to mitigate Coronavirus Disease 2019]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>200000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>200000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Pui Ho</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>puiho@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032920000</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The SARS-CoV-2 causes the novel coronavirus infectious disease 2019 (COVID-19). The binding of the viral spike protein to a receptor protein (called the angiotensin converting enzyme 2, or ACE2) is the first step in the infection of the human host cell. Blocking or inhibiting this interaction could stop the invasion of the human cell by this highly infectious virus. With this award, the Chemistry of Life Processes program is supporting the research of Dr. Xiaohong Tan at Bowling Green University in Bowling Green, Ohio to create DNA aptamers to inhibit this initial step of viral invasion. Aptamers are short sequences of DNA that fold into a shape that matches that of a target molecule, thereby keeping other molecules from binding. These DNA aptamers are “designed” by successive selection of molecules from large mixtures of different sequences, resulting in a few sequences that keep all other DNAs from binding the target. Dr. Tan uses this selection process to find DNA aptamers that bind tightly to the SARS-CoV-2 spike protein. Two of more of the identified DNA aptamers are linked together to create “super binders” that are much better at inhibiting the interaction than would any single aptamer. Constructing DNA aptamers that block the invasion of SARS-CoV-2 into human cells may lead to the design of antiviral agents that help lessen the infectivity that causes the COVID-19 pandemic.  Educational and training activities will focus on postdoctoral researchers learning cutting edge techniques in chemical biology on a “front line” research problem. The team is developing ways to communicate their science to the public, to K-12 institutions, and to other research groups using distance learning technologies.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of this project is to develop polymeric molecules (fusion DNA aptamers) that significantly interact with the binding domain of SARS-CoV-2. The objective is to effectively block the virus from binding to the specific ACE2 receptor, thereby blocking the entry of the virus into human cells and, as a result, its ability to cause COVID-19 infections.  Professor Tan uses SELEX (systematic evolution of ligands by exponential enrichment) to identify individual aptamers that interact with three distinct regions on the cell binding domain of the spike (S) protein of SARS-CoV-2. The affinities of aptamers to their targets are measured through standard binding assays. These individual high affinity DNA aptamers are connected together using nucleic acid or chemical linkers to make fusion aptamers that have affinities comparable to those of antibodies. The ability of these fused DNA aptamer “super binders” to effectively block this interaction is tested against a recombinant SARS-CoV-2 spike protein using standard technologies, as well as live SARS-CoV-2 through collaboration with the University of Toledo Medical School.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/16/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/16/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2028531</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Xiaohong</FirstName>
<LastName>Tan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Xiaohong Tan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[tanx@bgsu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000824255</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/16/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Bowling Green State University</Name>
<CityName>BOWLING GREEN</CityName>
<ZipCode>434034401</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4193722481</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1851 N RESEARCH DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OH05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>SLT3EB6G3FA9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>BOWLING GREEN STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Bowling Green State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Bowling Green</CityName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>434030001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[211 Physical Sciences Lab Bldg]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OH05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>158Y</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>1N20</Code>
<Name>R&amp;RA CARES Act DEFC N</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>010N2021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[R&RA CARES Act DEFC N]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~200000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) uses its spike-protein to attach to the host cell via human angiotensin converting enzyme 2 (hACE2). One spike-protein trimer includes three spike-proteins, and each of them is composed of the subunits S1 and S2. S1 has the receptor-binding domain (RBD), establishing the direct interaction with hACE2. S2 plays a function in mediating the fusion of the viral membrane to the host cell.</p> <p>Nobody knows when the COVID-19 pandemic will end or when and where the next coronavirus will outbreak. Therefore, it is still necessary to develop SARS-CoV-2 inhibitors for different variants or even the new coronavirus. Since SARS-CoV-2 uses its surface spike-protein to recognize hACE2, mediating its entry into cells, ligands that can specifically recognize the spike-protein have the potential to prevent infection.</p> <p>We reported DNA aptamer based ligands to efficiently and specifically block this interaction: 1) We discovered the universal aptamer A1C1, binding to the spike-protein of WT, Delta or Omicron variant with low nanomolar affinities. A1C1 inhibits the interaction between hACE2 and various spike-proteins by 85&ndash;89%; 2) We discovered the first anti-S2 aptamer, S2A2C1, which inhibits the hACE2/spike-protein interaction via an RBD-independent approach. The anti-S2 and anti-RBD aptamers were conjugated to obtain the fusion aptamer, S1B6C3-A5-S2A2C1, which recognizes the spike-protein by an RBD-dependent approach. Anti-spike-protein fusion aptamers maintain high binding affinity toward the WT, Delta, and Omicron spike-proteins and high inhibition efficacies to prevent them from binding to hACE2. Our strategies, which discovered aptamer inhibitors targeting the highly conserved S2-protein, as well as the design of fusion aptamers, can be used to target new coronaviruses as they emerge.</p> <p>All of our aptamers can be used as diagnostic and therapeutic molecular tools to target SARS-CoV-2 and its variants.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/03/2022<br>      Modified by: Xiaohong&nbsp;Tan</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2028531/2028531_10664757_1667488907629_coverimage--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2028531/2028531_10664757_1667488907629_coverimage--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Fusion aptamers block SARS-CoV-2"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2028531/2028531_10664757_1667488907629_coverimage--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Fusion aptamers block SARS-CoV-2"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Anti-spike-protein DNA fusion aptamers maintain high binding affinity toward the WT, Delta, and Omicron spike-proteins and high inhibition efficacies to prevent them from binding to hACE2, rendering them well-suited as diagnostic and therapeutic molecular tools to target SARS-CoV-2 and its variants.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Tan lab in BGSU</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Xiaohong&nbsp;Tan</div> <div class="imageTitle">Fusion aptamers block SARS-CoV-2</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) uses its spike-protein to attach to the host cell via human angiotensin converting enzyme 2 (hACE2). One spike-protein trimer includes three spike-proteins, and each of them is composed of the subunits S1 and S2. S1 has the receptor-binding domain (RBD), establishing the direct interaction with hACE2. S2 plays a function in mediating the fusion of the viral membrane to the host cell.  Nobody knows when the COVID-19 pandemic will end or when and where the next coronavirus will outbreak. Therefore, it is still necessary to develop SARS-CoV-2 inhibitors for different variants or even the new coronavirus. Since SARS-CoV-2 uses its surface spike-protein to recognize hACE2, mediating its entry into cells, ligands that can specifically recognize the spike-protein have the potential to prevent infection.  We reported DNA aptamer based ligands to efficiently and specifically block this interaction: 1) We discovered the universal aptamer A1C1, binding to the spike-protein of WT, Delta or Omicron variant with low nanomolar affinities. A1C1 inhibits the interaction between hACE2 and various spike-proteins by 85&ndash;89%; 2) We discovered the first anti-S2 aptamer, S2A2C1, which inhibits the hACE2/spike-protein interaction via an RBD-independent approach. The anti-S2 and anti-RBD aptamers were conjugated to obtain the fusion aptamer, S1B6C3-A5-S2A2C1, which recognizes the spike-protein by an RBD-dependent approach. Anti-spike-protein fusion aptamers maintain high binding affinity toward the WT, Delta, and Omicron spike-proteins and high inhibition efficacies to prevent them from binding to hACE2. Our strategies, which discovered aptamer inhibitors targeting the highly conserved S2-protein, as well as the design of fusion aptamers, can be used to target new coronaviruses as they emerge.  All of our aptamers can be used as diagnostic and therapeutic molecular tools to target SARS-CoV-2 and its variants.          Last Modified: 11/03/2022       Submitted by: Xiaohong Tan]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
