<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[EAGER: SARE: Collaborative Research: Exploring and Mitigating Attacks of Millimeter-wave Radar Sensors in Autonomous Vehicles]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>170000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>170000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ECCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ale Lukaszew</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rlukasze@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928103</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Autonomous vehicles (AVs) have significant potentials to improve road safety, travel experience and transportation footprint, as well as the mobility and accessibility for all. However, the safety and security of AVs themselves have raised many concerns in recent years. As AVs use a plethora of sensors, including cameras and radars to detect, classify and track objects and obstacles on the road, their reliability and resilience have significant impacts on AV safety. Although risks from malicious attacks targeted at cameras and other sensors in AV systems have been studied, there is a lack of in-depth understanding of the vulnerability of millimeter-wave radar sensors in AVs. This EArly-concept Grant for Exploratory Research (EAGER) project seeks to explore insights to improve the security and resilience of AVs by investigating advanced attack and defense methods for millimeter-wave radar sensor-based systems. Since these radars are used exclusively today for adaptive cruise control, blind-spot detection, and collision avoidance, this project will benefit many safety-critical applications. The PIs plan to expand research opportunities for K-12 and underrepresented students, and integrate diversity in broadening participation in engineering through the educational programs of National Summer Transportation Institute (NSTI), Institute for Sustainable Transportation and Logistics (ISTL) and Louis Stokes Alliance for Minority Participation (LSAMP) at the University at Buffalo. The PIs will disseminate the results of the project through publications, talks, and demos, and integrate research materials into specific courses and education curricula. All newly developed research and teaching materials will be publicly accessible on the project website. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will first demonstrate that the millimeter-wave radar sensors can be spoofed and jammed while AVs are on the road through a non-cooperative over-the-air synchronization method. It can accurately identify the frequency band, modulation scheme and waveform patterns of victim radars to launch stealthy attacks. The team will conduct a proof-of-concept demo to attack real-world AV radars with fast-chirp signals. Second, the project will explore both hardware and software/algorithm-based defense mechanisms for avoiding such attacks, including beam feature based physical layer capacity estimation, machine learning physical identification, non-cooperative passive front-end architectures and band-limited coherent noise radars. The innovation of the project comes from not only the use of adaptive finite state machine based approaches that combine inter- and intra-chirp-sequence synchronization, but also data modeling techniques to efficiently adjust the attacker’s waveform parameters. Moreover, the project is among the first to explore the use of unique radiometrics, noise radars and passive radars as effective defense mechanisms against the attacks to AVs. Research thrusts in this project will significantly advance the state-of-the-art knowledge of the security of millimeter-wave sensors, and provide insights on developing more undeceivable, disclosure-resistant and robust AV radar solutions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/29/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/29/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2028872</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Chunming</FirstName>
<LastName>Qiao</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Chunming Qiao</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[qiao@computer.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000221592</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/29/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Wenyao</FirstName>
<LastName>Xu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Wenyao Xu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[wenyaoxu@buffalo.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000647900</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/29/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>SUNY at Buffalo</Name>
<CityName>AMHERST</CityName>
<ZipCode>142282577</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7166452634</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>520 LEE ENTRANCE STE 211</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>26</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY26</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>LMCJKRFW5R81</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH FOUNDATION FOR THE STATE UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>GMZUKXFDJMA9</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[SUNY at Buffalo]]></Name>
<CityName>Buffalo</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>142602500</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[338 Davis Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>26</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY26</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7564</Code>
<Text>CCSS-Comms Circuits &amp; Sens Sys</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~170000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>In the realm of technological innovation, autonomous vehicles (AVs) stand as a pinnacle of progress, promising to redefine transportation and mobility in the years to come. However, as we navigate through this futuristic landscape, ensuring the utmost security and resilience of these self-navigating machines is of paramount importance. Our project, spanning across extensive research and practical applications, delved deep into the intricacies of millimeter-wave radar sensor-based systems - a critical component in AV navigation. We aimed to dissect and understand the potential vulnerabilities of these systems, shedding light on sophisticated attack and defense mechanisms. Through rigorous experimentation and innovative methodologies, our team unveiled the susceptibility of millimeter-wave radar sensors to advanced spoofing and jamming attacks, particularly when AVs are cruising on the open road. This revelation underscored the urgent need for fortified defense strategies, leading us to explore both hardware and software-based solutions to shield these vehicles from potential threats. Our research through this complex terrain of security and resilience demonstrated the development of groundbreaking passive attack techniques and a suite of robust defense mechanisms, setting a new benchmark in the field of autonomous vehicle security.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The narrative of our project is characterized by innovation, determination, and a relentless pursuit of knowledge. We embarked on a quest to understand and mitigate the vulnerabilities of millimeter-wave radar sensors, recognizing their critical role in the autonomous driving ecosystem. Our approach was multifaceted, involving a comprehensive analysis of attack vectors, the development of innovative defense strategies, and a deep dive into the practical implications of our findings. The core of our project revolved around MetaWave, a novel passive millimeter-wave attack technique that utilized low-cost meta-material tags to manipulate mmWave echo signals, misleading crucial sensing measurements such as range, angle, and speed. This technique demonstrated a startling efficacy, achieving attack accuracy levels of up to 97% in range estimation, 96% in angle estimation, and 91% in speed estimation, all while maintaining a cost that was significantly lower than existing solutions.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The practical implications of our work extend far beyond the confines of the laboratory. In the bustling world of autonomous driving, millimeter-wave radar is a linchpin for object detection, revered for its resilience against adverse weather and lighting conditions. With the integration of deep neural networks (DNNs), radar object detection has witnessed a paradigm shift, enhancing the precision and decision-making capabilities of autonomous vehicles. However, this technological leap has not been without its challenges. Our project identified a critical vulnerability in DNN-based radar object detection models, exposing them to the risk of adversarial attacks. We addressed this issue head-on, exploring passive-reflection-based attacks using adversarial objects crafted from 3D printing and metal foils. These low-cost, easily disguised geometric objects proved to be a game-changer, deceiving radar detection systems with remarkable ease and stealth.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Education and community engagement were integral components of our project. We were driven by a commitment to fostering diversity and inclusivity in STEM fields, providing mentorship and support to multiple PhD students and undergraduates from underrepresented backgrounds. Our outreach efforts extended to the community, where we conducted educational workshops, engaged with K-12 students and their families, and showcased the potential and intricacies of mmWave sensing applications in AVs. These initiatives served not only to disseminate knowledge but also to inspire the next generation of innovators and thinkers.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>As we reflect on the journey and accomplishments of our project, the impact of our work resonates across various spheres. Our contributions to the field of autonomous vehicle security have been widely recognized and disseminated through publications, journal articles, and workshop presentations. The attention and interest from national and international media outlets further validate the significance and timeliness of our research. In the end, our project stands as a testament to the power of innovation, collaboration, and a unwavering commitment to advancing the safety and security of autonomous vehicles. We have set the stage for future endeavors, paving the way for more secure, resilient, and robust radar solutions, ensuring that the autonomous vehicles of tomorrow navigate safely and securely.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/31/2023<br>      Modified by: Wenyao&nbsp;Xu</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ In the realm of technological innovation, autonomous vehicles (AVs) stand as a pinnacle of progress, promising to redefine transportation and mobility in the years to come. However, as we navigate through this futuristic landscape, ensuring the utmost security and resilience of these self-navigating machines is of paramount importance. Our project, spanning across extensive research and practical applications, delved deep into the intricacies of millimeter-wave radar sensor-based systems - a critical component in AV navigation. We aimed to dissect and understand the potential vulnerabilities of these systems, shedding light on sophisticated attack and defense mechanisms. Through rigorous experimentation and innovative methodologies, our team unveiled the susceptibility of millimeter-wave radar sensors to advanced spoofing and jamming attacks, particularly when AVs are cruising on the open road. This revelation underscored the urgent need for fortified defense strategies, leading us to explore both hardware and software-based solutions to shield these vehicles from potential threats. Our research through this complex terrain of security and resilience demonstrated the development of groundbreaking passive attack techniques and a suite of robust defense mechanisms, setting a new benchmark in the field of autonomous vehicle security.     The narrative of our project is characterized by innovation, determination, and a relentless pursuit of knowledge. We embarked on a quest to understand and mitigate the vulnerabilities of millimeter-wave radar sensors, recognizing their critical role in the autonomous driving ecosystem. Our approach was multifaceted, involving a comprehensive analysis of attack vectors, the development of innovative defense strategies, and a deep dive into the practical implications of our findings. The core of our project revolved around MetaWave, a novel passive millimeter-wave attack technique that utilized low-cost meta-material tags to manipulate mmWave echo signals, misleading crucial sensing measurements such as range, angle, and speed. This technique demonstrated a startling efficacy, achieving attack accuracy levels of up to 97% in range estimation, 96% in angle estimation, and 91% in speed estimation, all while maintaining a cost that was significantly lower than existing solutions.     The practical implications of our work extend far beyond the confines of the laboratory. In the bustling world of autonomous driving, millimeter-wave radar is a linchpin for object detection, revered for its resilience against adverse weather and lighting conditions. With the integration of deep neural networks (DNNs), radar object detection has witnessed a paradigm shift, enhancing the precision and decision-making capabilities of autonomous vehicles. However, this technological leap has not been without its challenges. Our project identified a critical vulnerability in DNN-based radar object detection models, exposing them to the risk of adversarial attacks. We addressed this issue head-on, exploring passive-reflection-based attacks using adversarial objects crafted from 3D printing and metal foils. These low-cost, easily disguised geometric objects proved to be a game-changer, deceiving radar detection systems with remarkable ease and stealth.     Education and community engagement were integral components of our project. We were driven by a commitment to fostering diversity and inclusivity in STEM fields, providing mentorship and support to multiple PhD students and undergraduates from underrepresented backgrounds. Our outreach efforts extended to the community, where we conducted educational workshops, engaged with K-12 students and their families, and showcased the potential and intricacies of mmWave sensing applications in AVs. These initiatives served not only to disseminate knowledge but also to inspire the next generation of innovators and thinkers.     As we reflect on the journey and accomplishments of our project, the impact of our work resonates across various spheres. Our contributions to the field of autonomous vehicle security have been widely recognized and disseminated through publications, journal articles, and workshop presentations. The attention and interest from national and international media outlets further validate the significance and timeliness of our research. In the end, our project stands as a testament to the power of innovation, collaboration, and a unwavering commitment to advancing the safety and security of autonomous vehicles. We have set the stage for future endeavors, paving the way for more secure, resilient, and robust radar solutions, ensuring that the autonomous vehicles of tomorrow navigate safely and securely.       Last Modified: 10/31/2023       Submitted by: Wenyao Xu]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
