<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: THE CORONAVIRUS PANDEMIC: PREDICTORS AND CONSEQUENCES OF COMPLIANCE WITH SOCIAL DISTANCING RECOMMENDATIONS]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>200000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>200000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Melanie Hughes</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mehughes@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927318</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The need for social distancing measures implemented in the wake of the novel coronavirus pandemic is well established, but few studies have examined variability in compliance with this public health recommendation. It is particularly important to understand the social factors associated with this variability. This project builds on an ongoing longitudinal study of the life and relationship experiences of a large, diverse sample of young people interviewed first as adolescents, and subsequently interviewed multiple times as they have become adults. This provides an opportunity to interview these women and men to understand the process of navigating the guidelines, including: a) what factors predict more and less compliant responses to the social distancing guidelines; and b) what are the consequences of social distancing for emotional health, behavioral health, and relationship functioning. The findings of the project will alert researchers and policymakers to the myriad of personal and background characteristics that are associated with more or less compliance.  This information will allow for the crafting of more effective public policies and messaging about social distancing, with the goal of promoting faster and more complete compliance during future pandemics. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Social distancing is a vital tool in fighting the COVID-19 pandemic, but we know little about who complies with guidelines and who does not.  This project will draw on six waves of previously collected survey data (n=1,321) from the Toledo Adolescent Relationships Study (TARS) and a new COVID-19 online survey that will be administered to all respondents. These longitudinal data provide a unique opportunity to examine precursors and consequences of variations in response to the current social distancing guidelines. The design also includes in-depth phone interviews with a subset of respondents who were compliant (n=25) and others who did not change behavior or failed to comply consistently (n=25). The qualitative component will provide help to understand compliance as a process, and develop insights about the role of social networks in either encouraging or minimizing the need to  comply. In addition to assessing the role of sociodemographic characteristics, the project will analyze the effects of prior adverse childhood and adolescent experiences, economic and social uncertainties, and network embeddedness as influences on levels of compliance. The availability of previous measures of social and behavioral health and prior relationship circumstances will allow the project to determine effects of social distancing and the experience of the pandemic, controlling for prior background. The project will also examine whether consistent reports of depression at prior waves exacerbate or dampen the effect of the recent experience of social distancing. The emphasis on social determinants provides a counterpoint to approaches that conceptualize compliance with health-promoting recommendations as an individualistic, largely cognitive process, and more broadly, will contribute to the emerging science of behavior change.  Findings will inform sociological theories regarding identity and symbolic interaction, as well as theories of inequality, especially within the context of extreme events.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/20/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/20/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2028429</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Peggy</FirstName>
<LastName>Giordano</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Peggy C Giordano</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[pgiorda@bgsu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000395371</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/20/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Monica</FirstName>
<LastName>Longmore</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Monica A Longmore</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mseff@bgsu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000701459</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/20/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Wendy</FirstName>
<LastName>Manning</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Wendy D Manning</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[wmannin@bgsu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000701460</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/20/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Bowling Green State University</Name>
<CityName>BOWLING GREEN</CityName>
<ZipCode>434034401</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4193722481</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1851 N RESEARCH DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OH05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>SLT3EB6G3FA9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>BOWLING GREEN STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Bowling Green State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Bowling Green</CityName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>434030001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[215 Williams Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OH05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1331</Code>
<Text>Sociology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>1N20</Code>
<Name>R&amp;RA CARES Act DEFC N</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>010N2021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[R&RA CARES Act DEFC N]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~200000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This mixed-method project drew on a longitudinal data collection effort, a new survey focused on the pandemic, and in-depth interviews with a subset of respondents. This approach permitted examination of sources of variability in compliance with public health recommendations related to social distancing, and effects of navigating this unique period for a variety of well-being outcomes. Analyses examined a range of predictors of compliance, but results underscored the important role of social relationships in decision-making processes and behavioral choices. Respondents' reports about compliance were systematically related to parents', friends', and partners' own behaviors, controlling for other relevant factors. Consistent with other studies, health beliefs were related to compliance, but analyses also revealed that those with more liberal political views and individuals who endorsed altruistic considerations (i.e., distancing to protect others) were more likely to comply. Further, analysis showed that social distancing compliance was more common among women, those with greater educational attainment, and those with the ability to work from home during the pandemic. Importantly, the qualitative analyses provided additional information about aspects of respondents? lives (e.g., housing circumstances, complicated family lives) that influenced the ability to comply. In addition, these interviews demonstrated limitations of the view of individuals as either compliant or non-compliant, as many respondents made significant efforts to social distance, but did not do so across all contexts and situations. These analyses suggested the need to move beyond a static conception of social distancing, as the narratives include many references to change over time. These analyses also underscored that with respect to views about social distancing, individuals often constructed a kind of patchwork of beliefs that were not always fact-based, consistent, or associated with effective social distancing. The results suggest the importance of attending to the fluidity and complexity of social distancing processes, and the social considerations and pressures that affect variability in compliance. &nbsp;</p> <p>The longitudinal design supported other analyses focused on social distancing and effects of the pandemic that demonstrated the importance of recognizing pre-pandemic health and behavior starting points. To illustrate, individuals with pre-pandemic physical health diagnoses believed their health was at greater risk during the pandemic but were not more likely to comply with social distancing recommendations. In contrast, respondents who had pre-pandemic mental health diagnoses did not experience elevated perceptions of health risks but more often social distanced. Another analysis examined changes in stress among parents, and results revealed increases in stress for both mothers and fathers. Nevertheless, for mothers, spending less time with children was associated with increased stress, while for fathers spending <em>more</em> time with children was associated with increased stress. We also found that parents who experienced difficulties related to their children were more likely to increase the frequency of their drinking. In another paper we focused on the impact of the pandemic on stress among individuals who reported engaging in criminal and antisocial behaviors prior to the pandemic. These individuals experienced higher levels of overall stress relative to individuals with more settled lives, but we observed no increases during the pandemic in stress levels. Conversely, the more settled individuals reported significant increases in stress. This corresponds to the idea that the latter might have less experience with the array of concerns related to life during the pandemic, while the life challenges of those with a criminal background might have outweighed pandemic-related concerns.&nbsp;</p> <p>In more fundamental analyses focusing on emotional well-being, we found overall increases in anxiety and depression, but results again demonstrated the need to take into account health starting points. That is, most individuals who experienced the pandemic with prior high levels of depression or anxiety continued this pattern, but there were improvements in mental health for some individuals. For example, 25% of individuals who reported high depression pre-pandemic experienced declines and 65% who had no depressive symptoms experienced increases during the pandemic. A more refined analysis documented that greater economic hardship was associated with increased depression levels, but the receipt of public assistance was associated with improved mental health. This demonstrates the importance of public assistance not only for economic but also for emotional well-being, particularly during challenging periods such as the recent pandemic. In a final paper focused on conflict in intimate relationships, in contrast to some early reports, we found overall increases in verbal conflict during the pandemic, but on average declines in intimate partner violence. Only a small percentage (5%) of couples who had not experienced intimate partner violence prior to the pandemic engaged in physical violence during the pandemic. Nevertheless, individuals who experienced more economic hardship, relationship uncertainty, and stress reported increases in intimate partner violence. These results suggest some limitations of global statements about increases in intimate partner violence, the importance of taking into account pre-pandemic circumstances, and the emotional and economic variability in the way the pandemic has been experienced.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/22/2022<br>      Modified by: Peggy&nbsp;C&nbsp;Giordano</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This mixed-method project drew on a longitudinal data collection effort, a new survey focused on the pandemic, and in-depth interviews with a subset of respondents. This approach permitted examination of sources of variability in compliance with public health recommendations related to social distancing, and effects of navigating this unique period for a variety of well-being outcomes. Analyses examined a range of predictors of compliance, but results underscored the important role of social relationships in decision-making processes and behavioral choices. Respondents' reports about compliance were systematically related to parents', friends', and partners' own behaviors, controlling for other relevant factors. Consistent with other studies, health beliefs were related to compliance, but analyses also revealed that those with more liberal political views and individuals who endorsed altruistic considerations (i.e., distancing to protect others) were more likely to comply. Further, analysis showed that social distancing compliance was more common among women, those with greater educational attainment, and those with the ability to work from home during the pandemic. Importantly, the qualitative analyses provided additional information about aspects of respondents? lives (e.g., housing circumstances, complicated family lives) that influenced the ability to comply. In addition, these interviews demonstrated limitations of the view of individuals as either compliant or non-compliant, as many respondents made significant efforts to social distance, but did not do so across all contexts and situations. These analyses suggested the need to move beyond a static conception of social distancing, as the narratives include many references to change over time. These analyses also underscored that with respect to views about social distancing, individuals often constructed a kind of patchwork of beliefs that were not always fact-based, consistent, or associated with effective social distancing. The results suggest the importance of attending to the fluidity and complexity of social distancing processes, and the social considerations and pressures that affect variability in compliance.    The longitudinal design supported other analyses focused on social distancing and effects of the pandemic that demonstrated the importance of recognizing pre-pandemic health and behavior starting points. To illustrate, individuals with pre-pandemic physical health diagnoses believed their health was at greater risk during the pandemic but were not more likely to comply with social distancing recommendations. In contrast, respondents who had pre-pandemic mental health diagnoses did not experience elevated perceptions of health risks but more often social distanced. Another analysis examined changes in stress among parents, and results revealed increases in stress for both mothers and fathers. Nevertheless, for mothers, spending less time with children was associated with increased stress, while for fathers spending more time with children was associated with increased stress. We also found that parents who experienced difficulties related to their children were more likely to increase the frequency of their drinking. In another paper we focused on the impact of the pandemic on stress among individuals who reported engaging in criminal and antisocial behaviors prior to the pandemic. These individuals experienced higher levels of overall stress relative to individuals with more settled lives, but we observed no increases during the pandemic in stress levels. Conversely, the more settled individuals reported significant increases in stress. This corresponds to the idea that the latter might have less experience with the array of concerns related to life during the pandemic, while the life challenges of those with a criminal background might have outweighed pandemic-related concerns.   In more fundamental analyses focusing on emotional well-being, we found overall increases in anxiety and depression, but results again demonstrated the need to take into account health starting points. That is, most individuals who experienced the pandemic with prior high levels of depression or anxiety continued this pattern, but there were improvements in mental health for some individuals. For example, 25% of individuals who reported high depression pre-pandemic experienced declines and 65% who had no depressive symptoms experienced increases during the pandemic. A more refined analysis documented that greater economic hardship was associated with increased depression levels, but the receipt of public assistance was associated with improved mental health. This demonstrates the importance of public assistance not only for economic but also for emotional well-being, particularly during challenging periods such as the recent pandemic. In a final paper focused on conflict in intimate relationships, in contrast to some early reports, we found overall increases in verbal conflict during the pandemic, but on average declines in intimate partner violence. Only a small percentage (5%) of couples who had not experienced intimate partner violence prior to the pandemic engaged in physical violence during the pandemic. Nevertheless, individuals who experienced more economic hardship, relationship uncertainty, and stress reported increases in intimate partner violence. These results suggest some limitations of global statements about increases in intimate partner violence, the importance of taking into account pre-pandemic circumstances, and the emotional and economic variability in the way the pandemic has been experienced.           Last Modified: 08/22/2022       Submitted by: Peggy C Giordano]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
