<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Pandemic School Closures and Teacher-Student Relationships]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>150763.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>150763</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joseph Whitmeyer</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jwhitmey@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927808</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This project assesses how new efforts and strategies for action, developed due to the COVID-19 pandemic, challenge or compound pre-existing differences among students.  Existing scholarship predicts that during crises, people and organizations develop new strategies for action. As a consequence of the COVID-19 pandemic, more than half of America’s schools have closed down and transitioned to online learning.  This constitutes a unique natural experiment in how a crisis and uncertainty can affect teacher-student relationships (TSRs) and how these in turn can affect differences.  The current crisis may strengthen TSRs as teachers and schools reach out to students in novel ways and normally non-academic matters such as student’s health and access to the internet at home become priorities.  This study will help policymakers and school officials understand the impact of the COVID-19 pandemic and resulting school closures on different groups of students, informing efforts to redress the effects of this crisis and plan for future disasters.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project expands upon six months of ethnographic observations in two Virginia high schools (conducted prior to school closures) with online observations, interviews and weekly student time diaries and photojournals during the spring and summer of 2020, as well as resumed in-person data collection during fall 2020. Broadly, this project advances knowledge by showing 1) how school and teacher strategies to reach students during this crisis are received; 2) how TSRs change during moments of crisis and 3) how these changes inform differences in student experiences and outcomes.  Specific research questions include: (1) How do TSRs shape the impact of the crisis on student engagement and outcomes? (2) How does the ongoing impact of TSRs vary by student background? (3) How does school response to the crisis affect teachers’ connections with students? and (4) How does the impact of this response vary based on student background? To address these questions, this study’s data collection includes eight months of observations (both virtual and in-person when schools re-open), collection of weekly student time diaries and photojournals (N=80), and in-depth semi-structured interviews with administrators (N=20), students (N=120) and teachers (N=60).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/01/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/01/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2028331</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Allison</FirstName>
<LastName>Pugh</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Allison Pugh</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[apugh@virginia.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000170910</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/01/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Virginia Main Campus</Name>
<CityName>CHARLOTTESVILLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>229034833</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4349244270</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1001 EMMET ST N</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>VA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>JJG6HU8PA4S5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RECTOR &amp; VISITORS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Virginia Main Campus]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>229044766</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>VA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1331</Code>
<Text>Sociology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>1N20</Code>
<Name>R&amp;RA CARES Act DEFC N</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>010N2021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[R&RA CARES Act DEFC N]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~150763</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-a5df6243-7fff-7494-36da-9a0bd89200c3"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Project Outcomes Report</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>This project sought to assess how teacher and school efforts to respond to the Covid19 pandemic impacted the distribution of students with strong teacher-student relationships (TSR), and how these changes in TSRs affected inequalities in student experience and outcomes. Specifically, this project had four specific research questions: (1) How do TSRS shape the impact of crisis on student engagement and experience? (2) How do the impact of TSRs vary by class and minority background? (3) How does school response to the crisis affect teachers' connections with students?, and (4) How does the impact of this response vary based on student class and minority background?. To address these questions, this project expanded upon six months of ethnographic observations at two schools we dubbed CHS and NCHS, Virginia high schools where we observed prior to school closures. Over the course of the funding period, approximately 200 hours of observations of online classes were conducted at both schools between April 2020 - June 2021. These observations included the synchronous online classes of teachers (N=28) as well as online meetings of extracurricular groups, staff meetings and teacher trainings. Between December 2020 and February 2021, a stratified random sample of students (N=66 at CHS and N=69 at NCHS) completed six weekly time use surveys and photojournals. Lastly, interviews were conducted with 37 CHS students, 33 NCHS students, 18 CHS teachers and 23 NCHS teachers, for a total of 111 interviews.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Intellectual Merit&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>This project made a unique intellectual contribution by showing how schools' raced, classed, and&nbsp;</span>gendered cultures led to a cycle of misperception and distrust with steep consequences for working-class and Black students, with girls particularly impacted. Despite initial district and schoolwide efforts to address class disparities in internet and technology access, teachers' classroom practices during virtual learning in spring 2020 relied on a classed and gendered cultural model defining their students as dependents without financial or care work responsibilities. This erased the experiences of working-class students, the majority of whom were essential workers or working-class and middle-class girls who were caring for younger siblings and cousins while their parents continued to work outside the home or worked remotely. Consequently, teachers upheld a (false) narrative that students' struggles to adapt to online learning, resulting in missing work and absences, were driven primarily by disengagement and a lack of effort. Driven by these perceptions of widespread disengagement, both schools adopted strict policies governing missing work and absences in fall 2020. At both sites, these policies were disproportionately enforced in lower track classes where working-class and Black students were overrepresented.Thus, while initials efforts to address inequality during spring 2020 resulted in (limited) improvement to teacher-student relationships for some marginalized students, these gains were eroded by the cycle of misperception, distrust and miscommunication that characterized relationships during the 20-21 school year.</p> <p dir="ltr">Broader Impact&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>These findings were shared with sociologists and scholars of education in the form of three conference presentations. Additionally, this project made a methodological impact within the discipline of sociology, allowing for the development of interview and observations techniques that account for the challenges and limitations of online environments. These methodological advancements were shared in a national webinar hosted by the American Sociological Association as well as two campus talks.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>This project also made an important contribution to school officials' efforts to respond to the Covid19 pandemic. As part of the partnership with the two school districts in this study, project findings were shared with school officials on an ongoing basis. During summer 2020, a brief report was shared with data demonstrating that stronger teacher-student relationships lead to higher student engagement in virtual schooling and identifying specific practices teachers can use to strengthen relationships online. During winter 2021, a report summarizing the findings of student photojournals and time diaries was also shared with school officials.&nbsp;</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/08/2023<br>      Modified by: Allison&nbsp;Pugh</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   Project Outcomes Report This project sought to assess how teacher and school efforts to respond to the Covid19 pandemic impacted the distribution of students with strong teacher-student relationships (TSR), and how these changes in TSRs affected inequalities in student experience and outcomes. Specifically, this project had four specific research questions: (1) How do TSRS shape the impact of crisis on student engagement and experience? (2) How do the impact of TSRs vary by class and minority background? (3) How does school response to the crisis affect teachers' connections with students?, and (4) How does the impact of this response vary based on student class and minority background?. To address these questions, this project expanded upon six months of ethnographic observations at two schools we dubbed CHS and NCHS, Virginia high schools where we observed prior to school closures. Over the course of the funding period, approximately 200 hours of observations of online classes were conducted at both schools between April 2020 - June 2021. These observations included the synchronous online classes of teachers (N=28) as well as online meetings of extracurricular groups, staff meetings and teacher trainings. Between December 2020 and February 2021, a stratified random sample of students (N=66 at CHS and N=69 at NCHS) completed six weekly time use surveys and photojournals. Lastly, interviews were conducted with 37 CHS students, 33 NCHS students, 18 CHS teachers and 23 NCHS teachers, for a total of 111 interviews. Intellectual Merit  This project made a unique intellectual contribution by showing how schools' raced, classed, and gendered cultures led to a cycle of misperception and distrust with steep consequences for working-class and Black students, with girls particularly impacted. Despite initial district and schoolwide efforts to address class disparities in internet and technology access, teachers' classroom practices during virtual learning in spring 2020 relied on a classed and gendered cultural model defining their students as dependents without financial or care work responsibilities. This erased the experiences of working-class students, the majority of whom were essential workers or working-class and middle-class girls who were caring for younger siblings and cousins while their parents continued to work outside the home or worked remotely. Consequently, teachers upheld a (false) narrative that students' struggles to adapt to online learning, resulting in missing work and absences, were driven primarily by disengagement and a lack of effort. Driven by these perceptions of widespread disengagement, both schools adopted strict policies governing missing work and absences in fall 2020. At both sites, these policies were disproportionately enforced in lower track classes where working-class and Black students were overrepresented.Thus, while initials efforts to address inequality during spring 2020 resulted in (limited) improvement to teacher-student relationships for some marginalized students, these gains were eroded by the cycle of misperception, distrust and miscommunication that characterized relationships during the 20-21 school year. Broader Impact  These findings were shared with sociologists and scholars of education in the form of three conference presentations. Additionally, this project made a methodological impact within the discipline of sociology, allowing for the development of interview and observations techniques that account for the challenges and limitations of online environments. These methodological advancements were shared in a national webinar hosted by the American Sociological Association as well as two campus talks.  This project also made an important contribution to school officials' efforts to respond to the Covid19 pandemic. As part of the partnership with the two school districts in this study, project findings were shared with school officials on an ongoing basis. During summer 2020, a brief report was shared with data demonstrating that stronger teacher-student relationships lead to higher student engagement in virtual schooling and identifying specific practices teachers can use to strengthen relationships online. During winter 2021, a report summarizing the findings of student photojournals and time diaries was also shared with school officials.              Last Modified: 08/08/2023       Submitted by: Allison Pugh]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
