<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Social Network Consequences for Underrepresented STEM Students as a University Transitions to Remote Activities]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>199997.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>199997</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DRL</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jolene Jesse</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jjesse@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927303</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The COVID-19 pandemic has prompted universities worldwide to abruptly shift to remote learning. This coincides with a critical social change as students are urged to leave campus, “social distance,” and shelter-in-place; practices that will disrupt social network functioning and could lead to feelings of isolation, reduced motivation, and poorer learning outcomes. Worse, the social and academic consequences could be more severe for less academically prepared students (e.g., underrepresented minorities, first-generation college, low socioeconomic status) and first year students in particular, who are still adjusting to college life (e.g., building social networks, learning university culture). Given the uncertainty of the current situation, it is critical to understand how the pandemic and the "social distance" triggered by it may influence student social networks and whether disparities in social and academic outcomes result.  This RAPID was submitted in response to the NSF Dear Colleague letter related to the COVID-19 pandemic. This award is made by the EHR Core Research (ECR) program in the Division of Research on Learning, using funds from the Coronavirus Aid, Relief, and Economic Security (CARES) Act. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of this RAPID research project is to investigate how the shift to remote learning triggered by the COVID-19 pandemic is affecting social networks, psycho-social adjustment, and academic outcomes for first-year STEM majors, and whether disparities emerge for students from subgroups historically more likely to leave STEM. The research will examine these potential impacts, and how risks might be offset by an existing intervention at the University of California Irvine (UCI) -- the Enhanced Academic Success Experience (EASE) program. EASE is a learning community designed to improve academic outcomes for under-prepared students, with one-third of the approximately 1,000 first-year majors in the School of Biological Sciences (Bio Sci) participating each year. To date, research on the intervention has provided strong causal evidence that EASE has successfully increased motivation, engagement, and belongingness, with stronger effects for groups typically underrepresented within STEM. As part of the intervention, researchers have gathered longitudinal network data that are unique in both scale (~1,000 students/year within a major) and coverage (85-96% response rate). This research will characterize changes in friendship and study networks, psycho-social adjustment, and academic outcomes that result from the unprecedented shift to remote organizational activities. The new data collection and analysis will explore whether the shift to remote learning creates disparities in these important outcomes for subgroups of STEM students and whether the learning community provided by EASE may mitigate these effects. Through supplementary data collection, the study will consider how student networks have adapted to the organizational shift to remote learning and where students are obtaining the kinds of emotional and instrumental support they need. Mediation analysis will offer insight into which network characteristics explain psycho-social and academic consequences of the shift to remote learning. More generally, the unique data will enable assessment of how social networks adapt to societal-level disruption caused by the pandemic, and how well-implemented institutional support may offset the anticipated risks associated with the pandemic.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/29/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/08/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2028029</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Di</FirstName>
<LastName>Xu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Di Xu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[dix3@uci.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000690918</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/29/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Schaefer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David R Schaefer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[drschaef@uci.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000362583</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/29/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
<LastName>McPartlan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Peter M McPartlan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[pmcpartlan@sdsu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000824285</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/08/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Brian</FirstName>
<LastName>Sato</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Brian Sato</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[bsato@uci.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000641184</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/29/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Irvine</Name>
<CityName>IRVINE</CityName>
<ZipCode>926970001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9498247295</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>160 ALDRICH HALL</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>47</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA47</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>MJC5FCYQTPE6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA IRVINE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Irvine]]></Name>
<CityName>Irvine</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>926975100</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4253 Social Science Plaza B]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>47</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA47</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7980</Code>
<Text>ECR-EDU Core Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8212</Code>
<Text>Broaden Particip STEM Resrch</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8817</Code>
<Text>STEM Learning &amp; Learning Environments</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>4N20</Code>
<Name>EHR CARES Act DEFC N</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>040N2021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[EHR CARES Act DEFC N]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~199997</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; The COVID-19 pandemic prompted universities to abruptly shift to remote learning. This coincided with critical social change as students were urged to leave campus and &ldquo;social distance.&rdquo; These practices had the potential disrupt social network functioning and could lead to feelings of isolation, reduced motivation, and poorer learning outcomes. Worse, the social and academic consequences could be more severe for less academically prepared students (e.g., underrepresented minorities [URM], first-generation college students, low socioeconomic status [SES]) and freshmen in particular, who are still adjusting to college life. Given the uncertainty of the current situation, it is critical to understand how the pandemic and the "social distance" triggered by it may influence student social networks and whether disparities in social and academic outcomes result.<br />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; This project investigates how the shift to remote learning triggered by the COVID-19 pandemic affected the social networks, psychosocial adjustment, and academic outcomes for first-year STEM majors. We examine these impacts, within the context of an intervention designed to promote academic and social integration. Specifically, the Enhanced Academic Success Experience (EASE) program at the University of California Irvine (UCI) is a learning community (LC) aimed at improving academic outcomes for underprepared students. Each year, one-third of the approximately 1,000 first-year majors in Biological Sciences (Bio Sci) participate in EASE based on their lower Math SAT scores. Our prior research provides strong causal evidence that EASE has successfully increased motivation, engagement, and belongingness, with stronger effects for groups typically underrepresented within STEM. In this context, and with unique historical data on network and psychosocial measures from the past three years, we investigated the consequences of UCI&rsquo;s shift to remote learning, and how those effects are moderated by EASE. <br />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Our first project goal was to test the effect of EASE on student integration. We combined a regression discontinuity design with social network analysis to estimate the effect EASE on the size, strength, structure, and composition of friendship networks among Bio Sci students. Results of the quasi-experimental analysis indicate that LC participants acquired one additional friend in the major and increased their share of friends in the LC by 54 percentage-points. Exponential random-graph models that test mediation and alternative friendship mechanisms provide support for the theoretical argument that the LC promoted friendship development by structuring opportunities for interaction through block-registration into courses. Thus, we found that even simple LCs can shape the development of friendships through relatively low-cost administrative means. However, there is a potential downside when eligibility for participation is determined using academic metrics that separate the student population into distinct classroom environments. <br />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Given the role of EASE in promoting student integration, we tested whether EASE participation mitigated the negative impacts of the pandemic on social connection and academic outcomes. We found no evidence that EASE provided protective benefits above and beyond its main effects on belongingness and social integration (i.e., EASE participation did not moderate network change due to the pandemic). Moreover, we found no evidence that the shift to remote instruction affected disparities in social network integration, psychosocial adjustment, and academic outcomes (e.g., based on URM, income, or first-generation status).<br />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Analyses are ongoing and focused on several research questions: (1) How do first-generation youth transition to the university and is their integration shaped by their high-school community contexts?&nbsp; (2) What are the social network mechanisms that underlie successful first-year integration and development of social capital? (3) How does the formal curricular structure of college shape informal relational dynamics among students and what are the consequences for socialization?</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/12/2022<br>      Modified by: David&nbsp;R&nbsp;Schaefer</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[        The COVID-19 pandemic prompted universities to abruptly shift to remote learning. This coincided with critical social change as students were urged to leave campus and "social distance." These practices had the potential disrupt social network functioning and could lead to feelings of isolation, reduced motivation, and poorer learning outcomes. Worse, the social and academic consequences could be more severe for less academically prepared students (e.g., underrepresented minorities [URM], first-generation college students, low socioeconomic status [SES]) and freshmen in particular, who are still adjusting to college life. Given the uncertainty of the current situation, it is critical to understand how the pandemic and the "social distance" triggered by it may influence student social networks and whether disparities in social and academic outcomes result.        This project investigates how the shift to remote learning triggered by the COVID-19 pandemic affected the social networks, psychosocial adjustment, and academic outcomes for first-year STEM majors. We examine these impacts, within the context of an intervention designed to promote academic and social integration. Specifically, the Enhanced Academic Success Experience (EASE) program at the University of California Irvine (UCI) is a learning community (LC) aimed at improving academic outcomes for underprepared students. Each year, one-third of the approximately 1,000 first-year majors in Biological Sciences (Bio Sci) participate in EASE based on their lower Math SAT scores. Our prior research provides strong causal evidence that EASE has successfully increased motivation, engagement, and belongingness, with stronger effects for groups typically underrepresented within STEM. In this context, and with unique historical data on network and psychosocial measures from the past three years, we investigated the consequences of UCI’s shift to remote learning, and how those effects are moderated by EASE.         Our first project goal was to test the effect of EASE on student integration. We combined a regression discontinuity design with social network analysis to estimate the effect EASE on the size, strength, structure, and composition of friendship networks among Bio Sci students. Results of the quasi-experimental analysis indicate that LC participants acquired one additional friend in the major and increased their share of friends in the LC by 54 percentage-points. Exponential random-graph models that test mediation and alternative friendship mechanisms provide support for the theoretical argument that the LC promoted friendship development by structuring opportunities for interaction through block-registration into courses. Thus, we found that even simple LCs can shape the development of friendships through relatively low-cost administrative means. However, there is a potential downside when eligibility for participation is determined using academic metrics that separate the student population into distinct classroom environments.         Given the role of EASE in promoting student integration, we tested whether EASE participation mitigated the negative impacts of the pandemic on social connection and academic outcomes. We found no evidence that EASE provided protective benefits above and beyond its main effects on belongingness and social integration (i.e., EASE participation did not moderate network change due to the pandemic). Moreover, we found no evidence that the shift to remote instruction affected disparities in social network integration, psychosocial adjustment, and academic outcomes (e.g., based on URM, income, or first-generation status).        Analyses are ongoing and focused on several research questions: (1) How do first-generation youth transition to the university and is their integration shaped by their high-school community contexts?  (2) What are the social network mechanisms that underlie successful first-year integration and development of social capital? (3) How does the formal curricular structure of college shape informal relational dynamics among students and what are the consequences for socialization?       Last Modified: 09/12/2022       Submitted by: David R Schaefer]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
