<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID Collaborative proposal: Spatial dynamics of COVID-19]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>124654.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>124654</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Samuel Scheiner</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sscheine@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927175</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This project will develop a set of mathematical models of the spread of SARS-CoV-2, the cause of COVID-19. The 2019-2020 global corona virus pandemic is ongoing and poses an unprecedented challenge to the normal movement of people within and between countries. The models developed by this research will provide the means to determine how the risk of transmission varies over time between specific locations and can be combined with other data sources to help determine the primary routes of transmission and the actions that are successful in slowing or halting the spread. These methods are designed to provide initial models with limited data, while allowing for the integration of more robust datasets as they become available. The proposed project will produce information directly applicable to managing the geographic spread of SARS-CoV-2, will inform CDC decisions and responses to the pandemic, and will provide a way to assess changes to importation risk in close to real-time. In addition,the proposed project will contribute to the training of a graduate student and an undergraduate student. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Stochastic spatial models provide the means for determining the time-varying risk of pathogen transmission between specific locations. This project will develop extensions of these models that will be more effective at analyzing and forecasting spatial spread of emerging disease. The project will develop a spatial model that incorporates time-varying cases in each location, including a reliable method for parameterization. It will use those models to estimate the effects of travel restrictions and quarantines on the spread globally and within the U.S. By closely studying the spread at the source of the outbreak it will assess how travel patterns and interventions altered the pandemic trajectory. The models will also assist in identifying areas at greatest risk of importation of new cases when local transmission is controlled. These aims will be accomplished by using publicly available data sources and compiling new information on the timeline of interventions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/31/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/14/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2028097</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Andrew</FirstName>
<LastName>Kramer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Andrew M Kramer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[amkramer@usf.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000397003</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/31/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of South Florida</Name>
<CityName>TAMPA</CityName>
<ZipCode>336205800</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8139742897</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4202 E FOWLER AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>15</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL15</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NKAZLXLL7Z91</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF SOUTH FLORIDA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of South Florida]]></Name>
<CityName>Tampa</CityName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>336172008</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4019 E. Fowler Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>15</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL15</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>U323</Code>
<Text/>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021RB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~124654</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project develops a set of mathematical models for the geographical spread of SARS-CoV-2, the pathogen causing COVID-19. The COVID-19 pandemic is ongoing and has illustrated the immense challenges of limiting international spread of zoonotic pathogens. The models developed here provide a way to assess the risk of pathogen transport between places based on geographic location and characteristics of each place, and provides a way to assess whether interventions, such as restricting travel or screening travelers, can reduce spread. A strength of these methods is that they are designed to be used early in an outbreak, when data is limited. The models can be used by public health authorities to inform decision making, and can be readily adapted for novel pathogens as they arise in the future. The project has also contributed to training a graduate student and an undergraduate student. The undergraduate researcher supported here was recognized as a Rhodes and Marshall scholarship finalist and is pursuing a PhD to continue contributing to research on improving predictions of disease spread.</p> <p><br />The stochastic models developed here improve on existing models of disease spread on air, road, and shipping networks. This work also links datasets on first detection of COVID-19, numbers of cases, and travel restrictions in novel ways and will make those data openly available. This project is one of few that looks at the role of maritime shipping in disease transmission, which is of particular importance given the increased recognition of the importance of shipping in the global supply chain, and therefore the limitations to applying restrictions to shipping. This project has also produced a software library that will facilitate any researcher with simplifying the complex networks involved in pathogen transmission and related processes, including the spread of invasive species.<br /><br /><br /></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/21/2022<br>      Modified by: Andrew&nbsp;M&nbsp;Kramer</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project develops a set of mathematical models for the geographical spread of SARS-CoV-2, the pathogen causing COVID-19. The COVID-19 pandemic is ongoing and has illustrated the immense challenges of limiting international spread of zoonotic pathogens. The models developed here provide a way to assess the risk of pathogen transport between places based on geographic location and characteristics of each place, and provides a way to assess whether interventions, such as restricting travel or screening travelers, can reduce spread. A strength of these methods is that they are designed to be used early in an outbreak, when data is limited. The models can be used by public health authorities to inform decision making, and can be readily adapted for novel pathogens as they arise in the future. The project has also contributed to training a graduate student and an undergraduate student. The undergraduate researcher supported here was recognized as a Rhodes and Marshall scholarship finalist and is pursuing a PhD to continue contributing to research on improving predictions of disease spread.   The stochastic models developed here improve on existing models of disease spread on air, road, and shipping networks. This work also links datasets on first detection of COVID-19, numbers of cases, and travel restrictions in novel ways and will make those data openly available. This project is one of few that looks at the role of maritime shipping in disease transmission, which is of particular importance given the increased recognition of the importance of shipping in the global supply chain, and therefore the limitations to applying restrictions to shipping. This project has also produced a software library that will facilitate any researcher with simplifying the complex networks involved in pathogen transmission and related processes, including the spread of invasive species.          Last Modified: 12/21/2022       Submitted by: Andrew M Kramer]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
