<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Early Detection of Disease Outbreaks using Self-Organizing Patterns – COVID-19]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>200000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>200000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rebecca Shearman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rshearma@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927403</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This project will advance national health through the development of a robust, predictive model to graphically represent the spread of COVID-19 through an innovative integration of public health information and social media data. This project develops a predictive modeling tool to visually represent the spread of COVID-19 or other potential pandemics utilizing artificial intelligence techniques to support data gathering, analysis and representation of the outcomes.  The societal benefit is significant if the researchers are successful in developing a model that utilizes traditional public health data integrated with social media data to expeditiously create a reliable prediction of disease spread. This project will contribute towards building an open source database that can be accessed anywhere across the globe while providing early warning detection and signals to government agencies. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This RAPID project develops a large-scale pandemic model to enable data sharing, using AI-based approaches, and predictive modeling.  Specifically, the project proposes a model for rapid and early disease detection, by combining three novel intellectual approaches to outbreak detection. These three approaches include 1) Self-organizing systems theory to detect nascent pattern formation; 2) Leveraging topical proximity in research communications over geospatial proximity of infected individuals; and 3) Loss of complexity in topical networks as an indicator of an “unhealthy” system with an impending outbreak. This integrated approach has not been previously attempted in efforts to track disease outbreak.  The proposed methodology is expected to produce a working model within the 2nd quarter of the project.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/07/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/07/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2028051</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sylvia</FirstName>
<LastName>Thomas</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sylvia W Thomas</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[sylvia@usf.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000353845</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/07/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tempestt</FirstName>
<LastName>Neal</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Tempestt Neal</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[tjneal@usf.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000782026</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/07/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alessandro</FirstName>
<LastName>Negro</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alessandro Negro</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[alenegro81@gmail.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000824307</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/07/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of South Florida</Name>
<CityName>TAMPA</CityName>
<ZipCode>336205800</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8139742897</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4202 E FOWLER AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>15</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL15</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NKAZLXLL7Z91</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF SOUTH FLORIDA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of South Florida]]></Name>
<CityName>Tampa</CityName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>336209951</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4202 E. Fowler Ave., ENG 030]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>15</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL15</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>158Y</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>1N20</Code>
<Name>R&amp;RA CARES Act DEFC N</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>010N2021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[R&RA CARES Act DEFC N]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~200000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>RAPID: Early Detection of Disease Outbreaks using Self-Organizing Patterns - COVID-19</p> <p><strong>Project Outcomes</strong></p> <p>The COVID-19 pandemic revealed the critical need to understand the nature of a disease or virus before its outbreak and rapid spread throughout global communities. &nbsp;Previous studies show that individuals and communities respond more positively to public health guidelines when the scientific knowledge surrounding the health scare is stronger.&nbsp; Therefore, a grand challenge presents itself to change the way the world prepares for potential pandemics.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>To address this grand challenge, the main idea of this work is to apply algorithms to discover patterns and create ?storytelling? around the evolution of understanding new diseases and outbreaks, helping to predict how the disease will evolve; ultimately providing information to help society to be better prepared and respond faster.&nbsp; The novelty of the approach presented in this work is how keyword knowledge graphs can be used to identify trends and show the evolution of human knowledge regarding a new disease.&nbsp; This work presents a novel way to gather knowledge from keywords, or tags, and analyzes the knowledge quickly to gather key insights and concrete answers to unseen problems.</p> <p>One major goal of this research is to advance national healthcare strategies through the development of a robust, predictive model for early detection of disease outbreaks using self-organizing patterns.&nbsp; The objectives were to:</p> <p>1.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Gain an understanding of changes in the self-organization of keyword patterns surrounding a disease as early indicators of an outbreak</p> <p>2.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Represent the spread of a pandemic graphically through an innovative integration of public health information, data, phrases, and keywords</p> <p>3.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; To develop a predictive modeling tool to visually represent the spread of a potential pandemic</p> <p>A sample part of a larger knowledge graph is presented in Figure 1, capturing data about genes, diseases, compounds, and side effects, along with the interactions, e.g., how a disease is connected to a specific gene, how it can be treated by a specific compound, and the side effects of such compound.</p> <p>Figure 1. Part of knowledge graph showing connections of how a disease is connected to a specific gene connected to a specific compound and the side effects of such compound.</p> <p><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Key Findings</span></strong></p> <ul> <li>The research team finalized the COVID-19 Knowledge graphs (KGs) to capture the relevant information from a huge set of articles and tested relevant tasks to link prediction between a disease and a treatment or a compound.</li> <li>The research team conducted a qualitative study surveying doctors and researchers to provide scientific ?keywords? that allowed the team to build, test, and validate the KG algorithms and gain a deeper understanding of the trends used by the scientific community at-large </li> <li>High-level survey results revealed knowledge about the rapid spread of the disease were governmental responses to the pandemic and major sources of information, e.g. PubMed, news sources</li> <li>The result of this work is a fully functional knowledge graph ready to be used for human knowledge exploration to consolidate many sources of information ? new and old ? related to a disease in a single connected source of truth to facilitate knowledge extraction over time.<strong>&nbsp;</strong></li> </ul> <p>For future healthcare issues, this work is likely to have an impact on unique opportunities to address a critical problem in the US public health system by deploying new analytical methods and technologies to build an early warning system that can eventually be leveraged by federal agencies. The results of this work are likely to make an impact on communities that are not familiar with knowledge graphs and even beyond this concept, communities of color, that will benefit from the early predictive analysis that healthcare providers can make by using the techniques of this work.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/16/2023<br>      Modified by: Sylvia&nbsp;W&nbsp;Thomas</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2028051/2028051_10669131_1681621450362_RAPIDOutcomesFigure1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2028051/2028051_10669131_1681621450362_RAPIDOutcomesFigure1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 1"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2028051/2028051_10669131_1681621450362_RAPIDOutcomesFigure1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 1"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Part of knowledge graph showing connections of how a disease is connected to a specific gene connected to a specific compound and the side effects of such compound.</div> <div class="imageCredit">this work</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Sylvia&nbsp;W&nbsp;Thomas</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 1</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ RAPID: Early Detection of Disease Outbreaks using Self-Organizing Patterns - COVID-19  Project Outcomes  The COVID-19 pandemic revealed the critical need to understand the nature of a disease or virus before its outbreak and rapid spread throughout global communities.  Previous studies show that individuals and communities respond more positively to public health guidelines when the scientific knowledge surrounding the health scare is stronger.  Therefore, a grand challenge presents itself to change the way the world prepares for potential pandemics.    To address this grand challenge, the main idea of this work is to apply algorithms to discover patterns and create ?storytelling? around the evolution of understanding new diseases and outbreaks, helping to predict how the disease will evolve; ultimately providing information to help society to be better prepared and respond faster.  The novelty of the approach presented in this work is how keyword knowledge graphs can be used to identify trends and show the evolution of human knowledge regarding a new disease.  This work presents a novel way to gather knowledge from keywords, or tags, and analyzes the knowledge quickly to gather key insights and concrete answers to unseen problems.  One major goal of this research is to advance national healthcare strategies through the development of a robust, predictive model for early detection of disease outbreaks using self-organizing patterns.  The objectives were to:  1.         Gain an understanding of changes in the self-organization of keyword patterns surrounding a disease as early indicators of an outbreak  2.         Represent the spread of a pandemic graphically through an innovative integration of public health information, data, phrases, and keywords  3.         To develop a predictive modeling tool to visually represent the spread of a potential pandemic  A sample part of a larger knowledge graph is presented in Figure 1, capturing data about genes, diseases, compounds, and side effects, along with the interactions, e.g., how a disease is connected to a specific gene, how it can be treated by a specific compound, and the side effects of such compound.  Figure 1. Part of knowledge graph showing connections of how a disease is connected to a specific gene connected to a specific compound and the side effects of such compound.  Key Findings  The research team finalized the COVID-19 Knowledge graphs (KGs) to capture the relevant information from a huge set of articles and tested relevant tasks to link prediction between a disease and a treatment or a compound. The research team conducted a qualitative study surveying doctors and researchers to provide scientific ?keywords? that allowed the team to build, test, and validate the KG algorithms and gain a deeper understanding of the trends used by the scientific community at-large  High-level survey results revealed knowledge about the rapid spread of the disease were governmental responses to the pandemic and major sources of information, e.g. PubMed, news sources The result of this work is a fully functional knowledge graph ready to be used for human knowledge exploration to consolidate many sources of information ? new and old ? related to a disease in a single connected source of truth to facilitate knowledge extraction over time.    For future healthcare issues, this work is likely to have an impact on unique opportunities to address a critical problem in the US public health system by deploying new analytical methods and technologies to build an early warning system that can eventually be leveraged by federal agencies. The results of this work are likely to make an impact on communities that are not familiar with knowledge graphs and even beyond this concept, communities of color, that will benefit from the early predictive analysis that healthcare providers can make by using the techniques of this work.             Last Modified: 04/16/2023       Submitted by: Sylvia W Thomas]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
