<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>RAPID: Collaborative Research: Influencing Young Adults’ Science Engagement and Learning with COVID-19 Media Coverage</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>102142.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>102142</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DRL</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sandra Welch</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>swelch@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925094</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This RAPID was submitted in response to the NSF Dear Colleague letter related to the COVID-19 pandemic. This award is made by the AISL program in the Division of Research on Learning, using funds from the Coronavirus Aid, Relief, and Economic Security (CARES) Act.   The major public policy of social distancing relies, in part, on the cooperation of younger and healthier people who may not experience symptoms and can spread the virus unknowingly to more vulnerable populations. Science journalists, who are on the front lines of covering the pandemic, can play an important role in educating millennial audiences about the science behind the virus, how it is transmitted and effective ways to prevent the virus from spreading.  This award will help the STEM field better understand how to engage millennial audiences with effective COVID-19 media content and to urgently capture professional knowledge on crisis reporting.  KQED and Texas Tech University are suited to rapidly implement a science media informal science learning project targeting millennials and younger audiences in light of their current NSF-funded "Cracking the Code: Influencing Millennial Science Engagement" collaborative research and evaluation project (DRL 1810990 and 1811091). The project team has built a functional research protocol for its media practitioner and academic researcher collaboration, and  will apply these new RAPID funds to complement on-going efforts, mobilize the existing team, research protocol, and  research tools to respond to the communication challenge of reaching younger adults posed by COVID-19.  Content to be created includes:  1) Radio broadcasts - daily news coverage, live talks; 2) A real-time blog - live Coronavirus updates and 3) Social media content on Facebook, Instagram and Twitter.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project team will explore the following research questions:&lt;br/&gt;1) How could COVID-19 coverage be designed to best inform, engage and educate millennials and younger audiences about the science of virus transmission and prevention?&lt;br/&gt;2) What are some best practices for crisis reporting, as journalists respond to both constantly updated information and changing audience needs, that can be used by media outlets (such as advisors PBS Digital Studios, PBS NewsHour, NOVA, NPR Science, and more)?  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research protocol centers around "media testing cycles," which are time-bounded studies (5 months long) exploring a subset of research questions about the effectiveness of KQED's science content (articles, videos, social media posts and radio reporting) at reaching younger audiences. Steps include identifying problems that are suited for empirical examination; formulating plausible competing hypotheses on the nature of those problems and their potential solutions; and crafting study designs calculated to support valid, realistic inferences on the relative strength of those hypotheses. Data will be gathered from COVID-19 audience "chatter" from Twitter and Facebook through Crimson Hexagon, a social media listening platform. In addition to the social media listening, researchers will conduct a thematic analysis of the questions currently being collected through the audience engagement platform Hearken, where KQED has gathered nearly 2,000 questions to date about the virus and lifestyle changes. This data will also help the project team understand knowledge gaps about prevention and transmission of the virus. These two qualitative studies will be conducted concurrently and reported to KQED journalists quickly to inform reporting.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Texas Tech researchers will create a virus transmission and prevention knowledge assessment. This assessment will be validated using a national online survey. The project will examine knowledge differences based on, for example, generation and gender. TTU will examine relationships between performance on this assessment and two relevant measures: science curiosity and ordinary science intelligence. The national survey will help identify what knowledge gaps are present in which audiences. Using this information, KQED journalists will develop "explainers" and other news content, to meet audience needs and to fill knowledge gaps.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/29/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/29/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2028469</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sue Ellen</FirstName>
<LastName>McCann</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME>Ms</PI_SUFX_NAME>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sue Ellen McCann</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>smccann@kqed.org</EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000466286</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/29/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sevda</FirstName>
<LastName>Eris</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sevda Eris</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>seris@kqed.org</EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000736897</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/29/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>KQED Inc</Name>
<CityName>San Francisco</CityName>
<ZipCode>941173317</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4158642000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2601 Mariposa Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>004770921</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>KQED INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>004770921</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[KQED Inc]]></Name>
<CityName>San Francisco</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>941051813</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[50 Beale Street, 5th Floor]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7259</Code>
<Text>AISL</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>4N20</Code>
<Name>EHR CARES Act DEFC N</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>040N2021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[EHR CARES Act DEFC N]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~102142</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-e5321ac8-7fff-c8be-33f8-d7f12eb9cc79"> </span></p> <p><span id="docs-internal-guid-a64c6d96-7fff-8796-1d4f-6d078e3aca88"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Influencing Young Adults' Science Engagement and Learning with COVID-19 Media is a RAPID Advancing Informal STEM Learning collaborative research project between KQED, a public media organization serving the San Francisco Bay Area, Texas Tech University and Rockman et al. The collaborative team built on its audience research on millennials through the NSF-funded Cracking the Code: Influencing Millennial Science Engagement, to research and deliver effective COVID-19 content for young adult audiences. While they were less likely to get seriously ill themselves, young adults were a critical group for "flattening the curve" early in the pandemic, reaching "herd immunity" through vaccinations, and preventing the rise of virus variants. &nbsp; </span><span>&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><strong>Broader Impacts: Media, Millennials, and Public Health</strong><span>&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>KQED and TTU conducted several "Knowledge Gap" and social media research studies to address our first research question: How could COVID-19 coverage be designed to best inform, engage and educate millennials and younger audiences about the science of virus transmission and prevention? This research included:&nbsp;&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span style="text-decoration: underline;">-A Twitter Misinformation study</span><span> to understand major COVID-19 misinformation narratives on Twitter discussed in the San Francisco Bay Area, and how they compared to the United States as a whole from Mar. 1 - Oct. 20, 2020</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Knowledge Gap studies:</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>-Mask Wearing study</span><span>. We examined the effectiveness of two messaging strategies -- scientific consensus messaging and infographic visuals -- that can be used to encourage mask-wearing and support for mask-wearing policies. Infographic visuals were prefered over scientific messaging.&nbsp;&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>-Germ Knowledge study</span><span>.&nbsp; We looked at knowledge gaps in the general public, not only surrounding misinformation about COVID-19, but also viruses and bacteria. We found that young adults have limited or mis-understanding of viruses and bacteria in comparison to older generations.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>-Conceptual Mapping study</span><span>. We conducted interviews and mapped responses </span><span>a little over one year into the pandemic with the aim of discovering more about what sorts of understandings and misunderstandings about COVID-19 are still prevalent.&nbsp;&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Social Media testing:</span></p> <p>The KQED Science Engagement team applied findings from our Knowledge Gap studies to develop social media posts that addressed trending knowledge gap topics during the earlier stages of the pandemic. They created fun and informative social distancing and mask use graphics to communicate the importance of these behaviors during the pandemic.</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The key takeaways for news organization include:&nbsp;</span></p> <ul> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Conduct research on knowledge gaps and misinformation and then address those gaps and misunderstandings in your reporting. </span><span>Focus on widely-held views of misinformation or those that will affect decision making.</span></p> </li> </ul> <ul> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Consider audience demographics (age, political ideology, income, race/ethnicity, etc) when communicating health/science messages and designing effective engagement strategies.</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Use visuals and social media to engage </span><span>millennial or Gen Z audiences and&nbsp; target ?missing? audiences (audiences that don?t currently engage in your content). We found that GIFs were the most engaging, followed by a short video, and then a simple image.</span></p> </li> </ul> <ul> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Use infographics or visuals to communicate complex ideas during a health or scientific crisis, especially to millennial or Gen Z audiences who displayed a larger knowledge gap in understanding the basics about viruses and bacteria.</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Verify and report&nbsp; information on necessary and unnecessary health practices.</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Create simple media explainers: mRNA technology, difference between emergency use and regular authorization for vaccines.&nbsp;&nbsp;</span></p> </li> </ul> <ul> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Make consistent efforts over time to counter false information. Combating misinformation takes time.</span></p> </li> </ul> <p dir="ltr"><strong>Intellectual Merit: Professional Knowledge, Crisis Reporting, and Evaluation</strong></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>KQED and Texas Tech advanced professional knowledge in the journalism and science communication fields around crisis reporting and building a media practitioner and academic researcher collaboration for audience research through a study conducted by Scott Burg of Rockman et al.&nbsp; Rockman gathered data between October 2020 - May 2021, interviewed KQED Science staff and participated in virtual observations of KQED project and related staff meetings to answer our second research question:</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Can KQED develop a more efficient process of disaster reporting that responds to both constantly updating information and changing audience needs which can be used and expanded upon by media outlets?</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Conclusions and key takeaways from the study include:&nbsp;</span></p> <ul> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Disasters have to be covered holistically, not as single disconnected events.</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Identify, cover, explain and explore the root causes and long term impacts of these catastrophic events.</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Journalists need to establish and sustain richer relationships with impacted communities, and focus on solution-based reporting.&nbsp;</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Hire news staff that reflect the community.&nbsp;</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Use a variety of information platforms for communicating with your audience -- broadcast, web, social media and increase the use of engagement strategies.</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Provide resources for real time fact-checking.&nbsp;</span></p> </li> </ul> <p dir="ltr"><span>As a result of this study, news organizations and media makers now have a deeper understanding of what types of media (social, online, video, audio) and what communications factors (storytelling style, visuals, length, platform, etc.) influence science learning and engagement around COVID-19 for young audiences. The project also provided media professionals a much-needed chance to reflect on disaster reporting, which will inform future planning and effectiveness.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/27/2021<br>      Modified by: Sevda&nbsp;Eris</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[      Influencing Young Adults' Science Engagement and Learning with COVID-19 Media is a RAPID Advancing Informal STEM Learning collaborative research project between KQED, a public media organization serving the San Francisco Bay Area, Texas Tech University and Rockman et al. The collaborative team built on its audience research on millennials through the NSF-funded Cracking the Code: Influencing Millennial Science Engagement, to research and deliver effective COVID-19 content for young adult audiences. While they were less likely to get seriously ill themselves, young adults were a critical group for "flattening the curve" early in the pandemic, reaching "herd immunity" through vaccinations, and preventing the rise of virus variants.     Broader Impacts: Media, Millennials, and Public Health  KQED and TTU conducted several "Knowledge Gap" and social media research studies to address our first research question: How could COVID-19 coverage be designed to best inform, engage and educate millennials and younger audiences about the science of virus transmission and prevention? This research included:   -A Twitter Misinformation study to understand major COVID-19 misinformation narratives on Twitter discussed in the San Francisco Bay Area, and how they compared to the United States as a whole from Mar. 1 - Oct. 20, 2020 Knowledge Gap studies: -Mask Wearing study. We examined the effectiveness of two messaging strategies -- scientific consensus messaging and infographic visuals -- that can be used to encourage mask-wearing and support for mask-wearing policies. Infographic visuals were prefered over scientific messaging.   -Germ Knowledge study.  We looked at knowledge gaps in the general public, not only surrounding misinformation about COVID-19, but also viruses and bacteria. We found that young adults have limited or mis-understanding of viruses and bacteria in comparison to older generations. -Conceptual Mapping study. We conducted interviews and mapped responses a little over one year into the pandemic with the aim of discovering more about what sorts of understandings and misunderstandings about COVID-19 are still prevalent.   Social Media testing:  The KQED Science Engagement team applied findings from our Knowledge Gap studies to develop social media posts that addressed trending knowledge gap topics during the earlier stages of the pandemic. They created fun and informative social distancing and mask use graphics to communicate the importance of these behaviors during the pandemic. The key takeaways for news organization include:    Conduct research on knowledge gaps and misinformation and then address those gaps and misunderstandings in your reporting. Focus on widely-held views of misinformation or those that will affect decision making.     Consider audience demographics (age, political ideology, income, race/ethnicity, etc) when communicating health/science messages and designing effective engagement strategies.   Use visuals and social media to engage millennial or Gen Z audiences and  target ?missing? audiences (audiences that don?t currently engage in your content). We found that GIFs were the most engaging, followed by a short video, and then a simple image.     Use infographics or visuals to communicate complex ideas during a health or scientific crisis, especially to millennial or Gen Z audiences who displayed a larger knowledge gap in understanding the basics about viruses and bacteria.   Verify and report  information on necessary and unnecessary health practices.   Create simple media explainers: mRNA technology, difference between emergency use and regular authorization for vaccines.       Make consistent efforts over time to counter false information. Combating misinformation takes time.   Intellectual Merit: Professional Knowledge, Crisis Reporting, and Evaluation KQED and Texas Tech advanced professional knowledge in the journalism and science communication fields around crisis reporting and building a media practitioner and academic researcher collaboration for audience research through a study conducted by Scott Burg of Rockman et al.  Rockman gathered data between October 2020 - May 2021, interviewed KQED Science staff and participated in virtual observations of KQED project and related staff meetings to answer our second research question: Can KQED develop a more efficient process of disaster reporting that responds to both constantly updating information and changing audience needs which can be used and expanded upon by media outlets? Conclusions and key takeaways from the study include:    Disasters have to be covered holistically, not as single disconnected events.   Identify, cover, explain and explore the root causes and long term impacts of these catastrophic events.   Journalists need to establish and sustain richer relationships with impacted communities, and focus on solution-based reporting.    Hire news staff that reflect the community.    Use a variety of information platforms for communicating with your audience -- broadcast, web, social media and increase the use of engagement strategies.   Provide resources for real time fact-checking.    As a result of this study, news organizations and media makers now have a deeper understanding of what types of media (social, online, video, audio) and what communications factors (storytelling style, visuals, length, platform, etc.) influence science learning and engagement around COVID-19 for young audiences. The project also provided media professionals a much-needed chance to reflect on disaster reporting, which will inform future planning and effectiveness.          Last Modified: 08/27/2021       Submitted by: Sevda Eris]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
