<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Collaborative Research: The Diffusion of State Policy Responses to the 2019 Novel Coronavirus]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>37528.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>44904</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jan Leighley</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[When the 2019 novel coronavirus arrived in the United States in February and March of 2020, state governments quickly began enacting policies intended to contain and mitigate its spread. Understanding the timing and sequence of these policy choices, and those policies’ eventual consequences, is critical for assessing how governments can be most effective during pandemics. This project collects data on state and local governments’ responses to COVID-19, including policies related to closing schools, canceling travel, banning public gatherings, closing restaurants and bars, delaying rent payments, and rules on medical licenses.  This data allows researchers to examine the factors that influence states’ policy choices, whether those factors differ from the ways in which states enact policies during normal times, which policies are effective in slowing the spread and morbidity of the virus, and how states roll back policies in a manner that allows economic activity to resume while maintaining preparedness to avoid and mitigated waves of the virus. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project collects data on state government responses to COVID-19 by scraping government websites daily, focusing on sites dedicated to COVID-19 and those associated with the executive branch, state legislatures, and state departments of public health.  It also collects data on the number of diagnosed cases, fatalities, recoveries in the states, and mobility data that tracks geographic movements from mobile phones. The policy recommendations or decisions recorded from state government pages include decisions related to closing schools, canceling travel, banning public gatherings (and their size), closing restaurants and bars, travel quarantines, postponing elections, safe shelter orders, limiting elective medical procedures, as well as when states modify these policies; additional data is collected from official state Twitter accounts. This data allows researchers to examine the factors that influence states’ policy choices, whether those factors differ from the ways in which states enact policies during normal times, which policies are effective in slowing the spread and morbidity of the virus, and how states roll back policies in a manner that allows economic activity to resume while maintaining preparedness to avoid and mitigate new waves of the virus. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is jointly funded by the Accountable Institutions and Behavior Program and the Established Program to Stimulate Competitive Research (EPSCoR).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/28/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/19/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2028724</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Frederick</FirstName>
<LastName>Boehmke</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Frederick J Boehmke</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[frederick-boehmke@uiowa.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000187779</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/28/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Iowa</Name>
<CityName>IOWA CITY</CityName>
<ZipCode>522421316</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3193352123</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>105 JESSUP HALL</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Iowa</StateName>
<StateCode>IA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IA01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>Z1H9VJS8NG16</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>THE UNIVERSITY OF IOWA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Iowa]]></Name>
<CityName>Iowa City</CityName>
<StateCode>IA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>522421409</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[363 SH]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Iowa</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IA01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>120Y</Code>
<Text>AIB-Acctble Institutions&amp;Behav</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EPSCoR Co-Funding</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>1N20</Code>
<Name>R&amp;RA CARES Act DEFC N</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>010N2021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[R&RA CARES Act DEFC N]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~37528</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~7376</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Prof. Boehmke, in collaboration with his co-PIs Bruce Desmarais and Jeff Harden, working on linked proposals, have completed work on their NSF-funded research project, "RAPID: Collaborative Research: The Diffusion of State Policy Responses to the 2019 Novel Coronavirus". Prof. Boehmke and his team worked for one year under the original proposal and an extra twelve months under a no-cost-extension to build and analyze a database, SPRC19, on the spread of state policy actions related to COVID-19 across the American states. These data were compiled from state government and other websites. While data collection continues as the pandemic evolves, the current collection includes over 10,000 state policy documents and the databased includes over 25,000 individual policy actions. &nbsp;</p> <p>These data offer opportunities for scholars, policymakers, and policy advocates to study the spread of COVID-19 related policies across the American states or to examine details on specific policies. The pandemic created a highly unusual policy making environment in which states made decisions quickly and, at least initially, with little information. This distinct decision environment provides an opportunity to examine policy choices and state policy leadership and diffusion in a different context than what we usually see, in which policies spread over years and decades and states have time to assess their effectiveness before adopting them. SPRC19 allows users to identify, for example, whether states that were policy leaders for COVID-19 policies mirror those that lead in general, both in terms of adopting new policies faster and by influencing other states decisions to adopt those policies.</p> <p>SPRC19 will be posted online for public access. To ensure widespread, continued access we have created a site to host it online at the Dataverse, a public data sharing repository, at <a href="https://dataverse.harvard.edu/dataverse/sprc19">https://dataverse.harvard.edu/dataverse/sprc19</a>. These data are described in a paper presented at the 2022 Midwest Political Science Association's Annual Conference.</p> <p>In addition to sharing the policy data, the work has a produced a number of other broader impacts. Most notably, the PIs have provided opportunities for nearly a dozen undergraduates to work on the project and collaborate on data analysis and paper writing. They have also successfully employed women and minorities on the project, including undergraduates interested in learning more about the application of data analytics in Political Science, some of whom have already been accepted to pursue advanced degrees starting in fall 2022.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/15/2022<br>      Modified by: Frederick&nbsp;J&nbsp;Boehmke</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2028724/2028724_10666777_1657829700913_mapping-covid03fb-map-quantile--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2028724/2028724_10666777_1657829700913_mapping-covid03fb-map-quantile--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Number of COVID-19 policies by state through April 30, 2020"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2028724/2028724_10666777_1657829700913_mapping-covid03fb-map-quantile--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Number of COVID-19 policies by state through April 30, 2020"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">States grouped by how many COVID-19 policy actions they had through April 30, 2020.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Frederick J Boehmke</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Frederick&nbsp;J&nbsp;Boehmke</div> <div class="imageTitle">Number of COVID-19 policies by state through April 30, 2020</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2028724/2028724_10666777_1657829893614_analyze-coviddata01-actions-by-type-week--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2028724/2028724_10666777_1657829893614_analyze-coviddata01-actions-by-type-week--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Total state COVID-19 policy actions by week and action type"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2028724/2028724_10666777_1657829893614_analyze-coviddata01-actions-by-type-week--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Total state COVID-19 policy actions by week and action type"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Total state COVID-19 policy actions by week and action type through April 30, 2020.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Frederick J Boehmke</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Frederick&nbsp;J&nbsp;Boehmke</div> <div class="imageTitle">Total state COVID-19 policy actions by week and action type</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2028724/2028724_10666777_1660584081024_analyze-coviddata01-innov-vs-spid--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2028724/2028724_10666777_1660584081024_analyze-coviddata01-innov-vs-spid--rgov-800width.jpg" title="State COVID-19 innovativeness"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2028724/2028724_10666777_1660584081024_analyze-coviddata01-innov-vs-spid--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="State COVID-19 innovativeness"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Comparison of state innovativeness on COVID-19 policies through April 30, 2020 to general policy innovativeness since 1959  taken from the State Policy, Innovation, and Diffusion database</div> <div class="imageCredit">Frederick J. Boehmke</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Frederick&nbsp;J&nbsp;Boehmke</div> <div class="imageTitle">State COVID-19 innovativeness</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2028724/2028724_10666777_1657829816221_analyze-coviddata01-adopt-by-state-week--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2028724/2028724_10666777_1657829816221_analyze-coviddata01-adopt-by-state-week--rgov-800width.jpg" title="State COVID-19 policy adoptions by week through April 30, 2020"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2028724/2028724_10666777_1657829816221_analyze-coviddata01-adopt-by-state-week--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="State COVID-19 policy adoptions by week through April 30, 2020"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Heatmap of State COVID-19 policy adoptions by week through April 30, 2020</div> <div class="imageCredit">Frederick J Boehmke</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Frederick&nbsp;J&nbsp;Boehmke</div> <div class="imageTitle">State COVID-19 policy adoptions by week through April 30, 2020</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Prof. Boehmke, in collaboration with his co-PIs Bruce Desmarais and Jeff Harden, working on linked proposals, have completed work on their NSF-funded research project, "RAPID: Collaborative Research: The Diffusion of State Policy Responses to the 2019 Novel Coronavirus". Prof. Boehmke and his team worked for one year under the original proposal and an extra twelve months under a no-cost-extension to build and analyze a database, SPRC19, on the spread of state policy actions related to COVID-19 across the American states. These data were compiled from state government and other websites. While data collection continues as the pandemic evolves, the current collection includes over 10,000 state policy documents and the databased includes over 25,000 individual policy actions.    These data offer opportunities for scholars, policymakers, and policy advocates to study the spread of COVID-19 related policies across the American states or to examine details on specific policies. The pandemic created a highly unusual policy making environment in which states made decisions quickly and, at least initially, with little information. This distinct decision environment provides an opportunity to examine policy choices and state policy leadership and diffusion in a different context than what we usually see, in which policies spread over years and decades and states have time to assess their effectiveness before adopting them. SPRC19 allows users to identify, for example, whether states that were policy leaders for COVID-19 policies mirror those that lead in general, both in terms of adopting new policies faster and by influencing other states decisions to adopt those policies.  SPRC19 will be posted online for public access. To ensure widespread, continued access we have created a site to host it online at the Dataverse, a public data sharing repository, at https://dataverse.harvard.edu/dataverse/sprc19. These data are described in a paper presented at the 2022 Midwest Political Science Association's Annual Conference.  In addition to sharing the policy data, the work has a produced a number of other broader impacts. Most notably, the PIs have provided opportunities for nearly a dozen undergraduates to work on the project and collaborate on data analysis and paper writing. They have also successfully employed women and minorities on the project, including undergraduates interested in learning more about the application of data analytics in Political Science, some of whom have already been accepted to pursue advanced degrees starting in fall 2022.       Last Modified: 08/15/2022       Submitted by: Frederick J Boehmke]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
