<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Funerary Practices, Pandemic Confinement, and the Implications for COVID-19 Transmission]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>97509.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>97509</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jeffrey Mantz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jmantz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927783</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[In April 2020, the US Centers for Disease Control and Prevention identified funerals as high-risk sites for COVID-19 transmission. Funerals are vital to the social health of a community. They allow people to grieve together and remember their deceased, but when the bereaved are not permitted to gather physically, communal mourning becomes more complicated. Therefore, understanding forms of adapted, and accepted, virtual (online) rituals and memorials and their role in preventing infection spread is paramount for addressing future surges of COVID-19 across the United States, as well as for future epidemics. Preliminary research with religious leaders and funeral home directors suggests that social distancing mandates that interrupt funeral, burial, and memorial practices have met with confusion and even resistance. This study will provide key information for the development of public health programs and guidelines that address the risks facing communities that continue to conduct in-person rituals. Given the social importance of funerals and the central role of mourning in the pandemic, communities urgently need to promote practices that preserve the cultural and religious significance of such rites but do not exacerbate viral transmission. The project also provides training for graduate and undergraduate students in methods of rigorous, scientific data collection and analysis.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;The study comes at a time when the rate of COVID-19 infections is at risk of rising exponentially and funeral capacity is being overwhelmed. The investigators thus seek to identify factors that enable or inhibit people’s ability to follow social distancing guidelines that interrupt or run counter to obligations of care for the dead. As research on the Ebola crisis demonstrated, anthropologists’ focus on the local perspectives of grieving communities provided crucial insights into the factors that reduced or heightened the risk of infection, and thus played an important role in public health interventions. In collaboration with diverse religious communities, funeral practitioners, and representatives from the National Funeral Directors Association, the study will assess how religious tradition (or lack thereof) influences the adaptation of funeral rites, and how COVID-19-related constraints on funeral care shift the burden of organizing collective mourning onto the family and into virtual spaces. The project incorporates a range of methodological approaches aimed at capturing in real time these adaptive processes, including virtual participant observation (e.g., synchronous religious rites, and funeral and memorial services), initial and follow-up semi-structured interviews, discourse analysis of digital media, and survey instruments. The researchers will pay special attention to variations in access to virtual media. Because rituals reflect the capacity for communities, whether religious or secular, to marshal material and symbolic resources, they illuminate how structural inequalities create disparities across communities and generations. The study thus contributes foundational knowledge to the social analysis of death marked in virtual space, broadening our understanding of the interconnected roles of media, technology, and religion and during times of crisis.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/29/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/21/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2029839</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sarah</FirstName>
<LastName>Wagner</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sarah E Wagner</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[sewagner@gwu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000507327</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/29/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jorge</FirstName>
<LastName>Benavides-Rawson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jorge Benavides-Rawson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jbenavides@gwu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000767744</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/29/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Devin</FirstName>
<LastName>Proctor</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Devin Proctor</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[dproctor@gwu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000715720</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/29/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Roy Richard</FirstName>
<LastName>Grinker</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Roy Richard Grinker</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[rgrink@gwu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000314556</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/29/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Joel</FirstName>
<LastName>Kuipers</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Joel C Kuipers</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[kuipers@gwu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000319337</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/29/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>George Washington University</Name>
<CityName>WASHINGTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>200520042</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2029940728</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1918 F ST NW</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>ECR5E2LU5BL6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GEORGE WASHINGTON UNIVERSITY (THE)</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[George Washington University]]></Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>200520001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1390</Code>
<Text>Cultural Anthropology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1390</Code>
<Text>CULTURAL ANTHROPOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>1N20</Code>
<Name>R&amp;RA CARES Act DEFC N</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>010N2021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[R&RA CARES Act DEFC N]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~97509</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project examined changes in funeral, burial, and commemorative practices resulting from the COVID-19 pandemic and the associated restrictions placed on social gathering. Specifically, we observed and analyzed how rituals typically conducted in the physical presence of others were being transformed into virtual sites and practices. The study tracked such adaptations of ritual activity around death among mourners, deathcare workers (funeral directors and their staff), religious communities, as well as hospice and healthcare professionals.</p> <p>In doing so, the project has highlighted the role of media (broadly understood) and knowledge production during times of crisis. By observing and analyzing ritualized action around death in real time, as it unfolded, the study identified improvised practices such as online and livestreamed memorial services, Zoom funerals, social media channels dedicated to mourning COVID loss, and virtual commemorative events, and the multiple processes of negotiation and expression that brought these spaces and communities to life. Likewise, as a corrective to overly generalized cultural explanations of group behavior, this project?s focus on rituals during periods of pandemic confinement showcased the way asymmetrical distribution of resources can lead to variations in behavior, for example, the accessibility of technology, or religious or cultural traditions that undercut the ritual efficacy of improvised shifts to virtual platforms. In carrying out this multifaceted research, the project established diverse connections between religious, funeral, and academic communities, made possible by the project?s engagement with multiple funeral practitioners and associations, including through the National Association of Funeral Directors, National Funeral Directors&nbsp;and&nbsp;Morticians Association, and the Order of the Good Rule; religious associations, such as the National Black Church Initiative, the Islamic Medical Association of North America, and the Baltimore Hebrew Congregation; and COVID advocacy and commemorative initiatives, such as Marked By COVID, COVID Survivors for Change, In America: Remember, Mourning Our Losses, WhoWeLost.org, Rami?s Heart Memorial, Yellow Heart Memorial, and FacesOfCOVID. Through extensive oral histories, the project also examined the importance of African American funeral directors as both culture keepers and ?last responders? in communities that have disproportionately been impacted by the pandemic. Through the ethnographic data collected, including data related to digital access, demographic variables such as socioeconomic status and age, as well as particular beliefs and practices of different religious and cultural traditions, the project generated critical information to aid community readiness for restricted funeral and burial practices in the case of a protracted pandemic as well as in future epidemics.</p> <p>The preliminary results of the study have been disseminated through various channels, including the project?s website (<a href="https://ritualsinthemaking.com/">https://ritualsinthemaking.com/</a>), over a dozen presentations to academic and non-expert audiences, four opinion editorials published in major national news outlets, and two essays co-authored with undergraduate research assistants. Several other peer-reviewed academic articles and book chapters are also forthcoming. The project was instrumental in assisting the <em>In America: Remember</em> public art installation hosted on the National Mall and is leading the effort to create a digital archive of its 20,000 individually dedicated flags. The project also provided hands-on training in ethnographic research methods for over two dozen undergraduate and graduate students, who assisted with developing survey and interview instruments, gathering data, uploading and organizing those data to the cloud, and creating datasets in MAXQDA. That unique collaborative structure and composition of the research team, with senior and junior faculty working alongside undergraduate and graduate research assistants, demonstrated the advantages of interdisciplinary research that employs diverse methodological approaches.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/30/2023<br>      Modified by: Sarah&nbsp;E&nbsp;Wagner</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2029839/2029839_10667089_1693435776523_Photo1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2029839/2029839_10667089_1693435776523_Photo1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Pandemic Remembrance at the Lincoln Memorial Plaza"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2029839/2029839_10667089_1693435776523_Photo1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Pandemic Remembrance at the Lincoln Memorial Plaza"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The candlelight vigil marked the second anniversary of the beginning of the pandemic and included speakers Rima Samman of Rami's Heart Memorial and Diane Canney, founder of the Hope Quilt.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Emmy Numann</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Sarah&nbsp;E&nbsp;Wagner</div> <div class="imageTitle">Pandemic Remembrance at the Lincoln Memorial Plaza</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2029839/2029839_10667089_1693436035559_Photo3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2029839/2029839_10667089_1693436035559_Photo3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Marked By COVID White House Vigil"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2029839/2029839_10667089_1693436035559_Photo3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Marked By COVID White House Vigil"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Marked By COVID organized a candlelight vigil on the Ellipse in Washington DC to kick off its "Lobby Days" on Capitol Hill, July 26, 2021.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Sarah Wagner</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Sarah&nbsp;E&nbsp;Wagner</div> <div class="imageTitle">Marked By COVID White House Vigil</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2029839/2029839_10667089_1693436176882_Photo4--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2029839/2029839_10667089_1693436176882_Photo4--rgov-800width.jpg" title="In America: Remember"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2029839/2029839_10667089_1693436176882_Photo4--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="In America: Remember"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Visual artist Suzanne Firstenberg's COVID memorial, In America: Remember hosted on the National Mall, September 17 - October 3, 2021.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Sarah Wagner</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Sarah&nbsp;E&nbsp;Wagner</div> <div class="imageTitle">In America: Remember</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2029839/2029839_10667089_1693436408891_IMG_1833--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2029839/2029839_10667089_1693436408891_IMG_1833--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Cleaning the flags from In America: Remember"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2029839/2029839_10667089_1693436408891_IMG_1833--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Cleaning the flags from In America: Remember"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Research assistant Sebastian Sirais assists with the cleaning of dedicated flags from the In America: Remember installation.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Sarah Wagner</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Sarah&nbsp;E&nbsp;Wagner</div> <div class="imageTitle">Cleaning the flags from In America: Remember</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2029839/2029839_10667089_1693436646585_Photo6--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2029839/2029839_10667089_1693436646585_Photo6--rgov-800width.jpg" title="COVID-19 March to Remember Memorial"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2029839/2029839_10667089_1693436646585_Photo6--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="COVID-19 March to Remember Memorial"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The COVID-19 March to Remember memorial walk across the Brooklyn Bridge, on August 5, 2022.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Maura Kelly-Yuoh</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Sarah&nbsp;E&nbsp;Wagner</div> <div class="imageTitle">COVID-19 March to Remember Memorial</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project examined changes in funeral, burial, and commemorative practices resulting from the COVID-19 pandemic and the associated restrictions placed on social gathering. Specifically, we observed and analyzed how rituals typically conducted in the physical presence of others were being transformed into virtual sites and practices. The study tracked such adaptations of ritual activity around death among mourners, deathcare workers (funeral directors and their staff), religious communities, as well as hospice and healthcare professionals.  In doing so, the project has highlighted the role of media (broadly understood) and knowledge production during times of crisis. By observing and analyzing ritualized action around death in real time, as it unfolded, the study identified improvised practices such as online and livestreamed memorial services, Zoom funerals, social media channels dedicated to mourning COVID loss, and virtual commemorative events, and the multiple processes of negotiation and expression that brought these spaces and communities to life. Likewise, as a corrective to overly generalized cultural explanations of group behavior, this project?s focus on rituals during periods of pandemic confinement showcased the way asymmetrical distribution of resources can lead to variations in behavior, for example, the accessibility of technology, or religious or cultural traditions that undercut the ritual efficacy of improvised shifts to virtual platforms. In carrying out this multifaceted research, the project established diverse connections between religious, funeral, and academic communities, made possible by the project?s engagement with multiple funeral practitioners and associations, including through the National Association of Funeral Directors, National Funeral Directors and Morticians Association, and the Order of the Good Rule; religious associations, such as the National Black Church Initiative, the Islamic Medical Association of North America, and the Baltimore Hebrew Congregation; and COVID advocacy and commemorative initiatives, such as Marked By COVID, COVID Survivors for Change, In America: Remember, Mourning Our Losses, WhoWeLost.org, Rami?s Heart Memorial, Yellow Heart Memorial, and FacesOfCOVID. Through extensive oral histories, the project also examined the importance of African American funeral directors as both culture keepers and ?last responders? in communities that have disproportionately been impacted by the pandemic. Through the ethnographic data collected, including data related to digital access, demographic variables such as socioeconomic status and age, as well as particular beliefs and practices of different religious and cultural traditions, the project generated critical information to aid community readiness for restricted funeral and burial practices in the case of a protracted pandemic as well as in future epidemics.  The preliminary results of the study have been disseminated through various channels, including the project?s website (https://ritualsinthemaking.com/), over a dozen presentations to academic and non-expert audiences, four opinion editorials published in major national news outlets, and two essays co-authored with undergraduate research assistants. Several other peer-reviewed academic articles and book chapters are also forthcoming. The project was instrumental in assisting the In America: Remember public art installation hosted on the National Mall and is leading the effort to create a digital archive of its 20,000 individually dedicated flags. The project also provided hands-on training in ethnographic research methods for over two dozen undergraduate and graduate students, who assisted with developing survey and interview instruments, gathering data, uploading and organizing those data to the cloud, and creating datasets in MAXQDA. That unique collaborative structure and composition of the research team, with senior and junior faculty working alongside undergraduate and graduate research assistants, demonstrated the advantages of interdisciplinary research that employs diverse methodological approaches.           Last Modified: 08/30/2023       Submitted by: Sarah E Wagner]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
