<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Conserved Regions of the SARS-CoV-2 virus (COVID-19) RNA-RNA Interactions that Mediate Genome Dimerization and/or Progression Through the Viral Life Cycle]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>200000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>200000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Pui Ho</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>puiho@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032920000</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The genome of the severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2), the virus that causes coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19), is encoded in RNA. This award funds studies by Drs. Mihaela-Rita Mihailescu and Jeffrey D. Evanseck at Duquesne University in to determine the structures and signals in the RNA that control the progression of the virus through various stages of its life cycle. Drs. Mihailescu and Evanseck use biophysical and computational methods to determine how structures of distantly separated parts of the RNA interact to switch from early stage protein production to late stage virus production. In addition, the project studies how conserved structures bring two separate RNAs together to allow parts to swap between genomes through a process called recombination. This recombination process provides an understanding for how the SARS-CoV-2 genome may have arisen from the exchange of genetic material among RNAs from viruses that infect different mammalian species. The impact of the project on society is to identify potential inhibitors against RNA-RNA interactions, which further provides leads for the development of therapeutic interventions against the SARS-CoV-2 virus and, correspondingly, stem the COVID-19 pandemic.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This goal of this study is to elucidate the molecular mechanisms controlling the progression of SARS-CoV-2 through essential steps of its life cycle and unravel a new, unexplored mechanism of RNA genomic dimerization that might facilitate its recombination. This research guides future development of new antivirals that target the genomic RNA of SARS-CoV-2 and potentially other similar RNA viruses. Bioinformatics and biophysical methods, including fluorescence spectroscopy, will be applied to elucidate the function of a highly conserved s2m RNA motif and to probe the long-range RNA-RNA interactions between the conserved sequences in the 5’- and 3’-untranslated regions (UTRs) of viral genes. The s2m RNA motif is proposed to form a “kissing complex” intermediate that mediates dimerization of the SARS-CoV-2 RNA genome, thereby facilitating recombination events in coronaviruses and other additional viral families that share this motif. The UTRs are proposed to form "kissing interactions" that mediate the genome circularization, molecular switch that controls the transition between the translation and replication viral life cycle steps.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This grant is being awarded using funds made available by the Coronavirus Aid, Relief, and Economic Security (CARES) Act supplemental funds allocated to MPS.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/23/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/28/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2029124</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jeffrey</FirstName>
<LastName>Evanseck</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jeffrey D Evanseck</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[evanseck@duq.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000288320</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/23/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mihaela-Rita</FirstName>
<LastName>Mihailescu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mihaela-Rita Mihailescu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mihailescum@duq.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000114277</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/23/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Duquesne University</Name>
<CityName>PITTSBURGH</CityName>
<ZipCode>152820001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4123961537</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>600 FORBES AVENUE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NGYSJ2L1LZX3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>DUQUESNE UNIVERSITY OF THE HOLY SPIRIT</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>R8GSG4QZV989</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Duquesne University]]></Name>
<CityName>Pittsburgh</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>152820001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[600 Forbes Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>158Y</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>1N20</Code>
<Name>R&amp;RA CARES Act DEFC N</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>010N2021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[R&RA CARES Act DEFC N]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~200000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Despite the success of vaccines that target the severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) in curtailing the current COVID-19 pandemic, the world remains highly vulnerable to SARS-CoV-2 emerging mutants and other coronavirus outbreaks with devastating consequences. These outbreaks are highly probable and it is essential and urgent for the scientific community to be proactive rather than reactive by building a fundamental knowledge base about coronaviruses to address not only the current COVID-19 pandemic but also to be prepared for the next major outbreak. This project aimed to answer major questions regarding the SARS-CoV-2 and other coronaviruses&rsquo; life cycle and interactions with the host which still remain unanswered. For example, how are the various steps of the virus life cycle being mediated by conserved RNA sequences/structures in the virus genome? &nbsp;Or what type of interactions between the virus genome and the host cause such different outcomes observed in COVID-19 patients, which range from asymptomatic to severe or fatal cases in at-risk populations including individuals with obesity, diabetes, or cardiovascular disease or older adults?</p> <p>Specifically, we focused on one conserved element, named s2m, in the SARS-CoV-2 genome, which is shared also by three other viral families, suggesting that it confers a selective advantage. We proposed a unique function for the s2m element, namely that it is mediating the SARS-CoV-2 dimerization, which could mediate the process of viral recombination. Interestingly, we uncovered that this mechanism of dimerization is similar to that employed by the human immunodeficiency virus 1 and hepatitis C virus, respectively.</p> <p>We have also determined that while there are only two mutations within the s2m from SARS-CoV, the virus which caused the 2002-2003 SARS outbreak, and SARS-CoV-2 s2m, their dimerization properties are very different, suggesting that they might have different functions in the context of each virus. To explain this difference, we used computational chemistry, where models of each viral s2m were created and studied the dynamics of their structure. Our results are able to explain the experimental findings, indicating that the two mutations in SARS-CoV-2 s2m alter its structure in such a way to increase its flexibility.</p> <p>Moreover, in this study we identified virus-host microRNA interactions which could explain the differences observed in the severity of COVID-19 cases and lead to the development of antiviral therapeutics. Viruses have been shown to hijack microRNAs, which are host regulatory non-coding RNAs, for their own benefit. We have identified such a microRNA which has two binding sites on SARS-CoV-2 s2m and also designed modified oligonucleotides that compete with this microRNA for binding to the SARS-CoV-2 genome. Interestingly, this microRNA is proposed to regulate the production of multiple proteins in the host which are implicated in the immune response to viral infection. Such proteins have been shown to contribute to the &ldquo;cytokine storm&rdquo; observed in the severe COVID-19 cases. Thus, this work identified a new therapeutic target in the s2m-microRNA interactions which can be disrupted by modified oligonucleotides, releasing the microRNA to perform its normal regulatory function in the host with respect to the production of inflammatory proteins, and potential prevent the &ldquo;cytokine storm&rdquo;.</p> <p>Overall, this study resulted so far in three production of three peer-reviewed articles published in high impact-factor journals, one of which is featured on the cover of the <em>ACS Physical Chemistry Au</em> and in the filling of one patent (under revision).</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/31/2022<br>      Modified by: Mihaela-Rita&nbsp;Mihailescu</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2029124/2029124_10665831_1667230209259_Picture1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2029124/2029124_10665831_1667230209259_Picture1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="SARS-CoV-2 s2m element"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2029124/2029124_10665831_1667230209259_Picture1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="SARS-CoV-2 s2m element"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Artistic view of the SARS-CoV-2 s2m element based on our molecular dynamics simulations showing that it is very flexible.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Adam Kensinger</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Mihaela-Rita&nbsp;Mihailescu</div> <div class="imageTitle">SARS-CoV-2 s2m element</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Despite the success of vaccines that target the severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) in curtailing the current COVID-19 pandemic, the world remains highly vulnerable to SARS-CoV-2 emerging mutants and other coronavirus outbreaks with devastating consequences. These outbreaks are highly probable and it is essential and urgent for the scientific community to be proactive rather than reactive by building a fundamental knowledge base about coronaviruses to address not only the current COVID-19 pandemic but also to be prepared for the next major outbreak. This project aimed to answer major questions regarding the SARS-CoV-2 and other coronaviruses’ life cycle and interactions with the host which still remain unanswered. For example, how are the various steps of the virus life cycle being mediated by conserved RNA sequences/structures in the virus genome?  Or what type of interactions between the virus genome and the host cause such different outcomes observed in COVID-19 patients, which range from asymptomatic to severe or fatal cases in at-risk populations including individuals with obesity, diabetes, or cardiovascular disease or older adults?  Specifically, we focused on one conserved element, named s2m, in the SARS-CoV-2 genome, which is shared also by three other viral families, suggesting that it confers a selective advantage. We proposed a unique function for the s2m element, namely that it is mediating the SARS-CoV-2 dimerization, which could mediate the process of viral recombination. Interestingly, we uncovered that this mechanism of dimerization is similar to that employed by the human immunodeficiency virus 1 and hepatitis C virus, respectively.  We have also determined that while there are only two mutations within the s2m from SARS-CoV, the virus which caused the 2002-2003 SARS outbreak, and SARS-CoV-2 s2m, their dimerization properties are very different, suggesting that they might have different functions in the context of each virus. To explain this difference, we used computational chemistry, where models of each viral s2m were created and studied the dynamics of their structure. Our results are able to explain the experimental findings, indicating that the two mutations in SARS-CoV-2 s2m alter its structure in such a way to increase its flexibility.  Moreover, in this study we identified virus-host microRNA interactions which could explain the differences observed in the severity of COVID-19 cases and lead to the development of antiviral therapeutics. Viruses have been shown to hijack microRNAs, which are host regulatory non-coding RNAs, for their own benefit. We have identified such a microRNA which has two binding sites on SARS-CoV-2 s2m and also designed modified oligonucleotides that compete with this microRNA for binding to the SARS-CoV-2 genome. Interestingly, this microRNA is proposed to regulate the production of multiple proteins in the host which are implicated in the immune response to viral infection. Such proteins have been shown to contribute to the "cytokine storm" observed in the severe COVID-19 cases. Thus, this work identified a new therapeutic target in the s2m-microRNA interactions which can be disrupted by modified oligonucleotides, releasing the microRNA to perform its normal regulatory function in the host with respect to the production of inflammatory proteins, and potential prevent the "cytokine storm".  Overall, this study resulted so far in three production of three peer-reviewed articles published in high impact-factor journals, one of which is featured on the cover of the ACS Physical Chemistry Au and in the filling of one patent (under revision).          Last Modified: 10/31/2022       Submitted by: Mihaela-Rita Mihailescu]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
