<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Hydrated Graphene Oxide Elastomeric Composites for Sterilizable and Reusable N95 Masks]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>200000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>200000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Paul Lane</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>plane@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922453</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The ongoing COVID-19 pandemic has led to a shortage of critical medical equipment, including N95 masks. In order to conserve resources and maintain some level of protection against COVID-19, medical workers have begun reusing masks. While ultraviolet germicidal irradiation (UVGI), a widely used sterilization technique in medical settings, has been shown to be effective at disinfecting mask filters, it is not recommended by mask manufacturers due to deterioration of elastomeric components such as the nose foam and head straps that prevents an effective fit following sterilization. UVGI utilizes radiation in the deep-UV portion of the electromagnetic spectrum due to its strong absorption by microbial nucleic acids, which leads to their degradation. However, currently used elastomeric materials are similarly compromised at these deep-UV wavelengths. Therefore, it is of high urgency to develop elastomeric materials that are resistant to UVGI irradiation to enable decontamination and reuse of N95 masks. It would be of even greater interest if the same UV-resistant elastomeric materials also possessed intrinsic antimicrobial properties to further minimize the spread of COVID-19. Hydrated graphene oxide is known to possess both of these desirable attributes concurrently – namely, strong optical absorption at deep-UV wavelengths and proven antimicrobial properties. This project thus aims to rapidly develop elastomeric composites based on hydrated graphene oxide in order to enable the sterilization and reuse of N95 masks. Importantly, the outcomes of this research not only address the current COVID-19 crisis, but are applicable for general medical use including future pandemics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is synthesizing elastomeric composites based on hydrated graphene oxide (hGO) to enable N95 mask sterilization and reuse during COVID-19 and future pandemics. Not only does hGO provide resistance to ultraviolet germicidal irradiation (UVGI) irradiation, it also imparts antimicrobial properties. UVGI resistance results from the fact that polymeric additives that absorb UV light provide UV resistance to the composite. In this case, like all graphene materials, hGO is highly absorbing at deep-UV wavelengths due to the conjugated portions of the hGO structure. In addition, the high radical content of hGO is known to induce lipid peroxidation, destroying the integrity of lipid membranes and hence imparting nearly ubiquitous antimicrobial properties. Since enveloped viruses like COVID-19 also possesses lipid membranes, hGO is expected to be effective as an antiviral agent in this context. To assess the effect of UVGI on elastomeric mechanical properties, the hGO composites are subjected to tensile and cyclic fatigue testing following deep-UV exposure for stress/strain measurements and lifetime durability. Electron paramagnetic resonance spectroscopy on control and deep-UV irradiated samples further quantify the radical content imparted by hGO, thus providing insight into how deep-UV exposure affects radical production and antimicrobial efficiency. By varying the amount of hGO and/or related chemically functionalized graphene materials, a durable elastomeric composite is being realized in which the UV resistance, mechanical properties, and antimicrobial activity are optimized for N95 mask sterilization and reuse.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/15/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/15/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2029058</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
<LastName>Hersam</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mark C Hersam</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[m-hersam@northwestern.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000307184</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/15/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Northwestern University</Name>
<CityName>EVANSTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>602080001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3125037955</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>633 CLARK STREET</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>EXZVPWZBLUE8</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORTHWESTERN UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Northwestern University]]></Name>
<CityName>Evanston</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>602080893</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2220 Campus Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1253</Code>
<Text>OFFICE OF MULTIDISCIPLINARY AC</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1712</Code>
<Text>DMR SHORT TERM SUPPORT</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1775</Code>
<Text>ELECTRONIC/PHOTONIC MATERIALS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8614</Code>
<Text>Nanomaterials</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~200000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Intellectual Merit:</strong></p> <p>The initial stages of the COVID-19 pandemic led to a dramatic shortage of critical personal protective equipment (PPE), including N95 masks, which offer high levels of protection against aerosol-borne pathogens. As a result, many medical personnel were forced to reuse N95 masks, oftentimes without proper sterilization. Ultraviolet germicidal irradiation (UVGI), utilizing the ultraviolet-C (UV-C) portion of the electromagnetic spectrum, is a widely used sterilization technique in medical settings that has been shown to be effective at disinfecting N95 mask filters due to strong UV-C absorption by microbial nucleic acids. However, UVGI is not recommended by N95 mask manufacturers, primarily due to degradation of the elastomeric head straps, which compromises an effective fit and hence decreases filtration efficacy. Although N95 masks are no longer in short supply, aging of N95 mask straps and seals can also influence fit and effectiveness, posing challenges to long-term stockpiling of N95 masks. Therefore, to be better prepared for future pandemics, it is of high urgency to develop elastomeric materials that are resistant to UVGI irradiation, enabling decontamination and reuse of N95 masks and related PPE.</p> <p>Through this NSF RAPID grant, the formulation and testing of free-standing composites of polyurethane (PU) and graphene were explored. PU was chosen as a prototypical elastomeric matrix due to its widespread use in many applications, including N95 mask straps. While graphene and graphene-based PU composites have been studied previously for UV and weathering resistance, these previous reports have focused on graphene coatings rather than free-standing composites, only explored UV wavelengths outside the UV-C spectrum, and/or did not perform mechanical testing. In contrast, the free-standing composites explored in this project were optimized to preserve their elastomeric mechanical properties following simulated UVGI conditions. In particular, unlike pristine PU that is microstructurally damaged and degrades in mechanical quality after prolonged UV-C exposure, the graphene-polyurethane (Gr-PU) composites developed in this project prevented UV-induced cracking and thus preserved mechanical properties. As an added benefit, the graphene additive serves as a mechanical reinforcement such that the Gr-PU composites after 30 hours of UV-C exposure still possess superior mechanical properties compared to PU before any UV-C exposure. In this manner, Gr-PU composite mask straps enable sterilization and reuse of N95 masks for at least 150 UVGI decontamination cycles. Since elastomers are used in many other PPE applications (e.g., safety gloves), these UVGI-compatible Gr-PU composites can be widely utilized in other PPE contexts, thus providing an effective means of minimizing disposable PPE waste.</p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts:</strong></p> <p>In addition to peer-reviewed publications, this grant resulted in substantial intellectual property and commercialization opportunities. The latest developments in graphene-based composite materials were also incorporated into education and outreach activities that target students and the general public. Specific broader impacts include:</p> <p>(1) PhD student and postdoctoral training: This grant involved 3 PhD students and 1 postdoctoral researcher in Materials Science and Engineering including 1 under-represented minority and 2 female researchers.</p> <p>(2) Undergraduate student training: An undergraduate researcher actively participated in all aspects of the project and was included as a co-author and co-inventor on the peer-reviewed publication and invention disclosure resulting from this work.</p> <p>(3) This project was disseminated to the general public via media reports developed in collaboration with the Northwestern University Global Marketing and Communications Department. These press releases highlighted the importance of scientific research in rapidly finding effective solutions to acute problems that arise during public health crises such as the COVID-19 pandemic.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/21/2022<br>      Modified by: Mark&nbsp;C&nbsp;Hersam</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Intellectual Merit:  The initial stages of the COVID-19 pandemic led to a dramatic shortage of critical personal protective equipment (PPE), including N95 masks, which offer high levels of protection against aerosol-borne pathogens. As a result, many medical personnel were forced to reuse N95 masks, oftentimes without proper sterilization. Ultraviolet germicidal irradiation (UVGI), utilizing the ultraviolet-C (UV-C) portion of the electromagnetic spectrum, is a widely used sterilization technique in medical settings that has been shown to be effective at disinfecting N95 mask filters due to strong UV-C absorption by microbial nucleic acids. However, UVGI is not recommended by N95 mask manufacturers, primarily due to degradation of the elastomeric head straps, which compromises an effective fit and hence decreases filtration efficacy. Although N95 masks are no longer in short supply, aging of N95 mask straps and seals can also influence fit and effectiveness, posing challenges to long-term stockpiling of N95 masks. Therefore, to be better prepared for future pandemics, it is of high urgency to develop elastomeric materials that are resistant to UVGI irradiation, enabling decontamination and reuse of N95 masks and related PPE.  Through this NSF RAPID grant, the formulation and testing of free-standing composites of polyurethane (PU) and graphene were explored. PU was chosen as a prototypical elastomeric matrix due to its widespread use in many applications, including N95 mask straps. While graphene and graphene-based PU composites have been studied previously for UV and weathering resistance, these previous reports have focused on graphene coatings rather than free-standing composites, only explored UV wavelengths outside the UV-C spectrum, and/or did not perform mechanical testing. In contrast, the free-standing composites explored in this project were optimized to preserve their elastomeric mechanical properties following simulated UVGI conditions. In particular, unlike pristine PU that is microstructurally damaged and degrades in mechanical quality after prolonged UV-C exposure, the graphene-polyurethane (Gr-PU) composites developed in this project prevented UV-induced cracking and thus preserved mechanical properties. As an added benefit, the graphene additive serves as a mechanical reinforcement such that the Gr-PU composites after 30 hours of UV-C exposure still possess superior mechanical properties compared to PU before any UV-C exposure. In this manner, Gr-PU composite mask straps enable sterilization and reuse of N95 masks for at least 150 UVGI decontamination cycles. Since elastomers are used in many other PPE applications (e.g., safety gloves), these UVGI-compatible Gr-PU composites can be widely utilized in other PPE contexts, thus providing an effective means of minimizing disposable PPE waste.  Broader Impacts:  In addition to peer-reviewed publications, this grant resulted in substantial intellectual property and commercialization opportunities. The latest developments in graphene-based composite materials were also incorporated into education and outreach activities that target students and the general public. Specific broader impacts include:  (1) PhD student and postdoctoral training: This grant involved 3 PhD students and 1 postdoctoral researcher in Materials Science and Engineering including 1 under-represented minority and 2 female researchers.  (2) Undergraduate student training: An undergraduate researcher actively participated in all aspects of the project and was included as a co-author and co-inventor on the peer-reviewed publication and invention disclosure resulting from this work.  (3) This project was disseminated to the general public via media reports developed in collaboration with the Northwestern University Global Marketing and Communications Department. These press releases highlighted the importance of scientific research in rapidly finding effective solutions to acute problems that arise during public health crises such as the COVID-19 pandemic.          Last Modified: 08/21/2022       Submitted by: Mark C Hersam]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
