<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Legal Epidemiology Satellite Conference at 2021 Law Enforcement in Public Health Conference</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>11/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>45651.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>45651</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Reginald Sheehan</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rsheehan@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925389</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Law enforcement and public health (LEPH)are historically distinct domains. Law enforcement has been tied primarily to public order and criminal investigations, while public health’s focus is most closely aligned with establishing conditions most conducive to health. In spite of that, the fields share much common ground, with the central objective of both being the preservation of human well-being through the regulation of behavior toward safety and security. Research on effectiveness and impact of interventions can and should be an indispensable guide to practice and policy-making. Past annual LEPH conferences hosted by the Global Law Enforcement and Public Health Association have included robust participation from researchers as well as practitioners. The conference in March 2021 and this proposed satellite offer a much-needed opportunity to engage more researchers in the dissemination of high quality research on the effects of law on public health (legal epidemiology). Linking this proposed satellite with the regular conference will give more researchers the opportunity to interact with the views, challenges and innovations of the practitioners they study. And, deliberately incorporating legal epidemiology methods and research into the LEPH conference exposes a greater, new audience of scholars and practitioners to the methods and their applications, and supports further integral connection between the disciplines.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;The satellite meeting provides an opportunity for researchers in criminology, public health and law, and society research to articulate a collaborative agenda, including important research questions and the development of shared, formalized metrics. The meeting will have four areas of inquiry: 1) measuring the effects of criminal law and law enforcement on the social determinants of health; 2) developing shared metrics to inform LEPH strategy and practice; 3) understanding people’s experiences of laws and legal practices and their effects on health; and 4) identifying the role of health law in promoting first responder health and wellness. The satellite also has broad-reaching impact by generating increased scientific literacy in the area of legal epidemiology among practitioners working at the interface of LEPH, and among junior scholars. For the research community, the satellite will advance translational research at the interface of law enforcement and public health, illustrating the value of legal epidemiology in bridging theories and methods across the two fields. It will advance scientific knowledge of the complex relationships between law, law enforcement and public health, and it will help make the case for an enhanced infrastructure for inter-disciplinary, cross-sector research on law and its various influences on the public's health. For the policy community, it will highlight areas of law-making and law enforcement that can be actionable targets of innovation and reform, in furtherance of public health. It will illuminate direct and indirect ways in which laws and law enforcement practices reinforce or exacerbate disparities in health.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>10/21/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/21/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2029992</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Scott</FirstName>
<LastName>Burris</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Scott Burris</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>scott.burris@temple.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2152046576</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000619191</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>10/21/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Temple University</Name>
<CityName>PHILADELPHIA</CityName>
<ZipCode>191226003</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2157077547</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1801 N BROAD ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>QD4MGHFDJKU1</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TEMPLE UNIVERSITY-OF THE COMMONWEALTH SYSTEM OF HIGHER EDUCATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>QD4MGHFDJKU1</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Temple University]]></Name>
<CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>191226003</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1801 N. Broad Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>128Y</Code>
<Text>Law &amp; Science</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~45651</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project sought to build a diverse intellectual environment that would bring empirical research more strongly into the programming of the largely practice-focused community at the 6th Global Conference on Law Enforcement and Public Health, and to establish a more formalized community of practice for research in law enforcement and public health (LEPH). The Center for Public Health Law Research at Temple University?s Beasley School of Law (CPHLR) is one of the nation?s leading centers of legal epidemiology research. Legal epidemiology is devoted to the scientific study and deployment of law as a factor in public health. For practitioners in both law enforcement and public health, research on effectiveness and impact of interventions can and should be an indispensable guide to practice. From a social perspective, only strong research can inform the public and policymakers as they make judgments about the direction of policy. Past LEPH conferences have included robust participation from researchers as well as practitioners. The US conference and this satellite offered a much-needed opportunity to engage more U.S. researchers in the global dissemination of high-quality research on the effects of law on public health.</p> <p>The Center for Public Health Law Research and the conference planning committee convened a virtual satellite conference in March 2021 on legal epidemiology and law enforcement and public health, that had more than 55 registrants from global research and practice-focused institutions. Attendees viewed two pre-conference plenaries and then participated in five, live virtual discussions featuring 23 researchers from around the world presenting their scholarship on the future of research on the health effects of policing; measuring the health effects of drug policy and its enforcement; measuring the health effects on legal drug use; mapping of laws related US, Australian, and US tribal criminal justice issues; and the impacts of police practices on health effects and the social determinants of health. These presentations are now available for public viewing on <a href="https://youtube.com/playlist?list=PLrpCbUDomLdkoHcStKCsSE0v4IvLkLpJV">YouTube</a>. The project team also produced an introductory video about the field of legal epidemiology (also available on <a href="https://youtu.be/tQEUj1rYAIw">YouTube</a>) that has increased awareness and understanding of the discipline.</p> <p>The conference has had broad-reaching impact by generating increased scientific literacy in the area of legal epidemiology among practitioners working at the interface of LEPH and among junior scholars. It has elevated the stature of legal epidemiology in the global field of law enforcement and public health by displaying prominent and high-quality examples of research from highly relevant areas of concern within the field (e.g., drug policy, effects of policing on mental health and other social determinants of health). For the specific research and policy communities that define the field, this conference supported opportunities to advance translational research at the intersection of law enforcement and public health, illustrating the value of legal epidemiology in bridging theories and methods across the two fields. It advanced scientific knowledge of the complex relationships between law, law enforcement and public health, by engaging with those theories and methods in a collegial and informal, discussion-based platform. It helped make the case for an enhanced infrastructure for inter-disciplinary, cross-sector research on law and its various influences on the public's health.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/09/2022<br>      Modified by: Scott&nbsp;Burris</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project sought to build a diverse intellectual environment that would bring empirical research more strongly into the programming of the largely practice-focused community at the 6th Global Conference on Law Enforcement and Public Health, and to establish a more formalized community of practice for research in law enforcement and public health (LEPH). The Center for Public Health Law Research at Temple University?s Beasley School of Law (CPHLR) is one of the nation?s leading centers of legal epidemiology research. Legal epidemiology is devoted to the scientific study and deployment of law as a factor in public health. For practitioners in both law enforcement and public health, research on effectiveness and impact of interventions can and should be an indispensable guide to practice. From a social perspective, only strong research can inform the public and policymakers as they make judgments about the direction of policy. Past LEPH conferences have included robust participation from researchers as well as practitioners. The US conference and this satellite offered a much-needed opportunity to engage more U.S. researchers in the global dissemination of high-quality research on the effects of law on public health.  The Center for Public Health Law Research and the conference planning committee convened a virtual satellite conference in March 2021 on legal epidemiology and law enforcement and public health, that had more than 55 registrants from global research and practice-focused institutions. Attendees viewed two pre-conference plenaries and then participated in five, live virtual discussions featuring 23 researchers from around the world presenting their scholarship on the future of research on the health effects of policing; measuring the health effects of drug policy and its enforcement; measuring the health effects on legal drug use; mapping of laws related US, Australian, and US tribal criminal justice issues; and the impacts of police practices on health effects and the social determinants of health. These presentations are now available for public viewing on YouTube. The project team also produced an introductory video about the field of legal epidemiology (also available on YouTube) that has increased awareness and understanding of the discipline.  The conference has had broad-reaching impact by generating increased scientific literacy in the area of legal epidemiology among practitioners working at the interface of LEPH and among junior scholars. It has elevated the stature of legal epidemiology in the global field of law enforcement and public health by displaying prominent and high-quality examples of research from highly relevant areas of concern within the field (e.g., drug policy, effects of policing on mental health and other social determinants of health). For the specific research and policy communities that define the field, this conference supported opportunities to advance translational research at the intersection of law enforcement and public health, illustrating the value of legal epidemiology in bridging theories and methods across the two fields. It advanced scientific knowledge of the complex relationships between law, law enforcement and public health, by engaging with those theories and methods in a collegial and informal, discussion-based platform. It helped make the case for an enhanced infrastructure for inter-disciplinary, cross-sector research on law and its various influences on the public's health.          Last Modified: 02/09/2022       Submitted by: Scott Burris]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
