<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Development of an ultrasensitive thermal contrast amplification lateral flow immunoassay for rapid, point-of-care COVID-19 diagnosis]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>200000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>200000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ron Joslin</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rjoslin@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927030</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Innovative and unique thermal contrast technology will be used to detect heat from laser irradiated gold nanoparticles to vastly improve the sensitivity of rapid diagnostics tests (i.e. lateral flow assays) designed to detect and diagnose COVID-19. This technology, which has been used to significantly improve lateral flow assays for HIV, malaria, Strep and influenza, will enable widespread, inexpensive (&lt; $1/test), rapid (≤ 10 minutes), point-of-care detection of COVID-19. Such detection does not exist and cannot exist using the current methodologies for detecting both early (i.e. viral protein) and late (i.e. antibody) stages of COVID-19 infection. These new, thermal contrast lateral flow assays, along with new thermal contrast “reading” technology, will accelerate effective and targeted testing and surveillance of disease spread and management and bring enormous benefits to both national and global society.  While first deployment will be in clinical settings, it is envisioned that this technology can eventually be used at schools, airports, sporting and entertainment events and even at home to assess the infection and spread of COVID-19 and other infectious diseases.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed research will develop new lateral flow assays to be used with innovative thermal contrast technology for highly sensitive, inexpensive, point-of-care detection of COVID-19. This new paradigm will, in the long term, be applied to a wide variety of diseases. Lateral flow assays are arguably the cheapest, fastest and easiest to use rapid diagnostic assays in the world.  While they are used qualitatively for numerous diseases, they have weaknesses that include lack of sensitivity and quantification of disease burden.  Both of these issues are addressed through our novel Thermal Contrast Assay technology. To address this specifically for COVID-19, two approaches are proposed: 1) optimizing gold nanoparticles and lateral flow assays for binding either COVID-19 protein or COVID-19 antibody analytes, and 2) the use of a new quantitative figure of merit called the “Binding Ratio” to rapidly identify reagents and components for optimized thermal contrast lateral flow assays. This project is part of a larger effort with industry partners to scale up the manufacturing of a proprietary thermal contrast reader so that it will be affordable for point-of-care clinical settings such as doctors’ offices, urgent care settings, emergency rooms, and field hospitals.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/29/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/29/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2029474</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Bischof</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John C Bischof</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[bischof@umn.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000438636</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/29/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Minnesota-Twin Cities</Name>
<CityName>MINNEAPOLIS</CityName>
<ZipCode>554552009</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6126245599</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>200 OAK ST SE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>KABJZBBJ4B54</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MINNESOTA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Minnesota-Twin Cities]]></Name>
<CityName>Minneapolis</CityName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>554550150</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[111 Church St SE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>158Y</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>1N20</Code>
<Name>R&amp;RA CARES Act DEFC N</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>010N2021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[R&RA CARES Act DEFC N]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~200000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The rapid NSF grant supported our lab to review and prospect the current and future ultrasensitive point-of-care (POC) diagnostics, develop lab-based advanced lateral flow immunoassay (LFA) coupled with thermal contrast amplification (TCA) for SARS-CoV-2 antigen diagnostics, and upgrade the TCA reader for ultrafast and ultrasensitive reading.</p> <p>In our Perspective paper, we reviewed the evolving efforts to increase the sensitivity and specificity of LFAs, as summarized in Figure 1. Recent work to improve the sensitivity through assay improvement includes optimization of the assay kinetics and signal amplification by either reader systems or additional reagents. Together, these efforts have produced LFAs with ELISA-level sensitivities (pM ? fM). In addition, sample pre-amplification can be applied to both nucleic acids (direct amplification) and other analytes (indirect amplification) prior to LFA testing, which can lead to PCR-level (aM) sensitivity (Figure 2). Perspectives are also provided to achieve future rapid (&lt; 30 min), ultra-sensitive (PCR-level), and ?sample-to-answer? POC diagnostics with high specificity.</p> <p>Recently, the SARS-CoV-2 global pandemic created an unprecedented need for rapid, sensitive, and inexpensive POC diagnostic tests to treat and control the disease. Many POC SARS-CoV-2 LFAs have been developed and/or commercialized, but with only limited sensitivity (M-fM). To improve POC diagnostic sensitivity, we created an advanced LFA based on gold nanospheres (GNSs) with comprehensive assay redesign for enhanced specific binding and thermal contrast signal amplification fold on GNSs for signal amplification, which enabled fM-aM detection sensitivity for SARS-CoV-2 spike receptor-binding domain (RBD) proteins within 30 min (Figure 3). The advanced LFA can visually detect RBD proteins down to 3.6 aM and 28.6 aM in buffer and human nasopharyngeal wash, respectively. This is the first reported LFA achieving sensitivity comparable to that of the PCR (aM-zM) by visual reading, which was much more sensitive than traditional LFAs (Figure 3). We also developed a fast (&lt; 1 min) TCA reading algorithm, with results showing that this TCA could distinguish 26%~32% visual false negatives for clinical commercial LFAs. When our advanced LFAs were applied with this TCA, the sensitivities were further improved by 8-fold to 0.45 aM (in buffer) and 3.6 aM (in human nasopharyngeal wash) with semi-quantitative readout. Our proposed advanced LFA with TCA diagnostic platform can help control the current SARS-CoV-2 pandemic. Furthermore, the simplicity and speed with which this assay was assembled may also facilitate preparedness for future pandemics.</p> <p>In addition to assay improvement, we also explored the limit TCA reading of gold nanoparticles (GNPs/mm2) at test regions in immunoassays. More specifically, we upgraded fast (minute scale) setup equipped with a continuous-wave (CW) laser to an ultrafast (seconds scale) TCA setup using ms pulsed lasers. &nbsp;Evaluation measurement showed that both TCAs improved the limit of detection (LoD) for silica-core gold nanoshells (GNShs) in model LFAs by10~20-fold over visual reading (unpublished). To allow higher laser power, and therefore amplification fold, we also explored transparent glass coverslip substrate as a model microfluidic immunoassay (MIA). It was found the ultrafast TCA reading of GNSh-coated coverslips achieved a maximal signal amplification (57-fold) over visual reading of LFAs (unpublished). Therefore, ultrafast TCA-MIA is promising for ultrasensitive and ultrafast diagnostics. Further advantages of using TCA in MIA vs. LFA could include lower sample volume, multiplexed tests, higher throughput, and fast reading. In summary, TCA technology is able to enhance the sensitivity and speed of reading GNPs (GNPs/mm2) within both LFAs and MIAs.</p> <p>In summary, our research funded by this rapid NSF grant focused on ultrasensitive point-of-care diagnostics based on photothermal GNPs. In addition to review and perspective work, we also developed our advanced LFA with TCA diagnostic platform for ultrasensitive diagnostics of SARS-CoV-2 antigen and upgraded TCA setup for ultrafast and ultrasensitive reading.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/12/2022<br>      Modified by: John&nbsp;C&nbsp;Bischof</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2029474/2029474_10666904_1655063612501_Picture1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2029474/2029474_10666904_1655063612501_Picture1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Overview of strategies to improve the sensitivity and specificity of lateral flow assays (LFAs)."><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2029474/2029474_10666904_1655063612501_Picture1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Overview of strategies to improve the sensitivity and specificity of lateral flow assays (LFAs)."></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">(A) Schematic of a sandwich LFA. (B) Sample enrichment: The analyte in a sample can be pre-concentrated and/or amplified to enhance the detection limit. (C) Assay optimization: Assay performance can be improved by altering the assay kinetics and reagents. (D) Signal amplification: Signals from LFAs</div> <div class="imageCredit">Zhan et al. Nano-Letters 2017</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">John&nbsp;C&nbsp;Bischof</div> <div class="imageTitle">Overview of strategies to improve the sensitivity and specificity of lateral flow assays (LFAs).</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2029474/2029474_10666904_1655063722723_Picture2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2029474/2029474_10666904_1655063722723_Picture2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Comparison of the analytical sensitivity and diagnostic speed of signal-amplified lateral flow assays (LFAs) with those of other diagnostic tools."><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2029474/2029474_10666904_1655063722723_Picture2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Comparison of the analytical sensitivity and diagnostic speed of signal-amplified lateral flow assays (LFAs) with those of other diagnostic tools."></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">(A) Comparison of signal-amplified LFAs with emerging isothermal nucleic acid amplification diagnostics, digital enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (dELISA), and commercial diagnostic tools. PCR: polymerase chain reaction; POC: point of care.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Liu et al. ACS Nano 2021</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">John&nbsp;C&nbsp;Bischof</div> <div class="imageTitle">Comparison of the analytical sensitivity and diagnostic speed of signal-amplified lateral flow assays (LFAs) with those of other diagnostic tools.</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2029474/2029474_10666904_1655063865645_Picture3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2029474/2029474_10666904_1655063865645_Picture3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Analytical performance of the SARS-CoV-2 spike receptor-binding domain (RBD) protein LFA with TCA."><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2029474/2029474_10666904_1655063865645_Picture3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Analytical performance of the SARS-CoV-2 spike receptor-binding domain (RBD) protein LFA with TCA."></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">(A) Thermal signals of test lines to test RBD proteins in running buffer. (B) Thermal signals of test lines to test RBD proteins in the pooled human nasopharyngeal wash. The covalent conjugation was used to prepare those LFAs. (C) Comparing detection sensitivity and assay time of the advanced LFA fr</div> <div class="imageCredit">Liu et al. ACS Appl. Nano Mater 2021</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">John&nbsp;C&nbsp;Bischof</div> <div class="imageTitle">Analytical performance of the SARS-CoV-2 spike receptor-binding domain (RBD) protein LFA with TCA.</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The rapid NSF grant supported our lab to review and prospect the current and future ultrasensitive point-of-care (POC) diagnostics, develop lab-based advanced lateral flow immunoassay (LFA) coupled with thermal contrast amplification (TCA) for SARS-CoV-2 antigen diagnostics, and upgrade the TCA reader for ultrafast and ultrasensitive reading.  In our Perspective paper, we reviewed the evolving efforts to increase the sensitivity and specificity of LFAs, as summarized in Figure 1. Recent work to improve the sensitivity through assay improvement includes optimization of the assay kinetics and signal amplification by either reader systems or additional reagents. Together, these efforts have produced LFAs with ELISA-level sensitivities (pM ? fM). In addition, sample pre-amplification can be applied to both nucleic acids (direct amplification) and other analytes (indirect amplification) prior to LFA testing, which can lead to PCR-level (aM) sensitivity (Figure 2). Perspectives are also provided to achieve future rapid (&lt; 30 min), ultra-sensitive (PCR-level), and ?sample-to-answer? POC diagnostics with high specificity.  Recently, the SARS-CoV-2 global pandemic created an unprecedented need for rapid, sensitive, and inexpensive POC diagnostic tests to treat and control the disease. Many POC SARS-CoV-2 LFAs have been developed and/or commercialized, but with only limited sensitivity (M-fM). To improve POC diagnostic sensitivity, we created an advanced LFA based on gold nanospheres (GNSs) with comprehensive assay redesign for enhanced specific binding and thermal contrast signal amplification fold on GNSs for signal amplification, which enabled fM-aM detection sensitivity for SARS-CoV-2 spike receptor-binding domain (RBD) proteins within 30 min (Figure 3). The advanced LFA can visually detect RBD proteins down to 3.6 aM and 28.6 aM in buffer and human nasopharyngeal wash, respectively. This is the first reported LFA achieving sensitivity comparable to that of the PCR (aM-zM) by visual reading, which was much more sensitive than traditional LFAs (Figure 3). We also developed a fast (&lt; 1 min) TCA reading algorithm, with results showing that this TCA could distinguish 26%~32% visual false negatives for clinical commercial LFAs. When our advanced LFAs were applied with this TCA, the sensitivities were further improved by 8-fold to 0.45 aM (in buffer) and 3.6 aM (in human nasopharyngeal wash) with semi-quantitative readout. Our proposed advanced LFA with TCA diagnostic platform can help control the current SARS-CoV-2 pandemic. Furthermore, the simplicity and speed with which this assay was assembled may also facilitate preparedness for future pandemics.  In addition to assay improvement, we also explored the limit TCA reading of gold nanoparticles (GNPs/mm2) at test regions in immunoassays. More specifically, we upgraded fast (minute scale) setup equipped with a continuous-wave (CW) laser to an ultrafast (seconds scale) TCA setup using ms pulsed lasers.  Evaluation measurement showed that both TCAs improved the limit of detection (LoD) for silica-core gold nanoshells (GNShs) in model LFAs by10~20-fold over visual reading (unpublished). To allow higher laser power, and therefore amplification fold, we also explored transparent glass coverslip substrate as a model microfluidic immunoassay (MIA). It was found the ultrafast TCA reading of GNSh-coated coverslips achieved a maximal signal amplification (57-fold) over visual reading of LFAs (unpublished). Therefore, ultrafast TCA-MIA is promising for ultrasensitive and ultrafast diagnostics. Further advantages of using TCA in MIA vs. LFA could include lower sample volume, multiplexed tests, higher throughput, and fast reading. In summary, TCA technology is able to enhance the sensitivity and speed of reading GNPs (GNPs/mm2) within both LFAs and MIAs.  In summary, our research funded by this rapid NSF grant focused on ultrasensitive point-of-care diagnostics based on photothermal GNPs. In addition to review and perspective work, we also developed our advanced LFA with TCA diagnostic platform for ultrasensitive diagnostics of SARS-CoV-2 antigen and upgraded TCA setup for ultrafast and ultrasensitive reading.          Last Modified: 06/12/2022       Submitted by: John C Bischof]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
