<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>I-Corps:  A cloud-based searchable catalog to link geographically and population diverse patient genomic, phenotypic and clinical data</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ruth Shuman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rshuman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922160</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this I-Corps project is to develop a cloud-based, searchable catalog to provide access to global patient data that can be used to provide improved treatments for patients.  Currently, there are many questions that require the ability to link and analyze patient data. The problem is that the majority of patient data currently used comes from the same few institutions in Northern Europe that lack geographic or population diversity. The result is that the patient data has limited use for questions related to populations that do not derive from Northern Europe. The patient dataset under development will allow academic and commercial institutions to ask questions that link patient data from around the world to get answers that are applicable to all patient populations. The data will be available to physicians treating patients to ensure more precise treatments and prescription of drugs.  The data also will allow research institutions and commercial enterprises to develop drugs and speed their delivery to market by shortening clinical trials.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project is based on the development of a single cloud-based, searchable data catalog containing patient genomic, phenotypic and clinical data from geographically diverse populations and a research environment within which the data can be analyzed. The ability to use patient data from geographically diverse patient populations will allow for the ability to determine patient-specific treatments with a high degree of precision, not just for those with a Northern European background, but patients everywhere. Academic and commercial institutions will be able to improve their research and expedite results by analyzing patients' data from geographically diverse regions to answer questions in a few hours or days that currently takes years. It will allow commercial institutions to expedite therapeutic research and streamline clinical trials. The result will be more drugs making it through clinical trials for more diseases in a shorter time for less money. The patient data set also will allow commercial institutions to find patients with rare diseases using genetic analysis from different geographies, instead of the current practice of extrapolating based on a doctor-determined prognosis. The goal is to improve medical research and patient treatment where patient data is used.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/13/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/13/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2029812</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Julian</FirstName>
<LastName>Whitelegge</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Julian Whitelegge</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jpw@chem.ucla.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3108259235</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000487437</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/13/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Los Angeles</Name>
<CityName>LOS ANGELES</CityName>
<ZipCode>900244201</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3107940102</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>10889 WILSHIRE BLVD STE 700</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>37</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA37</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>RN64EPNH8JC6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, LOS ANGELES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>NUDGYLBB4S99</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[UCLA Facilities Management]]></Name>
<CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>900957076</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[760 Westwood Plaza]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>33</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA33</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Project outcomes: This grant was an NSF I-Corps grant designed to focus a business hypothesis on what customers actually want vs what the business owner assumes they want.&nbsp; The outcomes of this grant reflect the 100+ customer interviews and the pivoting of the business to match this.&nbsp; Through this grant the business (MedaLynx) is a database of patient data recruiting collaborations from healthcare centers around the world.&nbsp; A major outcome of the grant was that the team learned how decisions are made and regulatory restrictions regarding the use of this data.&nbsp; What we also learned was that data entry is fragmented (different medical record platforms that do not talk to each other) and inconsistent (for example using multiple codes for the same disease, even within the same institution).&nbsp; We also learned that doctors would be excited to have the ability to use the Medalynx patient data to come to a more precise diagnosis for their patients based upon historic and searchable patient data. What we also learned was that doctors follow a &ldquo;Standard of Care&rdquo; to determine the treatment for a patient suffering from a disease.&nbsp; This one size fits all Standard of Care works well for some patients but does not necessarily provide the right treatment for others. We further learned that to change a Standard of Care, we would have to find a prominent doctor who is known for treating a particular disease and have them run a &ldquo;trial&rdquo; comparing the Standard of Care to the use of the recommendations provided by Medalynx from analysis of patient data of similar patients.&nbsp; This doctor would then have to publish the results and present at meetings.&nbsp; We learned that Medalynx would have to use the results and publications to show other doctors to change their Standard of Care to the use and analysis of the Medalynx patient data. We learned that while better outcomes could be used to change the Standard of Care, lowering cost of care would also potentially be found to be highly persuasive because many times the decision makers for adoption are most focused on this.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>We also learned that the data suppliers wanted to have some control over the use and commercialization of their data. Through this learning, we continued to obtain feedback from the data providers to hone and refine how Medalynx could successfully work with data providers. This has included determining the means and mechanisms through which data providers could influence how Medalynx uses and commercializes their data. We also learned that&nbsp;Prototyping:&nbsp; Medalynx has used its beta platform developed with money from the NSF grant using NHS publicly available patient data sets that were linked and then harmonized to conduct searches and analysis. Using the prepared database, the beta was able to conduct searches and analyze the search results.&nbsp;Impact to the Public: The future of medicine will be through the use of a patients clinical, genomic and phenotypic data, which will be compared to patients with similar data suffering from the same disease. This comparison, which will use patient data from multiple patients from multiple data providers will provide a personalized medical diagnosis and treatment that will likely result in a better health experience.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>Further, an outcome has also been the development of a minimal viable product (MVP) and we are working hard to get it ready for commercial launch and signing up patient data providers from around the world. Our first effort has been to obtain patient data from underrepresented populations. To this end, we have focused on collecting patient data from the middle east and, in particular, from Qatar and the Qatar Biobank. This has occurred through our work to create collaborative agreements with biobanks from the Middle East, Asia and soon Africa to supply data. We have continued to hone our business model to provide the data suppliers some influence on how their data is used, including the creation of a Data Consortium that allows the data provides a say in how their data is used and commercialized by Medalynx. This work continues to date. Medalynx has used its beta platform developed with money from the NSF grant using the UK&rsquo;s NHS publicly available patient data sets that were linked and then harmonized to conduct searches and analysis. Using the prepared database, the beta was able to conduct searches and analyze the search results.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Impact to the Public: The future of medicine will be through the use of a patients clinical, genomic and phenotypic data, which will be compared to patients with similar data suffering from the same disease. This comparison, which will use patient data from multiple patients from multiple data providers will provide a personalized medical diagnosis and treatment that will likely result in a better health experience.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/05/2021<br>      Modified by: Julian&nbsp;Whitelegge</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Project outcomes: This grant was an NSF I-Corps grant designed to focus a business hypothesis on what customers actually want vs what the business owner assumes they want.  The outcomes of this grant reflect the 100+ customer interviews and the pivoting of the business to match this.  Through this grant the business (MedaLynx) is a database of patient data recruiting collaborations from healthcare centers around the world.  A major outcome of the grant was that the team learned how decisions are made and regulatory restrictions regarding the use of this data.  What we also learned was that data entry is fragmented (different medical record platforms that do not talk to each other) and inconsistent (for example using multiple codes for the same disease, even within the same institution).  We also learned that doctors would be excited to have the ability to use the Medalynx patient data to come to a more precise diagnosis for their patients based upon historic and searchable patient data. What we also learned was that doctors follow a "Standard of Care" to determine the treatment for a patient suffering from a disease.  This one size fits all Standard of Care works well for some patients but does not necessarily provide the right treatment for others. We further learned that to change a Standard of Care, we would have to find a prominent doctor who is known for treating a particular disease and have them run a "trial" comparing the Standard of Care to the use of the recommendations provided by Medalynx from analysis of patient data of similar patients.  This doctor would then have to publish the results and present at meetings.  We learned that Medalynx would have to use the results and publications to show other doctors to change their Standard of Care to the use and analysis of the Medalynx patient data. We learned that while better outcomes could be used to change the Standard of Care, lowering cost of care would also potentially be found to be highly persuasive because many times the decision makers for adoption are most focused on this.     We also learned that the data suppliers wanted to have some control over the use and commercialization of their data. Through this learning, we continued to obtain feedback from the data providers to hone and refine how Medalynx could successfully work with data providers. This has included determining the means and mechanisms through which data providers could influence how Medalynx uses and commercializes their data. We also learned that Prototyping:  Medalynx has used its beta platform developed with money from the NSF grant using NHS publicly available patient data sets that were linked and then harmonized to conduct searches and analysis. Using the prepared database, the beta was able to conduct searches and analyze the search results. Impact to the Public: The future of medicine will be through the use of a patients clinical, genomic and phenotypic data, which will be compared to patients with similar data suffering from the same disease. This comparison, which will use patient data from multiple patients from multiple data providers will provide a personalized medical diagnosis and treatment that will likely result in a better health experience.    Further, an outcome has also been the development of a minimal viable product (MVP) and we are working hard to get it ready for commercial launch and signing up patient data providers from around the world. Our first effort has been to obtain patient data from underrepresented populations. To this end, we have focused on collecting patient data from the middle east and, in particular, from Qatar and the Qatar Biobank. This has occurred through our work to create collaborative agreements with biobanks from the Middle East, Asia and soon Africa to supply data. We have continued to hone our business model to provide the data suppliers some influence on how their data is used, including the creation of a Data Consortium that allows the data provides a say in how their data is used and commercialized by Medalynx. This work continues to date. Medalynx has used its beta platform developed with money from the NSF grant using the UK’s NHS publicly available patient data sets that were linked and then harmonized to conduct searches and analysis. Using the prepared database, the beta was able to conduct searches and analyze the search results.     Impact to the Public: The future of medicine will be through the use of a patients clinical, genomic and phenotypic data, which will be compared to patients with similar data suffering from the same disease. This comparison, which will use patient data from multiple patients from multiple data providers will provide a personalized medical diagnosis and treatment that will likely result in a better health experience.           Last Modified: 10/05/2021       Submitted by: Julian Whitelegge]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
