<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  A knowledge base and drug repurposing platform for COVID-19]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>255993.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>255993</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Erik Pierstorff</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>epiersto@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922165</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is to create a software platform to facilitate the identification of existing drugs that can be re-purposed for other diseases, such as COVID-19.  First, identifying FDA-approved drugs that could help COVID-19 patients is expected to save lives. Furthermore, this can prevent the economic consequences of extended or repeated mass quarantine episodes. Finally, the availability of a drug discovery platform for flu-like viruses that includes data from SARS-CoV-2 and other related viruses will add to the national cyberinfrastructure and will allow a better response at the next occurrence of a novel virus.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;The proposed project will develop a prototype platform to include: i) state-of-the-art data analysis methods, ii) a comprehensive knowledge base, and iii) an approach complementary to most other avenues currently pursued in the fight against COVID-19. The approach will focus on leveraging transcriptomics and other omics data focusing on the host’s immune response.  This system will enable efficient research into issues such as the acute reaction of the immune systems, enabling approaches to mitigate and/or avoid a cytokine storm.  This provides important information complementary to development of antiviral medications or vaccines, important for a future pandemic regardless of the virus strain.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/04/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/14/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041, 47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2029572</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Cristiana</FirstName>
<LastName>IOSEF</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Cristiana IOSEF</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[cristiana@advaitabio.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000881737</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/14/2022</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Aaron</FirstName>
<LastName>denDekker</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Aaron D denDekker</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[aaron@advaitabio.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000860325</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/20/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate>06/14/2022</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Cordelia</FirstName>
<LastName>Ziraldo</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Cordelia R Ziraldo</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[cordelia@advaitabio.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000739692</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/04/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate>07/20/2021</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Advaita Corporation</Name>
<CityName>ANN ARBOR</CityName>
<ZipCode>481052552</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7349220110</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3250 PLYMOUTH RD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[STE 303]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>Q81XNNYPK5H3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ADVAITA CORP</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>CRN1ELFDAP26</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Advaita Corporation]]></Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>481052552</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3250 Plymouth Rd. #303]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1718</Code>
<Text>BIOINFORMATICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8038</Code>
<Text>Biotechnology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~255993</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>We created a prototype knowledge base (KB) associated with an analysis platform meant to investigate COVID-19 data. The uncertainty in disease severity and progression makes uniform COVID-19 management difficult, indicating that patients could benefit from a precision medicine approach and deep analysis of the data using a platform like Advaita&rsquo;s. The results of our project comprise thus, a KB prototype that integrates data on SARS-CoV2 (causing COVID19) which can be computed comparatively to SARS-CoV1 (causing SARS), as well as other related viruses such as influenza A (IAV) (causing H1N1 influenza) and respiratory syncytial virus (RSV).&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span>Our KB prototype is accompanied by data analytics capabilities that allow researchers to identify FDA-approved drugs, drugs under trial, or other chemicals that could be used for the treatment of COVID19 patients. The prototype allows:&nbsp;<strong><em><span style="text-decoration: underline;">i)</span></em></strong>&nbsp;understanding of the mechanisms of COVID-9,&nbsp;<strong><em><span style="text-decoration: underline;">ii)</span></em></strong>&nbsp;identifies biological processes and pathways impacted by the disease, and&nbsp;<strong><em><span style="text-decoration: underline;">iii)</span></em></strong>&nbsp;identification of FDA-approved drugs that could be used and repurposed.</span></p> <p><span>We tested and validated our system using two studies, one for severe COVID-19 and the second for long COVID. The ultimate validation that demonstrated the accuracy of the results obtained with our software prototype is a peer-review publication which contains the clinical endorsement and the subsequent implementation of the drugs identified with our software. The drug repurposing work identified methylprednisolone as a medicine that would be effective in severe cases of COVID-19. These results were confirmed by a clinical trial undertaken at Henry Ford Health Systems. Currently, methylprednisolone has become the standard of care in severe cases of COVID-19 associated with a cytokine storm. A more detailed analysis of the vascular effects of severe COVID-19 in renal failure is following up, while the work describing the effects of long COVID19 is currently under review.&nbsp;</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/12/2022<br>      Modified by: Cristiana&nbsp;Iosef</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ We created a prototype knowledge base (KB) associated with an analysis platform meant to investigate COVID-19 data. The uncertainty in disease severity and progression makes uniform COVID-19 management difficult, indicating that patients could benefit from a precision medicine approach and deep analysis of the data using a platform like Advaita’s. The results of our project comprise thus, a KB prototype that integrates data on SARS-CoV2 (causing COVID19) which can be computed comparatively to SARS-CoV1 (causing SARS), as well as other related viruses such as influenza A (IAV) (causing H1N1 influenza) and respiratory syncytial virus (RSV).   Our KB prototype is accompanied by data analytics capabilities that allow researchers to identify FDA-approved drugs, drugs under trial, or other chemicals that could be used for the treatment of COVID19 patients. The prototype allows: i) understanding of the mechanisms of COVID-9, ii) identifies biological processes and pathways impacted by the disease, and iii) identification of FDA-approved drugs that could be used and repurposed.  We tested and validated our system using two studies, one for severe COVID-19 and the second for long COVID. The ultimate validation that demonstrated the accuracy of the results obtained with our software prototype is a peer-review publication which contains the clinical endorsement and the subsequent implementation of the drugs identified with our software. The drug repurposing work identified methylprednisolone as a medicine that would be effective in severe cases of COVID-19. These results were confirmed by a clinical trial undertaken at Henry Ford Health Systems. Currently, methylprednisolone has become the standard of care in severe cases of COVID-19 associated with a cytokine storm. A more detailed analysis of the vascular effects of severe COVID-19 in renal failure is following up, while the work describing the effects of long COVID19 is currently under review.           Last Modified: 12/12/2022       Submitted by: Cristiana Iosef]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
