<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Developing a novel biosensor for rapid, direct and selective detection of  COVID-19 using DNA aptamer-nanopore]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>154457.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>154457</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Aleksandr Simonian</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>asimonia@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922191</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[In response to the COVID-19 outbreak, Prof. Lu of the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign and Prof. Rong of the University of Illinois at Chicago collaborate to develop a novel, widely deployable method for detecting the infectious coronavirus (SARS-CoV-2).  The sensing method is designed to enable differentiation of infectious virus from those rendered non-infectious, as well as other viruses and interfering species.  Rapid and accurate detection of the infectious viruses provides to patients the opportunity to receive proper treatments early on, prevents patients from unknowingly spreading the infectious virus to others, eliminates unnecessary quarantine of non-contagious patients, and enables assessment of whether surfaces at critical locations has been properly disinfected.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research aims to develop a modular and scalable aptamer-nanopore sensor for direct detection of the intact coronavirus.  Specifically, this research will identify and synthesize DNA aptamers that bind the infectious SARS-CoV-2, but not the non-infectious forms, with high specificity and affinity.  Detection of infectious SARS-CoV-2 in the single nanochannel membrane will be performed using steady-state measurements, which is less resource intensive than the commonly used resistive pulse sensing technique.  The sensing method does not require sample pre-treatment or RNA amplification and, thus, simplifies the testing procedure and minimizes the chance of cross contamination.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/16/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/16/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2029215</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lijun</FirstName>
<LastName>Rong</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lijun Rong</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[lijun@uic.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000824714</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/16/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yi</FirstName>
<LastName>Lu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Yi Lu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[yi.lu@utexas.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000445840</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/16/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</Name>
<CityName>URBANA</CityName>
<ZipCode>618013620</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>506 S WRIGHT ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>Y8CWNJRCNN91</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ILLINOIS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign Henry Building]]></Name>
<CityName>Urbana</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>618013620</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[506 S. Wright Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>158Y</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>1N20</Code>
<Name>R&amp;RA CARES Act DEFC N</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>010N2021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[R&RA CARES Act DEFC N]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~154457</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This grant resulted in three peer reviewed publications in high impact journals. Below you will find a synopsis of the Project Outcomes of this research grant.</p> <p>Project outcomes:</p> <p><span>1. <span>Viral infections are a major global health issue, but no current method allows rapid, direct, and ultrasensitive quantification of intact viruses with the ability to inform infectivity, causing misdiagnoses and spread of the viruses.&nbsp;</span>Several applications in health diagnostics, food, safety, and environmental monitoring require rapid, simple, selective, and quantitatively accurate viral load monitoring. Here, we introduce the first label-free biosensing method that rapidly detects and quantifies intact virus in human saliva with single-virion resolution,&nbsp;<span>making the sensor generally applicable for detecting these and other emerging viruses of environmental and public health concern.</span></span></p> <p>2. &nbsp;We reviewed how several distinct classes of nanomaterials and nanochemistry enable simple assay workflows, high sensitivity, inexpensive instrumentation, point-of-care sample-to-answer virus diagnosis, and rapidly scaled manufacturing, especially helpful for COVID-19 testing.</p> <p>3. &nbsp;Viral infections are a major global health issue, but no current method allows rapid, direct, and ultrasensitive quantification of intact viruses with the ability to inform infectivity, causing misdiagnoses and spread of the viruses. We report a method for direct detection and differentiation of infectious from noninfectious human&nbsp;<span>adenovirus and SARS-CoV-2, as well as from other virus types, without any sample pretreatment.&nbsp;</span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/29/2022<br>      Modified by: Yi&nbsp;Lu</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This grant resulted in three peer reviewed publications in high impact journals. Below you will find a synopsis of the Project Outcomes of this research grant.  Project outcomes:  1. Viral infections are a major global health issue, but no current method allows rapid, direct, and ultrasensitive quantification of intact viruses with the ability to inform infectivity, causing misdiagnoses and spread of the viruses. Several applications in health diagnostics, food, safety, and environmental monitoring require rapid, simple, selective, and quantitatively accurate viral load monitoring. Here, we introduce the first label-free biosensing method that rapidly detects and quantifies intact virus in human saliva with single-virion resolution, making the sensor generally applicable for detecting these and other emerging viruses of environmental and public health concern.  2.  We reviewed how several distinct classes of nanomaterials and nanochemistry enable simple assay workflows, high sensitivity, inexpensive instrumentation, point-of-care sample-to-answer virus diagnosis, and rapidly scaled manufacturing, especially helpful for COVID-19 testing.  3.  Viral infections are a major global health issue, but no current method allows rapid, direct, and ultrasensitive quantification of intact viruses with the ability to inform infectivity, causing misdiagnoses and spread of the viruses. We report a method for direct detection and differentiation of infectious from noninfectious human adenovirus and SARS-CoV-2, as well as from other virus types, without any sample pretreatment.        Last Modified: 07/29/2022       Submitted by: Yi Lu]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
