<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Investigating molecular-level responses of coronavirus under UVC irradiation]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>199997.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>199997</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Mamadou Diallo</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mdiallo@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924257</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Coronaviruses such as SARS-CoV1, MERS-CoV, and SARS-CoV2 (the virus responsible for COVID-19), have caused several global pandemics of respiratory diseases over the last two decades. A primary exposure pathway for coronavirus infections is through skin contact with contaminated surfaces followed by touching of facial areas. Effective and safe methods for surface disinfection against coronaviruses is urgently needed.  This is particularly true in healthcare settings where reusable personal protective equipment (PPE), medical instruments, and surfaces in operating rooms need repeated disinfection. Beyond clinical settings, high-touch areas such as public transportation and commercial shops have an urgent need to stay virus-free as intervention efforts to control the pandemic are eased. Current surface disinfection methods using chemicals like bleach and alcohol can result in material corrosion and chemical residuals. A potential solution for surface disinfection is the use of ultraviolet light (UV) devices. UV light has been proven to be effective against other viruses but must be optimized to treat SARS-CoV2 and other coronaviruses because of their unique molecular structure. The study aims to understand how UV light from different sources (including newly available UVLEDs) damage the nucleic acid and proteins in SARS-CoV2 coatings. The findings will provide guidance for UV device design and operation for disinfecting contaminated surfaces, which will help in the fight against the COVID-19 global pandemic and future coronavirus-caused respiratory outbreaks. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Ultraviolet light (UV) devices emitting UVC irradiation (200-280 nm) have proven to be effective for virus disinfection by damaging nucleic acids and proteins. UV exposure to non-enveloped viruses revealed that DNA/RNA damage is the primary cause for virus inactivation, with a peak efficacy around 265nm, whereas protein damage is important at wavelengths at the high (~280 nm) and low (&lt;240 nm) ends of the UV spectrum. Coronavirus, which is an enveloped, non-segmented positive-sense RNA virus, may respond to UVC irradiation differently due to its unique molecular structure. The goal of this project is to investigate inactivation kinetics and RNA and structural protein damage of coronavirus under UVC irradiation across wavelengths from 220 to 280 nm. Murine coronavirus and murine hepatitis virus (MHV) will be used as a representative coronavirus and a surrogate of human coronavirus in this project. The UVC inactivation efficiencies and kinetics of coronavirus will be determined by exposing MHV contaminated surface samples and water samples under UVC irradiation in a bench-scale collimated beam apparatus with three different UV sources: a UVLED  system (emitting at 255, 265, and/or 285 nm), a KrCl excimer lamp (222 nm), and a low pressure UV lamp (254 nm). The RNA damage of MHV under UVC irradiation across wavelengths will be investigated using long range reverse transcript quantitative polymerase chain reaction and the protein damage will be assessed using peptide liquid chromatography tandem mass spectrometry. The fundamental scientific relationship between virus molecular structure and UV inactivation efficiency and mechanisms will be evaluated by comparing the UV action of coronavirus to those of nonenveloped viruses used in previous studies. These findings will lead to generation of definitive UV-disinfection kinetics of coronavirus on surfaces to inform proper operation and use of UV devices and support the engineering of new disinfection devices that will serve as urgent and effective interventions during relevant public health emergencies.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/12/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/12/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2029695</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Karl</FirstName>
<LastName>Linden</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>G</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Karl G Linden</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[karl.linden@colorado.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000157705</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/12/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Colorado at Boulder</Name>
<CityName>BOULDER</CityName>
<ZipCode>803090001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3034926221</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3100 MARINE ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[STE 481 572 UCB]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>SPVKK1RC2MZ3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>THE REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF COLORADO</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Colorado Boulder]]></Name>
<CityName>Boulder</CityName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>803031058</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3100 Marine St 572 UCB]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1440</Code>
<Text>EnvE-Environmental Engineering</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~199997</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Coronaviruses such as SARS-CoV1, MERS-CoV, and SARS-CoV2 (the virus responsible for COVID-19), have caused several global pandemics of respiratory diseases over the last two decades. Germicidal UV light is an effective tool to help stem the spread of coronaviruses and protect public health in commercial, public, transportation, and health care settings. For effective use of UV, there is a need to understand UV action on coronaviruses across UV wavelengths, to support efforts to control the ongoing COVID-19 global pandemic and future coronavirus-caused respiratory virus pandemics.</p> <p>In this research, we determined the UV inactivation efficiencies of coronaviruses in aqueous solutions (water) and on surfaces using five commonly available UVC devices that uniquely emit light at different wavelengths spanning 222nm emitting krypton chloride (KrCl*) excimers to 282 nm emitting UV LEDs. SARS-CoV-2 and other two coronaviruses, including murine hepatitis virus (MHV, mouse coronavirus), and Human Coronavirus 229E (HCoV 229E, capable of causing common cold-like symptoms), were tested. We found that coronaviruses can be inactivated using a broad range of UV wavelengths from 222nm and 282 nm. MHV and HCoV 229E exhibited similar UV sensitivities across wavelengths compared to SARS-CoV-2, suggesting that MHV can serve as a reliable surrogate of SARS-CoV-2 with a lower biological safety level requirement during UV disinfection tests. Among all tested UV wavelengths, 222 nm provided the best disinfection performance, due to its capability of causing high levels of nucleic acid and protein damage as indicated by molecular assays. Interestingly, 222-nm irradiation has been found to be safe for human exposure up to thresholds that are beyond those effective for inactivating viruses. Therefore, applying UV light from KrCl* excimers in public spaces can effectively help reduce viral aerosol or surface-based transmissions. This research provided important information for UV industry and public health officials in decision making for UV-based coronavirus interventions. It also provided fundamental understanding of the action of different UV wavelengths on nucleic acids and proteins that make up coronaviruses, and generation of definitive UV-disinfection kinetics of the virus to inform proper operation and use of current and future UV devices.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/08/2022<br>      Modified by: Karl&nbsp;G&nbsp;Linden</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2029695/2029695_10670197_1654712924700_TOC-jpg--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2029695/2029695_10670197_1654712924700_TOC-jpg--rgov-800width.jpg" title="UV action for inactivating viruses"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2029695/2029695_10670197_1654712924700_TOC-jpg--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="UV action for inactivating viruses"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Different UV sources and wavelengths are all effective for inactivating coronaviruses such as Murine and human respiratory viruses</div> <div class="imageCredit">Ben Ma</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Karl&nbsp;G&nbsp;Linden</div> <div class="imageTitle">UV action for inactivating viruses</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Coronaviruses such as SARS-CoV1, MERS-CoV, and SARS-CoV2 (the virus responsible for COVID-19), have caused several global pandemics of respiratory diseases over the last two decades. Germicidal UV light is an effective tool to help stem the spread of coronaviruses and protect public health in commercial, public, transportation, and health care settings. For effective use of UV, there is a need to understand UV action on coronaviruses across UV wavelengths, to support efforts to control the ongoing COVID-19 global pandemic and future coronavirus-caused respiratory virus pandemics.  In this research, we determined the UV inactivation efficiencies of coronaviruses in aqueous solutions (water) and on surfaces using five commonly available UVC devices that uniquely emit light at different wavelengths spanning 222nm emitting krypton chloride (KrCl*) excimers to 282 nm emitting UV LEDs. SARS-CoV-2 and other two coronaviruses, including murine hepatitis virus (MHV, mouse coronavirus), and Human Coronavirus 229E (HCoV 229E, capable of causing common cold-like symptoms), were tested. We found that coronaviruses can be inactivated using a broad range of UV wavelengths from 222nm and 282 nm. MHV and HCoV 229E exhibited similar UV sensitivities across wavelengths compared to SARS-CoV-2, suggesting that MHV can serve as a reliable surrogate of SARS-CoV-2 with a lower biological safety level requirement during UV disinfection tests. Among all tested UV wavelengths, 222 nm provided the best disinfection performance, due to its capability of causing high levels of nucleic acid and protein damage as indicated by molecular assays. Interestingly, 222-nm irradiation has been found to be safe for human exposure up to thresholds that are beyond those effective for inactivating viruses. Therefore, applying UV light from KrCl* excimers in public spaces can effectively help reduce viral aerosol or surface-based transmissions. This research provided important information for UV industry and public health officials in decision making for UV-based coronavirus interventions. It also provided fundamental understanding of the action of different UV wavelengths on nucleic acids and proteins that make up coronaviruses, and generation of definitive UV-disinfection kinetics of the virus to inform proper operation and use of current and future UV devices.       Last Modified: 06/08/2022       Submitted by: Karl G Linden]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
