<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[The effects of delayed auditory feedback on speech sequencing: acoustics, physiology, and computational modeling]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>393444.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>393444</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Betty Tuller</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>btuller@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927238</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Healthy individuals continuously monitor their sound output while speaking, allowing them to perceive and correct errors quickly. When the content or timing of this auditory feedback signal is experimentally altered, most speakers rapidly modify their speech. This project will primarily address how the timing of auditory feedback impacts the speech production system and will assess individual differences in the use of auditory feedback. Results will guide development of a computational model of speech planning and production that has the potential to accelerate the design of new therapeutic approaches to developmental and acquired disorders of speech. Additional benefits to society will accrue from a series of teaching modules that will be developed that explore the role of auditory feedback in normal and disordered speech. The project team will also develop educational materials that bridge neuroscience and communication sciences and that provide formative experiences for undergraduate and K-12 students, including those from disadvantaged backgrounds and with disabilities, to attract them to future study in this area. All project materials will be made available as a public database.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The investigators will use a combination of experimental and computational studies. The first research goal is to determine the role of delayed auditory feedback (DAF) on speech sequencing using multimodal experimental techniques. Acoustic data will be collected and analyzed to determine the impact of DAF on the production of non-word syllable sequences and sentences. These data will be used to assess the types of errors elicited by DAF and the relationship between these effects and responses to rapid shifts in the frequency content, rather than timing, of the feedback signal. The collected data and perceptual evaluations, obtained via a crowdsourcing platform, will enable the study of individual speaker variability. Data will also be made available as a large public database of speech under altered feedback conditions. The second research goal is to develop a computational model, informed also by kinematic measures of speech from a subset of participants, that can capture the interaction of auditory feedback with speech sequence production. The model will simulate a series of hypotheses about the interactions among speech perception and planning and production components and assess their ability to account for the patterns of errors observed in the experimental data. The model will also assess the sources of individual variation in susceptibility to the effects of DAF, as observed experimentally.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/14/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/14/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2029245</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jason</FirstName>
<LastName>Bohland</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jason W Bohland</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[j.bohland@pitt.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000559528</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/14/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Pittsburgh</Name>
<CityName>PITTSBURGH</CityName>
<ZipCode>152600001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4126247400</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4200 FIFTH AVENUE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>MKAGLD59JRL1</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF PITTSBURGH - OF THE COMMONWEALTH SYSTEM OF HIGHER EDUCATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Pittsburgh]]></Name>
<CityName>Pittsburgh</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>152132303</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[123 University Place]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7252</Code>
<Text>Perception, Action &amp; Cognition</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7252</Code>
<Text>Perception, Action and Cognition</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01001718DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~393444</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The overall objective of this project was to understand how delayed auditory feedback (DAF), in which speakers hear themselves with a short delay, disrupts speech motor sequencing. Despite a long history of studies using DAF, the mechanisms that lead to decreased speech rate and increased speech errors remain poorly understood and cannot be explained by contemporary speech motor control. Our specific research goals were to systematically determine the role of delayed auditory feedback using modern, multimodal experimental techniques and to develop computational models, based on our existing GODIVA model, that simulate the interaction of auditory feedback with speech sequence production.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Our research activities included the collection and management of a large set of acoustic recordings, detailed analyses of these data, and the creation of model simulations that explain aspects of our results. A key outcome is the generation of a large corpus of annotated acoustic recordings from 70 adult, neurotypical participants, who completed a series of speech tasks under DAF and other auditory feedback alterations. This corpus will be openly shared with the research community.</p> <p>Using these collected data, we demonstrated that DAF drives specific patterns of errors, notably including vowel and syllable repetition errors, as well as reductions in speech rate. We quantified the timing of errors, leading to computational hypotheses about the underlying mechanisms. Speech produced with delayed amplitude modulated noise feedback (lacking speech-specific content) contained fewer errors and was produced faster than canonical DAF, suggesting that the delayed speech sound inputs are critical for driving errors. We also demonstrated that participants can partially learn to overcome the effects of DAF when feedback latencies are gradually increased across a session, suggesting that speakers can modulate the expected timing of their own auditory feedback.</p> <p>Our computational modeling efforts focused on three key challenges to existing theories: (1) DAF drives a specific pattern of sound substitution errors; (2) these errors likely include both sound selection errors and co-production errors (e.g., blends of produced sounds); and (3) speakers&rsquo; vowel productions tended to steer toward the delayed feedback signals. Simulations demonstrated that an extended version of the GODIVA model, in which an auditory component is coupled with a speech planning component, offers a unified explanation for these results. In this account, delayed, self-generated speech inputs act similarly to externally generated speech, driving productions toward the feedback from previously produced sounds.</p> <p>The major impact of this work will be in speech motor control research. The results obtained led to proposed computational mechanisms that are likely to help advance theory in the field and explain long-standing effects of DAF. Better understanding of the coupling of motor and auditory systems during speech is also likely to have impact in characterizing and treating speech disorders, including stuttering. The systematic database created in this project is also expected to be useful in addressing a wide range of future questions in speech motor control.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/24/2022<br>      Modified by: Jason&nbsp;W&nbsp;Bohland</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The overall objective of this project was to understand how delayed auditory feedback (DAF), in which speakers hear themselves with a short delay, disrupts speech motor sequencing. Despite a long history of studies using DAF, the mechanisms that lead to decreased speech rate and increased speech errors remain poorly understood and cannot be explained by contemporary speech motor control. Our specific research goals were to systematically determine the role of delayed auditory feedback using modern, multimodal experimental techniques and to develop computational models, based on our existing GODIVA model, that simulate the interaction of auditory feedback with speech sequence production.     Our research activities included the collection and management of a large set of acoustic recordings, detailed analyses of these data, and the creation of model simulations that explain aspects of our results. A key outcome is the generation of a large corpus of annotated acoustic recordings from 70 adult, neurotypical participants, who completed a series of speech tasks under DAF and other auditory feedback alterations. This corpus will be openly shared with the research community.  Using these collected data, we demonstrated that DAF drives specific patterns of errors, notably including vowel and syllable repetition errors, as well as reductions in speech rate. We quantified the timing of errors, leading to computational hypotheses about the underlying mechanisms. Speech produced with delayed amplitude modulated noise feedback (lacking speech-specific content) contained fewer errors and was produced faster than canonical DAF, suggesting that the delayed speech sound inputs are critical for driving errors. We also demonstrated that participants can partially learn to overcome the effects of DAF when feedback latencies are gradually increased across a session, suggesting that speakers can modulate the expected timing of their own auditory feedback.  Our computational modeling efforts focused on three key challenges to existing theories: (1) DAF drives a specific pattern of sound substitution errors; (2) these errors likely include both sound selection errors and co-production errors (e.g., blends of produced sounds); and (3) speakers’ vowel productions tended to steer toward the delayed feedback signals. Simulations demonstrated that an extended version of the GODIVA model, in which an auditory component is coupled with a speech planning component, offers a unified explanation for these results. In this account, delayed, self-generated speech inputs act similarly to externally generated speech, driving productions toward the feedback from previously produced sounds.  The major impact of this work will be in speech motor control research. The results obtained led to proposed computational mechanisms that are likely to help advance theory in the field and explain long-standing effects of DAF. Better understanding of the coupling of motor and auditory systems during speech is also likely to have impact in characterizing and treating speech disorders, including stuttering. The systematic database created in this project is also expected to be useful in addressing a wide range of future questions in speech motor control.             Last Modified: 08/24/2022       Submitted by: Jason W Bohland]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
