<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[QuBBD: Fast, Efficient Mathematical Approach to the Analysis of the Human Microbiome through Biodiversity Optimization]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>167095.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>167095</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Pena Edsel</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Communities of microorganisms participate in and drive a variety of biochemical processes that have significant impact on the environment around them. This impact ranges widely from causing diseases to offering new kinds of antibiotics, to helping crops grow by fixing nitrogen in the soil. Metagenomics is the study of such microbial communities through their extracted DNA. One of the first questions to ask when studying such a community is: "which organisms are present and at what abundance?"  Most current approaches to this so-called community profiling problem take a parsimonious approach: infer the presence of the fewest organisms possible that still agrees with the observed data. However, treating each organism as completely different from any other can lead to mis-estimates of the different kinds and amounts of organisms present, referred to as biological diversity. This is further complicated by the fact that historically there has been much disagreement about the proper way to analytically measure biological diversity. In this project, the investigators leverage a recently defined, unifying notion of biological diversity to address the problem of correctly profiling a microbial community which has in it organisms of varying similarity. To accomplish this, a new mathematical framework is put forward that utilizes the big data approach of compressive sensing. After advancing the mathematical theory, the investigators will create a software implementation that will allow biomedical researchers to study metagenomic communities while properly accounting for varying organism similarity.  While advancing discovery, this project promotes graduate and undergraduate student teaching and learning. In particular, students are guided to excel at interdisciplinary work in the fields of mathematics and biology. Furthermore, beyond the traditional dissemination routes of conferences and papers, a wide audience is also engaged through a collaboration with SciShow, a popular YouTube channel that will work with the PIs in creating episodes featuring metagenomics suitable for the general public.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Microorganismal community profiling, determining the identity and relative abundance of all microbial organisms present in a given environmental sample through their sequenced DNA, is an important first step in the study of such communities. Many tools and approaches have been proposed to profile microbial communities, and while these tools take advantage of particular properties of microbial genetics to perform the classification task, there is a general lack of rigorous mathematical approaches that allow for definitive statements to be made about such classifications. Furthermore, the estimated biological diversity of a community can vary widely depending on the computational approach used. This is problematic given that biological diversity is a key metric when studying the impact of a bacterial community on its surrounding environment and aberrations of this quantity have been implicated in a number of diseases. This difficulty is further compounded by the fact that there is much disagreement in the scientific community on how to measure biodiversity. Recently, however, it was shown that a single formula subsumes and unifies many of the most popular biodiversity measures. In this project, the PIs utilize this definition of biodiversity to develop a rigorous mathematical approach to simultaneously profile a microbial community and characterize its biological diversity. Mathematically, this reduces to developing (and proving results about) an optimization procedure where the objective function includes biological diversity. Intriguingly, such an approach parallels that of compressive sensing and other such "big data" sparsity promoting optimization routines. The main approach will be to reduce this measure of biodiversity to a quasinorm and appropriately modify existing proofs about the convergence and guaranteed reconstruction of such optimization routines. This will result in an optimization framework that allows for simultaneously profiling a microbial community and characterizing its biodiversity directly while considering organism similarity. This will be implemented in user-friendly software and used to analyze gut samples from healthy and sick pre-term infants.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/14/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/15/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2029170</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Koslicki</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David M Koslicki</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[dmk333@psu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000603146</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/14/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Pennsylvania State Univ University Park</Name>
<CityName>UNIVERSITY PARK</CityName>
<ZipCode>168021503</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8148651372</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>201 OLD MAIN</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>15</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA15</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NPM2J7MSCF61</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>THE PENNSYLVANIA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Pennsylvania State Univ University Park]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>168027000</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT/>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA"</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8069</Code>
<Text>CDS&amp;E-MSS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8083</Code>
<Text>Big Data Science &amp;Engineering</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01001819DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~167095</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Faster, more accurate, and better-understood mathematical methods in metagenomics</p> <p>Communities of microorganisms participate in and drive a variety of biochemical processes that have significant impact on the environment around them. This impact ranges widely from causing diseases to offering new kinds of antibiotics, to helping crops grow by fixing nitrogen in the soil. Metagenomics is the study of such microbial communities through their extracted DNA. One of the first questions to ask when studying such a community is: "which organisms are present and at what abundance?" Most current approaches to this so-called community profiling problem take a parsimonious approach: infer the presence of the fewest organisms possible that still agrees with the observed data. However, treating each organism as completely different from any other can lead to mis-estimates of the different kinds and amounts of organisms present.</p> <p>This project advanced both the theory and practice of studying microbial communities. In particular, we used a recently developed notion of the similarity of microorganisms to better answer the question &ldquo;what is in my metagenomic sample?&rdquo; by properly considering organism similarity. Since the goal of this project involved the advancement of data analysis methods, we also undertook studies to benchmark current data analysis methods and quantify the quality of existing reference data. This allowed us to identify shortcomings in current methods and reference databases and make recommendations for how to overcome those shortcomings.</p> <p>In the course of this research, we also discovered a series of algorithmic innovations that serve to aid biologists when they are analyzing large data sets. These included approaches to create &ldquo;fingerprints&rdquo; of data that make it more efficient to ask and answer questions about the data, as well as approaches to reconstruct answers when given incomplete or compressed data. We were successful in advancing the theoretical basis for these approaches as well. This allows these approaches to come with guarantees in terms of accuracy and performance. Intriguingly, these theoretical and algorithmics advances have application outside of metagenomics. In particular, this work has already been applied by other researchers to fields such as genomics, blockchain data sharing, and privacy preservation. We have also published open-source software implementations of our algorithms on GitHub.</p> <p>This project also promoted trainee teaching and learning. We worked with undergraduates and graduate students to train them to excel at interdisciplinary work in the fields of mathematics and biology. This included involving trainees in research projects and equipping them with skills necessary to be successful in the workforce.</p> <p>Among various routes of disseminating this work, we also collaborated with SciShow, a popular YouTube channel, to design and produce an educational video on the topic of antibiotic resistant microorganisms. The technology developed in this project can be used to better understand such issues and gives biologists more &ldquo;tools in their toolbox&rdquo; to address this and other important topics in metagenomics.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/03/2022<br>      Modified by: David&nbsp;M&nbsp;Koslicki</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Faster, more accurate, and better-understood mathematical methods in metagenomics  Communities of microorganisms participate in and drive a variety of biochemical processes that have significant impact on the environment around them. This impact ranges widely from causing diseases to offering new kinds of antibiotics, to helping crops grow by fixing nitrogen in the soil. Metagenomics is the study of such microbial communities through their extracted DNA. One of the first questions to ask when studying such a community is: "which organisms are present and at what abundance?" Most current approaches to this so-called community profiling problem take a parsimonious approach: infer the presence of the fewest organisms possible that still agrees with the observed data. However, treating each organism as completely different from any other can lead to mis-estimates of the different kinds and amounts of organisms present.  This project advanced both the theory and practice of studying microbial communities. In particular, we used a recently developed notion of the similarity of microorganisms to better answer the question "what is in my metagenomic sample?" by properly considering organism similarity. Since the goal of this project involved the advancement of data analysis methods, we also undertook studies to benchmark current data analysis methods and quantify the quality of existing reference data. This allowed us to identify shortcomings in current methods and reference databases and make recommendations for how to overcome those shortcomings.  In the course of this research, we also discovered a series of algorithmic innovations that serve to aid biologists when they are analyzing large data sets. These included approaches to create "fingerprints" of data that make it more efficient to ask and answer questions about the data, as well as approaches to reconstruct answers when given incomplete or compressed data. We were successful in advancing the theoretical basis for these approaches as well. This allows these approaches to come with guarantees in terms of accuracy and performance. Intriguingly, these theoretical and algorithmics advances have application outside of metagenomics. In particular, this work has already been applied by other researchers to fields such as genomics, blockchain data sharing, and privacy preservation. We have also published open-source software implementations of our algorithms on GitHub.  This project also promoted trainee teaching and learning. We worked with undergraduates and graduate students to train them to excel at interdisciplinary work in the fields of mathematics and biology. This included involving trainees in research projects and equipping them with skills necessary to be successful in the workforce.  Among various routes of disseminating this work, we also collaborated with SciShow, a popular YouTube channel, to design and produce an educational video on the topic of antibiotic resistant microorganisms. The technology developed in this project can be used to better understand such issues and gives biologists more "tools in their toolbox" to address this and other important topics in metagenomics.          Last Modified: 08/03/2022       Submitted by: David M Koslicki]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
