<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Bridging the Health Care Skill Gap]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>199114.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>199114</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ITE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Innovation and Technology Ecosystems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Linda Molnar</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lmolnar@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928316</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The project aims to serve the national need of increasing the capacity to have more qualified healthcare providers to address the challenge of the Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID-19). By developing and deploying web-based tools that individuals and employers can use to explore healthcare-related competency frameworks, self-identify skill gaps, and find credentials and training, this project seeks to fill gaps in the healthcare workforce. These tools will help individuals identify healthcare areas where they have adjacent skill sets and will also help companies identify employees who are candidates for upskilling into healthcare. Once individual skills are inventoried, the tool will help users identify where they can obtain the requisite healthcare skills and credentials. The tool will be usable on desktop and mobile devices which broadens the reach of this project. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project seeks to address the COVID-19 crisis by providing end users with the ability to compare their own skills with those required for available healthcare roles and credentials and, in some cases, find ways to fill gaps. The frameworks and related credentials will come from the Credential Engine and additional data will come from the Open Syllabus Project. This project will apply artificial intelligence (AI), specifically  natural language understanding (NLU), to (a) crosswalk competency frameworks associated with these credentials, (b) compare skills entered by users to those required to earn those credentials, (c) generate an "alignment score" that measures and quantifies the gap between the two skill sets, and (d) suggest courses and credential programs with the potential to close those gaps. This will contribute to research into applications of NLU to competency-based credentialing and training and will provide data in a concrete domain (healthcare). Including validation and sharing of the underlying competency framework translation and alignment score services via an open data infrastructure will improve our nation’s healthcare talent pipeline.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This RAPID award is made by the Convergence Accelerator program in the Office of Integrative Activities and is associated with the Convergence Accelerator Track B: Future of Work and the Human-Technology Frontier.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/19/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/19/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.083</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2029590</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
<LastName>Robson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Robert Robson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[robby.robson@eduworks.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000222362</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/19/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Janette</FirstName>
<LastName>Hill</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Janette Hill</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[janette@uga.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000265616</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/19/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Garn</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael A Garn</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[myk@gatech.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000561553</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/19/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Eduworks Corporation</Name>
<CityName>CORVALLIS</CityName>
<ZipCode>973334899</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5417530844</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>400 SW 4TH ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[STE 110]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OR04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>FTJ1AV18B3X5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>EDUWORKS CORPORATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Eduworks Corporation]]></Name>
<CityName>Corvallis</CityName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<ZipCode>973334899</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[400 SW 4th Street STE 110]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OR04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>096Y</Code>
<Text>CA-FW-HTF: Convergence Acceler</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~199114</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-75d1871e-7fff-63d9-c17a-c1bb59f35058">&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span id="docs-internal-guid-a6ba14de-7fff-951e-8313-9a7f4932fa40"> <span id="docs-internal-guid-97e7548b-7fff-f694-cd98-ecc059170ab8"> </span></span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>COVID-19 created a need for persons to fill job roles created by the pandemic. Some of these roles, such as nurses trained in dealing with the psychological effects of the pandemic, required extensive training and certification. Others, such as contract tracing and compliance officers, could be filled quickly by persons with the correct skills after a short period of training. The goal of this project was to help people identify such roles that were good matches for their existing skills, to find training opportunities that would help them move into those roles, and to link them to potential job openings.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>This was done through a Health Job Advisor web app (</span><a href="http://www.c2health.org"><span>www.c2health.org</span></a><span>) developed as part of the project. This app allows users to self-report a skills inventory that includes transferable skills and technical skills. Proficiency levels are not externally assessed. The Advisor then displays suitable COVID-related jobs and can recommend training opportunities registered in the Credential Registry (</span><a href="https://credentialengine.org/credential-transparency/"><span>https://credentialengine.org/credential-transparency/</span></a><span>). The technology in this app includes the open source Competency and Skills System (</span><a href="http://www.cassproject.org"><span>www.CaSSproject.org</span></a><span>), the Credential Engine?s Credential Finder (</span><a href="https://credentialfinder.org"><span>https://credentialfinder.org</span></a><span>), skills-alignment technology that was being researched and developed as part of an NSF Convergence Accelerator Project (NSF Award #2033578, </span><a href="http://www.skillsync.com"><span>www.skillsync.com</span></a><span>), and an integration with Indeed.com.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><strong>Intellectual Merit</strong><span><strong>: </strong>Our first research problem was developing skills frameworks for specific jobs and for use in a general skills inventory. We started by searching for lists of skills from authoritative sources such as professional organizations or accreditation agencies. We found these to be too general or too specific and needed to combine and edit them to create frameworks at the required level of granularity. These were validated by healthcare subject matter experts (SMEs), and the skills were prioritized as required, desired, and ?nice to have.? This was a new process that differs from previously published processes that involve working with practitioners rather than SMEs and do not include prioritization. Our second research problem was the user interface and user experience (UI/UX). We needed to collect multiple screens of data from users without being overly burdensome. The UI/UX design went through internal and external testing and was developed in several iterations. Although the results were satisfactory, we concluded that AI services that automatically extract skills from resumes would increase usability. A third area of research was the underlying alignment services. The methods we implemented for the Advisor uses generic ontologies with a layer that considers prioritization. Although adequate to produce useful results, these have been replaced in the ongoing SkillSync project by more sophisticated and superior algorithms that use pre-trained language models.</span></p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts:</strong><span> The goal of this project was to move workers into areas of need in response to the COVID-19 pandemic. We had initially planned to address jobs in the nursing field, but found this to be impractical because of the length of training required and because of the highly specialized requirements that individual hospitals and healthcare facilities impose. We shifted to contact tracing and compliance, which at the time were in high demand. The Advisor app that is available online can be used for these two fields. It may be viewed as a proof-of-concept that can be quickly developed for other areas as new demands arise. The work of this project is being integrated into the SkillSync project, which is developing more powerful methods for matching worker skills to job skills and training offerings. </span></p> <p dir="ltr">&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/26/2022<br>      Modified by: Robert&nbsp;Robson</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2029590/2029590_10671773_1653596234199_Screenshot2022-05-26131443--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2029590/2029590_10671773_1653596234199_Screenshot2022-05-26131443--rgov-800width.jpg" title="C2-Health Advisor"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2029590/2029590_10671773_1653596234199_Screenshot2022-05-26131443--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="C2-Health Advisor"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Home Screen of C2 Health Advisor</div> <div class="imageCredit">Eduworks Corporation</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Robert&nbsp;Robson</div> <div class="imageTitle">C2-Health Advisor</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2029590/2029590_10671773_1653596380286_Screenshot2022-05-26131822--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2029590/2029590_10671773_1653596380286_Screenshot2022-05-26131822--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Communication Skills"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2029590/2029590_10671773_1653596380286_Screenshot2022-05-26131822--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Communication Skills"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Sample Skills Inventory Screen</div> <div class="imageCredit">Eduworks Corporation</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Robert&nbsp;Robson</div> <div class="imageTitle">Communication Skills</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2029590/2029590_10671773_1653596697485_Screenshot2022-05-26132119--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2029590/2029590_10671773_1653596697485_Screenshot2022-05-26132119--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Health Advisor Screen"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2029590/2029590_10671773_1653596697485_Screenshot2022-05-26132119--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Health Advisor Screen"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Health Advisor shows matches and provides links to jobs, credentials, and training. (Note: Links go to external sites so no screenshots are provided.)</div> <div class="imageCredit">Eduworks Corporation</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Robert&nbsp;Robson</div> <div class="imageTitle">Health Advisor Screen</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[       COVID-19 created a need for persons to fill job roles created by the pandemic. Some of these roles, such as nurses trained in dealing with the psychological effects of the pandemic, required extensive training and certification. Others, such as contract tracing and compliance officers, could be filled quickly by persons with the correct skills after a short period of training. The goal of this project was to help people identify such roles that were good matches for their existing skills, to find training opportunities that would help them move into those roles, and to link them to potential job openings.  This was done through a Health Job Advisor web app (www.c2health.org) developed as part of the project. This app allows users to self-report a skills inventory that includes transferable skills and technical skills. Proficiency levels are not externally assessed. The Advisor then displays suitable COVID-related jobs and can recommend training opportunities registered in the Credential Registry (https://credentialengine.org/credential-transparency/). The technology in this app includes the open source Competency and Skills System (www.CaSSproject.org), the Credential Engine?s Credential Finder (https://credentialfinder.org), skills-alignment technology that was being researched and developed as part of an NSF Convergence Accelerator Project (NSF Award #2033578, www.skillsync.com), and an integration with Indeed.com.  Intellectual Merit: Our first research problem was developing skills frameworks for specific jobs and for use in a general skills inventory. We started by searching for lists of skills from authoritative sources such as professional organizations or accreditation agencies. We found these to be too general or too specific and needed to combine and edit them to create frameworks at the required level of granularity. These were validated by healthcare subject matter experts (SMEs), and the skills were prioritized as required, desired, and ?nice to have.? This was a new process that differs from previously published processes that involve working with practitioners rather than SMEs and do not include prioritization. Our second research problem was the user interface and user experience (UI/UX). We needed to collect multiple screens of data from users without being overly burdensome. The UI/UX design went through internal and external testing and was developed in several iterations. Although the results were satisfactory, we concluded that AI services that automatically extract skills from resumes would increase usability. A third area of research was the underlying alignment services. The methods we implemented for the Advisor uses generic ontologies with a layer that considers prioritization. Although adequate to produce useful results, these have been replaced in the ongoing SkillSync project by more sophisticated and superior algorithms that use pre-trained language models.  Broader Impacts: The goal of this project was to move workers into areas of need in response to the COVID-19 pandemic. We had initially planned to address jobs in the nursing field, but found this to be impractical because of the length of training required and because of the highly specialized requirements that individual hospitals and healthcare facilities impose. We shifted to contact tracing and compliance, which at the time were in high demand. The Advisor app that is available online can be used for these two fields. It may be viewed as a proof-of-concept that can be quickly developed for other areas as new demands arise. The work of this project is being integrated into the SkillSync project, which is developing more powerful methods for matching worker skills to job skills and training offerings.             Last Modified: 05/26/2022       Submitted by: Robert Robson]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
