<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Lattice-Defective Copper Oxides as a Biocidal Tool for COVID-19 and Beyond]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>200000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>200000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Birgit Schwenzer</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bschwenz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924771</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[NON-TECHNICAL DESCRIPTION: The 2020 COVID-19 pandemic has generated tremendous interest in how the virus spreads throughout populations as well as how it is deactivated. New types of surface treatments that exhibit antipathogenic “contact-kill” capabilities are urgently sought to protect public health and welfare. To this end, cuprous oxide is reported as a highly effective antimicrobial compound; while the origin of its antimicrobial property remains unknown, it is hypothesized to be a consequence of atomic-level copper vacancies in its crystal lattice that provide highly charged atomic environments. These locally energetic regions in the lattice are thought to disrupt and destroy cell membranes and/or the protein shell of viruses. Interdisciplinary research quantifies connections between the cuprous oxide lattice condition and its biocidal activity to permit rational engineering of this abundant, inexpensive and easily handled material for incorporation into coatings for public spaces.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;TECHNICAL DETAILS: Correlations between the cuprous oxide lattice defect condition and its antipathogenic response to representative organisms are quantified through structural and electronic probes, including magnetometry and photoabsorption. Lattice-defective cuprous oxide, synthesized by high-energy mechanical processing, is incorporated into coatings and subjected to biological assays to quantify any reduction in viable bacteria and viruses after prolonged exposure. Students and junior researchers involved in this project work at the typically unfrequented intersection of inorganic materials science and biology. These tests, which are designed to simulate actual conditions where a pathogen might survive on a given surface, provide enabling knowledge to engineer cuprous oxide, and perhaps other oxide materials, for antipathogenic purposes to address the current COVID-19 pandemic and to proactively confront future health challenges.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award is being funded by the CARES Act supplemental funds allocated to MPS.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/21/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/21/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2029104</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Laura</FirstName>
<LastName>Lewis</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Laura H Lewis</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[lhlewis@neu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000460546</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/21/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Northeastern University</Name>
<CityName>BOSTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>021155005</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6173733004</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>360 HUNTINGTON AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>HLTMVS2JZBS6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORTHEASTERN UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>HLTMVS2JZBS6</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Northeastern University]]></Name>
<CityName>Boston</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021155005</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[360 Huntington Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>158Y</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>1N20</Code>
<Name>R&amp;RA CARES Act DEFC N</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>010N2021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[R&RA CARES Act DEFC N]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~200000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The SARS-CoV-2 global pandemic has reinvigorated interest in the creation and widespread deployment of durable, cost-effective and environmentally benign antipathogenic coatings for high-touch public surfaces. While the self-sterilizing, or contact-kill, capability and mechanism of metallic copper and its metallic alloys are well-established, the noted biocidal capacity of Cu<sub>2</sub>O (cuprous oxide, cuprite) remains poorly understood. Cu<sub>2</sub>O is a transition-metal oxide with copper atom lattice vacancies in its natural native state; it is hypothesized that these vacancies hold the key to cuprite's biocidal capacity. This project tested the hypotheses that intentional amplification of cuprite's lattice imperfections, such as atomic vacancies, will likewise amplify its antipathogenic character.</p> <p>In this work, commercial cuprous oxide (Cu<sub>2</sub>O, cuprite) powder was rapidly nanostructured using high-energy cryomechanical processing to deliver large amounts of plastic deformation, resulting in significant crystal lattice damage. This process was conducted at low temperature to minimize recovery of induced lattice damage that would otherwise disappear or "heal" during standard high-energy mechanical milling. It was demonstrated that cryomilling created well-crystallized nanoscale regions enmeshed within the highly lattice-defective particle matrix. Coatings made from these processed powders demonstrated a self-sterilizing response to <em>E. coli</em> bacteria that was 4x (400%) faster than coatings made from unprocessed powder. No viable bacteria (&gt; 99.999% (5-log10) reduction) were detected in bioassays performed after two hours of exposure of <em>E. coli</em> to coatings of processed cuprous oxide, while a greater than 99% bacterial reduction was achieved within 30 minutes of exposure. Further, these coatings were hydrophobic and no external energy input was required to activate their contact-kill capability. It is considered that increasing the relative proportion of lattice-defective cuprous oxide in coating surfaces will further enhance the antipathogenic capability of this abundant, inexpensive, robust and easily handled material.</p> <p>The intellectual merit of this project is the conclusion that the upregulated antibacterial response of the processed powders is indeed derived from extensive induced crystallographic disorder and microstrain in the Cu<sub>2</sub>O lattice. These regions are thought to contribute localized, highly charged regions that can disrupt cell membranes. Broader impacts include the development of a conceptual recipe to optimize the biocidal response of this compound for wider application in contact-kill surfaces to benefit public health. Additional broader impacts were the opportunity for cross-disciplinary training and education in electronic materials science and biology, two disciplines that do not often overlap, and the participation of undergraduate students in the research that was led by women.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/12/2022<br>      Modified by: Laura&nbsp;H&nbsp;Lewis</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The SARS-CoV-2 global pandemic has reinvigorated interest in the creation and widespread deployment of durable, cost-effective and environmentally benign antipathogenic coatings for high-touch public surfaces. While the self-sterilizing, or contact-kill, capability and mechanism of metallic copper and its metallic alloys are well-established, the noted biocidal capacity of Cu2O (cuprous oxide, cuprite) remains poorly understood. Cu2O is a transition-metal oxide with copper atom lattice vacancies in its natural native state; it is hypothesized that these vacancies hold the key to cuprite's biocidal capacity. This project tested the hypotheses that intentional amplification of cuprite's lattice imperfections, such as atomic vacancies, will likewise amplify its antipathogenic character.  In this work, commercial cuprous oxide (Cu2O, cuprite) powder was rapidly nanostructured using high-energy cryomechanical processing to deliver large amounts of plastic deformation, resulting in significant crystal lattice damage. This process was conducted at low temperature to minimize recovery of induced lattice damage that would otherwise disappear or "heal" during standard high-energy mechanical milling. It was demonstrated that cryomilling created well-crystallized nanoscale regions enmeshed within the highly lattice-defective particle matrix. Coatings made from these processed powders demonstrated a self-sterilizing response to E. coli bacteria that was 4x (400%) faster than coatings made from unprocessed powder. No viable bacteria (&gt; 99.999% (5-log10) reduction) were detected in bioassays performed after two hours of exposure of E. coli to coatings of processed cuprous oxide, while a greater than 99% bacterial reduction was achieved within 30 minutes of exposure. Further, these coatings were hydrophobic and no external energy input was required to activate their contact-kill capability. It is considered that increasing the relative proportion of lattice-defective cuprous oxide in coating surfaces will further enhance the antipathogenic capability of this abundant, inexpensive, robust and easily handled material.  The intellectual merit of this project is the conclusion that the upregulated antibacterial response of the processed powders is indeed derived from extensive induced crystallographic disorder and microstrain in the Cu2O lattice. These regions are thought to contribute localized, highly charged regions that can disrupt cell membranes. Broader impacts include the development of a conceptual recipe to optimize the biocidal response of this compound for wider application in contact-kill surfaces to benefit public health. Additional broader impacts were the opportunity for cross-disciplinary training and education in electronic materials science and biology, two disciplines that do not often overlap, and the participation of undergraduate students in the research that was led by women.                Last Modified: 07/12/2022       Submitted by: Laura H Lewis]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
