<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Developing a Benefits Distribution System to Facilitate Economic Recovery from the Impact of COVID-19]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>148589.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>148589</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ITE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Innovation and Technology Ecosystems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Linda Molnar</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lmolnar@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928316</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The project aims to serve the national need of developing Pandemic Response benefits distribution systems to support individuals eligible for unemployment benefits and other services. The Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID-19) has caused the shutdown of many sectors in the US economy, resulting in an unprecedented amount of unemployment claims in a short period of time. This project seeks to (1) help states develop and deploy Pandemic Response benefits distribution systems needed to meet the high demand of unemployment insurance claims, including for workers newly eligible under the Pandemic Unemployment Assistance (PUA) program; (2) analyze administrative data to understand needs of the impacted population; (3) develop and deploy outreach and support systems to connect the impacted population to government support systems and labor training programs to help individuals find gainful re-employment; and (4) facilitate the sharing of findings to increase the national impact. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project builds upon a pilot that was designed to facilitate and deploy a benefits application collection system for Rhode Islanders (NSF award 1937061). The pilot successfully developed and deployed the system through a collaborative effort with Research Improving People's Lives, Amazon Web Services, and the Rhode Island Department of Labor and Training. This current project will expand and refine the pilot effort to be openly shared with other states. This project aims to design and deploy Pandemic Response benefits distribution systems, such as those needed for unemployment insurance claims, so that states can support their residents during the crisis. The project will analyze state administrative data, including administrative data on earnings, employment, and public assistance programs to quickly deliver insights that help identify needs of the impacted population. By deploying outreach support systems to connect impacted individuals to training programs and government support systems, this project aims to help individuals find gainful re-employment after the COVID-19 shutdown. The project will facilitate sharing findings through video conference meetings to disseminate results and evidence-based practices to the public, including state policy leaders, as an effort to support a national economic recovery.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This RAPID award is made by the Convergence Accelerator program in the Office of Integrative Activities and is associated with the Convergence Accelerator Track B: Future of Work and the Human-Technology Frontier.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/21/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/21/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.083</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2029746</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Justine</FirstName>
<LastName>Hastings</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Justine S Hastings</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jhastings@ripl.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000455730</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/21/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>National Bureau of Economic Research Inc</Name>
<CityName>CAMBRIDGE</CityName>
<ZipCode>021385359</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6178683900</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1050 MASSACHUSETTS AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>GT28BRBA2Q49</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NATIONAL BUREAU OF ECONOMIC RESEARCH INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[National Bureau of Economic Research Inc]]></Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021385398</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1050 Massachusetts Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>096Y</Code>
<Text>CA-FW-HTF: Convergence Acceler</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~148589</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The COVID-19 public health emergency caused widespread economic shutdown and unemployment. The resulting surge in Unemployment Insurance claims threatened to overwhelm the legacy systems state workforce agencies rely on to collect, process, and pay claims. In Rhode Island &mdash; in partnership with the RI Department of Labor and Training, the RI Office of the Governor, and Amazon Web Services &mdash; our team developed a scalable cloud solution to collect Pandemic Unemployment Assistance (PUA) claims as part of a new program created under the Coronavirus Aid, Relief and Economic Security Act to extend unemployment benefits to independent contractors and gig-economy workers not covered by traditional Unemployment Insurance. Our new system was developed, tested, and deployed within 10 days following the passage of the Coronavirus Aid, Relief and Economic Security Act, making Rhode Island the first state in the nation to collect, validate, and pay Pandemic Unemployment Assistance claims.</p> <p>With support from the National Science Foundation under the RAISE opportunity, our team developed a productionized version of the Rhode Island PUA system, developed real-time reporting for the Rhode Island Department of Labor and Training to monitor PUA and develop data-driven decisions for success; and developed new technologies and behavioral nudges to help American jobseekers connect with upskilling opportunities and job openings for in-demand careers; and disseminated learnings across 21 state partners across the country.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/22/2022<br>      Modified by: Justine&nbsp;S&nbsp;Hastings</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The COVID-19 public health emergency caused widespread economic shutdown and unemployment. The resulting surge in Unemployment Insurance claims threatened to overwhelm the legacy systems state workforce agencies rely on to collect, process, and pay claims. In Rhode Island &mdash; in partnership with the RI Department of Labor and Training, the RI Office of the Governor, and Amazon Web Services &mdash; our team developed a scalable cloud solution to collect Pandemic Unemployment Assistance (PUA) claims as part of a new program created under the Coronavirus Aid, Relief and Economic Security Act to extend unemployment benefits to independent contractors and gig-economy workers not covered by traditional Unemployment Insurance. Our new system was developed, tested, and deployed within 10 days following the passage of the Coronavirus Aid, Relief and Economic Security Act, making Rhode Island the first state in the nation to collect, validate, and pay Pandemic Unemployment Assistance claims.  With support from the National Science Foundation under the RAISE opportunity, our team developed a productionized version of the Rhode Island PUA system, developed real-time reporting for the Rhode Island Department of Labor and Training to monitor PUA and develop data-driven decisions for success; and developed new technologies and behavioral nudges to help American jobseekers connect with upskilling opportunities and job openings for in-demand careers; and disseminated learnings across 21 state partners across the country.          Last Modified: 12/22/2022       Submitted by: Justine S Hastings]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
