<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Collaborative Research: Relationships, social distancing, social media and the spread of COVID-19]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>100000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>117500</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jan Leighley</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This project seeks to improve the national response to the COVID-19 pandemic by launching large-scale data collection through a rolling national survey linked to individual social media data. We generate information useful to policymakers and local authorities and offer near-real-time state-by-state disease tracking. Our data allow officials to understand where the virus is currently spreading, facilitating improved allocation of resources. We also evaluate the networked nature of the disease, tracking its flow based on the reported social relationships of the survey participants and their social distancing behaviors. The project captures how well the information and communication needs of Americans are met during this crisis, observes patterns of citizen compliance with government recommendations, stay-at-home orders, and enforced lockdowns, and assesses their impact on suppressing the spread of the virus among diverse populations.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project has two core objectives: (1) producing information that will be immediately useful in improving the national response to COVID-19; and (2) using COVID-19 data to understand how people adapt to and make sense of a national crisis that has important and immediate ramifications for their daily lives. We rely on a large-scale, rolling national survey that is conducted on a daily basis, with approximately 3000 respondents per day.  We also link the survey data to the social media behavior of respondents. The large sample sizes collected daily offers near-real-time state-by-state disease tracking, as well as the ability to observe key differences in responses to policies across demographic groups. The design will capture how people use technology to work, get informed, and stay connected, and respondents’ financial difficulties, employment experiences, and parenting and educational challenges in response to the pandemic.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/11/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/21/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2029792</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Matthew</FirstName>
<LastName>Baum</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Matthew A Baum</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[matthew_baum@harvard.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000449932</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/11/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Harvard University</Name>
<CityName>CAMBRIDGE</CityName>
<ZipCode>021385366</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6174955501</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1033 MASSACHUSETTS AVE STE 3</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>LN53LCFJFL45</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PRESIDENT AND FELLOWS OF HARVARD COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Harvard Kennedy School]]></Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021385801</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[79 JFK Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>120Y</Code>
<Text>AIB-Acctble Institutions&amp;Behav</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8060</Code>
<Text>Secure &amp;Trustworthy Cyberspace</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>025Z</Code>
<Text>SaTC: Secure and Trustworthy Cyberspace</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>065Z</Code>
<Text>Human factors for security research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7434</Code>
<Text>CNCI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>1N20</Code>
<Name>R&amp;RA CARES Act DEFC N</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>010N2021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[R&RA CARES Act DEFC N]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~100000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~17500</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Since the start of the project, we have completed 15 large-scale 50-state survey waves with approximately 20,000 respondents per wave. We have also completed 5 smaller national surveys with 1000-2000 respondents each. At present, we have conducted surveys with over 190,000 unique respondents, 40,000 of whom have participated in multiple waves.</p> <p>The large-scale longitudinal data collection allowed us to examine patterns at the state and national level. The oversampling of minority populations enabled us to reliably capture the attitudes and behaviors of diverse gender, age, racial, ethnic, and geographic groups.</p> <p>A secondary data collection for the project includes the monitoring of social media content. Over 30,000 consenting survey respondents have provided us with valid Twitter handles that have been matched to existing accounts on the platform. The combination of social media records and survey responses is especially powerful as they have complementary strengths. Merging the Twitter data with survey data can provide important insights concerning people?s attitudes and behaviors, as well as their information seeking and sharing practices.</p> <p>The project disseminates information to the public and to policy-makers in a number of ways. We have a public-facing website (<a href="https://covidstates.org/">https://covidstates.org</a>) that contains reports, interactive dashboards, and aggregated data. Among other products, we offer interactive trackers with state-by-state information on social distancing and policy approval, as well as a tracker of public trust in key social and political institutions to handle the COVID-19 pandemic.</p> <p>The project team has completed and published 54 reports covering a wide variety of topics; examples include:</p> <p>-&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;COVID-19 vaccine hesitancy, resistance, and acceptance&nbsp;</p> <p>-&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;COVID-19 testing times and key barriers to testing</p> <p>-&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Health-related behaviors, including mask-wearing and social distancing</p> <p>-&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Support for COVID-19 measures (e.g. business closures, travel restrictions)</p> <p>-&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Approval of state and national governments handling of the pandemic</p> <p>-&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Sources of information regarding COVID-19</p> <p>-&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Belief in misinformation about COVID-19</p> <p>-&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Mental health consequences of COVID-19</p> <p>-&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Trust in public figures and institutions</p> <p>-&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;COVID-19 and school reopening</p> <p>-&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;COVID-19 and political behavior</p> <p>The team has published three academic papers in peer-reviewed journals (two on COVID-19 and mental health, another one on health misinformation). Ten other academic papers are in various stages of development and submission.</p> <p>Team members have presented works from this project at six national conferences and have given over 15 invited talks for a variety of audiences.&nbsp;&nbsp;Our survey findings were well-received by federal, state, and local government representatives, as well as by public health officials. We have, for instance, given briefings and provided information to the Office of the Surgeon General (OSG), which has also requested regular updates from us.</p> <p>Our initiative distributes information to local journalists (via a database of several hundred reporters and an opt-in alert system) and national media (print, radio, TV, and online). Our work has been featured in major national news outlets, including New York Times, Washington Post, Wall Street Journal, NPR, and USA Today, among others.&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>References</strong>:&nbsp;</p> <p>Druckman, J., Ognyanova, K., Baum, M., Lazer, D., Perlis, R., Volpe, J., Santillana, M., Chwe, H., Quintana, A., &amp; Simonson, M. (2021). The role of race, religion, and partisanship in misinformation about COVID-19.&nbsp;<em>Group Processes &amp; Intergroup Relations</em>, 24(4), 638?657. doi:10.1177/1368430220985912</p> <p>Perlis, R. H., Ognyanova, K., Santillana, M., Baum, M. A., Lazer, D., Druckman, J., &amp; Della Volpe, J. (2021). Association of Acute Symptoms of COVID-19 and Symptoms of Depression in Adults.&nbsp;<em>JAMA Network Open</em>, 4(3). doi: 10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2021.3223</p> <p>Perlis, R. H., Santillana, M., Ognyanova, K., Green, J., Druckman, J., Lazer, D., &amp; Baum, M. A. (2021). Factors Associated With Self-reported Symptoms of Depression Among Adults With and Without a Previous COVID-19 Diagnosis.&nbsp;<em>JAMA Network Open</em>, 4(6), e2116612. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2021.16612</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/30/2021<br>      Modified by: Matthew&nbsp;A&nbsp;Baum</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Since the start of the project, we have completed 15 large-scale 50-state survey waves with approximately 20,000 respondents per wave. We have also completed 5 smaller national surveys with 1000-2000 respondents each. At present, we have conducted surveys with over 190,000 unique respondents, 40,000 of whom have participated in multiple waves.  The large-scale longitudinal data collection allowed us to examine patterns at the state and national level. The oversampling of minority populations enabled us to reliably capture the attitudes and behaviors of diverse gender, age, racial, ethnic, and geographic groups.  A secondary data collection for the project includes the monitoring of social media content. Over 30,000 consenting survey respondents have provided us with valid Twitter handles that have been matched to existing accounts on the platform. The combination of social media records and survey responses is especially powerful as they have complementary strengths. Merging the Twitter data with survey data can provide important insights concerning people?s attitudes and behaviors, as well as their information seeking and sharing practices.  The project disseminates information to the public and to policy-makers in a number of ways. We have a public-facing website (https://covidstates.org) that contains reports, interactive dashboards, and aggregated data. Among other products, we offer interactive trackers with state-by-state information on social distancing and policy approval, as well as a tracker of public trust in key social and political institutions to handle the COVID-19 pandemic.  The project team has completed and published 54 reports covering a wide variety of topics; examples include:  -    COVID-19 vaccine hesitancy, resistance, and acceptance   -    COVID-19 testing times and key barriers to testing  -    Health-related behaviors, including mask-wearing and social distancing  -    Support for COVID-19 measures (e.g. business closures, travel restrictions)  -    Approval of state and national governments handling of the pandemic  -    Sources of information regarding COVID-19  -    Belief in misinformation about COVID-19  -    Mental health consequences of COVID-19  -    Trust in public figures and institutions  -    COVID-19 and school reopening  -    COVID-19 and political behavior  The team has published three academic papers in peer-reviewed journals (two on COVID-19 and mental health, another one on health misinformation). Ten other academic papers are in various stages of development and submission.  Team members have presented works from this project at six national conferences and have given over 15 invited talks for a variety of audiences.  Our survey findings were well-received by federal, state, and local government representatives, as well as by public health officials. We have, for instance, given briefings and provided information to the Office of the Surgeon General (OSG), which has also requested regular updates from us.  Our initiative distributes information to local journalists (via a database of several hundred reporters and an opt-in alert system) and national media (print, radio, TV, and online). Our work has been featured in major national news outlets, including New York Times, Washington Post, Wall Street Journal, NPR, and USA Today, among others.   References:   Druckman, J., Ognyanova, K., Baum, M., Lazer, D., Perlis, R., Volpe, J., Santillana, M., Chwe, H., Quintana, A., &amp; Simonson, M. (2021). The role of race, religion, and partisanship in misinformation about COVID-19. Group Processes &amp; Intergroup Relations, 24(4), 638?657. doi:10.1177/1368430220985912  Perlis, R. H., Ognyanova, K., Santillana, M., Baum, M. A., Lazer, D., Druckman, J., &amp; Della Volpe, J. (2021). Association of Acute Symptoms of COVID-19 and Symptoms of Depression in Adults. JAMA Network Open, 4(3). doi: 10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2021.3223  Perlis, R. H., Santillana, M., Ognyanova, K., Green, J., Druckman, J., Lazer, D., &amp; Baum, M. A. (2021). Factors Associated With Self-reported Symptoms of Depression Among Adults With and Without a Previous COVID-19 Diagnosis. JAMA Network Open, 4(6), e2116612. doi:10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2021.16612          Last Modified: 11/30/2021       Submitted by: Matthew A Baum]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
