<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Symposium SICB 2021 An Evolutionary Tail: EvoDevo, structure, and function of post-anal appendages.]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>14630.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>14630</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08090300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IOS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kathryn Dickson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kdickson@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927380</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Non-Technical Abstract&lt;br/&gt;Many animal species have tails, which are remarkably diverse in shape and function. They can be short, long, thick, thin, feathered, hairy, bald, spiked, or even absent. Tails can serve many functions, including propulsion, communication, flagging or rattling, balancing, and grasping. However, although tails are important to animal function and evolution, compared to limbs, tails are vastly understudied. Relatively little is known about their development, morphological diversity, or mechanical function. This award supports a cross-disciplinary symposium that will bring together scientists and engineers who study a wide variety of tail and tail-related topics in animals and robots. It will facilitate and enhance exchange of knowledge and expertise. The outcomes of this symposium will be a collaborative workshop that will identify critical unanswered questions concerning the biology of tails and a roadmap for addressing these challenges through future research. The symposium highlights early-career researchers and members of groups under-represented in the sciences. In partnership with Howard University and the Society for Integrative and Comparative Biology Broadening Participation Committee, participants in the symposium will host an outreach event to provide a networking experience for students from Howard University and potentially other Historically Black Colleges and Universities in the Washington, D.C. area.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical Abstract&lt;br/&gt;Although diverse and common among animals, tails are vastly understudied structures, even though the importance of a functional post-anal appendage is recognized in many robotic designs. Understanding how tails develop and function contributes insight to potential evolutionary significance of the appendage. This symposium brings together investigators from multiple disciplines with research interests in this area who have worked relatively independently, from distinct perspectives. They will share findings on the diversity of development, form, and functions of tails - in animals and robots – and seek general principles that have driven the success of this appendage. The symposium will facilitate cross-disciplinary research discussions among fields including developmental biology, engineering, physics, and behavioral biology. In addition, an organized luncheon will further facilitate the active exchange of ideas, concepts, and approaches among diverse researchers who employ different model systems.  The symposium emphasizes early-career researchers and groups under-represented in STEM, and provides opportunities for mentoring, sharing of ideas and concepts, and development of new collaborations. The outcomes of the symposium will be a forward-looking review article that will delineate the current state of tail research and identify the unanswered questions with potential to be addressed by interdisciplinary collaborations. This review article will introduce the compilation of this symposium’s papers in Integrative and Comparative Biology. Finally, the grant will help support an outreach event centered on Minority Serving Institutions in the region of Washington, D.C.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/12/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/11/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2029523</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Nagler</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>James J Nagler</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jamesn@uidaho.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000413536</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/11/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Craig</FirstName>
<LastName>McGowan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Craig McGowan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[cmcgowan@usc.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000578376</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/12/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate>12/11/2020</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Regents of the University of Idaho</Name>
<CityName>MOSCOW</CityName>
<ZipCode>838449803</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2088856651</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>875 PERIMETER DR MS 3020</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Idaho</StateName>
<StateCode>ID</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>ID01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>QWYKRJH5NNJ3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF IDAHO</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Idaho]]></Name>
<CityName>Moscow</CityName>
<StateCode>ID</StateCode>
<ZipCode>838443051</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[875 Perimeter Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Idaho</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT/>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>ID"</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7658</Code>
<Text>Physiol Mechs &amp; Biomechanics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~14630</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Many animal species have tails, which are remarkably diverse in shape and function. Tails can serve many functions, including propulsion, communication, flagging or rattling, balancing, and grasping. However, although tails are important to animal function and evolution, compared to limbs,<em> </em>tails are vastly understudied. The goal of this project was to create a cross-disciplinary symposium to bring together scientists and engineers who study a wide variety of tail and tail-related topics, in animals and robots, to facilitate and enhance exchange of knowledge and expertise. In line with organizers? priorities, we emphasized inviting speakers who are early-career researchers and members of under-represented groups in the sciences.</p> <p>This project focused on a 1-day symposium at the 2021 annual meeting of the Society for Integrative and Comparative Biology (SICB), which was made virtual due to COVID-19. Associated with the symposium, we held two video conference virtual workshops in which participants in the symposium and complimentary sessions met to brainstorm ideas around open questions in tail research and propose goals for how these questions could be addressed. We leveraged the virtual format of the conference to focus on broadening participation at the high school level by supporting registration for students from Moscow, Idaho and Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. Under the guidance of their teachers, students participated in activities designed to determine the impact attendance at the SICB meeting had on their views of science and the likelihood they would pursue a career in a STEM field (Science, Technology, Engineering, and Math).</p> <p>The virtual format for the meeting and workshop proved to be highly successful with over 2,500 people registered for the meeting. The symposium and workshop resulted in 18 publications and achieved the goal of introducing scientists from across a broad range of backgrounds and career stages. Our broadening participation efforts opened the door for over 100 high school students to experience what fundamental biological research is like. It provided opportunities for them to ask questions of graduate students just getting started and seasoned faculty who have been attending conferences for decades. A subgroup of these students worked with their teachers and SICB communications staff to create blogs and vlogs about their experience attending the SICB meeting. This training included two writing workshops provided by the Managing Editor of a high impact science journal, Integrative and Comparative Biology. The feedback from the students was overwhelmingly positive and many reported gaining new interest in Biology, and an ongoing study will quantify the impact this project had on students? view of STEM fields.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/01/2021<br>      Modified by: James&nbsp;J&nbsp;Nagler</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Many animal species have tails, which are remarkably diverse in shape and function. Tails can serve many functions, including propulsion, communication, flagging or rattling, balancing, and grasping. However, although tails are important to animal function and evolution, compared to limbs, tails are vastly understudied. The goal of this project was to create a cross-disciplinary symposium to bring together scientists and engineers who study a wide variety of tail and tail-related topics, in animals and robots, to facilitate and enhance exchange of knowledge and expertise. In line with organizers? priorities, we emphasized inviting speakers who are early-career researchers and members of under-represented groups in the sciences.  This project focused on a 1-day symposium at the 2021 annual meeting of the Society for Integrative and Comparative Biology (SICB), which was made virtual due to COVID-19. Associated with the symposium, we held two video conference virtual workshops in which participants in the symposium and complimentary sessions met to brainstorm ideas around open questions in tail research and propose goals for how these questions could be addressed. We leveraged the virtual format of the conference to focus on broadening participation at the high school level by supporting registration for students from Moscow, Idaho and Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. Under the guidance of their teachers, students participated in activities designed to determine the impact attendance at the SICB meeting had on their views of science and the likelihood they would pursue a career in a STEM field (Science, Technology, Engineering, and Math).  The virtual format for the meeting and workshop proved to be highly successful with over 2,500 people registered for the meeting. The symposium and workshop resulted in 18 publications and achieved the goal of introducing scientists from across a broad range of backgrounds and career stages. Our broadening participation efforts opened the door for over 100 high school students to experience what fundamental biological research is like. It provided opportunities for them to ask questions of graduate students just getting started and seasoned faculty who have been attending conferences for decades. A subgroup of these students worked with their teachers and SICB communications staff to create blogs and vlogs about their experience attending the SICB meeting. This training included two writing workshops provided by the Managing Editor of a high impact science journal, Integrative and Comparative Biology. The feedback from the students was overwhelmingly positive and many reported gaining new interest in Biology, and an ongoing study will quantify the impact this project had on students? view of STEM fields.         Last Modified: 10/01/2021       Submitted by: James J Nagler]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
