<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: A physics-based model for droplet drying on varying surfaces and changing seasonal conditions and the implications for COVID-19 survival]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>199544.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>199544</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ying Sun</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The COVID-19 outbreak has resulted in enormous loss of lives and economic damage. Seasonal return of the coronavirus (SARS-CoV-2) will be even more devastating. One of the primary ways that SARS-CoV-2 appears to spread is through people touching surfaces with virus-laden droplets. Virus survivability on surfaces varies greatly by droplet size and composition, surface material and texture, and the ambient temperature and relative humidity. These factors impact the concentration of salt and other solutes in the process of droplets drying on surfaces, which strongly influences the survival of viruses in the droplets. This project will address survivability of viruses inside droplets and its relationship to droplet size, type of surface and ambient conditions representing seasonal variations. The team will especially seek to understand conditions under which virus survival in surface-adherent droplets is diminished. This information is crucial for public health officials, virologists, and other experts working on disinfection efforts to control and mitigate current and future COVID-19 outbreaks.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will bring together an interdisciplinary team of engineers, virologists, and infectious disease experts to understand the mechanisms that determine virus survival/annihilation on different surfaces under varying seasonal conditions. The research plan combines computer simulations and experiments to reveal what happens inside droplets under conditions specific to COVID-19 scenarios. More specifically, this project will study the thermal and mass transport processes that occur in droplets drying on various surfaces. Project results will include quantitative information on the solute (salt, protein) concentration-time pathways in the interior of virus-carrying droplets drying on surfaces. These pathways will be quantified as functions of droplet size, composition, ambient temperature and relative humidity, and surface characteristics. Novel laser and chemical treatments of surfaces will be employed to modify hydrophobicity and hydrophilicity over a wide range to examine the effect of such modifications on droplet drying processes. This project will therefore reveal what types of seasonal conditions and surface modifications will contribute to diminished survival of viruses within droplets. The project team will transition project results to experts who study methods to deactivate viruses. Arming them with precise knowledge on the thermochemical conditions faced by the pathogens within drying droplets will enable them to focus attention on effective disinfection techniques.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is jointly funded by the Thermal Transport Processes program and the Established Program to Stimulate Competitive Research (EPSCoR).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/20/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/20/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2029263</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Holavanahalli</FirstName>
<LastName>Udaykumar</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Holavanahalli S Udaykumar</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[hs-kumar@uiowa.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000484633</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/20/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Hongtao</FirstName>
<LastName>Ding</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Hongtao Ding</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[hongtao-ding@uiowa.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000675291</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/20/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Iowa</Name>
<CityName>IOWA CITY</CityName>
<ZipCode>522421316</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3193352123</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>105 JESSUP HALL</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Iowa</StateName>
<StateCode>IA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IA01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>Z1H9VJS8NG16</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>THE UNIVERSITY OF IOWA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Iowa]]></Name>
<CityName>Iowa City</CityName>
<StateCode>IA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>522421320</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2 Gilmore Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Iowa</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IA01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>158Y</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EPSCoR Co-Funding</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>1N20</Code>
<Name>R&amp;RA CARES Act DEFC N</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>010N2021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[R&RA CARES Act DEFC N]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~199544</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The evaporation rate of droplets plays a large role in surface-based transmission of many Infectious viral diseases including that of COVID 19. The key determinants of survival/inactivation of viruses contained in droplets on surfaces are ambient temperature, relative humidity, composition of the droplet and the substrate material. One of the measures for inactivation of viruses is the cumulative dose of solutes in the droplet (mainly salt) experienced by the pathogens, defined as the product of concentration (C) and time (T). This project work successfully developed a surrogate model for the cumulative dose (CxT) as function of temperature, relative humidity, and droplet substrate by combining the computer models and experimental work. The project revealed key physical mechanisms of drying of droplets with different compositions (3.5 % salt and 35g/L protein water droplet) on different substrates (superhydrophobic/untreated/hydrophilic surfaces) and tracked evolution of key droplet attributes such as diameter, height, contact angle, contact radii and the solute concentration. An important finding in the experimental work is that droplets with different compositions do not dry out completely and can remain as a thin film for several days, acting as an insulating layer for the virus increasing its survivability.&nbsp; This project successfully modeled the physical mechanisms of droplet drying observed in the experiments and calculated the evolution of solute concentration over time for droplets with different compositions. This key quantity of interest, CxT (or simply CT), obtained from the simulation were validated against the experimental result. A series of computer simulations were run to cover a wide parameter space in temperature, relative humidity and contact angle (measure of surface roughness) and a model for cumulative dose was built for both salt and protein water droplets. The results obtained confirm and reveal the physics of the &lsquo;U&rsquo; shaped survivability of the virus under differing ambient conditions (temperature and relative humidity). More importantly, the model provides quantifiable information on the survivability of viruses and regions and will enable design of surfaces that minimize survival of viruses and bacteria in droplets. This information can play a crucial role in controlling the spread of diseases in the future.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/29/2021<br>      Modified by: Hongtao&nbsp;Ding</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The evaporation rate of droplets plays a large role in surface-based transmission of many Infectious viral diseases including that of COVID 19. The key determinants of survival/inactivation of viruses contained in droplets on surfaces are ambient temperature, relative humidity, composition of the droplet and the substrate material. One of the measures for inactivation of viruses is the cumulative dose of solutes in the droplet (mainly salt) experienced by the pathogens, defined as the product of concentration (C) and time (T). This project work successfully developed a surrogate model for the cumulative dose (CxT) as function of temperature, relative humidity, and droplet substrate by combining the computer models and experimental work. The project revealed key physical mechanisms of drying of droplets with different compositions (3.5 % salt and 35g/L protein water droplet) on different substrates (superhydrophobic/untreated/hydrophilic surfaces) and tracked evolution of key droplet attributes such as diameter, height, contact angle, contact radii and the solute concentration. An important finding in the experimental work is that droplets with different compositions do not dry out completely and can remain as a thin film for several days, acting as an insulating layer for the virus increasing its survivability.  This project successfully modeled the physical mechanisms of droplet drying observed in the experiments and calculated the evolution of solute concentration over time for droplets with different compositions. This key quantity of interest, CxT (or simply CT), obtained from the simulation were validated against the experimental result. A series of computer simulations were run to cover a wide parameter space in temperature, relative humidity and contact angle (measure of surface roughness) and a model for cumulative dose was built for both salt and protein water droplets. The results obtained confirm and reveal the physics of the ‘U’ shaped survivability of the virus under differing ambient conditions (temperature and relative humidity). More importantly, the model provides quantifiable information on the survivability of viruses and regions and will enable design of surfaces that minimize survival of viruses and bacteria in droplets. This information can play a crucial role in controlling the spread of diseases in the future.          Last Modified: 08/29/2021       Submitted by: Hongtao Ding]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
