<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[EAGER: Collaborative Research: Origami-Based Extremely-Packed Multistable Pop-Up Design for Medical Masks]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EFMA</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Emerging Frontiers &amp; Multidisciplinary Activities</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Alias Smith</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>alismith@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928367</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Intellectual Merit:&lt;br/&gt;The research project aims to develop fundamental understanding of novel twisting-enabled pop-up origami structures with multi-stability. Practical applications of origami pop-up structures require a canopy and connected multiple origami rings to form a functional continuous face, which limits the accessibility of folding paths. This research will study how interactions among origami rings will affect folding and unfolding and provide understanding and identify the rules to design folding paths to overcome constraints imposed by these interactions. The research will yield knowledge about the energy landscape of origami rings and the stability of different states. Such understanding will facilitate the design of novel twisting-enabled pop-up and self-assembled structures with multi-stability.   &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: &lt;br/&gt;This research project could enable a new class of origami structures with great potential for future applications. The proposed Origami design with rapid pop-up and self-assembly could greatly increase transportation efficiency of masks during the fight against the COVID-19 pandemic. Moreover, the proposed origami concept can be readily applied to design other personal protection equipment such as eyewear, gowns, etc. It could also lead to new origami structures that are highly desirable in many demanding applications such as national security and human health. The research will increase the public scientific literacy and public engagement with science and technology and encourage the participation of women and underrepresented minorities in STEM through integration of the research with carefully designed educational tasks and by integrating the advanced material research from the project into course development in existing undergraduate and high-level graduate courses.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/27/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/27/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2029643</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ruike Renee</FirstName>
<LastName>Zhao</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ruike Renee Zhao</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[rrzhao@stanford.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000792657</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/27/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Ohio State University</Name>
<CityName>COLUMBUS</CityName>
<ZipCode>432101016</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6146888735</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1960 KENNY RD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OH03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>DLWBSLWAJWR1</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OHIO STATE UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>MN4MDDMN8529</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[The Ohio State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Columbus</CityName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>432101016</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1960 Kenny Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OH03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>158Y</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>1N20</Code>
<Name>R&amp;RA CARES Act DEFC N</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>010N2021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[R&RA CARES Act DEFC N]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This EAGER project is to explore the fundamental mechanisms that can enable the rapid transformation of pop-up origami structures from a 2D extremely packed state to a 3D state. The fundamental understandings can be employed to design a new generation of 3D active thin shell structures, such as medical masks. Pop-up origami structures have been used in some daily consumer products. In these products, the structure can change from one small fully packed near-2D shape to a large 3D shape, through the transition of the multistable states of the origami structure. Inspired by the mechanism of pop-up structures, the proposed work will establish fundamental understandings and mechanics-guide design of origami-based extremely-packed multi-stable and self-assembled pop-up structures for medical masks, which has not been explored before. Once applying an actuation (such as a small force) to overcome the energy barrier, the structure can self-assemble and pop up from a small-volume extremely-packed 2D shape to a 3D shape, such as a full-size mask. The initial fully extremely packed shape can facilitate easy transportation and portability. For example, a dozen of masks could be folded and packed into the size of a gum pack.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>PI Zhao is involved in the research task on developing numerical platform to systemetically investigate the foldability of the ring origami structures:</p> <p><em>Mechanisms and </em><em>mechanics-guided design of </em><em>origami-based multi-stable pop-up structures.&nbsp;</em>We studied the principle in such pop-up origami structures. Our hypothesis is that the transition between two stable states is facilitated by a twisting deformation. We proposed and study different ring geomemetries incudling cibular, elliptical, rectangular, and triangular shpaes and investigate how the geometry can affect the energy landscape and the folding/deployment paths. Based on the learned principle, we further conducted the simulation-based design of extremely-packed multi-stable and self-assembled pop-up structures with the desired face-mask geometry.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The fowlling outcomes have been achieved during the award period.</p> <p>&bull;<span> </span>Understood how the geometric parameters affects the foldability and stability of ring origami.&nbsp;&bull;<span> </span>Understood folding of ring origami for geometries including circular, elliptical, rounded rectangular, and triangular shapes.&bull;<span> </span>Introduced a theoretical model based on the rod model to capture the ring folding behavior.&bull;<span> </span>Designed and fabricated ring assemblies.&bull;<span> </span>Designed ring origami with surface membrane for functional foldable / deployable structures.&bull;<span> </span>Designed and fabricated ring electronic devices for foldable /wearable electronics.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/25/2021<br>      Modified by: Ruike Renee&nbsp;Zhao</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This EAGER project is to explore the fundamental mechanisms that can enable the rapid transformation of pop-up origami structures from a 2D extremely packed state to a 3D state. The fundamental understandings can be employed to design a new generation of 3D active thin shell structures, such as medical masks. Pop-up origami structures have been used in some daily consumer products. In these products, the structure can change from one small fully packed near-2D shape to a large 3D shape, through the transition of the multistable states of the origami structure. Inspired by the mechanism of pop-up structures, the proposed work will establish fundamental understandings and mechanics-guide design of origami-based extremely-packed multi-stable and self-assembled pop-up structures for medical masks, which has not been explored before. Once applying an actuation (such as a small force) to overcome the energy barrier, the structure can self-assemble and pop up from a small-volume extremely-packed 2D shape to a 3D shape, such as a full-size mask. The initial fully extremely packed shape can facilitate easy transportation and portability. For example, a dozen of masks could be folded and packed into the size of a gum pack.     PI Zhao is involved in the research task on developing numerical platform to systemetically investigate the foldability of the ring origami structures:  Mechanisms and mechanics-guided design of origami-based multi-stable pop-up structures. We studied the principle in such pop-up origami structures. Our hypothesis is that the transition between two stable states is facilitated by a twisting deformation. We proposed and study different ring geomemetries incudling cibular, elliptical, rectangular, and triangular shpaes and investigate how the geometry can affect the energy landscape and the folding/deployment paths. Based on the learned principle, we further conducted the simulation-based design of extremely-packed multi-stable and self-assembled pop-up structures with the desired face-mask geometry.     The fowlling outcomes have been achieved during the award period.  &bull; Understood how the geometric parameters affects the foldability and stability of ring origami. &bull; Understood folding of ring origami for geometries including circular, elliptical, rounded rectangular, and triangular shapes.&bull; Introduced a theoretical model based on the rod model to capture the ring folding behavior.&bull; Designed and fabricated ring assemblies.&bull; Designed ring origami with surface membrane for functional foldable / deployable structures.&bull; Designed and fabricated ring electronic devices for foldable /wearable electronics.       Last Modified: 09/25/2021       Submitted by: Ruike Renee Zhao]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
