<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID – Impacts of COVID-19 on the Geoscience Enterprise:  How Permanent Will Academic Program and Workforce Changes Be?]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>159028.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>397977</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>RISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div of Res, Innovation, Synergies, &amp; Edu</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Brandon Jones</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mbjones@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924713</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The rapid onset of the COVID-19 pandemic and the sudden dramatic actions taken by society to protect public health have led to significant economic and social disruption of indeterminant duration. This one-year project by the American Geological Institute seeks to capture the nature and extent of the impact of COVID-19 responses on the geoscience workforce and geoscience academic programs. It will also track those changes through the period when businesses, educational institutions, and citizens resume in-person interactions. This longitudinal study aims to understand how geoscience employers and educational institutions are changing their workplace and instructional environments. It will also seek to discover which of the implemented changes to normal operations will be remain in place once institutions and companies resume pre-COVID-19 operations. Broader impacts of the work will help academic institutions, employers, and decision makers in geoscience-related fields move forward effectively in the potentially changed post-COVID environment. It will also help improve response- and recovery-planning for future crises. Although focusing on a single scientific and economic sector, additional broader impacts of the project will be an increased understanding of the short and long-term impacts of crises to the workforce and on education and the private sector, as well as economic impacts for supply chains and workforce/educational institution resilience. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This study conducted by the American Geophysical Institute (AGI) will establish a baseline of pre- and post- COVID-19 workplace environments and an understanding of the types, magnitude and permanency of changes to geoscience academic programs and departments, employers, and the workforce. The project’s results will be useful for informing future areas of research as well as those related to human-technology interfaces and new approaches in learning and teaching within digital environments. To conduct the project, the investigators will collect and follow, over a 52-week period, both publicly available workforce and economic data. This information will be combined with survey results for five cohorts: (1) geoscience employers, (2) geoscience workers (as of start of the crisis), (3) academic faculty, (4) geoscience college and university students, and (5) recent geoscience graduates who graduated between 2014 and 2019. These cohorts will be established by sending invitations to over 800 U.S. degree-granting and community-college geoscience programs, to AGI's member societies membership networks, and to AGI’s contact network of over 124,000 geoscience professionals. AGI will survey each participant at least every other week to assess employment status and/or status of employees, work environment, work activities, and challenges faced. In addition, AGI will utilize the publicly available economic and workforce data to provide a broader context to the macroeconomic dynamics of the survey results. Weekly data briefs will be published on the AGI website to report on the ongoing state of the geosciences and new insights from the federal and/or survey data. It will also publish a synthesis report that details the changes each of the considered cohorts experienced, including the duration and permanency of changes to the work environment and cohort work status. Reports will examine survey results in the light of reported geoscience employment and economic indicators from federal agencies and assess any lags between federal data and survey responses. The report will be available in hard copy and freely available in digital format on AGI’s website. Digital copies will be sent to all geoscience university and college programs. Summary results of the final report will also be published online, used in conference presentations, and if appropriate, published in peer-reviewed journals.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/22/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/06/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2029570</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Christopher</FirstName>
<LastName>Keane</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Christopher M Keane</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[keane@agiweb.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000227419</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/22/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Leila</FirstName>
<LastName>Gonzales</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Leila M Gonzales</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[lmg@americangeosciences.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000808288</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/22/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>American Geological Institute</Name>
<CityName>ALEXANDRIA</CityName>
<ZipCode>223021507</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7033792480</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4220 KING ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>VA08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>YS5HC7ZF9L24</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>AMERICAN GEOSCIENCES INSTITUTE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[American Geological Institute]]></Name>
<CityName>Alexandria</CityName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>223021502</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4220 King Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>VA08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>0619</Code>
<Text>SPECIAL EMPHASIS PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1574</Code>
<Text>Geophysics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1690</Code>
<Text>EDUCATION/HUMAN RESOURCES,OCE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7699</Code>
<Text>Integrat &amp; Collab Ed &amp; Rsearch</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7700</Code>
<Text>EDUCATIONAL LINKAGES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>097Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Impacts on Existing Activities</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>4444</Code>
<Text>INTERDISCIPLINARY PROPOSALS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002223DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~159028</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~85154</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2022~153795</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The prolonged duration of the COVID-19 pandemic led to significant and unprecedented changes in social, economic, and educational systems worldwide, including the United States. Frequent surges in virus activity caused ongoing disruptions to educational and business sectors. Academic institutions and businesses adapted by integrating virtual technologies and creating more flexible working and learning models to ensure continuity despite the volatility.</p> <p>In May 2020, the American Geosciences Institute initiated this study to investigate the short-term and long-term effects of the pandemic on the geoscience workforce and academic programs. The project's goal was to establish a baseline of pre-pandemic and post-pandemic work and learning environments to gauge the magnitude and permanence of pandemic-related changes. Initially planned as a 12-month study, the project eventually expanded into a multi-year investigation that concluded in December 2022. Primary data were collected through a multi-cohort longitudinal survey conducted over 2020-2022, focusing on five primary cohorts: geoscience employers, non-academic geoscientists, academic faculty, geoscience students, and recent geoscience graduates. Additional insights were gained in 2022 through oral history interviews and a three-part webinar series, gathering best practices from study cohorts on how they managed pandemic-related impacts.</p> <p>The study explored changes in work and instructional environments, including how research conduct evolved, what new opportunities emerged from the pandemic, what skills and knowledge gaps affected post-2020 geoscience graduates, and what strategies were implemented to address these gaps. By providing insights into the short-term and long-term effects of this crisis that necessitated rapid structural workforce changes, the study aimed to assist institutions, employers, and decision-makers in improving response and recovery planning for future crises of a similar nature. Furthermore, the project sought to inform future areas of research, including those related to new approaches in digital learning and teaching.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <h2>Key Findings</h2> <p>The pandemic brought about widespread disruptions to the geoscience profession, affecting various aspects of academia, employment, and research. Academic departments faced challenges such as budget cuts, staffing issues, limitations on fieldwork and travel, and declines in student enrollment. The rapid shift from in-person to remote instruction led to significant changes in research methods, mainly towards virtual and computational studies, and caused delays in degree completion due to alterations in project tasks, and course availability.</p> <p>Employers struggled with financial and staffing impacts, regulatory constraints, supply chain problems, and limitations on travel and field activities. Hiring and onboarding new employees into virtual working environments presented substantial obstacles, and employers noted skills and knowledge gaps in hires made during the pandemic era. The profession also faced obstacles in fieldwork and laboratory activities, impeded by restrictions and increased health protocols. The swift shift to remote work affected families with increased caregiving responsibilities and led to reduced productivity, imbalanced work/life equilibrium, and supply shortages. Concerns were also raised about workplace safety, job security, and financial stability, particularly among new graduates and students.</p> <p>Within the geosciences, various strategies were employed to adapt to pandemic-related impacts. Instructional methods were modified, including shifting courses to a mix of in-person and online formats, necessitating faculty to redesign curricula. Departments adjusted degree program requirements to accommodate research project delays and restrictions on in-person activities. Many projects shifted focus to literature reviews and computational modeling, while others were redesigned to fit within pandemic constraints.</p> <p>Resourcefulness and technological platforms became key in maintaining progress in work, school, and research. Technology served as a bridge for communication, skill learning, and teamwork on projects. Supportive actions from employers, departments, and faculty were also vital, including providing equipment and financial assistance for the transition to remote work, and allowing flexibility in deadlines and work hours. These measures eased some challenges faced by employees and students, particularly with project delays, supply chain disruptions, and family care responsibilities.</p> <p>The pandemic prompted significant advancements in education, affecting online courses, degree programs, and teaching methodologies. A notable shift towards flexible working and learning arrangements was seen, which revealed both the challenges and benefits of remote and in-office work and learning. Recent graduates encountered gaps in skills and knowledge and had to adjust to new working and learning methods, often engaging in professional development activities to acquire new technical abilities. Hiring trends also saw major changes, including fluctuations in desired skill sets and hiring rates, and adjustments in employee requirements, and differing trends between academic and geoscience employers.</p> <p>The pandemic has brought about lasting transformations in the geosciences, particularly with the incorporation of virtual technologies into working and learning environments. Academic departments have integrated virtual instructional methods to enhance student learning or accommodate those who cannot attend in-person sessions. Employers have also adopted virtual technologies, leading to more flexible work conditions and allowing employees greater leeway in their work location and hours. Beyond the challenges it posed, the pandemic also enabled an increase in technical proficiency across the geosciences, opening new opportunities in virtual work and collaboration that many have seized.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/18/2023<br>      Modified by: Leila&nbsp;M&nbsp;Gonzales</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The prolonged duration of the COVID-19 pandemic led to significant and unprecedented changes in social, economic, and educational systems worldwide, including the United States. Frequent surges in virus activity caused ongoing disruptions to educational and business sectors. Academic institutions and businesses adapted by integrating virtual technologies and creating more flexible working and learning models to ensure continuity despite the volatility.  In May 2020, the American Geosciences Institute initiated this study to investigate the short-term and long-term effects of the pandemic on the geoscience workforce and academic programs. The project's goal was to establish a baseline of pre-pandemic and post-pandemic work and learning environments to gauge the magnitude and permanence of pandemic-related changes. Initially planned as a 12-month study, the project eventually expanded into a multi-year investigation that concluded in December 2022. Primary data were collected through a multi-cohort longitudinal survey conducted over 2020-2022, focusing on five primary cohorts: geoscience employers, non-academic geoscientists, academic faculty, geoscience students, and recent geoscience graduates. Additional insights were gained in 2022 through oral history interviews and a three-part webinar series, gathering best practices from study cohorts on how they managed pandemic-related impacts.  The study explored changes in work and instructional environments, including how research conduct evolved, what new opportunities emerged from the pandemic, what skills and knowledge gaps affected post-2020 geoscience graduates, and what strategies were implemented to address these gaps. By providing insights into the short-term and long-term effects of this crisis that necessitated rapid structural workforce changes, the study aimed to assist institutions, employers, and decision-makers in improving response and recovery planning for future crises of a similar nature. Furthermore, the project sought to inform future areas of research, including those related to new approaches in digital learning and teaching.    Key Findings  The pandemic brought about widespread disruptions to the geoscience profession, affecting various aspects of academia, employment, and research. Academic departments faced challenges such as budget cuts, staffing issues, limitations on fieldwork and travel, and declines in student enrollment. The rapid shift from in-person to remote instruction led to significant changes in research methods, mainly towards virtual and computational studies, and caused delays in degree completion due to alterations in project tasks, and course availability.  Employers struggled with financial and staffing impacts, regulatory constraints, supply chain problems, and limitations on travel and field activities. Hiring and onboarding new employees into virtual working environments presented substantial obstacles, and employers noted skills and knowledge gaps in hires made during the pandemic era. The profession also faced obstacles in fieldwork and laboratory activities, impeded by restrictions and increased health protocols. The swift shift to remote work affected families with increased caregiving responsibilities and led to reduced productivity, imbalanced work/life equilibrium, and supply shortages. Concerns were also raised about workplace safety, job security, and financial stability, particularly among new graduates and students.  Within the geosciences, various strategies were employed to adapt to pandemic-related impacts. Instructional methods were modified, including shifting courses to a mix of in-person and online formats, necessitating faculty to redesign curricula. Departments adjusted degree program requirements to accommodate research project delays and restrictions on in-person activities. Many projects shifted focus to literature reviews and computational modeling, while others were redesigned to fit within pandemic constraints.  Resourcefulness and technological platforms became key in maintaining progress in work, school, and research. Technology served as a bridge for communication, skill learning, and teamwork on projects. Supportive actions from employers, departments, and faculty were also vital, including providing equipment and financial assistance for the transition to remote work, and allowing flexibility in deadlines and work hours. These measures eased some challenges faced by employees and students, particularly with project delays, supply chain disruptions, and family care responsibilities.  The pandemic prompted significant advancements in education, affecting online courses, degree programs, and teaching methodologies. A notable shift towards flexible working and learning arrangements was seen, which revealed both the challenges and benefits of remote and in-office work and learning. Recent graduates encountered gaps in skills and knowledge and had to adjust to new working and learning methods, often engaging in professional development activities to acquire new technical abilities. Hiring trends also saw major changes, including fluctuations in desired skill sets and hiring rates, and adjustments in employee requirements, and differing trends between academic and geoscience employers.  The pandemic has brought about lasting transformations in the geosciences, particularly with the incorporation of virtual technologies into working and learning environments. Academic departments have integrated virtual instructional methods to enhance student learning or accommodate those who cannot attend in-person sessions. Employers have also adopted virtual technologies, leading to more flexible work conditions and allowing employees greater leeway in their work location and hours. Beyond the challenges it posed, the pandemic also enabled an increase in technical proficiency across the geosciences, opening new opportunities in virtual work and collaboration that many have seized.       Last Modified: 09/18/2023       Submitted by: Leila M Gonzales]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
