<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Speech as a modality for airborne transport of virus-laden droplets in the COVID-19 pandemic]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>199369.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>199369</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ron Joslin</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rjoslin@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927030</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This RAPID project will advance the understanding of how infectious diseases are spread from speaking, which is directly relevant to informing decisions regarding social distancing measures in the current COVID-19 pandemic. During regular conversation, small virus-laden droplets are generated in the respiratory and vocal tract. They are then expelled into the surrounding environment as airflow exits the mouth. Larger droplets may impact surfaces in the immediate vicinity, while smaller ones may stay suspended in the air as aerosols for long periods of time. Both types of expiratory droplets pose an infection risk. Larger droplets may land directly on individuals that are in close proximity, while smaller aerosolized particles are capable of traveling longer distances and infecting people much farther away by being inhaled into the respiratory tract. Currently, the range of distances that particles travel when produced by speech, and the resulting infection risk posed to individuals in the immediate (near field) and more distant (far field) vicinity, is not well understood. The potential for increased infection risk due to prolonged speech in indoor environments, where airborne particles may accumulate over time and reach higher concentrations, is also not known. This research proposal aims to answer these questions by performing physical measurements of speech in tandem with numerical modeling of droplet transport to predict infection risks in both the near and far field of an infected speaker.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of this project is to determine how virus-laden droplets are spread during speech. Particular emphasis is placed on investigating specific vocal intonations that produce high velocity bursts of air at the mouth (i.e., fricatives and plosives), which are hypothesized to propel particles over relatively long distances and increase infection risk in both the near and far field. Experimental velocity field measurements of the human mouth jet will be acquired using particle image velocimetry for sustained vowels, fricatives, and plosives, at varying levels of loudness. Separately, aerodynamic particle size spectrometry will measure the droplet size distributions generated by these same utterances. These data will be used to validate and inform an unsteady Reynolds-averaged Navier-Stokes computational fluid dynamics model that adopts an Eulerian-Lagrangian approach to model and quantify droplet dynamics. Coupling the expiratory velocity fields and particle dynamics for specific speech utterances will facilitate predicting the infection risk arising from voiced speech by using viral titer levels and infectious doses for the SARS-CoV-2 virus. Near and far field infection risks will be quantified for both open and confined surroundings, where the competing times scales associated with ventilation, particle settling, and virus inactivation rates, will influence the steady-state particle accumulation. Mitigation strategies to decrease infection risk in indoor environments will also be explored.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/24/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/24/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2029548</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Deborah</FirstName>
<LastName>Brown</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Deborah M Brown</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[dbrown@trudeauinstitute.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000544677</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/24/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Brian</FirstName>
<LastName>Helenbrook</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Brian Helenbrook</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[helenbrk@clarkson.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000183156</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/24/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Andrea</FirstName>
<LastName>Ferro</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Andrea Ferro</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[aferro@clarkson.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000103808</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/24/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Byron</FirstName>
<LastName>Erath</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Byron D Erath</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[berath@clarkson.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000641483</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/24/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Goodarz</FirstName>
<LastName>Ahmadi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Goodarz Ahmadi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ahmadi@clarkson.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000359096</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/24/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Clarkson University</Name>
<CityName>POTSDAM</CityName>
<ZipCode>136761401</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3152686475</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>8 CLARKSON AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>21</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY21</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>SL2PF6R7MRN1</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CLARKSON UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Clarkson University]]></Name>
<CityName>Potsdam</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>136761401</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[8 Clarkson Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>21</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY21</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>158Y</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>1N20</Code>
<Name>R&amp;RA CARES Act DEFC N</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>010N2021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[R&RA CARES Act DEFC N]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~199369</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The mechanics of respiratory droplet emission during speech was explored by directly measuring aerosol size distributions during sustained phonation, as well as the velocity field expirated at the mouth during continous speech.&nbsp;</p> <p>Respiratory droplet emission rates increased with both loudness and frequency of speech. However, this accounted for less than 50% of the variability in emission rates that was observed in a large sample size of participants (N=40). These findings show that there remain unexplored variables that result in emission rates that can vary by up to two orders of magnitude. One subject in the population group was identified as a "superemitter", which was defined as being a statistical outlier in the data.&nbsp;</p> <p>Experimental measruements and computational simulations of the flow field exiting the mouth during both fricative pronunciations and continuous speech highlighted that the expiratory flow field is highly complex. The flow produced by continuous speech was investigated in five subjects. The formation of three distinct flow patterns was observed in the data, which varied with intonation. Namely, the flow exiting the mouth during continuous speech was characterized by transient jets, puffs, and vortex rings. Transient jets and puffs were most prevalent (~90%) while vortex rings arose during the production of plosives, but were characterized by high momentum transport that resulted in the flow field propagating much farther into the surroundings than the other flow structures.</p> <p>The momentum and trajectory of the flow field expelled at the mouth was significantly different from one subject to the next. However, when repeating the same sentences, trial-to-trial variations for each subject were relatively minimal. More detailed investigations related to the stability of the flow exiting the mouth identified that very small variations in the positioning of the lips, tongue, teeth, etc. during speech can result in drastically varying flow behaviors. This occured due to the inherent instability of the flow arising from the divergent orientation of the mouth and lips. This was particularly evident for the production of fricative consonants (such as "f" and "th") where sound is produced by air passing through a narrow constriction at the teeth/lips/tongue before it exits the mouth.</p> <p>The influence of the expiratory velocity fields on respiratory droplet transport was investigated using computational models of particle transport. While larger particles followed a ballstic-like trajectory, particles less than 5 &mu;m in diameter followed the flow patterns. they were found to have the highest concentrations within the near field of the flow, while experiencing limited penetration into the ambient surroudings.</p> <p>This work has direct application to the COVID-19 pandemic, identifying respiratory droplet size distributions, human behaviors that influence the production rate, and the transport mechancis of the flow exiting the mouth. The results of this work are particularly relevant to modeling approaches that seek to predict infection risk. Traditionally, these models rely upon simplified assumptions regarding the flow field expirated at the mouth. In contrast, the work performed under this grant identifies the complex, highly-variable behavior of the flow. In addition, it provides detailed, quantifiable measures of the expiratory flow field. As such, it can yield more realistic prescriptions of the transport mechanics that spread infectious droplets from an individual into the surroundings. These findings can inform public health policy with respect to defining safe distances in indoor environments to mimize infectious disease transmission, as well as improving indoor spaces that aim to improve air quality in commercial and residential environments.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/28/2022<br>      Modified by: Byron&nbsp;D&nbsp;Erath</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The mechanics of respiratory droplet emission during speech was explored by directly measuring aerosol size distributions during sustained phonation, as well as the velocity field expirated at the mouth during continous speech.   Respiratory droplet emission rates increased with both loudness and frequency of speech. However, this accounted for less than 50% of the variability in emission rates that was observed in a large sample size of participants (N=40). These findings show that there remain unexplored variables that result in emission rates that can vary by up to two orders of magnitude. One subject in the population group was identified as a "superemitter", which was defined as being a statistical outlier in the data.   Experimental measruements and computational simulations of the flow field exiting the mouth during both fricative pronunciations and continuous speech highlighted that the expiratory flow field is highly complex. The flow produced by continuous speech was investigated in five subjects. The formation of three distinct flow patterns was observed in the data, which varied with intonation. Namely, the flow exiting the mouth during continuous speech was characterized by transient jets, puffs, and vortex rings. Transient jets and puffs were most prevalent (~90%) while vortex rings arose during the production of plosives, but were characterized by high momentum transport that resulted in the flow field propagating much farther into the surroundings than the other flow structures.  The momentum and trajectory of the flow field expelled at the mouth was significantly different from one subject to the next. However, when repeating the same sentences, trial-to-trial variations for each subject were relatively minimal. More detailed investigations related to the stability of the flow exiting the mouth identified that very small variations in the positioning of the lips, tongue, teeth, etc. during speech can result in drastically varying flow behaviors. This occured due to the inherent instability of the flow arising from the divergent orientation of the mouth and lips. This was particularly evident for the production of fricative consonants (such as "f" and "th") where sound is produced by air passing through a narrow constriction at the teeth/lips/tongue before it exits the mouth.  The influence of the expiratory velocity fields on respiratory droplet transport was investigated using computational models of particle transport. While larger particles followed a ballstic-like trajectory, particles less than 5 &mu;m in diameter followed the flow patterns. they were found to have the highest concentrations within the near field of the flow, while experiencing limited penetration into the ambient surroudings.  This work has direct application to the COVID-19 pandemic, identifying respiratory droplet size distributions, human behaviors that influence the production rate, and the transport mechancis of the flow exiting the mouth. The results of this work are particularly relevant to modeling approaches that seek to predict infection risk. Traditionally, these models rely upon simplified assumptions regarding the flow field expirated at the mouth. In contrast, the work performed under this grant identifies the complex, highly-variable behavior of the flow. In addition, it provides detailed, quantifiable measures of the expiratory flow field. As such, it can yield more realistic prescriptions of the transport mechanics that spread infectious droplets from an individual into the surroundings. These findings can inform public health policy with respect to defining safe distances in indoor environments to mimize infectious disease transmission, as well as improving indoor spaces that aim to improve air quality in commercial and residential environments.       Last Modified: 01/28/2022       Submitted by: Byron D Erath]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
