<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[EAGER: Engineered nano-scale barrier to prevent viral infections]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>299999.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>299999</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EFMA</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Emerging Frontiers &amp; Multidisciplinary Activities</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Alias Smith</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>alismith@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928367</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This project proposes to use in silico simulations to engineer nanoscale, biocompatible, protective barrier that will enhance our first line of defenses - prevention of pathogenic infection from entering and infecting the host. The principal investigator aims to develop a topical method that will enhance protection against virus attachment onto the nasal and oral as well as conjunctival epithelial cells, while preserving normal physiology and biochemistry. The project team will use computer models to engineer delivery devices to produce the optimal particle characteristics to maximally prevent microbial infection. If successful, this project can lead to paradigm changing alternatives to reducing public health risk to air borne infections like COVID-19 and seasonal flu which may be associated with devastating effects on the United States and World economy. The proposed approach will be swiftly conducted to present realistic solutions that may be useable in the face of this COVID-19 pandemic as well as future flu viruses of similar magnitude.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research will fundamentally contribute to modeling the interactions between viral membranes and nanoscale barriers. The production of an innovative nanoscale biodegradable barrier may reduce the socioeconomic and public health burden significantly by lowering the risk of viral infection during the flu season or pandemics. The project team comprise of an interdisciplinary team that include engineers, ophthalmologists, molecular biologist, virologist and pharmacologist to explore a problem that could have a tremendous impact on the way we respond to seasonal flu or pandemics. Besides the potential benefits to reduce COVID-19 and influenza related deaths in the US and worldwide, the proposed work will afford us the opportunity to train engineering and biomedical students in a highly interdisciplinary research activity.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/28/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/28/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2029677</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
<LastName>Humayun</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mark S Humayun</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[humayun@usc.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000371509</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/28/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gianluca</FirstName>
<LastName>Lazzi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gianluca Lazzi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[lazzi@usc.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000493205</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/28/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Southern California</Name>
<CityName>LOS ANGELES</CityName>
<ZipCode>900894304</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2137407762</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3720 S FLOWER ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[FL 3]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>37</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA37</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>G88KLJR3KYT5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF SOUTHERN CALIFORNIA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Southern California]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>900890001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>37</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA37</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>158y</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>1N20</Code>
<Name>R&amp;RA CARES Act DEFC N</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>010N2021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[R&RA CARES Act DEFC N]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~299999</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The COVID-19 pandemic has dramatically impacted the way humans live, including costing many lives. There is a need for a topical barrier that enhances the largest defense mechanism, the mucocutaneous barrier, to prevent SARS CoV-2 attachment onto susceptible cells in the eyes, nose, and mouth. To address this challenge, this project focused on engineering a nanoscale biocompatible coating capable of enhancing the lining of the nose and mouth to prevent viral and microbial infectivity and transmissibility across populations. The first aim of the project was to find the best features for the nano-formulation barrier to provide the best protection against viruses within the nose. The second aim evaluated the efficacy of the barrier to prevent viral infection of the cells in the nose.</p> <p>The project successfully developed a 3D-model of the nasal cavity that can be used to perform other investigations on nasal products in the nasal cavity. Based on computer simulations, the best specification for the nasal barrier and its delivery spray were identified. &nbsp;This model is useful in predicting where viral droplets of different sizes land within the nasal cavity so that the susceptible areas can be targeted for protection by the barrier. In addition, the project also found the barrier is able to prevent the entry of dyes, lentiviruses, and SARS CoV-2 pseudotyped viruses into mammalian cells. The barrier also inactivates the viruses and prevents them from re-infecting other mammalian cells. The barrier can be applied to susceptible regions in the nasal cavity to prevent the infectivity of respiratory enveloped viruses like SARS-CoV-2. With the guidance of the 3D- simulations, the recommended product parameters for efficient delivery and optimal protection of susceptible regions of the nasal cavity have been identified. In summary, this project has identified the barrier and the key characteristics of the barrier needed for optimal delivery to the needed sites in the nasal cavity to prevent respiratory viral infections. Next steps, include pre-clinical testing for translation to clinical use.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/28/2022<br>      Modified by: Mark&nbsp;S&nbsp;Humayun</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The COVID-19 pandemic has dramatically impacted the way humans live, including costing many lives. There is a need for a topical barrier that enhances the largest defense mechanism, the mucocutaneous barrier, to prevent SARS CoV-2 attachment onto susceptible cells in the eyes, nose, and mouth. To address this challenge, this project focused on engineering a nanoscale biocompatible coating capable of enhancing the lining of the nose and mouth to prevent viral and microbial infectivity and transmissibility across populations. The first aim of the project was to find the best features for the nano-formulation barrier to provide the best protection against viruses within the nose. The second aim evaluated the efficacy of the barrier to prevent viral infection of the cells in the nose.  The project successfully developed a 3D-model of the nasal cavity that can be used to perform other investigations on nasal products in the nasal cavity. Based on computer simulations, the best specification for the nasal barrier and its delivery spray were identified.  This model is useful in predicting where viral droplets of different sizes land within the nasal cavity so that the susceptible areas can be targeted for protection by the barrier. In addition, the project also found the barrier is able to prevent the entry of dyes, lentiviruses, and SARS CoV-2 pseudotyped viruses into mammalian cells. The barrier also inactivates the viruses and prevents them from re-infecting other mammalian cells. The barrier can be applied to susceptible regions in the nasal cavity to prevent the infectivity of respiratory enveloped viruses like SARS-CoV-2. With the guidance of the 3D- simulations, the recommended product parameters for efficient delivery and optimal protection of susceptible regions of the nasal cavity have been identified. In summary, this project has identified the barrier and the key characteristics of the barrier needed for optimal delivery to the needed sites in the nasal cavity to prevent respiratory viral infections. Next steps, include pre-clinical testing for translation to clinical use.          Last Modified: 08/28/2022       Submitted by: Mark S Humayun]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
