<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID/Collaborative Research: Investigating Attitudinal and Behavioral Changes in US Households Before, During, and After the COVID-19 Pandemic]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>56334.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>72334</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Yueyue Fan</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>yfan@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924453</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This Rapid Response Research (RAPID) grant will investigate how American households have adapted their attitudes and behaviors in response to the COVID-19 pandemic with the end goal to help a rapid and stable recovery. Virtually overnight, a large fraction of American households has transitioned from a reality of long commutes, in-person classes and business meetings, and in-store shopping to one of telecommuting, online classes and business meetings, and online shopping – even for groceries. Many of these changes were happening already, but COVID-19 has pressed the fast-forward button. Not all American households have been affected in a similar fashion, however, bringing about many questions. In particular, this grant will help answer four questions. (1) How are different socio-economic segments of the U.S. population changing their attitudes and behaviors during the COVID-19 pandemic? (2) To what extent are current (during pandemic) behaviors likely to persist after the pandemic? (3)  To what extent do behaviors return to before pandemic patterns within the one year time period of this study? (4) How do attitudes and perceptions evolve over the course of the COVID-19 pandemic and beyond?&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research will be pursued through a nationwide, multi-wave survey. The survey includes retrospective questions related to attitudes and behavior before the pandemic (e.g., being risk averse, attitudes toward the economy, environment, technology), and sections about current attitudes and preferences including activity and travel behavior (e.g., scheduling, commuting and discretionary travel choices pre-, during, and post COVID-19 as well as long-distance travel), socio-demographics (e.g., employment type and status, and household composition), and social networking and social behavior. Using a combination of recruiting strategies (Facebook ad and targeted emailing), the grant will help collect at least 5,000 responses, disproportionately stratified across the nation, and distributed across a variety of socio-demographics (e.g., household types, urban vs. rural, income, employment status during COVID-19). Follow-up waves will be conducted 3, 6, and 9 months after the first version of the survey has been taken to track the evolution of attitudes and behaviors over time.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/15/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/07/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2029962</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ram</FirstName>
<LastName>Pendyala</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ram Pendyala</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ram.pendyala@asu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000081071</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/15/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Deborah</FirstName>
<LastName>Salon</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Deborah Salon</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[dsalon@asu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000824944</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/15/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Arizona State University</Name>
<CityName>TEMPE</CityName>
<ZipCode>852813670</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4809655479</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>660 S MILL AVENUE STE 204</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AZ04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NTLHJXM55KZ6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ARIZONA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Arizona State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Tempe</CityName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>852876011</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[PO Box 876011]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AZ04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>158Y</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1631</Code>
<Text>CIS-Civil Infrastructure Syst</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>029E</Code>
<Text>INFRASTRUCTURE SYSTEMS MGT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>036E</Code>
<Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>116E</Code>
<Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR UNDERGRADS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9102</Code>
<Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9231</Code>
<Text>SUPPL FOR UNDERGRAD RES ASSIST</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>1N20</Code>
<Name>R&amp;RA CARES Act DEFC N</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>010N2021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[R&RA CARES Act DEFC N]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~56334</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~16000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Human behavior is notoriously difficult to change, but a disruption of the magnitude of the COVID-19 pandemic has the potential to bring about long-term behavioral changes. During the pandemic, people were forced to experience new ways of interacting, working, learning, shopping, traveling, and eating meals. A critical question going forward is how these experiences have actually changed preferences and habits in ways that might persist after the pandemic ends. This NSF project supported the development, deployment, collection, cleaning, processing, and sharing of a national-level, three-wave panel survey that aims to shed light on this question. The final clean datasets are publicly available so that anyone can access and analyze them.</p> <p>The first survey wave includes responses from 8,152 individuals collected between late June 2020 and early June 2021, with most responses collected between July 2020 and October 2020. Wave 2 includes responses from 2,566 Wave 1 respondents collected approximately four months after they completed Wave 1. Wave 3 includes responses from 2,424 Wave 1 respondents collected in October and November of 2021. All survey waves are weighted to be representative of the U.S. adult population.</p> <p>Key results include evidence on how much U.S. adults expect their own post-pandemic choices to differ from their pre-pandemic lifestyles in the areas of telecommuting, car commuting, transit use, restaurant patronage, air travel, uptake of walking and biking, online shopping, vehicle ownership, and home location. We find that the post-pandemic "new normal" will feature approximately a doubling of telecommuting and associated reductions in both car commuting and transit commuting, compared to the pre-pandemic period. We also find evidence that demand for both business air travel and restaurant patronage will continue to be lower than pre-pandemic norms, as well as evidence that people may walk more than they used to. Although a sizable increase in online shopping for groceries is expected to persist, we do not find evidence that the pandemic experience dramatically reshaped non-grocery online shopping trends.</p> <p>Further, we also do not find evidence that the pandemic experience resulted in large changes in vehicle ownership or where people choose to live. This may be because these changes may take longer to occur, and therefore may not be evident yet in this dataset even if they are happening.</p> <p>Lastly, we do not find large differences across the three waves of the survey in these key findings about expectations for the future across the survey waves. This is remarkable, since the data collection period spanned more than one year during a highly tumultuous period in U.S. history. The data collected in this project is publicly and permanently available on the ASU Dataverse (https://dataverse.asu.edu/dataverse/covidfuture). This project resulted in more than 7 publications and more than 28 presentations / seminars.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/14/2022<br>      Modified by: Deborah&nbsp;Salon</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2029962/2029962_10670969_1652564845695_ProjectOutcomes-Figure2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2029962/2029962_10670969_1652564845695_ProjectOutcomes-Figure2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Project Website"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2029962/2029962_10670969_1652564845695_ProjectOutcomes-Figure2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Project Website"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Screenshot of project website</div> <div class="imageCredit">COVID Future Survey</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Deborah&nbsp;Salon</div> <div class="imageTitle">Project Website</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2029962/2029962_10670969_1652564274512_ProjectOutcomes-Figure1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2029962/2029962_10670969_1652564274512_ProjectOutcomes-Figure1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Survey Timeline"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2029962/2029962_10670969_1652564274512_ProjectOutcomes-Figure1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Survey Timeline"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Timeline of the three survey waves along with major pandemic milestones</div> <div class="imageCredit">COVID Future Survey</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Deborah&nbsp;Salon</div> <div class="imageTitle">Survey Timeline</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Human behavior is notoriously difficult to change, but a disruption of the magnitude of the COVID-19 pandemic has the potential to bring about long-term behavioral changes. During the pandemic, people were forced to experience new ways of interacting, working, learning, shopping, traveling, and eating meals. A critical question going forward is how these experiences have actually changed preferences and habits in ways that might persist after the pandemic ends. This NSF project supported the development, deployment, collection, cleaning, processing, and sharing of a national-level, three-wave panel survey that aims to shed light on this question. The final clean datasets are publicly available so that anyone can access and analyze them.  The first survey wave includes responses from 8,152 individuals collected between late June 2020 and early June 2021, with most responses collected between July 2020 and October 2020. Wave 2 includes responses from 2,566 Wave 1 respondents collected approximately four months after they completed Wave 1. Wave 3 includes responses from 2,424 Wave 1 respondents collected in October and November of 2021. All survey waves are weighted to be representative of the U.S. adult population.  Key results include evidence on how much U.S. adults expect their own post-pandemic choices to differ from their pre-pandemic lifestyles in the areas of telecommuting, car commuting, transit use, restaurant patronage, air travel, uptake of walking and biking, online shopping, vehicle ownership, and home location. We find that the post-pandemic "new normal" will feature approximately a doubling of telecommuting and associated reductions in both car commuting and transit commuting, compared to the pre-pandemic period. We also find evidence that demand for both business air travel and restaurant patronage will continue to be lower than pre-pandemic norms, as well as evidence that people may walk more than they used to. Although a sizable increase in online shopping for groceries is expected to persist, we do not find evidence that the pandemic experience dramatically reshaped non-grocery online shopping trends.  Further, we also do not find evidence that the pandemic experience resulted in large changes in vehicle ownership or where people choose to live. This may be because these changes may take longer to occur, and therefore may not be evident yet in this dataset even if they are happening.  Lastly, we do not find large differences across the three waves of the survey in these key findings about expectations for the future across the survey waves. This is remarkable, since the data collection period spanned more than one year during a highly tumultuous period in U.S. history. The data collected in this project is publicly and permanently available on the ASU Dataverse (https://dataverse.asu.edu/dataverse/covidfuture). This project resulted in more than 7 publications and more than 28 presentations / seminars.       Last Modified: 05/14/2022       Submitted by: Deborah Salon]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
