<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Exploring Causes and Cures for COVID-19 through Improved Access to Biomedical Research]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>186227.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>186227</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SMA</Abbreviation>
<LongName>SBE Off Of Multidisciplinary Activities</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Mary Feeney</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mfeeney@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927197</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Resolving the COVID-19 pandemic, and future crises, demands rapid and comprehensive access to pertinent research knowledge. This project promotes the progress of science to advance national health and welfare by enhancing the nation’s capability to understand the related global research literature and to identify findings in disparate fields that are relevant for combating the virus. This body of relevant literature comprises tens of thousands of biomedical articles and is growing explosively each week. This project will provide means to access vital findings and to develop tools to discover connections across disciplines and among causes, biomarkers, conditions, and treatments for COVID-19. The project will provide bi-weekly summaries of key findings in the biomedical literature pertaining to COVID-19 on an open website. The information will be arranged by topic, country, and organization, so that it can be easily accessed by researchers and clinicians. The project will also uncover connections across research domains that could identify novel treatments. Both approaches strive to connect disparate research findings and innovative developments. The first approach profiles the directly relevant research literature to make findings more accessible and allow researchers to discover complementary knowledge. Literature Based Discovery methods, using machine learning and related methods, help bridge distinct research findings. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will make available a spectrum of research knowledge to help develop prevention and treatment for corona viruses. Literature Based Discovery methods serve to extract key components of a target domain and then explore other distinct domains for potential causes, vital biomechanisms, and treatments that could be repurposed. This approach seeks to discover previously unrecognized commonalities in research on other viruses that affect key physiological systems susceptible to the target viruses (for example respiratory and immune systems). Such commonalities, such as in ways that different viruses affect particular biosystems, may open doors to recognition of co-morbidities or development of novel treatments. The project will advance understanding of text mining and scientific discovery. The work will employ human judges to classify a moderate number of abstract records on multiple dimensions (such as virus type, physiological mechanisms addressed, causes, drug types, and other treatment modalities), then use software to auto-classify the 30,000 and growing COVID-19-related research articles. Clues emerging from such classification could open windows into other biomedical research and clinical studies to seek novel approaches. By making these data immediately and publicly available, the project will serve the community of those researching and practicing in the area and accelerate scientific discovery around the coronavirus.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/26/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/26/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2029673</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jan</FirstName>
<LastName>Youtie</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jan Youtie</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jan.youtie@innovate.gatech.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000342944</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/26/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alan</FirstName>
<LastName>Porter</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alan L Porter</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[aporter@searchtech.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000545566</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/26/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Search Technology Inc</Name>
<CityName>PEACHTREE CORNERS</CityName>
<ZipCode>300923328</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7704411457</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>6025 THE CORNERS PARKWAY</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[STE 202]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>PVTUFN472MM8</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SEARCH TECHNOLOGY, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>VGMCMN6LEFX5</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Search Technology Inc]]></Name>
<CityName>Peachtree Corners</CityName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>300923328</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[6025 The Corners Parkway, STE 20]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>125Y</Code>
<Text>Science of Science</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7626</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE OF SCIENCE POLICY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~186227</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project sought to compile, analyze, and represent COVID-19 research to make it more accessible to researchers and other interested parties.&nbsp;</p> <p>We provide three sets of findings.&nbsp; The first two mainly offer substantive intellectual merit, while the third is methodological:</p> <ol> <li>1) Research profiles of the COVID-19 core literature -- with dig-down capabilities.</li> <li>2) A recommender system to identify relevant research records found outside that core literature.by scanning the full PubMed database.</li> <li>3) A companion goal to advance "intelligent bibliometrics" methods to enhance retrieval and representation of related research.&nbsp;</li> </ol> <p>This project applied a standard, replicable search strategy to extract PubMed (MEDLINE) records pertaining to COVID-19 research.&nbsp; We created a public dataset using this search strategy.&nbsp; Retention of the sequence of biweekly, then monthly, searches provides a rich resource for examination of the hyper-exponential research growth.&nbsp; We continue to use these data to model scientific/technical emergence.</p> <p>We constructed a public dashboard to present that COVID-19-related research compiled from PubMed.&nbsp; As of October 20, 2021, we profile 134,620 such research paper abstract records.&nbsp; The dashboard offers trend analyses, geo-mapping of results by country, top author-affiliated organizations, top sponsors based on funding acknowledgements, and customized categories for grouping PubMed records. The dashboard can be found at:&nbsp;<a href="https://searchtechnology.github.io/VPDashboard/">https://searchtechnology.github.io/VPDashboard/</a> with a video demo explaining how to navigate it. The image here called "COVID Results Dashboard" shows one of seven available ways to break out the research.</p> <p>We developed an AI-enabled recommender system drawing on Literature-Based Discovery (LBD) concepts. This can detect articles relating to a subtopic (identified in COVID publication records) in the entirety of the PubMed database, without using explicit keywords or MeSH terms to identify these articles.&nbsp; In other words, it guides one to pertinent research outside the COVID-19 dataset.&nbsp; Human review of the results of the recommender system by biomedical and library scientists was supportive.</p> <p>We acquired and analyzed COVID-19 clinical trials by overlaying trials data onto MeSH term similarity maps.&nbsp; Clinical trial analyses draw on LBD and knowledge searching concepts. A link to a COVID-19 vaccine "bullseye" landscape map is available at:</p> <p><a href="https://sites.google.com/searchtech.com/covidproject/home">https://sites.google.com/searchtech.com/covidproject/home</a>.&nbsp; The image here entitled "COVID Project Dashboard" shows this.</p> <p>Porter et al. (2020) [https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/frma.2020.594060] present key project results.&nbsp; We include two images from this article here.&nbsp; "COVID Emergent Topics" compares the prevalence of the most prominently emergent topics in corona virus research through 2019, to COVID-19 research in 2020, through July 1.&nbsp; "Topic Evolution Pathways in COVID-19 Research" illustrates analyses to track relationships among, and heritage of, research topics in the domain.</p> <p>Shapira et al. (2020) [<a href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.12.06.413682">https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.12.06.413682</a>] report on the extent to which scientific, social science, and humanities fields have pivoted to topics related to COVID-19.&nbsp; We observe a bimodal distribution of clinical trials in terms of movement from prior work to COVID-19 trials; some trials reflect prior COVID-related research while most trials represent substantial movement from unrelated prior investigatory work.</p> <p>We also contribute to "intelligent bibliometrics."&nbsp; This emerging methodology combines bibliometrics, text analyses, and Artificial Intelligence (AI) tools to assess R&amp;D data in target domains. The novel contribution here is to, first, combine an optimized Principal Components Analysis (PCA) factor (cluster) result, with knowledge modeling, to categorize research documents in the target domain (COVID-19 related research). &nbsp;Second, we then identify related research anywhere in the full PubMed database.&nbsp; This provides an LBD system to recommend top articles to which a researcher should attend).&nbsp;</p> <p>Regarding Broader Impact, our COVID-19 dashboards and recommender system aim to help researchers access relevant research results to help overcome the current pandemic and develop tools to defend against future viral attacks.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/23/2021<br>      Modified by: Alan&nbsp;L&nbsp;Porter</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2029673/2029673_10680903_1634665577800_COVIDProjectDashboard--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2029673/2029673_10680903_1634665577800_COVIDProjectDashboard--rgov-800width.jpg" title="COVID Project Dashboard"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2029673/2029673_10680903_1634665577800_COVIDProjectDashboard--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="COVID Project Dashboard"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">COVID-19 Research Profiling Dashboard</div> <div class="imageCredit">Search Technology, Inc.</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Alan&nbsp;L&nbsp;Porter</div> <div class="imageTitle">COVID Project Dashboard</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2029673/2029673_10680903_1634665956838_Figure4.TopicEvolutionPathwaysinCOVID-19Research--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2029673/2029673_10680903_1634665956838_Figure4.TopicEvolutionPathwaysinCOVID-19Research--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Topic Evolution Pathways in COVID-19 Research"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2029673/2029673_10680903_1634665956838_Figure4.TopicEvolutionPathwaysinCOVID-19Research--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Topic Evolution Pathways in COVID-19 Research"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Topic Evolution based on 47,607 core PubMed COVID-19 search as of July 1, 2020</div> <div class="imageCredit">Yi Zhang</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Alan&nbsp;L&nbsp;Porter</div> <div class="imageTitle">Topic Evolution Pathways in COVID-19 Research</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2029673/2029673_10680903_1634666225883_Table3.COVIDEmergentTopics--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2029673/2029673_10680903_1634666225883_Table3.COVIDEmergentTopics--rgov-800width.jpg" title="COVID Emergent Topics"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2029673/2029673_10680903_1634666225883_Table3.COVIDEmergentTopics--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="COVID Emergent Topics"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Emergent Topics prevalence in COVID-19 related research through 2019 vs. January through June, 2020</div> <div class="imageCredit">Search Technology, Inc.</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Alan&nbsp;L&nbsp;Porter</div> <div class="imageTitle">COVID Emergent Topics</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2029673/2029673_10680903_1635019201503_COVIDResultsDashboard10-20-2021--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2029673/2029673_10680903_1635019201503_COVIDResultsDashboard10-20-2021--rgov-800width.jpg" title="COVID Results Dashboard"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2029673/2029673_10680903_1635019201503_COVIDResultsDashboard10-20-2021--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="COVID Results Dashboard"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">1 of 7 COVID Results Dashboard options, here showing top U.S. research publication breakouts</div> <div class="imageCredit">Search Technology, Inc.</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Alan&nbsp;L&nbsp;Porter</div> <div class="imageTitle">COVID Results Dashboard</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project sought to compile, analyze, and represent COVID-19 research to make it more accessible to researchers and other interested parties.   We provide three sets of findings.  The first two mainly offer substantive intellectual merit, while the third is methodological:  1) Research profiles of the COVID-19 core literature -- with dig-down capabilities. 2) A recommender system to identify relevant research records found outside that core literature.by scanning the full PubMed database. 3) A companion goal to advance "intelligent bibliometrics" methods to enhance retrieval and representation of related research.    This project applied a standard, replicable search strategy to extract PubMed (MEDLINE) records pertaining to COVID-19 research.  We created a public dataset using this search strategy.  Retention of the sequence of biweekly, then monthly, searches provides a rich resource for examination of the hyper-exponential research growth.  We continue to use these data to model scientific/technical emergence.  We constructed a public dashboard to present that COVID-19-related research compiled from PubMed.  As of October 20, 2021, we profile 134,620 such research paper abstract records.  The dashboard offers trend analyses, geo-mapping of results by country, top author-affiliated organizations, top sponsors based on funding acknowledgements, and customized categories for grouping PubMed records. The dashboard can be found at: https://searchtechnology.github.io/VPDashboard/ with a video demo explaining how to navigate it. The image here called "COVID Results Dashboard" shows one of seven available ways to break out the research.  We developed an AI-enabled recommender system drawing on Literature-Based Discovery (LBD) concepts. This can detect articles relating to a subtopic (identified in COVID publication records) in the entirety of the PubMed database, without using explicit keywords or MeSH terms to identify these articles.  In other words, it guides one to pertinent research outside the COVID-19 dataset.  Human review of the results of the recommender system by biomedical and library scientists was supportive.  We acquired and analyzed COVID-19 clinical trials by overlaying trials data onto MeSH term similarity maps.  Clinical trial analyses draw on LBD and knowledge searching concepts. A link to a COVID-19 vaccine "bullseye" landscape map is available at:  https://sites.google.com/searchtech.com/covidproject/home.  The image here entitled "COVID Project Dashboard" shows this.  Porter et al. (2020) [https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/frma.2020.594060] present key project results.  We include two images from this article here.  "COVID Emergent Topics" compares the prevalence of the most prominently emergent topics in corona virus research through 2019, to COVID-19 research in 2020, through July 1.  "Topic Evolution Pathways in COVID-19 Research" illustrates analyses to track relationships among, and heritage of, research topics in the domain.  Shapira et al. (2020) [https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.12.06.413682] report on the extent to which scientific, social science, and humanities fields have pivoted to topics related to COVID-19.  We observe a bimodal distribution of clinical trials in terms of movement from prior work to COVID-19 trials; some trials reflect prior COVID-related research while most trials represent substantial movement from unrelated prior investigatory work.  We also contribute to "intelligent bibliometrics."  This emerging methodology combines bibliometrics, text analyses, and Artificial Intelligence (AI) tools to assess R&amp;D data in target domains. The novel contribution here is to, first, combine an optimized Principal Components Analysis (PCA) factor (cluster) result, with knowledge modeling, to categorize research documents in the target domain (COVID-19 related research).  Second, we then identify related research anywhere in the full PubMed database.  This provides an LBD system to recommend top articles to which a researcher should attend).   Regarding Broader Impact, our COVID-19 dashboards and recommender system aim to help researchers access relevant research results to help overcome the current pandemic and develop tools to defend against future viral attacks.          Last Modified: 10/23/2021       Submitted by: Alan L Porter]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
