<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID/Collaborative Research: Quantifying Social Media Data for Improved Modeling of Mitigation Strategies for the COVID-19 Pandemic]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>141527.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>141527</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Eva Kanso</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ekanso@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032920000</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This Rapid Response Research (RAPID) grant will support research that will contribute new knowledge related to modeling social behavior and community activity during the COVID-19 pandemic, as well as future pandemics with COVID-19 characteristics.  The model focuses on compliance with mitigation strategies and public health guidelines, thus enabling the selection of policies that are most effective in promoting both the progress of science and advancing national health and prosperity. Various pandemic models are currently being used to predict the spread of a virus and establish which mitigation strategies are the most effective. These models are heavily based on assumptions and may include an oversimplified reality of how populations react and behave. This research will provide needed knowledge and methods for the development of a model of how individuals in the U.S. react to certain mitigation strategies, such as social-distancing, stay-at-home orders, quarantines, and travel advisories, by mining and analyzing social media data during the COVID-19 crisis. This enhanced modeling approach and its resultant model will be of great value to disaster response managers and policy/decision makers to understand human social behavior. This work allows assessment of the effectiveness of mitigation strategies and public health guidelines during pandemics (and other crises). This project will also form the basis of a publicly available case study suitable for university level students that can be widely incorporated in courses. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Although individual-based and homogeneous mixing pandemic models provide useful insights and predictive capabilities within a range of possibilities, they are highly sensitive to people’s actions. This research aims to provide an enhanced approach to model social behavior and community activity during a pandemic in terms of compliance with mitigation strategies and public health guidelines. Social media data present a brief window of opportunity for research on how, and to what extent, the public does or does not comply with the recommended mitigation strategies and public health guidelines. The research team will collect real-time data from social media related to COVID19-exposed regional populations in the U.S. The data will be analyzed using machine learning techniques to identify non-mutually exclusive clusters of people based on similarity of their demographic, geographic, and time information, and establish relationships among clusters. The analyzed data will form the basis of a data-driven multi-paradigm simulation model that captures changes in public sentiment over time, quantifies the resistance/compliance with mitigation strategies and health guidelines, and gauges overall effectiveness of various mitigation strategies and advice over time.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/30/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/30/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2029739</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Konstantinos</FirstName>
<LastName>Mykoniatis</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Konstantinos Mykoniatis</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mzk0141@auburn.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000823892</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/30/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alice</FirstName>
<LastName>Smith</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alice E Smith</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[smithae@auburn.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000399261</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/30/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Auburn University</Name>
<CityName>AUBURN</CityName>
<ZipCode>368490001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3348444438</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>321-A INGRAM HALL</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Alabama</StateName>
<StateCode>AL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AL03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>DMQNDJDHTDG4</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>AUBURN UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Auburn University]]></Name>
<CityName>Auburn</CityName>
<StateCode>AL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>368490001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[345 W Magnolia Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Alabama</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AL03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>158Y</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>034E</Code>
<Text>Dynamical systems</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>1N20</Code>
<Name>R&amp;RA CARES Act DEFC N</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>010N2021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[R&RA CARES Act DEFC N]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~141527</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><div> <p>This research contributed new knowledge related to modeling social behavior and, in particular, opinion change in social media during the COVID-19 pandemic, with applicability to future pandemics with COVID-19 characteristics. The research involved the collection and analysis of Twitter data during the pandemics and the development of a data-driven hybrid simulation model.</p> <p>The data collection resulted in three new large-scale datasets with a total of N=465,764 tweets related to COVID-19 mitigation strategies collected from June 10th, 2020, until April 30th, 2021. The three datasets include 305,015 mask-wearing-related tweets, 12,876 social-distancing-related tweets, and 147,873 quarantine/lockdown-related tweets.</p> <p>The data analysis provided a sentiment-oriented overview of the U.S. public discussion concerning the aforementioned COVID-19-related policies among Twitter users grouped by similar demographic characteristics (e.g., age and gender). More specifically, discussions containing positive sentiment towards mitigation strategies prevailed and revolved around the benefits of the measures and trust of the government, while topics of negative sentiment involved conspiracy theories, skepticism, and distrust of government mandates. It is also notable that discussions among people 19-29 and over 40 years old focus on government officials and political parties, benefits or inefficiency of mitigation measures, and conspiracy theories relatively more often than other demographic groups.</p> <p>The model development focused on simulating the compliance with, and resistance to, mitigation strategies and public health guidelines and investigating the opinion change among different age-gender groups. The simulation model results indicated that the number of regular users, influencers, or super spreaders with specific sentiment can affect users to change opinion towards mitigation strategies. However, bots have no impact on opinion change. A preprocessing framework that can be used as a procedure to label, summarize, and present the topics and sentiments of any dataset of tweets also resulted from this project. This project&rsquo;s data, model, and approaches are publicly available, allowing other researchers to extend or reuse this work. The model and results can also be of great value to disaster response managers and policy/decision makers to understand human social behavior and enable the selection of policies that are most effective in promoting both the progress of science and advancing national health and prosperity to certain demographic groups.</p> </div> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/01/2022<br>      Modified by: Konstantinos&nbsp;Mykoniatis</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  This research contributed new knowledge related to modeling social behavior and, in particular, opinion change in social media during the COVID-19 pandemic, with applicability to future pandemics with COVID-19 characteristics. The research involved the collection and analysis of Twitter data during the pandemics and the development of a data-driven hybrid simulation model.  The data collection resulted in three new large-scale datasets with a total of N=465,764 tweets related to COVID-19 mitigation strategies collected from June 10th, 2020, until April 30th, 2021. The three datasets include 305,015 mask-wearing-related tweets, 12,876 social-distancing-related tweets, and 147,873 quarantine/lockdown-related tweets.  The data analysis provided a sentiment-oriented overview of the U.S. public discussion concerning the aforementioned COVID-19-related policies among Twitter users grouped by similar demographic characteristics (e.g., age and gender). More specifically, discussions containing positive sentiment towards mitigation strategies prevailed and revolved around the benefits of the measures and trust of the government, while topics of negative sentiment involved conspiracy theories, skepticism, and distrust of government mandates. It is also notable that discussions among people 19-29 and over 40 years old focus on government officials and political parties, benefits or inefficiency of mitigation measures, and conspiracy theories relatively more often than other demographic groups.  The model development focused on simulating the compliance with, and resistance to, mitigation strategies and public health guidelines and investigating the opinion change among different age-gender groups. The simulation model results indicated that the number of regular users, influencers, or super spreaders with specific sentiment can affect users to change opinion towards mitigation strategies. However, bots have no impact on opinion change. A preprocessing framework that can be used as a procedure to label, summarize, and present the topics and sentiments of any dataset of tweets also resulted from this project. This project’s data, model, and approaches are publicly available, allowing other researchers to extend or reuse this work. The model and results can also be of great value to disaster response managers and policy/decision makers to understand human social behavior and enable the selection of policies that are most effective in promoting both the progress of science and advancing national health and prosperity to certain demographic groups.           Last Modified: 05/01/2022       Submitted by: Konstantinos Mykoniatis]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
