<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Coronavirus, new patterns in electricity demand, and energy inequality]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>199996.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>199996</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ECCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Aranya Chakrabortty</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>achakrab@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928113</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The aim of this project is to advance national health and welfare through investigating the impact of the coronavirus pandemic on electricity demand. The pandemic has resulted in widespread stay-at-home policies meaning that, vulnerable populations such as those with low income, ethnic minorities, and the elderly might face a disproportionally higher increase in electricity expenditure. The likely inequitable energy impact on these groups could be a result of less energy-efficient homes, increased need for electrical appliances (i.e. school computers), and larger household sizes. The resulting higher energy expenditure burden might imply constraints of these groups to create a comfortable indoor environment, which is particularly vital to maintaining good health during a pandemic. This project will (1) quantify the electricity expenditure re-distribution and uncover how this relates to the wealth redistribution as lay-offs increase; (2) develop a deeper understanding of the pandemic's impact on the electricity grid for different consumer types. This work will inform policies that can reduce the energy burden of the most vulnerable populations whose job security, educational development, and mental health are linked to their ability to satisfy their energy demand, particularly during an international crisis.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In pursuit of this research the research team will conduct consumer-level statistical and machine learning analyses using large samples of individual-consumer-level hourly smart meter electricity demand data in the residential, commercial, industrial, and agricultural sectors in Phoenix metropolitan, Arizona, and Chicago metropolitan, Illinois, as well as electricity and heating gas consumption data in New York City, New York. This will be combined with detailed socio-demographic and building attribute information for residential consumers which will allow for a more detailed analysis of electricity impacts, and impacts on energy expenditure. We will also conduct a consumer survey examining the changes in electricity consumption behaviors due to the pandemic. The pandemic has also highlighted the need to improve the measurement of energy inequality and poverty. We will develop an index based on the distance in energy consumption levels to measure the inability of households to obtain sufficient energy services. Once developed this index can then be used by the utilities and policymakers to identify the consumers suffering from energy poverty in a timely and precise fashion. We will examine energy poverty in the context of load profiles so that our findings can inform utilities regarding what types of demand-side management practices such as time-of-use pricing can help or hurt the consumers suffering from energy poverty. The consumer-level analysis on the load profiles will provide heterogeneous impact estimates and thus can better help utilities forecast future impacts on load and evaluate the uncertainties. This is especially important because there might be long-term structural changes in the demand patterns so that the load curves may not rebound back to the original patterns when the virus is gone. Lastly, our consumer-level analysis will quantify the heterogeneous changes in the temperature-response functions (how consumers change their electricity consumption in response to temperature change) due to the crisis. Quantifying the impact of such a complex redistribution of electricity demand on the load shape will help utilities better plan for capacity and portfolio management. This will be particularly important if coronavirus is persistent throughout the summer when cooling loads are high, or when there is a possibility of more waves of coronavirus.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/15/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/15/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2029511</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yueming Lucy</FirstName>
<LastName>Qiu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Yueming Lucy Qiu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[yqiu16@umd.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000669608</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/15/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Destenie</FirstName>
<LastName>Nock</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Destenie S Nock</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[dnock@andrew.cmu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000814167</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/15/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Maryland, College Park</Name>
<CityName>College Park</CityName>
<ZipCode>207420001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3014056269</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3112 LEE BLDG 7809 REGENTS DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MD04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NPU8ULVAAS23</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MARYLAND, COLLEGE PARK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>KMGEN62NKEM9</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Maryland College Park]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>207425141</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MD04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7607</Code>
<Text>EPCN-Energy-Power-Ctrl-Netwrks</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>155E</Code>
<Text>Electric power networks</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~199996</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>To mitigate the impact of COVID-19, states have issued &ldquo;stay-at-home&rdquo; orders. Many businesses have instituted work from home, or layoff policies. There is a large uncertainty surrounding how these exogenous changes will impact electricity demand patterns across different sectors, and the energy burden of the poor. Using individual consumer level high frequency smart meter datasets in Arizona and Illinois, combined with consumer surveys, this project generated four major outcomes: &nbsp;1) development of a new energy poverty metric that incorporates consumers&rsquo; energy limiting behaviors; 2) estimation of the heterogeneous impacts of COVID-19 on energy insecurity in the residential and commercial sectors; 3) using machine learning methods to forecast future residential electric load under work-from-home era; 4) using consumer survey to elicit willingness-to-pay for improving indoor temperature settings and to evaluate the impact of COVID on energy poverty</p> <p>For 1), income-based energy poverty metrics miss people's behavior (i.e., reducing energy consumption to limit financial stress). We introduce a novel method for calculating energy-limiting behavior in low-income households using a residential electricity consumption dataset.&nbsp;We first determine the outdoor temperature at which households start using cooling systems, the inflection temperature. Our energy poverty metric, the energy equity gap, is defined as the difference in the inflection temperatures between low and high-income groups. In 2015-2016, within our sample of 4,577 households, we found 86 energy-poor and 214 energy-insecure households. In contrast, the income-based energy burden metric identified 141 households as energy insecure when the threshold was set to 10%. Only three households overlapped between the energy equity gap and energy burden measures. Thus, the energy equity gap reveals a hidden but complementary aspect of energy poverty.</p> <p>For 2), we provide the first empirical evidence of the degree to which COVID-19 mitigation measures, especially the mandates of school closure and limiting business operations, impact electricity consumption behavior in low income and ethinic minority groups.&nbsp; We find that the mandates of school closures and limiting business operations increase residential electricity consumption by 4-5%, but reduce commercial electricity consumption by 5-8%. Considerable heterogeneity is observed across income and race: low-income and ethnic-minority populations experience a larger electricity consumption increase, reflecting disproportionate impact of COVID-19 on electricity insecurity in the residential sector.</p> <p>For 3), the COVID-mandates in 2020 have accelerated the transition to remote work, generating major uncertainty regarding how residential power consumptions patterns will shift. Understanding these shifts is vital for regional operators who will need to implement long term planning strategies in the event that companies continue to adopt remote work practices, or if new COVID variants prompt further extended stay-at home mandates, because the shifts will decide the optimal combination of power generation in a region. &nbsp;Using machine learning methods, our results show that COVID-mandates increase the power consumption in the afternoon by 13%, and change the power consumption pattern in winter from two-peaked shape to one-peaked shape. Furthermore, we show that the residents' income, race, and house size are significantly correlated with the changes in power consumption, and the correlation is not linear. We find that, by calibrating TOU rate for 10%, the peaked demand could be reduced by 10%. Our results show: (1) the need for modifying previous energy generation combination planning due to changes in the peak demand hours; (2) equity concerns regarding TOU pricing and inability of vulnerable consumers to shift electricity consumption under the new remote work era.</p> <p>For 4), we have deployed a survey of 2000 consumers and analyzed how unemployment and household income changes have led to changes in energy consumption during COVID.&nbsp; We used a choice experiment to investigate the willingness to pay for improving indoor room temperature settings of different household demographic types.&nbsp;</p> <p>Overall, our project provides important implications for policy makers to reduce the energy burden of the most vulnerable populations whose job security, educational development, and health are linked to their ability to satisfy their energy demand. Our results have been disseminated to broader communities including electric utility companies, EPRI, and academic institutions.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/09/2021<br>      Modified by: Yueming Lucy&nbsp;Qiu</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ To mitigate the impact of COVID-19, states have issued "stay-at-home" orders. Many businesses have instituted work from home, or layoff policies. There is a large uncertainty surrounding how these exogenous changes will impact electricity demand patterns across different sectors, and the energy burden of the poor. Using individual consumer level high frequency smart meter datasets in Arizona and Illinois, combined with consumer surveys, this project generated four major outcomes:  1) development of a new energy poverty metric that incorporates consumers’ energy limiting behaviors; 2) estimation of the heterogeneous impacts of COVID-19 on energy insecurity in the residential and commercial sectors; 3) using machine learning methods to forecast future residential electric load under work-from-home era; 4) using consumer survey to elicit willingness-to-pay for improving indoor temperature settings and to evaluate the impact of COVID on energy poverty  For 1), income-based energy poverty metrics miss people's behavior (i.e., reducing energy consumption to limit financial stress). We introduce a novel method for calculating energy-limiting behavior in low-income households using a residential electricity consumption dataset. We first determine the outdoor temperature at which households start using cooling systems, the inflection temperature. Our energy poverty metric, the energy equity gap, is defined as the difference in the inflection temperatures between low and high-income groups. In 2015-2016, within our sample of 4,577 households, we found 86 energy-poor and 214 energy-insecure households. In contrast, the income-based energy burden metric identified 141 households as energy insecure when the threshold was set to 10%. Only three households overlapped between the energy equity gap and energy burden measures. Thus, the energy equity gap reveals a hidden but complementary aspect of energy poverty.  For 2), we provide the first empirical evidence of the degree to which COVID-19 mitigation measures, especially the mandates of school closure and limiting business operations, impact electricity consumption behavior in low income and ethinic minority groups.  We find that the mandates of school closures and limiting business operations increase residential electricity consumption by 4-5%, but reduce commercial electricity consumption by 5-8%. Considerable heterogeneity is observed across income and race: low-income and ethnic-minority populations experience a larger electricity consumption increase, reflecting disproportionate impact of COVID-19 on electricity insecurity in the residential sector.  For 3), the COVID-mandates in 2020 have accelerated the transition to remote work, generating major uncertainty regarding how residential power consumptions patterns will shift. Understanding these shifts is vital for regional operators who will need to implement long term planning strategies in the event that companies continue to adopt remote work practices, or if new COVID variants prompt further extended stay-at home mandates, because the shifts will decide the optimal combination of power generation in a region.  Using machine learning methods, our results show that COVID-mandates increase the power consumption in the afternoon by 13%, and change the power consumption pattern in winter from two-peaked shape to one-peaked shape. Furthermore, we show that the residents' income, race, and house size are significantly correlated with the changes in power consumption, and the correlation is not linear. We find that, by calibrating TOU rate for 10%, the peaked demand could be reduced by 10%. Our results show: (1) the need for modifying previous energy generation combination planning due to changes in the peak demand hours; (2) equity concerns regarding TOU pricing and inability of vulnerable consumers to shift electricity consumption under the new remote work era.  For 4), we have deployed a survey of 2000 consumers and analyzed how unemployment and household income changes have led to changes in energy consumption during COVID.  We used a choice experiment to investigate the willingness to pay for improving indoor room temperature settings of different household demographic types.   Overall, our project provides important implications for policy makers to reduce the energy burden of the most vulnerable populations whose job security, educational development, and health are linked to their ability to satisfy their energy demand. Our results have been disseminated to broader communities including electric utility companies, EPRI, and academic institutions.             Last Modified: 09/09/2021       Submitted by: Yueming Lucy Qiu]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
