<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Addressing Families’ Covid-19 Information and Education Needs Through Podcast Media]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>200000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>200000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DRL</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sandra Welch</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This RAPID was submitted in response to the NSF Dear Colleague letter related to the COVID-19 pandemic. This award is made by the AISL program in the Division of Research on Learning, using funds from the Coronavirus Aid, Relief, and Economic Security (CARES) Act. The goal of this award is to advance understanding of how children’s science podcasts can provide families with information to help ease children’s anxiety and fears during a pandemic. The project’s hypothesis is that through listening to Brains On! coronavirus-related episodes, children will increase their understanding of science concepts related to the pandemic. As they gain this understanding, it is predicted that their overall fear and anxiety about the pandemic will diminish, they will feel empowered to ask pandemic-related questions and will engage in more science- based conversations with their family members.  The project will develop three Brains On! podcast episodes focused specifically on the COVID-19 pandemic for kids aged 5 to 12 and their families. The research questions include:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;1. How and to what extent do Brains On!’s coronavirus-based episodes help children and their families understand and talk about science-related pandemic topics? &lt;br/&gt;What kind of conversations are sparked by these episodes?&lt;br/&gt;2. What kinds of questions do children have after listening to the Brains On! coronavirus episodes and what are the reasons for their questions? What can the questions tell us about the impact of listening on kids' science engagement and learning?&lt;br/&gt;3. What resources do parents need to answer children’s questions and help them understand science topics related to the pandemic?&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is a collaboration between a media producer, Minnesota Public Radio and researchers at The Science Museum of Minnesota.  Brains On! already has a large listening audience, with 7 million downloads a year, and more than 200,000 unique listeners a month and these new episodes are likely to increase listenership further.  The research findings will be quickly disseminated to a wide range of audiences that can immediately apply the findings to create media and other coronavirus-related educational resources for families.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The PI's prior NSF funded projects have found that previous Brains On! podcasts with a range of STEM content increase the number and sophistication of the science questions children ask and lead to science-based conversations with family members. This project will study the impacts in relation to a singular topic, COVID-19.  Three online surveys of Brains On! listeners (families with children ages 5 - 12 years old) will be conducted. The first survey to be conducted as soon as the project begins will focus on parents reflecting on what information is needed at that stage of the pandemic. Two additional listener surveys will occur immediately after new COVID-19 podcast episodes are released. These surveys will ask content-specific questions to understand how well the episode conveys that information to children and their families, what conversations were sparked from the content, and what additional information needs families have. Prior to administering each of the three surveys, video-based think-aloud interviews with 10 families will test and revise survey questions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Survey participants will be recruited using language in Brains On! episodes, social media, website, and newsletters. A sample size of around 1,000 for each of the surveys is planned (based on a 95% confidence interval and ±3% sampling error).   Analyses will include descriptive statistics and thematic coding of open-ended survey questions.  Subgroup samples, when large enough will look at differences in responses by demographic variables (e.g. race/ethnicity, household income, highest level of education in the household, an adult in the household with a STEM career, gender of child, geographic location). The researchers and Brains On! staff will work together to identify how the findings can be applied to the development of subsequent coronavirus-related episodes and shared with the ISE field to further support families’ education and information needs.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/29/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/29/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2029209</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Molly</FirstName>
<LastName>Bloom</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Molly Bloom</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mbloom@mpr.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000738014</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/29/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Choua</FirstName>
<LastName>Her</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Choua Her</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[cher@smm.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000742454</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/29/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Evelyn</FirstName>
<LastName>Christian Ronning</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>G</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Evelyn G Christian Ronning</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[eronning@smm.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000762578</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/29/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Amy</FirstName>
<LastName>Grack Nelson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Amy Grack Nelson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[agnelson@smm.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000535150</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/29/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Minnesota Public Radio</Name>
<CityName>SAINT PAUL</CityName>
<ZipCode>551012217</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6512901584</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>480 CEDAR ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MN04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>GKURMECZ9BR7</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MINNESOTA PUBLIC RADIO</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Science Museum of Minnesota]]></Name>
<CityName>Saint Paul</CityName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>551021202</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[120 West Kellogg Boulevard]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MN04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7259</Code>
<Text>AISL</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>4N20</Code>
<Name>EHR CARES Act DEFC N</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>040N2021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[EHR CARES Act DEFC N]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~200000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-c4165fd1-7fff-8b77-a996-7c6620b4253f"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Over the course of the COVID-19 pandemic, caregivers were seeking out trusted information to address the questions, worries, and information needs their children had about this unique moment in their lives. The children's science podcast Brains On! was well-positioned to rapidly respond to children's and their families' information needs. Since Brains On! episodes had always been based on kids' questions and they already had a process in place for audience engagement (they receive an average of 100 questions from children each week), they could easily be responsive to children's changing questions during this global crisis. As of September 2021, Brains On! has produced ten&nbsp;</span><a href="https://www.brainson.org/page/coronavirus" target="_blank"><span>coronavirus-related podcast episodes</span></a><span>.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><strong>Research design</strong></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The goal of this RAPID research project was to advance understanding of how children's science podcasts, such as&nbsp; Brains On!, can provide families with information to help ease children's worries during a pandemic by increasing children's understanding of pandemic-related science concepts and supporting pandemic-related family conversations. Our research was guided by the following questions:</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>1) How and to what extent do Brains On!'s coronavirus-based episodes help children and their families understand and talk about science-related pandemic topics? What kinds of conversations are sparked by these episodes?</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>2)&nbsp; What kinds of worries and questions do Brains On! listeners have about the coronavirus and related aspects of the pandemic? How do children's worries and questions change over the course of the pandemic?</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>3) What resources do caregivers need to answer children's questions and help them understand science topics related to the pandemic?</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Our research design included two surveys and an analysis of children's pandemic-related questions. The first survey was conducted in June 2020, early in the COVID-19 pandemic. The second survey was administered a year into the pandemic in January 2021. We analyzed coronavirus-related questions submitted to Brains On! between February - June 2020. A year into the pandemic Brains On! was receiving fewer COVID-related questions, so we asked caregivers to report any questions that their children had on the January 2021 survey.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><strong>Findings</strong></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Our research uncovered the important role this informal science education medium played during the COVID-19 pandemic. Brains On! positively impacted children's learning, helped to ease children's worries and fears, and supported important child-caregiver pandemic conversations. The research also uncovered insights into the design features of the Brains On! coronavirus episodes that helped to support these impacts including the variety of episode topics; kid-friendly and age-appropriate content; information presented in a fun and interesting way such as the use of humor and skits; providing accurate, trustworthy information; modeling calmness; conveying that we are all in this together; interviewing scientists and other topical experts; and featuring kids and their questions.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Our research also revealed general insights, not specific to Brains On!, into the kinds of pandemic-related questions children were asking at the beginning and a year into the pandemic and the worries they had at these two time points. While questions about preventative measures, uncertainty around the length of the pandemic, and treatment/vaccines were frequent at both time points, questions about preventative measures were more frequent between February - June 2020 and questions around the uncertainty of the length of the pandemic and treatments/vaccines were more frequent in January 2021. Many of the worries children had stayed the same over the course of the pandemic (comparing January 2021 and June 2020 worries). Children remained worried about the many changes in their life due to following preventative measures (school, socializing with others, doing activities) and the continued uncertainty of when their life would be back to "normal." They were still worried about prevention and transmission, people getting sick (themselves and others), and death from COVID-19. Worries about people not following safety guidelines were more prevalent in January 2021 than early in the pandemic.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>We also uncovered a need for more pandemic-related resources for children. Many caregivers were turning to adult-focused resources to address their children's questions and information needs and translating this information into more child-friendly language. In January 2021, caregivers were looking for more child-focused resources focused on children's mental health struggles  and emotional wellbeing during  the pandemic as well as resources about vaccine-related topics.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><strong>Implications&nbsp;</strong></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Although this research focused on one children's science podcast, we hope our research findings can inform the development of coronavirus-related educational resources responsive to the information and learning needs of families during the COVID-19 pandemic. We also hope the findings are useful for anyone looking to develop science podcasts for children and their families around a range of topics, particularly in relation to creating child-focused media content during times of science-related crises.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <div><span><br /></span></div> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/17/2021<br>      Modified by: Amy&nbsp;Grack Nelson</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2029209/2029209_10666915_1630768663860_ScreenShot2020-09-24at5.18.11PM--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2029209/2029209_10666915_1630768663860_ScreenShot2020-09-24at5.18.11PM--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Drawing of Kara &amp; Gilly"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2029209/2029209_10666915_1630768663860_ScreenShot2020-09-24at5.18.11PM--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Drawing of Kara &amp; Gilly"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Drawing of Kara & Gilly, virus podcasters regularly featured on the Brains On! coronavirus episodes.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Drawing by Brains On! Listener</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Amy&nbsp;Grack Nelson</div> <div class="imageTitle">Drawing of Kara & Gilly</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2029209/2029209_10666915_1630769234638_vaccine--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2029209/2029209_10666915_1630769234638_vaccine--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Coronavirus vaccine"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2029209/2029209_10666915_1630769234638_vaccine--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Coronavirus vaccine"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Drawing of the coronavirus vaccine and how it works in the body.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Brains On! Listener</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Amy&nbsp;Grack Nelson</div> <div class="imageTitle">Coronavirus vaccine</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   Over the course of the COVID-19 pandemic, caregivers were seeking out trusted information to address the questions, worries, and information needs their children had about this unique moment in their lives. The children's science podcast Brains On! was well-positioned to rapidly respond to children's and their families' information needs. Since Brains On! episodes had always been based on kids' questions and they already had a process in place for audience engagement (they receive an average of 100 questions from children each week), they could easily be responsive to children's changing questions during this global crisis. As of September 2021, Brains On! has produced ten coronavirus-related podcast episodes.  Research design The goal of this RAPID research project was to advance understanding of how children's science podcasts, such as  Brains On!, can provide families with information to help ease children's worries during a pandemic by increasing children's understanding of pandemic-related science concepts and supporting pandemic-related family conversations. Our research was guided by the following questions: 1) How and to what extent do Brains On!'s coronavirus-based episodes help children and their families understand and talk about science-related pandemic topics? What kinds of conversations are sparked by these episodes? 2)  What kinds of worries and questions do Brains On! listeners have about the coronavirus and related aspects of the pandemic? How do children's worries and questions change over the course of the pandemic? 3) What resources do caregivers need to answer children's questions and help them understand science topics related to the pandemic? Our research design included two surveys and an analysis of children's pandemic-related questions. The first survey was conducted in June 2020, early in the COVID-19 pandemic. The second survey was administered a year into the pandemic in January 2021. We analyzed coronavirus-related questions submitted to Brains On! between February - June 2020. A year into the pandemic Brains On! was receiving fewer COVID-related questions, so we asked caregivers to report any questions that their children had on the January 2021 survey. Findings Our research uncovered the important role this informal science education medium played during the COVID-19 pandemic. Brains On! positively impacted children's learning, helped to ease children's worries and fears, and supported important child-caregiver pandemic conversations. The research also uncovered insights into the design features of the Brains On! coronavirus episodes that helped to support these impacts including the variety of episode topics; kid-friendly and age-appropriate content; information presented in a fun and interesting way such as the use of humor and skits; providing accurate, trustworthy information; modeling calmness; conveying that we are all in this together; interviewing scientists and other topical experts; and featuring kids and their questions. Our research also revealed general insights, not specific to Brains On!, into the kinds of pandemic-related questions children were asking at the beginning and a year into the pandemic and the worries they had at these two time points. While questions about preventative measures, uncertainty around the length of the pandemic, and treatment/vaccines were frequent at both time points, questions about preventative measures were more frequent between February - June 2020 and questions around the uncertainty of the length of the pandemic and treatments/vaccines were more frequent in January 2021. Many of the worries children had stayed the same over the course of the pandemic (comparing January 2021 and June 2020 worries). Children remained worried about the many changes in their life due to following preventative measures (school, socializing with others, doing activities) and the continued uncertainty of when their life would be back to "normal." They were still worried about prevention and transmission, people getting sick (themselves and others), and death from COVID-19. Worries about people not following safety guidelines were more prevalent in January 2021 than early in the pandemic.  We also uncovered a need for more pandemic-related resources for children. Many caregivers were turning to adult-focused resources to address their children's questions and information needs and translating this information into more child-friendly language. In January 2021, caregivers were looking for more child-focused resources focused on children's mental health struggles  and emotional wellbeing during  the pandemic as well as resources about vaccine-related topics. Implications  Although this research focused on one children's science podcast, we hope our research findings can inform the development of coronavirus-related educational resources responsive to the information and learning needs of families during the COVID-19 pandemic. We also hope the findings are useful for anyone looking to develop science podcasts for children and their families around a range of topics, particularly in relation to creating child-focused media content during times of science-related crises.                  Last Modified: 09/17/2021       Submitted by: Amy Grack Nelson]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
