<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Virtual Workshops on the Response of Higher Education to COVID-19]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>100000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>100000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Alexandra Medina-Borja</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>amedinab@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927557</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This project will contribute to the national needs for a strong STEM workforce, resilient STEM research enterprise, and a public that understands science and technology. To this end, the award will support a series of public, online workshops that will explore the effects of the COVID-19 pandemic on higher education, including undergraduate and graduate studies, STEM teaching, and the STEM research enterprise. They will also identify potential best practices for responding to the pandemic, thus providing a starting point for broader national conversations.  The Board on Science Education and the Board on Higher Education and Workforce at the National Academy of Sciences will convene the workshops, which will focus on sharing of challenges and responses among stakeholders.  These conversations will illuminate the areas of greatest challenge, including challenge areas that disproportionately affect certain populations of students, faculty, or types of institutions. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;As the nation addresses the immediate impacts of COVID-19, these workshops will provide an opportunity to deepen understanding of the resiliency of the postsecondary education system in the U.S. in terms of disaster preparedness, the ability to provide access and accommodation for all students and faculty, and the ripple effects of this public health event on the research enterprise. The workshops will provide an opportunity for institutions to share strategies and lessons learned in the early months of the pandemic. By providing a forum for institutions of all types to come together and learn from each other, the workshops will make it possible for institutions to modify their strategies in real-time and, thus, can have an immediate impact on campuses across the country. Furthermore, the workshops will examine how institutions’ responses might have differential effects on students and faculty depending on their backgrounds (race/ethnicity, gender, SES), age, disability status and other factors in their lives.  These insights can help institutions examine the impacts on their own campuses and adapt their responses to better serve all members of the educational and research communities they serve.  This award is co-funded by the NSF's Division of Undergraduate Education and the Division of Graduate Education.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/05/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/05/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2029539</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Heidi</FirstName>
<LastName>Schweingruber</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Heidi Schweingruber</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[hschweingruber@nas.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000295303</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/05/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>National Academy of Sciences</Name>
<CityName>WASHINGTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>204180007</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2023342254</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2101 CONSTITUTION AVE NW</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>PKFJZHG2MLG9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NATIONAL ACADEMY OF SCIENCES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>PKFJZHG2MLG9</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[National Academy of Sciences]]></Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>200012721</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1997</Code>
<Text>NSF Research Traineeship (NRT)</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1998</Code>
<Text>IUSE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8209</Code>
<Text>Improv Undergrad STEM Ed(IUSE)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0420</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~100000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>On March 11, 2020, the World Health Organization declared COVID-19 to be a global pandemic. From that moment, leaders of institutions of higher education have had to make quick decisions about how to provide high-quality educational experiences for their students while protecting the health of their students, faculty, and staff and maintaining the fiscal stability of their institutions. Institutions of higher learning took various approaches to the COVID-19 pandemic, which raised two questions: what factors informed decisions at these institutions, and what new initiatives or practices seem to be effective for students during the COVID-19 pandemic?&nbsp;To explore these questions and others regarding the effect of higher education&rsquo;s current COVID-19 response on students in undergraduate and graduate science, technology, engineering, and mathematics (STEM) programs, the National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine held a virtual workshop consisting of four online sessions that took place between September 22 and October 6, 2020. Organized by the Board on Science Education and the Board on Higher Education and Workforce, the virtual workshops provided an opportunity for participants from a range of institutions to share strategies and lessons learned.</p> <p>In the opening remarks, Robin Wright of the National Science Foundation (NSF) said that NSF&rsquo;s hope in sponsoring these workshops was for participants to encounter ideas that would assist them (1) in creating better institutions that serve all students, (2) becoming resilient to disruptions large and small, and (3) ensuring that the nation will be able to leverage the power of STEM to maintain the health, security, and prosperity of its people. Planning committee chair Tasha Inniss of Spelman College said that the global health crisis provides higher education with a unique opportunity to do things differently, to consider factors and constituent voices in creating new initiatives and infrastructure, and to make changes in ways that could dismantle the systemic racism that affects STEM students.</p> <p>A Proceedings of the Virtual Workshop Series was prepared as a factual summary of what occurred at the virtual meetings.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/28/2021<br>      Modified by: Heidi&nbsp;Schweingruber</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ On March 11, 2020, the World Health Organization declared COVID-19 to be a global pandemic. From that moment, leaders of institutions of higher education have had to make quick decisions about how to provide high-quality educational experiences for their students while protecting the health of their students, faculty, and staff and maintaining the fiscal stability of their institutions. Institutions of higher learning took various approaches to the COVID-19 pandemic, which raised two questions: what factors informed decisions at these institutions, and what new initiatives or practices seem to be effective for students during the COVID-19 pandemic? To explore these questions and others regarding the effect of higher education’s current COVID-19 response on students in undergraduate and graduate science, technology, engineering, and mathematics (STEM) programs, the National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine held a virtual workshop consisting of four online sessions that took place between September 22 and October 6, 2020. Organized by the Board on Science Education and the Board on Higher Education and Workforce, the virtual workshops provided an opportunity for participants from a range of institutions to share strategies and lessons learned.  In the opening remarks, Robin Wright of the National Science Foundation (NSF) said that NSF’s hope in sponsoring these workshops was for participants to encounter ideas that would assist them (1) in creating better institutions that serve all students, (2) becoming resilient to disruptions large and small, and (3) ensuring that the nation will be able to leverage the power of STEM to maintain the health, security, and prosperity of its people. Planning committee chair Tasha Inniss of Spelman College said that the global health crisis provides higher education with a unique opportunity to do things differently, to consider factors and constituent voices in creating new initiatives and infrastructure, and to make changes in ways that could dismantle the systemic racism that affects STEM students.  A Proceedings of the Virtual Workshop Series was prepared as a factual summary of what occurred at the virtual meetings.          Last Modified: 09/28/2021       Submitted by: Heidi Schweingruber]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
