<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Ecological Dynamics of Human Coronavirus]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>200000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>200000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>MCB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>David Rockcliffe</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>drockcli@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927123</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[With the zoonotic spillover of coronavirus into humans and the rapid emergence of coronavirus disease (COVID-19), humanity faces its first global pandemic in more than a century. Current molecular, cellular and animal studies of the infectious agent, SARS-CoV-2, use purified virus stocks that ignore a more likely scenario which is that the natural infection spreads as a mixture of active and defective virus strains. This project is developing mathematical models and wet-lab experiments on human coronaviruses that highlight how ecological interactions between such strains and their host cells critically impact the dynamics of virus growth, spread and ultimately their ability to cause disease. The developed models account for the presence of defective virus strains. The broader impact of the results of this project would guide clinical and front-line researchers with direct access to patients, in exploring broader and deeper measures of the infection dynamics and in applying novel therapies.  The project has potential to significantly impact the development of strategies that mitigate the pandemic. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project develops mathematical models and performs wet-lab experiments on human coronaviruses. The outcome will highlight how ecological interactions between strains and their host cells could critically impact the dynamics of virus growth, spread and ultimately their ability to cause disease. The project goals are to: (i) extract essential mechanisms and parameters of coronavirus intracellular growth from the literature, (ii) build mathematical models that account for the kinetics of viral entry, gene expression, genome replication and particle assembly in the absence and presence of defective interfering (DI) particles, and (iii) implement wet-lab experiments to demonstrate the emergence of DI particles from coronavirus cultures, activation immune cytokine signaling, and validate the intracellular kinetic models.  This RAPID award is made by the Systems and Synthetic Biology Cluster in the Division of Molecular and Cellular Biology, using funds from the Coronavirus Aid, Relief, and Economic Security (CARES) Act.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/04/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/04/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2029281</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Yin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John Yin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[john.yin@wisc.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000237121</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/04/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Wisconsin-Madison</Name>
<CityName>MADISON</CityName>
<ZipCode>537151218</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6082623822</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>21 N PARK ST STE 6301</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>LCLSJAGTNZQ7</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF WISCONSIN SYSTEM</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>QAFKGG7YY396</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Wisconsin-Madison]]></Name>
<CityName>Madison</CityName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>537151218</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>158Y</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7465</Code>
<Text>NANOSCALE BIO CORE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>1N20</Code>
<Name>R&amp;RA CARES Act DEFC N</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>010N2021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[R&RA CARES Act DEFC N]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~200000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The major goals of the project, ?RAPID: Ecological Dynamics of Human Coronavirus?&nbsp;(Federal Award ID:&nbsp;2029281)&nbsp;were: (1) to develop a kinetic model for the intracellular growth of coronavirus, (2) perform quantitative wet-lab experiments on human coronavirus growth, (3) expand the virus kinetic model to account for defective interfering (DI) particle co-infections, and (4) expand both experiments and modeling to a broader range of human coronaviruses compatible with biosafety-level 2 studies. &nbsp;</p> <p>Intellectual Merit: In language geared for the tax-paying United States public, to whom we owe a major debt of gratitude, there is a big mystery why some people who test positive for COVID-19 exhibit no symptoms, while others have severe symptoms or suffer death. We hypothesized that there was a missing player: Zombie viruses (technically known as defective interfering particles). We like the term Zombie viruses because it reflects two important facets. Zombie viruses are dead; they can deliver their genomes to susceptible cells, but unlike their normal-virus counterparts, they are unable to convert such cells into virus factories. Zombie viruses are byproducts of normal infection that carry defective genomes. But Zombie viruses can spring to life; if a Zombie virus encounters a cell that is already productively infected by a fully functional virus, then it can hijack the resources of the normal infection, making Zombie viruses at the expense of normal virus growth. In a sense, Zombie viruses are molecular parasites of normal virus infection. We hypothesize that the presence of Zombie viruses can modify how effectively normal virus reproduce and ultimately how severely they cause disease. We have initiated laboratory studies to better understand how Zombie viruses of human coronavirus arise and impact normal virus growth. We have also teamed up with computer scientists (experts in analyzing gene sequences of viruses from patient swab samples), and we have found evidence of the same Zombie virus present in swabs from patients in the United Kingdom and the United States; the funding provided for this NSF project has enabled us to start building a cross-disciplinary team of experts from computer science, public health (access to patient swabs and info of disease severity), virologists, and epidemiologists.&nbsp;</p> <p>Broader Impact: The project supported training of scientists and engineers in Zombie viruses and cross-disciplinary research spanning a wide range: one post-doctoral fellow, one PhD trainee, one post-baccalaureate, three undergraduates, and one high-school student. Although the focus of the project was not on human health or disease, but rather the kinds of ecological interactions viruses establish with their hosts, a key impact of the project was potentially on how such ecological interactions are potentially linked to the severity of diseases caused by viruses, including the effects of defective viral genomes (DVGs) of SARS-CoV-2 on the severity of COVID-19. This project was critical in establishing our preliminary exciting results that provide evidence for DVGs in the broad range of disease severity, from asymptomatic to death. Microbiologists who study the consortia of microbial cells (or 'microbiome') associated with the human gut, skin, respiratory tract, living environments, and soil, are already well aware of the importance of ecological and evolutionary principles on microbial communities. By analogy, our project contributed to make the case for a deeper understanding of the consortia of viruses (or 'virome') associated with animal, human, and other host environments.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/29/2022<br>      Modified by: John&nbsp;Yin</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2029281/2029281_10668225_1661802458848_169YinLab2022copy--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2029281/2029281_10668225_1661802458848_169YinLab2022copy--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Yin Lab 2022"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2029281/2029281_10668225_1661802458848_169YinLab2022copy--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Yin Lab 2022"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The NSF funding for the project supported diverse training, including post-doctoral fellows, PhD trainees, undergraduate students, and one high school student.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Pat Pointer</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">John&nbsp;Yin</div> <div class="imageTitle">Yin Lab 2022</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The major goals of the project, ?RAPID: Ecological Dynamics of Human Coronavirus? (Federal Award ID: 2029281) were: (1) to develop a kinetic model for the intracellular growth of coronavirus, (2) perform quantitative wet-lab experiments on human coronavirus growth, (3) expand the virus kinetic model to account for defective interfering (DI) particle co-infections, and (4) expand both experiments and modeling to a broader range of human coronaviruses compatible with biosafety-level 2 studies.    Intellectual Merit: In language geared for the tax-paying United States public, to whom we owe a major debt of gratitude, there is a big mystery why some people who test positive for COVID-19 exhibit no symptoms, while others have severe symptoms or suffer death. We hypothesized that there was a missing player: Zombie viruses (technically known as defective interfering particles). We like the term Zombie viruses because it reflects two important facets. Zombie viruses are dead; they can deliver their genomes to susceptible cells, but unlike their normal-virus counterparts, they are unable to convert such cells into virus factories. Zombie viruses are byproducts of normal infection that carry defective genomes. But Zombie viruses can spring to life; if a Zombie virus encounters a cell that is already productively infected by a fully functional virus, then it can hijack the resources of the normal infection, making Zombie viruses at the expense of normal virus growth. In a sense, Zombie viruses are molecular parasites of normal virus infection. We hypothesize that the presence of Zombie viruses can modify how effectively normal virus reproduce and ultimately how severely they cause disease. We have initiated laboratory studies to better understand how Zombie viruses of human coronavirus arise and impact normal virus growth. We have also teamed up with computer scientists (experts in analyzing gene sequences of viruses from patient swab samples), and we have found evidence of the same Zombie virus present in swabs from patients in the United Kingdom and the United States; the funding provided for this NSF project has enabled us to start building a cross-disciplinary team of experts from computer science, public health (access to patient swabs and info of disease severity), virologists, and epidemiologists.   Broader Impact: The project supported training of scientists and engineers in Zombie viruses and cross-disciplinary research spanning a wide range: one post-doctoral fellow, one PhD trainee, one post-baccalaureate, three undergraduates, and one high-school student. Although the focus of the project was not on human health or disease, but rather the kinds of ecological interactions viruses establish with their hosts, a key impact of the project was potentially on how such ecological interactions are potentially linked to the severity of diseases caused by viruses, including the effects of defective viral genomes (DVGs) of SARS-CoV-2 on the severity of COVID-19. This project was critical in establishing our preliminary exciting results that provide evidence for DVGs in the broad range of disease severity, from asymptomatic to death. Microbiologists who study the consortia of microbial cells (or 'microbiome') associated with the human gut, skin, respiratory tract, living environments, and soil, are already well aware of the importance of ecological and evolutionary principles on microbial communities. By analogy, our project contributed to make the case for a deeper understanding of the consortia of viruses (or 'virome') associated with animal, human, and other host environments.          Last Modified: 08/29/2022       Submitted by: John Yin]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
