<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Impacts of COVID-19 Pandemic on Rural Attitudes about Federal Aid and Recovery]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>178698.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>178698</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joseph Whitmeyer</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jwhitmey@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927808</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The scale of the COVID-19 pandemic necessitated historic action by the federal government to stem social and economic fallout, as demonstrated by federal relief programs exceeding $2.2 trillion. These and other federal interventions in the U.S. economy and society represent a potential shift in the role of government. Yet public opposition to federal programs is historically strong in many rural areas of the country. Given the magnitude of the pandemic, how will this crisis affect long standing attitudes towards federal aid programs and the role of government in society in rural areas? Furthermore, how will public attitudes towards federal aid in rural communities shape how much aid is allocated, what form it takes, and how it is received by rural communities? This project examines the impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on public attitudes towards federal aid and the role of government in rural U.S. communities. Findings from the project will be useful to leaders at several levels of government as they work with their communities to distribute aid to facilitate recovery.  As such, the findings will also be useful to leaders within the context of future pandemics or other extreme events, thus promoting U.S. safety and security.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The COVID-19 pandemic has necessitated historic investment in federal relief programs, and yet such programs have often been viewed negatively in rural areas of the country.  This project will address this development through a new two-wave representative survey of residents in rural communities across eleven states in the western United States (Arizona, California, Colorado, Idaho, Montana, Nevada, New Mexico, Oregon, Utah, Washington, Wyoming). Each wave will consist of 1,200 respondents and will be conducted through a mix of telephone and online outreach by a professional survey firm. The first wave will be conducted immediately, in the midst of the pandemic, and the second wave in spring 2021. The survey will be supplemented with 33 semi-structured interviews (three per state) with government staff, elected officials, and NGO leaders, all based in counties sampled through the survey. These interviews will augment information from rural communities and will provide a macro-level picture of how communities have been impacted by the pandemic.  Findings from the project will inform sociological theories related to changes in social ideology in the context of extreme events, as well as theories explaining political and moral identities.  In addition, the project integrates findings and concepts related to heretofore largely distinct literatures, one involving rural sociology and the other involving disaster research.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/07/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/07/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2029990</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Justin</FirstName>
<LastName>Farrell</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Justin Farrell</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[justin.farrell@yale.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000743650</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/07/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Yale University</Name>
<CityName>NEW HAVEN</CityName>
<ZipCode>065118917</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2037854689</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>105 WALL ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CT03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>FL6GV84CKN57</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>YALE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>FL6GV84CKN57</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Yale School of Forestry & Environmental Studies]]></Name>
<CityName>New Haven</CityName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>065112387</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[195 Prospect Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CT03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1331</Code>
<Text>Sociology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~178698</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The coronavirus pandemic disrupted life for millions of people across the United States. Yet, there was a lack of rapid and reliable information about the scope of its impact and potential solutions in underserved areas such as the rural U.S. West. Current information relied on national surveys or focused on urban regions with greater institutional resources, rather than tailored specifically to the unique needs of rural communities.&nbsp;<br />The goal of this project was to use current sociological theory to test questions about the large-scale disruption of social life. The coronavirus pandemic disrupted life for millions of people across the United States. This was an opportunity to test theoretical questions about "unsettled times" as well as to generate reliable information about the scope of the pandemic's impact and potential solutions in underserved areas such as the rural U.S. West. &nbsp;<br />Use a new two-wave rural survey to test theoretical questions about the impacts of a large-scale pandemic. Use this data to conduct sociological analysis. Share the data with other researchers interested in sociological questions about rural America, disasters, and the environment.<br />We published a paper in PNAS that has been very influential on scholarship and policy related to rural Americans experience of the pandemic. We presented the work in rural commuinities as well as to the United Nations, to local governments, to other universities and research centers focused on how rural America responds to large-scale shocks like the pandemic. The PI spoke on national NPR and other media outlets. We have several papers currently under review that seek to extend sociological theory concerning the impacts of pandemics. This is exciting work, and our analysis is ongoing. See our project website CovidRuralWest.org for more.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/31/2021<br>      Modified by: Justin&nbsp;Farrell</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The coronavirus pandemic disrupted life for millions of people across the United States. Yet, there was a lack of rapid and reliable information about the scope of its impact and potential solutions in underserved areas such as the rural U.S. West. Current information relied on national surveys or focused on urban regions with greater institutional resources, rather than tailored specifically to the unique needs of rural communities.  The goal of this project was to use current sociological theory to test questions about the large-scale disruption of social life. The coronavirus pandemic disrupted life for millions of people across the United States. This was an opportunity to test theoretical questions about "unsettled times" as well as to generate reliable information about the scope of the pandemic's impact and potential solutions in underserved areas such as the rural U.S. West.   Use a new two-wave rural survey to test theoretical questions about the impacts of a large-scale pandemic. Use this data to conduct sociological analysis. Share the data with other researchers interested in sociological questions about rural America, disasters, and the environment. We published a paper in PNAS that has been very influential on scholarship and policy related to rural Americans experience of the pandemic. We presented the work in rural commuinities as well as to the United Nations, to local governments, to other universities and research centers focused on how rural America responds to large-scale shocks like the pandemic. The PI spoke on national NPR and other media outlets. We have several papers currently under review that seek to extend sociological theory concerning the impacts of pandemics. This is exciting work, and our analysis is ongoing. See our project website CovidRuralWest.org for more.              Last Modified: 08/31/2021       Submitted by: Justin Farrell]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
