<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Integrative analysis of multi-omics data to understand ACE2 regulation and cytokine storm]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>200000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>200000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Steven Peretti</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>speretti@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924201</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Many drugs are being tested for efficacy against COVID-19. The side effects of these drugs are poorly understood. The issue is complicated because a number of organ systems (lungs, heart, liver) can be affected by the infection. In addition, underlying conditions such as hypertension, diabetes, or cardiovascular disease increase the likelihood of serious complications or death. This project is designed to identify the effects of these drugs on the organ systems of vulnerable populations. This information would inform the selection and application of effective drugs that also cause minimal negative consequences. This project will also advance the education and research experience of under-represented groups in the STEM disciplines.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project combines “horizontal” and “vertical” analyses of global genomic datasets. The “horizontal” perspective will map the landscape of gene expression under various conditions that will enable broader consideration of potential changes that drug treatments could have on Covid-19. The “vertical” perspective will identify regulatory mechanisms that suggest possible treatments to target specific responses (e.g., increases in the different types and levels of cytokines or decreases in the ACE2 levels) for the different phenotypes. The integrative approach of this proposal will capitalize on the timely results from the latest studies and incorporate these results into the gene regulatory network analysis to provide phenotypic-specific guidance on potential anti-inflammatory treatments and insight into the host response as a function of the phenotype. The scientific and engineering contribution of this project is the development and application of an integrative, multi-scale, and multi-faceted approach that models cellular interactions (signaling and regulatory) to enable prediction of the phenotypic responses to external stimuli, including drugs and pathogens. This integrative modeling framework will be applicable to other pathogens and patient populations.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/28/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/28/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2029319</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Christina</FirstName>
<LastName>Chan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Christina Chan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[krischan@egr.msu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000187768</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/28/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Michigan State University</Name>
<CityName>EAST LANSING</CityName>
<ZipCode>488242600</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5173555040</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>426 AUDITORIUM RD RM 2</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>R28EKN92ZTZ9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MICHIGAN STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>VJKZC4D1JN36</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Michigan State University]]></Name>
<CityName>East Lansing</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>488241226</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[428 S. Shaw Lane]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>158y</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1757</Code>
<Text>Quantitative sys bio and biotech</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>1N20</Code>
<Name>R&amp;RA CARES Act DEFC N</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>010N2021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[R&RA CARES Act DEFC N]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~200000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project&nbsp;investigated factors that influenced the severity of COVID-19. Much of the studies of -omics data uses single cohort data or proteomic data from blood samples. Our study differs from those in the literature in that 1) we analyzed protein data from blood sample obtained from multiple cohorts of patients from different locations, and 2) we obtain transcriptomics data from lung tissues from health and COVID (varying severity) patients. Given that ACE2, along with serine proteases are involved in the entry of SARS-CoV-2 into numerous organs and tissues in the body <span>and drive cytokine storm and multi-organ failure (MOF)</span>, the data from lung tissues are important in identifying targets that drive COVID severity specifically&nbsp;in the lungs.&nbsp;Through our proteo-transcriptomic analysis, we identified a gene set (markers) that significantly affected the discrimination of COVID-19 severity/non-severity in the lungs. Signature proteins/genes that are important or drive the severity of COVID-19 depend on the cohort sample. Thus, a diverse and more cohorts of patient data increases the robustness of the signature/targets.&nbsp;COVID-19 severity has multi-faceted affects on lung and other tissue functions. Thus, identifying markers from blood samples provides a "sum total" effect of all the tissues and may not identify the most relevant targets for addressing lung function. This is particularly important when attempting to combat&nbsp;acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS). Finally,&nbsp;SARS-CoV-2 infection can lead to cytokine storm (overproduction of proinflammatory cytokines), acute respiratory distress syndrome, multi-organ failure (MOF), and eventually death. An approach like ours, which combine transcriptomic data from a tissue/organ with the proteomics data from&nbsp; blood could be applied to multiple organs and thereby help uncover the most relevant targets involved in&nbsp;acute lung injury, acute kidney injury, cardiac injury, liver dysfunction, and thereby MOF.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/30/2023<br>      Modified by: Christina&nbsp;Chan</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project investigated factors that influenced the severity of COVID-19. Much of the studies of -omics data uses single cohort data or proteomic data from blood samples. Our study differs from those in the literature in that 1) we analyzed protein data from blood sample obtained from multiple cohorts of patients from different locations, and 2) we obtain transcriptomics data from lung tissues from health and COVID (varying severity) patients. Given that ACE2, along with serine proteases are involved in the entry of SARS-CoV-2 into numerous organs and tissues in the body and drive cytokine storm and multi-organ failure (MOF), the data from lung tissues are important in identifying targets that drive COVID severity specifically in the lungs. Through our proteo-transcriptomic analysis, we identified a gene set (markers) that significantly affected the discrimination of COVID-19 severity/non-severity in the lungs. Signature proteins/genes that are important or drive the severity of COVID-19 depend on the cohort sample. Thus, a diverse and more cohorts of patient data increases the robustness of the signature/targets. COVID-19 severity has multi-faceted affects on lung and other tissue functions. Thus, identifying markers from blood samples provides a "sum total" effect of all the tissues and may not identify the most relevant targets for addressing lung function. This is particularly important when attempting to combat acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS). Finally, SARS-CoV-2 infection can lead to cytokine storm (overproduction of proinflammatory cytokines), acute respiratory distress syndrome, multi-organ failure (MOF), and eventually death. An approach like ours, which combine transcriptomic data from a tissue/organ with the proteomics data from  blood could be applied to multiple organs and thereby help uncover the most relevant targets involved in acute lung injury, acute kidney injury, cardiac injury, liver dysfunction, and thereby MOF.          Last Modified: 08/30/2023       Submitted by: Christina Chan]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
