<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Examining Community Corrections Agencies During COVID-19]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>105467.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>129899</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Naomi Hall-Byers</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>nhallbye@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922672</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This award is funded in whole or in part under the American Rescue Plan Act of 2021 (Public Law 117-2).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The COVID-19 pandemic has created extreme challenges for community corrections agencies across the United States, a population at a high risk for infectious diseases due to a prevalence of social, economic, and behavioral risk factors. This RAPID project will measure and track agency-level responses to prevent, contain, and respond to the COVID-19 outbreak. Additionally, this project will examine how community corrections (the largest arm of the corrections system) respond to the COVID-19 pandemic and balance public health and public safety. Consequently, this study will investigate the circumstances under which community supervision agencies alter their policies and procedures during the COVID-19 pandemic, while examining the impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on the physical and mental health of community supervision officers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Through surveys and interviews with community supervision administrators and officers, and based on a theory of organization change, this project will take a longitudinal approach to examine how community corrections agencies adapt during the COVID-19 pandemic. These methods will enable a study of the circumstances under which community supervision agencies alter their policies and procedures during the COVID-19 pandemic. This project will produce data and research results that will provide key information on the strategies agencies use during the COVID-19 pandemic. Findings will aid scholarship and agency decision making in response to the COVID-19 pandemic, while informing the development of plans to protect the health and well-being of correctional staff and clients in future infectious disease events.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/01/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/17/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2030344</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jill</FirstName>
<LastName>Viglione</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jill Viglione</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jill.viglione@ucf.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000662568</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/01/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>The University of Central Florida Board of Trustees</Name>
<CityName>ORLANDO</CityName>
<ZipCode>328168005</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4078230387</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4000 CENTRAL FLORIDA BLVD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>RD7MXJV7DKT9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>THE UNIVERSITY OF CENTRAL FLORIDA BOARD OF TRUSTEES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[The University of Central Florida Board of Trustees]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>328161250</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>128Y</Code>
<Text>Law &amp; Science</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>098Z</Code>
<Text>LS-Law and Science</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>102Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-Disproportionate Impcts Inst-Indiv</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9102</Code>
<Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>1N20</Code>
<Name>R&amp;RA CARES Act DEFC N</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>1V21</Code>
<Name>R&amp;RA ARP Act DEFC V</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>010N2021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[R&RA CARES Act DEFC N]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>010V2122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[R&RA ARP Act DEFC V]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~105467</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~24432</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The COVID-19 pandemic presented unprecedented challenges for the community corrections system in the United States &ndash; a system that supervises nearly 3.9 million individuals annually. The goal of this project was to examine the multi-faceted impact of the pandemic on community corrections agencies and officers across the U.S. To achieve these goals, this project included a team of graduate and undergraduate students, resulting in five major outcomes related to better understanding the impact of COVID-19 on the community corrections system.</p> <p>First, the project resulted in a database of county-level, regional, and state contact information of community corrections agencies and directors in every state across the U.S., including Washington D.C. Prior to this study, there was no existing comprehensive database of this kind.</p> <p>Second, using this database, the project resulted in survey responses from 658 unique community corrections agencies across 47 states in the U.S. Participating agencies represented a mix of small, medium, and large offices serving adult and/or juvenile clients across rural, urban, and/or suburban geographic regions, and supervised individuals convicted of both felony and misdemeanors and who were serving county, state, or federal probation and parole. Survey data from these agencies were collected longitudinally with wave one occurring in June-August 2020; wave two in October 2020-January 2021; and wave three in October 2021-January 2022. These data document the experiences of participating agencies throughout the course of the pandemic which can be used to study the adaptations, challenges, and successes for these agencies as the pandemic progressed. These findings are critical for providing important context for understanding trends in community supervision populations and outcomes, as well as identifying key areas for future emergency planning and reform across community corrections. For example, overall findings suggest vast increases in the use of technology to continue supervising individuals during the pandemic. Agencies reported the consistent use of video conferencing and telehealth services over the course of the pandemic. Likewise, agency directors and community supervision officers continuously reported virtual supervision and remote work as two of the most beneficial strategies implemented during the pandemic, with the majority of agencies planning to sustain virtual supervision once COVID-19 was no longer a concern.</p> <p>Third, this project resulted in the creation of a public website containing a searchable database of the strategies and solutions agencies implemented in response to the pandemic. This database was updated over the course of the study, is freely available to the public, and allows all users to export a CSV file of the entire database. The goal of this database is to assist practitioners and decision makers by generating a comprehensive resource that details the containment, prevention, and response strategies agency directors reported implementing. These strategies cover a wide range of issues such as drug testing, health protocols, office modifications, screening/assessment, and supervision modifications.</p> <p>Fourth, this project examined the experiences of community corrections officers while working throughout the pandemic. Officers were interviewed from May 2020 through June 2022, providing firsthand accounts of how the process of supervision was impacted by the COVID-19 pandemic. These data provide an essential perspective to consider alongside the director viewpoints recorded via surveys. Preliminary findings suggest most community corrections officers reported remote work during the pandemic was critical for reducing stress and improving work/life balance, with many hoping remote work could continue beyond the pandemic. However, officers also discussed practical concerns with implementing virtual supervision, which can inform how to sustain this technology moving forward. For example, officers discussed challenges surrounding development of rapport with clients and implementing evidence-based practices while using technology as the primary means of communication. Additionally, community corrections officers reported supervising clients with more needs than ever before and having to fulfill a role more aligned with a social worker.</p> <p>Fifth, this project assessed the most pressing challenges facing the field of community corrections. For example, consistent pressing issues for participating agencies was the limited ability to respond to noncompliance and conduct drug testing. As the pandemic progressed, directors reported increased concerns surrounding financial strains, lack of available community-based treatment options, and major staffing issues. These findings contribute to a better understanding of the areas where more research and resources are needed to increase the effectiveness of the community corrections system.&nbsp; &nbsp;</p> <p>Moving forward, this project will use the data collected to complete a comprehensive analysis of the impact of the pandemic on community corrections agencies, including a longitudinal analysis of the responses to and impacts of COVID-19 on agencies and community corrections officers. A thorough understanding of the perspectives and experiences of agencies and officers during the pandemic can contribute to advances in research and policy regarding effective strategies for informing preparations for future emergency events, as well as key areas of reform for the community corrections system more generally.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/01/2022<br>      Modified by: Jill&nbsp;Viglione</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The COVID-19 pandemic presented unprecedented challenges for the community corrections system in the United States &ndash; a system that supervises nearly 3.9 million individuals annually. The goal of this project was to examine the multi-faceted impact of the pandemic on community corrections agencies and officers across the U.S. To achieve these goals, this project included a team of graduate and undergraduate students, resulting in five major outcomes related to better understanding the impact of COVID-19 on the community corrections system.  First, the project resulted in a database of county-level, regional, and state contact information of community corrections agencies and directors in every state across the U.S., including Washington D.C. Prior to this study, there was no existing comprehensive database of this kind.  Second, using this database, the project resulted in survey responses from 658 unique community corrections agencies across 47 states in the U.S. Participating agencies represented a mix of small, medium, and large offices serving adult and/or juvenile clients across rural, urban, and/or suburban geographic regions, and supervised individuals convicted of both felony and misdemeanors and who were serving county, state, or federal probation and parole. Survey data from these agencies were collected longitudinally with wave one occurring in June-August 2020; wave two in October 2020-January 2021; and wave three in October 2021-January 2022. These data document the experiences of participating agencies throughout the course of the pandemic which can be used to study the adaptations, challenges, and successes for these agencies as the pandemic progressed. These findings are critical for providing important context for understanding trends in community supervision populations and outcomes, as well as identifying key areas for future emergency planning and reform across community corrections. For example, overall findings suggest vast increases in the use of technology to continue supervising individuals during the pandemic. Agencies reported the consistent use of video conferencing and telehealth services over the course of the pandemic. Likewise, agency directors and community supervision officers continuously reported virtual supervision and remote work as two of the most beneficial strategies implemented during the pandemic, with the majority of agencies planning to sustain virtual supervision once COVID-19 was no longer a concern.  Third, this project resulted in the creation of a public website containing a searchable database of the strategies and solutions agencies implemented in response to the pandemic. This database was updated over the course of the study, is freely available to the public, and allows all users to export a CSV file of the entire database. The goal of this database is to assist practitioners and decision makers by generating a comprehensive resource that details the containment, prevention, and response strategies agency directors reported implementing. These strategies cover a wide range of issues such as drug testing, health protocols, office modifications, screening/assessment, and supervision modifications.  Fourth, this project examined the experiences of community corrections officers while working throughout the pandemic. Officers were interviewed from May 2020 through June 2022, providing firsthand accounts of how the process of supervision was impacted by the COVID-19 pandemic. These data provide an essential perspective to consider alongside the director viewpoints recorded via surveys. Preliminary findings suggest most community corrections officers reported remote work during the pandemic was critical for reducing stress and improving work/life balance, with many hoping remote work could continue beyond the pandemic. However, officers also discussed practical concerns with implementing virtual supervision, which can inform how to sustain this technology moving forward. For example, officers discussed challenges surrounding development of rapport with clients and implementing evidence-based practices while using technology as the primary means of communication. Additionally, community corrections officers reported supervising clients with more needs than ever before and having to fulfill a role more aligned with a social worker.  Fifth, this project assessed the most pressing challenges facing the field of community corrections. For example, consistent pressing issues for participating agencies was the limited ability to respond to noncompliance and conduct drug testing. As the pandemic progressed, directors reported increased concerns surrounding financial strains, lack of available community-based treatment options, and major staffing issues. These findings contribute to a better understanding of the areas where more research and resources are needed to increase the effectiveness of the community corrections system.     Moving forward, this project will use the data collected to complete a comprehensive analysis of the impact of the pandemic on community corrections agencies, including a longitudinal analysis of the responses to and impacts of COVID-19 on agencies and community corrections officers. A thorough understanding of the perspectives and experiences of agencies and officers during the pandemic can contribute to advances in research and policy regarding effective strategies for informing preparations for future emergency events, as well as key areas of reform for the community corrections system more generally.       Last Modified: 08/01/2022       Submitted by: Jill Viglione]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
