<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Facilitating Early Childhood Teacher and Family Engagement During COVID-19]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>256000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>256000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Diane Hickey</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is to ensure that the nation’s youngest learners and their families are supported as their educational experiences are disrupted due to the at-home learning configuration associated with the COVID-19 pandemic. Parents and caregivers are overwhelmed with all of the changes due to remote learning models. This project can ease their burden by enabling teachers to more closely collaborate with families and support their child in a remote learning context. A lapse in high-quality early childhood education puts the youngest learners at risk of falling behind in school readiness. With this project, teachers will have access to ongoing information on each child’s development and be able to provide better support in the remote context. Moreover, families will have access to high-quality, low-touch resources to support their child at home, even if the classrooms are closed.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed project is developing an early childhood teacher and family engagement tool to support remote enrichment for young children at home. The approach brings together the organization’s game-based assessment system to support teachers in the classroom with the organization’s research-based learning games for children. This project will make its assessment product accessible within a home context. Parents and caregivers will be able to use their smartphones or tablets to collect assessment data. Research will be conducted to ascertain ease of use and fidelity of assessment data collected in a remote context.  This data will then be used to power recommendations on the organization’s research-based games, two of which will be developed through this work, as well as other educational resources that families and children can do together. Assessment data is typically collected by teachers through an observation-based approach in the classroom; this project will enable parents and caregivers to collect assessment data pertaining to school readiness at home through touchscreen games. Early childhood teachers will then be able to use the data from the assessment and learning products to guide their remote instructional plans.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/03/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/03/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2030644</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tammy</FirstName>
<LastName>Kwan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Tammy Kwan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[tammy@cognitivetoybox.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000697231</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/03/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Cognitive ToyBox</Name>
<CityName>BROOKLYN</CityName>
<ZipCode>112016274</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7607156923</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>150 COURT ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[STE 2]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>MUMRD8Q2YU73</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>COGNITIVE TOYBOX INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>MV5CHGYCD8A1</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Cognitive ToyBox]]></Name>
<CityName>Brooklyn</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>112016274</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[150 Court St Floor 2]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1707</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED LEARNING TECHNOLOGIES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~256000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-74299242-7fff-89ef-06fd-3c87957e9909"> <p dir="ltr"><span><span style="white-space: pre;"> </span>The NSF Phase I scope was proposed during the 19-20 school year and implemented during the 20-21 school year, when more than 40 million students in US public schools were affected by school closures due to Covid-19. As remote learning became widespread during the Covid-19 crisis, early childhood educators were faced with an especially daunting task. Families in Head Start and publicly funded Pre-K programs often have inconsistent access to technology devices and internet. Moreover, there was a lack of developmentally appropriate, educational content for remote learning for children birth to five years of age. Thus, many early childhood programs were relying on handouts or worksheet packets for children to take home. Unfortunately, these paper packets do not provide opportunities for feedback or differentiated support for students. At the same time, families were and continue to be overwhelmed with unexpected &ldquo;homeschooling&rdquo; responsibilities. </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span><span style="white-space: pre;"> </span>To ease the burden on families and ensure that teachers have the information needed to support children at home, the Cognitive ToyBox (CTB) team developed </span><em>CTB at Home</em><span> to address two unmet needs in remote learning for early childhood education: (1) high-quality educational resources that are &ldquo;light-touch&rdquo; for families and children, and (2) assessment and learning data to inform teachers&rsquo; remote instructional support and interventions.&nbsp;</span></p> <span id="docs-internal-guid-2f445ea5-7fff-ff79-6b20-0ea4271750e5"> <p dir="ltr"><span><span style="white-space: pre;"> </span>In Phase I, the CTB team built </span><span>CTB at Home</span><span>, a teacher and family engagement tool to support children from birth to five year olds during the Covid-19 lockdown and beyond. To do this, the CTB team adapted the in-classroom CTB Assessment into a platform that enabled families to access assessment and learning activities at home, while also sharing data with teachers to inform their remote instructional support.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span><span style="white-space: pre;"> </span>The assessment games played at home give teachers a window into each child&rsquo;s development, and the learning activities provide differentiated support for children at home. Moreover, teachers can review children&rsquo;s assessment data and use that to inform their remote instructional support plans.&nbsp;</span></p> </span> <p dir="ltr"><span><br /></span></p> <div><span><br /></span></div> </span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/12/2021<br>      Modified by: Tammy&nbsp;Kwan</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   The NSF Phase I scope was proposed during the 19-20 school year and implemented during the 20-21 school year, when more than 40 million students in US public schools were affected by school closures due to Covid-19. As remote learning became widespread during the Covid-19 crisis, early childhood educators were faced with an especially daunting task. Families in Head Start and publicly funded Pre-K programs often have inconsistent access to technology devices and internet. Moreover, there was a lack of developmentally appropriate, educational content for remote learning for children birth to five years of age. Thus, many early childhood programs were relying on handouts or worksheet packets for children to take home. Unfortunately, these paper packets do not provide opportunities for feedback or differentiated support for students. At the same time, families were and continue to be overwhelmed with unexpected "homeschooling" responsibilities.   To ease the burden on families and ensure that teachers have the information needed to support children at home, the Cognitive ToyBox (CTB) team developed CTB at Home to address two unmet needs in remote learning for early childhood education: (1) high-quality educational resources that are "light-touch" for families and children, and (2) assessment and learning data to inform teachers’ remote instructional support and interventions.    In Phase I, the CTB team built CTB at Home, a teacher and family engagement tool to support children from birth to five year olds during the Covid-19 lockdown and beyond. To do this, the CTB team adapted the in-classroom CTB Assessment into a platform that enabled families to access assessment and learning activities at home, while also sharing data with teachers to inform their remote instructional support.  The assessment games played at home give teachers a window into each child’s development, and the learning activities provide differentiated support for children at home. Moreover, teachers can review children’s assessment data and use that to inform their remote instructional support plans.                 Last Modified: 10/12/2021       Submitted by: Tammy Kwan]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
