<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research: RAPID: Statistical Tools to Quantify and Mitigate the Spread of COVID-19]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>171936.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>171936</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Yulia Gel</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ygel@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927888</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This project will develop rigorous statistical models and inference tools to better understand the spread of COVID-19 as well as the type of the interventions that are most likely to work to prevent further outbreak. The work will result in concrete approaches for quantifying uncertainty of possible outcomes and provide reliable tools to assist decision makers in designing mitigation strategies for the COVID-19 pandemic. In particular, a new statistical inference tool will be developed to estimate the key epidemic parameters that describe the nature of the COVID-19 spread in an interpretable manner. These parameters are critical for providing reliable forecasts through real-time simulation of potential outbreaks. The new models will analyze the effects of changing social contact structures on the spread of COVID-19, and account for missing or partial data in a systematic way. The results of this project will contribute to the scientific and mathematical approaches needed to provide effective and quick understanding of future epidemics or relevant phenomena.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Existing epidemic models largely rely on deterministic systems that are unable to quantify the uncertainty critical for decision making. In addition, data analysis and predictive modeling for the COVID-19 pandemic require statistical tools for fitting epidemic models with only partially available data. However, most stochastic models face challenges in the face of missing data. To address this gap, the project team will develop new stochastic compartmental models that extend classical approaches to explicitly account for changes to the social contact network underlying the disease spread. These new developments will be accompanied by likelihood-based methods to infer key epidemic parameters that offer mechanistic interpretations with uncertainty quantification. In particular, missing data such as infection times at the individual level will be accounted for via novel data augmentation techniques. The results of this project will provide guidance both to the scientific community on how to evaluate the COVID-19 pandemic, and to the general public on which mitigation strategies would be most effective.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This grant is being awarded using funds made available by the Coronavirus Aid, Relief, and Economic Security (CARES) Act supplemental funds allocated to MPS.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/30/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/30/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2030355</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alexander</FirstName>
<LastName>Volfovsky</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alexander Volfovsky</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[alexander.volfovsky@duke.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000654901</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/30/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jason</FirstName>
<LastName>Xu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jason Xu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jason.q.xu@duke.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000705123</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/30/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Duke University</Name>
<CityName>DURHAM</CityName>
<ZipCode>277054640</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9196843030</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2200 W MAIN ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>TP7EK8DZV6N5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>DUKE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Duke University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>277054136</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>158Y</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>1N20</Code>
<Name>R&amp;RA CARES Act DEFC N</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>010N2021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[R&RA CARES Act DEFC N]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~171936</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><div class="page" title="Page 19"> <div class="layoutArea"> <div class="column"> <p><span>The outcomes of this project contribute significant additions to the statistical toolkit for learning from and acting on data informing the spread of COVID-19. Briefly, the PIs contributed &nbsp;new mathematical, computational, and epidemioloigcal insights that allow researchers to learn key epidemic parameters from models that describe the mechanisms of disease spread. New models are proposed that capture the complex interplay between the transmission dynamics of a disease through a heterogeneous population, and the changes in contact structures that affect as well as respond to these dynamics. In particular, we jointly model the dynamics of contact patterns together with disease transmission flow. The rates governing the process can depend on individual-level covariates, and allow for heterogeneity both in susceptibility/infectivity as well as in the mixing pattern between contacts. These mathematical models come equipped with algorithms for inference given observational data. By newly enabling likelihood-based inference, these tools not only give best estimates from noisy data, but provide a quantification of how certain we can be of these estimates. These tools were applied a diverse range of scenarios, including learning dynamics and patterns from mobile health studies of flu-like symptoms, evaluating school closure policies in response to COVID-19, and forecasting intensive care occupancy from noisy hospital time series. A key mathematical contribution is the rigorous probabilistic accounting for the uncertainty arising from missing data in these observational settings. Not only do insights gained from the simulation studies and real data analyses influence policy decisions, but the work lead to the design of new longitudinal studies of health care personnel and their contact networks to better understand COVID and related diseases in medical systems.&nbsp;</span></p> <p>This award partially supported three PhD research assistants and an undergraduate research assistant, who gained training in an interdisciplinary environment. The students as well as PIs presented results at several national and international conferences, synergizing with fields including epidemiology, mathematical biology, economics, statistics, and computer science. The PIs also contributed to organizing a national NSF Student Conference on COVID-19 Modeling, which provided both a platform for the urgent dissemination of related research toward mitigating the effects of the pandemic, but also featured mentoring and career enhancement for a diverse group of students.</p> </div> </div> </div> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/29/2022<br>      Modified by: Jason&nbsp;Xu</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[    The outcomes of this project contribute significant additions to the statistical toolkit for learning from and acting on data informing the spread of COVID-19. Briefly, the PIs contributed  new mathematical, computational, and epidemioloigcal insights that allow researchers to learn key epidemic parameters from models that describe the mechanisms of disease spread. New models are proposed that capture the complex interplay between the transmission dynamics of a disease through a heterogeneous population, and the changes in contact structures that affect as well as respond to these dynamics. In particular, we jointly model the dynamics of contact patterns together with disease transmission flow. The rates governing the process can depend on individual-level covariates, and allow for heterogeneity both in susceptibility/infectivity as well as in the mixing pattern between contacts. These mathematical models come equipped with algorithms for inference given observational data. By newly enabling likelihood-based inference, these tools not only give best estimates from noisy data, but provide a quantification of how certain we can be of these estimates. These tools were applied a diverse range of scenarios, including learning dynamics and patterns from mobile health studies of flu-like symptoms, evaluating school closure policies in response to COVID-19, and forecasting intensive care occupancy from noisy hospital time series. A key mathematical contribution is the rigorous probabilistic accounting for the uncertainty arising from missing data in these observational settings. Not only do insights gained from the simulation studies and real data analyses influence policy decisions, but the work lead to the design of new longitudinal studies of health care personnel and their contact networks to better understand COVID and related diseases in medical systems.   This award partially supported three PhD research assistants and an undergraduate research assistant, who gained training in an interdisciplinary environment. The students as well as PIs presented results at several national and international conferences, synergizing with fields including epidemiology, mathematical biology, economics, statistics, and computer science. The PIs also contributed to organizing a national NSF Student Conference on COVID-19 Modeling, which provided both a platform for the urgent dissemination of related research toward mitigating the effects of the pandemic, but also featured mentoring and career enhancement for a diverse group of students.             Last Modified: 08/29/2022       Submitted by: Jason Xu]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
