<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Collaborative Research: A "Citizen Science" approach to examine COVID-19 social distancing effects on children's language development]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>47504.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>47504</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Soo-Siang Lim</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>slim@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927878</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The COVID-19 pandemic is a significant threat to learning and language development for large numbers of children. Such challenges are compounded for those facing social and economic adversity, factors that are associated with decreased parental interactions, child development, and school achievement.  This study examines the scope and magnitude of learning impacts from COVID19 pandemic by engaging families as “Citizen Scientists” who will track their children’s language use during the crisis. Social-distancing policies vary by state, enabling the researchers to compare how these different decisions affect children’s language development. This will help policymakers and educators make more informed decisions, both about crisis management and strategies to mitigate negative effects of crisis-related policies. More broadly, this work will make important contributions to the science of language learning, which in turn will help clinicians and educators best address the needs of children from varying demographics. Finally, by using a Citizen Science paradigm, this project establishes a conduit for science outreach and education. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will recruit thousands of “volunteer researchers” to record data about their own family environment, parent-child conversations, and child language development using a web-based application accessible through a laptop or mobile phone. In addition to collecting survey responses, this app enables parents to make short audio recordings of their child’s speech and build a scrapbook of developing language abilities over time. When paired with comprehensive recruitment, this platform will assemble speech samples that are both broad and deep and will support more accurate models of relations between children’s learning and long- vs. short-term adversity. Additionally, the varied timing of social disruptions across locations permits both between-family and within-family comparisons of COVID-19 impacts, and yields estimates of effect sizes and modulation by race and socioeconomic status. The data will address questions of urgent societal interest, including a) how COVID-19 policies impact language-learning environments; b) how family stress changes children’s language and communication behavior; and c) what impacts the COVID-19 crisis has on developmental outcomes. Moreover, since social disruptions affect a wide demographic and are largely outside family control, this project leverages the COVID-19 crisis as an unusually clean manipulation of social and economic adversity. This avoids confounds that are persistently problematic in existing research, and will deepen theoretical insight into the factors that affect children’s language learning.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/09/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/09/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2030160</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yi Ting</FirstName>
<LastName>Huang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Yi Ting Huang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ythuang1@umd.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000623912</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/09/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Maryland, College Park</Name>
<CityName>College Park</CityName>
<ZipCode>207420001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3014056269</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3112 LEE BLDG 7809 REGENTS DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MD04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NPU8ULVAAS23</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MARYLAND, COLLEGE PARK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>KMGEN62NKEM9</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Maryland College Park]]></Name>
<CityName>College Park</CityName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>207425141</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MD04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>127Y</Code>
<Text>Sci of Lrng &amp; Augmented Intel</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>059Z</Code>
<Text>Science of Learning</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~47504</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>As a result of the COVID-19 crisis, families have lost access to education, childcare, social networks, and financial resources. Since these disruptions are not uniformly distributed in the US and vary with time, COVID-19 offers an unusually clean and profound manipulation of social and economic challenges and an unprecedented opportunity to address how COVID-19 policy decisions impact family language environments and child language development. For 6 months, this project recruited participants to act as &ldquo;volunteer researchers,&rdquo; recording data about: a) family environment, b) parent-child conversations, and c) child language development using a custom-built application (&ldquo;KidTalk Language Scrapbooking&rdquo;).</p> <p>The primary findings of our research are two fold. First, the survey questions reveal that COVID-19 disruptions are widespread, and increase stress for families from varying socioeconomic status. Relative to pre-pandemic times, families who had lost more income during the pandemic reported greater anxiety. This was true irrespective of the baseline family income. Second, our project highlights the feasibility of virtual and asynchronous methods for collecting speech samples from families. Our recruitment efforts have yielded demographic diversity with respect to child age, race/ethnicity, and language background. This suggests that platforms for collecting virtual data can expand the breadth of sampling in language research. Through this project, we trained one doctoral student, two post-bac researchers, and one undergraduate student. We established new community partnerships with six local and national organizations that focus on supporting families across a wide range of sociodemographic backgrounds and improving youth well being, shared our research through presentations to three state-level policy making divisions, and disseminated this work to the general public through print media, television news, podcasts, and social media. We initiated partnerships with technology experts, leading to five submitted grant proposals and one on-going research collaboration with computer scientists and engineers.</p> <p>This research has three broader impacts. First, this project serves as a model for how to increase diversity of language-science data by moving research outside of the lab. This technology does not yield fully automated systems (set it and forget it), but instead combines with an understanding of how and why people participate in research and tailored workflows for collecting and analyzing complex datasets. Second, this project provides a model for how to create trust with the community in service of increasing research participation. By assembling teams of diverse researchers and empowering them to apply their experiences and expertise, these changes in research practices offer necessary steps towards creating more accurate knowledge and effective practice. Third, this project provides a model for how to solve problems at the intersection of science and policy making. Covid-19 offers a window into the nature of today&rsquo;s societal challenges, which involve sudden changes within historical forces (e.g., climate, migrant), and require coordination across interactive systems (e.g., families, schools, states), and specialized knowledge of individuals and communities (e.g., sociodemographics). By training bridge builders and cultural brokers, the new model isolates shared goals from the beginning and pursues ambitious targets for knowledge creation en route to solving today&rsquo;s societal challenges.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/20/2022<br>      Modified by: Yi Ting&nbsp;Huang</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ As a result of the COVID-19 crisis, families have lost access to education, childcare, social networks, and financial resources. Since these disruptions are not uniformly distributed in the US and vary with time, COVID-19 offers an unusually clean and profound manipulation of social and economic challenges and an unprecedented opportunity to address how COVID-19 policy decisions impact family language environments and child language development. For 6 months, this project recruited participants to act as "volunteer researchers," recording data about: a) family environment, b) parent-child conversations, and c) child language development using a custom-built application ("KidTalk Language Scrapbooking").  The primary findings of our research are two fold. First, the survey questions reveal that COVID-19 disruptions are widespread, and increase stress for families from varying socioeconomic status. Relative to pre-pandemic times, families who had lost more income during the pandemic reported greater anxiety. This was true irrespective of the baseline family income. Second, our project highlights the feasibility of virtual and asynchronous methods for collecting speech samples from families. Our recruitment efforts have yielded demographic diversity with respect to child age, race/ethnicity, and language background. This suggests that platforms for collecting virtual data can expand the breadth of sampling in language research. Through this project, we trained one doctoral student, two post-bac researchers, and one undergraduate student. We established new community partnerships with six local and national organizations that focus on supporting families across a wide range of sociodemographic backgrounds and improving youth well being, shared our research through presentations to three state-level policy making divisions, and disseminated this work to the general public through print media, television news, podcasts, and social media. We initiated partnerships with technology experts, leading to five submitted grant proposals and one on-going research collaboration with computer scientists and engineers.  This research has three broader impacts. First, this project serves as a model for how to increase diversity of language-science data by moving research outside of the lab. This technology does not yield fully automated systems (set it and forget it), but instead combines with an understanding of how and why people participate in research and tailored workflows for collecting and analyzing complex datasets. Second, this project provides a model for how to create trust with the community in service of increasing research participation. By assembling teams of diverse researchers and empowering them to apply their experiences and expertise, these changes in research practices offer necessary steps towards creating more accurate knowledge and effective practice. Third, this project provides a model for how to solve problems at the intersection of science and policy making. Covid-19 offers a window into the nature of today’s societal challenges, which involve sudden changes within historical forces (e.g., climate, migrant), and require coordination across interactive systems (e.g., families, schools, states), and specialized knowledge of individuals and communities (e.g., sociodemographics). By training bridge builders and cultural brokers, the new model isolates shared goals from the beginning and pursues ambitious targets for knowledge creation en route to solving today’s societal challenges.       Last Modified: 01/20/2022       Submitted by: Yi Ting Huang]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
