<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Development and deployment of a digital game to combat COVID-19 misconceptions]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>199614.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>199614</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Soo-Siang Lim</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>slim@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927878</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Early reports show that the general public holds several misconceptions regarding the risks, transmission, prevention, and treatment of the novel coronavirus. If not acted upon, such misconceptions may lead to serious and irreversible harm to individuals and societies. This project responds to the urgent need to more effectively correct misconceptions about COVID-19 and to improve upon prior failed attempts to change beliefs about controversial or emotionally-laden subjects. By promoting affective engagement via digital games, this project seeks to overcome some of the psychological barriers to belief change. The potential for broad dissemination through gamification will provide important insights into whether gamified digital platforms may be a venue to overcome limitations of traditional direct routes of belief revision.  The project will provide important insights into the pressing question of whether gamified educational content can effectively correct emotionally-laden and polarized COVID-19 misconceptions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The solutions this project provides for successful revision of COVID-19 misconception centers on two interlocking objectives: (1) design of content specifically to promote the forms of cognitive processes known to revise misconceptions and (2) develop a new delivery method to present such content that mitigates negative affect and biased reasoning. This project will address both problems with a novel digital game that integrates cognitive and gamification design principles for belief revision and may represent a transformational augmentation in how individuals interact with challenging educational content. The digital game will be widely disseminated online in the U.S. and can be played on mobile or desktop devices. Overall, the quiz game will be designed to positively engage learners as they process educational content via game elements and mechanics. Affect, belief, and user interactions on the platform will be data mined for relevant learner analytic variables, profiles, and predictors of success. Findings will be used to iteratively modify subsequent game development and design to optimize success metrics. The project will advance fundamental knowledge of digital learning contexts and processes in correcting challenging misconceptions and address important national concerns of strengthening the general public’s knowledge of COVID-19.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/20/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/14/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2030273</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gregory</FirstName>
<LastName>Trevors</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gregory Trevors</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[TREVORSG@mailbox.sc.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000823734</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/20/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of South Carolina at Columbia</Name>
<CityName>COLUMBIA</CityName>
<ZipCode>292083403</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8037777093</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1600 HAMPTON ST # 414</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>South Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>SC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>SC06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>J22LNTMEDP73</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF SOUTH CAROLINA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>J22LNTMEDP73</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of South Carolina at Columbia]]></Name>
<CityName>Columbia</CityName>
<StateCode>SC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>292084104</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>South Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>SC06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>127Y</Code>
<Text>Sci of Lrng &amp; Augmented Intel</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>059Z</Code>
<Text>Science of Learning</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~199614</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project sought to impact public understanding of COVID-19 and advance theoretical knowledge about digital learning contexts and affective processes involved in correcting emotionally laden misconceptions. Recent interventions to correct such misconceptions have revealed the limits of existing methods and theories, which have largely relied on an information deficit model of science communication. In contrast to a deficit model, the current study represents a new theoretical approach to misconception correction among the public that uses gamification to capitalize on individuals' inherent motivational and emotional strengths. This person-centered approach was intended to augment how individuals affectively interact with challenging educational content, which may overcome limitations of traditional models of science communication that may fail to capture attention or positive engagement.</p> <p>We found four key findings:&nbsp;(1) the digital game interventions captured and sustained engagement;&nbsp;(2) interventions led to growth and retention of correct knowledge; (3) there was demonstrable needs for differentiated support across demographic segments; and (4) gamification modulated affective engagement associated with key outcomes.</p> <p>Although more research is needed, we believe that the present study advances our understanding of the emotional and motivational mechanisms involved in correcting challenging misconceptions and how to optimize them with person-centered technological designs, which we hope will ultimately result in more effective educational interventions.</p> <p>In terms of broader impacts, the integration of two heretofore separate lines of research - belief change and gamification - produced a digital platform with strong potential for future growth and ability to tackle critical STEM issues. Persistence of socioscientific misconceptions may lead to serious harm if acted upon. As such, by recruiting a large sample (<em>N</em> = 20,000) to engage with this educational intervention, this research directly addressed important national concerns of strengthening the public's engagement with STEM and digital environments, which may have impacts that extend beyond the particular content. The large, general population sample also supported conclusions with relatively strong external validity in the present research and demonstrated potential to support public engagement with science at a broad scale. These advancements can be further built on in future interventions outside of the current pandemic to evaluate generalizability to other contexts and to expand the benefit of refutations for a broader segment of the public across other socioscientific or health topics. Additionally, an educational goal of this cross-sectoral project was to train new scholars to become the next generation of scientists and policymakers who have the interdisciplinary skillset and perspective to analyze complex public education problems and contribute to their solution.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/15/2023<br>      Modified by: Gregory&nbsp;Trevors</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project sought to impact public understanding of COVID-19 and advance theoretical knowledge about digital learning contexts and affective processes involved in correcting emotionally laden misconceptions. Recent interventions to correct such misconceptions have revealed the limits of existing methods and theories, which have largely relied on an information deficit model of science communication. In contrast to a deficit model, the current study represents a new theoretical approach to misconception correction among the public that uses gamification to capitalize on individuals' inherent motivational and emotional strengths. This person-centered approach was intended to augment how individuals affectively interact with challenging educational content, which may overcome limitations of traditional models of science communication that may fail to capture attention or positive engagement.  We found four key findings: (1) the digital game interventions captured and sustained engagement; (2) interventions led to growth and retention of correct knowledge; (3) there was demonstrable needs for differentiated support across demographic segments; and (4) gamification modulated affective engagement associated with key outcomes.  Although more research is needed, we believe that the present study advances our understanding of the emotional and motivational mechanisms involved in correcting challenging misconceptions and how to optimize them with person-centered technological designs, which we hope will ultimately result in more effective educational interventions.  In terms of broader impacts, the integration of two heretofore separate lines of research - belief change and gamification - produced a digital platform with strong potential for future growth and ability to tackle critical STEM issues. Persistence of socioscientific misconceptions may lead to serious harm if acted upon. As such, by recruiting a large sample (N = 20,000) to engage with this educational intervention, this research directly addressed important national concerns of strengthening the public's engagement with STEM and digital environments, which may have impacts that extend beyond the particular content. The large, general population sample also supported conclusions with relatively strong external validity in the present research and demonstrated potential to support public engagement with science at a broad scale. These advancements can be further built on in future interventions outside of the current pandemic to evaluate generalizability to other contexts and to expand the benefit of refutations for a broader segment of the public across other socioscientific or health topics. Additionally, an educational goal of this cross-sectoral project was to train new scholars to become the next generation of scientists and policymakers who have the interdisciplinary skillset and perspective to analyze complex public education problems and contribute to their solution.       Last Modified: 02/15/2023       Submitted by: Gregory Trevors]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
