<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Optimizing distance learning programs to mitigate the effects of the COVID-19 Pandemic on REU sites in biology.]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>77892.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>77892</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DBI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sally O'Connor</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>soconnor@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924552</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The COVID-19 pandemic has undermined national capacity to offer onsite Research Experiences for Undergraduates (REU) Sites. Due to the rapid onset of the pandemic, BIO-REU principal investigators (PIs) were caught largely unprepared to deliver REU learning through distance technologies. This proposal will capitalize of the organizing activities started by BIO-REU PIs to provide distance REU programs. Specifically, PIs are making substantial changes to their programs to engage students in research at a distance, including shifting to research projects that can be conducted at a distance, offering research mentoring and professional development online, and providing informal avenues for communication at a distance. The shift to distance programming is both necessary and unprecedented. Substantive evaluation is needed in order to refine these approaches to maximize student learning and minimize disruption to REU offerings, which play a critical role in developing the research workforce. This project will improve student learning and development in distance BIO-REU sites by carrying out such an evaluation. First, the distance REUs will be evaluated early in their programming through virtual focus groups with students and mentors as well as observations of synchronous, distance activities. The results of these evaluations will be reported rapidly to the BIO-REU PIs to enable prompt adjustments and refinements of distance program activities. Then, additional focus group and survey data will be collected to determine the extent to which distance REUs are able to (a) build a sense of community in their cohorts, (b) ensure student ownership of their research projects, (c) provide quality mentorship at a distance, and (d) influence students’ professional growth and their education and career interests. Data will be compared across REU sites and with published studies of in-person REU sites to identify strategies useful for improving student learning in distance REUs. Results will be shared in reports to each REU site in order to make improvements and published for the undergraduate STEM education community to apply lessons learned in future undergraduate research programming. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will accomplish two major goals: (1) evaluating distance REUs in order to improve student learning and research workforce development and (2) producing new knowledge about the effectiveness of distance REU programming. Using established approaches and measurements for evaluating undergraduate research experiences, the project will involve conducting focus groups, observing program activities, and collecting survey data from undergraduate researchers and their research mentors at REU sites across the country that are operating at a distance due to COVID19. Results from analysis of focus groups and observations will be rapidly reported to REU site leaders to make immediate improvements to better support student learning. Results from surveys and focus groups will be used to determine the extent to which distance REUs are able to achieve similar goals to in-person REUs, including building a sense of community, ensuring robust student involvement in research, providing quality mentorship at a distance, and influencing students’ professional growth and their education and career interests. The project will produce tested strategies for engaging undergraduates in research at a distance, which could be applied to other circumstances such as serving students who are not able to travel to a distant REU site or engaging students following natural disasters. The project will be conducted in the context of biology, which is the domain of STEM with the largest number of undergraduate researchers. This RAPID award is made by the Division of Biological Infrastructure (DBI) using funds from the Coronavirus Aid, Relief, and Economic Security (CARES) Act.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/28/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/28/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2030530</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Erin</FirstName>
<LastName>Dolan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Erin L Dolan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[eldolan@uga.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000429680</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/28/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Georgia Research Foundation Inc</Name>
<CityName>ATHENS</CityName>
<ZipCode>306021589</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7065425939</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>310 E CAMPUS RD RM 409</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NMJHD63STRC5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF GEORGIA RESEARCH FOUNDATION, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Georgia]]></Name>
<CityName>Athens</CityName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>306021589</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[310 East Campus Rd]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>158Y</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9250</Code>
<Text>REU SITE-Res Exp for Ugrd Site</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>1N20</Code>
<Name>R&amp;RA CARES Act DEFC N</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>010N2021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[R&RA CARES Act DEFC N]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~77892</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The COVID-19 pandemic shut down research experience for undergraduate (REU) programs across the U.S. during summer 2020. A group of 23 colleges, universities, and research institutes re-organized to host remote REU programs in the life sciences. Given the unprecedented offering of remote REU programs, we carried out a study to describe and evaluate them. Using structured templates, we documented how REU programs were designed and implemented at a distance. Through focus groups and surveys, we identified programmatic strengths and shortcomings as well as recommendations for improvements from students? perspectives. Strengths included the quality of mentorship, opportunities for learning and professional development, and a feeling of connection with a larger community. Weaknesses included limited cohort building, challenges with insufficient structure, and issues with technology. Our results provided evidence for designing remote REUs that are experienced favorably by students. Our results also indicate that remote REUs are sufficiently positive to further investigate their affordances and constraints, including the potential to scale up offerings, with minimal concern about disenfranchising students.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>We also examined whether students who participated in remote REUs experienced integration into the scientific community, which is important for preparing the next generation of science researchers. We found that students experienced gains in scientific self-efficacy pre- to post-REUs, similar to results reported for in-person REUs. We also found that students experienced gains in scientific identity, graduate and career intentions, and perceptions of the benefits of doing research if they started their remote REUs at lower levels on these variables. Collectively, students did not change in their perceptions of the costs of doing research despite the challenges of working remotely. Yet, students who started with lower cost perceptions increased in these perceptions. These findings, which have been published in a peer reviewed journal, indicate that remote REUs can support students? self-efficacy development, but may otherwise be limited in their potential to promote scientific integration.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>When considered collectively, these results indicate that remotely implemented REU programs can, at least under certain circumstances, afford many of the same opportunities that in-person programs offer. These results should provide some reassurance that remote REUs are worth offering and may offer some advantages over or in addition to in-person programming. For example, remote programs could involve undergraduates in research whose personal situations would preclude participating in an onsite program. In-person programs could consider adopting some of the strategies used during remote programming, such as networking across programs and holding sessions using video conferencing so that students can interact with speakers, panelists, and collaborators beyond those who are available onsite. Our results also indicate that several elements of REUs were more challenging to implement at a distance. To assist the community in planning future offerings of REU programs and overcome these challenges, we curated students? feedback along with relevant guidance from the literature into a single set of recommendations, which we presented to REU PIs and published in a peer-reviewed journal. &nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>In summary, the intellectual merits of this project are the new knowledge generated about how to effectively engage and support undergraduates and their mentors in research at a distance and the comparison of outcomes experienced by students in remote vs. in-person REUs. The broader impacts of this project are the recommendations for how to design and implement quality REU sites that engage students who would not otherwise have access to research experiences, such as students who are not able to travel to a distant REU or students in locations affected by natural disasters (e.g., hurricanes, earthquakes, pandemics).</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/29/2023<br>      Modified by: Erin&nbsp;L&nbsp;Dolan</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The COVID-19 pandemic shut down research experience for undergraduate (REU) programs across the U.S. during summer 2020. A group of 23 colleges, universities, and research institutes re-organized to host remote REU programs in the life sciences. Given the unprecedented offering of remote REU programs, we carried out a study to describe and evaluate them. Using structured templates, we documented how REU programs were designed and implemented at a distance. Through focus groups and surveys, we identified programmatic strengths and shortcomings as well as recommendations for improvements from students? perspectives. Strengths included the quality of mentorship, opportunities for learning and professional development, and a feeling of connection with a larger community. Weaknesses included limited cohort building, challenges with insufficient structure, and issues with technology. Our results provided evidence for designing remote REUs that are experienced favorably by students. Our results also indicate that remote REUs are sufficiently positive to further investigate their affordances and constraints, including the potential to scale up offerings, with minimal concern about disenfranchising students.     We also examined whether students who participated in remote REUs experienced integration into the scientific community, which is important for preparing the next generation of science researchers. We found that students experienced gains in scientific self-efficacy pre- to post-REUs, similar to results reported for in-person REUs. We also found that students experienced gains in scientific identity, graduate and career intentions, and perceptions of the benefits of doing research if they started their remote REUs at lower levels on these variables. Collectively, students did not change in their perceptions of the costs of doing research despite the challenges of working remotely. Yet, students who started with lower cost perceptions increased in these perceptions. These findings, which have been published in a peer reviewed journal, indicate that remote REUs can support students? self-efficacy development, but may otherwise be limited in their potential to promote scientific integration.     When considered collectively, these results indicate that remotely implemented REU programs can, at least under certain circumstances, afford many of the same opportunities that in-person programs offer. These results should provide some reassurance that remote REUs are worth offering and may offer some advantages over or in addition to in-person programming. For example, remote programs could involve undergraduates in research whose personal situations would preclude participating in an onsite program. In-person programs could consider adopting some of the strategies used during remote programming, such as networking across programs and holding sessions using video conferencing so that students can interact with speakers, panelists, and collaborators beyond those who are available onsite. Our results also indicate that several elements of REUs were more challenging to implement at a distance. To assist the community in planning future offerings of REU programs and overcome these challenges, we curated students? feedback along with relevant guidance from the literature into a single set of recommendations, which we presented to REU PIs and published in a peer-reviewed journal.       In summary, the intellectual merits of this project are the new knowledge generated about how to effectively engage and support undergraduates and their mentors in research at a distance and the comparison of outcomes experienced by students in remote vs. in-person REUs. The broader impacts of this project are the recommendations for how to design and implement quality REU sites that engage students who would not otherwise have access to research experiences, such as students who are not able to travel to a distant REU or students in locations affected by natural disasters (e.g., hurricanes, earthquakes, pandemics).          Last Modified: 05/29/2023       Submitted by: Erin L Dolan]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
