<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Photoactivated coatings &amp; cleaners to disable COVID-19 on hospital high touch surfaces]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>256000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>256000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anna Brady</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>abrady@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927077</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is the development of new tools to reduce transmission of SARS-CoV-2 virus and the associated COVID-19 pandemic.  The materials platform developed in this project will help control and prevent surface-borne transmission of viruses, bacteria, and other pathogens with the potential to cause pandemics. The project will advance a robust coating that can be applied at point-of-use to reduce the hand-to-face spread of COVID-19. This technology may help reduce infection transmission among patients and care providers. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This SBIR Phase I project proposes to develop durable and non-toxic virucidal coatings containing visible-light-stimulated photocatalytic materials and a dark active material in a robust polymer matrix. The continuous antipathogenic action is activated with room light; the dark active material provides disinfecting species between daily cleanings. The coating will disable viruses, such as SARS-CoV-2, as well as other bacteria and bacterial spores.  These objectives overcome key drawbacks of current antimicrobial coating technology that limit its application, including the use of ultraviolet light (UV), degradation of polymeric coatings with time, and toxicity and ineffectiveness of the coatings in low-lighting conditions.  The proposed research will develop a non-toxic coating offering improved viricidal activity with white light, by modifying the photocatalyst and coating, enhancing the performance in low-light environments, and exploiting chemical synergistic interactions between the coating and commonly used liquid disinfectants.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/06/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/06/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2030025</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jeffrey</FirstName>
<LastName>Roeder</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>F</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jeffrey F Roeder</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[Jr@sonatascientific.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000196078</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/06/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>SONATA SCIENTIFIC LLC</Name>
<CityName>DANBURY</CityName>
<ZipCode>068108802</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2034486767</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>41 EAGLE RD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[STE 1]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CT05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>RJK3YJYBMRT6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SONATA SCIENTIFIC LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[SONATA SCIENTIFIC LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>Bethel</CityName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>068012873</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[25 Francis J Clarke Circle]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CT05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8030</Code>
<Text>Chemical Technology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~256000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>In Phase I, novel highly wear-resistant coatings were developed for self-disinfecting activity against viral and bacterial pathogens.&nbsp; The coatings consist of a polymer matrix with photocatalytic additives tuned for activation by room light. Light-activated photocatalytic coatings reduced 99% of viable MS2 bacteriophage (SARS-CoV-2 surrogate) on the surface in 1 hour compared to control coatings.&nbsp; Further, a new approach to sustained self-disinfecting properties was developed using inorganic additives designed to provide synergy with oxidizing cleaning solutions without the need for light illumination. &nbsp;Using these methods, &gt;99% reduction of MS2 bacteriophage and human rhinovirus were observed in &lt;2 hours on surfaces with the novel coatings.&nbsp; In addition, sustained disinfection was observed 4 hours cleaner treatment, demonstrating self-disinfecting activity.&nbsp; The oxidizing species generated by these methods are broadly antimicrobial, antiviral, and sporicidal.&nbsp; Preliminary data also showed reductions of <em>Staphylococcus aureus</em> (methicillin resistant <em>S. aureus</em> (MRSA) surrogate) and <em>Bacillus subtilis (Clostridioides difficile (C.Diff)</em> surrogate). &nbsp;Synergy between a coating and cleaner, particularly with respect to persistent self-disinfecting properties, represents a new area in which to advance the state of knowledge of disinfecting solutions and clinical practice.&nbsp;</p> <p>Surface borne transmission of disease is a major cause of human infection.&nbsp; Although the primary transmission route for SARS-CoV-2 is via aerosols, this coronavirus can remain active on surfaces for significant periods of time, providing a secondary pathway for transmission. The cost of the current pandemic is in the trillions of dollars in the United States alone. &nbsp;Technologies to mitigate the risk of future pandemics have significant value. &nbsp;In addition to future pandemics of varying severity, infectious agents like influenza, norovirus, antibiotic-resistantbacteria, and spores present serious threats to human health.&nbsp; In healthcare settings, nosocomial infections are a leading cause of morbidity and mortality.&nbsp; Healthcare acquired infections lead to more than 2 million cases per year in the US with on the order of 100,000 unnecessary deaths.&nbsp; Annual costs range from $8-11B. &nbsp;Key contributors to these problems include MRSA and <em>C. diff</em>.&nbsp; The technology demonstrated in Phase I has the potential to significantly reduce surface-borne infections when deployed on frequently touched surfaces in healthcare, transportation, and other public settings.&nbsp; The broader impact of this technology includes reduced deaths, increased economic productivity, and lower healthcare costs.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/23/2021<br>      Modified by: Jeffrey&nbsp;F&nbsp;Roeder</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ In Phase I, novel highly wear-resistant coatings were developed for self-disinfecting activity against viral and bacterial pathogens.  The coatings consist of a polymer matrix with photocatalytic additives tuned for activation by room light. Light-activated photocatalytic coatings reduced 99% of viable MS2 bacteriophage (SARS-CoV-2 surrogate) on the surface in 1 hour compared to control coatings.  Further, a new approach to sustained self-disinfecting properties was developed using inorganic additives designed to provide synergy with oxidizing cleaning solutions without the need for light illumination.  Using these methods, &gt;99% reduction of MS2 bacteriophage and human rhinovirus were observed in &lt;2 hours on surfaces with the novel coatings.  In addition, sustained disinfection was observed 4 hours cleaner treatment, demonstrating self-disinfecting activity.  The oxidizing species generated by these methods are broadly antimicrobial, antiviral, and sporicidal.  Preliminary data also showed reductions of Staphylococcus aureus (methicillin resistant S. aureus (MRSA) surrogate) and Bacillus subtilis (Clostridioides difficile (C.Diff) surrogate).  Synergy between a coating and cleaner, particularly with respect to persistent self-disinfecting properties, represents a new area in which to advance the state of knowledge of disinfecting solutions and clinical practice.   Surface borne transmission of disease is a major cause of human infection.  Although the primary transmission route for SARS-CoV-2 is via aerosols, this coronavirus can remain active on surfaces for significant periods of time, providing a secondary pathway for transmission. The cost of the current pandemic is in the trillions of dollars in the United States alone.  Technologies to mitigate the risk of future pandemics have significant value.  In addition to future pandemics of varying severity, infectious agents like influenza, norovirus, antibiotic-resistantbacteria, and spores present serious threats to human health.  In healthcare settings, nosocomial infections are a leading cause of morbidity and mortality.  Healthcare acquired infections lead to more than 2 million cases per year in the US with on the order of 100,000 unnecessary deaths.  Annual costs range from $8-11B.  Key contributors to these problems include MRSA and C. diff.  The technology demonstrated in Phase I has the potential to significantly reduce surface-borne infections when deployed on frequently touched surfaces in healthcare, transportation, and other public settings.  The broader impact of this technology includes reduced deaths, increased economic productivity, and lower healthcare costs.          Last Modified: 11/23/2021       Submitted by: Jeffrey F Roeder]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
