<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: The Impact of the Coronavirus (COVID-19) Pandemic on Municipal Solid Waste Management Systems]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>152165.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>176129</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Bruce Hamilton</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bhamilto@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032920000</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The coronavirus pandemic is challenging municipal solid waste management systems (MSWMSs). In an effort to prevent its spread, most people are working from home, which means that they are generating a larger amount of residential waste than normal. Further, the capacity of MSWMSs is being constrained by the increasing number of unavailable workers due to self-quarantining and the isolation of local areas as a result of travel bans. With a pandemic, the function and interplay of different system components (i.e., waste collection companies, waste transfer stations, local government agencies, material recovery facilities, and landfills) must become more adaptive to maximize the limited capacity, which is key to accommodating excessive waste demand. In this RAPID project, the project team will collect ephemeral data on the impact of the coronavirus pandemic on MSWMSs in multiple U.S. states including Florida, New York, and California. Since the impact of the coronavirus on MSWMSs and their responses vary across states and from urban to rural setting, these data can be used to (i) identify and characterize a broad range of regional waste management challenges, (ii) track the emerging adaptive behaviors different system entities take to adequately operate municipal waste services, and (iii) specify the system requirements and characteristics (i.e., system composition, topology, and control) that enable successful adaptation during a pandemic. This project will yield a database of pandemic impacts and responses and associated attributes and variables in MSWMSs that will guide researchers, private sectors, regulators, and planning agencies toward the creation and implementation of resilient waste management operations for pandemics. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The primary project tasks are threefold. First, the team will identify and map entities, operations, relationships, and controls in each system through virtual meetings with waste management companies and solid waste management authorities, and review of waste management guidelines. This step will establish a baseline structure for the normal operation, which will help to distinguish entities' emerging behaviors during the pandemic. Second, an online survey will ask system entities about their waste-related challenges and responses; the survey will occur once per month over a six-month period. If normal operations require adaptation of system structure, an interview will be held to gain more insight into the collective decision-making context. Third, a virtual workshop with a technical advisory group will be organized at the end of this project to review MSWMSs' reported adaptive measures and discuss recommendations.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/27/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/19/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2030254</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tarek</FirstName>
<LastName>Abichou</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Tarek Abichou</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[abichou@eng.famu.fsu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000338348</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/27/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Juyeong</FirstName>
<LastName>Choi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Juyeong Choi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jchoi@eng.famu.fsu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000788575</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/27/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Florida State University</Name>
<CityName>TALLAHASSEE</CityName>
<ZipCode>323060001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8506445260</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>874 TRADITIONS WAY</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>JF2BLNN4PJC3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>FLORIDA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>D4GCCCMXR1H3</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[FAMU-FSU College of Engineering]]></Name>
<CityName>Tallahassee</CityName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>323106046</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2525 Pottsdamer St]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>158Y</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7643</Code>
<Text>EnvS-Environmtl Sustainability</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>1N20</Code>
<Name>R&amp;RA CARES Act DEFC N</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>010N2021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[R&RA CARES Act DEFC N]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~152165</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~23964</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The coronavirus pandemic significantly challenged municipal solid waste management systems (MSWMSs). In an effort to prevent its spread, most people worked from home, thus generating a larger amount of residential waste than normal. Further, the capacity of MSWMSs was constrained by the increasing number of unavailable workers due to self-quarantining and the isolation of local areas as a result of travel bans. During a pandemic, the function and interplay of different system components (i.e., waste collection companies, waste transfer stations, local government agencies, material recovery facilities, and landfills) become more adaptive and spontaneous to maximize the limited capacity, which is key to accommodating excessive waste demand. Municipal waste services are critical infrastructure and should be adequately operated even during a disruptive event. In particular, MSWMSs become more important during a pandemic since proper municipal waste services protect communities by minimizing waste contamination and limiting the spread of infectious diseases. However, present approaches to address various challenges caused by the pandemic have mostly been reactive and ad hoc due to the lack of accumulated knowledge about their post-pandemic operations.</p> <p>In an effort to fill this knowledge gap, this RAPID project collected ephemeral data on the longitudinal impact of the coronavirus pandemic on nine MSWMSs in three U.S. states: five systems for Florida, two systems for New York, and two systems for California. Three data collection methods were employed to supplement one another: monthly interviews, new media content analysis, and waste tonnage report analysis. Since the impact of the coronavirus on MSWMSs and their responses vary across states and from urban to rural settings, these data can be used to (i) identify and characterize a broad range of regional waste management challenges, (ii) track the emerging adaptive behaviors different system entities take to adequately operate municipal waste services, and (iii) specify the system requirements and characteristics (i.e., system composition, topology, and control) that enable successful adaptation during a pandemic.</p> <p class="paragraph">The findings of this study have shown that the COVID-19 pandemic has brought a range of operational and managerial challenges to MSWMSs, which can be grouped under seven main categories (i.e., waste collection, recycling, landfilling, waste-to-energy (WTE), construction &amp; demolition (C&amp;D) waste management, business continuity, and health). In the waste collection category, the most commonly reported challenges were a decrease in commercial waste volumes and an increase in residential waste volumes, primarily due to stay-home ordinances and closures of local businesses. Improper disposal of plastic waste and an increase in the number of customer visits were reported as major challenges among the waste recycling and landfilling categories, respectively. As for the main challenges reported under the WTE, C&amp;D waste management, and business continuity categories, these include difficulty in maintaining social distancing in incineration facilities, an increase in the volume of unacceptable C&amp;D waste, and concerns about the loss in revenue, respectively. Lastly, the top health-related challenges faced by MSWMSs during the pandemic were limited availability of PPE for waste workers, difficulty implementing social distancing practices at the workplace, and the unavailability of workers due to quarantining. In general, among all of the aforementioned challenges, those found to have affected MSWMSs in all three states throughout most of the study timeline are: (i) an increase in residential volume, (ii) a decrease in waste collection revenues, (iii) shortages of waste collection personnel due to illness and quarantining, (iv) concern for workers' exposure to the virus, and (v) an increase in recycling contamination. In response to these challenges, and all other challenges reported in this study, MSWMSs have adopted various adaptation and mitigation strategies to successfully maintain waste management services during the pandemic. This study has found, however, that the adaptation pathways MSWMSs followed differ depending on their main system characteristics (i.e., interdependencies/waste disposal preferences, availability of entities, and control).</p> <p>The emerging and dynamic nature of the impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on MSWMSs, along with how they distinctly responded and adapted, highlighted the need for documenting such time-bound and system-specific information in a comprehensive knowledge base. Such need motivated the design and establishment of an informational database, capturing the post-pandemic information focusing on the challenges and adaptive measures of MSWMSs with varying system characteristics and regional factors. This initiative will facilitate accumulating the knowledge on post-pandemic waste management systems and enable different MSWMSs to look for the pandemic information specific to their systems, thereby guiding the development of their resilience plans for future pandemic events.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/29/2022<br>      Modified by: Juyeong&nbsp;Choi</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2030254/2030254_10666340_1661805653030_2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2030254/2030254_10666340_1661805653030_2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Database dashboard tab"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2030254/2030254_10666340_1661805653030_2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Database dashboard tab"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The post-pandemic MSWMS informational database tab</div> <div class="imageCredit">Juyeong Choi</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Juyeong&nbsp;Choi</div> <div class="imageTitle">Database dashboard tab</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2030254/2030254_10666340_1661805704959_3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2030254/2030254_10666340_1661805704959_3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Entities tab"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2030254/2030254_10666340_1661805704959_3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Entities tab"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The entities tab of the post-pandemic MSWMS informational database</div> <div class="imageCredit">Juyeong Choi</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Juyeong&nbsp;Choi</div> <div class="imageTitle">Entities tab</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2030254/2030254_10666340_1661805816421_4--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2030254/2030254_10666340_1661805816421_4--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Material flow tab"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2030254/2030254_10666340_1661805816421_4--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Material flow tab"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The material flow tab of the post-pandemic MSWMS informational database</div> <div class="imageCredit">Juyeong Choi</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Juyeong&nbsp;Choi</div> <div class="imageTitle">Material flow tab</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2030254/2030254_10666340_1661806112485_5--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2030254/2030254_10666340_1661806112485_5--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Identified MSWMS challenges tab"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2030254/2030254_10666340_1661806112485_5--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Identified MSWMS challenges tab"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The challenges tab of the post-pandemic MSWMS informational database</div> <div class="imageCredit">Juyeong Choi</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Juyeong&nbsp;Choi</div> <div class="imageTitle">Identified MSWMS challenges tab</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2030254/2030254_10666340_1661806252688_6--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2030254/2030254_10666340_1661806252688_6--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Adaptive measures tab"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2030254/2030254_10666340_1661806252688_6--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Adaptive measures tab"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The adaptive measures tab of the post-pandemic MSWMS informational database</div> <div class="imageCredit">Juyeong Choi</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Juyeong&nbsp;Choi</div> <div class="imageTitle">Adaptive measures tab</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The coronavirus pandemic significantly challenged municipal solid waste management systems (MSWMSs). In an effort to prevent its spread, most people worked from home, thus generating a larger amount of residential waste than normal. Further, the capacity of MSWMSs was constrained by the increasing number of unavailable workers due to self-quarantining and the isolation of local areas as a result of travel bans. During a pandemic, the function and interplay of different system components (i.e., waste collection companies, waste transfer stations, local government agencies, material recovery facilities, and landfills) become more adaptive and spontaneous to maximize the limited capacity, which is key to accommodating excessive waste demand. Municipal waste services are critical infrastructure and should be adequately operated even during a disruptive event. In particular, MSWMSs become more important during a pandemic since proper municipal waste services protect communities by minimizing waste contamination and limiting the spread of infectious diseases. However, present approaches to address various challenges caused by the pandemic have mostly been reactive and ad hoc due to the lack of accumulated knowledge about their post-pandemic operations.  In an effort to fill this knowledge gap, this RAPID project collected ephemeral data on the longitudinal impact of the coronavirus pandemic on nine MSWMSs in three U.S. states: five systems for Florida, two systems for New York, and two systems for California. Three data collection methods were employed to supplement one another: monthly interviews, new media content analysis, and waste tonnage report analysis. Since the impact of the coronavirus on MSWMSs and their responses vary across states and from urban to rural settings, these data can be used to (i) identify and characterize a broad range of regional waste management challenges, (ii) track the emerging adaptive behaviors different system entities take to adequately operate municipal waste services, and (iii) specify the system requirements and characteristics (i.e., system composition, topology, and control) that enable successful adaptation during a pandemic. The findings of this study have shown that the COVID-19 pandemic has brought a range of operational and managerial challenges to MSWMSs, which can be grouped under seven main categories (i.e., waste collection, recycling, landfilling, waste-to-energy (WTE), construction &amp; demolition (C&amp;D) waste management, business continuity, and health). In the waste collection category, the most commonly reported challenges were a decrease in commercial waste volumes and an increase in residential waste volumes, primarily due to stay-home ordinances and closures of local businesses. Improper disposal of plastic waste and an increase in the number of customer visits were reported as major challenges among the waste recycling and landfilling categories, respectively. As for the main challenges reported under the WTE, C&amp;D waste management, and business continuity categories, these include difficulty in maintaining social distancing in incineration facilities, an increase in the volume of unacceptable C&amp;D waste, and concerns about the loss in revenue, respectively. Lastly, the top health-related challenges faced by MSWMSs during the pandemic were limited availability of PPE for waste workers, difficulty implementing social distancing practices at the workplace, and the unavailability of workers due to quarantining. In general, among all of the aforementioned challenges, those found to have affected MSWMSs in all three states throughout most of the study timeline are: (i) an increase in residential volume, (ii) a decrease in waste collection revenues, (iii) shortages of waste collection personnel due to illness and quarantining, (iv) concern for workers' exposure to the virus, and (v) an increase in recycling contamination. In response to these challenges, and all other challenges reported in this study, MSWMSs have adopted various adaptation and mitigation strategies to successfully maintain waste management services during the pandemic. This study has found, however, that the adaptation pathways MSWMSs followed differ depending on their main system characteristics (i.e., interdependencies/waste disposal preferences, availability of entities, and control).  The emerging and dynamic nature of the impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on MSWMSs, along with how they distinctly responded and adapted, highlighted the need for documenting such time-bound and system-specific information in a comprehensive knowledge base. Such need motivated the design and establishment of an informational database, capturing the post-pandemic information focusing on the challenges and adaptive measures of MSWMSs with varying system characteristics and regional factors. This initiative will facilitate accumulating the knowledge on post-pandemic waste management systems and enable different MSWMSs to look for the pandemic information specific to their systems, thereby guiding the development of their resilience plans for future pandemic events.       Last Modified: 08/29/2022       Submitted by: Juyeong Choi]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
