<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: ECONOMIC AND SOCIAL CONSEQUENCES OF THE COVID-19 PANDEMIC FOR LOW INCOME, LATE MIDDLE-AGED AFRICAN AMERICANS]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>200000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>200000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Melanie Hughes</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mehughes@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927318</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The COVID-19 pandemic has fostered a number of dramatic social changes, including sheltering in place and job loss for millions of Americans. The African American community has been disproportionately impacted. As African American families struggle with self-quarantine, a faltering economy, and high rates of infection, there is a need for detailed information regarding how they are coping, and a need to identify resources they are successfully or unsuccessfully accessing. This project will build on an on-going longitudinal survey of African Americans living in the South and Midwest to evaluate the effects of the pandemic on family functioning and well-being. Findings will inform policies of governmental and private agencies tasked with providing support to citizens during extreme events.  These findings will aid in recovery from the current crisis and provide information as to how to better prepare for another pandemic or similar emergency, thus promoting safety, security and well-being in our society.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The COVID-19 pandemic has had a disproportionately negative impact on the African-American community.  This project will investigate the impact of financial hardship and self-quarantine using a longitudinal data set comprised of close to 500 middle-age African Americans living in the South and Midwest (250 married, 74 live alone, 174 live in multigenerational households). This data set currently consists of eight waves of data collected over 25 years, with the most recent wave completed in 2019. It includes data regarding work, economic hardship, family relationships, social support, religious activities, and psychological well-being over several waves, thus forming a baseline in assessing the impact of the COVID-19 pandemic. These baseline data provide a unique opportunity to assess the degree of change in various domains of life following self-quarantine and unemployment, including emotional well-being (anxiety, depression, anger, loneliness) and, in turn, quality of family interaction and involvement in risky behaviors such as smoking, heavy alcohol consumption, and an unhealthy diet.  The project will also analyze whether the pandemic’s impact on economic hardship, family relationships, and emotional well-being vary by social class and by household composition. Findings from the project will inform sociological theories of family functioning, including the family stress model.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/08/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/19/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2030569</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Leslie</FirstName>
<LastName>Simons</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>G</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Leslie G Simons</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[lgsimons@uga.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000691296</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/08/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Chalandra</FirstName>
<LastName>Bryant</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Chalandra M Bryant</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[cmbryant@umn.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000691294</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/08/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Georgia Research Foundation Inc</Name>
<CityName>ATHENS</CityName>
<ZipCode>306021589</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7065425939</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>310 E CAMPUS RD RM 409</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NMJHD63STRC5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF GEORGIA RESEARCH FOUNDATION, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Georgia]]></Name>
<CityName>Athens</CityName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>306021589</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[310 East Campus Rd. Rm. 409]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1331</Code>
<Text>Sociology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~200000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The American Psychological Association's annual survey of stress in America has consistently found that economic problems are rated by Americans as the most stressful of stressors. Consistent with this finding, a profusion of research, much of it guided by the Family Stress Model, has found that financial difficulties lead to increases in anxiety, anger, and depression, with these mood changes, in turn, leading to arguments and conflict with romantic partners and other family members. While this general pattern is likely currently taking place among American families as they struggle with the fallout of a faltering economy and quarantine, there is a need for <em><span style="text-decoration: underline;">specific</span></em> information regarding how families are being affected, the unique stressors that are being encountered, the supports and coping resources being utilized, and the way these processes vary by social class and other social categories.</p> <p>Toward that end, the proposed study investigated the impact of financial hardship and sheltering-in-place using a longitudinal dataset comprised of middle-aged African Americans living in the South and Midwest. That dataset consisted of eight waves of data collected over 25 years, with the most recent being completed in 2018. It included a vast array of information, including data regarding economic hardship, family relationships, social support, religious activities, psychological well-being, diet, exercise, and substance use. Those data are being used as a baseline in assessing the impact of the COVID-19 pandemic. Thus, our research team was in a strategically ideal position to assess the degree of <em>change </em>in various domains of life associated with sheltering-in-place and unemployment. In addition to documenting the impact of the epidemic on change in these various domains of life, we investigated unique features of daily living under quarantine, including financial, social, and medical challenges.</p> <p>Information was collected about (1) psychosocial and economic circumstances of study participants; (2) difficulties in securing housing, food, prescription medications, and medical care; (3) sources of support from relatives and the community; (4) success/failure/challenges in implementing sheltering-in-place; (5) types of activities engaged in while sheltering-in-place; (6) family cohesion and conflict during sheltering-in-place; and (7) activities and behaviors of youth residing in the home. We also asked if any household members contracted COVID-19, and what type of medical care they received.</p> <p>We expected that the impact on economic hardship, family relationships, and emotional well-being will vary by social class, such that families with fewer economic resources will experience increased difficulties in these domains. While low income individuals risked catching the virus when they went to work, this risk was reduced for many.&nbsp; Many hourly workers had their hours cut back or they were laid off. Thus, fear of catching the virus has been replaced with pressing financial concerns.</p> <p>Preliminary results revealed that over 60% of our sample reported a period of unemployment due to layoffs.&nbsp; Consequently, trouble buying food during this time was significantly associated with depression. Many indicated that someone in their household had to keep working because they were healthcare providers providing direct care.&nbsp; Those are just a few examples of the stressors endured. In depth information regarding psychosocial implications was obtained.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/02/2022<br>      Modified by: Leslie&nbsp;G&nbsp;Simons</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The American Psychological Association's annual survey of stress in America has consistently found that economic problems are rated by Americans as the most stressful of stressors. Consistent with this finding, a profusion of research, much of it guided by the Family Stress Model, has found that financial difficulties lead to increases in anxiety, anger, and depression, with these mood changes, in turn, leading to arguments and conflict with romantic partners and other family members. While this general pattern is likely currently taking place among American families as they struggle with the fallout of a faltering economy and quarantine, there is a need for specific information regarding how families are being affected, the unique stressors that are being encountered, the supports and coping resources being utilized, and the way these processes vary by social class and other social categories.  Toward that end, the proposed study investigated the impact of financial hardship and sheltering-in-place using a longitudinal dataset comprised of middle-aged African Americans living in the South and Midwest. That dataset consisted of eight waves of data collected over 25 years, with the most recent being completed in 2018. It included a vast array of information, including data regarding economic hardship, family relationships, social support, religious activities, psychological well-being, diet, exercise, and substance use. Those data are being used as a baseline in assessing the impact of the COVID-19 pandemic. Thus, our research team was in a strategically ideal position to assess the degree of change in various domains of life associated with sheltering-in-place and unemployment. In addition to documenting the impact of the epidemic on change in these various domains of life, we investigated unique features of daily living under quarantine, including financial, social, and medical challenges.  Information was collected about (1) psychosocial and economic circumstances of study participants; (2) difficulties in securing housing, food, prescription medications, and medical care; (3) sources of support from relatives and the community; (4) success/failure/challenges in implementing sheltering-in-place; (5) types of activities engaged in while sheltering-in-place; (6) family cohesion and conflict during sheltering-in-place; and (7) activities and behaviors of youth residing in the home. We also asked if any household members contracted COVID-19, and what type of medical care they received.  We expected that the impact on economic hardship, family relationships, and emotional well-being will vary by social class, such that families with fewer economic resources will experience increased difficulties in these domains. While low income individuals risked catching the virus when they went to work, this risk was reduced for many.  Many hourly workers had their hours cut back or they were laid off. Thus, fear of catching the virus has been replaced with pressing financial concerns.  Preliminary results revealed that over 60% of our sample reported a period of unemployment due to layoffs.  Consequently, trouble buying food during this time was significantly associated with depression. Many indicated that someone in their household had to keep working because they were healthcare providers providing direct care.  Those are just a few examples of the stressors endured. In depth information regarding psychosocial implications was obtained.             Last Modified: 06/02/2022       Submitted by: Leslie G Simons]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
