<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Easing COVID-19 Restrictions: How Variation in State Policy and Public Health Messaging Strategies Impact Risk Perceptions and Behaviors Across Time]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>164638.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>164638</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Robert O'Connor</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>roconnor@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927263</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Recent studies of the transmission dynamics of COVID-19 suggest that intermittent physical distancing may be required until well into 2022 in order to reduce the continued spread of this novel disease. However, many individuals are eager to return to normalcy sooner, and state governments have begun the process of easing such restrictions and “restarting” their economies, despite continued warnings by public health officials. Effective risk communication is imperative to successfully navigating this next phase of the pandemic and reducing the possibility of a resurgence of COVID-19 in the coming months and years. This research studies the ways in which individual risk perceptions and consequent behaviors interact with and, more importantly, are shaped by policy and public health messaging strategies in the context of COVID-19. Based on data collected through a multi-wave panel survey across six U.S. states on individual risk perceptions and behaviors, this project provides usable information to policy makers and public health officials to inform risk communication for the COVID-19 pandemic in near real-time, particularly as  restrictions related to social distancing, business closures, and other risk mitigation measures are lifted and changed. This project measures the extent to which individual risk perceptions and behaviors are shaped by not only the differential policies and risk messaging strategies utilized by government officials, but also by preexisting structural factors, such as racial, economic, and gender disparities. As such, the findings simultaneously inform existing public health strategies while advancing the extant literature on risk communication relevant to other on-going and emerging hazards.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The COVID-19 pandemic emerged against the backdrop of an uneven landscape of health and social disparities, risk preparedness policies, and political factors across the United States (i.e., at pre-COVID time T0). In response to this threat, states have taken actions, most notably issuing stay-at-home orders, to attempt to mitigate risk. These initial state-level COVID-19 restrictions serve as T1 baseline data for understanding policy design and risk communication, against which individual risk perception and risk mitigation behavior can be assessed during the crisis phase of the pandemic. As COVID-19-related restrictions are eased across states (or tightened in the face of a second wave) over time, this study will assess changes in policy design, risk communication, risk perception, and risk mitigation behavior in the recovery phase at T2 and T3. Collecting repeated data from a diverse sample of individuals across multiple states characterized by different initial conditions and policy responses at three time points will allow tracking how risk perceptions and behaviors change over time, how these states’ policies and risk communication influence such changes, and how the effects of similar risk communication approaches vary across states with different pre-COVID structural conditions. These insights inform policy makers’ evolving risk communication strategies about the COVID-19 pandemic in near real-time, as well as generating new knowledge across multiple fields of social science that can inform mitigation of other emerging risks.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/15/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/15/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2030316</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Katherine</FirstName>
<LastName>Dickinson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Katherine L Dickinson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[katherine.dickinson@ucdenver.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000685422</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/15/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Deserai</FirstName>
<LastName>Crow</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Deserai A Crow</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[deserai.crow@ucdenver.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000622933</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/15/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rob</FirstName>
<LastName>DeLeo</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Rob A DeLeo</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[rdeleo@bentley.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000757992</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/15/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Elizabeth</FirstName>
<LastName>Shanahan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Elizabeth A Shanahan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[shanahan@montana.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000086525</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/15/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Elizabeth</FirstName>
<LastName>Koebele</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Elizabeth A Koebele</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ekoebele@unr.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000767471</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/15/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Bentley University</Name>
<CityName>WALTHAM</CityName>
<ZipCode>024524705</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7818912660</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>175 FOREST ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>N6DAMDJXFJ65</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>BENTLEY UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Bentley University]]></Name>
<CityName>Waltham</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>024524705</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[175 Forest Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1321</Code>
<Text>Decision, Risk &amp; Mgmt Sci</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~164638</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Project Outcomes Report</strong></p> <p>Award Title: RAPID: Easing COVID-19 Restrictions: How Variation in State Policy and Public Health Messaging Strategies Impact Risk Perceptions and Behaviors Across Time</p> <p>PI: Rob A. DeLeo, Bentley University</p> <p>Federal Award ID: 2030316</p> <p>In June of 2020, we received a $164,638 NSF award entitled &ldquo;RAPID: Easing COVID-19 Restrictions: How Variation in State Policy and Public Health Messaging Strategies Impact Risk Perceptions and Behaviors Across Time.&rdquo; The project paired data derived from a multi-wave panel survey of individuals in six U.S. states (Louisiana, Massachusetts, Michigan, Colorado, Washington, and Iowa) with public health policy data scraped from state legislative websites to investigate the extent to which individual risk perceptions and behaviors regarding COVID-19 evolved over the course of the pandemic and in response to the easing of COVID-19 policies (e.g., stay-at-home orders, mask mandates, business closures). Our project yielded a number of important outcomes and findings.&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>The Risk and Social Policy Working Group.&nbsp;</strong>Confronting complex global challenges like the COVID-19 pandemic requires transdisciplinary teams of researchers working in partnership with communities and decision-makers to gather evidence and inform effective action. Through the support of this RAPID grant, we were able to convene a national, diverse team of researchers spanning political science, public health, psychology, and communications.&nbsp;&nbsp;We met frequently, often multiple times per week, over the funding period and formed strong bonds that enabled our innovative and adaptive research strategy. We developed a website and used this platform to rapidly disseminate public-facing technical reports after each survey wave. This partnership enabled a second RAPID grant focused on the politicization of COVID-19 vaccine uptake and has created lasting ties that will support future work on COVID-19 and other social-public health-policy challenges.</p> <p><strong>Determinants of Mask Wearing Across Time:</strong>&nbsp;Our project provides insight into how individuals perceive COVID-19 risks and how those risk perceptions relate to risk mitigation behavior. For example, one study explored the key determinants of mask wearing behavior. Whereas previous research suggests mask wearing is tied to sociodemographic factors as well as perceived COVID-19 risks, our findings suggest mask wearing is determined by an individual&rsquo;s ability to wear a mask as well as whether they believe a mask is an effective tool protecting them against COVID-19. A second study, currently under review, shows that individuals who report greater trust for&nbsp;NIAID Director Dr. Anthony Fauci are more likely to wear a mask.&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Policymaking During Disaster:</strong>&nbsp;In addition to studying individual risk perceptions and behaviors across time, we also sought to understand how governments adjust and recalibrate policy in response to changing pandemic conditions. We show that during the early stages of the pandemic, the novelty of the virus coupled with the accumulating cases and deaths catapulted COVID-19 to the top of both the federal and various state government agendas, triggering a flurry of new public health mitigation policies. However, as the pandemic wore on, policy change was often driven by the party affiliation of state policymaker rather than changes in pandemic conditions,&nbsp;namely upticks or downticks in the number of COVID-19 cases. &nbsp;</p> <p><strong>COVID-19 and Structural Racism:</strong>&nbsp;Our work contributed to the robust body of literature demonstrating the impact of longstanding structural inequality health outcomes during the pandemic. For example, we show that essential workers, who were more likely to be Black or Hispanic compared to non-essential workers, were also more likely to be working outside the home early in the pandemic and less likely to be able to practice social distancing and mask wearing consistently. Moreover, Black and Hispanic survey respondents were more likely to experience factors that increase exposure to COVID-19, such as living in larger households and taking public transportation. They were also significantly more likely to know someone who had died of COVID-19.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/02/2022<br>      Modified by: Rob&nbsp;A&nbsp;Deleo</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Project Outcomes Report  Award Title: RAPID: Easing COVID-19 Restrictions: How Variation in State Policy and Public Health Messaging Strategies Impact Risk Perceptions and Behaviors Across Time  PI: Rob A. DeLeo, Bentley University  Federal Award ID: 2030316  In June of 2020, we received a $164,638 NSF award entitled "RAPID: Easing COVID-19 Restrictions: How Variation in State Policy and Public Health Messaging Strategies Impact Risk Perceptions and Behaviors Across Time." The project paired data derived from a multi-wave panel survey of individuals in six U.S. states (Louisiana, Massachusetts, Michigan, Colorado, Washington, and Iowa) with public health policy data scraped from state legislative websites to investigate the extent to which individual risk perceptions and behaviors regarding COVID-19 evolved over the course of the pandemic and in response to the easing of COVID-19 policies (e.g., stay-at-home orders, mask mandates, business closures). Our project yielded a number of important outcomes and findings.   The Risk and Social Policy Working Group. Confronting complex global challenges like the COVID-19 pandemic requires transdisciplinary teams of researchers working in partnership with communities and decision-makers to gather evidence and inform effective action. Through the support of this RAPID grant, we were able to convene a national, diverse team of researchers spanning political science, public health, psychology, and communications.  We met frequently, often multiple times per week, over the funding period and formed strong bonds that enabled our innovative and adaptive research strategy. We developed a website and used this platform to rapidly disseminate public-facing technical reports after each survey wave. This partnership enabled a second RAPID grant focused on the politicization of COVID-19 vaccine uptake and has created lasting ties that will support future work on COVID-19 and other social-public health-policy challenges.  Determinants of Mask Wearing Across Time: Our project provides insight into how individuals perceive COVID-19 risks and how those risk perceptions relate to risk mitigation behavior. For example, one study explored the key determinants of mask wearing behavior. Whereas previous research suggests mask wearing is tied to sociodemographic factors as well as perceived COVID-19 risks, our findings suggest mask wearing is determined by an individual’s ability to wear a mask as well as whether they believe a mask is an effective tool protecting them against COVID-19. A second study, currently under review, shows that individuals who report greater trust for NIAID Director Dr. Anthony Fauci are more likely to wear a mask.   Policymaking During Disaster: In addition to studying individual risk perceptions and behaviors across time, we also sought to understand how governments adjust and recalibrate policy in response to changing pandemic conditions. We show that during the early stages of the pandemic, the novelty of the virus coupled with the accumulating cases and deaths catapulted COVID-19 to the top of both the federal and various state government agendas, triggering a flurry of new public health mitigation policies. However, as the pandemic wore on, policy change was often driven by the party affiliation of state policymaker rather than changes in pandemic conditions, namely upticks or downticks in the number of COVID-19 cases.    COVID-19 and Structural Racism: Our work contributed to the robust body of literature demonstrating the impact of longstanding structural inequality health outcomes during the pandemic. For example, we show that essential workers, who were more likely to be Black or Hispanic compared to non-essential workers, were also more likely to be working outside the home early in the pandemic and less likely to be able to practice social distancing and mask wearing consistently. Moreover, Black and Hispanic survey respondents were more likely to experience factors that increase exposure to COVID-19, such as living in larger households and taking public transportation. They were also significantly more likely to know someone who had died of COVID-19.          Last Modified: 09/02/2022       Submitted by: Rob A Deleo]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
