<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Instantons, Representations and Low Dimensional Topology]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>77450.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>77450</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Swatee Naik</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>snaik@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924876</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Low dimensional topology is an area of mathematics that studies qualities of three- and four-dimensional spaces which are insensitive to continuous deformations such as stretching and bending. These spaces model real world objects and low dimensional topology is highly relevant to other scientific disciplines. For example, knot theory, a branch of low dimensional topology, is an effective tool in studying configurations of protein and DNA. In addition, topology plays an essential role in formulating modern theories in physics. Perhaps more surprisingly, tools from modern physics, more specifically quantum filed theory, have yielded significant progresses in low dimensional topology. This National Science Foundation funded project promotes systematic application of ideas in physics to topology and vice versa.  The PI aims to investigate applications of the Yang-Mills theory of high energy physics in the topological properties of three-and four-dimensional objects. The proposed research also partly focuses on foundational questions in symplectic geometry, a field with close ties with Physics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Instanton Floer homology, defined using Yang-Mills gauge theory, provides algebraic invariants of three- and four-dimensional manifolds. The PI will apply different versions of instanton Floer homology to the study of problems in low dimensional topology. The focus of the first part of the project is the Atiyah-Floer conjecture. This conjecture states that one can apply methods from symplectic geometry to define three-manifold invariants. Furthermore, the resulting invariant, often called symplectic instanton Floer homology, is isomorphic to instanton Floer homology. The PI and his collaborators will develop tools in symplectic topology which can be used to construct new types of symplectic instanton Floer homology. They will also use a certain partial differential equation, called the mixed equation, to address various versions of the Atiyah-Floer conjecture. Another goal of this project is to prove the existence of non-trivial representations of knot groups into the special unitary group SU(N). An outcome of this project would be to give gauge theoretical proofs of the Smith conjecture and the Covering Conjecture. The final goal of this project is to employ instanton Floer homology in the study of the homology cobordism group. The PI recently constructed a family of new invariants for the homology cobordism group using Yang-Mills gauge theory. The PI will apply these invariants to better understand the structure of the homology cobordism group.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/23/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/23/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2030179</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Aliakbar</FirstName>
<LastName>Daemi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Aliakbar Daemi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[adaemi@wustl.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000708492</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/23/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Washington University</Name>
<CityName>SAINT LOUIS</CityName>
<ZipCode>63110</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3147474134</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>ONE BROOKINGS DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MO01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>L6NFUM28LQM5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WASHINGTON UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Washington University in ST. Louis]]></Name>
<CityName>St. Louis</CityName>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>631304899</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[One Brookings drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MO01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1267</Code>
<Text>TOPOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01001819DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~77450</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="root-block-node">One of the fundamental ideas in geometry and topology is to study spaces by examining appropriate functions defined on them. Morse theory exemplifies this concept, asserting that the topology of a smooth manifold can be understood using a Morse function defined on the manifold. Morse homology, which is defined in terms of the critical points of a Morse function, provides a method to organize the information derived from the Morse function. By considering the values of Morse functions at these critical points, it becomes possible to introduce additional structure on Morse homology in the form of a filtration. Morse homology inspired the construction of a powerful range of tools known as Floer homology, which extends the ideas of Morse homology to infinite-dimensional contexts.</p> <p class="root-block-node">There are several different types of Floer homology in low-dimensional homology and symplectic topology, providing powerful tools in these two fields. The present project focuses on instanton Floer homology in low-dimensional topology and Lagrangian Floer homology in symplectic topology. Instanton Floer homology yields a 3-manifold invariant and is defined by applying techniques of Morse theory to the Chern-Simons functional, which is defined on the (infinite-dimensional) space of all connections. In particular, the values of the Chern-Simons functional provide a filtration on instanton Floer homology. These filtrations are employed by the PI to define an invariant called 'Gamma' for an important family of 3-manifolds. A key property of Gamma is that it is well-behaved with respect to cobordisms between 3-manifolds. On the other hand, Lagrangian Floer homology serves as an invariant for a pair of Lagrangians in a symplectic manifold. In desirable cases, it admits a filtration analogous to instanton Floer homology.</p> <p class="root-block-node">One of the main scientific outcomes of this project is the establishment of a version of the Atiyah-Floer conjecture, which provides a connection between instanton Floer homology and Lagrangian Floer homology. Specifically, given a Heegaard splitting&mdash;a decomposition of a 3-manifold&mdash;one obtains a pair of Lagrangians in a symplectic manifold. The Floer homology of these Lagrangians, when well-defined, is referred to as symplectic instanton Floer homology. The Atiyah-Floer conjecture states that instanton Floer homology and its symplectic counterpart are isomorphic. In fact, there exist various approaches to formulate (symplectic) instanton Floer homology, and one of these formulations is known as (symplectic) framed Floer homology. Through this project, it has been demonstrated that this particular version of instanton Floer homology together with its filtration is indeed isomorphic to its symplectic counterpart. This result, along with its method of proof, holds promise for various other applications. For instance, Fukaya and the PI use similar techniques to explore Legendrian contact homology of Legendrians in the 1-jet space of a smooth manifold.</p> <p class="root-block-node">Other outcomes of the project include various applications of the invariant Gamma and related tools in low-dimensional topology. For example, the invariant Gamma is utilized to prove that there exist homology three-spheres that bound definite four-manifolds. However, any such bounding four-manifold must be constructed using a large number of handles. This result specifically demonstrates the existence of an integer homology sphere that bounds a homology ball, but the minimum number of handles in any such homology ball is larger than a given integer N. In another project, employing similar tools, it is shown that certain 3-manifolds cannot be embedded in any closed symplectic 4-manifold, thus disproving a conjecture by Etnyre-Min-Mukherjee. Additionally, in a series of collaborative projects with Chris Scaduto, a collection of knot invariants, including the counterpart of Gamma for knots, is defined. Several topological applications of these invariants are presented, such as demonstrating that there exist knots for which the difference between the (positive) clasp number and the slice genus of the knot can be arbitrarily large.</p> <p class="root-block-node"><br />Beyond the scientific outcomes, the project has had broader impacts through dissemination of results and the training of students. The PI presented progress in various talks, made relevant papers accessible on arXiv and submitted them for publication. Graduate students and researchers actively engaged in the project. For instance, the PI organized several reading groups on topics related to the project. The PI also mentored a graduate student who is working on his PhD thesis and already finished a paper based on a problem related to the project. &nbsp;Additionally, the PI co-organized a summer research program for undergraduate students, providing research experiences in mathematics and focusing on important skills <span>including collaboration, presentations, and report writing.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/30/2023<br>      Modified by: Aliakbar&nbsp;Daemi</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[One of the fundamental ideas in geometry and topology is to study spaces by examining appropriate functions defined on them. Morse theory exemplifies this concept, asserting that the topology of a smooth manifold can be understood using a Morse function defined on the manifold. Morse homology, which is defined in terms of the critical points of a Morse function, provides a method to organize the information derived from the Morse function. By considering the values of Morse functions at these critical points, it becomes possible to introduce additional structure on Morse homology in the form of a filtration. Morse homology inspired the construction of a powerful range of tools known as Floer homology, which extends the ideas of Morse homology to infinite-dimensional contexts. There are several different types of Floer homology in low-dimensional homology and symplectic topology, providing powerful tools in these two fields. The present project focuses on instanton Floer homology in low-dimensional topology and Lagrangian Floer homology in symplectic topology. Instanton Floer homology yields a 3-manifold invariant and is defined by applying techniques of Morse theory to the Chern-Simons functional, which is defined on the (infinite-dimensional) space of all connections. In particular, the values of the Chern-Simons functional provide a filtration on instanton Floer homology. These filtrations are employed by the PI to define an invariant called 'Gamma' for an important family of 3-manifolds. A key property of Gamma is that it is well-behaved with respect to cobordisms between 3-manifolds. On the other hand, Lagrangian Floer homology serves as an invariant for a pair of Lagrangians in a symplectic manifold. In desirable cases, it admits a filtration analogous to instanton Floer homology. One of the main scientific outcomes of this project is the establishment of a version of the Atiyah-Floer conjecture, which provides a connection between instanton Floer homology and Lagrangian Floer homology. Specifically, given a Heegaard splitting&mdash;a decomposition of a 3-manifold&mdash;one obtains a pair of Lagrangians in a symplectic manifold. The Floer homology of these Lagrangians, when well-defined, is referred to as symplectic instanton Floer homology. The Atiyah-Floer conjecture states that instanton Floer homology and its symplectic counterpart are isomorphic. In fact, there exist various approaches to formulate (symplectic) instanton Floer homology, and one of these formulations is known as (symplectic) framed Floer homology. Through this project, it has been demonstrated that this particular version of instanton Floer homology together with its filtration is indeed isomorphic to its symplectic counterpart. This result, along with its method of proof, holds promise for various other applications. For instance, Fukaya and the PI use similar techniques to explore Legendrian contact homology of Legendrians in the 1-jet space of a smooth manifold. Other outcomes of the project include various applications of the invariant Gamma and related tools in low-dimensional topology. For example, the invariant Gamma is utilized to prove that there exist homology three-spheres that bound definite four-manifolds. However, any such bounding four-manifold must be constructed using a large number of handles. This result specifically demonstrates the existence of an integer homology sphere that bounds a homology ball, but the minimum number of handles in any such homology ball is larger than a given integer N. In another project, employing similar tools, it is shown that certain 3-manifolds cannot be embedded in any closed symplectic 4-manifold, thus disproving a conjecture by Etnyre-Min-Mukherjee. Additionally, in a series of collaborative projects with Chris Scaduto, a collection of knot invariants, including the counterpart of Gamma for knots, is defined. Several topological applications of these invariants are presented, such as demonstrating that there exist knots for which the difference between the (positive) clasp number and the slice genus of the knot can be arbitrarily large.  Beyond the scientific outcomes, the project has had broader impacts through dissemination of results and the training of students. The PI presented progress in various talks, made relevant papers accessible on arXiv and submitted them for publication. Graduate students and researchers actively engaged in the project. For instance, the PI organized several reading groups on topics related to the project. The PI also mentored a graduate student who is working on his PhD thesis and already finished a paper based on a problem related to the project.  Additionally, the PI co-organized a summer research program for undergraduate students, providing research experiences in mathematics and focusing on important skills including collaboration, presentations, and report writing.          Last Modified: 06/30/2023       Submitted by: Aliakbar Daemi]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
