<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Winners and Losers when Science Moves Home: Differential Effects of COVID-19 based on Discipline, Caregiving, and Career Stage]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>175687.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>175687</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SMA</Abbreviation>
<LongName>SBE Off Of Multidisciplinary Activities</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Georgia Kosmopoulou</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>gkosmopo@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928760</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[COVID-19 is having widespread—but disparate—effects on the nation's scientific capacity housed in the higher education sector, including the STEM researchers who conduct basic and applied research, and who train future generations of scientists.  One-half of basic research conducted in the United States is performed in the higher education sector, and the federal government finances over half of it.  The research universities, and the academic STEM researchers who are employed by them, are essential to the national science system.  The overarching question of this project is, how do changes brought about by COVID-19 affect the productivity of academic STEM researchers and the science they conduct?  Results will inform policy making to help the core of the nation's research enterprise to meet the challenge of conducting research vital to the nation’s interests during a worldwide pandemic. Although COVID-19 is a specific instance of a macro-level disruption to science, findings from this study will also inform how to build STEM research capacity to be resilient when confronted with future large-scale changes.  Because academic STEM researchers are also student research mentors and educators, understanding adaptations such as use of new technologies, will improve the quality and impact of STEM education and contribute to a better prepared STEM workforce.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In this multi-method study, we study the impacts of macro social disruption and dislocation on patterns of academic productivity, choice of research topics and projects pursed, and sustaining or rethinking patterns of collaboration and teamwork.  The first arm of the study is to conduct semi-structured qualitative interviews of STEM professors in the following broad areas:  large-scale infrastructure-dependent research (e.g., that requiring large congregate specialized research facilities, such as observatories); smaller-scale infrastructure-dependent research (e.g., laboratories located at universities); fieldwork dependent research; applied research; and analytic research.  We expect differences in impact on research productivity across these different types:   We hypothesize that infrastructure-dependent science will be affected more negatively than other modes of science.    In selecting participants in the qualitative arm, we will ensure diversity across a variety of dimensions to test our hypothesis that the COVID-19 crisis will have especially negative impacts on early career researchers, and those with more caretaking responsibilities.  Results from the qualitative arm of the study will enable the development of extensive indices of potential impacts and scientific adjustments, which will then form the basis of a national survey to assess the project's hypotheses on a nationally representative survey of academic scientists.  The study design is longitudinal, including two waves of the survey.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/03/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/03/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2030013</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Stephanie</FirstName>
<LastName>Pfirman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Stephanie L Pfirman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[spfirman@asu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000159076</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/03/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Miki</FirstName>
<LastName>Kittilson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Miki Kittilson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[Miki.Kittilson@asu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000303691</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/03/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Barry</FirstName>
<LastName>Bozeman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Barry Bozeman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[bbozeman@asu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000264174</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/03/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Monica</FirstName>
<LastName>Gaughan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Monica Gaughan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[monica.gaughan@asu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000118011</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/03/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Arizona State University</Name>
<CityName>TEMPE</CityName>
<ZipCode>852813670</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4809655479</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>660 S MILL AVENUE STE 204</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AZ04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NTLHJXM55KZ6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ARIZONA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Arizona State University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>852876011</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AZ04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>110Y</Code>
<Text>SBP-Science of Broadening Part</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>125Y</Code>
<Text>Science of Science</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~175687</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>RAPID: Winners and Losers when Science Moves Home: Differential Effects of COVID-19 based on Discipline, Caregiving, and Career Stage was a just-in-time social science research project undertaken during the Covid-19 pandemic.&nbsp; Our goal was to study how the global shutdowns affected the ability of scientists to continue their scientific work.&nbsp; We interviewed 65 scientists working at research universities in the United States, reviewed documents from national policy making bodies, and tracked policy changes at the university level.</p> <p>As has been demonstrated by other scholarship on pandemic impacts, women and caregivers were particularly negatively affected by Covid-19 shutdowns. Respondents understood these impacts to derive from the general policy failure of the United States with respect to caregiver support.&nbsp; Although respondents recognized that American academic science as an institution plays a role in maintaining barriers to caregivers, the general sense was that the problems flowed from American policy failure.&nbsp; What is interesting about this finding is the attribution of the difficulties to American policy failure rather than failure of university policies.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>Early career researchers and graduate students were also seriously negatively affected; our respondents fear a "lost generation" in many of the scientific disciplines, particularly those that rely on large-scale instrumentation, field work, and bench research.&nbsp; Other scholars are also finding these negative effects on young scholars, which has serious implications for the nation's capacity to conduct critical scientific research in the future.&nbsp; While respondents articulated &nbsp;the need for national policy makers to provide guidance about how to deal with the threats to early career researchers, the locus of responsibility was much more identified in university policies that needed to be changed to accommodate these early career researchers.&nbsp; It is also noteworthy the lengths to which our respondents went to support their students and postdoctoral students through their own finances, both personal and programmatic.</p> <p>Finally, we hypothesized that some disciplines would be more negatively affected than others.&nbsp; What we found were widespread negative impacts on the capacity to conduct research by all respondents, an effect that operated through the significant increases in time devoted to teaching (because of the disruptive shifts to teaching modality for which few academics or universities were prepared).&nbsp; Focusing narrowly on research capacity, we found mixed effects.&nbsp; First, most respondents indicated this was a period of time that allowed them to finish manuscripts, and to exploit extant data sets more fully.&nbsp; In this sense, the forced closures were positive.&nbsp; With respect to long-term impacts, however, there were differential impacts based on research modality (and not discipline, as we originally hypothesized).&nbsp; Analytic researchers&mdash;whether they were in social, physical, or life science disciplines&mdash;reported the fewest negative impacts on their ability to conduct research.&nbsp; Researchers who rely on field work&mdash;again, in all areas of science&mdash;were most negatively affected in that travel restrictions completely shut down research programs.&nbsp; Between these two poles, scientists who rely on laboratories experienced significant curtailment of research capacity, but not as extensive as field researchers.&nbsp; It is also important to note that many scientists have mixed methodological scientific repertoires; these researchers were able to move among modalities in their research program to mitigate negative impacts.&nbsp;</p> <p>In general, the scientists we studied reported an impressive amount of flexibility, ingenuity, and can-do spirit in responding to Covid-19 disruptions to their research programs.&nbsp; From a science policy perspective, however, government and higher education institutions need to evaluate policies and procedures to ensure that the disruptions of the pandemic do not become permanent in the form of lost generations of researchers, or loss of critical scientific infrastructure.&nbsp; Rebounding from Covid-19 is possible, but it will require proactive policy leadership from key actors&mdash;and not just rely on the grit of individual researchers.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/31/2022<br>      Modified by: Monica&nbsp;Gaughan</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ RAPID: Winners and Losers when Science Moves Home: Differential Effects of COVID-19 based on Discipline, Caregiving, and Career Stage was a just-in-time social science research project undertaken during the Covid-19 pandemic.  Our goal was to study how the global shutdowns affected the ability of scientists to continue their scientific work.  We interviewed 65 scientists working at research universities in the United States, reviewed documents from national policy making bodies, and tracked policy changes at the university level.  As has been demonstrated by other scholarship on pandemic impacts, women and caregivers were particularly negatively affected by Covid-19 shutdowns. Respondents understood these impacts to derive from the general policy failure of the United States with respect to caregiver support.  Although respondents recognized that American academic science as an institution plays a role in maintaining barriers to caregivers, the general sense was that the problems flowed from American policy failure.  What is interesting about this finding is the attribution of the difficulties to American policy failure rather than failure of university policies.    Early career researchers and graduate students were also seriously negatively affected; our respondents fear a "lost generation" in many of the scientific disciplines, particularly those that rely on large-scale instrumentation, field work, and bench research.  Other scholars are also finding these negative effects on young scholars, which has serious implications for the nation's capacity to conduct critical scientific research in the future.  While respondents articulated  the need for national policy makers to provide guidance about how to deal with the threats to early career researchers, the locus of responsibility was much more identified in university policies that needed to be changed to accommodate these early career researchers.  It is also noteworthy the lengths to which our respondents went to support their students and postdoctoral students through their own finances, both personal and programmatic.  Finally, we hypothesized that some disciplines would be more negatively affected than others.  What we found were widespread negative impacts on the capacity to conduct research by all respondents, an effect that operated through the significant increases in time devoted to teaching (because of the disruptive shifts to teaching modality for which few academics or universities were prepared).  Focusing narrowly on research capacity, we found mixed effects.  First, most respondents indicated this was a period of time that allowed them to finish manuscripts, and to exploit extant data sets more fully.  In this sense, the forced closures were positive.  With respect to long-term impacts, however, there were differential impacts based on research modality (and not discipline, as we originally hypothesized).  Analytic researchers&mdash;whether they were in social, physical, or life science disciplines&mdash;reported the fewest negative impacts on their ability to conduct research.  Researchers who rely on field work&mdash;again, in all areas of science&mdash;were most negatively affected in that travel restrictions completely shut down research programs.  Between these two poles, scientists who rely on laboratories experienced significant curtailment of research capacity, but not as extensive as field researchers.  It is also important to note that many scientists have mixed methodological scientific repertoires; these researchers were able to move among modalities in their research program to mitigate negative impacts.   In general, the scientists we studied reported an impressive amount of flexibility, ingenuity, and can-do spirit in responding to Covid-19 disruptions to their research programs.  From a science policy perspective, however, government and higher education institutions need to evaluate policies and procedures to ensure that the disruptions of the pandemic do not become permanent in the form of lost generations of researchers, or loss of critical scientific infrastructure.  Rebounding from Covid-19 is possible, but it will require proactive policy leadership from key actors&mdash;and not just rely on the grit of individual researchers.          Last Modified: 12/31/2022       Submitted by: Monica Gaughan]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
