<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Testing Science Communication Strategies and Impact among Policymakers During a National Crisis]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>149950.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>149950</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SMA</Abbreviation>
<LongName>SBE Off Of Multidisciplinary Activities</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Mary Feeney</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mfeeney@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927197</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Given the magnitude of the current crisis caused by COVID-19, it has arguably never been more important for scientists to communicate to policymakers their research on virus transmission, prevention, and social and economic consequences that families face. The time sensitive nature of policymakers’ acquisition and use of information sources regarding COVID-19 presents a unique opportunity to study effective science communication practices and their impact. This proposal aims to capitalize and expand upon recent successes of a theory-based model, the Research-to-Policy Collaboration (RPC), by: (1) facilitating science communication and dissemination among federal and state policymakers, (2) studying mechanisms for improving science communication strategies and (3) testing the impact of science dissemination efforts and added value of scientist interactions with state and federal policymakers.  By getting critical scientific information regarding a current national crisis into the hands of individuals who can act on it, science-based policies may improve the lives of individuals affected by the COVID-19 crisis. We need to identify ways to effectively reach policymakers and inform research communication strategies that can achieve social impact. Scientific information often takes over a decade before it is used in decision making. Effective research dissemination approaches have the potential to shorten that time horizon and improve the societal impact of revolutionary, cutting-edge scientific knowledge.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Study methods involve (1) deploying rapid-cycle randomized controlled trials (RCT) that examine open- and click-rates of emails that disseminate scientific information on COVID-19 to approximately 3,500 federal legislative staff and state legislators and staff who are identified as being assigned to health-related policy issues, and (2) examining the use of research in bill language and public statements (e.g., press releases, social media). Federal legislators will be randomly assigned to three groups: (i) dissemination + interactions, (ii) dissemination only, and (iii) control group. This sampling strategy builds on a current study investigating congressional-researcher interactions facilitated by an active RPC implementation. The proposed study will investigate science dissemination as an add-on component to that interactive approach. State legislators have not been assigned to receive researcher interactions via the active RPC implementation. To increase the reach of time-sensitive information, 75% of state legislators assigned to health-related committees will receive the dissemination and 25% serve as a control group. Observed use of research evidence (URE) will be quantitatively assessed in bill language and public statements, including social media, based on language that was used to validate a URE codebook in prior work. This includes a pre-test period of 1 year prior to US-based responses to COVID-19 (approximately March 1, 2020) and 1-year post-test period following the initial COVID-19 outbreak (March 2021). While the literature illustrates that timeliness and relevance are essential to URE, particularly in times of crisis, studies are needed to examine the impact of science communications and dissemination during such periods of crisis. The proposed work would build the literature base by prospectively assessing the impact of strategies for enhancing evidence use. Importantly, most studies of URE in policymaking have been done retrospectively by asking policymakers to explain how they access research and use it when developing policies. The proposed study will be a substantial asset for the URE field because it will: (1) advance knowledge of what mechanisms are most effective for conveying important and actionable scientific evidence to policymakers at both the federal and state levels and (2) improve our understanding of the impact of real-time science dissemination and interactive approaches.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/20/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/14/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2030660</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jennifer</FirstName>
<LastName>Scott</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>T</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jennifer T Scott</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jxs1622@psu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000825456</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/20/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
<LastName>Crowley</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Daniel M Crowley</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[dmc397@psu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000771431</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/20/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Elizabeth</FirstName>
<LastName>Long</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Elizabeth C Long</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ecl5218@psu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000825026</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/20/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Pennsylvania State Univ University Park</Name>
<CityName>UNIVERSITY PARK</CityName>
<ZipCode>168021503</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8148651372</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>201 OLD MAIN</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>15</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA15</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NPM2J7MSCF61</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>THE PENNSYLVANIA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Pennsylvania State Univ University Park]]></Name>
<CityName>University Park</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>168021503</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[110 Technology Center Building]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>15</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA15</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>125Y</Code>
<Text>Science of Science</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7626</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE OF SCIENCE POLICY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~149950</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The COVID-19 pandemic triggered a surge in research activities, including $4.9 billion for NIH grants and over a quarter of a million results published articles on PubMed related to ?COVID-19?. That research was intended to support the world through the pandemic, and such impact can be best achieved if it reaches decision-makers such as policymakers. However, there has been little work evaluating strategies that support policymakers? acquisition and use of research evidence. This project involved rigorously testing the reach and impact of brief research-based resources for state legislators and staff. This involved two primary aims and methods: (1) improving science communication strategies using rapid-cycle randomized controlled trials (RCTs), (2) experimentally assessing the impact of the dissemination intervention by measuring legislators? use of research evidence. The intervention, SciComm Optimizer for Policy Engagement (SCOPE), was designed based on the theory that researcher-policymaker interactions are important conduits for supporting the use of evidence in policymaking (see Figure 1). The authors of about 32 educational, research-based resources were involved in emailing 4000-7000 state legislators, state staffers, and federal staffers, providing them with a platform for sharing their work as well as technical support for responding to the replies. On average, each dissemination received over 100 replies from and prompted two state legislative requests for meetings with researchers. These meetings provided opportunities for direct collaboration between researchers and policymakers and helped determine what topics might be timely and relevant for policy audiences. The SCOPE model incorporates continuous quality improvements by deploying rapid-cycle RCTs testing science communication strategies. These revealed ten key lessons for sharing science with legislators: 1) cue relevance; 2) keep it short; 3) try to connect as a person; 4) be transparent that the message contains science; 5) do not try to use click-baiting tactics; 6) appeal to authentic, but not inauthentic, emotions; 7) balance the problems with solutions; 8) different policymakers engage with email differently; 9) the timing and political context can impact message engagement; and 10) routinely evaluate these strategies over time and on different subject matters. Further explanation on each of these topics is available here: https://research2policy.org/messaging-science-for-legislators/, and so far three (#1, #6, and #8) have associated manuscripts published in peer-reviewed journals. This study also experimentally tested the impact of the SCOPE model on legislators? use of research evidence language in public documents (bills, statements, and social media). State legislators randomized to the SCOPE intervention, relative to the control group, used more research keywords in their social media posts related to technical concepts (e.g., statistics) and research-based concepts (e.g., social determinants of health), and fewer research keywords related to disseminating new knowledge (see Figure 2). This effect was driven by greater use of phrases about research concepts as well as technical data and analytic phrases, whereas intervention legislators used fewer phrases suggesting a need for more research and dissemination activities (see Figure 3). Among federal legislators, the number of SCOPE dissemination emails they received was not related to how much research they used, and in some cases was associated with less frequent use. However, those who also received a relational intervention (the Research-to-Policy Collaboration model) in addition to the dissemination intervention used more research evidence in statements relative to those who did not receive the relational model when referring to the severity of the problem, solutions to the problem, accountability of the parties implicated in the legislation, and in research-based concepts. Overall, this project uplifted research and the voice of researchers themselves, developed a sustainable model for facilitating and studying science communication, revealed tangible strategies for how to improve researcher-policymaker communication writ large, and ultimately had a documentable impact on the use of research evidence among policymakers.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/22/2022<br>      Modified by: Jennifer&nbsp;T&nbsp;Scott</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2030660/2030660_10700101_1669139981001_fig1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2030660/2030660_10700101_1669139981001_fig1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Science Communication Optimizer for Policy Engagement (SCOPE) Model Steps"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2030660/2030660_10700101_1669139981001_fig1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Science Communication Optimizer for Policy Engagement (SCOPE) Model Steps"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Members of relevant committees receive timely research syntheses directly from researchers. Content is disseminated via field experiments to inform how to increase its reach. Direct contact between researchers and legislators prompts new interactions that create a feedback loop of timely content.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Taylor Scott</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jennifer&nbsp;T&nbsp;Scott</div> <div class="imageTitle">Science Communication Optimizer for Policy Engagement (SCOPE) Model Steps</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2030660/2030660_10700101_1669140040052_fig2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2030660/2030660_10700101_1669140040052_fig2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Main Effect of Intervention on URE in Social Media"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2030660/2030660_10700101_1669140040052_fig2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Main Effect of Intervention on URE in Social Media"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">State legislators receiving the intervention from the RPC produced 24% more COVID-related social media posts with URE than those not in the intervention group, controlling for the effect of state professionalism on zero-inflation.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Megan Collier</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jennifer&nbsp;T&nbsp;Scott</div> <div class="imageTitle">Main Effect of Intervention on URE in Social Media</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2030660/2030660_10700101_1669140152793_Picture3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2030660/2030660_10700101_1669140152793_Picture3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Intervention Effect on URE Categories in COVID-Related Social Media"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2030660/2030660_10700101_1669140152793_Picture3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Intervention Effect on URE Categories in COVID-Related Social Media"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The intervention group produced 67% more posts with Data/Analytics URE, and 28% more Conceptual URE posts than the control group, controlling for the effect of state professionalism on inflation. Legislators in the control group produced 69% more Knowledge Generation posts.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Megan Collier</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jennifer&nbsp;T&nbsp;Scott</div> <div class="imageTitle">Intervention Effect on URE Categories in COVID-Related Social Media</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The COVID-19 pandemic triggered a surge in research activities, including $4.9 billion for NIH grants and over a quarter of a million results published articles on PubMed related to ?COVID-19?. That research was intended to support the world through the pandemic, and such impact can be best achieved if it reaches decision-makers such as policymakers. However, there has been little work evaluating strategies that support policymakers? acquisition and use of research evidence. This project involved rigorously testing the reach and impact of brief research-based resources for state legislators and staff. This involved two primary aims and methods: (1) improving science communication strategies using rapid-cycle randomized controlled trials (RCTs), (2) experimentally assessing the impact of the dissemination intervention by measuring legislators? use of research evidence. The intervention, SciComm Optimizer for Policy Engagement (SCOPE), was designed based on the theory that researcher-policymaker interactions are important conduits for supporting the use of evidence in policymaking (see Figure 1). The authors of about 32 educational, research-based resources were involved in emailing 4000-7000 state legislators, state staffers, and federal staffers, providing them with a platform for sharing their work as well as technical support for responding to the replies. On average, each dissemination received over 100 replies from and prompted two state legislative requests for meetings with researchers. These meetings provided opportunities for direct collaboration between researchers and policymakers and helped determine what topics might be timely and relevant for policy audiences. The SCOPE model incorporates continuous quality improvements by deploying rapid-cycle RCTs testing science communication strategies. These revealed ten key lessons for sharing science with legislators: 1) cue relevance; 2) keep it short; 3) try to connect as a person; 4) be transparent that the message contains science; 5) do not try to use click-baiting tactics; 6) appeal to authentic, but not inauthentic, emotions; 7) balance the problems with solutions; 8) different policymakers engage with email differently; 9) the timing and political context can impact message engagement; and 10) routinely evaluate these strategies over time and on different subject matters. Further explanation on each of these topics is available here: https://research2policy.org/messaging-science-for-legislators/, and so far three (#1, #6, and #8) have associated manuscripts published in peer-reviewed journals. This study also experimentally tested the impact of the SCOPE model on legislators? use of research evidence language in public documents (bills, statements, and social media). State legislators randomized to the SCOPE intervention, relative to the control group, used more research keywords in their social media posts related to technical concepts (e.g., statistics) and research-based concepts (e.g., social determinants of health), and fewer research keywords related to disseminating new knowledge (see Figure 2). This effect was driven by greater use of phrases about research concepts as well as technical data and analytic phrases, whereas intervention legislators used fewer phrases suggesting a need for more research and dissemination activities (see Figure 3). Among federal legislators, the number of SCOPE dissemination emails they received was not related to how much research they used, and in some cases was associated with less frequent use. However, those who also received a relational intervention (the Research-to-Policy Collaboration model) in addition to the dissemination intervention used more research evidence in statements relative to those who did not receive the relational model when referring to the severity of the problem, solutions to the problem, accountability of the parties implicated in the legislation, and in research-based concepts. Overall, this project uplifted research and the voice of researchers themselves, developed a sustainable model for facilitating and studying science communication, revealed tangible strategies for how to improve researcher-policymaker communication writ large, and ultimately had a documentable impact on the use of research evidence among policymakers.       Last Modified: 11/22/2022       Submitted by: Jennifer T Scott]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
