<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: COVID-19 Information Visualizations]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>200000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>200000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Robert O'Connor</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>roconnor@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927263</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[COVID-19 has upended daily life across the globe. Government leaders, medical professions, and the media are communicating the impact of various public health measures such as social distancing by describing predictions of epidemiological models. Social media has been inundated with visualizations that have been created to help communicate the need for these measures. People’s everyday decisions, as well as their support of public health policy, will depend on their understanding of the COVID-19 pandemic. The research identifies the best way to communicate COVID-19 risk data to the public and to help people understand the potential impacts of different behaviors and policies. The public has many questions about what behaviors are safe. If the results show that simulations can help convey the information to the public, simulations that center on specific questions people are asking will be a valuable tool as people navigate the uncertainty surrounding COVID-19. The simulations are available to the general public and shared with the news media.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;People’s everyday decisions, as well as their support of public health policy, will depend on their understanding of the COVID-19 pandemic. Unfortunately, lack of understanding has led to claims that public health officials’ dire warnings are merely scare tactics of propaganda. In general, there is a fundamental misunderstanding and distrust in uncertain simulations of hypothetical data and outcomes. The current project develops visualizations for communicating important risk-related COVID epidemiological models to support comprehension and trust in science-based forecasts and recommendations and improving COVID-related decision making. The research tests key proposed visualization design features to assess their value in the current pandemic. The scholars also determine the influence of individual difference factors (numeracy, trust in science, and current anxiety levels) on the effectiveness of different visualization design features on comprehension of personal and global risk models, trust, and macro- (general actions such as social distancing) and micro-level (using a face mask while shopping) COVID-19 decisions asked before and after experience with the visualizations. The proposed research tests the generalizability of key cognitive principles to visualizations in a real-life context. While prior research has independently considered these factors in artificial contexts, limited work has addressed how these factors interact with each other, and also how the factors influence not only comprehension but also trust and behavioral intentions. If principles developed in these artificial contexts do not generalize to COVID, this would necessitate revision of risk visualization guidelines. Thus, the intellectual impact of this work is to improve our understanding of how to communicate complex risk models to individuals with varying backgrounds and prior beliefs.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/06/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/06/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2030059</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jessica</FirstName>
<LastName>Witt</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>K</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jessica K Witt</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[Jessica.Witt@colostate.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000498726</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/06/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Priti</FirstName>
<LastName>Shah</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Priti R Shah</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[priti@umich.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000580492</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/06/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Eytan</FirstName>
<LastName>Adar</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Eytan Adar</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[eadar@umich.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000543609</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/06/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Twila</FirstName>
<LastName>Tardif</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Twila Tardif</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[twila@umich.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000117369</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/06/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Regents of the University of Michigan - Ann Arbor</Name>
<CityName>ANN ARBOR</CityName>
<ZipCode>481091079</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1109 GEDDES AVE, SUITE 3300</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>GNJ7BBP73WE9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MICHIGAN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Michigan Ann Arbor]]></Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>481091043</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1321</Code>
<Text>Decision, Risk &amp; Mgmt Sci</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~200000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Intellectual Merit</p> <p>COVID-19 upended daily life across the globe. Government leaders, public health experts, and the media had to communicate the impact of various public health measures by describing predictions of epidemiological models or presenting risk data. Nonetheless, many decried that public health warnings were mere scare tactics or propaganda. Unfortunately, trust in the data is associated with public health attitudes and behaviors. Across several studies, we tested how visualizations that improved individual understanding of COVID risk-related data impacted their trust in that data and their attitudes towards public health messages.&nbsp;&nbsp;We found viewing or interacting with explanatory visualizations (process simulations, narrative &ldquo;data-walkthroughs&rdquo;, and animations linking multiple representations of data) led to increased understanding, which in turn had an impact on trust in data, attitudes towards public health messages, and/or behavioral intentions.</p> <p>In one set of studies, we found that viewing a process visualization that provides an &ldquo;under-the-hood&rdquo; view of epidemiological models of disease transmission impacts intentions and attitudes towards social distancing. To understand process visualizations, it may be useful to think of the contrast, a static visualization that shows only the model&rsquo;s outputs. In the context of epidemiology, the output of the model might be the number of active cases of a disease over time. Variations based on specific parameter changes (e.g., disease transmission rates, social distancing measures in place) can also be presented in a comparison visualization. &nbsp;</p> <p>In a second set of studies,&nbsp;we identified a sub-class of narrative visualizations (which we call&nbsp;<em>data walkthroughs</em>) that achieve a balance between the benefits of three common risk communication mediums (static visualizations, interactive simulations, and affect-laden anecdotes). We demonstrated empirically that a data walkthrough mitigates the mistrust induced by a static visualization when communicating COVID-19 transmission risk, and through mediation analysis we showed that data walkthroughs increase trust via a different mechanism compared to anecdotes. We argued that data walkthroughs deserve attention as a distinct class of visualizations that have the potential to be powerful tools for scientific communication (especially in contexts where data are surprising and empiricism is important).</p> <p>In a third set of studies, we sought to test whether people understood the concept of accumulation as it related to common visualizations of COVID data seen in the media (i.e., daily and cumulative case curves). We found that overall, people misunderstood the relationship between daily and cumulative case curves, but their understanding could be improved by interacting with a brief animated video intervention. In fact, participants better understood cumulative growth, in non-disease with effects lasting a minimum of 6-7 weeks after intervention. Most importantly, we found evidence that understanding of the relationship between daily and cumulative cases was associated with greater support for social distancing during a time where social distancing was important for public safety. &nbsp;</p> <p>Together, our studies show that process visualizations (in the form of interactive simulations, narrative visualizations with &ldquo;data walkthroughs&rdquo; that help people understand the etiology of the data, and video explanations can increase understanding and trust in data and, ultimately, attitude towards, and intentions to heed public health recommendations.&nbsp;&nbsp;Our studies enhance our understanding of visualization design and demonstrate the importance of presenting not only static outcome data but process models. Importantly, these results suggest that understanding is a malleable factor for increasing trust, attitudes, and behaviors.</p> <p><em>Broader Impacts</em></p> <p>The research supported by this funding has several practical implications. First, our results suggest presenting process and narrative visualizations that explain how data and predictions are derived may be a useful approach for helping people understand and trust public health data and scientific evidence.&nbsp;&nbsp;Second, our results suggest that such visualizations can help communicate challenging mathematical concepts such as how exponential functions arise.&nbsp;&nbsp;More generally, we show that trust and belief in scientific evidence can be increased with explanations.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/29/2023<br>      Modified by: Priti&nbsp;R&nbsp;Shah</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[    Intellectual Merit  COVID-19 upended daily life across the globe. Government leaders, public health experts, and the media had to communicate the impact of various public health measures by describing predictions of epidemiological models or presenting risk data. Nonetheless, many decried that public health warnings were mere scare tactics or propaganda. Unfortunately, trust in the data is associated with public health attitudes and behaviors. Across several studies, we tested how visualizations that improved individual understanding of COVID risk-related data impacted their trust in that data and their attitudes towards public health messages.  We found viewing or interacting with explanatory visualizations (process simulations, narrative "data-walkthroughs", and animations linking multiple representations of data) led to increased understanding, which in turn had an impact on trust in data, attitudes towards public health messages, and/or behavioral intentions.  In one set of studies, we found that viewing a process visualization that provides an "under-the-hood" view of epidemiological models of disease transmission impacts intentions and attitudes towards social distancing. To understand process visualizations, it may be useful to think of the contrast, a static visualization that shows only the model’s outputs. In the context of epidemiology, the output of the model might be the number of active cases of a disease over time. Variations based on specific parameter changes (e.g., disease transmission rates, social distancing measures in place) can also be presented in a comparison visualization.    In a second set of studies, we identified a sub-class of narrative visualizations (which we call data walkthroughs) that achieve a balance between the benefits of three common risk communication mediums (static visualizations, interactive simulations, and affect-laden anecdotes). We demonstrated empirically that a data walkthrough mitigates the mistrust induced by a static visualization when communicating COVID-19 transmission risk, and through mediation analysis we showed that data walkthroughs increase trust via a different mechanism compared to anecdotes. We argued that data walkthroughs deserve attention as a distinct class of visualizations that have the potential to be powerful tools for scientific communication (especially in contexts where data are surprising and empiricism is important).  In a third set of studies, we sought to test whether people understood the concept of accumulation as it related to common visualizations of COVID data seen in the media (i.e., daily and cumulative case curves). We found that overall, people misunderstood the relationship between daily and cumulative case curves, but their understanding could be improved by interacting with a brief animated video intervention. In fact, participants better understood cumulative growth, in non-disease with effects lasting a minimum of 6-7 weeks after intervention. Most importantly, we found evidence that understanding of the relationship between daily and cumulative cases was associated with greater support for social distancing during a time where social distancing was important for public safety.    Together, our studies show that process visualizations (in the form of interactive simulations, narrative visualizations with "data walkthroughs" that help people understand the etiology of the data, and video explanations can increase understanding and trust in data and, ultimately, attitude towards, and intentions to heed public health recommendations.  Our studies enhance our understanding of visualization design and demonstrate the importance of presenting not only static outcome data but process models. Importantly, these results suggest that understanding is a malleable factor for increasing trust, attitudes, and behaviors.  Broader Impacts  The research supported by this funding has several practical implications. First, our results suggest presenting process and narrative visualizations that explain how data and predictions are derived may be a useful approach for helping people understand and trust public health data and scientific evidence.  Second, our results suggest that such visualizations can help communicate challenging mathematical concepts such as how exponential functions arise.  More generally, we show that trust and belief in scientific evidence can be increased with explanations.              Last Modified: 08/29/2023       Submitted by: Priti R Shah]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
