<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research:  RAPID--Urban Air Quality during the Coronavirus (COVID-19) Shelter-In-Place Orders]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>101072.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>101072</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06020104</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AGS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sylvia Edgerton</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sedgerto@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928522</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[In this RAPID project, a collaborative PI team intends to collect time sensitive atmospheric samples in the Los Angeles, CA, area, where historically high pollutant levels of ozone (O3) and fine particulate matter (PM2.5) have plagued public health. By taking advantage of significant reductions in atmospheric emissions associated with current COVID-19 shelter-in-place orders, a natural experiment has presented itself that allows for observations to be made under uniquely useful conditions. Results will help constrain predictive models of pollutant concentrations and guide regulatory agencies in best strategies to mitigate poor air quality.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Gaseous and particulate samples will be collected during and after the lifting of COVID-19 by co-locating sampling devices on Caltech’s established roof-top sampling platform, where continuous monitoring of essential parameters, including NOx, O3, and PM2.5, is ongoing. Focus in this study is on the detailed chemical speciation of the important precursor group of compounds denoted as volatile to intermediate volatility organic compounds (I/VOCs) containing 1 to 15 carbon atoms (C1-C15). These compounds are emitted through a number of different sources, including from fossil fuel production and burning, use of chemical products, and biological productivity. Their ill-defined sources and reactivities have been attributed to an existing gap in knowledge that could describe higher-than-expected O3 levels in megacities where precursor emissions have seen a general decrease in past decades. Here, I/VOC sources and source markers will be determined during a period when transportation associated emissions to VOCs and NOx are low. State-of-the-art analyses of collected samples at PIs’ laboratories include two-dimensional gas chromatography (GC×GC) with time-of-flight mass spectrometry (TOFMS) and a multi-column/detector GC system with 5 different types of separation and detection combinations. Results will (i) provide new insight into the intricate mechanisms of O3 and PM2.5 production under uniquely low NOx conditions and a changing mix of VOCs, and (ii) help constrain predictive models of atmospheric chemistry and air quality.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/01/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/01/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2030049</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kelley</FirstName>
<LastName>Barsanti</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kelley Barsanti</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[kbarsanti@engr.ucr.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000530551</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/01/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Riverside</Name>
<CityName>RIVERSIDE</CityName>
<ZipCode>925210001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9518275535</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>200 UNIVERSTY OFC BUILDING</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>39</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA39</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>MR5QC5FCAVH5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA AT RIVERSIDE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California, Riverside]]></Name>
<CityName>riverside</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>925072134</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1084 Columbia ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>39</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA39</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1524</Code>
<Text>Atmospheric Chemistry</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~101072</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The 2020 Los Angeles Air Quality (LAAQC-2020) campaign was envisioned to capture atmospheric composition and chemistry during an unprecedented period in our history. A suite of measurements was made in the Los Angeles Basin from mid-April to mid-July 2020; beginning one month after COVID-19 shelter-in-place restrictions were put in place and capturing a gradient of human activity following these restrictions. Our group focused on collection and analysis of volatile organic compounds (VOCs), which serve as precursors for photochemical ozone (O<sub>3</sub>) and fine particulate matter (PM<sub>2.5</sub>). Data were collected 2-3 times/day, 5-7 days/week over the duration of the campaign. These measurements have allowed us and others to test our understanding of O<sub>3 </sub>and PM<sub>2.5 </sub>production under current and future conditions (e.g., negligible passenger vehicle emissions). Our findings support observations in recent peer-reviewed literature that the role of transportation emissions in the formation of O<sub>3</sub> and secondary PM<sub>2.5 </sub>has decreased, and other sources of anthropogenic VOCs play an increasingly important role. Specifically, in the context of combustion emissions, our findings suggested a growing contribution from off-road/other mobile sources relative to on-road sources. We also found that relative to measurements made in 2010, OH exposure is markedly higher, due to decreases in nitrogen oxides (NO<sub>x</sub>) levels over the last decade.</p> <p>Characterizing current chemical conditions and identifying relevant pollutant sources are critical to developing and maintaining accurate chemical models and effective mitigation strategies. The data collected during LAAQC-2020 have been archived and are available for current and future atmospheric composition and chemistry investigations. Such measurements have been repeatedly demonstrated to be critical for understanding atmospheric chemistry and evolving chemical mechanisms and predictive models. Due to the relevance of this work for the regulatory communities that are tasked with developing mitigation strategies and demonstrating compliance with the National Ambient Air Quality Standards (NAAQS) we have communicated our findings with air quality agencies, including the California Air Resources Board and the South Coast Air Quality Management District. The results of this work have been disseminated through scientific publications and networks, &nbsp;integrated into other efforts to understand the impacts of human activities on the earth system more broadly, and have been communicated to undergraduate students and non-scientific audiences.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/24/2023<br>      Modified by: Kelley&nbsp;Barsanti</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2030049/2030049_10667683_1674589276154_VanRooyetal_ACS_basedonTOC--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2030049/2030049_10667683_1674589276154_VanRooyetal_ACS_basedonTOC--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Summary of Major Findings"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2030049/2030049_10667683_1674589276154_VanRooyetal_ACS_basedonTOC--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Summary of Major Findings"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Left: A 30% increase in on-road vehicle miles traveled did not increase median CO (or related VOCs). Over the same time period a 3 K increase in T increased  evaporative emissions. Right: Emissions from the mobile source sector have shifted over the last 10 years influencing atmospheric composition.</div> <div class="imageCredit">https://doi.org/10.1021/acsearthspacechem.1c00248</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Kelley&nbsp;Barsanti</div> <div class="imageTitle">Summary of Major Findings</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2030049/2030049_10667683_1674589760729_ACS_MobileSourceProfileChanges--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2030049/2030049_10667683_1674589760729_ACS_MobileSourceProfileChanges--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Evolution of Mobile Sources in the LA Basin"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2030049/2030049_10667683_1674589760729_ACS_MobileSourceProfileChanges--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Evolution of Mobile Sources in the LA Basin"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Projected emissions of: a) CO, b) VOCs, and c) VOCs:CO from on-road and other/off-road mobile sources in the LA Basin estimated by CARB. The solid line in c) represents the 2010 VOC to CO ratio, the dotted line the 2020 ratio, for all mobile sources (on-road motor vehicles + other mobile sources).</div> <div class="imageCredit">https://doi.org/10.1021/acsearthspacechem.1c00248</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Kelley&nbsp;Barsanti</div> <div class="imageTitle">Evolution of Mobile Sources in the LA Basin</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The 2020 Los Angeles Air Quality (LAAQC-2020) campaign was envisioned to capture atmospheric composition and chemistry during an unprecedented period in our history. A suite of measurements was made in the Los Angeles Basin from mid-April to mid-July 2020; beginning one month after COVID-19 shelter-in-place restrictions were put in place and capturing a gradient of human activity following these restrictions. Our group focused on collection and analysis of volatile organic compounds (VOCs), which serve as precursors for photochemical ozone (O3) and fine particulate matter (PM2.5). Data were collected 2-3 times/day, 5-7 days/week over the duration of the campaign. These measurements have allowed us and others to test our understanding of O3 and PM2.5 production under current and future conditions (e.g., negligible passenger vehicle emissions). Our findings support observations in recent peer-reviewed literature that the role of transportation emissions in the formation of O3 and secondary PM2.5 has decreased, and other sources of anthropogenic VOCs play an increasingly important role. Specifically, in the context of combustion emissions, our findings suggested a growing contribution from off-road/other mobile sources relative to on-road sources. We also found that relative to measurements made in 2010, OH exposure is markedly higher, due to decreases in nitrogen oxides (NOx) levels over the last decade.  Characterizing current chemical conditions and identifying relevant pollutant sources are critical to developing and maintaining accurate chemical models and effective mitigation strategies. The data collected during LAAQC-2020 have been archived and are available for current and future atmospheric composition and chemistry investigations. Such measurements have been repeatedly demonstrated to be critical for understanding atmospheric chemistry and evolving chemical mechanisms and predictive models. Due to the relevance of this work for the regulatory communities that are tasked with developing mitigation strategies and demonstrating compliance with the National Ambient Air Quality Standards (NAAQS) we have communicated our findings with air quality agencies, including the California Air Resources Board and the South Coast Air Quality Management District. The results of this work have been disseminated through scientific publications and networks,  integrated into other efforts to understand the impacts of human activities on the earth system more broadly, and have been communicated to undergraduate students and non-scientific audiences.       Last Modified: 01/24/2023       Submitted by: Kelley Barsanti]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
