<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I: COVID-19: Self-Disinfecting Nanofiber Filters and Reusable Facemasks]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>256000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>256000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Muralidharan Nair</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is a demonstration of a high-quality, self-disinfecting facemask, which is safe, comfortable, and reusable, and will have an immediate impact during the current COVID-19 pandemic. The filter media used in modern facemasks are either inefficient in filtrating submicron size viruses or are difficult to breathe through and highly uncomfortable. Viruses can be active on a facemask for up to one week. With the possibility of contamination and without a self-disinfection function, facemasks must be disposed of after single use. The proposed highly efficient and self-disinfecting filtration technology will solve these problems. The reusability will also directly address the facemask supply shortage as well as waste disposal issue.  In the long term, this technology may be further applied as window screens for blocking and disinfecting airborne pathogen particles. The self-disinfection function could be adapted for other personnel protective equipment as well as for environment self-disinfection and for food packaging, etc.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project will develop an innovative filtration medium for a disruptive facemask technology by effectively capturing submicron particles including viruses via a nanoparticle-functionalized nanofiber mat that has high filtration efficiency and is thin with low air flow resistance.  The technology will also deactivate pathogens in-situ via the   ambient, light-enabled, photocatalytic disinfection function of nanoparticles and the subsequent synergetic effects that include physical and chemical disruption of virus membranes and their RNA/DNA. The functionalized catalysts absorb ambient light, producing reactive oxygen species to disinfect pathogens, while the plasmonic effects enhance the light absorption. The charged nanoparticles are firmly embedded on the electrospun nanofibers, and the resulted surface irregularity, the improved charge density, and the hydrophilic absorption further boost the filtration and trapping efficiency through mechanical and electrostatic capture of aerosol particles. Taken together, all these effects may lead to a highly efficient, breathable, reusable facemask with in-situ self-disinfection functionality to combat highly infectious viruses and a broad spectrum of pathogens.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/21/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/11/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2030197</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Amita</FirstName>
<LastName>Nakarmi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Amita Nakarmi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[itanakarmi30@gmail.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000846976</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/11/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yujiao</FirstName>
<LastName>Zu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Yujiao Zu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[yujiao.zu1230@gmail.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000825451</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/21/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate>02/11/2021</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>BAONANO, LLC</Name>
<CityName>CHANDLER</CityName>
<ZipCode>852864210</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8063170744</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1370 W JAVELINA DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AZ05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>XAZKD2FRZB82</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>BAONANO, LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[BaoNano, LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>Lubbock</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>794099805</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3911 4th St.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>19</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX19</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>6840</Code>
<Text>ROBOTICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8034</Code>
<Text>Hardware Components</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~256000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The quick spread of the COVID-19 virus has been causing tremendous life and economic losses all over the world. Although the successful development of vaccines gave direct and timely solution to prevent more worsen situations from happening, the COVID-19 virus and the newly appeared variants are still a great danger to the human being. The transmission of these viruses is mainly via aerosols, meaning that the viruses can easily spread in the air and infect people through the respiratory system. Face masks turn out to be the last line of defense against virus transmission, and their importance goes without saying. However, the currently available facemasks including surgical masks and N-95 respirators are either not efficient in infiltrating the submicron size viruses or having high airflow resistance causing uncomfortableness. Moreover, their lack of reusability caused severe supply shortages, materials waste, and environmental pollution.</p> <p>Aiming to solve these urgent issues, BaoNano, LLC has been developing its unique functional filter materials, which are comprised of nanoparticles composited with nanofibers (NP-NF), and the related filtration technology. Unlike the traditional filters using micron-scale fibers, our nanofiber-based filters can efficiently block submicron pathogens and in particular, the incorporated nanoparticles provide the disinfection function to kill the blocked viruses and bacteria. Thus, the innovative filters from BaoNano have a much thinner thickness to guarantee lower airflow resistance and better breathability in the mask, and more importantly, the self-disinfection function ensures the blocked viruses and bacteria being killed, thus improving the safety and longevity of the mask products.</p> <p>In this phase I project, BaoNano successfully demonstrated the proof-of-concept of NP-NF based facemasks and achieved the three main goals proposed for the phase I period: 1) We developed nanofiber-based filters with high particle filtration efficiency and low airflow resistance. We established the electrospinning system and process to produce the polymer-based nanofiber films, including optimizing the related parameters such as polymer solution concentration, voltage, temperature, pump speed, etc.; We synthesized TiO<sub>2</sub>-Ag nanoparticles through the wet-chemical method and incorporate them into polymer nanofibers to obtain the functionalized nanofiber films; We studied the physicochemical features of the nanofiber films and mask-related tests including particle filtration, breathability, etc. 2) We tested disinfection capability of the functionalized nanofiber films, including their antiviral capability and their antibacterial capability. 3) We developed functionalized fabric-based face masks. We modified face mask fabrics using functionalized nanofiber films, prepared prototype face masks and conducted standard tests including latex particle filtration efficiency, bacterial filtration efficiency, and differential pressure tests.</p> <p>The results of the research conducted in this NSF SBIR Phase I project demonstrate the commercial feasibility of our nanofiber-based self-disinfection facemask technology. The Phase I outcomes lay the foundation for the expansion of R&amp;D to create prototyping devices and the subsequent commercialization. Our customer discovery and market research have verified some niche market segments for our facemask technology, and potentially our nanofiber-based self-disinfection filtration technology may also be applied for air filters and air purifiers.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/09/2021<br>      Modified by: Amita&nbsp;Nakarmi</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The quick spread of the COVID-19 virus has been causing tremendous life and economic losses all over the world. Although the successful development of vaccines gave direct and timely solution to prevent more worsen situations from happening, the COVID-19 virus and the newly appeared variants are still a great danger to the human being. The transmission of these viruses is mainly via aerosols, meaning that the viruses can easily spread in the air and infect people through the respiratory system. Face masks turn out to be the last line of defense against virus transmission, and their importance goes without saying. However, the currently available facemasks including surgical masks and N-95 respirators are either not efficient in infiltrating the submicron size viruses or having high airflow resistance causing uncomfortableness. Moreover, their lack of reusability caused severe supply shortages, materials waste, and environmental pollution.  Aiming to solve these urgent issues, BaoNano, LLC has been developing its unique functional filter materials, which are comprised of nanoparticles composited with nanofibers (NP-NF), and the related filtration technology. Unlike the traditional filters using micron-scale fibers, our nanofiber-based filters can efficiently block submicron pathogens and in particular, the incorporated nanoparticles provide the disinfection function to kill the blocked viruses and bacteria. Thus, the innovative filters from BaoNano have a much thinner thickness to guarantee lower airflow resistance and better breathability in the mask, and more importantly, the self-disinfection function ensures the blocked viruses and bacteria being killed, thus improving the safety and longevity of the mask products.  In this phase I project, BaoNano successfully demonstrated the proof-of-concept of NP-NF based facemasks and achieved the three main goals proposed for the phase I period: 1) We developed nanofiber-based filters with high particle filtration efficiency and low airflow resistance. We established the electrospinning system and process to produce the polymer-based nanofiber films, including optimizing the related parameters such as polymer solution concentration, voltage, temperature, pump speed, etc.; We synthesized TiO2-Ag nanoparticles through the wet-chemical method and incorporate them into polymer nanofibers to obtain the functionalized nanofiber films; We studied the physicochemical features of the nanofiber films and mask-related tests including particle filtration, breathability, etc. 2) We tested disinfection capability of the functionalized nanofiber films, including their antiviral capability and their antibacterial capability. 3) We developed functionalized fabric-based face masks. We modified face mask fabrics using functionalized nanofiber films, prepared prototype face masks and conducted standard tests including latex particle filtration efficiency, bacterial filtration efficiency, and differential pressure tests.  The results of the research conducted in this NSF SBIR Phase I project demonstrate the commercial feasibility of our nanofiber-based self-disinfection facemask technology. The Phase I outcomes lay the foundation for the expansion of R&amp;D to create prototyping devices and the subsequent commercialization. Our customer discovery and market research have verified some niche market segments for our facemask technology, and potentially our nanofiber-based self-disinfection filtration technology may also be applied for air filters and air purifiers.             Last Modified: 12/09/2021       Submitted by: Amita Nakarmi]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
