<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Structure of Membrane-Bound Fusion Peptide of SARS-CoV-2 Required for Infection]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>200000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>220184</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>MCB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jaroslaw Majewski</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jmajewsk@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927278</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The 2019 novel coronavirus spread quickly and became a global pandemic. Infection by an enveloped virus, like SARS-CoV-2, requires fusion of the viral membrane with a host cell membrane. This NSF Rapid Response Research (RAPID) project will support studies to characterize a coronavirus fusion peptide before and after it binds to the cell membrane. The understanding of this process will inform the active development of vaccines and antibodies. The scientific activities will provide a special opportunity for the PI and his lab members to show local high school students how basic research can assist technology development to safeguard public health and safety.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR)-guided studies of SARS-CoV-2 docking into the human cells will provide the first structural models of lipid bilayer coordinates bound to a viral fusion peptide, thereby providing details of fusion peptide manipulation of the lipids. The results will prompt immune developers to consider the presence and format of the fusion peptide as antigen. The dynamic structure of the unbound state of the fusion peptide should represent its behavior as a solvent-exposed antigen and the structure of its bilayer-associated state will inform about sites accessible to antibodies outside the bilayer. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This RAPID award is made by the Molecular Biophysics Program in the Division of Molecular and Cellular Biosciences, using funds from the Coronavirus Aid, Relief, and Economic Security (CARES) Act.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/27/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/08/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2030473</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Steven</FirstName>
<LastName>Van Doren</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Steven R Van Doren</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[vandorens@missouri.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000392443</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/27/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Missouri-Columbia</Name>
<CityName>COLUMBIA</CityName>
<ZipCode>652113020</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5738827560</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>121 UNIVERSITY HALL</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MO03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>SZPJL5ZRCLF4</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MISSOURI SYSTEM</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Missouri-Columbia]]></Name>
<CityName>Columbia</CityName>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>652115100</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[117 Schweitzer Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MO03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1144</Code>
<Text>Molecular Biophysics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>158Y</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7465</Code>
<Text>NANOSCALE BIO CORE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>1N20</Code>
<Name>R&amp;RA CARES Act DEFC N</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002223DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>010N2021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[R&RA CARES Act DEFC N]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~200000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2022~20184</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Infection by SARS-CoV-2 joins the surface of the virus particle with the cell. This uses the fusion peptide part of Spike. The fusion peptide shifts its shape to its environment, which changes during infection.</p> <p><strong>Intellectual Merit</strong></p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; This project found the fusion peptide to adopt a wedge shape in simple membranes. Three spiral-shaped helices came together to form this wedge in the membrane. (The first of these helices is targeted by antibodies recently reported to protect against varied coronaviruses.) The project found the fusion peptide to insert some charged amino acids into membranes and disturb the membrane in the process. Part of the apparent disturbance appears to result from the fusion peptide bringing water with it into the membrane. --Simulations and experiments agreed on this water recruitment. &nbsp;The fusion peptide was also simulated to pinch the membrane and move the fatty acids around in the membrane. The membrane distortions could aid the approach and merger of the viral and host cell membranes, to help infections proceed.</p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts</strong></p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Training component: Three undergraduate students, one ethnically underrepresented in science, and another young scientist gained research experience. &nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Conceptual component: The membrane pinching and water recruitment into the membrane observed is attributable to insertion of charge into the membrane. These behaviors can be expected where other key proteins insert charge into a membrane.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/31/2023<br>      Modified by: Steven&nbsp;R&nbsp;Van Doren</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2030473/2030473_10666280_1690831007218_FPfoldb--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2030473/2030473_10666280_1690831007218_FPfoldb--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 1. The shape of the fusion peptide of SARS-CoV-2 in a membrane-like environment"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2030473/2030473_10666280_1690831007218_FPfoldb--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 1. The shape of the fusion peptide of SARS-CoV-2 in a membrane-like environment"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The backbone of the experimental structure is shown with a ribbon. The three side chains plotted in ball-and-stick style represent charged, membrane-penetrating amino acids.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Steven R. Van Doren</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Steven&nbsp;R&nbsp;Van Doren</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 1. The shape of the fusion peptide of SARS-CoV-2 in a membrane-like environment</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2030473/2030473_10666280_1690831548639_membr_distort--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2030473/2030473_10666280_1690831548639_membr_distort--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 2. Simulated membrane insertion and deformation by the SARS-CoV-2 fusion peptide"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2030473/2030473_10666280_1690831548639_membr_distort--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 2. Simulated membrane insertion and deformation by the SARS-CoV-2 fusion peptide"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The small dots represent water. The fusion peptide is plotted with a gold backbone ribbon and the sidechains of the three membrane-disturbing amino acids. These amino acids appear to promote the pinching of the membrane and water recruitment into the membrane.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Steven Van Doren et al. (2023, Structure, in press)</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Steven&nbsp;R&nbsp;Van Doren</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 2. Simulated membrane insertion and deformation by the SARS-CoV-2 fusion peptide</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Infection by SARS-CoV-2 joins the surface of the virus particle with the cell. This uses the fusion peptide part of Spike. The fusion peptide shifts its shape to its environment, which changes during infection.  Intellectual Merit       This project found the fusion peptide to adopt a wedge shape in simple membranes. Three spiral-shaped helices came together to form this wedge in the membrane. (The first of these helices is targeted by antibodies recently reported to protect against varied coronaviruses.) The project found the fusion peptide to insert some charged amino acids into membranes and disturb the membrane in the process. Part of the apparent disturbance appears to result from the fusion peptide bringing water with it into the membrane. --Simulations and experiments agreed on this water recruitment.  The fusion peptide was also simulated to pinch the membrane and move the fatty acids around in the membrane. The membrane distortions could aid the approach and merger of the viral and host cell membranes, to help infections proceed.  Broader Impacts       Training component: Three undergraduate students, one ethnically underrepresented in science, and another young scientist gained research experience.         Conceptual component: The membrane pinching and water recruitment into the membrane observed is attributable to insertion of charge into the membrane. These behaviors can be expected where other key proteins insert charge into a membrane.          Last Modified: 07/31/2023       Submitted by: Steven R Van Doren]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
