<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Longitudinal Modeling of Teams and Teamwork during the COVID-19 Crisis]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>197667.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>197667</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Songqi Liu</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>soliu@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928950</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The ability to effectively work as a team is essential to meet the demands of the modern world and workforce. However, the COVID-19 crisis has drastically changed how teams collaborate, including periods of extended remote work, mixed remote and in-person teams, blurred home and work boundaries, elevated stress and anxiety, and extreme uncertainty about the future. The swift onset of the crisis required individuals, teams, and organizations to abruptly adapt to rapidly changing circumstances with little to no preparation. The proposed research will investigate disruptions to teamwork and how teams adapt during the COVID-19 crisis and in the ensuing recovery period. The project will investigate 30 real-world teams over a three-month period while in the midst of the crisis and for an additional one-month follow-up as events unfold. The goal is to understand how teams respond to changing contexts, how teams support each other, how conflict is managed, and how teams develop, adapt, and sustain the rhythms of teamwork during COVID-19 and in the ensuing recovery period. This foundational research will be essential to help organizations establish team structures and collaborative processes that enable them to more successfully address disruptions in the current and in future crises. The project will provide unique opportunities for interdisciplinary training of students in computer science and psychology, will broaden participation by recruiting diverse students, and will share a rich and unique dataset with the broad scientific community.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;The specific aims are to: (1) understand states, processes, and behaviors (e.g., team cohesion, communication patterns, collective stress) of teams during the COVID-19 crisis with a focus on factors associated with team performance; (2) investigate how individuals and teams experience and adapt to major COVID-related life events, such as school closings, enforcing of social distancing, budget cuts, illnesses, and so on; and (3) identify patterns in team states and behaviors over time, detect disruptions to these patterns, and study how new patterns emerge during the crisis and in the ensuing period of recovery. The project will use wearable sensors to track heart rate, sleep, physical activity, and relative location (home or away), communication tools (e.g., team calendars, email metadata), ecological momentary assessments (EMAs), validated survey instruments, and semi-structured interviews to investigate team states, team processes, team behaviors, and team performances in context and over time. The findings will contribute basic knowledge on teaming under the unique context of COVID-19, what factors are associated with team performance, and whether changes teams adopt are temporary or permanent.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/25/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/25/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2030599</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sidney</FirstName>
<LastName>D'Mello</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sidney D'Mello</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[sidney.dmello@gmail.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000744176</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/25/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Aaron</FirstName>
<LastName>Striegel</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Aaron D Striegel</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[striegel@nd.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000390401</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/25/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Colorado at Boulder</Name>
<CityName>BOULDER</CityName>
<ZipCode>803090001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3034926221</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3100 MARINE ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[STE 481 572 UCB]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>SPVKK1RC2MZ3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>THE REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF COLORADO</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Colorado at Boulder]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>803031058</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8031</Code>
<Text>SoO-Science Of Organizations</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~197667</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><br id="docs-internal-guid-887d9d16-7fff-271a-0ef5-fc2e44aa91fc" /></p> <p style="line-height: 1.2; margin-top: 0pt; margin-bottom: 12pt;" dir="ltr"><span style="font-size: 12pt; font-family: 'Times New Roman'; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">The ability to effectively work as a team is an essential skill to meet the demands of the modern world and its workforce. However, the COVID-19 crisis drastically changed the nature of work and how teams collaborate. At the onset of this project (starting Fall 2020), previously co-located teams were engaged in extended remote work with home and work boundaries becoming blurred (if not eliminated); the stay-at-home orders and the economic shutdown caused considerable financial strain for people and organizations; almost everyone (at least knew someone who) was experiencing elevated stress and anxiety brought on by personal, work-related, and societal factors; and there was widespread uncertainty about what would come next. The swift onset of the pandemic required individuals, teams, and organizations to abruptly adapt to rapidly changing circumstances with little to no preparation.&nbsp;</span></p> <p style="line-height: 1.2; margin-top: 0pt; margin-bottom: 12pt;" dir="ltr"><span style="font-size: 12pt; font-family: 'Times New Roman'; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">Accordingly, this project investigated disruptions to teamwork and associated adaptation strategies during the COVID-19 crisis and in the ensuing transition to a ?new normal? of work and teamwork. We used longitudinal precision tracking (using behavioral/physiological sensing) to enable a deep understanding of how teams responded to changing context, how teams supported each other, how conflict was managed, and how teams developed, adapted, and sustained the rhythms of teamwork during COVID-19.&nbsp;</span></p> <p style="line-height: 1.2; margin-top: 0pt; margin-bottom: 12pt;" dir="ltr"><span style="font-size: 12pt; font-family: 'Times New Roman'; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">The main outcomes of this two year project include:</span></p> <ul style="margin-top: 0; margin-bottom: 0; padding-inline-start: 48px;"> <li style="list-style-type: disc; font-size: 12pt; font-family: 'Times New Roman'; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre;" dir="ltr"><span style="font-size: 12pt; font-family: 'Times New Roman'; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: bold; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">Longitudinal, multimodal data. </span><span style="font-size: 12pt; font-family: 'Times New Roman'; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">Collection of longitudinal, multimodal data from real-world teams by utilizing consumer-grade wearable sensors that track heart rate, sleep duration, physical activity, and relative location (home or away), communication tools (e.g., team calendars), ecological momentary assessments (EMAs), validated survey instruments, and semi-structured interviews to understand team states, processes, (e.g., team affect, team conflict, communication), and performance in context and over time.</span> </li> <li style="list-style-type: disc; font-size: 12pt; font-family: 'Times New Roman'; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre;" dir="ltr"><span style="font-size: 12pt; font-family: 'Times New Roman'; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: bold; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">Latent diversity:</span><span style="font-size: 12pt; font-family: 'Times New Roman'; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;"> Identifying the concept of latent diversity. In the wake of the abrupt transition to working from home, participants became aware of latent diversities that had remained inconspicuous and predominantly inconsequential while teams had been working in the office. These included diversity in the homelife responsibilities of team members as well as their diverse work rhythms and sleep/wake cycles.</span> </li> <li style="list-style-type: disc; font-size: 12pt; font-family: 'Times New Roman'; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre;" dir="ltr"><span style="font-size: 12pt; font-family: 'Times New Roman'; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: bold; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">Sleep alignment.</span><span style="font-size: 12pt; font-family: 'Times New Roman'; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;"> Documenting a curvilinear relationship between team members? misalignment in sleep behaviors (bedtime, waketime, sleep duration) and their perceptions of teamwork in that too much or too little alignment (as sensed via the wearable device) was found to be negatively associated with teamwork.</span> </li> <li style="list-style-type: disc; font-size: 12pt; font-family: 'Times New Roman'; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: bold; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre;" dir="ltr"><span style="font-size: 12pt; font-family: 'Times New Roman'; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: bold; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">Work location. </span><span style="font-size: 12pt; font-family: 'Times New Roman'; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">Finding that work location (private home office, shared home office, workplace) was not associated with team members? perceptions of teamwork. However, the association of work location with team conflict was moderated both by job autonomy and the degree of task interdependence in the team.</span> </li> <li style="list-style-type: disc; font-size: 12pt; font-family: 'Times New Roman'; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: bold; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre;" dir="ltr"><span style="font-size: 12pt; font-family: 'Times New Roman'; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: bold; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">Emotion contagion. </span><span style="font-size: 12pt; font-family: 'Times New Roman'; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">Discovering that supervisors? positive affect influenced their team members? positive affect and that team members? negative affect influenced their supervisors negative affect. In other words, positive affect flows downwards (from supervisors to members) whereas negative affect flows upwards (from members to supervisors)</span> </li> </ul> <p style="line-height: 1.2; margin-top: 0pt; margin-bottom: 12pt;" dir="ltr">&nbsp;</p> <p style="line-height: 1.2; margin-top: 0pt; margin-bottom: 12pt;" dir="ltr"><span style="font-size: 12pt; font-family: 'Times New Roman'; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">Broader impacts of the research include dissemination of the findings in seven publications, one community talk on the future of teamwork, a keynote, partly supporting two PhD students and two part-time postdoctoral researchers. In terms of societal impact, this foundational research, which could only be meaningfully conducted in the context of an authentic crisis, will be essential to prepare future teams to collaborate effectively in similar circumstances. Specifically, this research helped shed light on the structures and rhythms of teams to understand how teams adapted to the crisis. This can have impacts in helping organizations establish team structures and collaborative processes that enable them to more successfully address disruptions caused by this and future crises and thrive in the new normal of work from home.</span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/16/2022<br>      Modified by: Sidney&nbsp;D'mello</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  The ability to effectively work as a team is an essential skill to meet the demands of the modern world and its workforce. However, the COVID-19 crisis drastically changed the nature of work and how teams collaborate. At the onset of this project (starting Fall 2020), previously co-located teams were engaged in extended remote work with home and work boundaries becoming blurred (if not eliminated); the stay-at-home orders and the economic shutdown caused considerable financial strain for people and organizations; almost everyone (at least knew someone who) was experiencing elevated stress and anxiety brought on by personal, work-related, and societal factors; and there was widespread uncertainty about what would come next. The swift onset of the pandemic required individuals, teams, and organizations to abruptly adapt to rapidly changing circumstances with little to no preparation.  Accordingly, this project investigated disruptions to teamwork and associated adaptation strategies during the COVID-19 crisis and in the ensuing transition to a ?new normal? of work and teamwork. We used longitudinal precision tracking (using behavioral/physiological sensing) to enable a deep understanding of how teams responded to changing context, how teams supported each other, how conflict was managed, and how teams developed, adapted, and sustained the rhythms of teamwork during COVID-19.  The main outcomes of this two year project include:  Longitudinal, multimodal data. Collection of longitudinal, multimodal data from real-world teams by utilizing consumer-grade wearable sensors that track heart rate, sleep duration, physical activity, and relative location (home or away), communication tools (e.g., team calendars), ecological momentary assessments (EMAs), validated survey instruments, and semi-structured interviews to understand team states, processes, (e.g., team affect, team conflict, communication), and performance in context and over time.  Latent diversity: Identifying the concept of latent diversity. In the wake of the abrupt transition to working from home, participants became aware of latent diversities that had remained inconspicuous and predominantly inconsequential while teams had been working in the office. These included diversity in the homelife responsibilities of team members as well as their diverse work rhythms and sleep/wake cycles.  Sleep alignment. Documenting a curvilinear relationship between team members? misalignment in sleep behaviors (bedtime, waketime, sleep duration) and their perceptions of teamwork in that too much or too little alignment (as sensed via the wearable device) was found to be negatively associated with teamwork.  Work location. Finding that work location (private home office, shared home office, workplace) was not associated with team members? perceptions of teamwork. However, the association of work location with team conflict was moderated both by job autonomy and the degree of task interdependence in the team.  Emotion contagion. Discovering that supervisors? positive affect influenced their team members? positive affect and that team members? negative affect influenced their supervisors negative affect. In other words, positive affect flows downwards (from supervisors to members) whereas negative affect flows upwards (from members to supervisors)     Broader impacts of the research include dissemination of the findings in seven publications, one community talk on the future of teamwork, a keynote, partly supporting two PhD students and two part-time postdoctoral researchers. In terms of societal impact, this foundational research, which could only be meaningfully conducted in the context of an authentic crisis, will be essential to prepare future teams to collaborate effectively in similar circumstances. Specifically, this research helped shed light on the structures and rhythms of teams to understand how teams adapted to the crisis. This can have impacts in helping organizations establish team structures and collaborative processes that enable them to more successfully address disruptions caused by this and future crises and thrive in the new normal of work from home.       Last Modified: 09/16/2022       Submitted by: Sidney D'mello]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
