<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: IIBR Informatics: Predicting All-atom Structure of SARS-CoV-2 Related Protein Complex from 3D Cryo-Electron Microscopy Data]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>200000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>200000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DBI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jean Gao</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The outbreak of novel coronavirus disease (COVID-19) has caused a global pandemic. Knowledge on the molecular basis of novel coronavirus (SARS-CoV-2) related protein complexes is essential to providing insight of the virus and how it infects human cells, a first step in developing novel drugs and vaccines to combat SARS-CoV-2. This study will enable development of all-atom structure prediction of CoV-related protein complexes, including complex surfaces of human cells the virus infects. Prediction results will be broadly and quickly disseminated through interactive web applications to maximize the impact of the research. The results will lead to a broad range of biomedical applications, such as a better understanding of important biological functions, disease processes, development of novel drugs and vaccines, and improved preventive therapies leading to reduced health care costs. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project seeks to study ab initio all-atom structure prediction of CoV-related protein complexes based on electron cryo-microscopy (cryo-EM). Methods based on the state-of-the-art technologies of image processing for pre-processing the data, deep learning for complex structure prediction, and dynamic optimization for final refinement to reveal fundamental mechanisms of CoV-related macromolecules will be developed. The project will also provide an open-source and interactive web portal for public access of the developed tools. The work could have immediate impact on steps taken to halt the spread of SARS-CoV-2 and the current pandemic. Training opportunities for students at all levels, particularly women and underrepresented minorities will also be carried out. The results of the project can be found at: http://faculty.washington.edu/dongsi.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This RAPID award is made by the Infrastructure Innovation for Biological Research (IIBR Informatics) Program in the Division of Biological Infrastructure, using funds from the Coronavirus Aid, Relief, and Economic Security (CARES) Act.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/20/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/20/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2030381</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dong</FirstName>
<LastName>Si</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Dong Si</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[dongsi@uw.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000745461</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/20/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Washington</Name>
<CityName>SEATTLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>981951016</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2065434043</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4333 BROOKLYN AVE NE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>HD1WMN6945W6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF WASHINGTON</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Washington Bothell]]></Name>
<CityName>Bothell</CityName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>980118246</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[18115 Campus Way NE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WA01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>158Y</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1165</Code>
<Text>ADVANCES IN BIO INFORMATICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>1N20</Code>
<Name>R&amp;RA CARES Act DEFC N</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>010N2021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[R&RA CARES Act DEFC N]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~200000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Intellectual merit:</p> <p>This project developed methods of geometric modeling, artificial intelligence, and computational biology to provide a biophysical characterization of SARS-CoV-2 and other CoV-related protein complexes using cryo-electron microscopy (cryo-EM) (Figure 1). This project revealed information that is relevant to the function and potential targeting and disruption of the viruses.</p> <p>We developed&nbsp;fast,&nbsp;accurate, and&nbsp;fully automated de novo&nbsp;protein&nbsp;large complex&nbsp;structure prediction from a 3D electron density map and conducted case studies on CoV-related data (Pfab et al. PNAS 2021). We introduced deep learning methods and optimization techniques to predict the locations of atoms, secondary structure elements, and amino acid types. The work has been highlighted in Nature Computational Science (Chirigati, F. Predicting protein structure from cryo-EM data.&nbsp;Nat Comput Sci&nbsp;1,&nbsp;96, 2021).</p> <p>We developed an interactive web portal <a href="https://deeptracer.uw.edu/covid">https://deeptracer.uw.edu/covid</a> for public access to the CoV-related predictions. The work could have an immediate impact on steps taken to halt the spread of SARS-CoV-2 and the current pandemic. The web portal automatically updates the predictions for the&nbsp;new CoV-related EM data. The interactive web applications provide workflows for stages from data uploading, modeling, and tools that facilitate visualization and evaluation of the prediction process. The predictions include atomic protein structures of SARS-CoV-2, SARS-CoV, MERS-CoV, H-CoV, MHV, AIBV, FIPV, PD-CoV, PEDV, Spike, Non-Spike, ACE2 receptor, Fab, Polymerase, Ribosome. Which are the key entities involved in the molecular mechanism of COVID-19. Our work successfully built the atomic models for the CoV-related EM maps, especially for the ones that have&nbsp;no previous deposited model structure available in the data bank.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Broader of impacts:</p> <p>We remain steadfast and dedicated to the global fight against SARS-CoV-2 (COVID-19) with our DeepTracer web server and COV-related prediction web portal. The project and results could have led to a broad range of biomedical applications, such as a better understanding of important biological functions, disease processes, the development of novel drugs and vaccines, and improved preventive therapies leading to reduced health care costs. The methods and results developed in this project have been broadly disseminated to multiple communities including biology, biochemistry, health science, and pharmaceutical sciences. The data mining and artificial intelligence techniques developed in this project are very likely to be applicable for solving the computational problems from the closely related 3D volume data generated from different imaging techniques, and those in which one has to deal with data errors and noises.</p> <p>The research has concretely demonstrated the applicability of data mining from the 3DEMDaraResource and the use of sophisticated deep learning methods for fast, accurate, and fully automated protein structure determination from COVID-related EM data.&nbsp;The computational methods and tools developed in this project have been used to interpret&nbsp;large&nbsp;molecular assemblies&nbsp;that have important biological functions such as viruses and cellular machines. Understanding these mechanisms is crucial for designing drugs and vaccines for current and future pandemics.</p> <p>The project has been supporting the mentorship and training of high school, undergraduate, and graduate students both in the conduct of research and in the mentorship of more junior students. This project attracted more than thirty students in multiple disciplines including&nbsp;Computer Science, Biology, Chemistry, Physics, Health Science, Information Science, and Math. Students have been involved in the project in the frontend and backend design, research and product development, testing, and publishing. This project also involved female students and students from underrepresented ethnic groups. The PI engaged in local, national, and global community outreach activities to disseminate the broad impact of this project and the value of NSF.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/05/2022<br>      Modified by: Dong&nbsp;Si</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2030381/2030381_10671834_1659739497288_figuire12--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2030381/2030381_10671834_1659739497288_figuire12--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Models built from SARS-CoV-2 density maps"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2030381/2030381_10671834_1659739497288_figuire12--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Models built from SARS-CoV-2 density maps"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">DeepTracer predicted model for EMD-30044 (Top) showing a human receptor ACE2 to which spike proteins of SARS-CoV-2 virus bind and (Bottom) EMD-21374 depicting a SARS-CoV-2 spike glycoprotein. No model structure was deposited to EMDataResource as of the date of publication (Pfab et al. PNAS 2021).</div> <div class="imageCredit">Dong Si</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Dong&nbsp;Si</div> <div class="imageTitle">Models built from SARS-CoV-2 density maps</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Intellectual merit:  This project developed methods of geometric modeling, artificial intelligence, and computational biology to provide a biophysical characterization of SARS-CoV-2 and other CoV-related protein complexes using cryo-electron microscopy (cryo-EM) (Figure 1). This project revealed information that is relevant to the function and potential targeting and disruption of the viruses.  We developed fast, accurate, and fully automated de novo protein large complex structure prediction from a 3D electron density map and conducted case studies on CoV-related data (Pfab et al. PNAS 2021). We introduced deep learning methods and optimization techniques to predict the locations of atoms, secondary structure elements, and amino acid types. The work has been highlighted in Nature Computational Science (Chirigati, F. Predicting protein structure from cryo-EM data. Nat Comput Sci 1, 96, 2021).  We developed an interactive web portal https://deeptracer.uw.edu/covid for public access to the CoV-related predictions. The work could have an immediate impact on steps taken to halt the spread of SARS-CoV-2 and the current pandemic. The web portal automatically updates the predictions for the new CoV-related EM data. The interactive web applications provide workflows for stages from data uploading, modeling, and tools that facilitate visualization and evaluation of the prediction process. The predictions include atomic protein structures of SARS-CoV-2, SARS-CoV, MERS-CoV, H-CoV, MHV, AIBV, FIPV, PD-CoV, PEDV, Spike, Non-Spike, ACE2 receptor, Fab, Polymerase, Ribosome. Which are the key entities involved in the molecular mechanism of COVID-19. Our work successfully built the atomic models for the CoV-related EM maps, especially for the ones that have no previous deposited model structure available in the data bank.     Broader of impacts:  We remain steadfast and dedicated to the global fight against SARS-CoV-2 (COVID-19) with our DeepTracer web server and COV-related prediction web portal. The project and results could have led to a broad range of biomedical applications, such as a better understanding of important biological functions, disease processes, the development of novel drugs and vaccines, and improved preventive therapies leading to reduced health care costs. The methods and results developed in this project have been broadly disseminated to multiple communities including biology, biochemistry, health science, and pharmaceutical sciences. The data mining and artificial intelligence techniques developed in this project are very likely to be applicable for solving the computational problems from the closely related 3D volume data generated from different imaging techniques, and those in which one has to deal with data errors and noises.  The research has concretely demonstrated the applicability of data mining from the 3DEMDaraResource and the use of sophisticated deep learning methods for fast, accurate, and fully automated protein structure determination from COVID-related EM data. The computational methods and tools developed in this project have been used to interpret large molecular assemblies that have important biological functions such as viruses and cellular machines. Understanding these mechanisms is crucial for designing drugs and vaccines for current and future pandemics.  The project has been supporting the mentorship and training of high school, undergraduate, and graduate students both in the conduct of research and in the mentorship of more junior students. This project attracted more than thirty students in multiple disciplines including Computer Science, Biology, Chemistry, Physics, Health Science, Information Science, and Math. Students have been involved in the project in the frontend and backend design, research and product development, testing, and publishing. This project also involved female students and students from underrepresented ethnic groups. The PI engaged in local, national, and global community outreach activities to disseminate the broad impact of this project and the value of NSF.       Last Modified: 08/05/2022       Submitted by: Dong Si]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
