<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>RAPID: Collaborative Research: Development of Biocidal Nanofiber Air Filters for Reusable Personal Protective Equipment during Outbreaks of Viral Pathogens</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>99985.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>99985</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Christina Payne</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cpayne@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922895</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The COVID-19 pandemic has highlighted a critical need for reliable PPE for medical professionals and essential workers.  This project aims to fabricate self-sterilizing personal protective equipment (PPE) material. The material will be made using electrospinning, which produces small-diameter fibers. The fibrous material will be treated with two types of biocidal agents to destroy pathogens such as viruses. These materials are expected to be transformative because they offer the potential for extended use and/or reuse of PPE. This will aid in both reducing PPE shortages in times of increased use and contribute to reduced waste. The investigators have identified hospital and industrial partners for this project. Additionally, future applications of these materials may include filtration systems for hospitals, on airplanes, and in homes and buildings, and to protect those working in agriculture.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This proposal aims to produce biocidal filtration materials by electrospinning and adding novel biocide and antimicrobial treatments (tetrabutyl ammonium bromide (TBAB) and silver (Ag) nanoparticles) to produce PPE that captures and neutralizes viral pathogens. The investigators hypothesize that these novel antimicrobial composites will exhibit synergistic performance for virus inactivation by coupling physical and (bio)chemical removal mechanisms. To test this hypothesis, filter materials of varying fiber diameters will be electrospun from polystyrene and poly(vinylidene fluoride), and their filtrations performance will be evaluated using various sized polystyrene beads. The outcome of the project will be fundamental understanding of the synergistic effects of surfactant biocide (TBAB), antimicrobial silver, and easy-to-synthesize, electrospun materials.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/18/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/18/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2030571</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nosang</FirstName>
<LastName>Myung</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>V</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nosang V Myung</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>nmyung@nd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9518277710</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000471498</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/18/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kyle</FirstName>
<LastName>Bibby</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kyle Bibby</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kbibby@nd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5746311130</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000630532</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/18/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Notre Dame</Name>
<CityName>NOTRE DAME</CityName>
<ZipCode>465565708</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5746317432</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>940 Grace Hall</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IN02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>FPU6XGFXMBE9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF NOTRE DAME DU LAC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>KKBMKNFZ5PJ4</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Notre Dame]]></Name>
<CityName>Notre Dame</CityName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>465565708</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[940 Grace Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IN02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1642</Code>
<Text>Special Initiatives</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~99985</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-c83f82d5-7fff-b852-b76e-55e392e314d0"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>This project developed alternative approaches for the fabrication of personal protective equipment (PPE) that can be used both by frontline healthcare workers and the general public in settings where exposure to pathogenic aerosols is a public health concern. COVID-19 revealed weaknesses in existing supply chains for more conventionally fabricated PPE, including N95 Filtering Facepiece Respirators (FFRs) that contain an active filtration layer produced using melt blown polypropylene fibers. In response, research conducted through this RAPID grant has developed two viable pathways for the fabrication of nonwoven, electrospun materials as alternatives to melt blown polypropylene fibers.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>First, relying on only two raw ingredients (a polymer and a solvent), we produced a single, unsupported microfiber filter that meets or exceeds performance standards for N95 FFRs. We also demonstrated multiple approaches by which these microfiber filters could be decontaminated, either via aerosolized disinfectants or embedded antimicrobial agents that promote pathogen inactivation. Without need for a supporting material, we anticipate these high performance filters can be integrated into existing masks and other filtration platforms relatively easily.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Second, we produced a supported nanofiber filter layer that meets or exceeds the filtration efficiency and breathability standards for N95 FFRs. We further demonstrated our ability to optimize pathogen inactivation on this material at very low levels of integrated antimicrobial agents. Using this supported framework, which deposited a thin film of nonwoven nanofibers on a commercially available interfacing fabric, we envision a smooth transition to high throughput, mass production given the relatively small amount of material needed to produce the high-performance nanofiber filter layer.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The primary impact of this work is derived from our diverse suite of filter formulations that meet and exceed the performance of conventional filter materials, while also bypassing well-recognized problems with conventional synthesis routes for fibrous filter materials. Throughout this project, we have prioritized minimizing raw material inputs, both in terms of the number of ingredients and total amount of required ingredients necessary to produce a functional filter layer. This should make fabrication of these materials less vulnerable to supply chain disruptions given their limited raw materials and ease of fabrication using electrospinning.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>There are clear benefits of these materials for society, especially health care professionals who rely on high-performance PPE. More broadly, these materials are ideally suited for any application where disease transmission could occur through air, particularly in indoor or confined environments. The versatility of electrospinning also allows their use across a range of application scales (from standard in-home filtration to portable devices for air purification). Accordingly, we envision potential use of these materials in hospitals, on airplanes, in homes and buildings, and to protect those working in animal agriculture at confined animal feedlots. Variations of these materials may also have applications in water treatment and in applications where antimicrobial surfaces may prove beneficial (e.g., consumer goods packaging, food production services, wound bandages, etc.).</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/24/2022<br>      Modified by: Nosang&nbsp;V&nbsp;Myung</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   This project developed alternative approaches for the fabrication of personal protective equipment (PPE) that can be used both by frontline healthcare workers and the general public in settings where exposure to pathogenic aerosols is a public health concern. COVID-19 revealed weaknesses in existing supply chains for more conventionally fabricated PPE, including N95 Filtering Facepiece Respirators (FFRs) that contain an active filtration layer produced using melt blown polypropylene fibers. In response, research conducted through this RAPID grant has developed two viable pathways for the fabrication of nonwoven, electrospun materials as alternatives to melt blown polypropylene fibers.  First, relying on only two raw ingredients (a polymer and a solvent), we produced a single, unsupported microfiber filter that meets or exceeds performance standards for N95 FFRs. We also demonstrated multiple approaches by which these microfiber filters could be decontaminated, either via aerosolized disinfectants or embedded antimicrobial agents that promote pathogen inactivation. Without need for a supporting material, we anticipate these high performance filters can be integrated into existing masks and other filtration platforms relatively easily.  Second, we produced a supported nanofiber filter layer that meets or exceeds the filtration efficiency and breathability standards for N95 FFRs. We further demonstrated our ability to optimize pathogen inactivation on this material at very low levels of integrated antimicrobial agents. Using this supported framework, which deposited a thin film of nonwoven nanofibers on a commercially available interfacing fabric, we envision a smooth transition to high throughput, mass production given the relatively small amount of material needed to produce the high-performance nanofiber filter layer.  The primary impact of this work is derived from our diverse suite of filter formulations that meet and exceed the performance of conventional filter materials, while also bypassing well-recognized problems with conventional synthesis routes for fibrous filter materials. Throughout this project, we have prioritized minimizing raw material inputs, both in terms of the number of ingredients and total amount of required ingredients necessary to produce a functional filter layer. This should make fabrication of these materials less vulnerable to supply chain disruptions given their limited raw materials and ease of fabrication using electrospinning.  There are clear benefits of these materials for society, especially health care professionals who rely on high-performance PPE. More broadly, these materials are ideally suited for any application where disease transmission could occur through air, particularly in indoor or confined environments. The versatility of electrospinning also allows their use across a range of application scales (from standard in-home filtration to portable devices for air purification). Accordingly, we envision potential use of these materials in hospitals, on airplanes, in homes and buildings, and to protect those working in animal agriculture at confined animal feedlots. Variations of these materials may also have applications in water treatment and in applications where antimicrobial surfaces may prove beneficial (e.g., consumer goods packaging, food production services, wound bandages, etc.).          Last Modified: 02/24/2022       Submitted by: Nosang V Myung]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
