<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Effective Recovery for Organizations from the COVID-19: Optimizing Strategic Responses]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>120925.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>120925</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Songqi Liu</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>soliu@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928950</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[How do business organizations recover from a crisis?  Studies of crises show that human communities differ significantly in their responses; a crisis presents individual organizations and communities of organizations with a common problem, yet solutions may be elusive. This project will advance basic knowledge about the effectiveness of organizational recovery in response to the COVID-19 pandemic and global economic crisis. The project will help organizations and managers to better understand the conditions under which organizations responding to a crisis of unprecedented magnitude may recover more effectively. Results will equip organizations and managers with knowledge and skills about how to choose strategic responses to crisis, by highlighting the insights derived from study conditions. In collaboration with the University of Florida Entrepreneurship and Innovation Center, the project will disseminate results to business and scientific communities by providing free-of-charge webinars that explain to managers and researchers the strategic responses that can help organizations, particularly small-and-medium sized enterprises, to more effectively recover from the current crisis. Project findings and activities will help to ensure the economic competitiveness of the United States and promote our nation's safety and security.   &lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;When crises occur, business organizations need to move strategically to recover, but leaders and managers may be unclear as to which actions to take. The project will provide prescriptive theoretical directions for the development of processes and actions toward effective recovery from the COVID-19 pandemic and global economic crisis. The project will classify, explain, and evaluate organizations’ strategic responses to the current crisis for effective recovery and answer three research questions: First, among the multiple paths toward organizational recovery, which ones are more effective? Second, what organizational and environmental factors are most conducive to effective recovery? Third, would dynamic adaptation (e.g., switching resource allocation from the organization’s own rebuilding to community-based self-organizing efforts, and vice versa) be effective for recovery? Interview data will be used to inform, validate and improve a computational model designed to explain and evaluate the effectiveness of strategic responses of organizations. The project will use this model to compare a wide range of variation in responses, and probe the conditions under which certain responses could be more effective for organizational recovery. The project will produce: (1) a multi-level taxonomy of strategic responses to crisis for organizational recovery and (2) an explanation and evaluation of strategic responses to crisis for effective recovery. Using a mixed-method approach, the project will not only corroborate a computational model with interview data, but also use the model to extend understanding beyond case observations. Findings will inform theories of organization regarding business strategy, especially within the context of crises and extreme events.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/11/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/11/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2030830</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gwendolyn</FirstName>
<LastName>Lee</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>K</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gwendolyn K Lee</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[gwendolyn.lee@warrington.ufl.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000531920</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/11/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mo</FirstName>
<LastName>Wang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mo Wang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mo.wang@warrington.ufl.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000548879</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/11/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Florida</Name>
<CityName>GAINESVILLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>326111941</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3523923516</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1523 UNION RD RM 207</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NNFQH1JAPEP3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF FLORIDA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>D4GCCCMXR1H3</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Florida]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>326112002</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8031</Code>
<Text>SoO-Science Of Organizations</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>1N20</Code>
<Name>R&amp;RA CARES Act DEFC N</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>010N2021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[R&RA CARES Act DEFC N]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~120925</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>How do business organizations recover from a crisis? Studies of crises show that human communities differ significantly in their responses and business organizations need to move strategically so as to recover effectively. However, solutions may be elusive because leaders of organizations may be uncertain as to which actions to take. Our project has developed basic knowledge about the effectiveness of organizational recovery in response to the COVID-19 pandemic and global economic crisis. The knowledge helps members of organizations better understand the conditions under which organizations responding to a crisis of unprecedented turbulence may recover more effectively.</p> <p>Our project has developed (1) a multi-level taxonomy of strategic responses to crisis for organizational recovery; and (2) an explanation and evaluation of strategic responses to crisis for effective recovery. Project findings provide prescriptive theoretical directions for the development of processes and actions toward effective recovery. The findings can equip organizations with knowledge about how to choose strategic responses to crisis, by highlighting the insights derived from study conditions. In collaboration with the University of Florida Entrepreneurship and Innovation Center, the project has disseminated results to business and scientific communities by providing free-of-charge webinars that explain to managers and researchers the strategic responses that can help organizations, particularly small-and-medium sized enterprises, to more effectively recover from the current crisis. Project findings and activities help to ensure the economic competitiveness of the United States and promote our nation's safety and security.</p> <p>The research uses a mixed-method approach. The mixed-method approach allows us to not only corroborate a computational model with interview data, but also use the model to extend understanding beyond case observations. Specifically, the interview data are used to inform, validate and improve a computational model designed to explain and evaluate the effectiveness of strategic responses of organizations. We conducted 53 case studies across 147 interviews with decision makers&mdash;business owners, executives and managers to start-up founders and entrepreneurs&mdash;to understand how they process information and make decisions under uncertainty. With interviews spanning as many as four rounds between May 2020 and May 2021, we discuss how decision makers in businesses with various purposes (for profit and not for profit) are searching for solutions to problems that arise as a result of the pandemic.</p> <p>The businesses and decision makers that we interviewed are diverse. We met with businesses in 11 categories of industries, including senior living and memory care; healthcare; food; technology; telecommunications; logistics; retail; not-for-profit; education; consulting; real estate; and professional services, representing over 30 specific industries. The businesses we learned from also varied in size, from a single employee up to large-sized businesses, including both privately owned and publicly traded organizations. Our interviewees also included leaders from underrepresented groups (minority and women business owners).</p> <p>We learned from the interviewees that there are three strategic responses&mdash;Mission, Adaptation, and Communication.</p> <p>Mission: Set priorities and goals of the recovery. For setting priorities and goals of the recovery, we learned from the interviewees that they use two systems of thinking: fast and slow. System 1 is fast. It is intuitive and emotional. System 1 is used when the organization is in Survival mode, thinking about how to keep the lights on given the burn rate. System 2 is slow. It is deliberative and logical. System 2 is used when the organization is in Thriving mode, thinking about how to emerge from the crisis as a higher-performing organization.</p> <p>Adaptation: Improve the match between decisions and the demands of the decision environments.</p> <p>Communication: Engage in the social process of forming and transmitting information in order to translate that information into effective action.</p> <p>These Strategic Responses affect the Performance Metrics that are used to assess an organization&rsquo;s progress on the Road to Recovery. The progress is measured in terms of Margin, Growth, and Optionality.</p> <p>Our computational simulations for solving complex problems suggest the following for managerial take-away:</p> <p class="Default">In a turbulent environment, an organization excels across all three performance metrics (level of fitness, speed of performance improvement, and diversity of search) by using centralized decision-making (a centralized organization channels the processing power from the department managers to the top of the organization, which is the chief executive officer, CEO) and System 2 thinking&mdash;thinking slowly, the CEO deliberates how to emerge from the crisis as a higher-performing organization.</p> <p class="Default">In a stable environment, an organization reaches higher speed of performance improvement in the first period of search and diversity of search by using centralized decision-making and System 2 thinking.</p> <p class="Default">In a stable environment, an organization reaches higher level of fitness by using lateral communication (a lateral communication organization provides incentives for cooperation among departments and has strong power to process composite alternatives, which result from combining various proposals) and System 1 thinking&mdash;thinking fast, the departments of an organization mutually adjust about how to keep the lights on given the burn rate.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/26/2022<br>      Modified by: Gwendolyn&nbsp;K&nbsp;Lee</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2030830/2030830_10669716_1661539908546_Project_Outcomes_Report_Image6--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2030830/2030830_10669716_1661539908546_Project_Outcomes_Report_Image6--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Summary of findings from our computational simulations on strategic responses for organizational recovery"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2030830/2030830_10669716_1661539908546_Project_Outcomes_Report_Image6--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Summary of findings from our computational simulations on strategic responses for organizational recovery"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">In a turbulent environment, an organization excels across all three performance metrics (fitness, speed of performance improvement, and diversity of search) by using centralized decision-making and System 2 thinking.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Research team</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Gwendolyn&nbsp;K&nbsp;Lee</div> <div class="imageTitle">Summary of findings from our computational simulations on strategic responses for organizational recovery</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2030830/2030830_10669716_1661538965822_Project_Outcomes_Report_Image2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2030830/2030830_10669716_1661538965822_Project_Outcomes_Report_Image2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Mission: Setting priorities and goals"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2030830/2030830_10669716_1661538965822_Project_Outcomes_Report_Image2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Mission: Setting priorities and goals"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Setting priorities and goals uses two systems of thinking, fast and slow.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Research team</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Gwendolyn&nbsp;K&nbsp;Lee</div> <div class="imageTitle">Mission: Setting priorities and goals</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2030830/2030830_10669716_1661538788643_Project_Outcomes_Report_Image1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2030830/2030830_10669716_1661538788643_Project_Outcomes_Report_Image1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Strategic Responses for Organizational Recovery"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2030830/2030830_10669716_1661538788643_Project_Outcomes_Report_Image1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Strategic Responses for Organizational Recovery"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Mission, Adaptation, and Communication are the three strategic responses that our study reveals.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Research team</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Gwendolyn&nbsp;K&nbsp;Lee</div> <div class="imageTitle">Strategic Responses for Organizational Recovery</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2030830/2030830_10669716_1661539168459_Project_Outcomes_Report_Image3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2030830/2030830_10669716_1661539168459_Project_Outcomes_Report_Image3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Adaptation: Improve the match between decisions and the demands of the decision environments"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2030830/2030830_10669716_1661539168459_Project_Outcomes_Report_Image3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Adaptation: Improve the match between decisions and the demands of the decision environments"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Improving the match covers three areas: (1) Resource allocation and redeployment; (2) Pre-crisis baseline; and (3) Mutual adaptation among stakeholders.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Research team</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Gwendolyn&nbsp;K&nbsp;Lee</div> <div class="imageTitle">Adaptation: Improve the match between decisions and the demands of the decision environments</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2030830/2030830_10669716_1661539703261_Project_Outcomes_Report_Image5--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2030830/2030830_10669716_1661539703261_Project_Outcomes_Report_Image5--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Organizational Recovery in a turbulent environment"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2030830/2030830_10669716_1661539703261_Project_Outcomes_Report_Image5--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Organizational Recovery in a turbulent environment"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">In a turbulent environment, learning from the past is not directly applicable to the current task at hand.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Research team</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Gwendolyn&nbsp;K&nbsp;Lee</div> <div class="imageTitle">Organizational Recovery in a turbulent environment</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2030830/2030830_10669716_1661539368307_Project_Outcomes_Report_Image4--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2030830/2030830_10669716_1661539368307_Project_Outcomes_Report_Image4--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Communication: Engage in the social process of forming and transmitting information in order to translate that information into effective action"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2030830/2030830_10669716_1661539368307_Project_Outcomes_Report_Image4--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Communication: Engage in the social process of forming and transmitting information in order to translate that information into effective action"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Engaging in the social process covers three approaches: (1) Involve stakeholders; (2) Catalyze stakeholders' positive attitudes towards change; and (3) Use logic of persuasion.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Research team</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Gwendolyn&nbsp;K&nbsp;Lee</div> <div class="imageTitle">Communication: Engage in the social process of forming and transmitting information in order to translate that information into effective action</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ How do business organizations recover from a crisis? Studies of crises show that human communities differ significantly in their responses and business organizations need to move strategically so as to recover effectively. However, solutions may be elusive because leaders of organizations may be uncertain as to which actions to take. Our project has developed basic knowledge about the effectiveness of organizational recovery in response to the COVID-19 pandemic and global economic crisis. The knowledge helps members of organizations better understand the conditions under which organizations responding to a crisis of unprecedented turbulence may recover more effectively.  Our project has developed (1) a multi-level taxonomy of strategic responses to crisis for organizational recovery; and (2) an explanation and evaluation of strategic responses to crisis for effective recovery. Project findings provide prescriptive theoretical directions for the development of processes and actions toward effective recovery. The findings can equip organizations with knowledge about how to choose strategic responses to crisis, by highlighting the insights derived from study conditions. In collaboration with the University of Florida Entrepreneurship and Innovation Center, the project has disseminated results to business and scientific communities by providing free-of-charge webinars that explain to managers and researchers the strategic responses that can help organizations, particularly small-and-medium sized enterprises, to more effectively recover from the current crisis. Project findings and activities help to ensure the economic competitiveness of the United States and promote our nation's safety and security.  The research uses a mixed-method approach. The mixed-method approach allows us to not only corroborate a computational model with interview data, but also use the model to extend understanding beyond case observations. Specifically, the interview data are used to inform, validate and improve a computational model designed to explain and evaluate the effectiveness of strategic responses of organizations. We conducted 53 case studies across 147 interviews with decision makers&mdash;business owners, executives and managers to start-up founders and entrepreneurs&mdash;to understand how they process information and make decisions under uncertainty. With interviews spanning as many as four rounds between May 2020 and May 2021, we discuss how decision makers in businesses with various purposes (for profit and not for profit) are searching for solutions to problems that arise as a result of the pandemic.  The businesses and decision makers that we interviewed are diverse. We met with businesses in 11 categories of industries, including senior living and memory care; healthcare; food; technology; telecommunications; logistics; retail; not-for-profit; education; consulting; real estate; and professional services, representing over 30 specific industries. The businesses we learned from also varied in size, from a single employee up to large-sized businesses, including both privately owned and publicly traded organizations. Our interviewees also included leaders from underrepresented groups (minority and women business owners).  We learned from the interviewees that there are three strategic responses&mdash;Mission, Adaptation, and Communication.  Mission: Set priorities and goals of the recovery. For setting priorities and goals of the recovery, we learned from the interviewees that they use two systems of thinking: fast and slow. System 1 is fast. It is intuitive and emotional. System 1 is used when the organization is in Survival mode, thinking about how to keep the lights on given the burn rate. System 2 is slow. It is deliberative and logical. System 2 is used when the organization is in Thriving mode, thinking about how to emerge from the crisis as a higher-performing organization.  Adaptation: Improve the match between decisions and the demands of the decision environments.  Communication: Engage in the social process of forming and transmitting information in order to translate that information into effective action.  These Strategic Responses affect the Performance Metrics that are used to assess an organization’s progress on the Road to Recovery. The progress is measured in terms of Margin, Growth, and Optionality.  Our computational simulations for solving complex problems suggest the following for managerial take-away: In a turbulent environment, an organization excels across all three performance metrics (level of fitness, speed of performance improvement, and diversity of search) by using centralized decision-making (a centralized organization channels the processing power from the department managers to the top of the organization, which is the chief executive officer, CEO) and System 2 thinking&mdash;thinking slowly, the CEO deliberates how to emerge from the crisis as a higher-performing organization. In a stable environment, an organization reaches higher speed of performance improvement in the first period of search and diversity of search by using centralized decision-making and System 2 thinking. In a stable environment, an organization reaches higher level of fitness by using lateral communication (a lateral communication organization provides incentives for cooperation among departments and has strong power to process composite alternatives, which result from combining various proposals) and System 1 thinking&mdash;thinking fast, the departments of an organization mutually adjust about how to keep the lights on given the burn rate.       Last Modified: 08/26/2022       Submitted by: Gwendolyn K Lee]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
