<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Collaborative Research: Social Distancing During Pandemics: Developing Methods to Balance Affiliation and Disease-Avoidance Motivations]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>105999.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>105999</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Steven Breckler</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sbreckle@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927369</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[People have a powerful need to interact with each other. They also have strong desires to avoid disease.  Social distancing is the primary behavioral method to stop disease from spreading.  Yet, social distancing goes against the natural desire for social interactions. The tension between those dual motives can cause psychological distress, and may lead people to violate restrictions on face-to-face contact in their effort to relieve stress and loneliness. This is especially likely for people who do not have access to highly immersive forms of virtual socialization, such as internet-based video calls that let people see friends and family. It may also apply more often for older adults (who are most vulnerable to COVID-19) because of less familiarity with technology-based interaction platforms.  By better understanding how people resolve the tension between the need to interact with others and the desire to avoid disease, this project will inform the development of public health interventions aimed at curbing the spread of disease.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project contrasts the need to affiliate with the desire to avoid disease.  One aim is to inform the development of interventions designed to avoid loneliness while engaging in social distancing.  Study 1 collects data from the same participants across multiple days. Measures of loneliness, concerns with contracting an illness, and amounts and types of social interactions will be collected. The research tests the hypothesis that participants with limited access to virtual social interactions (e.g., those with limited financial means, the elderly) will feel most lonely and report decreased concerns about disease, which will be associated with more frequent violations of social distancing behaviors. Study 2 experimentally manipulates feelings of inclusion versus exclusion to test for effects of social isolation and for the concern of contracting the disease.  Both studies are based on large and representative samples of U.S. residents to ensure the findings are applicable across different age ranges, geographical regions, and socioeconomic groups within the country.  The research elucidates how various psychological processes work against each other and in interaction to ultimately influence social behavior.  The research further investigates how people can safely satisfy their motives to affiliate without sacrificing safety.  The long-term goal is to inform the development of interventions that may be developed to promote appropriate behavioral responses during the current and future pandemics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/14/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/14/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2030886</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Steven</FirstName>
<LastName>Young</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Steven Young</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[Steven.Young@baruch.cuny.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000622108</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/14/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>CUNY Baruch College</Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<ZipCode>100105585</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6463122211</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1 BERNARD BARUCH WAY # D509</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>CBKYNSMGNDD5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH FOUNDATION OF THE CITY UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[CUNY Baruch College]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>100105585</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1332</Code>
<Text>Social Psychology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1332</Code>
<Text>SOCIAL PSYCHOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>1N20</Code>
<Name>R&amp;RA CARES Act DEFC N</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>010N2021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[R&RA CARES Act DEFC N]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~105999</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>This proposal sought to optimize public health initiatives by extending and applying an understanding of two critical social motivational systems: social affiliation and disease avoidance motives. To do so, we proposed two large-scale studies including nationally representative samples to examine how best to support and maintain social distancing efforts while still satisfying belonging needs. We have completed data collection for the first study, which used experiencing sampling methods to track participants&rsquo; engagement with different forms of technology-mediated social interactions (e.g., Zoom, text messaging, phone calls) and how these mediums differentially satisfy social affiliation needs and tolerance for social distancing, which we then considered as the basis for subsequent interest in physical interactions as an index of (non)compliance with social distancing initiatives. This study also examined how factors including age and regional infrastructure (e.g., high speed internet availability) affect the willingness and ability to engage in technology-mediated interactions. This first study (N=2,409 participants) was led by co-PI Young and I assisted with programming, data collection and analysis, and manuscript preparation.&nbsp; Results of this study were submitted to a journal with broad and extensive interdisciplinary readership, <em>Computers in Human Behavior </em>(Impact Factor: 5.00), received a revise and resubmit designation, and the manuscript is under review for the second time.&nbsp; Study 2 (Target N=600 participants) was my primary responsibility.&nbsp; We are working to finish data collection for this study and have a skeleton manuscript prepared to submit once data collection is completed (Target journal: <em>Social Psychology</em>).&nbsp; This study is an experiment designed to provide causal evidence that indirect socialization experiences can ease the burden of isolation and increase adherence to social distancing protocols. Based on data we have already collected related to this project, we have also published a review paper in <em>Social and Personality Psychology Compass</em> that synthesizes our findings with our previous work in this program research that stands to inform critical theory-building in motivation research. This review paper is currently gaining considerable attention through research-based social media (e.g., ResearchGate, Twitter), suggesting these ideas have sustainable broad appeal.</span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/23/2022<br>      Modified by: Steven&nbsp;Young</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This proposal sought to optimize public health initiatives by extending and applying an understanding of two critical social motivational systems: social affiliation and disease avoidance motives. To do so, we proposed two large-scale studies including nationally representative samples to examine how best to support and maintain social distancing efforts while still satisfying belonging needs. We have completed data collection for the first study, which used experiencing sampling methods to track participants’ engagement with different forms of technology-mediated social interactions (e.g., Zoom, text messaging, phone calls) and how these mediums differentially satisfy social affiliation needs and tolerance for social distancing, which we then considered as the basis for subsequent interest in physical interactions as an index of (non)compliance with social distancing initiatives. This study also examined how factors including age and regional infrastructure (e.g., high speed internet availability) affect the willingness and ability to engage in technology-mediated interactions. This first study (N=2,409 participants) was led by co-PI Young and I assisted with programming, data collection and analysis, and manuscript preparation.  Results of this study were submitted to a journal with broad and extensive interdisciplinary readership, Computers in Human Behavior (Impact Factor: 5.00), received a revise and resubmit designation, and the manuscript is under review for the second time.  Study 2 (Target N=600 participants) was my primary responsibility.  We are working to finish data collection for this study and have a skeleton manuscript prepared to submit once data collection is completed (Target journal: Social Psychology).  This study is an experiment designed to provide causal evidence that indirect socialization experiences can ease the burden of isolation and increase adherence to social distancing protocols. Based on data we have already collected related to this project, we have also published a review paper in Social and Personality Psychology Compass that synthesizes our findings with our previous work in this program research that stands to inform critical theory-building in motivation research. This review paper is currently gaining considerable attention through research-based social media (e.g., ResearchGate, Twitter), suggesting these ideas have sustainable broad appeal.       Last Modified: 08/23/2022       Submitted by: Steven Young]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
