<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Stress and Emotional Response to Uncertainty in the COVID-19 Pandemic]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>73189.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>87825</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Steven Breckler</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sbreckle@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927369</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Many significant social decisions are made in situations of high uncertainty. A person’s ability to resolve such uncertainty can have profound implications for outcomes ranging from health to work performance.  Past research has shown that people exhibit reliable tendencies to respond to uncertainty with either positive or negative emotions.  These personal biases play a significant role in responding well or poorly to high uncertainty. This project leverages the urgent opportunity presented by the COVID-19 pandemic to advance the understanding of individual-level biases in the context of a societal-level stressor.  Very little is currently known about the effects of societal-level stressors, such as a global pandemic, on individual-level trait-like biases.  The negative thoughts and feelings some individuals experience in response to extreme societal uncertainty can have deleterious outcomes on health, work performance, and relationships.  This project lays the foundation for developing interventions to disrupt these maladaptive processes in favor of more productive responses.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;An online study includes three distinct measures of valence bias (the tendency to ascribe uncertainty with a negative meaning).  Measures of mood/temperament, resilience, and social factors likely affected by the COVID-19 pandemic (e.g., loneliness) are collected.  A subset of participants in the study completed the valence bias tasks before the pandemic (Wave 1).  In a longitudinal design, these same participants will be re-assessed at the height of the pandemic (Wave 2) and again after the pandemic ends (Wave 3).  By following people over time, it is possible to gauge the effects associated with a greater increase in negativity as a function of the global pandemic, as well as greater recovery after it ends.  A new group of participants will be added at Waves 2 and 3 to provide additional data for a cross-sectional exploration of the mechanisms that predict individual differences in valence bias at each time point. Age-related effects will also be explored at each wave. The research considers how people can learn to "do it better" to increase well-being and resilience in response to societal threats and uncertainty. The findings will shed light on how some individuals are able to override stress-related increases in negativity and instead resolve uncertainty in a positive light.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/04/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/19/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2031101</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Maital</FirstName>
<LastName>Neta</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Maital Neta</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[maitalneta@unl.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000753402</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/04/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</Name>
<CityName>LINCOLN</CityName>
<ZipCode>685032427</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4024723171</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2200 VINE ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Nebraska</StateName>
<StateCode>NE</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NE01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>HTQ6K6NJFHA6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>BOARD OF REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF NEBRASKA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Nebraska-Lincoln]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NE</StateCode>
<ZipCode>685830861</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Nebraska</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NE01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1332</Code>
<Text>Social Psychology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1332</Code>
<Text>SOCIAL PSYCHOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>1N20</Code>
<Name>R&amp;RA CARES Act DEFC N</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>010N2021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[R&RA CARES Act DEFC N]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~73189</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~14636</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Many significant social decisions are made in situations of high uncertainty. A person&rsquo;s ability to resolve such uncertainty can have profound implications for outcomes ranging from health to work performance and social relationships.&nbsp; Past research has shown that people exhibit reliable tendencies to respond to uncertainty with either positive or negative emotions.&nbsp; These personal biases play a significant role in responding well or poorly to high uncertainty. &nbsp;They are also vulnerable to the context, such as stressors in the environment.&nbsp; This RAPID project leverages the urgent opportunity presented by the COVID-19 pandemic to advance the understanding of individual-level biases in the context of a societal-level stressor.&nbsp; Very little is currently known about the effects of societal-level stressors, such as a global pandemic, on individual-level trait-like biases.&nbsp; The negative thoughts and feelings some individuals experience in response to extreme societal uncertainty can have deleterious outcomes on health, work performance, and relationships. &nbsp;This project lays the foundation for developing interventions to disrupt these maladaptive processes in favor of more productive responses.</p> <p>Our online study included three distinct measures of valence bias (the tendency to ascribe uncertainty with a negative meaning). &nbsp;Measures of mood/temperament, resilience, and social factors likely affected by the COVID-19 pandemic (e.g., loneliness) were also collected.&nbsp; A subset of participants in the study completed the valence bias tasks before the pandemic (Wave 1).&nbsp; In a longitudinal design, these same participants will be re-assessed at the height of the pandemic (Wave 2) and again several times throughout the subsequent year (Waves 3-5). &nbsp;By following people over time, it is possible to gauge the effects associated with a greater increase in negativity as a function of the global pandemic, as well as greater recovery after it ends. &nbsp;A new group of participants was also added at each of Waves 2-5 to provide additional data for a cross-sectional exploration of the mechanisms that predict individual differences in valence bias at each time point. Age-related effects were also be explored at each wave, as the data were collected from a wide age range of adults (ages 18-89 years). The research considers how people can learn to "do it better" to increase well-being and resilience in response to societal threats and uncertainty. The findings also shed light on how individuals with a more optimistic style of response are able to override stress-related increases in negativity and instead resolve uncertainty in a positive light.</p> <p>We found that, overall, people became significantly more negative from before to during the early stage of the pandemic. This shift in valence bias continued to the intermediate and late stage of the pandemic, albeit to a lesser degree. This pattern suggests that the societal challenges and uncertainty presented by the pandemic had a significant impact on how people view their social world, leading to a more negative valence bias.</p> <p>We also found that greater perceived stress predicted a larger shift towards a more negative valence bias from before to the early stage of the pandemic, but that a tendency to adaptively regulate one&rsquo;s emotions in daily life weakened this stress-related increase in negativity.</p> <p>Finally, we found evidence of risk and resilience factors related to valence bias during the early stage of the pandemic, when there was an otherwise robust shift toward increased negativity. These findings have the potential to inform future research and even intervention efforts. Specifically, we found that greater pandemic-related feelings of loneliness predicted a more negative valence bias, but that more frequent use of interpersonal emotion regulation strategies, especially tending to share <em>positive</em> emotions with others, led to a weaker relationship between loneliness and a more negative valence bias. Likewise, modifiable lifestyle factors, like engaging in physical activity, tended to predict a more positive valence bias at the early stage of the pandemic, and may even contribute to reduced reliance on emotion regulation strategies. Altogether, our findings highlight the importance of both intrapersonal and interpersonal emotion regulation strategies, along with healthy lifestyle behaviors, in reducing stress- or loneliness-related negativity. Ongoing work will continue to explore these risk and resilience factors, especially as they change over time with valence bias.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/24/2021<br>      Modified by: Maital&nbsp;Neta</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Many significant social decisions are made in situations of high uncertainty. A person’s ability to resolve such uncertainty can have profound implications for outcomes ranging from health to work performance and social relationships.  Past research has shown that people exhibit reliable tendencies to respond to uncertainty with either positive or negative emotions.  These personal biases play a significant role in responding well or poorly to high uncertainty.  They are also vulnerable to the context, such as stressors in the environment.  This RAPID project leverages the urgent opportunity presented by the COVID-19 pandemic to advance the understanding of individual-level biases in the context of a societal-level stressor.  Very little is currently known about the effects of societal-level stressors, such as a global pandemic, on individual-level trait-like biases.  The negative thoughts and feelings some individuals experience in response to extreme societal uncertainty can have deleterious outcomes on health, work performance, and relationships.  This project lays the foundation for developing interventions to disrupt these maladaptive processes in favor of more productive responses.  Our online study included three distinct measures of valence bias (the tendency to ascribe uncertainty with a negative meaning).  Measures of mood/temperament, resilience, and social factors likely affected by the COVID-19 pandemic (e.g., loneliness) were also collected.  A subset of participants in the study completed the valence bias tasks before the pandemic (Wave 1).  In a longitudinal design, these same participants will be re-assessed at the height of the pandemic (Wave 2) and again several times throughout the subsequent year (Waves 3-5).  By following people over time, it is possible to gauge the effects associated with a greater increase in negativity as a function of the global pandemic, as well as greater recovery after it ends.  A new group of participants was also added at each of Waves 2-5 to provide additional data for a cross-sectional exploration of the mechanisms that predict individual differences in valence bias at each time point. Age-related effects were also be explored at each wave, as the data were collected from a wide age range of adults (ages 18-89 years). The research considers how people can learn to "do it better" to increase well-being and resilience in response to societal threats and uncertainty. The findings also shed light on how individuals with a more optimistic style of response are able to override stress-related increases in negativity and instead resolve uncertainty in a positive light.  We found that, overall, people became significantly more negative from before to during the early stage of the pandemic. This shift in valence bias continued to the intermediate and late stage of the pandemic, albeit to a lesser degree. This pattern suggests that the societal challenges and uncertainty presented by the pandemic had a significant impact on how people view their social world, leading to a more negative valence bias.  We also found that greater perceived stress predicted a larger shift towards a more negative valence bias from before to the early stage of the pandemic, but that a tendency to adaptively regulate one’s emotions in daily life weakened this stress-related increase in negativity.  Finally, we found evidence of risk and resilience factors related to valence bias during the early stage of the pandemic, when there was an otherwise robust shift toward increased negativity. These findings have the potential to inform future research and even intervention efforts. Specifically, we found that greater pandemic-related feelings of loneliness predicted a more negative valence bias, but that more frequent use of interpersonal emotion regulation strategies, especially tending to share positive emotions with others, led to a weaker relationship between loneliness and a more negative valence bias. Likewise, modifiable lifestyle factors, like engaging in physical activity, tended to predict a more positive valence bias at the early stage of the pandemic, and may even contribute to reduced reliance on emotion regulation strategies. Altogether, our findings highlight the importance of both intrapersonal and interpersonal emotion regulation strategies, along with healthy lifestyle behaviors, in reducing stress- or loneliness-related negativity. Ongoing work will continue to explore these risk and resilience factors, especially as they change over time with valence bias.       Last Modified: 09/24/2021       Submitted by: Maital Neta]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
