<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: The Virtual Field: Educational mitigation for the Covid-19 Pandemic]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>199030.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>238835</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DBI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Reed Beaman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rsbeaman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927163</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The Covid-19 pandemic is causing massive disruption to field education in the U.S. and internationally and is forecasted to continue to cause field course cancellations over the next year. The impacts of this disruption on STEM education is anticipated to be substantial. A 2014 study by the National Research Council found that field experiences boost motivation, retention, critical thinking and academic success for students of all backgrounds and disciplines and are particularly important for recruitment into the environmental sciences. Building on a grassroots effort of 50 Field Stations and Marine Laboratories representing 34 field site networks (e.g., NEON, LTER, LTAR, GLEON), this project will leverage existing collaborations, programs and initiatives to: establish a field learning portal to advertise and distribute virtual materials and live-streaming research-based field events to universities across the U.S.; create novel cross-site virtual field learning experiences that boost critical observation and research skills; evaluate the efficacy of virtual field experiences on student learning outcomes. These experiences will help fulfill graduation requirements and prepare undergraduates and graduates impacted by the Covid-19 pandemic for future careers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This pandemic offers unique opportunities to generate insights for the development of virtual field experiences as a novel teaching tool. The urgent need for virtual teaching materials across all disciplines encourages adoption by faculty who might otherwise never have used either virtual or field experiences in their courses.  The synchronous prioritization of virtual offerings by field stations and marine laboratories opens the window to creating a broad array of multi-site virtual experiences around the world. The resulting dramatic expansion in the availability and use of virtual field experiences can create new opportunities to assess the effects of this teaching tool on student observation and research skills and to enhance preparedness for future disruptions.  This RAPID award is made by the Division of Biological Infrastructure using funds from the Coronavirus Aid, Relief, and Economic Security (CARES) Act.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/06/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/06/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2031815</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Claudia</FirstName>
<LastName>Luke</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Claudia Luke</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[claudia.luke@sonoma.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000540204</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/06/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Hilary</FirstName>
<LastName>Swain</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Hilary Swain</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[hswain@archbold-station.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000484218</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/06/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kari</FirstName>
<LastName>O'Connell</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kari B O'Connell</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[kari.oconnell@oregonstate.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000253591</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/06/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Sonoma State University</Name>
<CityName>ROHNERT PARK</CityName>
<ZipCode>949283613</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7076643972</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1801 E COTATI AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>GZ6NCMJFL6R4</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SONOMA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Sonoma State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Rohnert Park</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>949283609</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1801 East Cotati Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>158Y</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>169Y</Code>
<Text>Capacity: Field Stations</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>097Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Impacts on Existing Activities</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>102Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-Disproportionate Impcts Inst-Indiv</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1104</Code>
<Text>FIELD STATIONS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>1N20</Code>
<Name>R&amp;RA CARES Act DEFC N</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>010N2021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[R&RA CARES Act DEFC N]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~199030</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~39805</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-1f57e45a-7fff-186f-a3f2-3f8c47400790"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The Covid-19 pandemic caused massive disruptions to education in the U.S. and internationally. The impacts on science education was substantial for disciplines reliant on field trips for building student skills. Field trip experiences not only teach&nbsp;</span>observation, identification and communication skills but also boost motivation, retention, critical thinking and academic success for students of all backgrounds.&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Building on a grassroots effort of 50 Field Stations and Marine Laboratories (FSMLs), The Virtual Field (TVF) project leveraged existing collaborations and rapidly created a series of skill-building virtual field experiences. These experiences allow students to "travel" to ecosystems around the world and reduces logistic, financial and social barriers for students of all backgrounds and disciplines.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Specific goals for the project were to help fulfill graduation requirements and prepare undergraduates for future careers by:&nbsp;</span></p> <p><strong>1. Establishing a virtual field learning portal </strong>to advertise and distribute virtual materials and live-streaming research-based field events to U.S. and international universities.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The Virtual Field platform (thevirtualfield.org) which went live in October 2020. Thevirtualfield.org is a robust portal that allows FSMLs around the world to share virtual educational materials. The portal engages students and teachers of all ages and discipilines. During the life of this grant, the website had over 63,000 page views and 16,019 new visitors.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>&nbsp;</span><strong>2. Creating novel cross-site virtual field learning experiences</strong> that boost critical observation and research skills.</p> <p>We created five series of virtual field experiences to enhance student observation, communication, and critical thinking skills. Each comes with a set of user guides for instructors and are designed to be used as supplemental assignments as part of existing courses.</p> <ul> <li>Ecosystem Exploration: A series of 31 videos were developed to build student observation and communication skills. Each 3-minute point-of-view video takes students on a guided, but unnarrated, tour of an ecosystem. A series of increasingly challenging ?Explorer Guides? help them build foundational research skills. Concepts are linked to the Ecological Society of America?s 4DEE content criteria.&nbsp;</li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Live from the Field Series: 11 live events and resulting videos provide students with perspectives on the process of field research. At each event, students visit three researchers at theeir field sites around the world and engage in live Q&amp;A about their work.&nbsp;</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>360-Degree Seasonal Video Series:&nbsp; 5-minute 360 videos were taken of four times each year during fall, winter, spring and summer in 70 ecosystems across the planet, allowing students to explore seasonal changes in a variety of ecosystems. Three ?Explorer Guides? help build observation, communication and questioning skills.</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Virtual Events: The Virtual Field website allows FSMLs to advertise virtual events to a national and international audience.</span></p> </li> </ul> <ul> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Discover More: FSMLs shared their own digital educational content to a searchable database on the website.</span></p> </li> </ul> <p><strong>3. Evaluating the efficacy of virtual field experiences on student learning outcomes</strong> and set the stage for further virtual field learning initiatives around the world.&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>We developed and revised both website and virtual field experiences with feedback from faculty and students collected as part of on-line surveys, faculty-FSML learning communities (as part of a separate NSF grant), FSML learning communities, and a panel of 26 experts in virtual learning and field trips (a paper with results of the expert panel is in press). The most robust evaluation was conducted on EE videos: 80% of the 1,892 students responding rated the exercise as moderately to very effective. Faculty responded that the exercises engaged their students, improved their observational skills and gave students access to environments previously unavailable.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>This grant has also made significant progress towards broader societal goals.&nbsp;</span></p> <ol> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Building a competitive STEM workforce</span><span> both during the pandemic and into the future. The project set the stage for broader use of virtual field learning. TVF preliminary surveys indicate that the materials effectively teach foundational science skills and that they were used by faculty from over 160 universities in a wide diversity of scientific disciplines, such as chemistry, earth sciences, ecology, field methods, aquatic systems, geography, biology, microbiology and sustainability. In a separate TVF grant, 20 faculty at community colleges, urban campuses and minority serving institutions also found the materials effective, suggesting that this approach can be used to overcome logistical, social and administrative barriers to participation by students under-represented in the sciences.&nbsp;&nbsp;</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Increasing public scientific literacy and public engagement with science and technology</span><span>. The TVF portal is publicly accessible and welcomes learners of all ages. Of the survey respondents using the materials, 35% were high-school students. A separate grant is now modifying TVF materials for K-8 and high-school student audiences.&nbsp;</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Enhancing infrastructure for research and education. </span><span>FSMLs are traditionally focused on the advantages of providing in-person hands-on experiences. However the infrastructure available (~900 worldwide) is not sufficient to host everyone interested in visiting these sites. The TVF website effectively expands the capacity of existing FSMLs to allow virtual visitation by a broad and diverse audience.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</span></p> </li> </ol> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/02/2023<br>      Modified by: Claudia&nbsp;Luke</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2031815/2031815_10668876_1677785735190_TVFHomepage--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2031815/2031815_10668876_1677785735190_TVFHomepage--rgov-800width.jpg" title="The Virtual Field"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2031815/2031815_10668876_1677785735190_TVFHomepage--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="The Virtual Field"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">thevirtualfield.org</div> <div class="imageCredit">Claudia Luke</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Claudia&nbsp;Luke</div> <div class="imageTitle">The Virtual Field</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   The Covid-19 pandemic caused massive disruptions to education in the U.S. and internationally. The impacts on science education was substantial for disciplines reliant on field trips for building student skills. Field trip experiences not only teach observation, identification and communication skills but also boost motivation, retention, critical thinking and academic success for students of all backgrounds.  Building on a grassroots effort of 50 Field Stations and Marine Laboratories (FSMLs), The Virtual Field (TVF) project leveraged existing collaborations and rapidly created a series of skill-building virtual field experiences. These experiences allow students to "travel" to ecosystems around the world and reduces logistic, financial and social barriers for students of all backgrounds and disciplines.  Specific goals for the project were to help fulfill graduation requirements and prepare undergraduates for future careers by:   1. Establishing a virtual field learning portal to advertise and distribute virtual materials and live-streaming research-based field events to U.S. and international universities.   The Virtual Field platform (thevirtualfield.org) which went live in October 2020. Thevirtualfield.org is a robust portal that allows FSMLs around the world to share virtual educational materials. The portal engages students and teachers of all ages and discipilines. During the life of this grant, the website had over 63,000 page views and 16,019 new visitors.   2. Creating novel cross-site virtual field learning experiences that boost critical observation and research skills.  We created five series of virtual field experiences to enhance student observation, communication, and critical thinking skills. Each comes with a set of user guides for instructors and are designed to be used as supplemental assignments as part of existing courses.  Ecosystem Exploration: A series of 31 videos were developed to build student observation and communication skills. Each 3-minute point-of-view video takes students on a guided, but unnarrated, tour of an ecosystem. A series of increasingly challenging ?Explorer Guides? help them build foundational research skills. Concepts are linked to the Ecological Society of America?s 4DEE content criteria.   Live from the Field Series: 11 live events and resulting videos provide students with perspectives on the process of field research. At each event, students visit three researchers at theeir field sites around the world and engage in live Q&amp;A about their work.    360-Degree Seasonal Video Series:  5-minute 360 videos were taken of four times each year during fall, winter, spring and summer in 70 ecosystems across the planet, allowing students to explore seasonal changes in a variety of ecosystems. Three ?Explorer Guides? help build observation, communication and questioning skills.   Virtual Events: The Virtual Field website allows FSMLs to advertise virtual events to a national and international audience.     Discover More: FSMLs shared their own digital educational content to a searchable database on the website.    3. Evaluating the efficacy of virtual field experiences on student learning outcomes and set the stage for further virtual field learning initiatives around the world.  We developed and revised both website and virtual field experiences with feedback from faculty and students collected as part of on-line surveys, faculty-FSML learning communities (as part of a separate NSF grant), FSML learning communities, and a panel of 26 experts in virtual learning and field trips (a paper with results of the expert panel is in press). The most robust evaluation was conducted on EE videos: 80% of the 1,892 students responding rated the exercise as moderately to very effective. Faculty responded that the exercises engaged their students, improved their observational skills and gave students access to environments previously unavailable.  This grant has also made significant progress towards broader societal goals.    Building a competitive STEM workforce both during the pandemic and into the future. The project set the stage for broader use of virtual field learning. TVF preliminary surveys indicate that the materials effectively teach foundational science skills and that they were used by faculty from over 160 universities in a wide diversity of scientific disciplines, such as chemistry, earth sciences, ecology, field methods, aquatic systems, geography, biology, microbiology and sustainability. In a separate TVF grant, 20 faculty at community colleges, urban campuses and minority serving institutions also found the materials effective, suggesting that this approach can be used to overcome logistical, social and administrative barriers to participation by students under-represented in the sciences.     Increasing public scientific literacy and public engagement with science and technology. The TVF portal is publicly accessible and welcomes learners of all ages. Of the survey respondents using the materials, 35% were high-school students. A separate grant is now modifying TVF materials for K-8 and high-school student audiences.    Enhancing infrastructure for research and education. FSMLs are traditionally focused on the advantages of providing in-person hands-on experiences. However the infrastructure available (~900 worldwide) is not sufficient to host everyone interested in visiting these sites. The TVF website effectively expands the capacity of existing FSMLs to allow virtual visitation by a broad and diverse audience.                  Last Modified: 03/02/2023       Submitted by: Claudia Luke]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
