<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID Collaborative Research: Economic Preferences and Preventative Health Measures During a Pandemic]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>55827.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>55827</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kwabena Gyimah-Brempong</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kgyimahb@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927466</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The research team will conduct choice experiments combined with a survey to determine how the COVID-19 pandemic may be shaping economic preferences. They also want to determine whether those preferences are correlated with preventive health actions taken by individuals. The project will include subjects from a variety of different racial and ethnic groups, to get solid information on the groups that to date have been especially affected by COVID-19 in the United States. The project should help us understand whether and how methods developed for use in behavioral economics and consumer choice can also help us predict the extent of health promoting behaviors. The results may also give us new insights into how to best target public health communications.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The experimental tasks will measure risk tolerance, time preference, altruism, willingness to contribute to public goods, cooperation, willingness to lie in self protection, preference for competition, and over/under confidence. Economic theory suggests that each of these aspects of individual preferences play a role in determining the extent to which a given individual carries out recommended health behaviors. Examples of these behaviors are wearing a mask (altruism, willingness to contribute to public goods), truthfully informing others about possible exposure (willingness to lie), avoiding crowds and indoor spaces (risk tolerance, over confidence), and limiting social gatherings today for future benefits (time preference). Survey methods will be used to measure health behaviors. The team will use the data to test whether or not economic preference measurements do indeed predict health behaviors.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/07/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/07/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2031446</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Erkut</FirstName>
<LastName>Ozbay</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>Y</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Erkut Y Ozbay</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ozbay@econ.umd.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000524212</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/07/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Maryland, College Park</Name>
<CityName>College Park</CityName>
<ZipCode>207420001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3014056269</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3112 LEE BLDG 7809 REGENTS DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MD04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NPU8ULVAAS23</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MARYLAND, COLLEGE PARK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>KMGEN62NKEM9</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Maryland College Park]]></Name>
<CityName>College Park</CityName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>207425103</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3112 Lee Bldg 7809 Regents Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MD04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1320</Code>
<Text>Economics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~55827</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Summary:&nbsp;</strong>We study the changes in economic behaviors of Amazon Mechanical Turk (MTurk) workers due to the COVID19 pandemic, and compare it to a pre-pandemic MTurker sample, a student sample, and a representative sample of the United States. We find that MTurkers during the pandemic behave differently than previous MTurkers in many contexts, even after accounting for changes in demographic composition. These MTurkers behave more similarly to a representative sample than a student sample. Additionally, we revisit gender differences in preferences and document fewer and smaller differences in many contexts.&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Intellectual Merit:</strong></p> <ol> <li> <p><span>Advancement of Knowledge</span>: The project contributes to our understanding of how global events like a pandemic can influence behavior, particularly in the context of online work. This is a relatively unexplored area of research, and the findings could have significant implications for various fields, including economics, psychology, and sociology.</p> </li> <li> <p><span>Conceptual Innovation</span>: The project uses an innovative approach by leveraging an online platform (MTurk) to study behavior changes. This not only allows for data collection during a global event like a pandemic but also opens up new possibilities for research methodologies.</p> </li> <li> <p><span>Researcher Qualification</span>: The researchers involved in the project have demonstrated their qualifications through the successful execution of the project and the publication of their findings.</p> </li> </ol> <p><strong>Broader Impacts:</strong></p> <ol> <li> <p><span>Societal Benefit</span>: The findings of the project could inform public policy decisions and workplace practices, leading to societal benefits. For example, understanding how behavior changes during a pandemic can help policymakers and companies develop more effective strategies for managing such events.</p> </li> <li> <p><span>Education and Training</span>: The project could impact education and training programs by highlighting the importance of understanding human behavior in online environments. This could lead to the development of new curricula or training programs.</p> </li> <li> <p><span>Infrastructure for Research and Education</span>: The project demonstrates the potential of online platforms like MTurk as tools for research and education. This could lead to greater use of such platforms, thereby enhancing the infrastructure for research and education.</p> </li> <li> <p><span>Broadening Participation</span>: The project involves MTurk workers from diverse backgrounds, thereby broadening participation in research.</p> </li> </ol> <p><span><br /></span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/27/2023<br>      Modified by: Erkut Yusuf&nbsp;Ozbay</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Summary: We study the changes in economic behaviors of Amazon Mechanical Turk (MTurk) workers due to the COVID19 pandemic, and compare it to a pre-pandemic MTurker sample, a student sample, and a representative sample of the United States. We find that MTurkers during the pandemic behave differently than previous MTurkers in many contexts, even after accounting for changes in demographic composition. These MTurkers behave more similarly to a representative sample than a student sample. Additionally, we revisit gender differences in preferences and document fewer and smaller differences in many contexts.   Intellectual Merit:    Advancement of Knowledge: The project contributes to our understanding of how global events like a pandemic can influence behavior, particularly in the context of online work. This is a relatively unexplored area of research, and the findings could have significant implications for various fields, including economics, psychology, and sociology.    Conceptual Innovation: The project uses an innovative approach by leveraging an online platform (MTurk) to study behavior changes. This not only allows for data collection during a global event like a pandemic but also opens up new possibilities for research methodologies.    Researcher Qualification: The researchers involved in the project have demonstrated their qualifications through the successful execution of the project and the publication of their findings.    Broader Impacts:    Societal Benefit: The findings of the project could inform public policy decisions and workplace practices, leading to societal benefits. For example, understanding how behavior changes during a pandemic can help policymakers and companies develop more effective strategies for managing such events.    Education and Training: The project could impact education and training programs by highlighting the importance of understanding human behavior in online environments. This could lead to the development of new curricula or training programs.    Infrastructure for Research and Education: The project demonstrates the potential of online platforms like MTurk as tools for research and education. This could lead to greater use of such platforms, thereby enhancing the infrastructure for research and education.    Broadening Participation: The project involves MTurk workers from diverse backgrounds, thereby broadening participation in research.                  Last Modified: 09/27/2023       Submitted by: Erkut Yusuf Ozbay]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
