<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Host-pathogen interactions during genome replication of SARS-CoV2]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>162283.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>162283</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>MCB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Manju Hingorani</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mhingora@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927323</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Replication of coronaviruses, including SARS-CoV-2 – the causative agent of COVID-19, is expected to involve protein factors from the infected host cell that provide activities not encoded in the viral genome. This project focuses on the need for the virus to co-opt a host 3’ to 5’ RNA helicase to synthesize the negative-strand RNA that serves as template for copying the positive-strand genome. A recent proteomic screen identified a candidate host helicase, DDX10, that interacts with SARS-CoV-2 proteins. The research will employ a suite of experimental approaches to characterize this enzyme and two other host RNA helicases also implicated in SARS-CoV-2 genome replication. Detailed knowledge of how host proteins contribute to viral replication will provide new targets for therapeutic intervention, importantly, in ways that help circumvent drug resistance through viral mutation. The project will also support training of a postdoctoral scholar and development of a new undergraduate biophysics course centered on coronavirus-related topics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Biochemical and biophysical techniques, such as X-ray crystallography, cryo-EM and single molecule spectroscopy, will be applied to determine structure-function properties that govern the helicase mechanism, including polarity, speed, processivity and associated energetics, and how its interactions with the viral NSP7/8 primase influence genome replication. The outcomes are expected to reveal the workings of host proteins during SARS-CoV-2 replication, and thereby open new avenues and novel drug targets to block its proliferation.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This RAPID award is made by the Genetic Mechanisms Program in the Division of Molecular and Cellular Biosciences, using funds from the Coronavirus Aid, Relief, and Economic Security (CARES) Act.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/11/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/11/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2031094</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Taekjip</FirstName>
<LastName>Ha</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Taekjip Ha</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[tjha@jhu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000488247</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/11/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Berger</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>James M Berger</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jmberger@jhmi.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000826001</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/11/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Johns Hopkins University</Name>
<CityName>BALTIMORE</CityName>
<ZipCode>212182608</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4439971898</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3400 N CHARLES ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MD07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>FTMTDMBR29C7</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>JOHNS HOPKINS UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>FTMTDMBR29C7</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Johns Hopkins University]]></Name>
<CityName>Baltimore</CityName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>212052105</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[725 N. Wolfe Street,  WBSB 625]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MD07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>158Y</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7465</Code>
<Text>NANOSCALE BIO CORE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>1N20</Code>
<Name>R&amp;RA CARES Act DEFC N</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>010N2021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[R&RA CARES Act DEFC N]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~162283</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Infection by SARS-CoV-2 and disease progression is a result of complex interaction between the virus proteins and host proteins. Because of a high-throughput screen which identified a host protein DDX10, which is an RNA unwinding enzyme, as a potential candidate for controlling replication of SARS-CoV-2, this project aimed to study the structure and activities of DDX10 in relation to the viral replication machineries. Because multiple efforts to express and purify DDX10 protein failed, and because a subsequent high-throughput screen showed that DDX10 is not an important host factor for corona virus infection, the efforts were redirected to Covid-19 diagnostics.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The team introduced a conceptually new strategy for nucleic acid detection called SENTINEL that utilizes isothermal amplification with sequence-specific on-target cleavage by an endonuclease to actuate exonuclease-mediated target degradation.This approach combines the high sensitivity of initial isothermal amplification at attomolar limits of detection with improved specificity from endonuclease-mediated discrimination between closely related sequences. This results in an assay that is highly convenient requiring minimal laboratory reagents, modular in the choice of sequence-specific endonuclease, fast with under 1-hour total time and minimal hands-on time, and versatile in detecting SARS-CoV-2 virus particles in human saliva with high sensitivity. <strong>Reference. </strong>R. S. Zou, M. Gavrilov, Y. Liu, D. Rasoloson, M. Conte, J. P. Hardick, L. Shen, S. Chen, A. Pekosz, G. Seydoux, Y.C. Manabe and T. Ha, ?Improving the specificity of nucleic acid detection with endonuclease-actuated degradation?, Communications Biology 5:290 (2022).</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The team also introduced a new isothermal DNA amplification method that utilizes a highly processive DNA unwinding enzyme (superhelicase) to replace thermal cycling in the conventional DNA amplification methods. The new method, named SHARP, can produce DNA products with lengths of up to 6000 base pairs, a feature no existing isothermal amplification method can match.&nbsp; SHARP can produce functional DNA, a plasmid that imparts cells with antibiotic resistance, and can amplify specific fragments from genomic DNA of human cells. Further, SHARP can be used for assessing the outcome of CRISPR-Cas9 genome editing at endogenous genomic sites.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/05/2022<br>      Modified by: Taekjip&nbsp;Ha</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Infection by SARS-CoV-2 and disease progression is a result of complex interaction between the virus proteins and host proteins. Because of a high-throughput screen which identified a host protein DDX10, which is an RNA unwinding enzyme, as a potential candidate for controlling replication of SARS-CoV-2, this project aimed to study the structure and activities of DDX10 in relation to the viral replication machineries. Because multiple efforts to express and purify DDX10 protein failed, and because a subsequent high-throughput screen showed that DDX10 is not an important host factor for corona virus infection, the efforts were redirected to Covid-19 diagnostics.     The team introduced a conceptually new strategy for nucleic acid detection called SENTINEL that utilizes isothermal amplification with sequence-specific on-target cleavage by an endonuclease to actuate exonuclease-mediated target degradation.This approach combines the high sensitivity of initial isothermal amplification at attomolar limits of detection with improved specificity from endonuclease-mediated discrimination between closely related sequences. This results in an assay that is highly convenient requiring minimal laboratory reagents, modular in the choice of sequence-specific endonuclease, fast with under 1-hour total time and minimal hands-on time, and versatile in detecting SARS-CoV-2 virus particles in human saliva with high sensitivity. Reference. R. S. Zou, M. Gavrilov, Y. Liu, D. Rasoloson, M. Conte, J. P. Hardick, L. Shen, S. Chen, A. Pekosz, G. Seydoux, Y.C. Manabe and T. Ha, ?Improving the specificity of nucleic acid detection with endonuclease-actuated degradation?, Communications Biology 5:290 (2022).     The team also introduced a new isothermal DNA amplification method that utilizes a highly processive DNA unwinding enzyme (superhelicase) to replace thermal cycling in the conventional DNA amplification methods. The new method, named SHARP, can produce DNA products with lengths of up to 6000 base pairs, a feature no existing isothermal amplification method can match.  SHARP can produce functional DNA, a plasmid that imparts cells with antibiotic resistance, and can amplify specific fragments from genomic DNA of human cells. Further, SHARP can be used for assessing the outcome of CRISPR-Cas9 genome editing at endogenous genomic sites.          Last Modified: 08/05/2022       Submitted by: Taekjip Ha]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
