<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Connecting Researchers in Sharing and Re-Use of Research Data and Software]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>46793.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>46793</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OAC</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure (OAC)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Martin Halbert</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mhalbert@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928516</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Open science practices have gained widespread adoption, globally, with the help of federal funding and&lt;br/&gt;publisher policies, as well as the increasing visibility and growing awareness of the value of sharing&lt;br/&gt;work. This has been largely evident in light of the current COVID19 pandemic, with data sharing driving&lt;br/&gt;many areas of research, and open software resources must evolve to meet the needs of researchers.  To meet the emerging demands and growing requirements of the research community who need support for both data and software sharing, Dryad and California Digital Library partnered in 2018 and Dryad and Zenodo partnered in 2019. These partnerships have allowed for the three organizations to re-think the data and publishing processes, explore ways for data curation, software preservation, and for output re-use to be tied together more seamlessly. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is a one-day, invitational workshop bringing together researchers and adjacent community members with diverse backgrounds to discuss needs, challenges, and priorities for re-using research data and software.  The goal of the meeting is to develop pathways for consistent engagement with individuals and groups across the diverse scientific disciplines in order to be connected with and responsive to researchers' needs and goals.  Meeting topics include dataset re-use, deposition guidance, curation standards and requirements, integrations and relationships between data and code, and advocacy and adoption. The anticipated outputs are a set of requirements and needs to better enable data and software sharing and re-use.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/17/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/17/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2031647</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Guenter</FirstName>
<LastName>Waibel</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Guenter Waibel</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[guenter.waibel@ucop.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000750535</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/17/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California, Office of the President, Oakland</Name>
<CityName>OAKLAND</CityName>
<ZipCode>946075201</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5109879850</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1111 FRANKLIN ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>PKK5TD16N4H1</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California, Office of the President, Oakland]]></Name>
<CityName>Oakland</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>946122901</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[415-20th Street, 4 FL]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6892</Code>
<Text>CI REUSE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7414</Code>
<Text>NSF Public Access Initiative</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>077Z</Code>
<Text>CSSI-1: Cyberinfr for Sustained Scientif</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8004</Code>
<Text>Software Institutes</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~46793</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-3f528360-7fff-5214-2518-31177a2df90c"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>In response to the COVID19 pandemic, causing a break in collaborations and in-person connections, we gathered a group of open source data and software infrastructure providers to focus on how we could work together to prioritize and build for a more seamless software and data publishing ecosystem. The group represented large-scale data and software repositories, discipline specific repositories, persistent identifier and metadata organizations, data management experts, data training experts, and open source software projects.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Over two-days, participants worked through current problem areas and generated ideas for new collaborations and integrations that could significantly drive forward data and software publishing. Participants brainstormed with prompts such as if resources were limitless what would each individual want to change in the ecosystem to make software and data publishing more seamless and best practices better adopted across research disciplines. This resulted in potential projects and collaborations centered around the topics of: increasing data and software publishing capacity upstream in data skills training (academic and other), code-sharing across generalist and disciplinary repositories for broader implementation of necessary tools integrations, and automation of software practices. Discussions around evaluating what has worked and what is needed for a trusted forum for collaboration sparked ideas for how existing infrastructure could be adapted to better fit adapting needs.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The collaborations and knowledge sharing from the workshop could lead to an increase in data and software publishing educational resources (especially upstream in research careers) for scientists and help to further drive adoption of data and software publishing across diverse scientific disciplines.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/29/2023<br>      Modified by: Guenter&nbsp;Waibel</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   In response to the COVID19 pandemic, causing a break in collaborations and in-person connections, we gathered a group of open source data and software infrastructure providers to focus on how we could work together to prioritize and build for a more seamless software and data publishing ecosystem. The group represented large-scale data and software repositories, discipline specific repositories, persistent identifier and metadata organizations, data management experts, data training experts, and open source software projects.  Over two-days, participants worked through current problem areas and generated ideas for new collaborations and integrations that could significantly drive forward data and software publishing. Participants brainstormed with prompts such as if resources were limitless what would each individual want to change in the ecosystem to make software and data publishing more seamless and best practices better adopted across research disciplines. This resulted in potential projects and collaborations centered around the topics of: increasing data and software publishing capacity upstream in data skills training (academic and other), code-sharing across generalist and disciplinary repositories for broader implementation of necessary tools integrations, and automation of software practices. Discussions around evaluating what has worked and what is needed for a trusted forum for collaboration sparked ideas for how existing infrastructure could be adapted to better fit adapting needs. The collaborations and knowledge sharing from the workshop could lead to an increase in data and software publishing educational resources (especially upstream in research careers) for scientists and help to further drive adoption of data and software publishing across diverse scientific disciplines.          Last Modified: 03/29/2023       Submitted by: Guenter Waibel]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
