<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Frontera Travel Grant: Fundamental Studies of Compressible Turbulence and Turbulent Mixing]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>9598.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>9598</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OAC</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure (OAC)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Edward Walker</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>edwalker@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924863</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[For nearly four decades, the National Science Foundation (NSF) has played a leadership role in provisioning advanced cyberinfrastructure capabilities for the Nation's Science and Engineering (S&amp;E) researchers. An important component in this investment is the leadership-class computing program that provides computational and data analytics capabilities at the largest scale to inspire transformative S&amp;E discoveries that would not be possible otherwise. NSF's current leadership-class computing investment supports Frontera, the largest High-Performance Computing (HPC) system on a US academic campus. The Frontera system is deployed and operated by the Texas Advanced Computing Center (TACC) at the University of Texas (UT) at Austin. This travel grant will support the participation of researchers who have been awarded a computer time allocation on the Frontera system at a future Principal Investigator (PI) meeting organized by TACC. The award will also support travel for technical coordination between researchers and the Frontera project to ensure optimal and effective utilization of the Frontera system.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of the PI meeting is to allow Frontera research users, as well as their students, to share scientific results, exchange practical lessons-learned, and present their overall experience from using the Frontera system. In addition to research presentations, the meeting will have ample time, as well as facilitated sessions, to promote increased interaction between Frontera research users and project staff. The outcome of the PI meeting will not only enable the Frontera project to better understand and serve the scientific research community, but also build a community to better represent the unique needs of S&amp;E research that require access to NSF leadership computing facilities. To facilitate deeper coordination beyond the PI meeting, this award will also provide travel support to enable technical coordination between the research user teams and the Frontera project.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/12/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/12/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2031913</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Diego</FirstName>
<LastName>Donzis</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Diego A Donzis</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[donzis@tamu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000543975</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/12/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Texas A&amp;M Engineering Experiment Station</Name>
<CityName>COLLEGE STATION</CityName>
<ZipCode>778433124</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9798626777</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3124 TAMU</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>QD1MX6N5YTN4</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TEXAS A&amp;M ENGINEERING EXPERIMENT STATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>QD1MX6N5YTN4</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Texas A&M Engineering Experiment Station]]></Name>
<CityName>College Station</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>778433141</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[TAMU 3141]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7781</Code>
<Text>Leadership-Class Computing</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~9598</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span style="font-family: monospace;"><span style="color: #000000; background-color: #ffffff;">The purpose of this project was to to support our collaborative efforts with the Texas Advanced </span><span style="color: #000000; background-color: #54ffff;">Superco</span><br />mputing<span style="color: #000000; background-color: #ffffff;"> Center to advance our Leadership Resource Allocation on </span><span style="color: #000000; background-color: #ffd7d7;">Frontera</span><span style="color: #000000; background-color: #ffffff;">, the latest NSF leadership-cla</span><br />ss computing resource. This supercomputer allocation allows us to study mixing in compressible turbulen<br />ce using high-fidelity numerical simulations to reach conditions not possible before and providing data<br /> at unprecedented levels of realism in a data-scarce field. The simulations on <span style="color: #000000; background-color: #ffd7d7;">Frontera</span><span style="color: #000000; background-color: #ffffff;"> are at sufficie</span><br />ntly high Reynolds numbers to permit the investigation, for the first time, of an emerging inertial ran<br />ge dynamics of the velocity as well as the scalar fields, providing data to further our understanding o<br />f mixing processes in compressible flows. The level of details of the generated fields allows us to stu<br />dy long-standing and new questions, including the nature of the inertial range for the two components o<br />f the velocity field, the scalar field, the nature of small-scale fluctuations, and deep concepts of up<br />-to-now-elusive universal scaling laws. The size and characteristics of <span style="color: #000000; background-color: #ffd7d7;">Frontera</span><span style="color: #000000; background-color: #ffffff;"> also allow us to explo</span><br />re new paradigms including mixed-precision computing, as well as a new algorithmic approach based on <span style="color: #000000; background-color: #54ffff;">as</span><br />ynchrony<span style="color: #000000; background-color: #ffffff;"> which could potentially mitigate all bottlenecks expected at extreme scales. </span><br /> <br />Travel, which was an important part of this supplement to interact with expert consultants at <span style="color: #000000; background-color: #ffd7d7;">TACC</span><span style="color: #000000; background-color: #ffffff;">, was</span><br /> significantly affected due to <span style="color: #000000; background-color: #ffd7d7;">COVID</span><span style="color: #000000; background-color: #ffffff;">. However, we have still been able to interact with expert </span><span style="color: #000000; background-color: #ffd7d7;">TACC</span><span style="color: #000000; background-color: #ffffff;"> </span><span style="color: #000000; background-color: #ffd7d7;">con</span><br />sultans<span style="color: #000000; background-color: #ffffff;"> and port our code on </span><span style="color: #000000; background-color: #ffd7d7;">Frontera</span><span style="color: #000000; background-color: #ffffff;">. We have identified specific performance bottlenecks. In particul</span><br />ar, we found great sensitivity to the how we map the physical domain to the network topology. Since the<br /> code is based on a <span style="color: #000000; background-color: #54ffff;">2D</span><span style="color: #000000; background-color: #ffffff;"> processor grid decomposition of a </span><span style="color: #000000; background-color: #54ffff;">3D</span><span style="color: #000000; background-color: #ffffff;"> domain, the selection of the shape of the </span><span style="color: #000000; background-color: #54ffff;">2</span><br />D<span style="color: #000000; background-color: #ffffff;"> processor grid has a first-order effect on performance. While an accurate performance model is still </span><br />being formulated, we have found that smaller core count in the first dimension of the processor grid ge<br />nerally leads to higher performance. We continue to investigate this issue. <br /> <br />Under this project a student was able to interact with experts at <span style="color: #000000; background-color: #ffd7d7;">TACC</span><span style="color: #000000; background-color: #ffffff;"> in different areas of high-perfo</span><br />rmance computing (<span style="color: #000000; background-color: #ffd7d7;">HPC</span><span style="color: #000000; background-color: #ffffff;">). In part because of this, she has been selected to participate in selective </span><span style="color: #000000; background-color: #ffd7d7;">HPC</span><span style="color: #000000; background-color: #ffffff;"> </span><br />summer schools in the US and abroad. Furthermore, she is now also part of a team selected to be a <br />Characteristic Science Application (<span style="color: #000000; background-color: #54ffff;">CSA</span><span style="color: #000000; background-color: #ffffff;">) to aid NSF in planning for the next Leadership Class Computing</span><br /> Facility (<span style="color: #000000; background-color: #ffd7d7;">LCCF</span><span style="color: #000000; background-color: #ffffff;">) at </span><span style="color: #000000; background-color: #ffd7d7;">TACC</span><span style="color: #000000; background-color: #ffffff;">. The impact of this project will have, thus, long-lasting impact in the develo</span><br />pment of the next generation scientists and engineering.<br /></span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/18/2022<br>      Modified by: Diego&nbsp;A&nbsp;Donzis</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The purpose of this project was to to support our collaborative efforts with the Texas Advanced Superco mputing Center to advance our Leadership Resource Allocation on Frontera, the latest NSF leadership-cla ss computing resource. This supercomputer allocation allows us to study mixing in compressible turbulen ce using high-fidelity numerical simulations to reach conditions not possible before and providing data  at unprecedented levels of realism in a data-scarce field. The simulations on Frontera are at sufficie ntly high Reynolds numbers to permit the investigation, for the first time, of an emerging inertial ran ge dynamics of the velocity as well as the scalar fields, providing data to further our understanding o f mixing processes in compressible flows. The level of details of the generated fields allows us to stu dy long-standing and new questions, including the nature of the inertial range for the two components o f the velocity field, the scalar field, the nature of small-scale fluctuations, and deep concepts of up -to-now-elusive universal scaling laws. The size and characteristics of Frontera also allow us to explo re new paradigms including mixed-precision computing, as well as a new algorithmic approach based on as ynchrony which could potentially mitigate all bottlenecks expected at extreme scales.    Travel, which was an important part of this supplement to interact with expert consultants at TACC, was  significantly affected due to COVID. However, we have still been able to interact with expert TACC con sultans and port our code on Frontera. We have identified specific performance bottlenecks. In particul ar, we found great sensitivity to the how we map the physical domain to the network topology. Since the  code is based on a 2D processor grid decomposition of a 3D domain, the selection of the shape of the 2 D processor grid has a first-order effect on performance. While an accurate performance model is still  being formulated, we have found that smaller core count in the first dimension of the processor grid ge nerally leads to higher performance. We continue to investigate this issue.    Under this project a student was able to interact with experts at TACC in different areas of high-perfo rmance computing (HPC). In part because of this, she has been selected to participate in selective HPC  summer schools in the US and abroad. Furthermore, she is now also part of a team selected to be a  Characteristic Science Application (CSA) to aid NSF in planning for the next Leadership Class Computing  Facility (LCCF) at TACC. The impact of this project will have, thus, long-lasting impact in the develo pment of the next generation scientists and engineering.        Last Modified: 08/18/2022       Submitted by: Diego A Donzis]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
