<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research: RAPID: Investigating Impacts of and Response to COVID-19 in the Technology Innovation Enterprise]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>15260.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>15260</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Allyson Kennedy</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>aykenned@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928905</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The COVID-19 pandemic is quickly altering the landscape of our personal and professional lives, and the impacts from the pandemic on the innovation enterprise are profound. Industry is seeing hiring freezes and layoffs. Teachers and college faculty have had to quickly shift to online course delivery. Students have also had to make the shift to online courses, and many face the loss of communal labs that are set-up to support their work. If we are to be able to respond effectively to the impacts of the pandemic, it is paramount that we quickly gather systematic data, in real-time, from the innovation community. This RAPID award will assess the state of the computing innovation community from K-12 education to the tech workforce. Through a survey of the short, medium, and long term effects of the COVID-19 pandemic on the community, this project will elucidate the current state of persistence in computing degree programs and professions and inform efforts to design and deliver education and workforce opportunities. This will support the technology innovation enterprise in mitigating the disruption caused by the COVD-19 pandemic, helping to stabilize the U.S. innovation ecosystem.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In this RAPID award, AnitaB.org, the National Center for Women &amp; Information Technology (NCWIT), and the STARS Computing Corps will gather data related to the short- and longer-term impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on the computing innovation enterprise. Due to the ever-changing COVID-19 situation, it is paramount to capture data in these early days and establish a baseline of information that we will be able to build on as the situation unfolds. The objective of this award is to understand the impact of the global pandemic on the conditions of work and educational environments related to factors associated with persistence in computing degree programs and professions. The team will sample across the computing ecosystem by gathering data from K-12 teachers; post-secondary program leaders, educators and students; and individuals in the computing workforce. They will assess the following research questions to understand impacts at both the individual and organizational levels: &lt;br/&gt;1. How is the computing ecosystem (K12, postsecondary, industry, startup) responding to the COVID-19 crisis? &lt;br/&gt;2. What are the short-term, intermediate, and longer-term impacts of the COVID-19 crisis on the computing community, in terms of the design and delivery of computing instruction (K12, postsecondary) and research and the experiences of technologists in industry?&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/19/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/19/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2031984</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jamie</FirstName>
<LastName>Payton</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jamie J Payton</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jamie.payton@temple.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000723533</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/19/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Temple University</Name>
<CityName>PHILADELPHIA</CityName>
<ZipCode>191226003</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2157077547</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1801 N BROAD ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>QD4MGHFDJKU1</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TEMPLE UNIVERSITY-OF THE COMMONWEALTH SYSTEM OF HIGHER EDUCATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>QD4MGHFDJKU1</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Temple University]]></Name>
<CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>191226003</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1801 N Broad Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>158y</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>1N20</Code>
<Name>R&amp;RA CARES Act DEFC N</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>010N2021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[R&RA CARES Act DEFC N]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~15260</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-83b7cc60-7fff-3d75-d7fc-7667e204f41f"> <p dir="ltr"><span>The investigation of the </span><span>Compounding Impacts of Racism &amp; COVID-19 on Learning &amp; Employment in Computing &amp; Technology (CIRCLE-CT)</span><span> was a collaborative research project between AnitaB.org, the National Center for Women &amp; Information Technology (NCWIT), and the STARS Computing Corps (#2031978, #2031984, #2031877). The project aimed to understand the impacts of the global COVID-19 pandemic and the accompanying racial justice movements on the computing community. We defined the computing community as technologists in industry, those who work and study in US colleges and universities, and those who teach computing in K-12 schools. Our focus was on understanding how individuals and organizations were impacted and the implications for initiatives to broaden participation in computing (BPC). The study involved three surveys administered over a two-year period. Survey 1 (Summer 2020) had 486 responses, Survey 2 (Fall 2020) 3,122 responses, and Survey 3 (Fall 2021) 138 responses. When there were sufficient numbers of responses, data were analyzed by intersectional demographic and identity groups (e.g., White women faculty, Asian men in industry, people with disabilities in higher education, etc.).</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The effects of COVID-19 were felt by nearly everyone within the computing community, particularly in the first two surveys. For example, most respondents reported decreased productivity (66%) and decreased enthusiasm about work/school (56%) -- with no notable differences between groups. We also found that respondents experienced different effects depending on their context and/or individual characteristics. For example, in Survey 1, relatively early in the pandemic,</span><span> respondents working in industry were more likely to report significant decreases to their workload (17% industry, 1% higher ed; p&lt;.001) compared to those working in higher education who were more likely to report significant increases (54% vs. 30%; p&lt;.05).&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Commonalities across sectors were observed, including increased isolation from colleagues, reduced networking, and concern for their career potential. Further, we observed that the impact of the COVID-19 pandemic was often significantly different for individuals depending on their gender, being a racial/ethnic minority within the field of computing, and identifying as LGBTQIA+, as well as the intersections of these identities. Consistently, when there were significant differences, the underrepresented and minoritized groups had worse experiences. A collective subset noted the &ldquo;tax&rdquo; that people of color are bearing because of racism. One student commented:</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>&ldquo;I am having a much harder time focusing on my studies/career than other students who are not POC [people of color] who the news/social upheaval seems to have little to no impact on their schooling or day to day lives.&rdquo; <em>-Asian woman student, no disability, LGBTQIA+ community, not a caregiver.</em></span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The heightened attention in the US to racial injustice during our study period had a&nbsp; particularly profound effect on those who have a marginalized identity within computing (and within US society)&mdash;women in general, people of color of all genders, and women from racial/ethnic groups historically underrepresented in computing. Across surveys, they all reported more negative outcomes than their counterparts. </span><span>For example, one survey participant shared that &ldquo;As a Black/African-American woman in technology, these two circumstances have rocked my world. The workplace has been unrelenting, even though they acknowledge the personal trauma of racism and death that I am working with.&rdquo;&nbsp;</span><em>-Black woman in higher education, no disability, not LGBTQIA+ community, not a caregiver.</em></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>O</span><span>ur findings also suggested that organizations have the potential to make a difference in individuals&rsquo; commitment to school or work and to the technology field in general. When organizations took a meaningful stand and authentically committed to diversity, equity, and inclusion principles and practices, students, faculty, and industry employees noticed and responded positively.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>By the third survey, respondents questioned the authenticity and follow-through on commitments and statements made by their organizations. When there was lack of follow-through, reactions were those of discouragement and frustration. Many individuals within computing expressed wanting to do more on behalf of social justice but not knowing what to do or how to proceed. Numerous others were simply fatigued by all of the constraints and fallout from the pandemic as well as watching the racial injustice all around them.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>We also noted tensions in opinions about the value and importance of anti-racism.&nbsp; These observations included perceptions that anti-racism is simply racism in another form and that there was no racism in computing, only different aptitudes, and opportunities.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Results may not reflect the entire computing community due to self-selection among survey respondents. However, this study offers crucial insights to ways in which the COVID-19 pandemic and heightened attention to racial justice had differential impacts on different sectors of the computing ecosystem and on the individuals within the system depending upon their identity characteristics.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>All anonymous data are available upon request, as well as through interactive dashboards at: ei@anitab.org.</span></p> </span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/28/2022<br>      Modified by: Jamie&nbsp;Payton</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  The investigation of the Compounding Impacts of Racism &amp; COVID-19 on Learning &amp; Employment in Computing &amp; Technology (CIRCLE-CT) was a collaborative research project between AnitaB.org, the National Center for Women &amp; Information Technology (NCWIT), and the STARS Computing Corps (#2031978, #2031984, #2031877). The project aimed to understand the impacts of the global COVID-19 pandemic and the accompanying racial justice movements on the computing community. We defined the computing community as technologists in industry, those who work and study in US colleges and universities, and those who teach computing in K-12 schools. Our focus was on understanding how individuals and organizations were impacted and the implications for initiatives to broaden participation in computing (BPC). The study involved three surveys administered over a two-year period. Survey 1 (Summer 2020) had 486 responses, Survey 2 (Fall 2020) 3,122 responses, and Survey 3 (Fall 2021) 138 responses. When there were sufficient numbers of responses, data were analyzed by intersectional demographic and identity groups (e.g., White women faculty, Asian men in industry, people with disabilities in higher education, etc.). The effects of COVID-19 were felt by nearly everyone within the computing community, particularly in the first two surveys. For example, most respondents reported decreased productivity (66%) and decreased enthusiasm about work/school (56%) -- with no notable differences between groups. We also found that respondents experienced different effects depending on their context and/or individual characteristics. For example, in Survey 1, relatively early in the pandemic, respondents working in industry were more likely to report significant decreases to their workload (17% industry, 1% higher ed; p&lt;.001) compared to those working in higher education who were more likely to report significant increases (54% vs. 30%; p&lt;.05).  Commonalities across sectors were observed, including increased isolation from colleagues, reduced networking, and concern for their career potential. Further, we observed that the impact of the COVID-19 pandemic was often significantly different for individuals depending on their gender, being a racial/ethnic minority within the field of computing, and identifying as LGBTQIA+, as well as the intersections of these identities. Consistently, when there were significant differences, the underrepresented and minoritized groups had worse experiences. A collective subset noted the "tax" that people of color are bearing because of racism. One student commented: "I am having a much harder time focusing on my studies/career than other students who are not POC [people of color] who the news/social upheaval seems to have little to no impact on their schooling or day to day lives." -Asian woman student, no disability, LGBTQIA+ community, not a caregiver. The heightened attention in the US to racial injustice during our study period had a  particularly profound effect on those who have a marginalized identity within computing (and within US society)&mdash;women in general, people of color of all genders, and women from racial/ethnic groups historically underrepresented in computing. Across surveys, they all reported more negative outcomes than their counterparts. For example, one survey participant shared that "As a Black/African-American woman in technology, these two circumstances have rocked my world. The workplace has been unrelenting, even though they acknowledge the personal trauma of racism and death that I am working with." -Black woman in higher education, no disability, not LGBTQIA+ community, not a caregiver. Our findings also suggested that organizations have the potential to make a difference in individuals’ commitment to school or work and to the technology field in general. When organizations took a meaningful stand and authentically committed to diversity, equity, and inclusion principles and practices, students, faculty, and industry employees noticed and responded positively.  By the third survey, respondents questioned the authenticity and follow-through on commitments and statements made by their organizations. When there was lack of follow-through, reactions were those of discouragement and frustration. Many individuals within computing expressed wanting to do more on behalf of social justice but not knowing what to do or how to proceed. Numerous others were simply fatigued by all of the constraints and fallout from the pandemic as well as watching the racial injustice all around them. We also noted tensions in opinions about the value and importance of anti-racism.  These observations included perceptions that anti-racism is simply racism in another form and that there was no racism in computing, only different aptitudes, and opportunities. Results may not reflect the entire computing community due to self-selection among survey respondents. However, this study offers crucial insights to ways in which the COVID-19 pandemic and heightened attention to racial justice had differential impacts on different sectors of the computing ecosystem and on the individuals within the system depending upon their identity characteristics.  All anonymous data are available upon request, as well as through interactive dashboards at: ei@anitab.org.        Last Modified: 09/28/2022       Submitted by: Jamie Payton]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
