<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Pandemic Anxiety, Recovery, and Inequality:  Evaluating Institutions and Policy in a Coronavirus Hotspot]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>138613.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>138613</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jan Leighley</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jleighle@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922686</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The COVID-19 pandemic simultaneously unleashed health and economic threats on American society, each of which produces anxiety. Ultimately, recovery will require reintegration into the social and economic fabric after periods defined by quarantine and social distancing measures aimed at mitigating the spread of the virus. To what extent will experiences of anxiety in the face of these threats curb downstream recovery? The objective of this project is to understand experiences of anxiety and recovery among a representative sample of adults in Louisiana, a coronavirus hotspot whose COVID-19 mortality rate is one of the deadliest in the nation. The proposed study will also offer guidance to governing officials in how anxiety inhibits economic and health recovery even as the experiences of threat change. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;To measure the durability of anxiety and its effects on social trust and engagement, data will be collected in a four-wave representative panel of adult Louisiana residents using YouGov. The investigators will measure respondents’ exposure to the health and economic threats and their anxiety over them, as well as outcome variables including perceptions of progress of recovery; trust in institutions, leaders, and residents of their communities; civic, social, and economic activity; and support for policies aimed at mitigating threat impact or reopening the economy. The major contribution of this study will be to extend the scope of analysis from the immediate, short-run effects of anxiety to the long-run patterns by which anxiety persists and has downstream consequences for social and economic engagement, as well as deepen our understanding individual differences in how anxiety is associated with social and economic judgments.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is jointly funded by the Accountable Institutions and Behavior (AIB) program and the Established Program to Stimulate Competitive Research (EPSCoR).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/07/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/09/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2031591</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Martin</FirstName>
<LastName>Johnson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Martin Johnson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[martinj@lsu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000360104</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/07/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate>12/09/2020</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Henderson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael Henderson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mbhende1@lsu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000677399</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/07/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Louisiana State University</Name>
<CityName>BATON ROUGE</CityName>
<ZipCode>708030001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2255782760</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>202 HIMES HALL</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
<StateCode>LA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>LA06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>ECQEYCHRNKJ4</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>LOUISIANA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>Z7ZNZH7LJ778</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Louisiana State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Baton Rouge</CityName>
<StateCode>LA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>708032701</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[202 Himes Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>LA06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>120Y</Code>
<Text>AIB-Acctble Institutions&amp;Behav</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EPSCoR Co-Funding</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~138613</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The COVID-19 epidemic simultaneously unleashed health and economic threats on American society, each of which produces anxiety. Ultimately, recovery from this ongoing pandemic will require reintegration into the social and economic fabric after periods defined by quarantine and social distancing measures aimed at mitigating the spread of the virus. To what extent will experiences of anxiety in the face of these threats curb downstream recovery? The objective of this project was to understand experiences of hardship during the pandemic, feelings of anxiety, and the willingness to reengage in social activities among a representative sample of adults in Louisiana, a hotspot of the pandemic.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Specifically, this research examined how feelings of anxiety about the health and economic threats of the pandemic emerged and persisted as events on the ground shifted. Addiotnally, the study tracked how anxiety shaped trust in leaders, attitudes toward policies aimed at mitigating health and economic risks, willingness to engage in social activities, and sense of inter-connection between different demographic groups. It also considered the persistence of these effects over time as the number of new cases and deaths rose and fell.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>To measure the durability of anxiety and its effects on social engagement, we tracked a group of Louisiana residents from the summer of 2020 through May of 2021, interviewing them on five separate occasions about the experiences during the pandemic. We found that personal experience of health risks (e.g., testing positive for COVID-19 or knowing someone who died from the disease) and economic (risks losing income or living with someone who lost their job) produced more anxiety than did community-wide experiences (e.g., the number of cases in a community or the amount of local unemployment). Furthermore, these feelings persisted even after threats faded. In other words, once people directly experienced a negative event, they remained worried about the health or economic risks of the pandemic for a much longer period. Addiotnally, feeling anxious about the pandemic tended to curb willingness to engage in social activities (such as attending religious services, attending public meetings of government officials, or voting in-person) and boost support for policies aimed at mitigating the spread of COVID-19 or defraying its economic effects on people and businesses. In some cases, these effects marked long-term shifts that outlasted the feelings of anxiety that initially caused them. Finally, the results show that initially, many people saw the pandemic&rsquo;s effects as isolated on particular demographic groups, particularly the elderly, Black people, and people living in urban areas. Over the ten months of the study, people began to see the pandemic as a shared threat affecting a larger variety of demographic backgrounds. However, this sense of shared threat did not translate into a greater sense of connectedness across these groups.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The intellectual merit of this study is that it looked at longer stretches of time. Past research on the social aspects of anxiety focused on its immediate, short-term causes and effects. Little was known about whether anxiety persist over longer periods. This research advanced the scholarship on anxiety by showing that it tends to reinforce itself over time and that its effects can outlast the experiences and emotions that produce them.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The broader impacts of the study are two-fold. First, this study shows how communities as a whole respond to moments of extended crisis. The results should serve as a caution for the future. Disparities of social and economic advantage shape the initial experience of hardship during a crisis, and even when threat spreads to impact more and more people, these groups do not necessarily pull together as one community. Second, this research advanced the educational experience of graduate students in the social sciences. The support of the National Science Foundation provided the opportunity for future social scientists to get hands-on experience designing and conducting research, developing their skills for use in future socially beneficial research.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/28/2021<br>      Modified by: Michael&nbsp;Henderson</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The COVID-19 epidemic simultaneously unleashed health and economic threats on American society, each of which produces anxiety. Ultimately, recovery from this ongoing pandemic will require reintegration into the social and economic fabric after periods defined by quarantine and social distancing measures aimed at mitigating the spread of the virus. To what extent will experiences of anxiety in the face of these threats curb downstream recovery? The objective of this project was to understand experiences of hardship during the pandemic, feelings of anxiety, and the willingness to reengage in social activities among a representative sample of adults in Louisiana, a hotspot of the pandemic.     Specifically, this research examined how feelings of anxiety about the health and economic threats of the pandemic emerged and persisted as events on the ground shifted. Addiotnally, the study tracked how anxiety shaped trust in leaders, attitudes toward policies aimed at mitigating health and economic risks, willingness to engage in social activities, and sense of inter-connection between different demographic groups. It also considered the persistence of these effects over time as the number of new cases and deaths rose and fell.     To measure the durability of anxiety and its effects on social engagement, we tracked a group of Louisiana residents from the summer of 2020 through May of 2021, interviewing them on five separate occasions about the experiences during the pandemic. We found that personal experience of health risks (e.g., testing positive for COVID-19 or knowing someone who died from the disease) and economic (risks losing income or living with someone who lost their job) produced more anxiety than did community-wide experiences (e.g., the number of cases in a community or the amount of local unemployment). Furthermore, these feelings persisted even after threats faded. In other words, once people directly experienced a negative event, they remained worried about the health or economic risks of the pandemic for a much longer period. Addiotnally, feeling anxious about the pandemic tended to curb willingness to engage in social activities (such as attending religious services, attending public meetings of government officials, or voting in-person) and boost support for policies aimed at mitigating the spread of COVID-19 or defraying its economic effects on people and businesses. In some cases, these effects marked long-term shifts that outlasted the feelings of anxiety that initially caused them. Finally, the results show that initially, many people saw the pandemic’s effects as isolated on particular demographic groups, particularly the elderly, Black people, and people living in urban areas. Over the ten months of the study, people began to see the pandemic as a shared threat affecting a larger variety of demographic backgrounds. However, this sense of shared threat did not translate into a greater sense of connectedness across these groups.     The intellectual merit of this study is that it looked at longer stretches of time. Past research on the social aspects of anxiety focused on its immediate, short-term causes and effects. Little was known about whether anxiety persist over longer periods. This research advanced the scholarship on anxiety by showing that it tends to reinforce itself over time and that its effects can outlast the experiences and emotions that produce them.     The broader impacts of the study are two-fold. First, this study shows how communities as a whole respond to moments of extended crisis. The results should serve as a caution for the future. Disparities of social and economic advantage shape the initial experience of hardship during a crisis, and even when threat spreads to impact more and more people, these groups do not necessarily pull together as one community. Second, this research advanced the educational experience of graduate students in the social sciences. The support of the National Science Foundation provided the opportunity for future social scientists to get hands-on experience designing and conducting research, developing their skills for use in future socially beneficial research.          Last Modified: 09/28/2021       Submitted by: Michael Henderson]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
