<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Rapid Antigen-based SERS assay for COVID-19 Detection (COVID-19)]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>255468.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>255468</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Alastair Monk</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>amonk@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924392</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact and commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is to allow testing of potential COVID-19 patients using a rapid and highly accurate diagnostic test, particularly for patients who are asymptomatic. This will provide a significant advantage in “flattening the curve” of the number of cases by preventing these patients from inadvertently infecting their family and community members. Current protocols require days to return a result, creating problems for public health.  This test, the first of many that can be produced using the underlying platform technology, would improve: 1) the ability to rapidly identify patients with active COVID-19 cases for expeditious clinical intervention, reducing transmission by that patient; and 2) outcomes because of the higher performance and accuracy. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project addresses the lack of rapid, accurate testing for COVID-19 in near patient settings. This effort will develop an infectious disease platform that combines: 1) DNA aptamers, a recognition element for target proteins; 2) surface enhanced Raman scattering (SERS), a vibrational spectroscopic detection method; 3) and orthogonal partial least squares differential analysis, a well-established statistical method often applied to vibrational spectroscopy-based analyses. By employing aptamers that target SARS-CoV-2 related proteins (e.g. the spike (S) protein), this assay is anticipated to identify the presence of this protein under 30 minutes after oro- or naso-pharyngeal sample is collected, and is ultimately expected to achieve &gt;95% clinical sensitivity and specificity.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/30/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/30/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2031056</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Joel</FirstName>
<LastName>Tabb</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Joel S Tabb</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[j.tabb@ionicasci.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000741030</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/30/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Ionica Sciences</Name>
<CityName>ITHACA</CityName>
<ZipCode>148537202</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6266763076</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>237 TOWER RD STE 414</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>19</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY19</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>M674Y89DSR86</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>IONICA SCIENCES, INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Ionica Sciences]]></Name>
<CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>148537202</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[414 Weill Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>19</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY19</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>090E</Code>
<Text>Chem/Bio and Physical Diagnostics</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~255468</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Ionica Sciences&rsquo; Phase I project focused on the development of a rapid, field deployable assay for SARS-CoV-2. The established testing paradigms, Polymerase Chain Reaction (PCR) and rapid antigen testing, were not sufficient at the time of the outbreak due to critical deficiencies in established methods. PCR methods are complex, prone to contamination and are inappropriate for field use, and rapid antigen testing, which is easier and faster to run, often lacks the required sensitivity. To address this gap in capabilities, Ionica&rsquo;s IonID platform was developed to enable rapid identification of infectious diseases. Specifically, this Phase I project sought to adapt the IonID platform for diagnosis of COVID-19, resulting in the development of an IonCOVID assay.</p> <p>The IonID<sup>TM</sup> platform for infectious disease diagnosis combines two technologies, aptamers and surface enhanced Raman scattering (SERS), to provide a sensitive and selective approach to infectious disease detection. The goals of this Phase I projected were to: (1) Identify aptamers capable of detecting antigen proteins from SARS-CoV-2; (2)<strong> </strong>Modify the aptamers SERS-active markers to improve the sensitivity for detection of target proteins in a complex sample matrix associated with Oropharyngeal (OP) and Nasopharyngeal (NP) samples, and (3) Demonstrate the efficacy of the aptamer-modified SERS substrates to detect SARS-CoV-2 in commercially available panels of OP/NP samples. Three commercially sourced DNA aptamers targeting SARS-CoV-2 Spike protein were identified and synthesized with modifications to enable integration into SERS substrates and detection by a SERS-based detection method.</p> <p>The DNA aptamers were tested with diluted human saliva spiked with recombinant SARS-CoV-2 Spike protein to determine the aptamer that functioned best in this assay. One aptamer was determined to display the highest clinical sensitivity and specificity via SERS analysis. Limit of detection analysis determined that approximately 100 viral particles per milliliter could be detected by the IonCOVID test. Reports for other SARS-CoV-2 assays display similar LOD levels. A small preclinical trial conducted with of 30 SARS-CoV-2 positive and 30 healthy control patients indicated that the IonCOVID test was able to achieve 70.0 % sensitivity and 66.7% specificity.</p> <p>The ability to diagnose diseases accurately and shortly after a patient has been exposed to infectious viruses or bacteria is critical in rapid treatment of the associated diseases. Because the IonID&trade; platform can be readily adapted by exchanging an aptamer specific for a protein associated with one disease for one targeting a protein associated with another disease, it can easily be adapted to detect biomarkers for multiple diseases at pg/ml detection levels. Additionally, because DNA aptamers are biologically stable, they can be used for high sensitivity detections in a variety of complex biological matrices such as serum, saliva, urine, and fecal material.</p> <p>Ionica&rsquo;s IonCOVID Test technology enables near-patient of point-of-care (POC) active virus testing capability with an ease of use for the operator that cannot be matched by PCR based tests.&nbsp; In the POC format, the IonCOVID Test can deliver accurate results in less than 30 minutes without the complicated pre-handling steps that current rt-PCR tests require. The IonCOVID Test technology can be developed easily for both high throughput laboratories (96 well plates and a high throughput reader allowing for thousands of tests per hour) as well as a small, portable, shoebox sized reader that utilizes single use cartridges to deliver results in less than 30 minutes at POC or in STAT laboratories within hospitals or clinics.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/13/2022<br>      Modified by: Joel&nbsp;S&nbsp;Tabb</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Ionica Sciences’ Phase I project focused on the development of a rapid, field deployable assay for SARS-CoV-2. The established testing paradigms, Polymerase Chain Reaction (PCR) and rapid antigen testing, were not sufficient at the time of the outbreak due to critical deficiencies in established methods. PCR methods are complex, prone to contamination and are inappropriate for field use, and rapid antigen testing, which is easier and faster to run, often lacks the required sensitivity. To address this gap in capabilities, Ionica’s IonID platform was developed to enable rapid identification of infectious diseases. Specifically, this Phase I project sought to adapt the IonID platform for diagnosis of COVID-19, resulting in the development of an IonCOVID assay.  The IonIDTM platform for infectious disease diagnosis combines two technologies, aptamers and surface enhanced Raman scattering (SERS), to provide a sensitive and selective approach to infectious disease detection. The goals of this Phase I projected were to: (1) Identify aptamers capable of detecting antigen proteins from SARS-CoV-2; (2) Modify the aptamers SERS-active markers to improve the sensitivity for detection of target proteins in a complex sample matrix associated with Oropharyngeal (OP) and Nasopharyngeal (NP) samples, and (3) Demonstrate the efficacy of the aptamer-modified SERS substrates to detect SARS-CoV-2 in commercially available panels of OP/NP samples. Three commercially sourced DNA aptamers targeting SARS-CoV-2 Spike protein were identified and synthesized with modifications to enable integration into SERS substrates and detection by a SERS-based detection method.  The DNA aptamers were tested with diluted human saliva spiked with recombinant SARS-CoV-2 Spike protein to determine the aptamer that functioned best in this assay. One aptamer was determined to display the highest clinical sensitivity and specificity via SERS analysis. Limit of detection analysis determined that approximately 100 viral particles per milliliter could be detected by the IonCOVID test. Reports for other SARS-CoV-2 assays display similar LOD levels. A small preclinical trial conducted with of 30 SARS-CoV-2 positive and 30 healthy control patients indicated that the IonCOVID test was able to achieve 70.0 % sensitivity and 66.7% specificity.  The ability to diagnose diseases accurately and shortly after a patient has been exposed to infectious viruses or bacteria is critical in rapid treatment of the associated diseases. Because the IonID&trade; platform can be readily adapted by exchanging an aptamer specific for a protein associated with one disease for one targeting a protein associated with another disease, it can easily be adapted to detect biomarkers for multiple diseases at pg/ml detection levels. Additionally, because DNA aptamers are biologically stable, they can be used for high sensitivity detections in a variety of complex biological matrices such as serum, saliva, urine, and fecal material.  Ionica’s IonCOVID Test technology enables near-patient of point-of-care (POC) active virus testing capability with an ease of use for the operator that cannot be matched by PCR based tests.  In the POC format, the IonCOVID Test can deliver accurate results in less than 30 minutes without the complicated pre-handling steps that current rt-PCR tests require. The IonCOVID Test technology can be developed easily for both high throughput laboratories (96 well plates and a high throughput reader allowing for thousands of tests per hour) as well as a small, portable, shoebox sized reader that utilizes single use cartridges to deliver results in less than 30 minutes at POC or in STAT laboratories within hospitals or clinics.                Last Modified: 01/13/2022       Submitted by: Joel S Tabb]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
