<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[APS Division of Fluid Dynamics Travel Support]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>30000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>30000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ron Joslin</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rjoslin@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927030</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The project will partially cover travel expenses of graduate students, post-doctoral researchers, and junior faculty members from institutions in the United States to participate in the conference entitled, "American Physical Society Division of Fluid Dynamics (DFD) 73rd Annual Meeting in Chicago, IL, November 22-24, 2020. This is the largest international annual meeting of fluid dynamics researchers in the world, with over 2,500 anticipated attendees.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The chief intellectual merit of this conference lies in the exchange of scientific ideas, presentations of cutting-edge research, and exposure to a richly diverse array of topics in virtually every sub-discipline of fluid dynamics. The conference will be attended by both prominent and young scientists in fluid dynamics from around the world, who will be discussing present and future directions of research and research challenges. The conference will foster cross-fertilization of ideas among researchers in cutting edge areas of fluid dynamics and will address challenges involved in advancing the field. The broader impact will be to increase participation of students and young scientists who would not otherwise be able to afford to travel to the meeting and pay associated costs. The travel grant program has traditionally prioritized meeting attendance by students, young scientists, and, in general, scientists from under-represented groups. Since the awards are meant to supplement participant travel funds, not to cover these entirely, the committee takes into account the travel budget entered on the application. Special effort is made to achieve diverse participation from underrepresented groups in engineering, including women and members of minority groups.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/20/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/20/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2031582</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Cortney</FirstName>
<LastName>Bougher</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Cortney A Bougher</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[bougher@aps.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000807576</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/20/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>American Physical Society</Name>
<CityName>COLLEGE PARK</CityName>
<ZipCode>207403841</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3012093657</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>ONE PHYSICS ELL IPSE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MD04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>CE5JV8E9K4S3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>AMERICAN PHYSICAL SOCIETY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[American Physical Society]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>207403841</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MD04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1406</Code>
<Text>TTP-Thermal Transport Process</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1415</Code>
<Text>PMP-Particul&amp;MultiphaseProcess</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1443</Code>
<Text>FD-Fluid Dynamics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~30000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The primary goal of this project was to provide support for early career and student scientists to travel to and participate in the annual APS Division of Fluid Dynamics (DFD) meeting over a period of three years. APS DFD is the largest international annual meeting of fluid dynamicists in the world, with 2,500-3,000 attendees. The chief intellectual merit of this conference lies in the exchange of scientific ideas, presentations of cutting edge research, and exposure to a richly diverse array of topics in virtually every sub-discipline of fluid dynamics.</p> <p>The broader impact of the grant was to increase participation of students and young scientists who would not otherwise be able to afford to travel to the meeting and pay associated costs. Preference is given: (i) to those presenting talks at the meeting, (ii) to students, (iii) to applicants from other than US, Canada, Western Europe, Japan, Russia, (iv) to those who have not received such an award in the past, and (v) to no more than one applicant from a given research advisor. Special effort is made to achieve diverse participation from underrepresented groups in engineering, including women and members of minority groups.</p> <p>The application and selection process were administered by the APS DFD External Affairs Committee. Consideration was given to the availability of funds to complement the travel award, clarity of the abstract, and the perceived quality of the scientific work described in the abstract. Additional categories for enabling or disability awards cover up to full travel costs in cases where researchers would not otherwise attend the meeting.</p> <p>A total of $30,000 in funding was received. This facilitated travel subsidies for 42 participants at the 2021 APS Division of Fluid Dynamics Meeting. The NSF support funded 42 individuals from the U.S. only. Awards were $300-$1000, with some larger, enabling grants also awarded.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/20/2022<br>      Modified by: Cortney&nbsp;A&nbsp;Bougher</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The primary goal of this project was to provide support for early career and student scientists to travel to and participate in the annual APS Division of Fluid Dynamics (DFD) meeting over a period of three years. APS DFD is the largest international annual meeting of fluid dynamicists in the world, with 2,500-3,000 attendees. The chief intellectual merit of this conference lies in the exchange of scientific ideas, presentations of cutting edge research, and exposure to a richly diverse array of topics in virtually every sub-discipline of fluid dynamics.  The broader impact of the grant was to increase participation of students and young scientists who would not otherwise be able to afford to travel to the meeting and pay associated costs. Preference is given: (i) to those presenting talks at the meeting, (ii) to students, (iii) to applicants from other than US, Canada, Western Europe, Japan, Russia, (iv) to those who have not received such an award in the past, and (v) to no more than one applicant from a given research advisor. Special effort is made to achieve diverse participation from underrepresented groups in engineering, including women and members of minority groups.  The application and selection process were administered by the APS DFD External Affairs Committee. Consideration was given to the availability of funds to complement the travel award, clarity of the abstract, and the perceived quality of the scientific work described in the abstract. Additional categories for enabling or disability awards cover up to full travel costs in cases where researchers would not otherwise attend the meeting.  A total of $30,000 in funding was received. This facilitated travel subsidies for 42 participants at the 2021 APS Division of Fluid Dynamics Meeting. The NSF support funded 42 individuals from the U.S. only. Awards were $300-$1000, with some larger, enabling grants also awarded.                Last Modified: 10/20/2022       Submitted by: Cortney A Bougher]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
