<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Critical Thinking and People-Place Relationships in Citizen Science]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>292304.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>350763</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DRL</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ellen McCallie</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>emccalli@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925115</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[As part of its overall strategy to enhance learning in informal environments, the Advancing Informal STEM Learning (AISL) program seeks to advance new approaches to, and evidence-based understanding of, the design and development of STEM learning in informal environments. This includes providing multiple pathways for broadening access to and engagement in STEM learning experiences, advancing innovative research on and assessment of STEM learning in informal environments, and developing understandings of deeper learning by participants. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This pilot and feasibility project will explore whether participation in informal science initiatives like citizen science, which is a form of Public Participation in Scientific Research, can foster or enhance participant attachment to the natural places participants investigate via these programs. The project also examines if participant attachment to place influences the development or application of critical thinking skills among adult learners. Critical thinking skills and the factors that enhance critical thinking skills are important areas of inquiry within the informal STEM learning community. Existing scholarship suggests that three components may be linked: (1) feelings of connection to specific places, (2) intentional exploration and investigation of those places (in this case via citizen science), and (3) understanding of complex socio-ecological systems, which is predicated on critical thinking skills ability. However, the degree to which these aspects are related to each other, the scale at which they occur (local to global), and the specific dimensions of place connection or informal science experiences implicated is not known. Working with the Coastal Observation and Seabird Survey Team (COASST) citizen science program, this project advances collaboration among experts from disparate fields to examine if and how citizen science contributes to increases in connection to place and higher-order critical thinking skills among participants and the potential links between those hypothesized outcomes. The ultimate goal of the project is to inform design of Public Participation in Scientific Research programming that optimizes participant learning, interest, and retention; produces societal outcomes like critical thinking in support of science literacy; and creates high quality data of the scale and grain needed to address questions and issues across the basic-applied science continuum.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;This research focuses on the degree to which Public Participation in Scientific Research, specifically citizen science, may foster the presence or intensity of place attachment felt by participants for the sites and settings investigated through these programs and to what extent place attachment may be linked to higher order critical thinking skills among adult learners. A three-pronged mixed-methods research strategy will include: (1) a re-analysis of existing survey and interview data for markers of three-dimensional (personal, social, natural) place attachment as well as critical thinking skills and dispositions; (2) an assessment survey to test for the presence and intensity of place attachment and critical thinking skills; and (3) in-depth interviews to better understand the qualitative nature and development of place attachment and critical thinking skills in a citizen science context. The survey and interview sample will be drawn from participants in the COASST citizen science program and will be stratified into four groups as a function of time engaged in the program, including new, novice, and long-term participants. An independent external advisory board and a committee of visitors comprised of experts in informal science, education, and sense of place will critique and help guide this work. Results are expected to reveal important factors that impact the learning and behavioral outcomes of informal STEM initiatives by probing questions about the essential experiences, exposures, and COASST program components that facilitate deeper critical thinking skills and place attachment. Synthesizing theoretical frameworks from the fields of geography, science education, and educational psychology while testing a unique methodological approach to best measure critical thinking skills and place attachment in an informal citizen science setting will enhance knowledge-building among research and practitioner communities. &lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;In a globalized and increasingly technologically complex world, the ability of citizens to interrogate and interpret scientific evidence, views, and values is critical. That is, scientific literacy is essential for the maintenance of robust and healthy economic, social, and environmental systems in the twenty-first century. Informal science learning fills an important gap in national educational efforts to cultivate a scientifically literate populace as research suggests that formal science training is not always capable of fostering the type of higher order critical thinking skills that undergird such scientific competency. This project aims to strengthen infrastructure and build capacity among informal science practitioners by clarifying whether specific aspects and forms of Public Participation in Scientific Research, especially those relating to people-place connections, are implicated in the development and/or application of critical thinking skills in STEM settings. This effort may expand opportunities to strengthen informal science learning program outcomes, including the cultivation of numerous 21st century skills like information literacy and social skills like conflict management. Through a greater understanding of the individual components that shape informal learning experiences and outcomes, this project also has the potential to support the broadening of participation in STEM fields by providing the groundwork for further research on whether or not underrepresented or traditionally marginalized groups of people experience and/or relate differently to both the "places" most common in citizen science and the practice of informal science programming itself.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/19/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/07/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2031884</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Benjamin</FirstName>
<LastName>Haywood</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>K</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Benjamin K Haywood</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[benjamin.haywood@furman.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000758014</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/22/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Benjamin</FirstName>
<LastName>Haywood</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>K</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Benjamin K Haywood</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[benjamin.haywood@furman.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000758014</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/19/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate>05/22/2020</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Julia</FirstName>
<LastName>Parrish</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>K</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Julia K Parrish</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jparrish@u.washington.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000207571</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/22/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Washington</Name>
<CityName>SEATTLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>981951016</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2065434043</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4333 BROOKLYN AVE NE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>HD1WMN6945W6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF WASHINGTON</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Washington]]></Name>
<CityName>Seatte</CityName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>981950001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4333 Broklynn Ave. NE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7259</Code>
<Text>AISL</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>043Z</Code>
<Text>PPSR- Public Participation in Scientific</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0419</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0420</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04001920DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>04002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~292304</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~58459</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-65f233ea-7fff-24e5-a8fa-d1e1a83035a5"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Results from this research suggest that repeated scientific observations at a set site over time, using a well-developed protocol, can facilitate a deepened understanding of the system and provoke a series of hypotheses about the system and the factors affecting it, all markers of critical thinking. In addition, the project has developed theoretical and methodological frameworks that help scholars and informal science practitioners understand links between feelings about a setting, connection and attachment to that place, and socio-ecological system understanding (informed by and informing critical thinking). Findings indicate that the deep relationships and interactions between participants and specific places observed through the COASST citizen science program have broader impacts on the ability of those participants to think critically and with a scientific lens.</span></p> <br /> <p dir="ltr"><span>Asking targeted questions about the situated and place-based knowledge that emerges from deep people-place relationships and the impact that has on critical thinking skills provides a foundation for novel scholarship on informal science and place-based learning. Specially, this project has:</span></p> <ol> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>advanced new theoretical and empirical frameworks for place attachment and critical thinking (see </span><a href="https://besjournals.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1002/pan3.10174"><span>this </span><span>People and Nature</span><span> article</span></a><span>)</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>expanded a common place attachment conceptual model to include novel context-specific characteristics around affinity for science, science community bonding, and social rootedness within citizen science communities</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>operationalized theoretical concepts of critical thinking within discernable and distinguishable component parts for analysis within the citizen science setting</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>provided resources for educators to engage learners in the primary research questions of the project and distilled insight from the project for citizen science program leaders (see </span><a href="https://futurumcareers.com/how-can-place-attachment-improve-scientific-literacy"><span>this Futurum Science Careers</span></a><span> magazine article)&nbsp;</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>developed specific research tools to explore place attachment and critical thinking in applied informal science settings.</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>theorized about the role of scale in place attachment and critical thinking that range from the spatial (local, regional, global) to the content-level (fine, medium, and coursegrain concepts)</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>shared key insight and stories from project participants (see our </span><a href="https://thecoastproject.com/"><span>COASSToryLines</span></a><span> project)</span></p> </li> </ol><br /> <p dir="ltr"><span>As a whole, this research has promoted innovation by considering more thoroughly the role of sense of place in informal citizen science settings and considering how and in what ways people-place relationships influence critical thinking and the development of local and actionable scientific knowledge. The degree to which place attachment fosters higher-order thinking and learning skills, and vice versa, is relevant over a wide range of learning settings and opportunities across the formal-informal continuum and may help elucidate key factors that influence the success of informal science learning. Such insight not only has practical outcomes (i.e., greater capacity to evaluate, understand, and improve current informal science practice), but will also lead to a deeper understanding of the role of informal science in shaping and responding to more systemic social changes in the public engagement in science. As such, both scientific and societal goals can be achieved, namely:&nbsp;</span></p> <ul> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>new knowledge (i.e. science) can be created, and this information can go straight into use within decision-making contexts (i.e. actionable science) in part because of the local engagement and place-based connections of participants who co-create it.</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>individual informal science participants can gain knowledge, understanding, and associated skills needed to participate in a project (i.e. learning), collectively advancing science literacy across communities and the non-expert public in an experiential and personally relevant setting.</span></p> </li> </ul> </span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/12/2023<br>      Modified by: Benjamin&nbsp;K&nbsp;Haywood</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Results from this research suggest that repeated scientific observations at a set site over time, using a well-developed protocol, can facilitate a deepened understanding of the system and provoke a series of hypotheses about the system and the factors affecting it, all markers of critical thinking. In addition, the project has developed theoretical and methodological frameworks that help scholars and informal science practitioners understand links between feelings about a setting, connection and attachment to that place, and socio-ecological system understanding (informed by and informing critical thinking). Findings indicate that the deep relationships and interactions between participants and specific places observed through the COASST citizen science program have broader impacts on the ability of those participants to think critically and with a scientific lens.   Asking targeted questions about the situated and place-based knowledge that emerges from deep people-place relationships and the impact that has on critical thinking skills provides a foundation for novel scholarship on informal science and place-based learning. Specially, this project has:   advanced new theoretical and empirical frameworks for place attachment and critical thinking (see this People and Nature article)   expanded a common place attachment conceptual model to include novel context-specific characteristics around affinity for science, science community bonding, and social rootedness within citizen science communities   operationalized theoretical concepts of critical thinking within discernable and distinguishable component parts for analysis within the citizen science setting   provided resources for educators to engage learners in the primary research questions of the project and distilled insight from the project for citizen science program leaders (see this Futurum Science Careers magazine article)    developed specific research tools to explore place attachment and critical thinking in applied informal science settings.   theorized about the role of scale in place attachment and critical thinking that range from the spatial (local, regional, global) to the content-level (fine, medium, and coursegrain concepts)   shared key insight and stories from project participants (see our COASSToryLines project)    As a whole, this research has promoted innovation by considering more thoroughly the role of sense of place in informal citizen science settings and considering how and in what ways people-place relationships influence critical thinking and the development of local and actionable scientific knowledge. The degree to which place attachment fosters higher-order thinking and learning skills, and vice versa, is relevant over a wide range of learning settings and opportunities across the formal-informal continuum and may help elucidate key factors that influence the success of informal science learning. Such insight not only has practical outcomes (i.e., greater capacity to evaluate, understand, and improve current informal science practice), but will also lead to a deeper understanding of the role of informal science in shaping and responding to more systemic social changes in the public engagement in science. As such, both scientific and societal goals can be achieved, namely:    new knowledge (i.e. science) can be created, and this information can go straight into use within decision-making contexts (i.e. actionable science) in part because of the local engagement and place-based connections of participants who co-create it.   individual informal science participants can gain knowledge, understanding, and associated skills needed to participate in a project (i.e. learning), collectively advancing science literacy across communities and the non-expert public in an experiential and personally relevant setting.          Last Modified: 04/12/2023       Submitted by: Benjamin K Haywood]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
