<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research: Travel Supplement for Frontera's "Multi-scale, MHD-Kinetic Modeling of the Solar Wind and its Interaction with the Local Interstellar Medium"]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>7082.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>7082</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OAC</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure (OAC)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Edward Walker</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>edwalker@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924863</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[For nearly four decades, the National Science Foundation (NSF) has played a leadership role in provisioning advanced cyberinfrastructure capabilities for the Nation's Science and Engineering (S&amp;E) researchers. An important component in this investment is the leadership-class computing program that provides computational and data analytics capabilities at the largest scale to inspire transformative S&amp;E discoveries that would not be possible otherwise. NSF's current leadership-class computing investment supports Frontera, the largest High-Performance Computing (HPC) system on a US academic campus. The Frontera system is deployed and operated by the Texas Advanced Computing Center (TACC) at the University of Texas (UT) at Austin. This travel grant will support the participation of researchers who have been awarded a computer time allocation on the Frontera system at a future Principal Investigator (PI) meeting organized by TACC. The award will also support travel for technical coordination between researchers and the Frontera project to ensure optimal and effective utilization of the Frontera system.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of the PI meeting is to allow Frontera research users, as well as their students, to share scientific results, exchange practical lessons-learned, and present their overall experience from using the Frontera system. In addition to research presentations, the meeting will have ample time, as well as facilitated sessions, to promote increased interaction between Frontera research users and project staff. The outcome of the PI meeting will not only enable the Frontera project to better understand and serve the scientific research community, but also build a community to better represent the unique needs of S&amp;E research that require access to NSF leadership computing facilities. To facilitate deeper coordination beyond the PI meeting, this award will also provide travel support to enable technical coordination between the research user teams and the Frontera project.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/12/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/12/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2031611</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nikolai</FirstName>
<LastName>Pogorelov</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>V</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nikolai V Pogorelov</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[np0002@uah.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000489063</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/12/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Alabama in Huntsville</Name>
<CityName>HUNTSVILLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>358051911</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2568242657</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>301 SPARKMAN DR NW</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Alabama</StateName>
<StateCode>AL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AL05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>HB6KNGVNJRU1</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>THE UNIVERSITY OF ALABAMA IN HUNTSVILLE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Alabama in Huntsville, Department SPA]]></Name>
<CityName>Huntsville</CityName>
<StateCode>AL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>358051912</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[320 Sparkman Dr.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Alabama</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AL05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7781</Code>
<Text>Leadership-Class Computing</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~7082</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Intellectual merits.</strong> The part of space beyond the solar system, whose properties are determined by the solar wind (SW) interaction with the local interstellar medium (LISM) is very often referred to as the outer heliosphere. Collision of these two streams of plasma creates a tangential discontinuity, the heliopause (HP), separating them, a heliospheric termination shock (TS), which decelerates the SW plasma to subsonic velocities, and possibly a bow shock (BS). We have demonstrated that the presence of the BS depends not only on the properties of the LISM plasma and the strength of the interstellar magnetic field (ISMF), but also on the secondary H atoms, which are born in the SW when its ions exchange charge with the LISM H atoms, propagate far upstream into the LISM, and heat up its ions. A number of space missions are currently providing intriguing new data on various aspects of the SW&ndash;LISM interaction, which stimulates a great deal of interest in the topic and gives a sense of urgency to modeling efforts.</p> <p>With Voyager 1 and Voyager 2 (V1 and V2) crossing the TS in December 2004 and August 2007, respectively, and their penetration of both spacecraft into the LISM understanding the SW-LISM interaction became one of the most exciting areas of space physics. Today,&nbsp; V1 and V2 are our most distant spacecraft, which after over 45 years of historic discoveries are exploring the LISM affected by the heliosphere.</p> <p>Launched in October 2008, IInterstellar Boundary Explorer (IBEX) is now exploring the outermost reaches of the heliosphere, but from an orbit at 1 Astronomical Unit (AU) using a sort of tomography based on the measurement of energetic neutral atoms (ENAs) -- hydrogen, oxygen, and helium -- created in the boundary regions separating the heliosphere from the LISM. A new NASA mission, Interstellar Mapping and Acceleration Probe (IMAP), scheduled for launch in 2024, will provide us with a revolutionary information both on the acceleration of energetic particles and SW--LISM interaction.<br /><br />Simulations of the SW--LISM interactions require accurate boundary conditions on a sphere surrounding the Sun, e.g., at 1 AU. Space Weather (SWx) is defined by the transients in the space environment traveling from the Sun, through the heliosphere, to Earth. In the recent decade, the difficult task of understanding and predicting violent solar eruptions and their terrestrial impacts has become a strategic national priority, as it affects the daily life of humans, including communication, transportation, power supplies, national defense, space travel, and more. Its importance is highlighted by the Promoting Research and Observations of SpaceWeather to Improve the Forecasting of Tomorrow Act (PL 116-181) passed by Congress in 2020. Our research is jiontly supported ny NSF and NASA as one of the six projects aimed to develop public software for accurate SWx predictions at Earth and other planets.<br /><br />Launched on Jan. 19, 2006, New Horizons (NH) provides us with invaluable scientific results. NH is now beyond 45 AU from the Sun, where it measures the properties of nonthermal, pickup ions (PUIs), which are born in the SW due to charge exchange and other processes ionising neutral atoms from the LISM. PUIs are known to affect the structure of the heliosphere.<br /><br />Parker Solar Probe (PSP), one of the latest NASA missions, was launched on Aug. 12, 2018. To investigate the mysteries of the Sun's atmosphere, PSP uses Venus' gravity during seven flybys over nearly seven years to gradually bring its orbit to a distance less than 10 solar radii from the Sun. Our team is on the SWEAP instrument of this mission performing numerical simulations along the PSP trajectory. Time-dependent, 3-D simulations are of great importance for the interpretation of PSP data.</p> <p>Time allocation on Pleiades made it possible to develop unprecedentetly complete model of the SW-LISM interaction. It now includes a fully kinetic treatment of H and He atoms, and MHD treatment of protons (both thermal and PUIs), He+ ions, and electrons. This allowed us to considerably improve agreement between the simulation results and observational results from all above-mentioned spacecraft. We use our experience to develop a new generation of free software for SWx predictions suitable for the efficient use of modern computer architechture.</p> <p><strong>Broader impacts.</strong> Space missions addressed in this project have enormous publicity. The physical processes we are investigating are of importance well beyond the space physics alone and reveal themselves on a broad range of astrophysical and laboratory plasma physics problems.&nbsp; The development of resource management technologies will be essential for all future modeling efforts that incorporate the diversity of scales and physical processes. It will allow us to promote the application of adaptive technologies to contemporary plasma physics problems through the development of packages suitable for multiple applications. In addition, our public SWx software development efforts<br />(https://www.tacc.utexas.edu/-/which-way-does-the-solar-wind-blow-) will provide leadership in promoting computational science and plasma physics nationwide.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/25/2023<br>      Modified by: Nikolai&nbsp;V&nbsp;Pogorelov</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Intellectual merits. The part of space beyond the solar system, whose properties are determined by the solar wind (SW) interaction with the local interstellar medium (LISM) is very often referred to as the outer heliosphere. Collision of these two streams of plasma creates a tangential discontinuity, the heliopause (HP), separating them, a heliospheric termination shock (TS), which decelerates the SW plasma to subsonic velocities, and possibly a bow shock (BS). We have demonstrated that the presence of the BS depends not only on the properties of the LISM plasma and the strength of the interstellar magnetic field (ISMF), but also on the secondary H atoms, which are born in the SW when its ions exchange charge with the LISM H atoms, propagate far upstream into the LISM, and heat up its ions. A number of space missions are currently providing intriguing new data on various aspects of the SW&ndash;LISM interaction, which stimulates a great deal of interest in the topic and gives a sense of urgency to modeling efforts.  With Voyager 1 and Voyager 2 (V1 and V2) crossing the TS in December 2004 and August 2007, respectively, and their penetration of both spacecraft into the LISM understanding the SW-LISM interaction became one of the most exciting areas of space physics. Today,  V1 and V2 are our most distant spacecraft, which after over 45 years of historic discoveries are exploring the LISM affected by the heliosphere.  Launched in October 2008, IInterstellar Boundary Explorer (IBEX) is now exploring the outermost reaches of the heliosphere, but from an orbit at 1 Astronomical Unit (AU) using a sort of tomography based on the measurement of energetic neutral atoms (ENAs) -- hydrogen, oxygen, and helium -- created in the boundary regions separating the heliosphere from the LISM. A new NASA mission, Interstellar Mapping and Acceleration Probe (IMAP), scheduled for launch in 2024, will provide us with a revolutionary information both on the acceleration of energetic particles and SW--LISM interaction.  Simulations of the SW--LISM interactions require accurate boundary conditions on a sphere surrounding the Sun, e.g., at 1 AU. Space Weather (SWx) is defined by the transients in the space environment traveling from the Sun, through the heliosphere, to Earth. In the recent decade, the difficult task of understanding and predicting violent solar eruptions and their terrestrial impacts has become a strategic national priority, as it affects the daily life of humans, including communication, transportation, power supplies, national defense, space travel, and more. Its importance is highlighted by the Promoting Research and Observations of SpaceWeather to Improve the Forecasting of Tomorrow Act (PL 116-181) passed by Congress in 2020. Our research is jiontly supported ny NSF and NASA as one of the six projects aimed to develop public software for accurate SWx predictions at Earth and other planets.  Launched on Jan. 19, 2006, New Horizons (NH) provides us with invaluable scientific results. NH is now beyond 45 AU from the Sun, where it measures the properties of nonthermal, pickup ions (PUIs), which are born in the SW due to charge exchange and other processes ionising neutral atoms from the LISM. PUIs are known to affect the structure of the heliosphere.  Parker Solar Probe (PSP), one of the latest NASA missions, was launched on Aug. 12, 2018. To investigate the mysteries of the Sun's atmosphere, PSP uses Venus' gravity during seven flybys over nearly seven years to gradually bring its orbit to a distance less than 10 solar radii from the Sun. Our team is on the SWEAP instrument of this mission performing numerical simulations along the PSP trajectory. Time-dependent, 3-D simulations are of great importance for the interpretation of PSP data.  Time allocation on Pleiades made it possible to develop unprecedentetly complete model of the SW-LISM interaction. It now includes a fully kinetic treatment of H and He atoms, and MHD treatment of protons (both thermal and PUIs), He+ ions, and electrons. This allowed us to considerably improve agreement between the simulation results and observational results from all above-mentioned spacecraft. We use our experience to develop a new generation of free software for SWx predictions suitable for the efficient use of modern computer architechture.  Broader impacts. Space missions addressed in this project have enormous publicity. The physical processes we are investigating are of importance well beyond the space physics alone and reveal themselves on a broad range of astrophysical and laboratory plasma physics problems.  The development of resource management technologies will be essential for all future modeling efforts that incorporate the diversity of scales and physical processes. It will allow us to promote the application of adaptive technologies to contemporary plasma physics problems through the development of packages suitable for multiple applications. In addition, our public SWx software development efforts (https://www.tacc.utexas.edu/-/which-way-does-the-solar-wind-blow-) will provide leadership in promoting computational science and plasma physics nationwide.       Last Modified: 01/25/2023       Submitted by: Nikolai V Pogorelov]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
