<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Collaborative Research: Bat goblet cells as immuno-hotspots for infection of coronavirus]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>59204.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>59204</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08090300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IOS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joanna Shisler</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jshisler@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925368</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Why are bats so likely to carry coronaviruses, yet seem little affected by them? Many studies have focused on their immune system, but there is much to learn about the cells viruses attack upon entry. Acute respiratory symptoms, as well as the curious loss of the sense of smell in human patients with COVID-19 hint that cells in the nasal passage are afflicted first. Indeed, cells that produce mucus in the nose, known as goblet cells, have been shown to be “ground zero” for viral entry. Since these cells are also present in bat noses, there must be a difference in how coronaviruses attack goblet cells in bats versus humans. However, virtually nothing is known about immune-related proteins in bat goblet cells. This project proposes a new approach to understand how bats are resistant to respiratory viruses such as those related to SARS-CoV-2. By generating a multi-dimensional study of the anatomy and physiology of the upper respiratory tract —nose and pharynx— of bats, the proposed work will enable researchers to better understand how viruses enter the body and infect or fail to infect their hosts. This project will also allow health agencies around the world to better survey bat populations and prevent future pandemics similar to COVID-19.  In addition, this proposal supports a graduate student and post-doctoral fellow to increase training in STEM fields.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Researchers supported by this award will test the hypothesis that bats with nasal anatomy similar to humans have a specific composition of the lining of their respiratory tract, evolved to prevent viruses such as SARS-CoV-2, from infecting them. To understand how the lining, or epithelium, is modified in bats compared to humans, this grant will compare the proteins, DNA, and histology of bats to humans and mice. The proposed work will highlight the role of goblet cells, which do not only produce mucus, but also have immune and inflammatory functions, as critical for infection from- versus resistance to viral attack. The team will also integrate layers of data, from 3D imaging to proteomics, to build a complete picture of the inner and outer workings of the upper respiratory tracts of bats. By visualizing the anatomy in high resolution and uncovering which specific proteins are produced by the lining of the bat’s nasal passage, this project will produce the most thorough study of the upper respiratory tracts of bats yet. This will be critical for humanity’s fight against zoonotic viruses, and surveillance of wildlife populations. This RAPID award is made by the Physiological and Structural Systems Cluster in the BIO Division of Integrative Organismal Systems, using funds from the Coronavirus Aid, Relief, and Economic Security (CARES) Act.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/09/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/09/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2031906</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Liliana</FirstName>
<LastName>Davalos Alvarez</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Liliana M Davalos Alvarez</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[liliana.davalos@stonybrook.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000507699</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/09/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>SUNY at Stony Brook</Name>
<CityName>STONY BROOK</CityName>
<ZipCode>117940001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6316329949</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>W5510 FRANKS MELVILLE MEMORIAL L</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>M746VC6XMNH9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>THE RESEARCH FOUNDATION FOR THE STATE UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[SUNY at Stony Brook]]></Name>
<CityName>Stony Brook</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>117940001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[WEST 5510 FRK MEL LIB]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>158Y</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>1N20</Code>
<Name>R&amp;RA CARES Act DEFC N</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>010N2021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[R&RA CARES Act DEFC N]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~59204</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>&nbsp;</strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Intellectual Merit:</span></p> <p>Despite the availability of vaccines and mitigations, COVID-19 continues to impact all aspects of our society. By reaching millions of viewers worldwide, our project has directly contributed to scientific literacy in the United States, beyond our borders. Engagement with the project has the potential to improve society, by presenting to the public with the scientific evidence for links between biodiversity and zoonotic spillovers. Our project also identified <strong>consistent differences among bats and between bats and other mammals that are likely involved in mediating viral entry and immune response</strong>. These differences encompass scales from gene expression to cell distribution, and organ location. While grounded in comparative histology, the techniques developed for this RAPID are of interest to scientists working on neurobiology, anatomy, and molecular ecology.</p> <p>The project had three major objectives:</p> <p>1) Compare the nasal passage of bats with and without VNOs, humans, and mice, using histology and 3D imaging.</p> <p>2) Analyze the gene and protein expression of markers of goblet cell function (including SARS-CoV2 receptors) in the nasal epithelium of bats, humans, and mice.</p> <p>3) Determine nasal epithelial function in bats with and without VNOs by combining transcriptomic data and immune staining.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Objective 1 is near completion. We were able to obtain histological specimens from samples &gt;100 years old, as well as complement our collections with de novo noses at no cost to this grant. In addition, our data helped annotate &gt;35 bats genomes to analyze the immune repertoires of Chiroptera and compared with outgroup mammals.</p> <p>Objective 2 is partially complete. Between-species transcriptome data took some time, but we now have a full pipeline culminating in Ornstein-Uhlenbeck models of gene expression evolution and finding differential expression in key genes in the nose and other organs.</p> <p>Objective 3 has been the most difficult. While immunostaining in formaldehyde preserved specimens can work, our older specimens (dating as far back as 1931) have proven difficult to immunostain. This is due, in part, to prolonged preservation in formaldehyde and ethanol, as well as unknowable elements during the specimen?s collection and preservation history. Our newly collected specimens in liquid nitrogen vapor, however, are currently being cut and should offer us with the best possible material to perform immunostaining yet.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p class="Normal0"><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Broader Impacts:</span> The COVID-19 pandemic was a hindrance to some objectives associated with this project, but we were still able to implement broader impact activities, reaching millions. in October 2020, NOVA/ARTE filmed the work of Drs. Corthals, Davalos, and Yohe on bat nasal anatomy in connection to COVID-19 at Stony Brook University. Work for this grant is extremely well represented and the documentary has reached a wide audience of millions of both public and researchers alike. This documentary aired first in the United States in September 2021, as part of the PBS series NOVA. In Europe it releases in the arts and science cable channel ARTE, and across both regions, the documentary is still in rotation at <a href="https://www.pbs.org/wgbh/nova/video/bat-superpowers/">https://www.pbs.org/wgbh/nova/video/bat-superpowers/</a></p> <p class="Normal0">&nbsp;</p> <p class="Normal0">Seven undergraduate students (Francesca Yalong, Rintaro Kato, Navita Peters, Mateo Sanz, Tyler Polakovich and joining this semester (Fall 2022) are Xitlali Maceda and Rahele Gadapaka) from a minority serving institution, John Jay College of Criminal Justice at the City University of New York (CUNY), have been collaborating on this project for research credit, giving them an exposure to research opportunity, but also a purpose and special value to their work by being part of the greater worldwide scientific community, as thousands of scientists around the world are trying to uncover the origins, treatment, and prophylactics for COVID-19.</p> <p class="Normal0">Our John Jay students have already presented their preliminary results at the PRISM and CUNY research days in May 2022 at the poster session. One of the students, Rintaro Kato, was offered a prestigious post-baccalaureate fellowship at the NIH based on a presentation of our preliminary results.</p> <p class="Normal0">Rahele and Xitlali are continuing the work on the immunostaining and are expected to present their results at next semester's CUNY Research Day, as well as next year's NASBR meeting in Winnipeg, Manitoba.</p> <p class="Normal0">Finally, the award was used to support three publications:</p> <p class="EndNoteBibliography">Moreno Santillan DD, Lama TM, Gutierrez Guerrero YT, Brown AM, Donat P, Zhao H, Rossiter SJ, Yohe LR, Potter JH, Teeling EC, et al. 2021. Large-scale genome sampling reveals unique immunity and metabolic adaptations in bats. Molecular Ecology 30:6449-6467.</p> <p class="EndNoteBibliography">Yohe LR, Fabbri M, Lee D, Davies KTJ, Yohe TP, Sanchez MKR, Rengifo EM, Hall R, Mutumi G, Hedrick BP, et al. 2022. Ecological constraints on highly evolvable olfactory receptor genes and morphology in neotropical bats. Evolution n/a.</p> <p class="EndNoteBibliography">Yohe LR, Leiser-Miller LB, Kaliszewska ZA, Donat P, Santana SE, Davalos LM. 2021. Diversity in olfactory receptor repertoires is associated with dietary specialization in a genus of frugivorous bat. G3 Genes|Genomes|Genetics 11:jkab260.</p> <p class="Normal0">We also delivered 14 seminars, lectures, or posters at a variety of local and international venues.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/27/2022<br>      Modified by: Liliana&nbsp;M&nbsp;Davalos Alvarez</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2031906/2031906_10675940_1666914228086_transcripts--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2031906/2031906_10675940_1666914228086_transcripts--rgov-800width.jpg" title="COVID-19 gene expression comparison"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2031906/2031906_10675940_1666914228086_transcripts--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="COVID-19 gene expression comparison"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Boxplots of normalized transcripts across target species. TMPRSS2 and SPDEF were significantly different in species with/without VNO in phylogenetically corrected Ornstein-Uhlenbeck models.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Liliana Davalos</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Liliana&nbsp;M&nbsp;Davalos Alvarez</div> <div class="imageTitle">COVID-19 gene expression comparison</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2031906/2031906_10675940_1666914148574_sinicus_perspicillata--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2031906/2031906_10675940_1666914148574_sinicus_perspicillata--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Nasal cavities of bats"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2031906/2031906_10675940_1666914148574_sinicus_perspicillata--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Nasal cavities of bats"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">3D reconstructed models from our diceCT scans of Rhinolophus (horseshoe bat) and Carollia (neotropical frugivore) illustrating extreme differences in nasal cavity rearrangements. We are building airflow models with new collaborator Saikat Basu.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Laurel Yohe</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Liliana&nbsp;M&nbsp;Davalos Alvarez</div> <div class="imageTitle">Nasal cavities of bats</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Intellectual Merit:  Despite the availability of vaccines and mitigations, COVID-19 continues to impact all aspects of our society. By reaching millions of viewers worldwide, our project has directly contributed to scientific literacy in the United States, beyond our borders. Engagement with the project has the potential to improve society, by presenting to the public with the scientific evidence for links between biodiversity and zoonotic spillovers. Our project also identified consistent differences among bats and between bats and other mammals that are likely involved in mediating viral entry and immune response. These differences encompass scales from gene expression to cell distribution, and organ location. While grounded in comparative histology, the techniques developed for this RAPID are of interest to scientists working on neurobiology, anatomy, and molecular ecology.  The project had three major objectives:  1) Compare the nasal passage of bats with and without VNOs, humans, and mice, using histology and 3D imaging.  2) Analyze the gene and protein expression of markers of goblet cell function (including SARS-CoV2 receptors) in the nasal epithelium of bats, humans, and mice.  3) Determine nasal epithelial function in bats with and without VNOs by combining transcriptomic data and immune staining.     Objective 1 is near completion. We were able to obtain histological specimens from samples &gt;100 years old, as well as complement our collections with de novo noses at no cost to this grant. In addition, our data helped annotate &gt;35 bats genomes to analyze the immune repertoires of Chiroptera and compared with outgroup mammals.  Objective 2 is partially complete. Between-species transcriptome data took some time, but we now have a full pipeline culminating in Ornstein-Uhlenbeck models of gene expression evolution and finding differential expression in key genes in the nose and other organs.  Objective 3 has been the most difficult. While immunostaining in formaldehyde preserved specimens can work, our older specimens (dating as far back as 1931) have proven difficult to immunostain. This is due, in part, to prolonged preservation in formaldehyde and ethanol, as well as unknowable elements during the specimen?s collection and preservation history. Our newly collected specimens in liquid nitrogen vapor, however, are currently being cut and should offer us with the best possible material to perform immunostaining yet.    Broader Impacts: The COVID-19 pandemic was a hindrance to some objectives associated with this project, but we were still able to implement broader impact activities, reaching millions. in October 2020, NOVA/ARTE filmed the work of Drs. Corthals, Davalos, and Yohe on bat nasal anatomy in connection to COVID-19 at Stony Brook University. Work for this grant is extremely well represented and the documentary has reached a wide audience of millions of both public and researchers alike. This documentary aired first in the United States in September 2021, as part of the PBS series NOVA. In Europe it releases in the arts and science cable channel ARTE, and across both regions, the documentary is still in rotation at https://www.pbs.org/wgbh/nova/video/bat-superpowers/   Seven undergraduate students (Francesca Yalong, Rintaro Kato, Navita Peters, Mateo Sanz, Tyler Polakovich and joining this semester (Fall 2022) are Xitlali Maceda and Rahele Gadapaka) from a minority serving institution, John Jay College of Criminal Justice at the City University of New York (CUNY), have been collaborating on this project for research credit, giving them an exposure to research opportunity, but also a purpose and special value to their work by being part of the greater worldwide scientific community, as thousands of scientists around the world are trying to uncover the origins, treatment, and prophylactics for COVID-19. Our John Jay students have already presented their preliminary results at the PRISM and CUNY research days in May 2022 at the poster session. One of the students, Rintaro Kato, was offered a prestigious post-baccalaureate fellowship at the NIH based on a presentation of our preliminary results. Rahele and Xitlali are continuing the work on the immunostaining and are expected to present their results at next semester's CUNY Research Day, as well as next year's NASBR meeting in Winnipeg, Manitoba. Finally, the award was used to support three publications: Moreno Santillan DD, Lama TM, Gutierrez Guerrero YT, Brown AM, Donat P, Zhao H, Rossiter SJ, Yohe LR, Potter JH, Teeling EC, et al. 2021. Large-scale genome sampling reveals unique immunity and metabolic adaptations in bats. Molecular Ecology 30:6449-6467. Yohe LR, Fabbri M, Lee D, Davies KTJ, Yohe TP, Sanchez MKR, Rengifo EM, Hall R, Mutumi G, Hedrick BP, et al. 2022. Ecological constraints on highly evolvable olfactory receptor genes and morphology in neotropical bats. Evolution n/a. Yohe LR, Leiser-Miller LB, Kaliszewska ZA, Donat P, Santana SE, Davalos LM. 2021. Diversity in olfactory receptor repertoires is associated with dietary specialization in a genus of frugivorous bat. G3 Genes|Genomes|Genetics 11:jkab260. We also delivered 14 seminars, lectures, or posters at a variety of local and international venues.       Last Modified: 10/27/2022       Submitted by: Liliana M Davalos Alvarez]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
