<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: The Impact of COVID-19 on Broadening Participation in Engineering at HBCUs]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>176730.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>176730</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EEC</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Engineering Education and Centers</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Dana L. Denick</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ddenick@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928866</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[COVID-19 spurs an unprecedented global crisis disrupting life as we know it, affecting the overall economy, and abruptly transmuting the traditional methods, experiences and abilities of higher education institutions’ faculty, staff and students. With strict social distancing measures and shelter-in-place orders by the Center for Disease Control (CDC) and state governments across the country, colleges and universities are forced to abruptly transition to forms of remote instruction. For Historically Black Colleges and Universities (HBCUs), smaller endowments to pull from and historic inequity from state and federal funding sources have exacerbated the negative impact of COVID-19. While HBCUs enroll a significant percentage of first-generation and low-income students, they award a disproportionately greater share of degrees to minority students in the science, technology, engineering and math (STEM) fields. Specifically, HBCU engineering programs graduated 20.3% of all bachelor’s degrees awarded to Blacks and permanent residents in engineering in the U.S. between 2002 and 2012, although they only make up 0.02% of all ABET accredited programs. High-touch student support and a sense of belonging displayed at HBCUs, through faculty and peer mentoring, in addition to a myriad of supplemental programming, have been credited with the heightened sense of community reported by students, faculty and staff. With limited contact to students, COVID-19 has introduced a new set of challenges for HBCU students, faculty and staff, especially those majoring in or working closely to STEM academic areas, who have higher requirements linked to labs, hardware (e.g., laptops), software and internet access. As students, faculty and staff within engineering programs are dealing with multiple challenges at once, this project will allow these experiences to be captured now and not lost over time. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of this project is to collect information from engineering stakeholders at HBCUs related to COVID-19 and its impact on engineering education at HBCUs. Through this process, the following research question will be answered: How has COVID-19 impacted the success and persistence of engineering students, faculty and staff at historically Black colleges and universities? A core research team at FIU and a group of experts in engineering and STEM from HBCUs (HBCU Knowledge Partners) and the National Society of Black Engineers (NSBE) will collaborate on a three phased project: Phase I: COVID-19 Impact on Engineering Stakeholders Survey (administered electronically), Phase II: detailed analysis and discussion of results – stakeholder and institutional implications, and Phase III: development of a cross-collaborative network between HBCU engineering programs. By gaining information from stakeholders related to the impact of this unprecedented event on their success and persistence, the research will add to the literature by demonstrating the impact of COVID-19 on engineering and STEM education at HBCUs. This study will provide insight around the type of support and partnerships that can be cultivated within engineering education at HBCUs to ensure on-going success and sustainability post COVID-19. By understanding the impact of COVID-19 at HBCUs, findings can be generalized to support other stakeholders and then disseminated to the broader engineering community.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/15/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/15/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2031221</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Trina</FirstName>
<LastName>Fletcher</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Trina Fletcher</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[trfletch@fiu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000792311</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/15/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Florida International University</Name>
<CityName>MIAMI</CityName>
<ZipCode>331992516</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3053482494</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>11200 SW 8TH ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>26</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL26</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>Q3KCVK5S9CP1</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>FLORIDA INTERNATIONAL UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>D4GCCCMXR1H3</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Florida International University]]></Name>
<CityName>Miami</CityName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>331990001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[11200 S. W. 8 Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>26</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL26</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>158Y</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>110E</Code>
<Text>EDUCATION RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7680</Code>
<Text>ENG DIVERSITY ACTIVITIES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>1N20</Code>
<Name>R&amp;RA CARES Act DEFC N</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>010N2021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[R&RA CARES Act DEFC N]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~176730</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Project Overview and Rationale</strong></p> <p>COVID-19 forced higher education institutions&rsquo; administrator&rsquo;s faculty, staff, and students to abruptly transition to remote forms of instruction. While HBCUs enroll a significant percentage of first-generation and low-income students, they still award a disproportionately greater share of degrees to minority students in the science, technology, engineering, and math (STEM) fields.&nbsp;<strong>Specifically,</strong>&nbsp;<strong>HBCU engineering programs graduated 20.3% of all bachelor&rsquo;s degrees awarded to Blacks and permanent U.S. engineering residents between 2002 and 2012 while only making up less than 1% of all ABET engineering accredited programs</strong>. High-touch student support and a sense of belonging displayed at HBCUs, through faculty/peer mentoring support and supplemental programming, have been credited with the heightened sense of community reported by their stakeholders. However, COVID-19 introduced a new set of challenges, especially for those majoring in or working closely in STEM academic areas with higher requirements linked to labs, hardware (e.g., laptops), software, and internet access. Given the critical role STEM education at HBCUs plays in broadening participation efforts, this project answered the overarching research question:&nbsp;<em>How has COVID-19 impacted the success and persistence of engineering (and STEM) students, faculty, and staff at historically Black colleges and universities</em>&nbsp;via surveys. The research team included key leaders from the&nbsp;<strong>National Society of Black Engineers (NSBE)&nbsp;</strong>and five (5)&nbsp;<strong>HBCU Knowledge Partners (KPs)</strong>&nbsp;that consisted of faculty and administrators from HBCUs to complete the following three phases:&nbsp;</p> <p><em>&nbsp;</em></p> <p><em>Phase I: COVID-19 Impact on Engineering Stakeholders Survey&nbsp;</em></p> <p><em>Phase II: Internal Detailed Discussion of Results</em></p> <p><em>Phase III: External Dissemination to the Broader community</em></p> <p><em><br /></em></p> <p><strong>Intellectual Merit</strong></p> <p>By gaining the following research findings from HBCUs stakeholders related to the impact of this unprecedented event, the following results added to the literature by demonstrating the impact of COVID-19 on engineering and STEM educators at HBCUs; a population often left out of the broader conversations within higher education:&nbsp;</p> <ul> <li>Results re-emphasized the positive institutional support and sense of belonging HBCUs have historically held within their practices.&nbsp;</li> <li>HBCU staff and faculty responded positively to their perceptions of their support, particularly how their institutions handled and managed the abrupt transition to online learning during the pandemic.</li> <li>Regarding the sense of belonging, of the 171 student respondents (126 engineering majors), 79% agreed that being unable to access faculty in person has affected their academic performance.&nbsp;</li> <li>59% of engineering students reported that being away from campus had negatively affected their sense of belonging to their HBCU.&nbsp; &nbsp;</li> <li>For all HBCU stakeholders&rsquo; surveys, students had a statistically significant higher response when asked if the transition to virtual learning increased their overall stress and anxiety levels.</li> <li>Faculty and students could not conduct research using campus laboratories or other facilities and did not have immediate access to supplies often used to conduct research or software used to analyze the work.&nbsp;</li> </ul> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>It is important to note that HBCU administrators were tasked with managing COVID-19-related challenges and addressing national-level social injustice and police brutality issues at the height of the pandemic (Murty &amp; Payne, 2021). This timeframe of 2020 has been coined as the dual-pandemic, particularly for Black and brown communities who are being aggressively impacted by both events (Galvin, 2020; Valburn, 2020). By recognizing how the removal of national-level barriers to achieving resource equity, including chronic underfunding pre-pandemic (Owens &amp; Commodore, 2018; Harper, 2020), could allow for HBCUs to further leverage their strengths in broadening their participation in STEM education, especially engineering. By understanding the impact of COVID-19 on STEM stakeholders at HBCUs, our findings can be used to support stakeholders at other HBCUs.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts</strong></p> <p>Results of this research have been disseminated via channels, including the annual AERA conference (April 2021) and a conference paper presentation at ASEE (July 2021). Additionally, critical findings around mental health inspired a journal paper, Advocating for Mental Health Equity: Reflections on the Multi-Layered Pandemic Experiences of Black College Students<em>,</em>&nbsp;that was submitted and accepted to the journal&nbsp;<em>Understanding and Dismantling Privilege.&nbsp;</em>Lastly, a journal publication is under final review with the&nbsp;<em>Journal of Engineering Education&nbsp;</em>detailing this study's findings. For Phase III, results were shared with leadership and stakeholders, including HBCU administration, staff, faculty, students, and non-HBCU allies. The webinar, A Path Forward: COVID-19 and STEM Education at HBCUs, took place on May 12, 2021, and was open to the public. All HBCU knowledge partners and project collaborators were on the call and assisted with responses to discussion questions from the guest. The recorded video was shared on YouTube and is still available for viewing (search title of the webinar). Through this expansive dissemination process, the broader HBCU community and other Predominately Black Institutions (PBIs) and Minority Serving Institutions (MSIs) can benefit from having this information.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/05/2022<br>      Modified by: Trina&nbsp;Fletcher</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Project Overview and Rationale  COVID-19 forced higher education institutions’ administrator’s faculty, staff, and students to abruptly transition to remote forms of instruction. While HBCUs enroll a significant percentage of first-generation and low-income students, they still award a disproportionately greater share of degrees to minority students in the science, technology, engineering, and math (STEM) fields. Specifically, HBCU engineering programs graduated 20.3% of all bachelor’s degrees awarded to Blacks and permanent U.S. engineering residents between 2002 and 2012 while only making up less than 1% of all ABET engineering accredited programs. High-touch student support and a sense of belonging displayed at HBCUs, through faculty/peer mentoring support and supplemental programming, have been credited with the heightened sense of community reported by their stakeholders. However, COVID-19 introduced a new set of challenges, especially for those majoring in or working closely in STEM academic areas with higher requirements linked to labs, hardware (e.g., laptops), software, and internet access. Given the critical role STEM education at HBCUs plays in broadening participation efforts, this project answered the overarching research question: How has COVID-19 impacted the success and persistence of engineering (and STEM) students, faculty, and staff at historically Black colleges and universities via surveys. The research team included key leaders from the National Society of Black Engineers (NSBE) and five (5) HBCU Knowledge Partners (KPs) that consisted of faculty and administrators from HBCUs to complete the following three phases:      Phase I: COVID-19 Impact on Engineering Stakeholders Survey   Phase II: Internal Detailed Discussion of Results  Phase III: External Dissemination to the Broader community     Intellectual Merit  By gaining the following research findings from HBCUs stakeholders related to the impact of this unprecedented event, the following results added to the literature by demonstrating the impact of COVID-19 on engineering and STEM educators at HBCUs; a population often left out of the broader conversations within higher education:   Results re-emphasized the positive institutional support and sense of belonging HBCUs have historically held within their practices.  HBCU staff and faculty responded positively to their perceptions of their support, particularly how their institutions handled and managed the abrupt transition to online learning during the pandemic. Regarding the sense of belonging, of the 171 student respondents (126 engineering majors), 79% agreed that being unable to access faculty in person has affected their academic performance.  59% of engineering students reported that being away from campus had negatively affected their sense of belonging to their HBCU.    For all HBCU stakeholders’ surveys, students had a statistically significant higher response when asked if the transition to virtual learning increased their overall stress and anxiety levels. Faculty and students could not conduct research using campus laboratories or other facilities and did not have immediate access to supplies often used to conduct research or software used to analyze the work.       It is important to note that HBCU administrators were tasked with managing COVID-19-related challenges and addressing national-level social injustice and police brutality issues at the height of the pandemic (Murty &amp; Payne, 2021). This timeframe of 2020 has been coined as the dual-pandemic, particularly for Black and brown communities who are being aggressively impacted by both events (Galvin, 2020; Valburn, 2020). By recognizing how the removal of national-level barriers to achieving resource equity, including chronic underfunding pre-pandemic (Owens &amp; Commodore, 2018; Harper, 2020), could allow for HBCUs to further leverage their strengths in broadening their participation in STEM education, especially engineering. By understanding the impact of COVID-19 on STEM stakeholders at HBCUs, our findings can be used to support stakeholders at other HBCUs.     Broader Impacts  Results of this research have been disseminated via channels, including the annual AERA conference (April 2021) and a conference paper presentation at ASEE (July 2021). Additionally, critical findings around mental health inspired a journal paper, Advocating for Mental Health Equity: Reflections on the Multi-Layered Pandemic Experiences of Black College Students, that was submitted and accepted to the journal Understanding and Dismantling Privilege. Lastly, a journal publication is under final review with the Journal of Engineering Education detailing this study's findings. For Phase III, results were shared with leadership and stakeholders, including HBCU administration, staff, faculty, students, and non-HBCU allies. The webinar, A Path Forward: COVID-19 and STEM Education at HBCUs, took place on May 12, 2021, and was open to the public. All HBCU knowledge partners and project collaborators were on the call and assisted with responses to discussion questions from the guest. The recorded video was shared on YouTube and is still available for viewing (search title of the webinar). Through this expansive dissemination process, the broader HBCU community and other Predominately Black Institutions (PBIs) and Minority Serving Institutions (MSIs) can benefit from having this information.           Last Modified: 09/05/2022       Submitted by: Trina Fletcher]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
