<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[I-Corps: Digital Platform for Informal Learning Experiences to Encourage Curiosity in STEM Career Paths]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ruth Shuman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rshuman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922160</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this I-Corps project is the development of a digital platform that transforms the way young children perceive and engage in STEM career exploration.  Factors promoting STEM education, particularly for under-represented groups, have not been incorporated into personalized learning plans.  This technology will use artificial intelligence to develop customized educational plans. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project is based on the development of the development and evaluation of a new approach to generate recommendations by combining a model of surprise with a model of user preference to deliver curiosity-inspiring recommendations. The proposed technology is a digital platform that empowers students to pursue STEM learning and careers. This project will incorporate artificial intelligence and informal learning practices to recommend learning modules on a personalized basis.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/10/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/14/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2031900</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mary Lou</FirstName>
<LastName>Maher</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mary Lou Maher</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[marylou.maher@gmail.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000284692</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Abimbola</FirstName>
<LastName>Olukeye</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Abimbola Olukeye</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[abi@smartgirlshq.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000791460</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of North Carolina at Charlotte</Name>
<CityName>CHARLOTTE</CityName>
<ZipCode>282230001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7046871888</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>9201 UNIVERSITY CITY BLVD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>JB33DT84JNA5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF NORTH CAROLINA AT CHARLOTTE, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>N8DMK1K4C2K5</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of North Carolina at Charlotte]]></Name>
<CityName>Charlotte</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>282230001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[9201 University City Blvd]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-084916b8-7fff-9bc7-5583-83c6fce788e6"><span>The contributions of women are undeniably important for driving U.S. innovation and competitiveness in science, technology, engineering, and mathematics (STEM), and yet women represent only 29% of the STEM workforce. Although many educational solutions have emerged to strengthen the overall STEM talent pipeline in the United States, the factors promoting the underrepresentation of girls and women in STEM, which take effect early in their education, remain largely unaddressed by educational technology. Through this project, we identify the value proposition and a pathway to a successful product for a novel digital platform called iLeap. The goal of iLeap is to empower young girls to pursue STEM learning and careers by providing personalized recommendations for informal learning. This system is intended to engage and support the key influencers of their out-of-school learning and career trajectories: their parents. The technology innovation in this project brings together artificial intelligence and informal learning practices to establish a recommender system that provides parents with subscription-based monthly STEM learning plans for their daughters based on personalized models of surprise and curiosity. </span><span>The business thesis for this project at the end of the I-Corps program is: </span><span>A progressive playlist of experiences that enables homeschooling parents to explore STEM.</span></span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/01/2021<br>      Modified by: Mary Lou&nbsp;Maher</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The contributions of women are undeniably important for driving U.S. innovation and competitiveness in science, technology, engineering, and mathematics (STEM), and yet women represent only 29% of the STEM workforce. Although many educational solutions have emerged to strengthen the overall STEM talent pipeline in the United States, the factors promoting the underrepresentation of girls and women in STEM, which take effect early in their education, remain largely unaddressed by educational technology. Through this project, we identify the value proposition and a pathway to a successful product for a novel digital platform called iLeap. The goal of iLeap is to empower young girls to pursue STEM learning and careers by providing personalized recommendations for informal learning. This system is intended to engage and support the key influencers of their out-of-school learning and career trajectories: their parents. The technology innovation in this project brings together artificial intelligence and informal learning practices to establish a recommender system that provides parents with subscription-based monthly STEM learning plans for their daughters based on personalized models of surprise and curiosity. The business thesis for this project at the end of the I-Corps program is: A progressive playlist of experiences that enables homeschooling parents to explore STEM.       Last Modified: 10/01/2021       Submitted by: Mary Lou Maher]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
