<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Analyzing forced habit change from COVID-19 using large-scale data]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>174313.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>174313</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kwabena Gyimah-Brempong</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kgyimahb@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927466</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[During the COVID-19 pandemic, people were forced to try new routine at school, work, and home — “forced exploration”. That is, habits used to guide how we work, conduct our daily routine, exercise, eat, go to school, and interact with friends and neighbors, Habits are formed to make the same routines effortless, to save time and mental effort, when routine choices work well. However, while the mental savings from habits are a benefit, when people are choosing habitually, they may not be exploring other options which could be even better— that is the hidden cost of habit. Forced exploration can actually be beneficial if it shows people better ways of school, work, and social interaction. This kind of exploration is like going to your favorite restaurant and finding out they have run out of your favorite dish — now you have to try something new, which you would not have explored without the disruption. This wave of forced exploration raises important questions: What new habits are formed that will persist— what will be the “new normal”? Consider, for example, wearing a face-mask outside of the house. This is exactly the kind of “muscle memory” behavior that usually habitizes— it can be triggered while stepping out of your car, or entering a store, and quickly becomes automatic and effortless. Whether a lot of other people are wearing masks or not can also be a trigger that prompts habit (in either direction).The same question arises across the board: Will people go back to movie theaters (or stay home with streaming)? Will restaurants fully reopen or will home delivery take over? Will knowledge firms switch to more remote “tele-work”? Will schools find better mixtures of home learning and in-school activity? This project will analyze two different kinds of big data to test whether or not this kind of forced exploration really does result in new habits.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In social sciences, habits are usually modelled mathematically using a simple equation in which the more an activity has been done in the past, the more it is done in the future. This is called a "reduced form" approach because it reduces a biologically complicated mechanism to something much simpler. It is a good starting point but cannot answer questions such as "What if past behavior is disrupted?” This research project uses a new approach to habits based on animal learning and human cognitive neuroscience. The starting point is that habits have developed to save effort ⎯— both physical and mental. The “neural autopilot” framework proposed here predicts that individuals develop habits for actions which, after repeated decisions, have proven to be reliably rewarding. Such habitual behavior drains fewer physical and mental resources. At the same time, when people are habitized⎯- about exercise, eating, or work — they ignore new goods and activities they would prefer if they actually tried them. While the neural autopilot approach has been tested in many lab studies of animal and human habituation, it has never been systematically explored using a large amount of data about how people actually behave in everyday life. An ideal test of this model is in a field setting where choice sets are artificially truncated, so people resort to new choices; and that is exactly what happened during the ongoing lockdowns. This project will use data from Weibo chat data and Fitbit fitness and sleep tracking. These large sets of data contain fine-grained measurements of behavior. Using this data, we will develop and test a statistical neural autopilot model, to recover values for the model’s main parameters. The parameters are numbers that measure, for each person, how fast habits are formed and the threshold to break out of a habit and explore something that might be better. The estimated parameter values will be used to make predictions about which habits acquired during the pandemic will persist, and which behavior will revert to pre-pandemic patterns.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/20/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/14/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2031287</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Colin</FirstName>
<LastName>Camerer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>F</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Colin F Camerer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[camerer@hss.caltech.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000234795</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/20/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Matthew</FirstName>
<LastName>Shum</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Matthew S Shum</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mshum@hss.caltech.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000509582</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/20/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lawrence</FirstName>
<LastName>Jin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lawrence Jin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jin@caltech.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000826272</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/20/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yi</FirstName>
<LastName>Xin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Yi Xin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[yixin@caltech.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000826215</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/20/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>California Institute of Technology</Name>
<CityName>PASADENA</CityName>
<ZipCode>911250001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6263956219</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1200 E CALIFORNIA BLVD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>28</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA28</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>U2JMKHNS5TG4</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CALIFORNIA INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[California Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>Pasadena</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>911250001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1200 E. California Blvd]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>28</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA28</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>158Y</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~174313</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-372a23ec-7fff-b66b-fb79-4376cc1e2a9d"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Our project studied how new habits form, in the special case of disruptions due to the COVID-19 pandemic. </span><span>Human behavior is often based on habits?for example, people have morning coffee and hygiene routines, often buy the same consumer products, and take the same route to work daily. During a pandemic, however, consumers are forced to experiment when some habitual choices are no longer available. Many businesses adapted quickly during the pandemic. Restaurants switched to delivery services; schools initiated distance learning; companies allowed employees to work from home. Such changes provide a large-scale ?natural experiment? to test habit change. The Nobel laureate Milton Friedman even suggested that ``only a crisis-- actual or perceived-- produces real change"..</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>We took up the </span><span>specific aim</span><span> of understanding social media usage on the platform Weibo in China before, during, and after extreme lockdowns. The Chinese example is a useful one because the lockdowns were among the most stringent in the world (and much more stringent than in North America or Europe). Unexpected disruptions in social lives forced people to explore new activities such as posting on Weibo. Do people form habits of using social media? Will people continue doing so after the pandemic? Our project aims to understand how people changed their behavior after disruptions such as pandemics: What will the ?new normal? be?&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span><br /></span><span>How habits change due to disruption is also a scientific challenge because the scientific understanding of habits is still developing. There is a lot of conventional wisdom about how habits work, but the fact that changing many types of habits?ranging from quitting smoking or poor eating to adoption of new technology?is so difficult, and varies across people, implies that engineering of habit change does not rest on a very sturdy foundation of science. &nbsp; The </span><span>scientific merit</span><span> of this proposal is therefore the use of a new type of&nbsp; ``neural autopilot" model of habits. Only one other exploration (in parallel with ours) has tried to statistically analyze this new theory with samples of fine-grained data from everyday life, instead of from simple experiments in a laboratory.&nbsp;</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>In the neural autopilot theory, people face a choice situation: Every day there are a set of possible choices, such as whether to post on Weibo or not. Over time, different choices are rewarded in different amounts which are subjectively valued: Rewards could be the taste of food, or how many ?likes? a post gets. The core of neural autopilot theory is two related numbers: One is the ?reward prediction error (RPE)?, or how surprisingly good or bad the reward is compared to a prediction based on the past. The second important number is the magnitude of RPE (regardless of whether it is positive or negative). When the RPE magnitude is low a choice is&nbsp; ``reliably rewarding? (like eating at a fast food chain that strives for consistency of taste). The way autopilot works is that every day, a person remembers what they did the last time they were in the choice situation, and compares the reward reliability to a threshold. If it?s below the threshold they repeat the choice. That?s what it means to have a habit. If the reward reliability is above the threshold, then from all the possible choices they pick the one with the highest predicted reward.&nbsp;</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>To test this theory using Weibo data, we hypothesized that the number of likes is the reward that drives habit formation of social media usage. Then using statistics, we found values of the different parameters in the theory, such as the reliability threshold and how fast RPEs are incorporated into new predictions (the ``learning rate?), which were best able to explain changes in posting rates.&nbsp;</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The main conclusion was that strong habits of posting were not formed. While Weibo posting did increase a lot during the lockdown periods, after lockdowns were removed posting went back to pre-lockdown rates. The new normal was a continuation of the old normal.&nbsp;&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The neural autopilot theory gives a precise language in which we can make educated guesses about what other changes during the pandemic will persist and what will not. The key feature is whether going back to business as usual is perceived as better than expected (positive RPE) or worse than expected. Consider workers who were working remotely during the pandemic and could keep doing so (such as knowledge professionals). Suppose they are now required to commute back to an office. If commuting and being in a busy, distracting office is surprisingly unpleasant, then the remote-working habit will stick and workers will quit rather than returning. If it?s fun and productive to be back with co-workers, the new normal of office work will revert to the old normal. Which of these scenarios occurs will depend on reward predictions, in a way that our theory can make clear. &nbsp; </span></p> <div><span><br /></span></div> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/07/2022<br>      Modified by: Colin&nbsp;F&nbsp;Camerer</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   Our project studied how new habits form, in the special case of disruptions due to the COVID-19 pandemic. Human behavior is often based on habits?for example, people have morning coffee and hygiene routines, often buy the same consumer products, and take the same route to work daily. During a pandemic, however, consumers are forced to experiment when some habitual choices are no longer available. Many businesses adapted quickly during the pandemic. Restaurants switched to delivery services; schools initiated distance learning; companies allowed employees to work from home. Such changes provide a large-scale ?natural experiment? to test habit change. The Nobel laureate Milton Friedman even suggested that ``only a crisis-- actual or perceived-- produces real change"..    We took up the specific aim of understanding social media usage on the platform Weibo in China before, during, and after extreme lockdowns. The Chinese example is a useful one because the lockdowns were among the most stringent in the world (and much more stringent than in North America or Europe). Unexpected disruptions in social lives forced people to explore new activities such as posting on Weibo. Do people form habits of using social media? Will people continue doing so after the pandemic? Our project aims to understand how people changed their behavior after disruptions such as pandemics: What will the ?new normal? be?     How habits change due to disruption is also a scientific challenge because the scientific understanding of habits is still developing. There is a lot of conventional wisdom about how habits work, but the fact that changing many types of habits?ranging from quitting smoking or poor eating to adoption of new technology?is so difficult, and varies across people, implies that engineering of habit change does not rest on a very sturdy foundation of science.   The scientific merit of this proposal is therefore the use of a new type of  ``neural autopilot" model of habits. Only one other exploration (in parallel with ours) has tried to statistically analyze this new theory with samples of fine-grained data from everyday life, instead of from simple experiments in a laboratory.     In the neural autopilot theory, people face a choice situation: Every day there are a set of possible choices, such as whether to post on Weibo or not. Over time, different choices are rewarded in different amounts which are subjectively valued: Rewards could be the taste of food, or how many ?likes? a post gets. The core of neural autopilot theory is two related numbers: One is the ?reward prediction error (RPE)?, or how surprisingly good or bad the reward is compared to a prediction based on the past. The second important number is the magnitude of RPE (regardless of whether it is positive or negative). When the RPE magnitude is low a choice is  ``reliably rewarding? (like eating at a fast food chain that strives for consistency of taste). The way autopilot works is that every day, a person remembers what they did the last time they were in the choice situation, and compares the reward reliability to a threshold. If it?s below the threshold they repeat the choice. That?s what it means to have a habit. If the reward reliability is above the threshold, then from all the possible choices they pick the one with the highest predicted reward.     To test this theory using Weibo data, we hypothesized that the number of likes is the reward that drives habit formation of social media usage. Then using statistics, we found values of the different parameters in the theory, such as the reliability threshold and how fast RPEs are incorporated into new predictions (the ``learning rate?), which were best able to explain changes in posting rates.     The main conclusion was that strong habits of posting were not formed. While Weibo posting did increase a lot during the lockdown periods, after lockdowns were removed posting went back to pre-lockdown rates. The new normal was a continuation of the old normal.       The neural autopilot theory gives a precise language in which we can make educated guesses about what other changes during the pandemic will persist and what will not. The key feature is whether going back to business as usual is perceived as better than expected (positive RPE) or worse than expected. Consider workers who were working remotely during the pandemic and could keep doing so (such as knowledge professionals). Suppose they are now required to commute back to an office. If commuting and being in a busy, distracting office is surprisingly unpleasant, then the remote-working habit will stick and workers will quit rather than returning. If it?s fun and productive to be back with co-workers, the new normal of office work will revert to the old normal. Which of these scenarios occurs will depend on reward predictions, in a way that our theory can make clear.                  Last Modified: 09/07/2022       Submitted by: Colin F Camerer]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
