<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Arresting the spread of SARS-CoV-2 on surfaces and in the air using engineered water nanostructures enriched with de novo designed neutralizing peptides]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>200000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>200000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Nora Savage</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>nosavage@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927949</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The recent COVID-19 pandemic has spotlighted the problem of rapid transmission of infectious diseases. The COVID-19 virus is transmitted to new hosts through contaminated surfaces as well as through the air. The virus is known to survive in air for hours and on surfaces for days. All current approaches for stopping the transmission, such as masks, frequent hand washing, and social distancing, are insufficient and cause other detriments, and the high numbers of asymptomatic cases and shortage of efficient facemasks are driving the number of infections higher. Current methods for general prevention of transmission of airborne infectious diseases, such as air filtration, use of chemical gases (such as hydrogen peroxide) and the use of ultraviolet radiation, have significant shortcomings and health risks, and they cannot be implemented indoors with people present. This project seeks to utilize the recently developed (by the investigators) nanotechnology-based carrier platform using Engineered Water Nanostructures to inactivate viruses. If this technology is proved successful it can be scaled up and systems can be built and used in various applications. This innovative technology is particularly applicable to closed indoor environments and could help in battling the COVID-19 pandemic as people emerge from their social isolation states and return to  work. As a part of the project, graduate and postdoctoral students will be recruited and trained in interdisciplinary research. The knowledge gained through the project will lead to better control and prevention of the COVID-19 threat. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In this RAPID project, novel computational methods will be used to design neutralizing disulfide-rich peptides de novo and functionalize them to bind the spike protein of COVID-19 and block it from interacting with angiotensin-converting enzyme 2, its endogenous receptor. Then, such peptides, along with other antimicrobials, will be incorporated in a nanocarrier platform using engineered water nanostructures synthesized using combination of electrospray and ionization. A thorough characterization of the physicochemical properties of these water-based nanostructures will be carried out using state of the art analytical methods. The capability of these materials to interact and inactivate the virus on both the air and on surfaces will be assessed using microbiological assays. The interdisciplinary approach of interweaving synthetic biology with nanotechnology would provide a solid tool for tackling COVID-19 on environmental media. Furthermore, the project will lead to the continuation and enhancement of educational activities on emerging aspects of environmental nanotechnology and nano-bio interactions. Results will be disseminated to relevant stakeholders through multifaceted communication activities including publications, conferences, and other out-reach activities. In summary, the proposed nanotechnology-based method has the potential to transform the way we currently control airborne infectious diseases. The social, technological, scientific, public health and economic impact will be significant if such a novel, sustainable, low energy, chemical-free and environmentally friendly method is proven to be effective in the battle against COVID-19.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/15/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/15/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2031785</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Christopher</FirstName>
<LastName>Bahl</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Christopher D Bahl</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[chris.bahl@proteininnovation.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000782385</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/15/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Philip</FirstName>
<LastName>Demokritou</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>K</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Philip K Demokritou</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[Philip.Demokritou@Rutgers.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000617058</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/15/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Harvard University</Name>
<CityName>CAMBRIDGE</CityName>
<ZipCode>021385366</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6174955501</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1033 MASSACHUSETTS AVE STE 3</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>LN53LCFJFL45</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PRESIDENT AND FELLOWS OF HARVARD COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Harvard T.H. Chan School of Public Health]]></Name>
<CityName>Boston</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021156028</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[665 Huntington Avenue, 1310B]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1179</Code>
<Text>Nanoscale Interactions Program</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1642</Code>
<Text>Special Initiatives</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~200000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>&nbsp;</p> <p>COVID-19 continues to persist, due to emerging strains of the SARS-CoV-2 virus. A crucial aspect of reducing viral transmission is environmental disinfection. To this end, a nanotechnology-based antimicrobial platform utilizing engineered water nanostructures (EWNS) was developed.</p> <p>As a part of this project, various antimicrobial active ingredients were incorporated into the nano-sized EWNS. THe EWNS paritcles were generated and analzyed for their size. These EWNS nanodroplets consisted of water, nanograms of antimicrobials, and ROS.</p> <p>These EWNS were then utilized to challenge the human coronavirus 229E (<em>HCoV-229E</em>), a surrogate of SARS-CoV-2. The results showed that EWNS were effective in completely inactivating <em>HCoV-229E</em> inoculated on surface.</p> <p>These results indicate the efficacy of EWNS as a nano-carrier for effective delivery of nanogram dose of antimicrobials, making this an attractive technology against SARS-CoV-2.</p> <p><strong>Intellectual Merit:</strong> The interdisciplinary research of the project&nbsp; combines excellence in nano-science and synthetic biology. Novel computational methods were used to design neutralizing DRPs <em>de novo</em> and functionalize them to bind the spike protein SARS-CoV-2 and block it from interacting with ACE2, it?s endogenous receptor. Such DRPs and other nature derived and inspired antimicrobials were incorporated in a nanocarrier platform using engineered water nanostructures and efficiently delivered to inactivate the virus.&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Broader Impact:</strong> The proposed nanotechnology-based method has the potential to transform the battle against SARS-CoV-2. and other infectious diseases The interdisciplinary approach of interweaving synthetic biology design with nanotechnology would provide a solid tool for tackling infectious diseases, especially airborne ones such as SARS-CoV-2 and influenza. <span style="text-decoration: underline;">This &nbsp;technology is particularly applicable to closed indoor environments and could help in battling the COVID-19 pandemic as people emerge from their social isolation state and return to their work.</span>&nbsp;&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/30/2022<br>      Modified by: Philip&nbsp;K&nbsp;Demokritou</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2031785/2031785_10671070_1658423906935_PictureforNanomaterials--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2031785/2031785_10671070_1658423906935_PictureforNanomaterials--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Engineered Water Nanostructure (EWNS)"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2031785/2031785_10671070_1658423906935_PictureforNanomaterials--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Engineered Water Nanostructure (EWNS)"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Engineered Water Nanostructure (EWNS) as a nano-carrier for antiviral active ingredients.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Authors</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Philip&nbsp;K&nbsp;Demokritou</div> <div class="imageTitle">Engineered Water Nanostructure (EWNS)</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[    COVID-19 continues to persist, due to emerging strains of the SARS-CoV-2 virus. A crucial aspect of reducing viral transmission is environmental disinfection. To this end, a nanotechnology-based antimicrobial platform utilizing engineered water nanostructures (EWNS) was developed.  As a part of this project, various antimicrobial active ingredients were incorporated into the nano-sized EWNS. THe EWNS paritcles were generated and analzyed for their size. These EWNS nanodroplets consisted of water, nanograms of antimicrobials, and ROS.  These EWNS were then utilized to challenge the human coronavirus 229E (HCoV-229E), a surrogate of SARS-CoV-2. The results showed that EWNS were effective in completely inactivating HCoV-229E inoculated on surface.  These results indicate the efficacy of EWNS as a nano-carrier for effective delivery of nanogram dose of antimicrobials, making this an attractive technology against SARS-CoV-2.  Intellectual Merit: The interdisciplinary research of the project  combines excellence in nano-science and synthetic biology. Novel computational methods were used to design neutralizing DRPs de novo and functionalize them to bind the spike protein SARS-CoV-2 and block it from interacting with ACE2, it?s endogenous receptor. Such DRPs and other nature derived and inspired antimicrobials were incorporated in a nanocarrier platform using engineered water nanostructures and efficiently delivered to inactivate the virus.   Broader Impact: The proposed nanotechnology-based method has the potential to transform the battle against SARS-CoV-2. and other infectious diseases The interdisciplinary approach of interweaving synthetic biology design with nanotechnology would provide a solid tool for tackling infectious diseases, especially airborne ones such as SARS-CoV-2 and influenza. This  technology is particularly applicable to closed indoor environments and could help in battling the COVID-19 pandemic as people emerge from their social isolation state and return to their work.         Last Modified: 07/30/2022       Submitted by: Philip K Demokritou]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
