<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: COVID-19 induced cessation of ecotourism and supplemental feeding: Implications for wildlife physiology, reproduction, and the microbiome]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>184519.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>184519</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08090300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IOS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Theodore Morgan</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tmorgan@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927868</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Wildlife feeding by tourists is a widespread phenomenon across various species and environments. While it can provide important economic benefits to countries and local communities, it also poses significant challenges for affected wildlife. These widespread practices may induce habituation, cause stress, impact health, and alter growth and survival, all of which can lead to population changes. However, the ability to control for extraneous factors in tourism-related wildlife feeding conditions is often difficult if not impossible, rendering scientific study challenging. Furthermore, the effects of termination of wildlife feeding have rarely been considered. The unprecedented cessation of tourism and food provisioning due to the COVID-19 global pandemic has created a natural experiment that meets the aforementioned challenges to directly test the effects of this phenomenon on critically endangered rock iguanas in The Bahamas. The proposed work will leverage this unique opportunity to test the effects of widescale resource restriction and dietary change on the health of free-living animals. The implications of this work reach far beyond that of the tourist sector and can inform the effects of resource restriction for natural populations across species on a broader scale. Thus, understanding the consequences of supplemental feeding cessation will help inform countries on a broader scale that are working at making tourism practices more sustainable, which is particularly important for endangered species.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The COVID-19 pandemic has created a unique situation via the restriction of human movement and contact resulting in severely reduced global travel. As a result, in countries like The Bahamas, there has been the complete removal of tourist stress and feeding pressures on wildlife across the country. Recent findings by the PIs examining critically endangered iguanas across an insular landscape in The Bahamas have illustrated significant tourist-driven effects on physiology and gut microbial composition. This work has also revealed significant associations among tourism, bacterial abundance, and physiology. The recent and sudden release from supplemental feeding by tourists has created a rare natural experiment by which the PIs can directly test the effects of diet shifts and restriction in natural populations of long-lived iguanas where pre-pandemic data are already available. The PIs will specifically focus on the gut microbiome, and test for direct associations and directionality with physiological systems important to health and survival. Moreover, the ongoing 40-year demographic study in this system will allow the PIs to relate this to survival, growth, and recruitment at the population level. The research group will work to facilitate transfer of results from this study to The Bahamas via long standing research partnerships and will provide opportunistic clarity on potential management strategies moving forward. To reach the broader community, outcomes will also be reported via Shedd Aquarium media and exhibits.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/27/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/27/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2031420</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Charles</FirstName>
<LastName>Knapp</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Charles Knapp</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[cknapp@sheddaquarium.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000733986</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/27/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Karen</FirstName>
<LastName>Kapheim</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Karen Kapheim</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[karen.kapheim@usu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000081527</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/27/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Susannah</FirstName>
<LastName>French</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Susannah French</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[sfrench@biology.usu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000555774</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/27/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Utah State University</Name>
<CityName>LOGAN</CityName>
<ZipCode>843221000</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4357971226</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1000 OLD MAIN HL</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Utah</StateName>
<StateCode>UT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>UT01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>SPE2YDWHDYU4</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UTAH STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Utah State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Logan</CityName>
<StateCode>UT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>843225305</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5305 Old Main Hill]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Utah</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>UT01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7657</Code>
<Text>Integrtv Ecological Physiology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~184519</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Wildlife feeding by tourists is a widespread activity popular with many animals living in a variety of habitats around the world. While the activity can provide important economic benefits to countries and local communities, it also poses significant challenges for affected wildlife. These widespread practices may induce habituation, cause stress, affect health and survival, all of which can affect population numbers. Admittedly, it can be challenging to conduct detailed cause-and-effect studies on wildlife feeding because there are many eternal factors to consider. It is also extremely difficult to study the cessation of wildlife feeding across wide areas. &nbsp;The unprecedented cessation of tourism and associated wildlife feeding due to the COVID-19 global pandemic created a natural experiment to directly test the effects of this phenomenon on rock iguanas in The Bahamas. We tested the effects of the cessation of supplemental feeding on the diet, microbiome, physiology, and demography (and their interactions) of a long-lived rock iguana. This model system is ideal because of the availability of a 40-year continuous life history data set, on both tourist-visited and unvisited islands, combined with pre-pandemic physiological, diet and microbiome data, which uniquely allowed us to investigate both the physiological and demographic consequences of this recent and extreme dietary shift.</p> <p>This project resulted significant outcomes for all of our specific aims. First, we found persistent differences in the microbiome across populations exposed to different levels of tourism and feeding, even after the significant reduction of tourism in 2020. Specifically, we found that iguanas from islands that have historically been visited by tourists have significantly higher diversity in their gut microbiomes than iguanas from islands with no tourism. This translates to significant differences in the overall gut bacteria community across islands with varying degrees of tourism. We recorded similar differences in two different subspecies of iguanas that we studied. We also found that males have higher bacterial diversity than females. All of these differences were present even after the slow-down of tourism due to COVID, suggesting that any changes to the microbiome that occurred due to the cessation of tourism were either transitory (i.e., our sample timing missed changes) or that even the reduced feeding from private boats was enough to sustain microbiome differences. Indeed, our preliminary dietary analyses indicate that supplemental feeding was still occurring during our 2021 sample collections. Scat samples collected from highly tourist-visited islands contained plant DNA originating from non-native (i.e. human fed) species in similar frequencies to pre-pandemic samples.</p> <p>Despite the resurgence of supplemental feeding, we did find pre-and post-pandemic differences in physiological and biological measures. Specifically, we found significant decreases in reproductive rates at high tourist sites coupled with reduced female body condition at one of our high-tourist sites. These results suggest that the COVID-induced reduction in tourism and feeding are having impacts on iguana populations. We also found that previous physiological distinctions from high-tourist sites were no longer present in most cases, where markers for energy and stress were reduced at the high-tourist sites following the pandemic. These physiology measures are also correlated with a broad range of bacterial families, including those that differ between islands with different tourism levels.</p> <p>Overall, the findings of this research have direct implications for conservation of endangered species and ecotourism management. In particular, the natural experiment that occurred over the last year due to the COVID pandemic helps to inform the effects of feeding cessation on these populations. The implications of this work may be broader and apply to other ecotourism systems as well. Finally, we were able to engage a community scientist, and graduate and undergraduate students in research. Results and outcomes of this work will also be incorporated into Shedd Aquarium Educational programs and media.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/13/2022<br>      Modified by: Susannah&nbsp;French</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Wildlife feeding by tourists is a widespread activity popular with many animals living in a variety of habitats around the world. While the activity can provide important economic benefits to countries and local communities, it also poses significant challenges for affected wildlife. These widespread practices may induce habituation, cause stress, affect health and survival, all of which can affect population numbers. Admittedly, it can be challenging to conduct detailed cause-and-effect studies on wildlife feeding because there are many eternal factors to consider. It is also extremely difficult to study the cessation of wildlife feeding across wide areas.  The unprecedented cessation of tourism and associated wildlife feeding due to the COVID-19 global pandemic created a natural experiment to directly test the effects of this phenomenon on rock iguanas in The Bahamas. We tested the effects of the cessation of supplemental feeding on the diet, microbiome, physiology, and demography (and their interactions) of a long-lived rock iguana. This model system is ideal because of the availability of a 40-year continuous life history data set, on both tourist-visited and unvisited islands, combined with pre-pandemic physiological, diet and microbiome data, which uniquely allowed us to investigate both the physiological and demographic consequences of this recent and extreme dietary shift.  This project resulted significant outcomes for all of our specific aims. First, we found persistent differences in the microbiome across populations exposed to different levels of tourism and feeding, even after the significant reduction of tourism in 2020. Specifically, we found that iguanas from islands that have historically been visited by tourists have significantly higher diversity in their gut microbiomes than iguanas from islands with no tourism. This translates to significant differences in the overall gut bacteria community across islands with varying degrees of tourism. We recorded similar differences in two different subspecies of iguanas that we studied. We also found that males have higher bacterial diversity than females. All of these differences were present even after the slow-down of tourism due to COVID, suggesting that any changes to the microbiome that occurred due to the cessation of tourism were either transitory (i.e., our sample timing missed changes) or that even the reduced feeding from private boats was enough to sustain microbiome differences. Indeed, our preliminary dietary analyses indicate that supplemental feeding was still occurring during our 2021 sample collections. Scat samples collected from highly tourist-visited islands contained plant DNA originating from non-native (i.e. human fed) species in similar frequencies to pre-pandemic samples.  Despite the resurgence of supplemental feeding, we did find pre-and post-pandemic differences in physiological and biological measures. Specifically, we found significant decreases in reproductive rates at high tourist sites coupled with reduced female body condition at one of our high-tourist sites. These results suggest that the COVID-induced reduction in tourism and feeding are having impacts on iguana populations. We also found that previous physiological distinctions from high-tourist sites were no longer present in most cases, where markers for energy and stress were reduced at the high-tourist sites following the pandemic. These physiology measures are also correlated with a broad range of bacterial families, including those that differ between islands with different tourism levels.  Overall, the findings of this research have direct implications for conservation of endangered species and ecotourism management. In particular, the natural experiment that occurred over the last year due to the COVID pandemic helps to inform the effects of feeding cessation on these populations. The implications of this work may be broader and apply to other ecotourism systems as well. Finally, we were able to engage a community scientist, and graduate and undergraduate students in research. Results and outcomes of this work will also be incorporated into Shedd Aquarium Educational programs and media.          Last Modified: 09/13/2022       Submitted by: Susannah French]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
