<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: IIBR: Instrumentation: Time-resolved studies of the SARS-CoV-2 endonuclease NP15]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>199993.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>199993</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DBI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Steven Ellis</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>stellis@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927876</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) crisis has produced an urgent need to understand the structure and dynamics of the proteins of SARS-CoV-2 (CoV-2), the coronavirus that is the cause of this severe infectious disease. Research supported by this award will unravel the catalytic mechanisms of one of the most interesting and unique CoV-2 enzymes, the RNA endoribonuclease, NendoU, which is only found in the highly virulent coronaviruses. NendoU plays a key role in limiting the sensing of viral RNA by host sensors and is thus a very important target to elucidate the mechanisms of viral pathogenesis at the molecular level.  The researchers will use a combination of advanced techniques and new innovations in sample preparation to make “molecular movies” that reveal the mechanism of action for the NendoU protein to advance our understanding of viral biology and may aid in the identification of potential therapeutic compounds.  Results from these studies will be shared through on-line seminars, at scientific meetings, in public data repositories, and through publications in peer-reviewed journals.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Static structures of the NendoU from SARS, MERS and most recently, also from CoV-2 have been determined by standard crystallography under cryogenic conditions, but no structures have been captured with the substrate RNA bound nor have any time-resolved studies been performed on the enzyme. This COVID-2019 RAPID award focuses on time resolved studies using a combination of time-resolved femtosecond crystallography (TR-SFX) and time resolved cryo-electron microscopy (TR-cryo-EM) to capture a molecular movie of the catalytic reaction of NendoU. After the establishment of micro/nano-crystallization conditions for NendoU, mix-and-inject TR-SFX studies will be performed at an x-ray free electron laser (XFEL) to capture snapshots of key reaction steps, including substrate binding as well as the catalytic reaction. Secondly, the mix-and-inject technology developed for Tr-SFX, will be adapted for TR-cryo-EM, which complement the TR-SFX study by unravelling the later time points in catalysis, including product release and the steady state. These time-resolved studies of NendoU will unravel the structure of the transition state and may provide a basis for development of novel drugs for severe coronavirus infections or investigations of the role of NendoU in suppression of the immune response. This RAPID award to Arizona State University is made by the Division of Biological Infrastructure using funds from the Coronavirus Aid, Relief, and Economic Security (CARES) Act.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/13/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/13/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2031343</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Petra</FirstName>
<LastName>Fromme</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Petra Fromme</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[petra.fromme@asu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000495004</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/13/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Arizona State University</Name>
<CityName>TEMPE</CityName>
<ZipCode>852813670</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4809655479</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>660 S MILL AVENUE STE 204</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AZ04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NTLHJXM55KZ6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ARIZONA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Arizona State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Tempe</CityName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>852876011</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AZ04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>158Y</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>1N20</Code>
<Name>R&amp;RA CARES Act DEFC N</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>010N2021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[R&RA CARES Act DEFC N]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~199993</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) crisis has produced a very urgent need to understand the structure and dynamics of the proteins of SARS-CoV-2 (CoV-2), the coronavirus that is the cause of this severe emerging infectious disease. This COVID-2019 RAPID proposal focused on time resolved studies to unravel the catalytic mechanisms of one of the most interesting and unique CoV-2 enzymes, the RNA endoribonuclease NendoU, which is only found in the highly virulent coronaviruses. A dual approach of time-resolved serial femtosecond crystallography (TR-SFX) and TR-cryogenic electron microscope (TR-Cryo-EM) was used to investigate the catalytic mechanism of NendoU, capitalizing upon a 2020 breakthrough in understanding this enzyme&rsquo;s ability to allow the virus to hide from detection by the immune system.</p> <p>The first room-temperature structure of NendoU, determined by serial femtosecond crystallography at an XFEL, was published (Jerningan <em>et al.</em>, Structure, 2023). Further, structural studies of highly transmissible mutants of NendoU were pursued and the first structure of NendoU E266Q mutation observed in the SARS-CoV-2 Epsilon variant was determined via room temperature serial millisecond crystallography at a synchrotron. Data sets were also collected for the T112I Omicron BA.2 variant along with NendoU co-crystallized with a single nucleotide; the difference density map clearly indicates that the nucleotide is located in the binding site and the refinement of this structure is in progress. This award enabled NendoU structures to be captured at room temperature and with the substrate RNA bound, advancing our understanding of the basic biology of the new SARS-CoV-2 virus.</p> <p>Structural determination using cryogenic electron microscopy (cryoEM) studies was also pursued. A major focus was also the further development of the technology of mix-and-inject nozzles for time resolved (TR) cryoEM as well as the dehumidified chamber design for the TR-cryoEM studies. Development of new technology for TR-cryoEM. Advances in technology development include the design of a novel design for mixing nozzles, specifically developed for TR-CryoEM and a provisional patent application has been submitted for these new TR-CryoEM nozzles. A new experimental chamber has been designed in detail for TR-CryoEM experiments where the picoliter droplets are deposited by the picoliter mix-and-inject dispensing nozzle after different time-points on a cryo-cooled EM grid that sits on a fully dehumidified cryo cooling block. This system will advance TR-cryoEM for many projects, encompassing a wide range of applications and biological systems by enabling TR-CryoEM with millisecond time resolution.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>These two time-resolved methods offer an opportunity to better understand the catalytic activity of proteins that are critical to viral pathogenesis, with involvement of faculty and both graduate and undergraduate students across multiple expertise areas&mdash;biochemistry, structural biology, and microfluidics engineering. Participation of advanced graduate students as well as training of a new cohort of graduate students in a range of structural biology techniques, collaboration between ASU faculty as well as participation of a postdoc with the core team was enabled by this award and achieved the development of an RNA cleavage assay for NendoU. Students learned to perform protein expression, isolation, and crystallization, and on-site serial crystallography experiments at synchrotrons which included sample preparation, crystallization as well as collaboration with sample delivery experts and data collection was performed at multiple beamtime facilities. Further, scaling of protein expression as needed for the proposed studies was achieved by partnership with a team of researchers, including students and postdocs from Lawrence Livermore National Lab. Data evaluation capabilities were expanded by ASU&rsquo;s data team in collaboration with faculty at University of Buffalo and University of Wisconsin at Milwaukee, and also enabled the participation of an undergraduate intern from Grand Canyon University. Finally, collaboration on time-resolved cryoEM development across ASU laboratories enabled biochemistry postdocs and students to participate in new technology development with innovative engineering faculty with expertise in mix-and-inject methods as well as in design of new sample delivery instrumentation.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/01/2023<br>      Modified by: Petra&nbsp;Fromme</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) crisis has produced a very urgent need to understand the structure and dynamics of the proteins of SARS-CoV-2 (CoV-2), the coronavirus that is the cause of this severe emerging infectious disease. This COVID-2019 RAPID proposal focused on time resolved studies to unravel the catalytic mechanisms of one of the most interesting and unique CoV-2 enzymes, the RNA endoribonuclease NendoU, which is only found in the highly virulent coronaviruses. A dual approach of time-resolved serial femtosecond crystallography (TR-SFX) and TR-cryogenic electron microscope (TR-Cryo-EM) was used to investigate the catalytic mechanism of NendoU, capitalizing upon a 2020 breakthrough in understanding this enzyme’s ability to allow the virus to hide from detection by the immune system.  The first room-temperature structure of NendoU, determined by serial femtosecond crystallography at an XFEL, was published (Jerningan et al., Structure, 2023). Further, structural studies of highly transmissible mutants of NendoU were pursued and the first structure of NendoU E266Q mutation observed in the SARS-CoV-2 Epsilon variant was determined via room temperature serial millisecond crystallography at a synchrotron. Data sets were also collected for the T112I Omicron BA.2 variant along with NendoU co-crystallized with a single nucleotide; the difference density map clearly indicates that the nucleotide is located in the binding site and the refinement of this structure is in progress. This award enabled NendoU structures to be captured at room temperature and with the substrate RNA bound, advancing our understanding of the basic biology of the new SARS-CoV-2 virus.  Structural determination using cryogenic electron microscopy (cryoEM) studies was also pursued. A major focus was also the further development of the technology of mix-and-inject nozzles for time resolved (TR) cryoEM as well as the dehumidified chamber design for the TR-cryoEM studies. Development of new technology for TR-cryoEM. Advances in technology development include the design of a novel design for mixing nozzles, specifically developed for TR-CryoEM and a provisional patent application has been submitted for these new TR-CryoEM nozzles. A new experimental chamber has been designed in detail for TR-CryoEM experiments where the picoliter droplets are deposited by the picoliter mix-and-inject dispensing nozzle after different time-points on a cryo-cooled EM grid that sits on a fully dehumidified cryo cooling block. This system will advance TR-cryoEM for many projects, encompassing a wide range of applications and biological systems by enabling TR-CryoEM with millisecond time resolution.    These two time-resolved methods offer an opportunity to better understand the catalytic activity of proteins that are critical to viral pathogenesis, with involvement of faculty and both graduate and undergraduate students across multiple expertise areas&mdash;biochemistry, structural biology, and microfluidics engineering. Participation of advanced graduate students as well as training of a new cohort of graduate students in a range of structural biology techniques, collaboration between ASU faculty as well as participation of a postdoc with the core team was enabled by this award and achieved the development of an RNA cleavage assay for NendoU. Students learned to perform protein expression, isolation, and crystallization, and on-site serial crystallography experiments at synchrotrons which included sample preparation, crystallization as well as collaboration with sample delivery experts and data collection was performed at multiple beamtime facilities. Further, scaling of protein expression as needed for the proposed studies was achieved by partnership with a team of researchers, including students and postdocs from Lawrence Livermore National Lab. Data evaluation capabilities were expanded by ASU’s data team in collaboration with faculty at University of Buffalo and University of Wisconsin at Milwaukee, and also enabled the participation of an undergraduate intern from Grand Canyon University. Finally, collaboration on time-resolved cryoEM development across ASU laboratories enabled biochemistry postdocs and students to participate in new technology development with innovative engineering faculty with expertise in mix-and-inject methods as well as in design of new sample delivery instrumentation.       Last Modified: 09/01/2023       Submitted by: Petra Fromme]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
