<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  An Ultra-Fast Battery Charger for Electric Vehicles]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>255642.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>255642</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anna Brady</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>abrady@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927077</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovative Research (SBIR) Phase I project has potential to bring about global reductions in air-pollution and greenhouse gas emissions as the technology encourages the use of electric vehicles.  There are over 272 million passenger cars registered in the United States and over one billion worldwide.  As the transition to electric vehicles takes hold, potential markets for ultra-fast battery chargers for these electric vehicles will be sizeable.  Estimates for the commercial market for electric vehicle charging stations is projected to reach $27.7 billion by 2027 from an estimated $2.5 billion in 2019.  This project addresses the persistent problem of long electric vehicle recharging times and associated “range anxiety” among consumers.  More specifically, an ultra-fast electric vehicle recharging system will be applied to emerging fast-charge batteries so that delays in re-energizing electric vehicles will be no more time-consuming than similar delays for refueling gasoline-powered vehicles.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This SBIR Phase I project proposes to demonstrate the basic feasibility of an ultra-fast battery-charging system for consumer applications that can fully re-energize a typical light-duty electric vehicle in as little as six minutes.  The project will focus on development of safe power conversion and transmission equipment that will be applied to power-matched fast-charge batteries currently emerging in commercial markets.  Because the power levels required for ultra-fast EV charging are necessarily high, the project will focus on innovative measures to ensure public safety and system reliability while obtaining high electrical efficiencies.  A relatively low power model will be constructed in Phase I for later scale-up. Solving technical challenges associated with an ultra-fast high-power electric vehicle charger has potential to advance knowledge of electromagnetics, power electronics, automated control, and materials science associated with ultra-fast electric vehicle recharging.  The project will lead to new findings that will help solve the persistent problem of long delays in recharging electric vehicle batteries.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/21/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/21/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2031026</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
<LastName>Owens</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Thomas Owens</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[aeonsciencesllc@gmail.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000820733</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/21/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>AEON SCIENCES, LLC</Name>
<CityName>FAIRMONT</CityName>
<ZipCode>265548743</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3043763858</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>303 OPEKISKA RD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>West Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>WV</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WV02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>GDTCQGHZC315</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>AEON SCIENCES, LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Aeon Sciences, LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>Fairmont</CityName>
<StateCode>WV</StateCode>
<ZipCode>265548743</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[303 Opekiska Rd]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>West Virginia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WV02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8399</Code>
<Text>Energy Storage or Transmission</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~255642</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The primary objective of the Phase I project is to demonstrate the feasibility of a safe, ultra-high-power, ultra-fast battery charger for resupplying energy to light-duty electric vehicles (EVs) on a time scale that competes very well with the time it takes to refuel a typical gasoline-powered vehicle.&nbsp; In charging an EV on this kind of time-scale, EV owners will find far greater convenience than is now experienced in charging an EV and reduced stress (range anxiety) in making long trips requiring multiple stops for re-energizing an EV.&nbsp; As a result, the general public will be less hesitant to purchase EVs and widespread adoption of EVs will be promoted.&nbsp; As EVs replace fossil-fueled vehicles, greenhouse gas emissions will be reduced and air quality will be improved, contributing to the broader impacts of the proposed ultra-fast EV charging system.</p> <p>It is assumed in this project that fast-charging battery technology is developed elsewhere.&nbsp; While there has been great progress in developing fast-charging EV batteries, very little attention has been devoted to matching the capabilities of new battery technologies with the high-power charger systems that will be needed to supply the batteries.&nbsp; Power levels in the range of hundreds of kilowatts to more than a megawatt will be involved.&nbsp; New issues arise with respect to safety and reliability at these power levels. &nbsp;The proposed device design addresses these issues in detail.&nbsp; The device utilizes an automated, hands-free wireless power-transfer approach that solves many of the important issues encountered at extreme power levels needed for ultra-fast EV charging. &nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>Through a combination of circuit simulations and bench-scale tests, basic operation of the power-transfer circuit was proven at relatively low power.&nbsp; This achievement marks one of the principal milestones for the Phase I project.&nbsp; Measured power coupling efficiencies compete very well with plug-in approaches and other wireless power transfer approaches.&nbsp; The proposed system brings with it many additional benefits that are outlined in the Final Report for the project.&nbsp; Phase I tests of ancillary elements needed for a complete ultra-fast EV charger have also been described in the Final Report.</p> <p>It is especially noteworthy that the Phase I circuit was tested at 85 kHz, which is in the range of the current standard for relatively low-power wireless automotive charging systems.&nbsp; Operation at 85 kHz was achieved using state-of-the-art commercial SiC switches.&nbsp; The fast-switching, high current characteristics of SiC switches will be needed to achieve 85 kHz operation in the range of hundreds of kilowatts during Phase II and beyond. The achievement of SiC operation at 85 kHz in Phase I is therefore a very important secondary milestone.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/09/2022<br>      Modified by: Thomas&nbsp;Owens</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The primary objective of the Phase I project is to demonstrate the feasibility of a safe, ultra-high-power, ultra-fast battery charger for resupplying energy to light-duty electric vehicles (EVs) on a time scale that competes very well with the time it takes to refuel a typical gasoline-powered vehicle.  In charging an EV on this kind of time-scale, EV owners will find far greater convenience than is now experienced in charging an EV and reduced stress (range anxiety) in making long trips requiring multiple stops for re-energizing an EV.  As a result, the general public will be less hesitant to purchase EVs and widespread adoption of EVs will be promoted.  As EVs replace fossil-fueled vehicles, greenhouse gas emissions will be reduced and air quality will be improved, contributing to the broader impacts of the proposed ultra-fast EV charging system.  It is assumed in this project that fast-charging battery technology is developed elsewhere.  While there has been great progress in developing fast-charging EV batteries, very little attention has been devoted to matching the capabilities of new battery technologies with the high-power charger systems that will be needed to supply the batteries.  Power levels in the range of hundreds of kilowatts to more than a megawatt will be involved.  New issues arise with respect to safety and reliability at these power levels.  The proposed device design addresses these issues in detail.  The device utilizes an automated, hands-free wireless power-transfer approach that solves many of the important issues encountered at extreme power levels needed for ultra-fast EV charging.     Through a combination of circuit simulations and bench-scale tests, basic operation of the power-transfer circuit was proven at relatively low power.  This achievement marks one of the principal milestones for the Phase I project.  Measured power coupling efficiencies compete very well with plug-in approaches and other wireless power transfer approaches.  The proposed system brings with it many additional benefits that are outlined in the Final Report for the project.  Phase I tests of ancillary elements needed for a complete ultra-fast EV charger have also been described in the Final Report.  It is especially noteworthy that the Phase I circuit was tested at 85 kHz, which is in the range of the current standard for relatively low-power wireless automotive charging systems.  Operation at 85 kHz was achieved using state-of-the-art commercial SiC switches.  The fast-switching, high current characteristics of SiC switches will be needed to achieve 85 kHz operation in the range of hundreds of kilowatts during Phase II and beyond. The achievement of SiC operation at 85 kHz in Phase I is therefore a very important secondary milestone.          Last Modified: 11/09/2022       Submitted by: Thomas Owens]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
