<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Determination of SARS-CoV-2 Spike Glycoprotein Palmitoylation and its Contribution to Virus-Cell Fusion and Surface Protein-Protein Interactions]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>200000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>200000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>MCB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Matt Buechner</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mbuechne@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924675</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Coronaviruses, such as SARS-CoV-2, the causative agent of COVID-19, are enveloped RNA viruses that encode three envelope proteins – spike glycoprotein (S), envelope protein (E), and membrane protein (M). Of special interest are the coronavirus S proteins, which coat the surface of the virus and form the distinctive “corona” structure. S proteins are responsible for interacting with specific receptors on the surface of host cells, thus initiating virus entry and infection. This project examines the role of S protein palmitoylation, a chemical modification of the S protein with the addition of a fatty acid, in the fusion of the virus to the host cell, and virus infectivity.  Understanding the role of S protein palmitoylation in virus infectivity can lead to the development of new therapeutic targets that block the infectivity of COVID-19.  This project will also contribute to the interdisciplinary training of two graduate students.  In addition, PI will engage in outreach activities with the San Diego educational community and the public, in part through a collaboration with the San Diego Science project, a K-12 professional development and teacher support organization.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of this RAPID proposal is to explore how palmitoylation mediates viral entry and infection of SARS-CoV-2, through S-mediated membrane fusion and host cell receptor interactions. The PIs propose that palmitoylation of the SARS-CoV-2 spike glycoprotein is necessary for these important viral processes that lead to host infection. The specific aims of this project are: (1) Determining the cysteine residues that are palmitoylated in the SARS-CoV-2 spike glycoprotein. (2) Characterizing the palmitoylation-dependence of S protein localization as well as S-mediated virus-cell fusion. (3) Evaluating the palmitoylation-dependent change in protein-protein interactions between host cell surface receptors and the novel coronavirus S protein. Understanding the functional outcomes of S protein palmitoylation can help better understand the role of palmitoylation in cellular dynamics and function and possibly spur development of novel therapeutics for the treatment of COVID-19.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This RAPID award is made by the Cellular Dynamics and Function Program in the Division of Molecular and Cellular Biosciences, using funds from the Coronavirus Aid, Relief, and Economic Security (CARES) Act.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/12/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/12/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2031068</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Neal</FirstName>
<LastName>Devaraj</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>K</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Neal K Devaraj</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ndevaraj@ucsd.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000601363</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/12/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-San Diego</Name>
<CityName>LA JOLLA</CityName>
<ZipCode>920930021</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8585344896</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>9500 GILMAN DRIVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>50</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA50</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>UYTTZT6G9DT1</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, SAN DIEGO</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-San Diego]]></Name>
<CityName>La Jolla</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>920930021</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[9500 Gilman Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>50</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA50</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>158y</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7465</Code>
<Text>NANOSCALE BIO CORE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>1N20</Code>
<Name>R&amp;RA CARES Act DEFC N</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>010N2021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[R&RA CARES Act DEFC N]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~200000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>Many viral proteins in coronaviruses are modified with lipid species, such as fatty acids. The roles and functions of these lipid modifications affect coronavirus biology as well as how virus interacts with the human host</span><span>. The spike glycoprotein is known to be lipid modified and this is found across multiple coronaviruses</span><span>. Not many studies have been done to fully characterize lipid modifications on coronavirus spike proteins and its effects on viral infection. Depending on the coronavirus, the function and role of lipid modification may change when it comes to infection related processes. We were interested in characterizing the lipid modification of spike protein&nbsp;<span>and to better understand its impact on virus-cell membrane fusion that contributes to viral infection. Gaining further insight on the effects of spike protein lipid modification on viral entry and infection could potentially provide a novel target on this viral protein for the treatment of COVID-19.&nbsp;<span>This work focused on characterizing the essential sites of lipid modification within the SARS-CoV-2 spike glycoprotein peptide sequence. We found that changing the cysteine residues within two different clusters of cysteine residues led to a decrease in lipidation levels compared to the natural spike protein. Additionally, we studied the effects of lipid inhibition, through treatment with drugs or genetic mutation screening, on spike protein localization and cell membrane fusion. Although localization of the spike protein did not change with drug or genetic manipulation, fewer membrane fusion events were found to occur between certain spike mutants and the ACE2 receptor. Overall, our study provides information on the role of lipid modification on viral function and membrane fusion processes. In addition, this work may aid the development of therapeutics that can target palmitoylation of SARS-CoV-2 spike protein as an approach to prevent infection in humans.</span></span></span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/28/2023<br>      Modified by: Neal&nbsp;K&nbsp;Devaraj</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Many viral proteins in coronaviruses are modified with lipid species, such as fatty acids. The roles and functions of these lipid modifications affect coronavirus biology as well as how virus interacts with the human host. The spike glycoprotein is known to be lipid modified and this is found across multiple coronaviruses. Not many studies have been done to fully characterize lipid modifications on coronavirus spike proteins and its effects on viral infection. Depending on the coronavirus, the function and role of lipid modification may change when it comes to infection related processes. We were interested in characterizing the lipid modification of spike protein and to better understand its impact on virus-cell membrane fusion that contributes to viral infection. Gaining further insight on the effects of spike protein lipid modification on viral entry and infection could potentially provide a novel target on this viral protein for the treatment of COVID-19. This work focused on characterizing the essential sites of lipid modification within the SARS-CoV-2 spike glycoprotein peptide sequence. We found that changing the cysteine residues within two different clusters of cysteine residues led to a decrease in lipidation levels compared to the natural spike protein. Additionally, we studied the effects of lipid inhibition, through treatment with drugs or genetic mutation screening, on spike protein localization and cell membrane fusion. Although localization of the spike protein did not change with drug or genetic manipulation, fewer membrane fusion events were found to occur between certain spike mutants and the ACE2 receptor. Overall, our study provides information on the role of lipid modification on viral function and membrane fusion processes. In addition, this work may aid the development of therapeutics that can target palmitoylation of SARS-CoV-2 spike protein as an approach to prevent infection in humans.       Last Modified: 03/28/2023       Submitted by: Neal K Devaraj]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
