<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[I-Corps:  Chalcogenide Hybrid Inorganic/Organic Polymers (CHIPs) for Infrared Thermal Imaging Technologies]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ruth Shuman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rshuman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922160</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this I-Corps project is the development of a new class of infrared (IR) optical polymeric materials.  The use of IR thermal imaging (i.e., “night vision”) has long been used for defense and military applications.  IR thermal imaging also has significant potential in consumer electronics, transportation, medical imaging, and robotic and aerospace industries.  One of the key limitations hindering wide-scale implementation of infrared thermal cameras for consumer markets is the high cost of these imaging systems.  In the current IR thermal imaging systems, the transmissive optical elements (e.g., lenses, windows) require the use of expensive inorganic elements (e.g., germanium).  To address this technology barrier, the goal is to pursue the development of IR optical polymers, which are composed of inexpensive starting materials and can easily be melt or solution processed into windows or lenses. Successfully implementation of these materials as inexpensive IR plastics may enable creation of less expensive IR cameras and the potential for entry of these IR imaging systems in automobiles, housing, and medical imaging sectors.&lt;br/&gt;  &lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project is based on the development of Chalcogenide Hybrid Inorganic/Organic Polymers (CHIPs), which are a new class of synthetic polymers with enhanced optical properties for IR applications.  These polymers have the highest refractive index of any synthetic polymer to date and possesses superior IR transparency in comparison to classical synthetic polymers due to a very high content of sulfur-sulfur (S-S), or sulfur-selenium (Se-S) bonds in the copolymer backbone.  CHIPs materials may be melted or solution processed into optical elements such as lenses or windows, which are directly suitable for IR-thermal imaging.   In the proposed research, the plan is to develop improved synthetic methods to enable large-scale synthesis of these materials and new additive manufacturing processing methods to fabricate windows, lenses, and optical elements.  In addition, the goal is to implement these polymer-processed optical elements into prototype IR thermal imaging systems to exploit the favorable properties of these new polymeric materials.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/06/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/08/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041, 47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2031833</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jeffrey</FirstName>
<LastName>Pyun</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jeffrey Pyun</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jpyun@email.arizona.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000170926</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/06/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Arizona</Name>
<CityName>TUCSON</CityName>
<ZipCode>85721</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5206266000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>845 N PARK AVE RM 538</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AZ07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>ED44Y3W6P7B9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ARIZONA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Arizona]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>857210041</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AZ07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The support from the I-Corps program has provided critical support for the UArizona PFI project to engage related industrial sectors for the sulfur based polymer and infrared (IR) plastic optics technology from this project.&nbsp; The key outcomes include engagement of over 100 companies from the IR optics, defense, automotive, oil &amp; gas, chemical, polymer and plastic optics sectors.&nbsp; This set of discovery interviews revealed numerous insights on the barriers and opportunities&nbsp; for the UArizona IR plastic optics technology.&nbsp; In person interview and meetings with potential industrial sponsors and licensing partners were also a critical aspect of this I-Corps project.&nbsp; From the start of the project, activities from this project have lead to the following key results:</p> <p>1)&nbsp;&nbsp; New NDA agreements and sponsored contracts agreement with leading plastic optics companies (PPG, Hoya) and with automotive companies interested in IR optics (Hyundai Motors)</p> <p>2)&nbsp;&nbsp; Licensing negotiations with IR optics companies and new licensing agreements (company prefers not be be disclosed)</p> <p>3)&nbsp;&nbsp; Training of the entrepreneurial lead (Dr. Tristan Kleine) on industrial engagement and possible business canvas designs, which directly enhanced professional development and employment with leading plastic optics company (PPG).</p> <p>4)&nbsp;&nbsp; Graduate students on the PFI project have also been trained on how to conduct discovery interviews and have been tasked with reaching out to potential industrial partners to learn about customer needs and opportunities.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/20/2023<br>      Modified by: Jeffrey&nbsp;Pyun</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The support from the I-Corps program has provided critical support for the UArizona PFI project to engage related industrial sectors for the sulfur based polymer and infrared (IR) plastic optics technology from this project.  The key outcomes include engagement of over 100 companies from the IR optics, defense, automotive, oil &amp; gas, chemical, polymer and plastic optics sectors.  This set of discovery interviews revealed numerous insights on the barriers and opportunities  for the UArizona IR plastic optics technology.  In person interview and meetings with potential industrial sponsors and licensing partners were also a critical aspect of this I-Corps project.  From the start of the project, activities from this project have lead to the following key results:  1)   New NDA agreements and sponsored contracts agreement with leading plastic optics companies (PPG, Hoya) and with automotive companies interested in IR optics (Hyundai Motors)  2)   Licensing negotiations with IR optics companies and new licensing agreements (company prefers not be be disclosed)  3)   Training of the entrepreneurial lead (Dr. Tristan Kleine) on industrial engagement and possible business canvas designs, which directly enhanced professional development and employment with leading plastic optics company (PPG).  4)   Graduate students on the PFI project have also been trained on how to conduct discovery interviews and have been tasked with reaching out to potential industrial partners to learn about customer needs and opportunities.          Last Modified: 05/20/2023       Submitted by: Jeffrey Pyun]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
