<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research: A research-practice partnership focused on creating equitable computer science opportunities for elementary students]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>150419.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>150419</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DRL</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Stephanie Teasley</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>steasley@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928752</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The project is being developed by an existing research-practice partnership (RPP) comprised of Broward County Public Schools, UChicago STEM Education, and the University of Florida. One goal is to create curriculum units that integrate computer science (CS) with other disciplines for PreK-8 students. The specific deliverable will be a unit on invasive species that incorporates science, social studies, and CS content and activities. The module's design will be based on culturally-responsive pedagogy and Universal Design for Learning to address the needs of learners with disabilities and African-American and Hispanic youth. A second goal is to study the student outcomes related to students' academic achievement, computer science proficiency, and attitudes towards computer science. Code.org, one of the largest providers of K-12 computer science content, has agreed to distribute the module to schools nationwide.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;As an implementation study, the research will investigate the module curriculum's impact on student academic achievement, CS proficiency, and CS attitudes. It will also determine which components of the module were most impactful for whom and under what conditions. The researchers will frame these contributions in the broader context of equity. Specifically, the project will generate knowledge about aspects of the intervention that promoted equitable academic and attitudinal outcomes across all groups of young learners. Finally, this project will contribute to knowledge about RPP improvement and RPP engagement with the educational system. The research team will pursue the answers to these questions through a quasi-experimental implementation study. An evaluation of the research-practice partnership itself will also be conducted to contribute to knowledge on the collaborative design and implementation process. This project is funded by the CS for All: Research and RPPs program.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/05/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/05/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2031426</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Maya</FirstName>
<LastName>Israel</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Maya Israel</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[misrael@coe.ufl.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000566077</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/05/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Florida</Name>
<CityName>GAINESVILLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>326111941</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3523923516</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1523 UNION RD RM 207</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NNFQH1JAPEP3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF FLORIDA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>D4GCCCMXR1H3</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Florida]]></Name>
<CityName>GAINESVILLE</CityName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>326112002</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1 UNIVERSITY OF FLORIDA]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>134Y</Code>
<Text>CSforAll-Computer Sci for All</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>023Z</Code>
<Text>Computer Science for All (CS for All)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8817</Code>
<Text>STEM Learning &amp; Learning Environments</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0420</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~150419</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
