<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Development of an oral recombinant subunit vaccine to protect against COVID-19]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>256000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>256000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kaitlin Bratlie</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is to develop a new self-administered vaccine for COVID-19 using a novel oral delivery platform.  This project will develop a new technique to generate a strong immune response.  It can be used in formulating and evaluating potential vaccines for many diseases, strongly supporting public health.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project proposes to develop an orally administered recombinant subunit vaccine targeting SARS-CoV-2. This will be achieved by adsorbing C-type lectin receptor agonist (mannan) and the target antigen (receptor binding domain subunit of spike protein) to aluminum adjuvant, followed by enteric microencapsulation for oral delivery, and spray drying. This platform has been shown to successfully induce mucosal immune response, which is ideal to protect against SARS-CoV-2, which enters via mucosal surfaces. This project will also help advance the technology by further developing analytical assays and optimizing the spray drying processes. Biophysical characterization of the target antigen RBD and formulation development and will first be conducted to achieve good antigen physical stability. Then, dried powder processes will be investigated and optimized. The stability of the dried powders will be analyzed in vitro by particle size, ELISA, during accelerated stability at high temperatures, and in vivo in mouse immunogenicity studies, to further understand the manufacturing process and its impact on vaccine stability and potency.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/02/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/14/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2031281</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Elodie</FirstName>
<LastName>Burlet</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Elodie Burlet</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[elodie.burlet@vaxform.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000779924</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/02/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>VAXFORM, LLC</Name>
<CityName>NAZARETH</CityName>
<ZipCode>180641462</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6108485047</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2213 EVENING SUN RD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>L2PLXD4EA569</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>VAXFORM LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>L2PLXD4EA569</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[VaxForm LLC,]]></Name>
<CityName>Bethlehem</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>180154731</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[116 Research Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>008E</Code>
<Text>Gene and Drug Delivery</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8038</Code>
<Text>Biotechnology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~256000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Oral administration of vaccines is the most convenient way to vaccinate - it is non-invasive, safe, and suitable for all age groups. It can also boost the economic value of vaccines by making needle-free delivery possible, reducing manufacturing costs, and allowing self-administration. Safety is improved through reduced reactogenicity and distribution and storage is not reliant on the cold chain. While injectable mRNA-based vaccines primarily elicit systemic responses, oral immunization efficiently elicits both systemic and mucosal immune responses. Immunity at mucosal surfaces can further enhance protection from infection and greatly minimize the spread of disease. Despite these key benefits, there are no oral COVID-19 vaccines approved for use anywhere in the world, and very few in development. The main challenge for an efficacious vaccine administered orally is to bypass the harsh acidic environment of the stomach.</p> <p>VaxForm has successfully developed a protein-based oral vaccine delivery technology that induces both systemic and mucosal immunity. The delivery platform consists of attaching antigen(s) and an intestinal cell targeting molecule to a delivery particle and encapsulating the particle with an enteric coating polymer to protect it from degradation in the stomach and enhance stability. Once in the intestines, the protective polymer dissolves, and the targeting molecule can bind to cells in the gut to activate the mucosal immune response.</p> <p>In this NSF SBIR Phase I funded project (Award #2031281), VaxForm used their proprietary vaccine delivery platform to develop an orally administered and thermostable COVID-19 vaccine. Results showed that SARS-CoV-2 antigens are compatible with the platform and remain associated with the particle when exposed to intestinal fluid, allowing efficient activation of immune response. The novel vaccine candidate was evaluated in mice and demonstrated successful induction of antigen-specific serum and mucosal antibodies. In addition to the development of the oral COVID-19 vaccine as a liquid suspension (drinkable), processes to manufacture the vaccine as a dried powder, using spray drying and freeze-drying methods, were developed. Manufacturing of oral vaccines as solid dose brings additional advantages such as the ability to stockpile, further enhanced stability, and easier shipment and distribution worldwide. The powder can then be filled into capsules for self-administration.</p> <p>All three versions of the vaccine (liquid suspension, spray dried, and freeze dried) were stored at 60?C for 14 days to compare the performance of the three versions of the vaccine and test their resistance to high temperature. Vaccines stored at 60C vs control vaccines stored at 25C (ambient temperature) were then orally administered to mice and the immune responses were evaluated. Results showed that different immune response profiles were induced from the 3 types of vaccines that were stored at 25C. Liquid suspension vaccine resulted in a balanced serum/mucosal response, the spray dried vaccine induced a predominantly mucosal response, and the freeze-dried vaccine induced a strong serum but weak mucosal response. While these findings warrant further investigation, they suggest that the particle size of the vaccines, once dissolved in the intestines, play a very important role in the activation of the mucosal response. These results provided further understanding of induction of intestinal / mucosal immunity and critical insight into how different formulations can be developed to obtain different types of protective immunity. Another great outcome of this project was the finding that 14 days storage at 60?C (140F) did not reduce the immune response of the liquid vaccine in mice, demonstrating an excellent stability profile of the oral platform.</p> <p>Overall, VaxForm?s oral COVID-19 vaccine?s demonstrated immune response and thermostability, in addition to its safe and convenient administration, shows great potential to contribute to the fight against the global SARS-CoV-2 pandemic. The project also allowed further development of a novel vaccine platform that has the potential to help prevent and control future pandemics better and provide enhanced patient experience during vaccination programs.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/18/2022<br>      Modified by: Elodie&nbsp;Burlet</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Oral administration of vaccines is the most convenient way to vaccinate - it is non-invasive, safe, and suitable for all age groups. It can also boost the economic value of vaccines by making needle-free delivery possible, reducing manufacturing costs, and allowing self-administration. Safety is improved through reduced reactogenicity and distribution and storage is not reliant on the cold chain. While injectable mRNA-based vaccines primarily elicit systemic responses, oral immunization efficiently elicits both systemic and mucosal immune responses. Immunity at mucosal surfaces can further enhance protection from infection and greatly minimize the spread of disease. Despite these key benefits, there are no oral COVID-19 vaccines approved for use anywhere in the world, and very few in development. The main challenge for an efficacious vaccine administered orally is to bypass the harsh acidic environment of the stomach.  VaxForm has successfully developed a protein-based oral vaccine delivery technology that induces both systemic and mucosal immunity. The delivery platform consists of attaching antigen(s) and an intestinal cell targeting molecule to a delivery particle and encapsulating the particle with an enteric coating polymer to protect it from degradation in the stomach and enhance stability. Once in the intestines, the protective polymer dissolves, and the targeting molecule can bind to cells in the gut to activate the mucosal immune response.  In this NSF SBIR Phase I funded project (Award #2031281), VaxForm used their proprietary vaccine delivery platform to develop an orally administered and thermostable COVID-19 vaccine. Results showed that SARS-CoV-2 antigens are compatible with the platform and remain associated with the particle when exposed to intestinal fluid, allowing efficient activation of immune response. The novel vaccine candidate was evaluated in mice and demonstrated successful induction of antigen-specific serum and mucosal antibodies. In addition to the development of the oral COVID-19 vaccine as a liquid suspension (drinkable), processes to manufacture the vaccine as a dried powder, using spray drying and freeze-drying methods, were developed. Manufacturing of oral vaccines as solid dose brings additional advantages such as the ability to stockpile, further enhanced stability, and easier shipment and distribution worldwide. The powder can then be filled into capsules for self-administration.  All three versions of the vaccine (liquid suspension, spray dried, and freeze dried) were stored at 60?C for 14 days to compare the performance of the three versions of the vaccine and test their resistance to high temperature. Vaccines stored at 60C vs control vaccines stored at 25C (ambient temperature) were then orally administered to mice and the immune responses were evaluated. Results showed that different immune response profiles were induced from the 3 types of vaccines that were stored at 25C. Liquid suspension vaccine resulted in a balanced serum/mucosal response, the spray dried vaccine induced a predominantly mucosal response, and the freeze-dried vaccine induced a strong serum but weak mucosal response. While these findings warrant further investigation, they suggest that the particle size of the vaccines, once dissolved in the intestines, play a very important role in the activation of the mucosal response. These results provided further understanding of induction of intestinal / mucosal immunity and critical insight into how different formulations can be developed to obtain different types of protective immunity. Another great outcome of this project was the finding that 14 days storage at 60?C (140F) did not reduce the immune response of the liquid vaccine in mice, demonstrating an excellent stability profile of the oral platform.  Overall, VaxForm?s oral COVID-19 vaccine?s demonstrated immune response and thermostability, in addition to its safe and convenient administration, shows great potential to contribute to the fight against the global SARS-CoV-2 pandemic. The project also allowed further development of a novel vaccine platform that has the potential to help prevent and control future pandemics better and provide enhanced patient experience during vaccination programs.       Last Modified: 03/18/2022       Submitted by: Elodie Burlet]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
