<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Antiviral Activity of Novel Nitrogen-Doped, Carbon Supported Catalysts Against Covid-19 Surrogates]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>256000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>256000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anna Brady</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>abrady@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927077</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) project would be to slow the spread of viruses indoors, mitigating the need for social distancing.  Microbes and viruses do not survive on specific surfaces. This project will explore if special nanoparticles can be used to kill viruses, such as that which causes COVID-19.  This would help slow contagion and protect indoor spaces. &lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;This SBIR Phase I project proposes to determine if carbon supported nanoparticles can destructively deactivate SARS-CoV-2 under biologically realistic conditions. This project will explore novel nitrogen-doped carbon supports loaded with catalytic nanoparticles to destructively interact with SARS-CoV-2. Nitrogen in carbonaceous materials interacts with viruses and can increase performance in catalytic chemical reactions; however, to date this has not been leveraged at scale. In this project, three different types of nitrogen-doped carbon supports will be produced and compared against two state-of-practice carbon supports. Each support will have four different catalytic nanoparticles attached and then will be tested for efficacy. These catalysts will be compared on their ability to destroy coronavirus surrogates using an ASTM standardized test for evaluating medical mask efficiency. Once a suitable combination of catalyst support and catalytic nanoparticles is determined, the solution and process can be optimized.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/09/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/14/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2032653</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Franchessa</FirstName>
<LastName>Sayler</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Franchessa M Sayler</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[franchessa@thrupore.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000634361</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/09/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>ThruPore Technologies</Name>
<CityName>NEW CASTLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>197201600</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2056570714</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>15 READS WAY STE 107</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Delaware</StateName>
<StateCode>DE</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DE00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>HA4ZD39UFFC3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>THRUPORE TECHNOLOGIES INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>HA4ZD39UFFC3</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[ThruPore Technologies, Inc]]></Name>
<CityName>Birmingham</CityName>
<StateCode>AL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>352031604</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1500 1st Ave. N, Suite R134]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Alabama</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8030</Code>
<Text>Chemical Technology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8042</Code>
<Text>Health and Safety</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~256000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This SBIR Phase I project focused on developing a safe and effective carbon-based coating that would kill the COVID-19 virus without restricting air flow. ThruPore successfully developed a proprietary porous carbon product loaded with zinc oxide that can be used in air filtration and mask applications, where the antibacterial and antiviral properties will be most effective at preventing spread of airborne disease.</p> <p>The project first set out to formulate a carbon structure capable of attracting viruses. Then multiple different metal ions that are known to have antiviral and antibacterial properties were added to the carbon and tested for effectiveness against different viruses. When comparing the advantages of the different metals, zinc oxide was found to be the best candidate with regards to antiviral/antibacterial efficacy, cost, and safety. The final product formulation was rigorously tested using the guidance of the Environmental Protection Agency (EPA.) Highly repeatable, accurate testing revealed ThruPore&rsquo;s final product was <strong>over 99.99% effective</strong> at killing EPA approved surrogates for the Sars-CoV-2 virus in an air stream without increasing the resistance to air flow.</p> <p>ThruPore is moving forward with commercializing this new antiviral product quickly. Used in air filtration applications, ThruPore&rsquo;s filtration<em> </em>technology provides safer environments in retail, office spaces, and schools such that as air is recirculated through the current HVAC units in these buildings, 99.99% of viral and bacterial contaminants in the air will be destroyed. This air filtration product will allow current HVAC units in schools, retail businesses, and office buildings to be cheaply outfitted with cutting edge technology that kills viruses and bacteria, all simply by changing the air filter. The direct impact this antiviral technology will reduce the probability of all airborne disease transmission from person to person. The broader impact of technology is that it will allow our society to safely return to the activities we most enjoy. This in turn will help increase our economic output by reducing the number of illnesses transmitted throughout our population, decrease money and time spent on sick leave and make people feel safe enough to return to work. More importantly by reducing the spread of disease ThruPore&rsquo;s new filtration technology can help protect the lives of people around the world, help put an end to the COVID-19 pandemic and prevent future pandemics from occurring.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/30/2021<br>      Modified by: Franchessa&nbsp;M&nbsp;Sayler</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This SBIR Phase I project focused on developing a safe and effective carbon-based coating that would kill the COVID-19 virus without restricting air flow. ThruPore successfully developed a proprietary porous carbon product loaded with zinc oxide that can be used in air filtration and mask applications, where the antibacterial and antiviral properties will be most effective at preventing spread of airborne disease.  The project first set out to formulate a carbon structure capable of attracting viruses. Then multiple different metal ions that are known to have antiviral and antibacterial properties were added to the carbon and tested for effectiveness against different viruses. When comparing the advantages of the different metals, zinc oxide was found to be the best candidate with regards to antiviral/antibacterial efficacy, cost, and safety. The final product formulation was rigorously tested using the guidance of the Environmental Protection Agency (EPA.) Highly repeatable, accurate testing revealed ThruPore’s final product was over 99.99% effective at killing EPA approved surrogates for the Sars-CoV-2 virus in an air stream without increasing the resistance to air flow.  ThruPore is moving forward with commercializing this new antiviral product quickly. Used in air filtration applications, ThruPore’s filtration technology provides safer environments in retail, office spaces, and schools such that as air is recirculated through the current HVAC units in these buildings, 99.99% of viral and bacterial contaminants in the air will be destroyed. This air filtration product will allow current HVAC units in schools, retail businesses, and office buildings to be cheaply outfitted with cutting edge technology that kills viruses and bacteria, all simply by changing the air filter. The direct impact this antiviral technology will reduce the probability of all airborne disease transmission from person to person. The broader impact of technology is that it will allow our society to safely return to the activities we most enjoy. This in turn will help increase our economic output by reducing the number of illnesses transmitted throughout our population, decrease money and time spent on sick leave and make people feel safe enough to return to work. More importantly by reducing the spread of disease ThruPore’s new filtration technology can help protect the lives of people around the world, help put an end to the COVID-19 pandemic and prevent future pandemics from occurring.          Last Modified: 11/30/2021       Submitted by: Franchessa M Sayler]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
