<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Frontera Travel Grant: 3-D Stellar Hydrodynamics  of Convective Boundary Mixing and Shell Mergers in Massive Stars]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>9977.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>9977</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OAC</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure (OAC)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Edward Walker</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>edwalker@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924863</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[For nearly four decades, the National Science Foundation (NSF) has played a leadership role in provisioning advanced cyberinfrastructure capabilities for the Nation's Science and Engineering (S&amp;E) researchers. An important component in this investment is the leadership-class computing program that provides computational and data analytics capabilities at the largest scale to inspire transformative S&amp;E discoveries that would not be possible otherwise. NSF's current leadership-class computing investment supports Frontera, the largest High-Performance Computing (HPC) system on a US academic campus. The Frontera system is deployed and operated by the Texas Advanced Computing Center (TACC) at the University of Texas (UT) at Austin. This travel grant will support the participation of researchers who have been awarded a computer time allocation on the Frontera system at a future Principal Investigator (PI) meeting organized by TACC. The award will also support travel for technical coordination between researchers and the Frontera project to ensure optimal and effective utilization of the Frontera system.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of the PI meeting is to allow Frontera research users, as well as their students, to share scientific results, exchange practical lessons-learned, and present their overall experience from using the Frontera system. In addition to research presentations, the meeting will have ample time, as well as facilitated sessions, to promote increased interaction between Frontera research users and project staff. The outcome of the PI meeting will not only enable the Frontera project to better understand and serve the scientific research community, but also build a community to better represent the unique needs of S&amp;E research that require access to NSF leadership computing facilities. To facilitate deeper coordination beyond the PI meeting, this award will also provide travel support to enable technical coordination between the research user teams and the Frontera project.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/12/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/12/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2032010</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
<LastName>Woodward</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Paul R Woodward</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[paul@lcse.umn.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000155670</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/12/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Minnesota-Twin Cities</Name>
<CityName>MINNEAPOLIS</CityName>
<ZipCode>554552009</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6126245599</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>200 OAK ST SE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>KABJZBBJ4B54</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MINNESOTA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Minnesota-Twin Cities]]></Name>
<CityName>Minneapolis</CityName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>554552070</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[117 Pleasant St. S. E.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7781</Code>
<Text>Leadership-Class Computing</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~9977</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="NSF-Section-Title">Outcomes Report:&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Travel for Research carried out on Frontera on 3-D Stellar Hydrodynamics <br /> of Convective Boundary Mixing and Shell Mergers in Massive Stars, NSF Award 2032010</p> <p class="NSF-Indent">The goals of this project were to support travel for members of the PPMstar code team to meet with each other and interact face-to-face, and also for us to meet with other experts who are dealing with issues of code scaling, accuracy, and performance that we encounter on NSF's Frontera computing system at TACC.&nbsp; This activity is in support of our research being carried out on the Frontera machine under annual allocations and associated with the research project of the same name as above, NSF award 1814181.</p> <p class="NSF-Indent">We consider multiple developments and enhancements of our 3-D stellar hydrodynamics code PPMstar as outcomes of this project.&nbsp; Among those enhancements were performance increases arising from a new and far more aggressive precompilation of the code using a custom precompiler program, written in Fortran by the PI.&nbsp; These developments boosted the performance of the code on Frontera to roughly 10% of the machine's peak performance, obtained with near linear speed-up up to and including the scale of 3510 nodes, or nearly half the machine, updating a 2688^3 grid on the largest configuration of nodes.&nbsp; Multiple additional enhancements were carried out, particularly modifications leading to more accurate computation while remaining in 32-bit precision.</p> <p class="NSF-Indent">Among the specific outcomes from this travel grant we include the development of a new 1-D model of the core convection zone of a massive star, complete with a region of penetrative convection.&nbsp; This modeling effort grew out of discussions we had with our close collaborator, Falk Herwig, while we were at a meeting at the Kavli Institute for Theoretical Physics in Santa Barbara, where we and other teams presented research results.&nbsp; After returning from the meeting, we ran a simulation of core convection in a stellar model of 25 solar masses on a grid of 896^3 cells for about 3 years for that star with a luminosity enhancement of a factor of 10,000 (see figure).&nbsp; This very long duration run at this highly enhanced luminosity allowed the convection zone to develop its penetrative convection region more fully, so that the rate of entrainment of gas from above the convection zone slowed by about a factor of 6 from its initial value.&nbsp; In the images here, the magnitude of the vorticity is shown in this simulation near its conclusion, when the convection zone has expanded significantly.&nbsp; The classic dipole circulation flow in the convection zone can be seen to only contact the convective boundary from time to time, which allows further gas entrainment to occur but only intermittently.&nbsp; An image of the same simulation is shown for comparison at a much earlier time.&nbsp; Not only is the convection zone significantly smaller, but the "contact" of the dipole circulation flow with the convective boundary extends roughly a quarter of the way around the circular extent of this boundary, producing the 6-times-larger gas entrainment that we observe at earlier times for this stellar model.</p> <p class="NSF-Indent">Our model of the convection zone identifies the thin, higher-entropy layer of convection zone gas right close to the convective boundary, which has developed in the images shown at the later times, as a key feature of the near-equilibrium penetrative convection structure.&nbsp; This layer is generated by local heating from a declining radiative diffusion heat flux that is approaching the total luminosity in this penetration region from above.&nbsp; Our analysis indicates that the size of the convection zone, the location of the Schwarzschild boundary, and the structure of the penetration region, including the compositional jump next to the convective boundary, does not change with the luminosity boost factor.</p> <p class="NSF-Indent">By careful analysis of the simulation results, we have constructed a model of the convection zone that could potentially be used in 1-D stellar evolution computations.&nbsp; This model has no free, adjustable parameters, but it does require a measurement, via a brief 3-D simulation on a relatively coarse grid, of the kinetic energy dissipation rate inside the Schwarzschild boundary.&nbsp; We expect that in a practical implementation of this model, some appropriately small number of such 3-D simulations would be carried out, their results tabulated, and interpolations performed in order to apply the model at any particular point in a star's main-sequence evolution.&nbsp; Such a procedure would be not unlike use of tabulated equations of state, which require very substantial computations that are carried out separately, and whose results are interpolated.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/29/2023<br>      Modified by: Paul&nbsp;R&nbsp;Woodward</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2032010/2032010_10670227_1680079770253_M252-10000x-896-fixKappa-lut831-Vort0101--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2032010/2032010_10670227_1680079770253_M252-10000x-896-fixKappa-lut831-Vort0101--rgov-800width.jpg" title="M252-10000x-896-Vorticity-0101"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2032010/2032010_10670227_1680079770253_M252-10000x-896-fixKappa-lut831-Vort0101--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="M252-10000x-896-Vorticity-0101"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Vorticity magnitude in the far hemisphere of a non-rotating main-sequence stellar model of 25 solar masses computed on a grid of 896^3 cells. In this simulation the luminosity of the star was boosted by a factor of 10,000 to speed its approach to equilibrium.  The time is 120.56 days.</div> <div class="imageCredit">P. R. Woodward, Univ. of Minnesota</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Paul&nbsp;R&nbsp;Woodward</div> <div class="imageTitle">M252-10000x-896-Vorticity-0101</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2032010/2032010_10670227_1680080006589_M252-10000x-896-fixKappa-lut831-Vort6136--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2032010/2032010_10670227_1680080006589_M252-10000x-896-fixKappa-lut831-Vort6136--rgov-800width.jpg" title="M252-10000x-896-Vorticity-6136"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2032010/2032010_10670227_1680080006589_M252-10000x-896-fixKappa-lut831-Vort6136--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="M252-10000x-896-Vorticity-6136"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Vorticity magnitude in the far hemisphere of a non-rotating main-sequence stellar model of 25 solar masses computed on a grid of 896^3 cells. In this simulation the luminosity of the star was boosted by a factor of 10,000 to speed its approach to equilibrium.  The time is 732.41 days.</div> <div class="imageCredit">P. R. Woodward, Univ. of Minnesota</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Paul&nbsp;R&nbsp;Woodward</div> <div class="imageTitle">M252-10000x-896-Vorticity-6136</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2032010/2032010_10670227_1680080184994_M252-10000x-896-fixKappa-lut831-Vort6139--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2032010/2032010_10670227_1680080184994_M252-10000x-896-fixKappa-lut831-Vort6139--rgov-800width.jpg" title="M252-10000x-896-Vorticity-6139"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2032010/2032010_10670227_1680080184994_M252-10000x-896-fixKappa-lut831-Vort6139--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="M252-10000x-896-Vorticity-6139"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Vorticity magnitude in the far hemisphere of a non-rotating main-sequence stellar model of 25 solar masses computed on a grid of 896^3 cells. In this simulation the luminosity of the star was boosted by a factor of 10,000 to speed its approach to equilibrium.  The time is 732.76 days.</div> <div class="imageCredit">P. R. Woodward, Univ. of Minnesota</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Paul&nbsp;R&nbsp;Woodward</div> <div class="imageTitle">M252-10000x-896-Vorticity-6139</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2032010/2032010_10670227_1680080399787_M252-10000x-896-fixKappa-lut831-Vort6180--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2032010/2032010_10670227_1680080399787_M252-10000x-896-fixKappa-lut831-Vort6180--rgov-800width.jpg" title="M252-10000x-896-Vorticity-6180"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2032010/2032010_10670227_1680080399787_M252-10000x-896-fixKappa-lut831-Vort6180--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="M252-10000x-896-Vorticity-6180"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Vorticity magnitude in the far hemisphere of a non-rotating main-sequence stellar model of 25 solar masses computed on a grid of 896^3 cells. In this simulation the luminosity of the star was boosted by a factor of 10,000 to speed its approach to equilibrium.  The time is 737.66 days.</div> <div class="imageCredit">P. R. Woodward, Univ. of Minnesota</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Paul&nbsp;R&nbsp;Woodward</div> <div class="imageTitle">M252-10000x-896-Vorticity-6180</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[Outcomes Report:    Travel for Research carried out on Frontera on 3-D Stellar Hydrodynamics   of Convective Boundary Mixing and Shell Mergers in Massive Stars, NSF Award 2032010 The goals of this project were to support travel for members of the PPMstar code team to meet with each other and interact face-to-face, and also for us to meet with other experts who are dealing with issues of code scaling, accuracy, and performance that we encounter on NSF's Frontera computing system at TACC.  This activity is in support of our research being carried out on the Frontera machine under annual allocations and associated with the research project of the same name as above, NSF award 1814181. We consider multiple developments and enhancements of our 3-D stellar hydrodynamics code PPMstar as outcomes of this project.  Among those enhancements were performance increases arising from a new and far more aggressive precompilation of the code using a custom precompiler program, written in Fortran by the PI.  These developments boosted the performance of the code on Frontera to roughly 10% of the machine's peak performance, obtained with near linear speed-up up to and including the scale of 3510 nodes, or nearly half the machine, updating a 2688^3 grid on the largest configuration of nodes.  Multiple additional enhancements were carried out, particularly modifications leading to more accurate computation while remaining in 32-bit precision. Among the specific outcomes from this travel grant we include the development of a new 1-D model of the core convection zone of a massive star, complete with a region of penetrative convection.  This modeling effort grew out of discussions we had with our close collaborator, Falk Herwig, while we were at a meeting at the Kavli Institute for Theoretical Physics in Santa Barbara, where we and other teams presented research results.  After returning from the meeting, we ran a simulation of core convection in a stellar model of 25 solar masses on a grid of 896^3 cells for about 3 years for that star with a luminosity enhancement of a factor of 10,000 (see figure).  This very long duration run at this highly enhanced luminosity allowed the convection zone to develop its penetrative convection region more fully, so that the rate of entrainment of gas from above the convection zone slowed by about a factor of 6 from its initial value.  In the images here, the magnitude of the vorticity is shown in this simulation near its conclusion, when the convection zone has expanded significantly.  The classic dipole circulation flow in the convection zone can be seen to only contact the convective boundary from time to time, which allows further gas entrainment to occur but only intermittently.  An image of the same simulation is shown for comparison at a much earlier time.  Not only is the convection zone significantly smaller, but the "contact" of the dipole circulation flow with the convective boundary extends roughly a quarter of the way around the circular extent of this boundary, producing the 6-times-larger gas entrainment that we observe at earlier times for this stellar model. Our model of the convection zone identifies the thin, higher-entropy layer of convection zone gas right close to the convective boundary, which has developed in the images shown at the later times, as a key feature of the near-equilibrium penetrative convection structure.  This layer is generated by local heating from a declining radiative diffusion heat flux that is approaching the total luminosity in this penetration region from above.  Our analysis indicates that the size of the convection zone, the location of the Schwarzschild boundary, and the structure of the penetration region, including the compositional jump next to the convective boundary, does not change with the luminosity boost factor. By careful analysis of the simulation results, we have constructed a model of the convection zone that could potentially be used in 1-D stellar evolution computations.  This model has no free, adjustable parameters, but it does require a measurement, via a brief 3-D simulation on a relatively coarse grid, of the kinetic energy dissipation rate inside the Schwarzschild boundary.  We expect that in a practical implementation of this model, some appropriately small number of such 3-D simulations would be carried out, their results tabulated, and interpolations performed in order to apply the model at any particular point in a star's main-sequence evolution.  Such a procedure would be not unlike use of tabulated equations of state, which require very substantial computations that are carried out separately, and whose results are interpolated.       Last Modified: 03/29/2023       Submitted by: Paul R Woodward]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
