<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Rapidly Deployable Virus Adsorbing Face Mask Coating to Reduce COVID-19 Transmission]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>256000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>256000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anna Brady</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>abrady@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927077</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of the Small Business Innovative Research (SBIR) project is the reduction of viral transmission of the novel coronavirus (SARS-CoV-2) and other viral pathogens. The ongoing COVID-19 pandemic has killed hundreds of thousands with widespread disruption to economic and healthcare systems. Face masks have been shown to play a critical role in reducing coronavirus transmission. However, cloth masks do a poor job protecting the wearer from exposure and effective alternatives (i.e., N95 respirators) are in short supply for front-line workers and the public, creating an urgent need for a low-cost, safe, effective, and simple coating technology that reduces virus transmission. This project will develop a coating that can be applied directly to a face mask or mask insert.  Beyond COVID-19, future coating compositions could be tuned to address new viral outbreaks. Furthermore, respiratory protection via coatings or filter inserts are likely to be in high demand given the increased awareness from the current crisis. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This SBIR Phase I project proposes to develop molecular coatings with amphoteric properties to enhance virus adsorption from water-based aerosols. Ion exchange (IEX) materials are commonly used in aqueous environments as effective virus adsorbents because of pH tunable electrostatic affinity. However, these design principles have not been translated to a face mask coating because commercially available IEX materials: 1) utilize hazardous chemicals that require complex and centralized production, 2) lack tunability for adsorption in a fixed pH environment (i.e., human breath), and 3) typically absorb water which is detrimental to the respiratory protection of a mask. This project will overcome these limitations through the design of a heterogeneous surface coating. The coating composition will be optimized to promote electrostatic virus adsorption under breathing conditions (i.e., pH ~ 7.7) while simultaneously enhancing hydrophobicity to minimize aerosol penetration through a porous mask. The key technical hurdles addressed by the proposed research are: 1) formation of a single phase coating solution, 2) coating application and optimization of amphoteric properties for selective adsorption, 3) achieving an increase viral protection factor of 2× or higher, and 4) assessing cradle-to-grave safety.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/09/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/10/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2032819</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Olivia</FirstName>
<LastName>Lenz</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Olivia Lenz</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[olivia@membrion.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000850849</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/10/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gregory</FirstName>
<LastName>Newbloom</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gregory M Newbloom</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[greg@membrion.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000724187</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/09/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate>03/10/2021</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Membrion, Inc.</Name>
<CityName>SEATTLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>981191763</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2062762944</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3257 17TH AVE W</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[BLDG 3]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>DEYBRB8DTGN3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MEMBRION INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>PW3CCASPYFL8</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Membrion, Inc.]]></Name>
<CityName>SEATTLE</CityName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>981043830</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[562 1ST AVE S, STE 700]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8030</Code>
<Text>Chemical Technology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~256000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Membrion performed research &amp; development for a face mask coating to improve virus filter efficacy. Commercially available cloth face masks are effective at reducing the spread of airborne communicable viruses, including SARS CoV-2, when used collectively but are not highly effective at protecting an individual user from contamination especially from unmasked individuals in close proximity for extended period of time. The goal was to leverage knowledge of silsesquioxane (SSQ) and other siloxane chemistry to develop a delivery system imparting functionality to the surface of woven and porous, non-woven materials able to trap charged particles including enveloped viruses.&nbsp;</p> <p>Membrion developed stable solutions able to coat cotton with a thin layer of functionalized silica to modify surface properties and improve aerosol filtration efficiencies. The formulations were able to impart simultaneous positive and negative charged functional groups to adjust the surface charge of the substrate material. Treated cotton has shown increased efficiency over untreated cotton and formulations survived accelerated aging conditions designed to imitate real world storage, transport, and shelf-life needs. Cradle to grave safety was analyzed and a family of functional formulations have passed all safety tests devised to be used in a customer product intended for face mask treatment. Further development is needed to commercialize this technology.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/12/2021<br>      Modified by: Olivia&nbsp;Lenz</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Membrion performed research &amp; development for a face mask coating to improve virus filter efficacy. Commercially available cloth face masks are effective at reducing the spread of airborne communicable viruses, including SARS CoV-2, when used collectively but are not highly effective at protecting an individual user from contamination especially from unmasked individuals in close proximity for extended period of time. The goal was to leverage knowledge of silsesquioxane (SSQ) and other siloxane chemistry to develop a delivery system imparting functionality to the surface of woven and porous, non-woven materials able to trap charged particles including enveloped viruses.   Membrion developed stable solutions able to coat cotton with a thin layer of functionalized silica to modify surface properties and improve aerosol filtration efficiencies. The formulations were able to impart simultaneous positive and negative charged functional groups to adjust the surface charge of the substrate material. Treated cotton has shown increased efficiency over untreated cotton and formulations survived accelerated aging conditions designed to imitate real world storage, transport, and shelf-life needs. Cradle to grave safety was analyzed and a family of functional formulations have passed all safety tests devised to be used in a customer product intended for face mask treatment. Further development is needed to commercialize this technology.          Last Modified: 11/12/2021       Submitted by: Olivia Lenz]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
