<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[STTR Phase I:  Rapid Acting Disinfectant Spray for Slowing the Spread of COVID-19]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>255536.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>255536</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anna Brady</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>abrady@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927077</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Technology Transfer (STTR) project is development of a disinfectant spray to curb the transmission of SARS-CoV-2 via contact with contaminated surfaces. COVID-19 transmission occurs primarily via respiratory droplets produced by an infected person and by contact with a surface where a droplet containing the virus exists. Mitigating infection by contact with surfaces is a measure that will slow the spread of novel viruses ahead of development of a vaccine or other protective measures. In conjunction with other measures, a novel disinfectant will support public health during the COVID-19 pandemic. Current disinfectants require times ranging from 30 seconds to 10 minutes for disinfection to begin after application and do not continue to disinfect. The proposed technology creates a temporary, continually disinfecting film that remains on the application surface. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This STTR Phase I project will demonstrate both the rapid performance of a novel spray and its ability to form a temporary and continually disinfecting film post=application. This technology employs a select medium containing fast-response doped nanoceria where the oxidizing response/mechanism is engineered to perform several disinfectant reactions in parallel. A safe, rapid, multi-disinfectant approach using engineered nanoceria has not previously been demonstrated for use. The project will also demonstrate the post-application disinfection properties. The goals of this project will be achieved with the following: 1) development of an anti-viral, multi-mechanism disinfectant formulation, 2) demonstration of efficacy and safety, 3) study of product stability, and 4) demonstration of temporary film formation, stability, and activity.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/10/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/21/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041, 47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2032056</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Christina</FirstName>
<LastName>Drake</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Christina Drake</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[cdrake@kismettechnologies.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000803748</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>KISMET TECHNOLOGIES Inc.</Name>
<CityName>ORLANDO</CityName>
<ZipCode>328225137</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4074134180</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>7101 TPC DR STE 130</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>GRRTHJ7VZN73</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>KISMET TECHNOLOGIES INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[KISMET TECHNOLOGIES LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>Orlando</CityName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>328263230</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3259 Progress Drive #175B]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1505</Code>
<Text>STTR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8030</Code>
<Text>Chemical Technology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~255536</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Kismet Technologies, along with our team at the University of Central Florida (UCF) (a Hispanic Serving Minority Institution (HSI)), made significant progress during our Phase I project: "Rapid Acting Disinfectant Spray for Slowing the Spread of COVID-19". The original Phase I outcomes were to develop a commercially appropriate disinfectant with the ability to engineer for solution stabilization and safety. We initially targeted curbing transmission of coronavirus. Importantly, our Phase I results were much more impactful, as they showed broad antimicrobial efficacy with NanoRAD (Nano-based Residual Active Disinfectant) that has benefits far beyond coronavirus. NanoRAD has the potential to greatly reduce Hospital Acquired Infections (HAIs) and other preventable infections from contact with surfaces. HAIs affect more than 1 in 30 US patients, with ~15% of HAIs resulting in death. During the COVID-19 pandemic, much of the progress made over the last 10 years in reducing HAIs in the US has been reversed. There is an intense need for effective infection control technologies to prevent illness and reduce healthcare costs.</p> <p><em><span style="text-decoration: underline;">We successfully demonstrated NanoRAD as a unique and new type of continuous disinfectant, leaving behind a temporary, continually disinfecting film with broad antimicrobial efficacy.</span></em> NanoRAD will be the first residual disinfectant able to: (1) <em>disinfect (99.9%) viruses and bacteria safely, </em>(2) act <em>continually in under an hour</em> and (3) <em>eradicate many microbes (no infectious units &gt;99.999%) by the 2-hour mark</em>.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong><em>Our Phase I findings demonstrate that NanoRAD can provide safe, continuous virus and bacteria protection on surfaces it is applied to. We have shown:</em></strong></p> <p>1)&nbsp; &nbsp; a new, specially engineered nanomaterial that demonstrated broad antimicrobial potency;</p> <p>2)&nbsp; &nbsp; the ability to formulate into a polymer to create an antimicrobial film on a surface;</p> <p>3)&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;the ability for the film to be continually re-challenged;</p> <p>4)&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;continuous and rapid disinfection that exceeds the EPA standard;</p> <p>5)&nbsp; &nbsp; no toxicity or irritation when the active ingredient is introduced to eye and skin cells</p> <p>NanoRAD has broad and potent antimicrobial effect as a dry film on treated surfaces. From our test results, NanoRAD disinfects all viruses and bacteria it is challenged with in well under an hour and for most pathogens eradicates a full viral or bacterial within 2 hours.This level of performance for a dry nanomaterial, with the lack of irritation or toxicity for eye and skin cells is a remarkable feat that has the potential to drastically reduce HAIs and healthcare costs.&nbsp;</p> <p><em>&nbsp;</em></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/17/2022<br>      Modified by: Christina&nbsp;Drake</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2032056/2032056_10695102_1660742275309_NanoRADPilotImage--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2032056/2032056_10695102_1660742275309_NanoRADPilotImage--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Pediatric Bathroom Floor 28 Day Pilot"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2032056/2032056_10695102_1660742275309_NanoRADPilotImage--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Pediatric Bathroom Floor 28 Day Pilot"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">NanoRAD was applied once at the beginning of a 28-day pilot to the floor behind a toilet in a pediatric facility. NanoRAD successfully prevented bacteria survival for 28 days with only one application.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Kismet Technologies</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Christina&nbsp;Drake</div> <div class="imageTitle">Pediatric Bathroom Floor 28 Day Pilot</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Kismet Technologies, along with our team at the University of Central Florida (UCF) (a Hispanic Serving Minority Institution (HSI)), made significant progress during our Phase I project: "Rapid Acting Disinfectant Spray for Slowing the Spread of COVID-19". The original Phase I outcomes were to develop a commercially appropriate disinfectant with the ability to engineer for solution stabilization and safety. We initially targeted curbing transmission of coronavirus. Importantly, our Phase I results were much more impactful, as they showed broad antimicrobial efficacy with NanoRAD (Nano-based Residual Active Disinfectant) that has benefits far beyond coronavirus. NanoRAD has the potential to greatly reduce Hospital Acquired Infections (HAIs) and other preventable infections from contact with surfaces. HAIs affect more than 1 in 30 US patients, with ~15% of HAIs resulting in death. During the COVID-19 pandemic, much of the progress made over the last 10 years in reducing HAIs in the US has been reversed. There is an intense need for effective infection control technologies to prevent illness and reduce healthcare costs.  We successfully demonstrated NanoRAD as a unique and new type of continuous disinfectant, leaving behind a temporary, continually disinfecting film with broad antimicrobial efficacy. NanoRAD will be the first residual disinfectant able to: (1) disinfect (99.9%) viruses and bacteria safely, (2) act continually in under an hour and (3) eradicate many microbes (no infectious units &gt;99.999%) by the 2-hour mark.     Our Phase I findings demonstrate that NanoRAD can provide safe, continuous virus and bacteria protection on surfaces it is applied to. We have shown:  1)    a new, specially engineered nanomaterial that demonstrated broad antimicrobial potency;  2)    the ability to formulate into a polymer to create an antimicrobial film on a surface;  3)     the ability for the film to be continually re-challenged;  4)     continuous and rapid disinfection that exceeds the EPA standard;  5)    no toxicity or irritation when the active ingredient is introduced to eye and skin cells  NanoRAD has broad and potent antimicrobial effect as a dry film on treated surfaces. From our test results, NanoRAD disinfects all viruses and bacteria it is challenged with in well under an hour and for most pathogens eradicates a full viral or bacterial within 2 hours.This level of performance for a dry nanomaterial, with the lack of irritation or toxicity for eye and skin cells is a remarkable feat that has the potential to drastically reduce HAIs and healthcare costs.                 Last Modified: 08/17/2022       Submitted by: Christina Drake]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
