<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[STTR Phase I:  Formulation of a COVID-19 mRNA Vaccine by Inverse Flash NanoPrecipitation]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>256000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>256000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Erik Pierstorff</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>epiersto@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922165</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this this Small Business Technology Transfer (STTR) Phase I project is the development of a novel messenger ribonucleic acid (mRNA)-based vaccine for COVID-19. The fastest-to-clinic vaccine for COVID-19 was mRNA-based; however, there are no mRNA-based vaccines on the market currently. This is, in part, because this class of vaccines is difficult to optimize and manufacture at a large scale. If clinical trials are successful, hundreds of millions of doses will be needed in the U.S. alone. This STTR project aims to pioneer a novel technique to manufacture mRNA-based vaccines initially for COVID-19. This technology is highly modular, allowing for the better understanding and optimization of this class of vaccines. Importantly, this new technique can be scaled to manufacture the doses needed both for the current COVID-19 pandemic and in the case of future outbreaks. The flexibility and scalability of this platform technology provide a durable competitive advantage. Following demonstration of preclinical efficacy, the company will work with an established pharmaceutical partner for testing and manufacturing. Capturing 5% of the U.S. COVID-19 vaccine market would bring an estimated $125 million in revenue. This is a beachhead market, and, once successful, the company will expand into other mRNA-based vaccine and therapeutic markets.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Technology Transfer (STTR) Phase I project aims to develop an mRNA-based nanoparticle vaccine for COVID-19 without the use of cationic materials. Current formulation methods require cationic lipids or polymers to form charge-based complexes with the anionic mRNA. Charge-based assembly limits the accessible nanoparticle surface chemistries, a feature crucial to directing which cell types will be transfected and the resulting immune response. Additionally, mRNA is only a minor component of the resulting formulations. The proposed formulation method decouples the mRNA encapsulation from the nanoparticle surface in a two-step process. The method does not require cationic materials, allowing for mRNA loadings up to 5-times higher than those achievable through other routes. However, mRNA transfection has not previously been demonstrated without the use of cationic materials. This will be achieved by completing three key milestones: (1) optimize mRNA encapsulation, (2) vary surface coatings to enhance dendritic cell uptake, and (3) demonstrate efficient cell transfection. A highly loaded nanoparticle formulation that can efficiently target and transfect dendritic cells is desired. Following the completion of this Phase I work, this formulation may be applied to a SARS-CoV-2 spike protein-coding mRNA to produce a COVID-19 vaccine.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/05/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/13/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2032023</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
<LastName>Prud'homme</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>K</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Robert K Prud'homme</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[prudhomm@phoenix.princeton.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000422820</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/05/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate>05/13/2021</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rodney</FirstName>
<LastName>Priestley</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Rodney D Priestley</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[rpriestl@princeton.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000569237</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/13/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
<LastName>Pagels</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Robert Pagels</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[rpagels@optimeos.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000779351</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/05/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Optimeos Life Sciences, Inc.</Name>
<CityName>PRINCETON</CityName>
<ZipCode>085427005</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6098655648</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>174 NASSAU ST STE 334</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NJ12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>LSBKUFPKAHW7</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OPTIMEOS LIFE SCIENCES, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Optimeos Life Sciences, Inc.]]></Name>
<CityName>Princeton</CityName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>085406608</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[303A College Rd E]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NJ12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1505</Code>
<Text>STTR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1982</Code>
<Text>BIOLOGICAL CHEMISTRY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8042</Code>
<Text>Health and Safety</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~256000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-faee06ea-7fff-79ce-17e0-0b752c3856e2"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Messenger RNA (mRNA) provides the cellular instructions for the production of proteins and enzymes, and thus has incredible therapeutic potential. For vaccine applications, mRNA encoding antigens specific to infectious agents are delivered to immune cells in order to train them to recognize and attack that pathogen. At the time this Phase I STTR application was submitted, no COVID-19 vaccines had been authorized, but it was clear that the mRNA-based vaccines developed by Moderna and Pfizer/BioNTech were progressing fastest in clinical testing. These vaccines depend on lipid nanoparticles (LNPs) to protect the mRNA from degradation, enable cellular uptake, and deliver it onto the cytosol where the antigen can be produced. LNP technology is limited by poor cell-specific targeting, low mRNA loadings, and dependency on cationic ionizable lipids for mRNA encapsulation and delivery.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The goal of this Phase I research project was to optimize Optimeos' nanoparticle manufacturing technology for mRNA encapsulation and delivery at higher mRNA loadings compared to LNPs. This goal was originally framed in the context of developing a COVID-19 vaccine; however, early in this Phase I research, the Moderna and Pfizer/BioNTech mRNA vaccines were authorized for emergency use. The success of these vaccines did not significantly change the research plan for this project, but did result in a pivot of the target application from vaccines to the delivery of mRNA encoding proteins that are missing due to genetic disease. LNPs have had limited success in addressing genetic diseases in large part because they initiate an immune response. This immune response is largely driven by the use of cationic ionizable materials, which is advantageous for vaccines, but detrimental in genetic disease applications.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The three key milestones of this Phase I research were to: (1) optimize mRNA encapsulation through solvent and salt-form choice, (2) impart varying surface coatings to enhance cellular uptake and demonstrate platform flexibility, and (3) demonstrate efficient mRNA transfection in cells. All three milestones were successfully accomplished. First, several mRNA salt forms were found to be suitable in Optimeos' process, with the choice of salt impacting the size of the final nanoparticles. Second, different surface coatings, including lipid- and polymer-based coatings, were successfully applied to the nanoparticles. These different coating compositions impact cellular uptake, and in the future may be used for tissue specific targeting. Finally, protein expression on par or up to 200% higher than that from a clinically validated LNP was demonstrated in vitro. Importantly, it was shown that Optimeos' formulation technology could produce nanoparticles loaded with 5x more mRNA than in traditional LNPs, and does not require any cationic ionizable materials to achieve high loadings and encapsulation efficiencies. All of these accomplishments are a significant advancement in the field of mRNA delivery and therapeutics.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>This Phase I research will have important broader impacts in the formulation of mRNA therapeutics. It is hypothesized that reducing or eliminating cationic ionizable materials from mRNA formulations will reduce the immune response generated by these therapeutics. This will extend the use of mRNA beyond vaccines to the treatment of genetic diseases, many of which currently have no viable treatments. The advancement and future commercialization of this technology will allow for new therapies that will improve the lives of patients living with genetic diseases and their caregivers.</span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/27/2022<br>      Modified by: Robert&nbsp;Pagels</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   Messenger RNA (mRNA) provides the cellular instructions for the production of proteins and enzymes, and thus has incredible therapeutic potential. For vaccine applications, mRNA encoding antigens specific to infectious agents are delivered to immune cells in order to train them to recognize and attack that pathogen. At the time this Phase I STTR application was submitted, no COVID-19 vaccines had been authorized, but it was clear that the mRNA-based vaccines developed by Moderna and Pfizer/BioNTech were progressing fastest in clinical testing. These vaccines depend on lipid nanoparticles (LNPs) to protect the mRNA from degradation, enable cellular uptake, and deliver it onto the cytosol where the antigen can be produced. LNP technology is limited by poor cell-specific targeting, low mRNA loadings, and dependency on cationic ionizable lipids for mRNA encapsulation and delivery.  The goal of this Phase I research project was to optimize Optimeos' nanoparticle manufacturing technology for mRNA encapsulation and delivery at higher mRNA loadings compared to LNPs. This goal was originally framed in the context of developing a COVID-19 vaccine; however, early in this Phase I research, the Moderna and Pfizer/BioNTech mRNA vaccines were authorized for emergency use. The success of these vaccines did not significantly change the research plan for this project, but did result in a pivot of the target application from vaccines to the delivery of mRNA encoding proteins that are missing due to genetic disease. LNPs have had limited success in addressing genetic diseases in large part because they initiate an immune response. This immune response is largely driven by the use of cationic ionizable materials, which is advantageous for vaccines, but detrimental in genetic disease applications. The three key milestones of this Phase I research were to: (1) optimize mRNA encapsulation through solvent and salt-form choice, (2) impart varying surface coatings to enhance cellular uptake and demonstrate platform flexibility, and (3) demonstrate efficient mRNA transfection in cells. All three milestones were successfully accomplished. First, several mRNA salt forms were found to be suitable in Optimeos' process, with the choice of salt impacting the size of the final nanoparticles. Second, different surface coatings, including lipid- and polymer-based coatings, were successfully applied to the nanoparticles. These different coating compositions impact cellular uptake, and in the future may be used for tissue specific targeting. Finally, protein expression on par or up to 200% higher than that from a clinically validated LNP was demonstrated in vitro. Importantly, it was shown that Optimeos' formulation technology could produce nanoparticles loaded with 5x more mRNA than in traditional LNPs, and does not require any cationic ionizable materials to achieve high loadings and encapsulation efficiencies. All of these accomplishments are a significant advancement in the field of mRNA delivery and therapeutics. This Phase I research will have important broader impacts in the formulation of mRNA therapeutics. It is hypothesized that reducing or eliminating cationic ionizable materials from mRNA formulations will reduce the immune response generated by these therapeutics. This will extend the use of mRNA beyond vaccines to the treatment of genetic diseases, many of which currently have no viable treatments. The advancement and future commercialization of this technology will allow for new therapies that will improve the lives of patients living with genetic diseases and their caregivers.       Last Modified: 05/27/2022       Submitted by: Robert Pagels]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
