<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Investigating the impact of online internships in the midst of the COVID-19 pandemic]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>145000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>145000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DGE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Graduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Earnestine Psalmonds</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>eeaster@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928112</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Researchers at the University of Wisconsin-Madison’s Center for Research on College-Workforce Transitions will partner with Parker Dewey to generate a robust mixed-methods dataset about the impact of online internships on student progression. Internships, mandated by many STEM academic programs, are a form of work-based learning that can lead to academic and workforce success for undergraduate and graduate students. Traditional face-to-face internships also can enhance students’ social networks and technical and transferrable  professional skills. However, the COVID-19 pandemic has made face-to-face internships untenable for many workplaces, with stay-at-home orders and social distancing requirements, resulting in a large influx of college students to vendors such as Parker Dewey seeking these opportunities.  However, there is little research on the quality of online or micro-internships, and higher education professionals have little knowledge about their students’ experiences with these new forms of work-based learning and their subsequent impact on students’ career and academic development. This study will fill this need by contributing both new empirical insights on online internships as well as actionable knowledge to inform faculty and career advisors’ decision making about students’ internship opportunities during and beyond the pandemic. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will examine the following research questions: (1) What are the demographic characteristics of past (2015 to early 2020) and current online interns? (2) What types of tasks and mentoring are experienced by online interns? (3) What is the impact of an online internship on student career and academic development, professional networks, and transferable skills? and, (4) What are the prospects for online internships to adopt innovations in virtual simulations to enhance the internship experience? These questions will be answered through three distinct yet inter-related studies that include analyses of Parker Dewey’s past student participants (n=1,500), surveys (n=2,500) and interviews (n=50) with current Parker Dewey program participants, and interviews with employers in STEM-related fields (n=25) regarding the format of internship programs amidst the COVID-19 pandemic. Thus, the research leverages the strengths of large-scale survey data and the more fine-grained “insider” perspective of qualitative data. The study will be the first empirical study of online internships and represents a significant contribution to the fields of experiential learning and workforce development. Given the likelihood that online internships and some form of social distancing will continue, generating rapid scientifically rigorous findings on this topic is a time-sensitive concern for U.S. higher education. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This RAPID award is made by the EHR Core Research (ECR) program in the Division of Graduate Education/Directorate of Education and Human Resources, using funds from the Coronavirus Aid, Relief, and Economic Security (CARES) Act. ECR supports fundamental research focused on STEM learning and learning environments, broadening participation in STEM, and STEM workforce development.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/20/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/20/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2032122</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Matthew</FirstName>
<LastName>Hora</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>T</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Matthew T Hora</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[hora@wisc.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000465017</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/20/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Wisconsin-Madison</Name>
<CityName>MADISON</CityName>
<ZipCode>537151218</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6082623822</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>21 N PARK ST STE 6301</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>LCLSJAGTNZQ7</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF WISCONSIN SYSTEM</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>QAFKGG7YY396</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[The Board of Regents of the University of Wisconsin System]]></Name>
<CityName>MADISON</CityName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>537151218</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[21 N. Park St., Ste. 6401]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7980</Code>
<Text>ECR-EDU Core Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8816</Code>
<Text>Workforce Development</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>4N20</Code>
<Name>EHR CARES Act DEFC N</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>040N2021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[EHR CARES Act DEFC N]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~145000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The goals of this project were to generate a robust mixed-methods  dataset about online internships and how college students experienced  them during the COVID-19 pandemic.&nbsp; Our hopes for this project were that the  results from the study wiould contribute both new empirical insights on  online internships as well as actionable knowledge that faculty and career advisors can draw upon when making decisions  about their students internship opportunities in the future.</p> <p>The research design used for this study is a multi-site case study, with three distinct cases: (1) two independent websites that provide online internship<br />networking platforms (OINP) for students seeking online internships and employers seeking student interns, (2) 11 colleges and universities, and (3) a single employer-hosted online internship program at TreeHouse Foods.</p> <p>Key findings include:</p> <dl class="clearing"><dd> <div class="tinyMCEContent" style="text-align: left;"> <ul> </ul> <strong>Finding #1: </strong>Internship participation was rather low during  the COVID-19 pandemic, with interns roughly split 50/50 between online  and in-person modalities. Of the 9,964 students from 11 campuses  answering our survey from the NSCI, one of the biggest findings is the  large number of students (77.9%, n=7,761) who did not take an  internship. Of the 22.1% (n=2,203) students who did take one, our key  finding is that 45.3% (n=993) had taken an online internship, with 47.6%  (n=1,044) having had an in-person experience.&nbsp; These finding indicate  that overall participation in internships during the pandemic was rather  low, with only 1 in 5 students successfully completing an internship.        <ul> </ul> <div class="tinyMCEContent" style="text-align: left;"><strong>Finding #2: Online internship networking platforms (OINPs) play an  important role in the ecosystem of internship opportunities, but during  the pandemic student demand outstripped the supply of available  positions. </strong>Another key finding pertained to the role that OINPs  played during the pandemic, with some arguing that they would fill an  important gap in providing access to online positions as in-person  positions were widely cancelled. Our data indicate, however, that while  OINPs did play an important role in the internship ecosystem and served  the needs of many students, there were more students registering with  these platforms than there were positions available for them.&nbsp;</div> <ul> </ul> <div class="tinyMCEContent" style="text-align: left;"><strong>Finding #3: Online interns in our sample tended to be  continuing-generation, have higher GPAs, come from upper-income  families, and were non-STEM majors. </strong>Our data indicate that the  demographics of students pursuing online internships varied  significantly along variables such as first-generation  status, grade point average, family income, major, race and gender. For those engaged in supporting  STEM education such as the National Science Foundation, these data  highlight the fact that online internships are currently not a feasible  option for STEM students.&nbsp; This situation may be due to the hands-on  nature of work in these disciplines and/or the predominance of Business  and non-STEM employers offering remote positions.</div> <ul> </ul> <div class="tinyMCEContent" style="text-align: left;"><strong>Finding #4: Online internships do not appear to solve the access and equity problem. </strong>For  some observers online internships have the potential to solve the  equity problem in the internship world, where unpaid  positions have excluded low-income or working students, too many  positions are available only through social networks, and geographically  isolated students have been unable to access positions located in large  urban areas.&nbsp; However, our data suggest that online interns are  predominantly from upper- and middle-income backgrounds (75.8%, n=634)  and that there are more unpaid online than in-person internships (42%  versus 34.9% unpaid).</div> <ul> </ul> <div class="tinyMCEContent" style="text-align: left;"><strong>Finding #5: Online interns report lower satisfaction,  developmental value, 21st century skills, professional network  development, and high-skill tasks than in-person interns. </strong>Our data indicate  that online interns have significantly lower level of satisfaction with  their experience, lower scores for both academic and developmental  value, lower level of acquiring new 21<sup>st</sup> century skills, and  less growth of professional networks than students pursuing in-person  internships.&nbsp; &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</div> <ul> </ul> <div class="tinyMCEContent" style="text-align: left;"><strong>Finding #6: Future online internships must pay especially close attention to task design, supervision and communication. </strong>Based  on data from both our surveys and interviews with students, it is clear  that while all internship providers (and their academic advisor  counterparts) need to pay close attention to the quality of task design,  supervision and communication, these issues are especially lacking in  some online internships.&nbsp;</div> <ul> </ul> <div class="tinyMCEContent" style="text-align: left;"><strong>Finding #7: Support services and training will need to be provided  to many employers (and academic advisors) regarding how to design and  implement an effective online internship.</strong> One of the primary  conclusions we can draw from the data collected for this study is that  while online internships are likely a permanent part of the ecosystem of  experiential learning for college students, and a potential answer to  some vexing issues related to equitable access, they remain a work in  progress.&nbsp; While not all organizations will be able to offer positions  like those featured by TreeHouse Foods, the goal for all online  internships should be to offer experiences that comply with NACE  standards, the principles of the Internship Scorecard and key elements  of effective remote work and digital learning.</div> <ul> </ul> </div> </dd></dl><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/26/2022<br>      Modified by: Matthew&nbsp;T&nbsp;Hora</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2032122/2032122_10671844_1651011520091_OnlineInternshipReportInfographic(4)[71]--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2032122/2032122_10671844_1651011520091_OnlineInternshipReportInfographic(4)[71]--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Online internship infographic"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2032122/2032122_10671844_1651011520091_OnlineInternshipReportInfographic(4)[71]--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Online internship infographic"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Summary of key findings from CCWT study of online internships</div> <div class="imageCredit">Matthew T Hora, Ryan Marks</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Matthew&nbsp;T&nbsp;Hora</div> <div class="imageTitle">Online internship infographic</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The goals of this project were to generate a robust mixed-methods  dataset about online internships and how college students experienced  them during the COVID-19 pandemic.  Our hopes for this project were that the  results from the study wiould contribute both new empirical insights on  online internships as well as actionable knowledge that faculty and career advisors can draw upon when making decisions  about their students internship opportunities in the future.  The research design used for this study is a multi-site case study, with three distinct cases: (1) two independent websites that provide online internship networking platforms (OINP) for students seeking online internships and employers seeking student interns, (2) 11 colleges and universities, and (3) a single employer-hosted online internship program at TreeHouse Foods.  Key findings include:     Finding #1: Internship participation was rather low during  the COVID-19 pandemic, with interns roughly split 50/50 between online  and in-person modalities. Of the 9,964 students from 11 campuses  answering our survey from the NSCI, one of the biggest findings is the  large number of students (77.9%, n=7,761) who did not take an  internship. Of the 22.1% (n=2,203) students who did take one, our key  finding is that 45.3% (n=993) had taken an online internship, with 47.6%  (n=1,044) having had an in-person experience.  These finding indicate  that overall participation in internships during the pandemic was rather  low, with only 1 in 5 students successfully completing an internship.          Finding #2: Online internship networking platforms (OINPs) play an  important role in the ecosystem of internship opportunities, but during  the pandemic student demand outstripped the supply of available  positions. Another key finding pertained to the role that OINPs  played during the pandemic, with some arguing that they would fill an  important gap in providing access to online positions as in-person  positions were widely cancelled. Our data indicate, however, that while  OINPs did play an important role in the internship ecosystem and served  the needs of many students, there were more students registering with  these platforms than there were positions available for them.    Finding #3: Online interns in our sample tended to be  continuing-generation, have higher GPAs, come from upper-income  families, and were non-STEM majors. Our data indicate that the  demographics of students pursuing online internships varied  significantly along variables such as first-generation  status, grade point average, family income, major, race and gender. For those engaged in supporting  STEM education such as the National Science Foundation, these data  highlight the fact that online internships are currently not a feasible  option for STEM students.  This situation may be due to the hands-on  nature of work in these disciplines and/or the predominance of Business  and non-STEM employers offering remote positions.   Finding #4: Online internships do not appear to solve the access and equity problem. For  some observers online internships have the potential to solve the  equity problem in the internship world, where unpaid  positions have excluded low-income or working students, too many  positions are available only through social networks, and geographically  isolated students have been unable to access positions located in large  urban areas.  However, our data suggest that online interns are  predominantly from upper- and middle-income backgrounds (75.8%, n=634)  and that there are more unpaid online than in-person internships (42%  versus 34.9% unpaid).   Finding #5: Online interns report lower satisfaction,  developmental value, 21st century skills, professional network  development, and high-skill tasks than in-person interns. Our data indicate  that online interns have significantly lower level of satisfaction with  their experience, lower scores for both academic and developmental  value, lower level of acquiring new 21st century skills, and  less growth of professional networks than students pursuing in-person  internships.                Finding #6: Future online internships must pay especially close attention to task design, supervision and communication. Based  on data from both our surveys and interviews with students, it is clear  that while all internship providers (and their academic advisor  counterparts) need to pay close attention to the quality of task design,  supervision and communication, these issues are especially lacking in  some online internships.    Finding #7: Support services and training will need to be provided  to many employers (and academic advisors) regarding how to design and  implement an effective online internship. One of the primary  conclusions we can draw from the data collected for this study is that  while online internships are likely a permanent part of the ecosystem of  experiential learning for college students, and a potential answer to  some vexing issues related to equitable access, they remain a work in  progress.  While not all organizations will be able to offer positions  like those featured by TreeHouse Foods, the goal for all online  internships should be to offer experiences that comply with NACE  standards, the principles of the Internship Scorecard and key elements  of effective remote work and digital learning.           Last Modified: 04/26/2022       Submitted by: Matthew T Hora]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
