<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: New Models for Online Social Experiences Supporting Immediate Needs of NSF REU students, Conferences and the Advancement of Remote Research]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>100005.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>100005</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Balakrishnan Prabhakaran</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The Covid-19 pandemic has dramatically impacted how and where work may take place, creating a profound demand for technologies and strategies supporting remote work and education.  While video conferencing and chat applications have been a great help during this time, their limitations have also become clear. This project explores how 3D virtual worlds can recreate the advantages of being in shared office and learning environments: awareness of the work of your colleagues or fellow students, a sense of being part of a shared community, and opportunities for impromptu interactions. The project promotes the design and development of more resilient work and learning environments by advancing knowledge of how 3D and virtual reality technologies enable people to connect and collaborate at a distance, simulating the physical constraints that naturally create social situations that are vital to  the emergence and diffusion of new ideas and professional networks. This project will study how 3D and virtual reality technologies may be effective at recreating the positive aspects of physical conditions of the real world, while allowing for social interaction to be more convenient and efficient than video or chat technologies. The project will also study how virtual reality technologies promote diversity and inclusion by reducing barriers to remote participation.      &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Virtual worlds technology will be used to support key social interactions of current and future scientists in three areas. First, the project will support a network of undergraduate research students over the summer as a starting point for exploring more regular sharing of research progress and community building, by situating ongoing research artifacts in virtual worlds to stimulate conversation as well as co-construction and review of the research products. The project will explore ongoing informal collaboration as well as formal presentations. Second, it will leverage work completed over the summer for exploring new approaches to online and multi-site models of conferencing in the fall. Third, it will build on both of these projects and previous work to support and study the transition of a major academic conference to an online or hybrid form. Throughout, the 3D and virtual reality technology will be systematically studied and advanced through feedback from participants and partnership with industry that can scale these approaches globally.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/29/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/29/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2032474</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sun Joo</FirstName>
<LastName>Ahn</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sun Joo Ahn</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[sjahn@uga.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000639396</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/29/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kyle</FirstName>
<LastName>Johnsen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kyle Johnsen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[kjohnsen@uga.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000582583</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/29/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Blair</FirstName>
<LastName>MacIntyre</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Blair MacIntyre</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[blair@cc.gatech.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000180260</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/29/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Georgia Research Foundation Inc</Name>
<CityName>ATHENS</CityName>
<ZipCode>306021589</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7065425939</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>310 E CAMPUS RD RM 409</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NMJHD63STRC5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF GEORGIA RESEARCH FOUNDATION, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Georgia]]></Name>
<CityName>Athens</CityName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>306021589</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[310 East Campus Rd.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7367</Code>
<Text>HCC-Human-Centered Computing</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7367</Code>
<Text>Cyber-Human Systems</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~100005</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-3795c994-7fff-2512-c3f7-7a91d9bd9642">&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The primary aim of this project was to determine how virtual worlds can enable effective social interactions during remote research, especially those forced by the Covid-19 pandemic.&nbsp; In pursuit of this aim, the project built new tools and extended existing tools for remote research collaborations, provided support in using such tools to to academic research partners.&nbsp; These experiences were studied through the lens of ethnographic research methods, where researchers were embedded into the social gatherings and conducted interviews of participants to better understand how tools were being used and what aspects were contributing to successful outcomes.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Our partners included several academic organizations (IEEE VR/ISMAR, ACM SUI/VRST and the International Communication Association) as well as two undergraduate research experiences, one at Georgia Tech and one at the University of Puerto Rico (NSF-funded Bio-IQ program).&nbsp; In the first year of the project, a primary focus was helping these programs use 3D virtual worlds, such as Mozilla Hubs and VirBela to support social engagement at research meetings.&nbsp; A key finding from studying these integrations was that participants did not favor the use of 3D virtual worlds and especially immersive virtual reality headset interfaces due to the difficulty of using them as a primary interface, especially when the majority of others were not using them.&nbsp;&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>As a result, the second year of the project focused on how to modify and design tools to make better use of immersive virtual reality in these experiences.&nbsp; In summer of 2021, we supported the Bio-IQ program again by sending virtual reality headsets to all participants (10) and (3) instructors distributed throughout the United States, providing a meeting application and encouraging their use for social engagements.&nbsp; This approach yielded the primary finding that while participants used the headsets extensively to engage with each other, their primary use case was social (e.g. play immersive games), despite the availability of more work-oriented products and an interest in using virtual reality for research.&nbsp;&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The project also resulted in contributions to the Mozilla Hubs open source product, as well as the creation and initial deployment of open source VR networking components that enable self-hosted virtual worlds.&nbsp; These were developed by undergraduate research assistants, and they have been made available through GitHub and are under active development and use.&nbsp;</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/26/2022<br>      Modified by: Kyle&nbsp;Johnsen</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   The primary aim of this project was to determine how virtual worlds can enable effective social interactions during remote research, especially those forced by the Covid-19 pandemic.  In pursuit of this aim, the project built new tools and extended existing tools for remote research collaborations, provided support in using such tools to to academic research partners.  These experiences were studied through the lens of ethnographic research methods, where researchers were embedded into the social gatherings and conducted interviews of participants to better understand how tools were being used and what aspects were contributing to successful outcomes. Our partners included several academic organizations (IEEE VR/ISMAR, ACM SUI/VRST and the International Communication Association) as well as two undergraduate research experiences, one at Georgia Tech and one at the University of Puerto Rico (NSF-funded Bio-IQ program).  In the first year of the project, a primary focus was helping these programs use 3D virtual worlds, such as Mozilla Hubs and VirBela to support social engagement at research meetings.  A key finding from studying these integrations was that participants did not favor the use of 3D virtual worlds and especially immersive virtual reality headset interfaces due to the difficulty of using them as a primary interface, especially when the majority of others were not using them.   As a result, the second year of the project focused on how to modify and design tools to make better use of immersive virtual reality in these experiences.  In summer of 2021, we supported the Bio-IQ program again by sending virtual reality headsets to all participants (10) and (3) instructors distributed throughout the United States, providing a meeting application and encouraging their use for social engagements.  This approach yielded the primary finding that while participants used the headsets extensively to engage with each other, their primary use case was social (e.g. play immersive games), despite the availability of more work-oriented products and an interest in using virtual reality for research.   The project also resulted in contributions to the Mozilla Hubs open source product, as well as the creation and initial deployment of open source VR networking components that enable self-hosted virtual worlds.  These were developed by undergraduate research assistants, and they have been made available through GitHub and are under active development and use.              Last Modified: 10/26/2022       Submitted by: Kyle Johnsen]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
