<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Supporting Responsible Action through COVID-19 Education]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>112004.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>112004</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ellen Carpenter</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>elcarpen@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925104</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[In response to the COVID-19 pandemic, U.S. citizens are balancing information from many sources to make crucial decisions such as whether to wear a mask or whether to practice social distancing.  In making their decisions, people need to distinguish legitimate scientific information from pervasive misinformation and pseudoscience.  Such misinformation promotes public distrust in science and affects decisions of individuals and groups, potentially placing everyone at greater risk.  This project seeks to determine how people think about and respond to COVID-19 information and to develop educational materials that will prepare people to respond effectively to an anticipated second wave of COVID-19.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Focusing specifically on undergraduate students enrolled in large introductory biology courses at Texas A&amp;M University, this project intends to: (1) determine how undergraduate students’ risk perceptions and decision-making regarding COVID-19 relate to their perceptions and understanding of science and sociocultural characteristics; (2) create data-driven instructional materials that promote understanding of the severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2), COVID-19 disease, and how science works, and that can also support personal and public health decision-making regarding the COVID-19 pandemic and the expected second wave; and (3) generate knowledge regarding the impacts of the instructional materials on undergraduate students’ conceptions regarding science content, the nature of science, confidence in science, and personal decision-making and behaviors regarding the COVID-19 pandemic. Knowledge generation will entail a sequential mixed methods quasi-experimental approach with emergent design flexibility to investigate the thinking and decision-making of post-secondary students regarding the COVID-19 pandemic, and the implications for development of effective instructional materials. Determining the efficacy of the instructional materials will entail dividing introductory biology students across three groups. The first group will experience instruction about viruses through typical biology undergraduate curricular experiences. The second group will receive the same in-class instruction as the first group, but their out-of-class work will be replaced with the COVID-19 on-line instructional materials developed in this project. The third group will experience an in-class case study regarding the anticipated COVID-19 second wave along with the out-of-class COVID-19 on-line project materials. Project materials and research will be widely distributed, ensuring that the impact of the project products and outcomes will broadly promote STEM knowledge, how it is developed, acceptance of STEM results, and more informed and appropriate personal and public policy decision-making.  This RAPID award is made by the Improving Undergraduate STEM Education (IUSE) program in the Division of Undergraduate Education: Education and Human Resources Directorate.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/15/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/21/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2032737</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Clough</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael P Clough</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mclough@tamu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000389480</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/15/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Benjamin</FirstName>
<LastName>Herman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Benjamin Herman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[bcherman@tamu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000574695</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/15/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Asha</FirstName>
<LastName>Rao</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Asha Rao</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[arao@bio.tamu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000746418</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/15/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Texas A&amp;M University</Name>
<CityName>COLLEGE STATION</CityName>
<ZipCode>778454375</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9798626777</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>400 HARVEY MITCHELL PKY S STE 30</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>JF6XLNB4CDJ5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TEXAS A &amp; M UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>HH6VX5XDL284</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Texas A&M University]]></Name>
<CityName>College Station</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>778434232</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4232 TAMU]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1998</Code>
<Text>IUSE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8209</Code>
<Text>Improv Undergrad STEM Ed(IUSE)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0420</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~112004</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This NSF DUE RAPID project created and investigated the impact of educational materials designed to promote research-based responsible action regarding the COVID-19 pandemic. Pervasive misinformation and pseudoscience thinking exist among the public regarding COVID-19 that promotes ill-informed and dangerous personal and societal decision-making. Our project developed data driven pedagogical curriculum materials that promote understanding of how science works and why the knowledge produced by the scientific community can be trusted in public and personal decision-making regarding the COVID-19 pandemic.</p> <p>The project's <span style="text-decoration: underline;">intellectual merit</span> is evident in the widespread COVID-19 misinformation and disinformation that places all of society at greater risk. Our project, in the midst of a raging global pandemic: (a) investigated citizen's thinking, emotions, and actions during the pandemic; and then (b) created data-driven COVID-19 education materials designed to promote accurate understanding of how science works and trust in the science-based health recommendations. Research involved 2,500 undergraduate biology students and focused on: 1) determining how undergraduate students' risk perceptions and decisions regarding COVID-19 related to their perceptions of science and sociocultural characteristics regarding their COVID-19 views and actions; and 2) the impacts of the project instructional materials on undergraduate students' conceptions regarding science content, the nature of science, trust in science, and personal decision-making and behaviors (e.g., masking practices, vaccination intent) regarding the pandemic. Salient findings of this research include that:</p> <ul> <li>higher levels of personal actions and support for societal measures that mitigates COVID-19 were strongly positively associated with holding more accurate views regarding COVID-19 spread prevention and misinformation/disinformation, and holding liberal, as opposed to conservative, political orientations. </li> <li>trust in the Centers for Disease Control (CDC) to provide the scientific consensus view and understanding of the emerging nature of COVID-19 science (e.g., COVID-19 scientific models) and its role in guiding policy and response was also associated with the students' personal actions and support for societal measures that mitigates COVID-19. However, these associations were moderated by the students' political orientations. More specifically, trust in the CDC and COVID-19 science models was not a significant positive predictor of liberal and very liberal student groups' actions and support for policies that mitigate COVID-19, but were a significant predictor of the actions and policy support of more politically conservative students. </li> <li>undergraduate biology students experiencing the project instructional materials consisting of COVID-19 science and pseudoscience stories in addition to COVID-19 content instruction demonstrated significantly more accurate nature of science views (e.g., trust in science for decision-making despite its revisionary character) than their peers experiencing just COVID-19 content instruction.</li> </ul> <p>The project's <span style="text-decoration: underline;">broader impacts</span> include:</p> <ul> <li>The creation and widespread dissemination of instructional and instructional assistance materials that promote understanding of SARS-CoV-2, COVID-19 disease, how science is often misrepresented, and how science works and why it should be trusted for making more appropriate COVID-19 decisions.</li> <li>Widespread dissemination of the freely-available and easily accessed COVID-19 education materials (<a href="https://www.storybehindthescience.org/covid19.html">https://www.storybehindthescience.org/covid19.html</a>) for post-secondary science courses, informal science education efforts, and public use.</li> <li>Increasing knowledge of public perceptions and attitudes toward science in the midst of socioscientific issues, and how to bolster understanding of and attitudes toward science-based decision-making.</li> </ul> <p>Project outcomes have been reported through a multitude of professional venues to include: two presentations at international conferences (spring 2021), two international conference presentation proposals (for spring 2022), one manuscript currently under review (submitted spring 2021), and five additional manuscripts in preparation for submission to reputable peer-reviewed journals. Dissemination efforts have also included the American Association for the Advancement of Science (AAAS) Member Community, International History and Philosophy of Science and Science Teaching (IHPS&amp;ST) Newsletter that goes to approximately 8,000 individuals, Association for Science Teacher Education (ASTE) Newsletter and listserv, and NARST listserv.</p> <p>We are grateful to receive public support for our work and take seriously the responsibility to judiciously use such funding for the common welfare of the public. The outcomes of our ?RAPID: Supporting Responsible Action through COVID-19 Education? project met and or exceeded what we put forward in our proposal, and we are continuing this work to serve the public good.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/06/2021<br>      Modified by: Benjamin&nbsp;Herman</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This NSF DUE RAPID project created and investigated the impact of educational materials designed to promote research-based responsible action regarding the COVID-19 pandemic. Pervasive misinformation and pseudoscience thinking exist among the public regarding COVID-19 that promotes ill-informed and dangerous personal and societal decision-making. Our project developed data driven pedagogical curriculum materials that promote understanding of how science works and why the knowledge produced by the scientific community can be trusted in public and personal decision-making regarding the COVID-19 pandemic.  The project's intellectual merit is evident in the widespread COVID-19 misinformation and disinformation that places all of society at greater risk. Our project, in the midst of a raging global pandemic: (a) investigated citizen's thinking, emotions, and actions during the pandemic; and then (b) created data-driven COVID-19 education materials designed to promote accurate understanding of how science works and trust in the science-based health recommendations. Research involved 2,500 undergraduate biology students and focused on: 1) determining how undergraduate students' risk perceptions and decisions regarding COVID-19 related to their perceptions of science and sociocultural characteristics regarding their COVID-19 views and actions; and 2) the impacts of the project instructional materials on undergraduate students' conceptions regarding science content, the nature of science, trust in science, and personal decision-making and behaviors (e.g., masking practices, vaccination intent) regarding the pandemic. Salient findings of this research include that:  higher levels of personal actions and support for societal measures that mitigates COVID-19 were strongly positively associated with holding more accurate views regarding COVID-19 spread prevention and misinformation/disinformation, and holding liberal, as opposed to conservative, political orientations.  trust in the Centers for Disease Control (CDC) to provide the scientific consensus view and understanding of the emerging nature of COVID-19 science (e.g., COVID-19 scientific models) and its role in guiding policy and response was also associated with the students' personal actions and support for societal measures that mitigates COVID-19. However, these associations were moderated by the students' political orientations. More specifically, trust in the CDC and COVID-19 science models was not a significant positive predictor of liberal and very liberal student groups' actions and support for policies that mitigate COVID-19, but were a significant predictor of the actions and policy support of more politically conservative students.  undergraduate biology students experiencing the project instructional materials consisting of COVID-19 science and pseudoscience stories in addition to COVID-19 content instruction demonstrated significantly more accurate nature of science views (e.g., trust in science for decision-making despite its revisionary character) than their peers experiencing just COVID-19 content instruction.   The project's broader impacts include:  The creation and widespread dissemination of instructional and instructional assistance materials that promote understanding of SARS-CoV-2, COVID-19 disease, how science is often misrepresented, and how science works and why it should be trusted for making more appropriate COVID-19 decisions. Widespread dissemination of the freely-available and easily accessed COVID-19 education materials (https://www.storybehindthescience.org/covid19.html) for post-secondary science courses, informal science education efforts, and public use. Increasing knowledge of public perceptions and attitudes toward science in the midst of socioscientific issues, and how to bolster understanding of and attitudes toward science-based decision-making.   Project outcomes have been reported through a multitude of professional venues to include: two presentations at international conferences (spring 2021), two international conference presentation proposals (for spring 2022), one manuscript currently under review (submitted spring 2021), and five additional manuscripts in preparation for submission to reputable peer-reviewed journals. Dissemination efforts have also included the American Association for the Advancement of Science (AAAS) Member Community, International History and Philosophy of Science and Science Teaching (IHPS&amp;ST) Newsletter that goes to approximately 8,000 individuals, Association for Science Teacher Education (ASTE) Newsletter and listserv, and NARST listserv.  We are grateful to receive public support for our work and take seriously the responsibility to judiciously use such funding for the common welfare of the public. The outcomes of our ?RAPID: Supporting Responsible Action through COVID-19 Education? project met and or exceeded what we put forward in our proposal, and we are continuing this work to serve the public good.          Last Modified: 09/06/2021       Submitted by: Benjamin Herman]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
