<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>RAPID: Biomimicry of SARS-CoV-2 and its consequences for infectivity and inflammation</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>200000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>200000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>MCB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Steve Clouse</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sclouse@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928440</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This research addresses two critically important questions concerning the severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2), the virus that causes the novel coronavirus disease (COVID-19):  Why is this virus so infectious, and why does it sometimes cause lethal inflammation? It is now well-known that COVID-19 infections can spread from hosts early, before onset of symptoms, which implies efficient viral entry and egress. The root causes of COVID-19 induced inflammation are less known, but cognate effects have been seen in other superviruses such as the coronavirus for the original severe acute respiratory syndrome (SARS), and the 1918 pandemic influenza virus. This research investigates the basic molecular mechanisms of how parts of this virus can mimic the functions of defensive molecules from the human innate immune system which restructure membranes and control inflammation, thereby allowing the virus to achieve both of the above effects. The multidisciplinary nature of the research will also provide training opportunities for students at multiple levels.&lt;br/&gt;  &lt;br/&gt;The overall goal of this project is to perform basic research that may help mitigate the current COVID-19 crisis by using artificial intelligence informed fundamental biophysics, immunology, and virology.  The project objectives are two-fold. 1: use machine learning methods to identify molecules encoded in the genome of the SARS-CoV-2 virus that remodel the membrane for viral entry and viral shedding, and design ways to turn off this activity by mimicking molecules found in bats, which harbor many coronaviruses and therefore have more evolved defenses against them. 2: Identify molecules from the SARS-CoV-2 virus that mimic molecules from the human innate immune system which are known to mediate potent inflammatory responses, thus allowing potential downstream design of molecular approaches to alleviate this type of inflammation.  These ideas will be tested using small angle x-ray scattering (SAXS) experiments performed at state-of-the-art 3rd generation synchrotron radiation facilities in the US, as well as traditional immunological and antiviral experiments, including those done at high containment biosafety level 3 facilities designed to handle SARS-CoV-2. Expected results from this basic research project can provide translational guidance for design of COVID-19 treatment strategies, even if current vaccine candidates fail.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;This RAPID award is made by the Cellular Dynamics and Function Program in the Division of Molecular and Cellular Biosciences, using funds from the Coronavirus Aid, Relief, and Economic Security (CARES) Act.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/09/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/09/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2032310</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gerard</FirstName>
<LastName>Wong</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gerard Wong</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>gclwong@seas.ucla.edu</EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000444957</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/09/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Los Angeles</Name>
<CityName>LOS ANGELES</CityName>
<ZipCode>900951406</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3107940102</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>10889 Wilshire Boulevard</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 700]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>33</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA33</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>092530369</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, LOS ANGELES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Los Angeles]]></Name>
<CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>900951600</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[420 Westwood Plaza, ENG V]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>33</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA33</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>158Y</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7465</Code>
<Text>NANOSCALE BIO CORE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>1N20</Code>
<Name>R&amp;RA CARES Act DEFC N</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>010N2021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[R&RA CARES Act DEFC N]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~200000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The most lethal consequence of COVID-19 is severe inflammation. It is not known how such inflammation is caused by SARS-CoV-2, the virus behind COVID-19, or why disease outcomes range from having no symptoms at one extreme to death at the other extreme. In this project, we learned that SARS-CoV-2 viral fragments have profound effects on uninfected, healthy cells: Such fragments are capable of mimicking peptide molecules from our own innate immune systems, resulting in a grossly distorted immune response.&nbsp; We used artificial intelligence methods to identify sequences in the SARS-CoV-2 genome that amplify inflammation, and find mimics of host antimicrobial peptides (xenoAMPs) in the spike and other viral components. We show using synchrotron small angle x-ray scattering (SAXS) that these xenoAMPs can chaperone and organize nucleic acid ligands into ordered complexes that drastically activate Toll-Like Receptors, in a manner cognate to the role of AMPs in lupus and rheumatoid arthritis, both autoimmune diseases. SARS-CoV-2 xenoAMP-dsRNA complexes trigger high levels of signaling molecules called cytokines in a broad range of cell types, including IL-6 and IL-8, which are both cytokines upregulated in severe COVID patients.&nbsp; Likewise, in collaborative work with other labs, we found that delivery of complexes to mice leads to elevated blood levels IL-6 and CXCL1, especially in the lung. This is significant since CXCL1 is known to recruit immune cells called neutrophils, which has been correlated to acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS), one of the ways in which COVID kills. Stimulation of dermal microvascular endothelial cells by such complexes also lead to increased IL-6 production, a common precursor of skin inflammation and a potential driver of COVID skin lesions, which are commonly referred to as ?COVID fingers?.&nbsp; Taken together, these results suggest an unanticipated origin of a broad range of COVID derived pathologies, such as severe inflammation, especially in the lung, and skin lesions, including potentially Multi-system Inflammatory Syndrome in Children (MIS-C).</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/24/2021<br>      Modified by: Gerard&nbsp;Wong</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The most lethal consequence of COVID-19 is severe inflammation. It is not known how such inflammation is caused by SARS-CoV-2, the virus behind COVID-19, or why disease outcomes range from having no symptoms at one extreme to death at the other extreme. In this project, we learned that SARS-CoV-2 viral fragments have profound effects on uninfected, healthy cells: Such fragments are capable of mimicking peptide molecules from our own innate immune systems, resulting in a grossly distorted immune response.  We used artificial intelligence methods to identify sequences in the SARS-CoV-2 genome that amplify inflammation, and find mimics of host antimicrobial peptides (xenoAMPs) in the spike and other viral components. We show using synchrotron small angle x-ray scattering (SAXS) that these xenoAMPs can chaperone and organize nucleic acid ligands into ordered complexes that drastically activate Toll-Like Receptors, in a manner cognate to the role of AMPs in lupus and rheumatoid arthritis, both autoimmune diseases. SARS-CoV-2 xenoAMP-dsRNA complexes trigger high levels of signaling molecules called cytokines in a broad range of cell types, including IL-6 and IL-8, which are both cytokines upregulated in severe COVID patients.  Likewise, in collaborative work with other labs, we found that delivery of complexes to mice leads to elevated blood levels IL-6 and CXCL1, especially in the lung. This is significant since CXCL1 is known to recruit immune cells called neutrophils, which has been correlated to acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS), one of the ways in which COVID kills. Stimulation of dermal microvascular endothelial cells by such complexes also lead to increased IL-6 production, a common precursor of skin inflammation and a potential driver of COVID skin lesions, which are commonly referred to as ?COVID fingers?.  Taken together, these results suggest an unanticipated origin of a broad range of COVID derived pathologies, such as severe inflammation, especially in the lung, and skin lesions, including potentially Multi-system Inflammatory Syndrome in Children (MIS-C).       Last Modified: 12/24/2021       Submitted by: Gerard Wong]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
