<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Using Real Life COVID-19 data to teach quantititative reasoning skills to undergraduate Hispanic STEM students]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>199978.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>199978</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div. of Equity for Excellence in STEM</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Elsa Gonzalez</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>elgonzal@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924690</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The Hispanic-Serving Institutions Program supports RAPID projects when there is a severe urgency with regard to availability of, or access to, data, facilities or specialized equipment, including quick-response research on natural or anthropogenic disasters and similar unanticipated events, such as the COVID-19 pandemic. The project at Laredo Community College, a two-year institution, seeks to investigate the effectiveness of using a fully-virtual undergraduate research format to enhance quantitative reasoning and literacy while promoting student persistence during a pandemic of COVID-19. Additionally, this project seeks to promote faculty development in guiding undergraduate research at a community college and in an online learning environment.  This work will include collecting and monitoring data on the rate of infection of the COVID-19 in high-poverty rural communities in Laredo thus increasing the diversity of the data available to scientists. The project may shed light on inequities that have occurred as learning has transitioned to fully-virtual formats and may provide targeted strategies for engaging and encouraging groups historically underrepresented in STEM to degree completion. Students and faculty comprise a two-tier model where the former conduct research on COVID-19 in their communities and the latter examine how these students learn in this setting; this structure may serve as a model for other rural community colleges. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;By gathering data from the COVID-19 spread in Laredo, this project can be an opportunity to use data to study, to learn, and to prepare for the future, an important component of resiliency. The unique data elements will only exist at this time.  An undergraduate research experience will be designed and implemented around data analysis utilizing existing COVID-19 data resources.  Students will increase their quantitative reasoning knowledge base, skills set, and confidence level by gathering, interpreting, analyzing data, and drawing conclusions based on numerical evidence, and communicating this information to others.  Faculty involved in the project will also gain a quantitative reasoning-focused professional development opportunity. The impact on faculty development for delivering research content material and guiding research virtually as well as students’ transitions into four-year institutions and quantitative reasoning ability will be evaluated. The proposal also includes plans for communicating results virtually throughout the college, city, and state, as well as to other HSIs through conferences and professional society meetings.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This RAPID award is made by the Hispanic-serving Institutions Program in the Division of Human Resource Development, Directorate of Education and Human Resources. The HSI Program aims to enhance undergraduate STEM education and build capacity at HSIs.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/09/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/09/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2032954</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gabriela</FirstName>
<LastName>Solis-Cavazos</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gabriela D Solis-Cavazos</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[gabriela.solis@laredo.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000827228</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/09/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nora</FirstName>
<LastName>Garza</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nora R Garza</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[nrgarza@laredo.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000368449</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/09/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Laredo Community College</Name>
<CityName>LAREDO</CityName>
<ZipCode>780404300</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9567215101</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1 W END WASHINGTON ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>28</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX28</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>KK7FY72Q8B41</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>LAREDO COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Laredo Community College]]></Name>
<CityName>Laredo</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>780404301</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[West End Washington Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>28</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX28</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>077Y</Code>
<Text>HSI-Hispanic Serving Instituti</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8817</Code>
<Text>STEM Learning &amp; Learning Environments</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0420</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~199978</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The RAPID: Using Real Life COVID-19 Data to Teach Quantitative Reasoning Skills to Undergraduate Hispanic STEM Students was a one-year, $199,978.00 National Science Foundation (NSF) RAPID grant. The purpose of the grant was to increase the number of Hispanic and other low-income students to enroll, persist and complete STEM degrees. The main objective for the RAPID: Using Real Life COVID-19 Data to Teach Quantitative Reasoning Skills to Undergraduate Hispanic STEM Students Project (RAPID Project) were to: 1) implement a data-analysis-research experience designed to improve students? quantitative reasoning capabilities; 2) create a professional development opportunity for STEM undergraduate research faculty in quantitative reasoning; and 3) evaluate students? quantitative reasoning skills, their attitudes towards quantitative information, their subsequent STEM course work and college success markers including retention rates and transitions from two-year to four-year institutions.</p> <p>The NSF grant (award# 2032954) was awarded on July 1, 2020 to Laredo College. Dr. Nora Garza, Vice President of Resource Development, and was the Principal Investigator (PI) of the RAPID: Using Real Life COVID-19 Data to Teach Quantitative Reasoning Skills to Undergraduate Hispanic STEM Students developed and began the program by creating three initiatives focused on students, faculty and research.</p> <p><strong>Students:</strong></p> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong>The program <strong>focused on getting low-income students interested in learning quantitative reasoning skills</strong> using the data available for the community from the Laredo COVID-19 Dashboard and the COVID-19 Dashboard created by the Center Systems Science and Engineering (CSSE) at John Hopkins University (JHU). 13 STEM students at Laredo College were trained on quantitative reasoning skills using different activities. Activities included the creation of the <strong>RAPID CANVAS Course</strong> which gave students access to the lessons an activity created by Laredo College faculty. Students were called <strong>RAPID research assistants</strong> and were paid to complete lessons and undergraduate research related to COVID-19. Grant activities included collecting data from the Laredo COVID-19 Dashboard and tracking fevers using the Kinsa brand thermometers. Research assistants (RA) were taught to analyze the information and interpret the data/tables provided on the Laredo and John Hopkins COVID-19 Dashboards.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Faculty:</strong></p> <p>The program included <strong>professional development </strong>for Laredo College faculty. Six faculty were selected to participate and were taught how to properly create and execute lessons incorporating quantitative reasoning skills. Two of the six faculty members had the opportunity to attend the <strong>DARE National Conference</strong> held by Dr. Ester Wilder and developed lesson plans which were incorporated into their curriculum. The lesson plans incorporated quantitative reasoning in the classes taught at Laredo College.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Research:</strong></p> <p>The program partnered RAPID research assistant with faculty and student mentors to guide them in the research and writing process. Research assistants created their own research questions on a topic related to COVID-19, created hypotheses, and determined methodology. They collected data and determined the appropriate data analysis techniques to use in the research. Research assistants analyzed data using SPSS, R-studio, and excel. The objective was to <strong>teach students quantitative literacy skills during the COVID-19 pandemic and keep them engaged in current events</strong>. Student?s undergraduate research skills (creativity, judgment, communication, organization and persistence) were assessed using Laredo College LEAPS URO Skills Survey/Scale during the fall 2020 and spring 2021 term. Eight research paper and posters addressing COVID-19 were completed: ?Artificial Organ and Their Benefits for COVID-19 Patients, Medical Professionals and Their Mental Health During COVID-19, Side Effects of COVID-19 Vaccines, COVID-19: Vaccine Hesitancy, COVID-19 and Teen Mental Health, COVID-19: Photocatalyst Against COVID-19 Virus, The Economic Impact During COVID-19 Pandemic, and The Effects Of the COVID-19 Vaccine. <strong>Research assistants showcased their findings</strong> at the Undergraduate Research Opportunities (URO) Symposium at Laredo College, National Conference of Undergraduate Research, and the 2022 LS-PAC MODELS DIVERSITY in STEM Conference.</p> <p>During the NSF grant, RAPID: Using Real Life COVID-19 Data to Teach Quantitative Reasoning Skills to Undergraduate Hispanic STEM Students, the PI (Principal Investigator) and Co-PI (Co- Principal Investigator) participated and engaged in the COVID Information Commons (CIC). Dr. Nora Garza and Gabriela Solis-Cavazos<span style="text-decoration: underline;"> </span>presented on the program to the Northeast Big Data Innovation Hub (NEBDHub) during the CIC Research Lightning Talks program in September 2020. Video can be found on NEBDHub website: <a href="https://covidinfocommons.datascience.columbia.edu/content/nora-garza-and-gabriela-solis-cavazos-laredo-college">Nora Garza and Gabriela Solis-Cavazos, Laredo College | COVID Information Commons (columbia.edu)</a>. <strong>Dissemination</strong> of the project and the results were presented at the CIC for Computer Networks, CODATA International FAIR Convergence Symposium, and TX HSI Consortium 2022.<strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <h3><strong>The RAPID: Using Real Life COVID-19 Data to Teach Quantitative Reasoning Skills to Undergraduate Hispanic STEM Students Team</strong></h3> <p>&#9679;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Dr. Nora Garza, Principal Investigator, Laredo College (Retired from Laredo College June 30, 2022) (<a href="mailto:nrgarza1971@yahoo.com">nrgarza1971@yahoo.com</a>)</p> <p>&#9679;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Gabriela Solis-Cavazos, co-Principal Investigator, Laredo College (gabriela.solis@laredo.edu)</p> <p>Support for the RAPID projects has been provided by the National Science Foundation's (NSF) award #2032954. We gratefully acknowledge the support from NSF for these projects.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/08/2022<br>      Modified by: Gabriela&nbsp;D&nbsp;Solis-Cavazos</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2032954/2032954_10675942_1659651261591_Picture1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2032954/2032954_10675942_1659651261591_Picture1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="RAPID CANVAS Course"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2032954/2032954_10675942_1659651261591_Picture1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="RAPID CANVAS Course"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The homepage for the RAPID CANVAS course to encourage students to learn quantitative skills.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Laredo College</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Gabriela&nbsp;D&nbsp;Solis-Cavazos</div> <div class="imageTitle">RAPID CANVAS Course</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2032954/2032954_10675942_1659651701685_RAPIDVirtualMeetings--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2032954/2032954_10675942_1659651701685_RAPIDVirtualMeetings--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Zoom Meetings"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2032954/2032954_10675942_1659651701685_RAPIDVirtualMeetings--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Zoom Meetings"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Due to the COVID-19 pandemic protocol at Laredo College, RAPID faculty and research assistant met through zoom every week.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Laredo College</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Gabriela&nbsp;D&nbsp;Solis-Cavazos</div> <div class="imageTitle">Zoom Meetings</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2032954/2032954_10675942_1659651837948_RAPIDResearchAssistants--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2032954/2032954_10675942_1659651837948_RAPIDResearchAssistants--rgov-800width.jpg" title="RAPID Research Assistants"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2032954/2032954_10675942_1659651837948_RAPIDResearchAssistants--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="RAPID Research Assistants"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Laredo College RAPID research assistants assisted at the LEAPS Summer Bridge. Each research assistants were in charged of presenting an activity at the summer bridge and teach other students what they learned as RAPID research assistants.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Laredo College</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Gabriela&nbsp;D&nbsp;Solis-Cavazos</div> <div class="imageTitle">RAPID Research Assistants</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2032954/2032954_10675942_1659652905301_PHOTO-2022-08-04-17-20-26--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2032954/2032954_10675942_1659652905301_PHOTO-2022-08-04-17-20-26--rgov-800width.jpg" title="RAPID Research Assistant Presenting"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2032954/2032954_10675942_1659652905301_PHOTO-2022-08-04-17-20-26--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="RAPID Research Assistant Presenting"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">RAPID research assistant presenting her findings at the2022 LS-PAC MODELS Diversity in STEM Conference in New Orleans.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Laredo College</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Gabriela&nbsp;D&nbsp;Solis-Cavazos</div> <div class="imageTitle">RAPID Research Assistant Presenting</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2032954/2032954_10675942_1659653361574_PHOTO-2022-08-04-17-42-17--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2032954/2032954_10675942_1659653361574_PHOTO-2022-08-04-17-42-17--rgov-800width.jpg" title="RAPID Research Assistant Presenting"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2032954/2032954_10675942_1659653361574_PHOTO-2022-08-04-17-42-17--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="RAPID Research Assistant Presenting"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">RAPID research assistant presenting at the 2022 LS-PAC MODELS Diversity in STEM Conference in New Orleans.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Laredo College</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Gabriela&nbsp;D&nbsp;Solis-Cavazos</div> <div class="imageTitle">RAPID Research Assistant Presenting</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2032954/2032954_10675942_1659653433510_PHOTO-2022-08-04-17-42-53--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2032954/2032954_10675942_1659653433510_PHOTO-2022-08-04-17-42-53--rgov-800width.jpg" title="RAPID Research Assistant Presenting"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2032954/2032954_10675942_1659653433510_PHOTO-2022-08-04-17-42-53--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="RAPID Research Assistant Presenting"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">RAPID research assistant presenting at the 2022 LS-PAC MODELS Diversity in STEM Conference in New Orleans.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Laredo College</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Gabriela&nbsp;D&nbsp;Solis-Cavazos</div> <div class="imageTitle">RAPID Research Assistant Presenting</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The RAPID: Using Real Life COVID-19 Data to Teach Quantitative Reasoning Skills to Undergraduate Hispanic STEM Students was a one-year, $199,978.00 National Science Foundation (NSF) RAPID grant. The purpose of the grant was to increase the number of Hispanic and other low-income students to enroll, persist and complete STEM degrees. The main objective for the RAPID: Using Real Life COVID-19 Data to Teach Quantitative Reasoning Skills to Undergraduate Hispanic STEM Students Project (RAPID Project) were to: 1) implement a data-analysis-research experience designed to improve students? quantitative reasoning capabilities; 2) create a professional development opportunity for STEM undergraduate research faculty in quantitative reasoning; and 3) evaluate students? quantitative reasoning skills, their attitudes towards quantitative information, their subsequent STEM course work and college success markers including retention rates and transitions from two-year to four-year institutions.  The NSF grant (award# 2032954) was awarded on July 1, 2020 to Laredo College. Dr. Nora Garza, Vice President of Resource Development, and was the Principal Investigator (PI) of the RAPID: Using Real Life COVID-19 Data to Teach Quantitative Reasoning Skills to Undergraduate Hispanic STEM Students developed and began the program by creating three initiatives focused on students, faculty and research.  Students:   The program focused on getting low-income students interested in learning quantitative reasoning skills using the data available for the community from the Laredo COVID-19 Dashboard and the COVID-19 Dashboard created by the Center Systems Science and Engineering (CSSE) at John Hopkins University (JHU). 13 STEM students at Laredo College were trained on quantitative reasoning skills using different activities. Activities included the creation of the RAPID CANVAS Course which gave students access to the lessons an activity created by Laredo College faculty. Students were called RAPID research assistants and were paid to complete lessons and undergraduate research related to COVID-19. Grant activities included collecting data from the Laredo COVID-19 Dashboard and tracking fevers using the Kinsa brand thermometers. Research assistants (RA) were taught to analyze the information and interpret the data/tables provided on the Laredo and John Hopkins COVID-19 Dashboards.     Faculty:  The program included professional development for Laredo College faculty. Six faculty were selected to participate and were taught how to properly create and execute lessons incorporating quantitative reasoning skills. Two of the six faculty members had the opportunity to attend the DARE National Conference held by Dr. Ester Wilder and developed lesson plans which were incorporated into their curriculum. The lesson plans incorporated quantitative reasoning in the classes taught at Laredo College.     Research:  The program partnered RAPID research assistant with faculty and student mentors to guide them in the research and writing process. Research assistants created their own research questions on a topic related to COVID-19, created hypotheses, and determined methodology. They collected data and determined the appropriate data analysis techniques to use in the research. Research assistants analyzed data using SPSS, R-studio, and excel. The objective was to teach students quantitative literacy skills during the COVID-19 pandemic and keep them engaged in current events. Student?s undergraduate research skills (creativity, judgment, communication, organization and persistence) were assessed using Laredo College LEAPS URO Skills Survey/Scale during the fall 2020 and spring 2021 term. Eight research paper and posters addressing COVID-19 were completed: ?Artificial Organ and Their Benefits for COVID-19 Patients, Medical Professionals and Their Mental Health During COVID-19, Side Effects of COVID-19 Vaccines, COVID-19: Vaccine Hesitancy, COVID-19 and Teen Mental Health, COVID-19: Photocatalyst Against COVID-19 Virus, The Economic Impact During COVID-19 Pandemic, and The Effects Of the COVID-19 Vaccine. Research assistants showcased their findings at the Undergraduate Research Opportunities (URO) Symposium at Laredo College, National Conference of Undergraduate Research, and the 2022 LS-PAC MODELS DIVERSITY in STEM Conference.  During the NSF grant, RAPID: Using Real Life COVID-19 Data to Teach Quantitative Reasoning Skills to Undergraduate Hispanic STEM Students, the PI (Principal Investigator) and Co-PI (Co- Principal Investigator) participated and engaged in the COVID Information Commons (CIC). Dr. Nora Garza and Gabriela Solis-Cavazos presented on the program to the Northeast Big Data Innovation Hub (NEBDHub) during the CIC Research Lightning Talks program in September 2020. Video can be found on NEBDHub website: Nora Garza and Gabriela Solis-Cavazos, Laredo College | COVID Information Commons (columbia.edu). Dissemination of the project and the results were presented at the CIC for Computer Networks, CODATA International FAIR Convergence Symposium, and TX HSI Consortium 2022.  The RAPID: Using Real Life COVID-19 Data to Teach Quantitative Reasoning Skills to Undergraduate Hispanic STEM Students Team  &#9679;     Dr. Nora Garza, Principal Investigator, Laredo College (Retired from Laredo College June 30, 2022) (nrgarza1971@yahoo.com)  &#9679;     Gabriela Solis-Cavazos, co-Principal Investigator, Laredo College (gabriela.solis@laredo.edu)  Support for the RAPID projects has been provided by the National Science Foundation's (NSF) award #2032954. We gratefully acknowledge the support from NSF for these projects.          Last Modified: 08/08/2022       Submitted by: Gabriela D Solis-Cavazos]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
