<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[STTR Phase I:  Advanced Microfluidic Devices for Point-of-Care COVID-19 Serological Testing]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>256000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>256000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Henry Ahn</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>hahn@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927069</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Technology Transfer (STTR) Phase I project may reach millions of people and provide a key tool in safeguarding the public health through the COVID-19 pandemic. Sensitive, selective and quantitative detection usually requires complex laboratory-based methods and instrumentation to achieve consistent results; however, this project advances technologies to simplify the process. Antibody testing provides information regarding previous infections; a simple tool to detect presence at low concentrations enables better testing to manage social distancing needs. The proposed technology aims to make blood testing for SARS-Cov-2 simple and quantitative for two types of antibodies. The device will be developed to take patient samples directly with no complicated sample prep. Unique reagents will be created for selective detection of the SARS-CoV-2 antibodies. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Technology Transfer (STTR) Phase I project aims to develop the next generation of low-cost point of care immunoassay technology with direct application to infectious disease detection.  The technology proposed here combines a new approach to controlling capillary flow driven systems applied to the steps of a traditional ELISA in a disposable device. The device developed in this project will detect SARSCoV-2 specific antibodies in patient samples, and will be able to provide information about the phase of the immune response of a patient. Additionally, adaption of ELISA-like enzymatic amplification into a point-of-care device will provide greater sensitivity and selectivity than traditional lateral flow assays, increasing assay sensitivity and improving detection of early infections. The immunoassays will be evaluated with deidentified patient samples and compared to state of the art laboratory-based detection methods.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/04/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/14/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2032222</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Charles</FirstName>
<LastName>Henry</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Charles S Henry</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[chuck.henry@colostate.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000393750</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/04/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
<LastName>Reilly</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Thomas H Reilly</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[tomreilly@accsensors.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000746835</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/04/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Access Sensor Technologies</Name>
<CityName>FORT COLLINS</CityName>
<ZipCode>805242325</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9708187520</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>320 E VINE DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[STE 221]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>GJNAJMVMXZ13</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ACCESS SENSOR TECHNOLOGIES LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Colorado State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Fort Collins</CityName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>805232002</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2002 Campus Delivery]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1505</Code>
<Text>STTR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>004E</Code>
<Text>BIOMEDICAL ENG AND DIAGNOSTICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8038</Code>
<Text>Biotechnology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~256000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Access Sensor Technologies was funded by the National Science Foundation through a Small Business Technology Transfer phase I grant. We partnered with Colorado State University (CSU) to evaluate and further develop a diagnostic device invented at CSU. The project was funded as part of a special program to accelerate tools to support managing the COVID-19 pandemic. One of the key needs identified was for cheap, accurate, and non-invasive tests to detect COVID-19 antibodies and COVID-19 active virus in patient samples such as nasal swabs, saliva or blood. By detecting antibodies, it is possible to see who has developed an antibody response to SARS-CoV-2 virus. By detecting the active virus in patient samples, it is possible to determine if a person is actively infected with the virus. A weakness of existing tests is the potential for user error in running a self-test and in limits of detection that may miss low concentrations of active virus. To address these weaknesses a small diagnostic device was investigated that used capillary action to move fluid samples through several different micro-tubes at once. These devices create the effect of delivering fluids in a set order to the zone for reading results which allows for loading and washing the detection zone to improve results. The project proved largely successful by allowing the company to evaluate unique advantages of the system. Deidentified blood and nasal swab samples were used to test and improve the designs. The designs were also improved to produce better manufacturing yield and provide more consistent user experience even for a non-technical user. The technology continues to be actively commercialized with broad applications outside of COVID-19 to many other human health diagnostic needs.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/08/2022<br>      Modified by: Thomas&nbsp;H&nbsp;Reilly</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Access Sensor Technologies was funded by the National Science Foundation through a Small Business Technology Transfer phase I grant. We partnered with Colorado State University (CSU) to evaluate and further develop a diagnostic device invented at CSU. The project was funded as part of a special program to accelerate tools to support managing the COVID-19 pandemic. One of the key needs identified was for cheap, accurate, and non-invasive tests to detect COVID-19 antibodies and COVID-19 active virus in patient samples such as nasal swabs, saliva or blood. By detecting antibodies, it is possible to see who has developed an antibody response to SARS-CoV-2 virus. By detecting the active virus in patient samples, it is possible to determine if a person is actively infected with the virus. A weakness of existing tests is the potential for user error in running a self-test and in limits of detection that may miss low concentrations of active virus. To address these weaknesses a small diagnostic device was investigated that used capillary action to move fluid samples through several different micro-tubes at once. These devices create the effect of delivering fluids in a set order to the zone for reading results which allows for loading and washing the detection zone to improve results. The project proved largely successful by allowing the company to evaluate unique advantages of the system. Deidentified blood and nasal swab samples were used to test and improve the designs. The designs were also improved to produce better manufacturing yield and provide more consistent user experience even for a non-technical user. The technology continues to be actively commercialized with broad applications outside of COVID-19 to many other human health diagnostic needs.          Last Modified: 09/08/2022       Submitted by: Thomas H Reilly]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
