<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Estimating the Reciprocal Relationship between COVID-19 Infections of Prisoners and Staff and Infections in the Surrounding Communities]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>199887.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>199887</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joseph Whitmeyer</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jwhitmey@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927808</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Controlling COVID-19 infections in prison is a critical part of “flattening the curve.” Prisons are high transmission and risk settings for the spread of infectious disease due to crowding, communal dining, and difficulty with sanitation. Prison staff may contribute to disease transmission between the local community and prisoners because staffers exit the prison and enter the community each shift (and vice-versa). This creates a bidirectional pathway for spreading the disease. Prisons, as well as other high density accommodations like nursing homes or cruise ships, are in immediate need of information concerning the spread of COVID-19. In particular, strategies are needed for halting or slowing the spread of COVID-19 in these settings. Prisons are a particularly difficult setting for such evaluative efforts because the current crisis leaves stakeholders little time to assess whether virus suppression strategies and their associated policies are working – creating a devastating information gap. Thus, quickly understanding the spread of COVID-19 both among people and across geographies, the effectiveness of policies and strategies for flattening the curve, as well as the return on investments (ROI) is critical for prisons to minimize and contain future outbreaks of COVID-19. This project will deepen our understanding of the reciprocal relationship between COVID-19 infections among prisoners, correctional staff and the communities where prisons are located. Findings will be useful to communities and congregate facility officials as they develop policies to manage these reciprocal infections in congregate settings, thus contributing to U. S. health and well-being. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Prisons are at high risk for the spread of COVID-19, due to their communal settings, and the movement of staff between prisons and communities on a daily basis.  To assess the dynamics of these risks, this project will develop a data driven dynamical disease model focusing on the temporal patterns in COVID-19 infections in the inter-connected prison/staff/community populations, and assess the relative efficacy of potential best practices for infection control, either aimed at the prisoner population and/or the staff population. In addition, the project will examine the reciprocal relationship between infections and deaths in prisons among prisoners and staff and the communities surrounding the prison from a geographic perspective. An ability to model the geospatial intricacies and the geodemographic impacts of this process is critical to developing a deeper understanding of how COVID-19 interacts with mobile (e.g., staff) and/or immobile (e.g., prisoner) populations. Specifically, the project will use geocomputational approaches for modeling the spatial envelopes of potential interactions between prison staff and their local residential communities. This includes the development of high-resolution spatiotemporal catchment areas to/from each federal prison in the United States. Finally, using return-on-investment (ROI) analysis, the project will illuminate the potential economic implications of COVID-19 infection control interventions targeting justice-involved populations. The anticipated insights from the ROI analysis include the identification of the key ROI drivers and the magnitude of impact required for the accrual of net savings to relevant decision-making agencies. Findings from the project will inform sociological theories regarding incarceration and literatures regarding reciprocal relationships between work and community.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/09/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/09/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2032747</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Danielle</FirstName>
<LastName>Wallace</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Danielle Wallace</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[Danielle.Wallace@asu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000552821</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/09/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Eason</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John M Eason</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jeason@urban.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000612293</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/09/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Arizona State University</Name>
<CityName>TEMPE</CityName>
<ZipCode>852813670</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4809655479</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>660 S MILL AVENUE STE 204</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AZ04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NTLHJXM55KZ6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ARIZONA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Arizona State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Phoenix</CityName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>850040685</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[411 N Central Ave Suite 680]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AZ03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1331</Code>
<Text>Sociology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~199887</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Controlling COVID-19 infections in prison is a critical part of &ldquo;flattening the curve&rdquo; of the pandemic. Prisons are high transmission settings for the spread of infectious disease due to crowding, communal dining, and difficulty with sanitation. Prison staff may contribute to disease transmission between the local community and incarcerated populations because staffers exit the prison and enter and exit the community with each shift. This creates a bidirectional pathway for spreading disease; however, little is known about how this works, particularly with COVID-19. We examined the temporal relationship between COVID-19 infections among prison staff, the incarcerated population, and the local community for federal prisons in the United States. To do this, we collected data from the Federal Bureau of Prisons (BOP) from March 2020 to June 2021 and augmented this data with information from epidemiological organizations tracking COVID-19 across the US. Additionally, we examined these relationships at a spatial level, considering prisons risky facilities for the spread of disease. A number of important findings have come from this work, both related to the experience of the pandemic in prisons and pandemic-related data.</p> <p>Our primary objective was to examine the temporal relationship between COVID-19 infections among prison staff, incarcerated individuals, and the general population surrounding the prison. When examining our data prior to the wide-spread introduction of vaccines, we found a significant, temporal relationship between the COVID-19 prevalence among staff and incarcerated persons in the U.S. federal prison system, suggesting that when staff rates of infection increased, infections in the incarcerated population were soon to follow. Additionally, we found that the community rates of COVID-19 around the prison influenced staff rates of infection, showing how ties among communities, prison staff and incarcerated persons influence the spread of infectious diseases within prisons. Moreover, when prison staff rates were low or at zero, COVID-19 incidence in the larger community continued to impact COVID-19 prevalence among incarcerated persons, suggesting patterns of possible pre-symptomatic and asymptomatic transmission of COVID-19 by prison staff to incarcerated persons.</p> <p>Taking a deeper look into the interlinked incarcerated population, staff, and community groups to better understand optimal control of COVID-19, we examined the per capita size of outbreaks in staff and the incarcerated population in non-administrative federal prisons between and compared them to outbreaks in the surrounding communities during the summer and winter waves of the pandemic. For both waves, we found that the per capita rates in the outbreaks among the incarcerated population, staff, and the community were strongly correlated. Regardless of wave, per capita rates were significantly higher in the incarcerated population than in both the staff and community. Average per capita rates of incarcerated population outbreaks were significantly associated with prison security level, with low security prisons having the largest outbreaks and high security prisons having far smaller outbreaks. Additionally, the BOP decarcerated (released to home confinement) a significant portion of the prison population as a mechanism of disease control. We found no significant impact of decarceration on per capita rates of infections in the staff and community populations, but decarceration was significantly associated with a decrease in per capita rates of COVID-19 among the incarcerated population during the winter wave.</p> <p>Third, we aimed to understand the geographically bound demographic and spatiotemporal impacts of COVID-19 in areas with facilities that could increase the spread of disease, like prisons. Using the state of Wisconsin as a case study, we explored the geographic nuances of COVID-19 and its spread in Wisconsin using several spatial statistical techniques. We discovered that hot spots of COVID-19 were linked to the presence of high-risk facilities, including federal and state correctional facilities. Our study suggests that COVID-19 disproportionately impacted several communities and geographically bound demographic groups that were more proximate to risky facilities such as prisons, which in turn, correlated to increased community infection rates.</p> <p>Finally, data related to COVID-19 and prisons was being rapidly released as the pandemic gained traction in mid-2020. The boon of available pandemic-related data, however, is not without problems. Elements of the US criminal justice system (i.e., policing, courts, prisons, etc.) and their associated data products were not designed to collect and release epidemiological data at a rapid rate. COVID-19 related data were commonly released without proper epidemiological measurement and statistics in mind. The data we collected from the BOP is no different; while these data too come with limitations regarding reconstructing epidemiological measures, like the incidence rate of COVID-19 within prisons. However, they remain useful for understanding disease-spreading relationships between incarcerated persons, staff, and the community around the prison.</p> <p>In closing, this project demonstrated the reciprocal relationship between COVID-19 infections among prisoners, correctional staff and the communities where prisons are located. Moreover, the project showed that prisons can be considered risky facilities to the larger community that surrounds the prison in regards to disease spread.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/29/2022<br>      Modified by: Danielle&nbsp;Wallace</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Controlling COVID-19 infections in prison is a critical part of "flattening the curve" of the pandemic. Prisons are high transmission settings for the spread of infectious disease due to crowding, communal dining, and difficulty with sanitation. Prison staff may contribute to disease transmission between the local community and incarcerated populations because staffers exit the prison and enter and exit the community with each shift. This creates a bidirectional pathway for spreading disease; however, little is known about how this works, particularly with COVID-19. We examined the temporal relationship between COVID-19 infections among prison staff, the incarcerated population, and the local community for federal prisons in the United States. To do this, we collected data from the Federal Bureau of Prisons (BOP) from March 2020 to June 2021 and augmented this data with information from epidemiological organizations tracking COVID-19 across the US. Additionally, we examined these relationships at a spatial level, considering prisons risky facilities for the spread of disease. A number of important findings have come from this work, both related to the experience of the pandemic in prisons and pandemic-related data.  Our primary objective was to examine the temporal relationship between COVID-19 infections among prison staff, incarcerated individuals, and the general population surrounding the prison. When examining our data prior to the wide-spread introduction of vaccines, we found a significant, temporal relationship between the COVID-19 prevalence among staff and incarcerated persons in the U.S. federal prison system, suggesting that when staff rates of infection increased, infections in the incarcerated population were soon to follow. Additionally, we found that the community rates of COVID-19 around the prison influenced staff rates of infection, showing how ties among communities, prison staff and incarcerated persons influence the spread of infectious diseases within prisons. Moreover, when prison staff rates were low or at zero, COVID-19 incidence in the larger community continued to impact COVID-19 prevalence among incarcerated persons, suggesting patterns of possible pre-symptomatic and asymptomatic transmission of COVID-19 by prison staff to incarcerated persons.  Taking a deeper look into the interlinked incarcerated population, staff, and community groups to better understand optimal control of COVID-19, we examined the per capita size of outbreaks in staff and the incarcerated population in non-administrative federal prisons between and compared them to outbreaks in the surrounding communities during the summer and winter waves of the pandemic. For both waves, we found that the per capita rates in the outbreaks among the incarcerated population, staff, and the community were strongly correlated. Regardless of wave, per capita rates were significantly higher in the incarcerated population than in both the staff and community. Average per capita rates of incarcerated population outbreaks were significantly associated with prison security level, with low security prisons having the largest outbreaks and high security prisons having far smaller outbreaks. Additionally, the BOP decarcerated (released to home confinement) a significant portion of the prison population as a mechanism of disease control. We found no significant impact of decarceration on per capita rates of infections in the staff and community populations, but decarceration was significantly associated with a decrease in per capita rates of COVID-19 among the incarcerated population during the winter wave.  Third, we aimed to understand the geographically bound demographic and spatiotemporal impacts of COVID-19 in areas with facilities that could increase the spread of disease, like prisons. Using the state of Wisconsin as a case study, we explored the geographic nuances of COVID-19 and its spread in Wisconsin using several spatial statistical techniques. We discovered that hot spots of COVID-19 were linked to the presence of high-risk facilities, including federal and state correctional facilities. Our study suggests that COVID-19 disproportionately impacted several communities and geographically bound demographic groups that were more proximate to risky facilities such as prisons, which in turn, correlated to increased community infection rates.  Finally, data related to COVID-19 and prisons was being rapidly released as the pandemic gained traction in mid-2020. The boon of available pandemic-related data, however, is not without problems. Elements of the US criminal justice system (i.e., policing, courts, prisons, etc.) and their associated data products were not designed to collect and release epidemiological data at a rapid rate. COVID-19 related data were commonly released without proper epidemiological measurement and statistics in mind. The data we collected from the BOP is no different; while these data too come with limitations regarding reconstructing epidemiological measures, like the incidence rate of COVID-19 within prisons. However, they remain useful for understanding disease-spreading relationships between incarcerated persons, staff, and the community around the prison.  In closing, this project demonstrated the reciprocal relationship between COVID-19 infections among prisoners, correctional staff and the communities where prisons are located. Moreover, the project showed that prisons can be considered risky facilities to the larger community that surrounds the prison in regards to disease spread.          Last Modified: 09/29/2022       Submitted by: Danielle Wallace]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
