<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Development of online-based research experiences to mitigate the negative impacts of the COVID-19 pandemic on undergraduate biology education]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>198979.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>198979</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DBI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Amanda Simcox</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>asimcox@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928165</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[RAPID: Development of online-based research experiences to mitigate the negative impacts of the COVID-19 pandemic on undergraduate biology education&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The COVID-19 pandemic has resulted in a shift to online learning for undergraduate educators on an unprecedented scale. This project will support the accelerated development and use of online digitized Natural History Collections (dNHC) to substitute for laboratory and field-based research projects that have been lost as a result of the pandemic. Implementation of dNHC-enabled online courses will engage hundreds to thousands of students at the introductory and advanced level. This approach is known to increase engagement, retention, and long-term success in undergraduates. Embedding research experiences in biology coursework is especially important for low income, first-generation, and minority undergraduate students who may be unable to dedicate time to research outside their normal course load due to personal and financial barriers. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Rapid grant is dedicated to bringing together undergraduate educators, natural history collections professionals, data professionals, and collections researchers to support the development and implementation of online Course-based Undergraduate Research Experiences (CUREs) using dNHC data for the 2020-2021 academic year. Extensive NSF-funded digitization of biological collections has created millions of specimen records on publicly-available data portals, resulting in unique and innovative opportunities for collections research. Using these resources in CUREs provides teaching and research opportunities to students and educators and requires only a computer, internet access, and time. Online CUREs using dNHCs are perfectly positioned to fill the gap in ecology and evolution research experiences as students lose access to laboratories and field sites. Teams of undergraduate educators and collections professionals will collaborate to develop teaching materials, course syllabi, and instructor guides to support the implementation of online dNHC CUREs in fall 2020 and beyond. This RAPID will recruit a diverse group of CURE developers and implementers and support members with collaboration and training opportunities. Faculty members who teach high proportions of underrepresented minorities and first-generation college students will be especially encouraged to participate, and resources created through this process will be widely disseminated to guide and support future dNHC CURE development.  This RAPID award is made by the Division of Biological Infrastructure (DBI) using funds from the Coronavirus Aid, Relief, and Economic Security (CARES) Act.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/18/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/18/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2032158</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Elizabeth</FirstName>
<LastName>Shea</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>K</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Elizabeth K Shea</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[eshea@delmnh.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000563891</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/18/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Janice</FirstName>
<LastName>Krumm</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Janice L Krumm</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jlkrumm@widener.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000796445</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/18/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Carly</FirstName>
<LastName>Jordan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>N</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Carly N Jordan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[cnjordan@gwu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000826529</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/18/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Widener University</Name>
<CityName>CHESTER</CityName>
<ZipCode>190135700</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6104994396</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1 UNIVERSITY PL</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>GP1SKG5MFH79</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WIDENER UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Widener University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>190135792</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[One University Place]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>158Y</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>1N20</Code>
<Name>R&amp;RA CARES Act DEFC N</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>010N2021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[R&RA CARES Act DEFC N]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~198979</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p style="margin-right: 0; margin-bottom: 14pt; margin-left: 0;"><span><span style="color: black; font-size: 12pt; font-family: Times New Roman,serif;">This  RAPID-COVID award supported the development and dissemination of  Course-based Undergraduate Research Experiences (CUREs) using open  access data from natural history collections that has been digitized and  is freely available online to all students, regardless of institutional  resources or location. These inquiry-driven, active learning research  experiences provide students with opportunities to better understand the  process of science, and the CUREs require only access to the internet  so they can be implemented at no cost in online, hybrid, and in-person  courses. By embedding research experiences in coursework, CUREs increase  accessibility for all students, including students with financial or  time limitations that limit access to apprentice style research  experiences. The use of digitized natural history collections data in  these CUREs supports student learning of transferable skills including  data management, science communication, and collaboration at all  institution types. These skills are critical elements in creating a  highly trained scientific workforce.&nbsp;</span></span></p> <p style="margin-right: 0; margin-bottom: 14pt; margin-left: 0;"><span><span style="color: black; font-size: 12pt; font-family: Times New Roman,serif;">Educational  materials for four CUREs using digitized natural history collections  were created in summer 2020 by teams of undergraduate educators and  natural history collections professionals. The CURE developers  participated in professional development workshops on topics including  introduction to natural history collections, data portals and  downloading, data cleaning, georeferencing, mapping with QGIS, aligning  CURE research goals and learning objectives, equity and inclusion in  research, scaffolding research activities and course design, and  assessment in research. The CURE materials are published as open  educational resources, freely available to all educators and interested  individuals, and published on the QUBES BCEENET (Biological Collections  in Ecology and Evolution Network) resources website.</span></span></p> <p style="margin-right: 0; margin-bottom: 14pt; margin-left: 0;"><span><span style="color: black; font-size: 12pt; font-family: Times New Roman,serif;">The  RAPID award also funded peer support for implementing faculty in the  2020-2021 academic year, while many institutions had shifted to online  learning during the COVID pandemic. These CUREs helped to maintain  access to undergraduate research experiences, helping to mitigate the  negative impacts of the pandemic. Continued implementation of the CUREs  beyond the shift back to in-person instruction has expanded the number  of research experiences available at many institutions, including  minority-serving institutions and community colleges. In the first two  years of implementation, 1894 undergraduates have participated in these  CUREs at 26 institutions, including 9 minority-serving institutions and 4  community colleges.&nbsp;</span></span></p> <p><span><span style="color: black; font-size: 12pt; font-family: Times New Roman,serif;">Information about the CURE educational materials supported by this award can be found on the BCEENET website (</span></span><span style="color: black; font-size: 12pt;"><a title="Original URL: https://bceenetwork.org/. Click or tap if you trust this link." rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://nam02.safelinks.protection.outlook.com/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fbceenetwork.org%2F&amp;data=05%7C01%7Cjlkrumm%40widener.edu%7C772b2047090c4904a98508daa17558ba%7C509e4716869747249169dc73ae0e81a2%7C1%7C0%7C637999822640247704%7CUnknown%7CTWFpbGZsb3d8eyJWIjoiMC4wLjAwMDAiLCJQIjoiV2luMzIiLCJBTiI6Ik1haWwiLCJXVCI6Mn0%3D%7C3000%7C%7C%7C&amp;sdata=46ozBifr3JRW23Ke%2FpsT%2Fb37%2B781VSPgWr%2BZA014Xag%3D&amp;reserved=0" target="_blank"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman,serif;">https://bceenetwork.org/</span></a></span><span><span style="color: black; font-size: 12pt; font-family: Times New Roman,serif;">) and on the QUBES BCEENET resources website (</span></span><span style="color: black; font-size: 12pt;"><a title="Original URL: https://qubeshub.org/community/groups/bceenet. Click or tap if you trust this link." rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://nam02.safelinks.protection.outlook.com/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fqubeshub.org%2Fcommunity%2Fgroups%2Fbceenet&amp;data=05%7C01%7Cjlkrumm%40widener.edu%7C772b2047090c4904a98508daa17558ba%7C509e4716869747249169dc73ae0e81a2%7C1%7C0%7C637999822640403943%7CUnknown%7CTWFpbGZsb3d8eyJWIjoiMC4wLjAwMDAiLCJQIjoiV2luMzIiLCJBTiI6Ik1haWwiLCJXVCI6Mn0%3D%7C3000%7C%7C%7C&amp;sdata=tmjBGgOBBEomSeRDd09xo%2FLl8D1PObL0UwuKh30Tut4%3D&amp;reserved=0" target="_blank"><span style="font-family: Times New Roman,serif;">https://qubeshub.org/community/groups/bceenet</span></a></span><span><span style="color: black; font-size: 12pt; font-family: Times New Roman,serif;">).  Through supporting CUREs using open-access, digitized natural history  collections data, this work supports the development of a diverse 21</span></span><span><sup><span style="color: black; font-size: 7pt; font-family: Times New Roman,serif;">st</span></sup></span><span><span style="color: black; font-size: 12pt; font-family: Times New Roman,serif;">&nbsp;century STEM workforce. <br /></span></span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/28/2022<br>      Modified by: Janice&nbsp;L&nbsp;Krumm</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[This  RAPID-COVID award supported the development and dissemination of  Course-based Undergraduate Research Experiences (CUREs) using open  access data from natural history collections that has been digitized and  is freely available online to all students, regardless of institutional  resources or location. These inquiry-driven, active learning research  experiences provide students with opportunities to better understand the  process of science, and the CUREs require only access to the internet  so they can be implemented at no cost in online, hybrid, and in-person  courses. By embedding research experiences in coursework, CUREs increase  accessibility for all students, including students with financial or  time limitations that limit access to apprentice style research  experiences. The use of digitized natural history collections data in  these CUREs supports student learning of transferable skills including  data management, science communication, and collaboration at all  institution types. These skills are critical elements in creating a  highly trained scientific workforce.  Educational  materials for four CUREs using digitized natural history collections  were created in summer 2020 by teams of undergraduate educators and  natural history collections professionals. The CURE developers  participated in professional development workshops on topics including  introduction to natural history collections, data portals and  downloading, data cleaning, georeferencing, mapping with QGIS, aligning  CURE research goals and learning objectives, equity and inclusion in  research, scaffolding research activities and course design, and  assessment in research. The CURE materials are published as open  educational resources, freely available to all educators and interested  individuals, and published on the QUBES BCEENET (Biological Collections  in Ecology and Evolution Network) resources website. The  RAPID award also funded peer support for implementing faculty in the  2020-2021 academic year, while many institutions had shifted to online  learning during the COVID pandemic. These CUREs helped to maintain  access to undergraduate research experiences, helping to mitigate the  negative impacts of the pandemic. Continued implementation of the CUREs  beyond the shift back to in-person instruction has expanded the number  of research experiences available at many institutions, including  minority-serving institutions and community colleges. In the first two  years of implementation, 1894 undergraduates have participated in these  CUREs at 26 institutions, including 9 minority-serving institutions and 4  community colleges.   Information about the CURE educational materials supported by this award can be found on the BCEENET website (https://bceenetwork.org/) and on the QUBES BCEENET resources website (https://qubeshub.org/community/groups/bceenet).  Through supporting CUREs using open-access, digitized natural history  collections data, this work supports the development of a diverse 21st century STEM workforce.         Last Modified: 09/28/2022       Submitted by: Janice L Krumm]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
