<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Infection Transmission of COVID19 in Urban Neighborhoods]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>199718.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>199718</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Scott Freundschuh</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Though most coverage of the COVID-19 pandemic has focused on the international and national levels, it necessarily unfolds also at the local level. Recent reports reveal that in many American cities the coronavirus is having disproportionate impacts on neighborhoods that are historically disadvantaged. This project will identify disparities in infection rates by examining how residents of different neighborhoods have varied in their ability and tendency to practice social distancing during the pandemic. While most research on how infection proceeds through communities focuses on international transmission, we expand this understanding to how it progresses through the finer geospatial scale of communities in a metropolitan area. This research will provide critical, replicable insights for not only the effectiveness of social distancing policies, but their equitability in diminishing infection rates across communities.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The consequences of disasters are often influenced by where one lives (i.e., neighborhood effects). A pandemic introduces the additional ingredient of network diffusion through interactions both within and between neighborhoods. This study synthesizes these two perspectives to understand how COVID19 infections spread through a city’s neighborhoods, leading to differential infection rates. The project will conduct a survey on social distancing practices and attitudes and exposure to infection leveraging the existing survey of Boston residents called BEACON. The survey responses will be cross-referenced with flows of movement across neighborhoods from cellphone-generated records; diagnosis records; and a list of neighborhood geographic features curated by the Boston Area Research Initiative. This project will enable tests of a four-part causal model, with neighborhood characteristics influencing social distancing practices, which in turn shape the mobility flows of the city, which then drive the network diffusion of infection. The results will be critical as cities around the world continue to manage the current pandemic while also preparing for similar crises in the future.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/16/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/16/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2032384</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>J. Lee</FirstName>
<LastName>Hargraves</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>J. Lee Hargraves</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[lee.hargraves@umb.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000639372</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/16/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
<LastName>O'Brien</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Daniel O'Brien</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[d.obrien@northeastern.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000642271</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/16/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Qi</FirstName>
<LastName>Wang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Qi Wang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[q.wang@northeastern.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000730734</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/16/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alina</FirstName>
<LastName>Ristea</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alina Ristea</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[a.ristea@northeastern.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000826379</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/16/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Russell</FirstName>
<LastName>Schutt</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>K</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Russell K Schutt</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[russell.schutt@umb.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000827003</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/16/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Northeastern University</Name>
<CityName>BOSTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>021155005</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6173733004</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>360 HUNTINGTON AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>HLTMVS2JZBS6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORTHEASTERN UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Northeastern University]]></Name>
<CityName>Boston</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021155005</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[360 Huntington Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1352</Code>
<Text>Geography and Spatial Sciences</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1352</Code>
<Text>GEOGRAPHY AND SPATIAL SCIENCES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~199718</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Different Neighborhoods, Different Pandemic: The Experiences of Boston, MA?s Diverse Communities through Multiple Datasets</strong></p> <p>This project sought to gain a comprehensive record of the different experiences of Boston, MA?s diverse neighborhoods during the early months of the pandemic. We especially focused on the interplay between neighborhood context, including demographics and socioeconomic status; the ability and tendency to practice social distancing; and the consequences for rates of infection.</p> <p>We undertook two main data collection activities, each leveraging an existing research infrastructure. These efforts were undertaken in collaboration with local policymakers and practitioners to ensure the ability to illuminate pressing challenges in the city. First, we collected resident surveys on attitudes and experiences during the early months of the pandemic, especially regarding social distancing through BEACON, an existing panel survey of Boston communities administered by UMass Boston?s Center for Survey Research (CSR). We recruited a new set of respondents for the panel, resulting in 1,626 total respondents who were well-distributed across Boston?s neighborhoods.</p> <p>Second, we updated and added to data resources contained by the Boston Data Portal (BDP; <a href="https://cssh.northeastern.edu/bari/boston-data-portal/">https://cssh.northeastern.edu/bari/boston-data-portal/</a>), a project of the Boston Area Research Initiative (BARI) at Northeastern University that gathers, processes, and publishes data from multiple sources that describe the people and places of the city. These efforts included administrative records (e.g., building permits, 311 complaints, 911 dispatches) and data scraped from internet sources (e.g., Craigslist housing listings, Airbnb listings, Yelp reviews for local restaurants). We also incorporated infection cases shared by the Boston Public Health Commission (BPHC), cellphone-generated mobility data shared by SafeGraph, and demographic indicators from the US Census Bureau?s American Community Survey.</p> <p>A major effort of the project was to disseminate the work in as close to real time as possible. The survey enabled a series of seven public reports (<a href="https://cssh.northeastern.edu/bari/projects/covid-19-in-boston/">https://cssh.northeastern.edu/bari/projects/covid-19-in-boston/</a>) that were released in collaboration with BPHC and shared directly with local leaders and the public. These and subsequent efforts to analyze the data have generated a wide array of insights on experiences of the pandemic in Boston?s neighborhoods, many of which highlighted deep racial and socioeconomic inequities. These include: how poor and historically-disenfranchised populations had fewer resources and opportunities for mitigating exposure risk; how fear and ambivalence varied by community; the manner in which the economic impact landed most heavily on those who were already poor; how lifestyle, ideology, and context had a tendency to influence people?s attitudes toward COVID; how vaccination intentions varied across neighborhoods, and the implications of this for long-term impacts of the pandemic; and how physical and mental health were impacted in varied ways, including the toll of continued social distancing. Many of these reports are now giving rise to journal publications.</p> <p>The project generated 14 new and updated datasets that have been published through the BDP as part of the COVID in Boston Database (user guide: <a href="https://dataverse.harvard.edu/dataset.xhtml?persistentId=doi:10.7910/DVN/TDKDJJ">https://dataverse.harvard.edu/dataset.xhtml?persistentId=doi:10.7910/DVN/TDKDJJ</a>). The survey data will be published there as well in the coming months. Our hope is that other researchers and policymakers will make use of these resources to reveal additional insights on the ways different communities responded to and experienced the pandemic.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/31/2021<br>      Modified by: Daniel&nbsp;O'brien</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Different Neighborhoods, Different Pandemic: The Experiences of Boston, MA?s Diverse Communities through Multiple Datasets  This project sought to gain a comprehensive record of the different experiences of Boston, MA?s diverse neighborhoods during the early months of the pandemic. We especially focused on the interplay between neighborhood context, including demographics and socioeconomic status; the ability and tendency to practice social distancing; and the consequences for rates of infection.  We undertook two main data collection activities, each leveraging an existing research infrastructure. These efforts were undertaken in collaboration with local policymakers and practitioners to ensure the ability to illuminate pressing challenges in the city. First, we collected resident surveys on attitudes and experiences during the early months of the pandemic, especially regarding social distancing through BEACON, an existing panel survey of Boston communities administered by UMass Boston?s Center for Survey Research (CSR). We recruited a new set of respondents for the panel, resulting in 1,626 total respondents who were well-distributed across Boston?s neighborhoods.  Second, we updated and added to data resources contained by the Boston Data Portal (BDP; https://cssh.northeastern.edu/bari/boston-data-portal/), a project of the Boston Area Research Initiative (BARI) at Northeastern University that gathers, processes, and publishes data from multiple sources that describe the people and places of the city. These efforts included administrative records (e.g., building permits, 311 complaints, 911 dispatches) and data scraped from internet sources (e.g., Craigslist housing listings, Airbnb listings, Yelp reviews for local restaurants). We also incorporated infection cases shared by the Boston Public Health Commission (BPHC), cellphone-generated mobility data shared by SafeGraph, and demographic indicators from the US Census Bureau?s American Community Survey.  A major effort of the project was to disseminate the work in as close to real time as possible. The survey enabled a series of seven public reports (https://cssh.northeastern.edu/bari/projects/covid-19-in-boston/) that were released in collaboration with BPHC and shared directly with local leaders and the public. These and subsequent efforts to analyze the data have generated a wide array of insights on experiences of the pandemic in Boston?s neighborhoods, many of which highlighted deep racial and socioeconomic inequities. These include: how poor and historically-disenfranchised populations had fewer resources and opportunities for mitigating exposure risk; how fear and ambivalence varied by community; the manner in which the economic impact landed most heavily on those who were already poor; how lifestyle, ideology, and context had a tendency to influence people?s attitudes toward COVID; how vaccination intentions varied across neighborhoods, and the implications of this for long-term impacts of the pandemic; and how physical and mental health were impacted in varied ways, including the toll of continued social distancing. Many of these reports are now giving rise to journal publications.  The project generated 14 new and updated datasets that have been published through the BDP as part of the COVID in Boston Database (user guide: https://dataverse.harvard.edu/dataset.xhtml?persistentId=doi:10.7910/DVN/TDKDJJ). The survey data will be published there as well in the coming months. Our hope is that other researchers and policymakers will make use of these resources to reveal additional insights on the ways different communities responded to and experienced the pandemic.          Last Modified: 08/31/2021       Submitted by: Daniel O'brien]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
