<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Developing a National Research Agenda for STEM Education for Students with Visual Impairments (VI)]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>88539.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>88539</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div. of Equity for Excellence in STEM</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Carrie Hall</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>carhall@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924641</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The conference will convene researchers and other stakeholders to develop a STEM education research plan that will focus on STEM education of students with visual impairments.  The goal is to identity and prioritize agenda topics that address the needs of this population, and to build capacity to conduct robust research focused on those needs.  The conference agenda will include an analysis of gaps in the research, appropriate methodologies for this type of research, and strategies for translating the research to practice. The project is expected to advance knowledge and understanding about STEM education for students with visual impairments by defining a focused research agenda and positioning scholars who can conduct high quality fundamental STEM education research and build a community of practice.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The conference will invite educators, researchers, parents, students, and technology developers to jointly conceptualize, design, and plan a research agenda that focuses on enhancing STEM learning and career preparation for persons with visual impairment. The sessions will address the challenges in defining research methods for this population and offer a coordinated effort to develop evidence-based practices and technological interventions to serve this population.  Conference topics will include design methods, collection and analysis of data, and secondary data analyses that can be employed.  The project is expected to advance knowledge and understanding in the field of visual impairments and STEM education and establish a community of practice. The project will highlight the instructional needs and gaps of students with visual impairments and guide interventions and strategies for mitigating the disruption of pandemics to ensure that students with visual impairments have access to STEM education.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is supported by the ECR: Building Capacity in STEM Education Research competition of the EHR Core Research (ECR) program.  ECR funds fundamental STEM education research focused on STEM learning and learning environments, broadening participation in STEM fields, and STEM professional workforce development.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/21/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/14/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2032668</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tiffany</FirstName>
<LastName>Wild</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Tiffany A Wild</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[wild.13@osu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000638049</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/21/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Ohio State University</Name>
<CityName>COLUMBUS</CityName>
<ZipCode>432101016</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6146888735</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1960 KENNY RD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OH03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>DLWBSLWAJWR1</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OHIO STATE UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>MN4MDDMN8529</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[The Ohio State University]]></Name>
<CityName>COLUMBUS</CityName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>432101016</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1960 KENNY RD]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OH03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>162Y</Code>
<Text>ECR:BCSER Capcity STEM Ed Rscr</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8055</Code>
<Text>Capacity-Building Projects</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8212</Code>
<Text>Broaden Particip STEM Resrch</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0420</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~88539</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>A major outcome of this project was to examine the research that has been conducted in STEM education for students with visual impairments.&nbsp; A comprehensive database was created and is part of the open-access materials found on our website.&nbsp; A searchable database was created that cataloged all articles in APA citation as well as a creation of an overall report noting trends and gaps in research.&nbsp; Within the created national agenda document, there is a call to action, noting the needed research for the field.&nbsp; The gathering of all those committed to STEM research allows for the capacity to conduct future research built upon the findings of this project.&nbsp; Research projects have already begun with partners within the project examining tactile graphic creation and education.&nbsp;</p> <p>All those invited to the conference worked together to identify causes of under-representation of persons with visual impairments in STEM careers.&nbsp; Persons invited to the project included current leading researchers, developers, parents, recent graduates and teachers of students with visual impairments. The goals produced as part of this project, if and when achieved, will work to increase representation of persons with visual impairments in STEM courses of study and careers.</p> <p>The national research agenda was created.&nbsp; This document is 65 pages long, that includes: 1) the need for the national research agenda, 2) the rationale for the national agenda, 3) development of the national agenda, 4) goal statements, 5) 12 identified areas for which additional research and development should be conducted in order to better promote STEM accessibility for students with visual impairments, 6) a list of our collaborators, 7) references, and 8) citation of the website for which all information of the project is housed.</p> <p>The planning team has presented about this project and the findings of the research review as well as the creation and information contained within the national research agenda booklet.&nbsp; Those conferences include:</p> <ul> <li>Association for Education and Rehabilitation of the      Blind and Visually Impaired International Conference - July 2022</li> <li>OCALICON - November 2022</li> <li>Michigan State Teachers of Students with Visual      Impairments - Michigan Department of Education - September 2022</li> <li>Council for Exceptional Children - Spring 2023</li> </ul> <p>The team has also written two articles.&nbsp; One has been published and one is in press:</p> <ul> <li>Lu, X. &amp;&nbsp;Wild, T.&nbsp;(2022).&nbsp;      Introducing the National Research Agenda for STEM Education for Students      with Visual Impairments.&nbsp;&nbsp;<em>Division on Visual      ImpairmentEducation Quarterly, &nbsp;</em>67(3), 14-20.&nbsp;      Available at:&nbsp;<a href="http://dvi.uberflip.com/i/1476599-vidbe-q-67-3-summer-back-to-school-issue-2022/1">http://dvi.uberflip.com/i/1476599-vidbe-q-67-3-summer-back-to-school-issue-2022/1</a></li> <li>Wild, T., Smith, D., Kelly, S., Fast, D., Lu, X.&nbsp;      (2022).&nbsp; Creation of a National Agenda for STEM Education for      Students with Visual Impairments.&nbsp;&nbsp;<em>Journal of Visual      Impairments and Blindness,&nbsp;</em>116(5).&nbsp; First available      online:&nbsp;<a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/0145482X221134372">https://doi.org/10.1177/0145482X221134372</a><em>&nbsp;</em></li> </ul> <p>Tiffany Wild has also presented on the agenda as part of her keynote presentation at the International Conference on Disability Inclusion.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>In addition, over 2,500 copies of the national agenda booklet have been handed out to educational service centers, state educational agencies, university preparation programs, the American Printing House for the Blind, and other educational agencies upon request.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>The website: https://u.osu.edu/nationalresearchstemvisualimpairment/ allows for anyone to access all portions of the project including: bios of the collaborative partners, bios of the subject matter professional partners, news and events, materials from the project such as the PowerPoint and database of STEM articles, resources for educators and researchers, a contact page, and the national research agenda downloadable booklet.&nbsp; The website also allows people to subscribe to allow for further updates and collaborations opportunities.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/19/2022<br>      Modified by: Tiffany&nbsp;A&nbsp;Wild</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2032668/2032668_10700732_1671035332956_COVER2PDF_Page_1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2032668/2032668_10700732_1671035332956_COVER2PDF_Page_1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Project title in print followed by a test tube being held on a stand.  Inside the test tube is the pie symbol, a gear, the power button image for the computer and a beaker to represent STEM.  Below the image are the letters &quot;STEM&quot; in red simulated braille and black print.text followed with STEM"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2032668/2032668_10700732_1671035332956_COVER2PDF_Page_1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Project title in print followed by a test tube being held on a stand.  Inside the test tube is the pie symbol, a gear, the power button image for the computer and a beaker to represent STEM.  Below the image are the letters &quot;STEM&quot; in red simulated braille and black print.text followed with STEM"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Logo of the project.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Dana House</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (restricted use - cannot be shared)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Tiffany&nbsp;A&nbsp;Wild</div> <div class="imageTitle">Project title in print followed by a test tube being held on a stand.  Inside the test tube is the pie symbol, a gear, the power button image for the computer and a beaker to represent STEM.  Below the image are the letters "STEM" in red simulated braille and black print.text followed with STEM</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ A major outcome of this project was to examine the research that has been conducted in STEM education for students with visual impairments.  A comprehensive database was created and is part of the open-access materials found on our website.  A searchable database was created that cataloged all articles in APA citation as well as a creation of an overall report noting trends and gaps in research.  Within the created national agenda document, there is a call to action, noting the needed research for the field.  The gathering of all those committed to STEM research allows for the capacity to conduct future research built upon the findings of this project.  Research projects have already begun with partners within the project examining tactile graphic creation and education.   All those invited to the conference worked together to identify causes of under-representation of persons with visual impairments in STEM careers.  Persons invited to the project included current leading researchers, developers, parents, recent graduates and teachers of students with visual impairments. The goals produced as part of this project, if and when achieved, will work to increase representation of persons with visual impairments in STEM courses of study and careers.  The national research agenda was created.  This document is 65 pages long, that includes: 1) the need for the national research agenda, 2) the rationale for the national agenda, 3) development of the national agenda, 4) goal statements, 5) 12 identified areas for which additional research and development should be conducted in order to better promote STEM accessibility for students with visual impairments, 6) a list of our collaborators, 7) references, and 8) citation of the website for which all information of the project is housed.  The planning team has presented about this project and the findings of the research review as well as the creation and information contained within the national research agenda booklet.  Those conferences include:  Association for Education and Rehabilitation of the      Blind and Visually Impaired International Conference - July 2022 OCALICON - November 2022 Michigan State Teachers of Students with Visual      Impairments - Michigan Department of Education - September 2022 Council for Exceptional Children - Spring 2023   The team has also written two articles.  One has been published and one is in press:  Lu, X. &amp; Wild, T. (2022).       Introducing the National Research Agenda for STEM Education for Students      with Visual Impairments.  Division on Visual      ImpairmentEducation Quarterly,  67(3), 14-20.       Available at: http://dvi.uberflip.com/i/1476599-vidbe-q-67-3-summer-back-to-school-issue-2022/1 Wild, T., Smith, D., Kelly, S., Fast, D., Lu, X.       (2022).  Creation of a National Agenda for STEM Education for      Students with Visual Impairments.  Journal of Visual      Impairments and Blindness, 116(5).  First available      online: https://doi.org/10.1177/0145482X221134372    Tiffany Wild has also presented on the agenda as part of her keynote presentation at the International Conference on Disability Inclusion.    In addition, over 2,500 copies of the national agenda booklet have been handed out to educational service centers, state educational agencies, university preparation programs, the American Printing House for the Blind, and other educational agencies upon request.    The website: https://u.osu.edu/nationalresearchstemvisualimpairment/ allows for anyone to access all portions of the project including: bios of the collaborative partners, bios of the subject matter professional partners, news and events, materials from the project such as the PowerPoint and database of STEM articles, resources for educators and researchers, a contact page, and the national research agenda downloadable booklet.  The website also allows people to subscribe to allow for further updates and collaborations opportunities.          Last Modified: 12/19/2022       Submitted by: Tiffany A Wild]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
