<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Creating Opportunities for Visualization of Data: Applying STEM Education Research]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>193101.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>193101</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Mike Ferrara</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mferrara@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922635</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This RAPID study incorporates a diverse project team of scientists and communicators to investigate how people interpret representations of quantitative data regarding COVID-19. Such representations include maps, graphs, and charts, which are commonly used in media such as newspapers, television, websites, and press briefings.  Research indicates that many people have difficulty interpreting the information presented in these representations.  As a result, the public may have limited tools for understanding the severity of the COVID-19 pandemic, which may limit their ability to use the data in making decisions about their risk and effective risk-mitigation actions.  The project responds to this pressing issue by immediately enacting a study to investigate individuals’ understandings and decisions during the pandemic.  It will use this information to develop new approaches to displaying quantitative data that can promote greater understanding.  Such approaches are likely to be useful for increasing scientific and mathematical literacy, and will also be incorporated into undergraduate STEM courses.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The study includes a multi-phase design-research approach to investigating COVID-19 quantitative data representations (QDRs) through an iterative sequence of task-based clinical interviews. In Phase I, the project team will investigate a diverse population to produce differentiated models of participants’ QDR interpretations and juxtapositions of these models that reveal key conceptual categories across participants. In Phase II, the project team will apply findings from Phase I and STEM education research to create research-based, project-designed QDRs while simultaneously investigating the extent to which these QDRs better support individuals’ understanding of the pandemic. In Phase III, the project team will actively disseminate the results, to draw attention to knowledge and products generated by the project. Reflecting the societal implications of COVID-19, the dissemination plan targets both educational and public communication media communities. Collectively, the project activities and deliverables have the potential to produce a deeper understanding and tangible examples of how STEM education research can be used to improve students’ and citizens’ learning and well-being.  Through working directly with members of education and media communities, the project team will improve project exposure and the QDRs made available for public use to ensure that STEM education research impacts not only students’ educational experiences, but also the general public’s ability to interpret quantitative data in ways that positively influence their lives.  This RAPID award is funded by the Improving Undergraduate STEM Education Program in the NSF Education and Human Resources/Division of Undergraduate Education.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/09/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/24/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2032688</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kevin</FirstName>
<LastName>Moore</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kevin C Moore</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[kvcmoore@uga.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000608427</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/09/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Cameron</FirstName>
<LastName>Byerley</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>O</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Cameron O Byerley</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[cbyerley@uga.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000775924</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/09/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Georgia Research Foundation Inc</Name>
<CityName>ATHENS</CityName>
<ZipCode>306021589</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7065425939</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>310 E CAMPUS RD RM 409</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NMJHD63STRC5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF GEORGIA RESEARCH FOUNDATION, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Georgia]]></Name>
<CityName>Athens</CityName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>306021589</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[310 East Campus Rd.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1998</Code>
<Text>IUSE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8209</Code>
<Text>Improv Undergrad STEM Ed(IUSE)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8817</Code>
<Text>STEM Learning &amp; Learning Environments</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0420</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~193101</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>In March 2020 the entire world was impacted significantly by the COVID-19 Pandemic. The COVID-19 Pandemic left citizens of all countries looking for information regarding the risk of the virus so that they could make informed decisions regarding their daily life decisions. Accordingly, there was an abundance of media outlets giving significant attention to the COVID-19 Pandemic and data associated with it. White House Press Briefings, daily news shows, digital and print news outlets, health organization websites, blogs, etc., a citizen (especially one in the US) was hard pressed to have a day pass without encountering numerous opportunities to digest COVID-19 Pandemic data. Although the availability of COVID-19 Pandemic data was significant, this is not to say that it is without issues.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Media, politicians, and health experts alike commonly employed Quantitative Data Representations (QDRs) such as Cartesian graphs (standard and log), tables, bar graphs, pie charts, etc. to convey COVID-19 Pandemic data across their outlets. For instance, the White House Press Briefings frequently used Cartesian graphs to convey infection and mortality trends and predictions. Although well-intentioned, our project team noted that the QDRs used by the media, politicians, and health experts were frequently poorly designed, incorrect, insensitive to mathematics education research, or a combination of the three. Complicating the matter, through a literature review we realized that we, as a field, know very little about how citizens? perceive QDRs for pandemic data.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>This project, titled RAPID: Creating Opportunities for Visualization of Data: Applying STEM Education Research (COVID-TASER), addressed the aforementioned situation by investigating citizens? understandings of QDRs conveying COVID-19 Pandemic data. The project team, consisting of health and education experts, focused on citizens in multiple countries including the United States, South Korea, and Kenya. In doing so, the project extended prior work in the areas of mathematics education, public health, and statistics education in order to better understand and respond to citizens? data interpretations and risk assessment. Three interrelated research questions guided the project: <em>RQ1</em>:&nbsp;How do people understand media and non-media QDRs of COVID-19 data? QDRs include graphs, charts with percentages, videos, and epidemiological models. <em>RQ2</em>:&nbsp;What reasons do people give to explain their choices about social distancing, and what data do they report as important for social distancing behavior choices?</p> <p><em>RQ3</em>:&nbsp;What improvements can be made to QDRs so as to better convey epidemic and pandemic data?</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>COVID-TASER addressed these questions by enacting an iterative, multi-phase study with United States, South Korean, and Kenyan citizens. The first phase of the study implemented a series of clinical interviews that produced knowledge on citizens? perceptions of QDRs. This knowledge, in combination with the project team?s expertise, was used to design QDRs that are more sensitive to citizens? perceptions of QDRs and risk. The second phase of the study implemented a series of clinical interviews and surveys to gain insights into citizens? perceptions of the project-designed QDRs. Furthermore, during this phase the project team shifted its focus to increase attention on vaccine data as compared to a focus restricted to pandemic mortality and infection rates. As this phase of the study progressed, the project team refined the project-based QDRs to incorporate ongoing findings and better support citizens in making accurate assessments of their vaccine, infection, and mortality risks. By situating the project with citizens from multiple countries, COVID-TASER produces research-based and public health driven deliverables that improve citizens? risk assessment and behavior.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>COVID-TASER contributed important knowledge to mathematics education, statistics education, and public health. More specifically, the project advanced attempts to translate mathematics and statistics education research in ways that impacts society at a broader level. The generated products which include research knowledge and project-designed QDRs fill a pressing need for academic work that spreads beyond the classroom or lab settings. For example, COVID-TASER helped clarify the manner in which individuals assess risk as it relates to pandemic data, and it produced QDRs that incorporated such knowledge so that society can be better prepared to respond to future pandemics. Beyond its research and societal contributions, the project generated knowledge and products have been disseminated to broader communities through numerous media outlets, a project website, and scholarly publications and presentations geared toward research and practitioner communities. The accessible project products (see: www.covidtaser.com) provide a model program for translating academic research in mathematics and statistics education to the public health arena.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/26/2022<br>      Modified by: Kevin&nbsp;C&nbsp;Moore</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2032688/2032688_10683964_1666721624982_ScreenShot2022-10-25at14.12.54--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2032688/2032688_10683964_1666721624982_ScreenShot2022-10-25at14.12.54--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Website Landing Page"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2032688/2032688_10683964_1666721624982_ScreenShot2022-10-25at14.12.54--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Website Landing Page"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Website Landing Page</div> <div class="imageCredit">Project Team</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Kevin&nbsp;C&nbsp;Moore</div> <div class="imageTitle">Website Landing Page</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2032688/2032688_10683964_1666721657394_ScreenShot2022-05-11at10.29.48AM--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2032688/2032688_10683964_1666721657394_ScreenShot2022-05-11at10.29.48AM--rgov-800width.jpg" title="RRT User Location"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2032688/2032688_10683964_1666721657394_ScreenShot2022-05-11at10.29.48AM--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="RRT User Location"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">RRT User Location</div> <div class="imageCredit">Project Team</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Kevin&nbsp;C&nbsp;Moore</div> <div class="imageTitle">RRT User Location</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2032688/2032688_10683964_1666721692328_ScreenShot2022-10-25at14.13.00--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2032688/2032688_10683964_1666721692328_ScreenShot2022-10-25at14.13.00--rgov-800width.jpg" title="RRT"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2032688/2032688_10683964_1666721692328_ScreenShot2022-10-25at14.13.00--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="RRT"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">RRT</div> <div class="imageCredit">Project Team</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Kevin&nbsp;C&nbsp;Moore</div> <div class="imageTitle">RRT</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2032688/2032688_10683964_1666721742245_ScreenShot2022-10-25at14.13.04--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2032688/2032688_10683964_1666721742245_ScreenShot2022-10-25at14.13.04--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Projection Tool"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2032688/2032688_10683964_1666721742245_ScreenShot2022-10-25at14.13.04--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Projection Tool"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Projection Tool</div> <div class="imageCredit">Project Team</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Kevin&nbsp;C&nbsp;Moore</div> <div class="imageTitle">Projection Tool</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2032688/2032688_10683964_1666721790077_ScreenShot2022-10-25at14.13.09--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2032688/2032688_10683964_1666721790077_ScreenShot2022-10-25at14.13.09--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Log Tool"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2032688/2032688_10683964_1666721790077_ScreenShot2022-10-25at14.13.09--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Log Tool"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Log Tool</div> <div class="imageCredit">Project Team</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Kevin&nbsp;C&nbsp;Moore</div> <div class="imageTitle">Log Tool</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2032688/2032688_10683964_1666721856725_ScreenShot2022-10-25at14.13.15--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2032688/2032688_10683964_1666721856725_ScreenShot2022-10-25at14.13.15--rgov-800width.jpg" title="RRT Prompt"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2032688/2032688_10683964_1666721856725_ScreenShot2022-10-25at14.13.15--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="RRT Prompt"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">RRT Prompt</div> <div class="imageCredit">Project Team</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Kevin&nbsp;C&nbsp;Moore</div> <div class="imageTitle">RRT Prompt</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ In March 2020 the entire world was impacted significantly by the COVID-19 Pandemic. The COVID-19 Pandemic left citizens of all countries looking for information regarding the risk of the virus so that they could make informed decisions regarding their daily life decisions. Accordingly, there was an abundance of media outlets giving significant attention to the COVID-19 Pandemic and data associated with it. White House Press Briefings, daily news shows, digital and print news outlets, health organization websites, blogs, etc., a citizen (especially one in the US) was hard pressed to have a day pass without encountering numerous opportunities to digest COVID-19 Pandemic data. Although the availability of COVID-19 Pandemic data was significant, this is not to say that it is without issues.     Media, politicians, and health experts alike commonly employed Quantitative Data Representations (QDRs) such as Cartesian graphs (standard and log), tables, bar graphs, pie charts, etc. to convey COVID-19 Pandemic data across their outlets. For instance, the White House Press Briefings frequently used Cartesian graphs to convey infection and mortality trends and predictions. Although well-intentioned, our project team noted that the QDRs used by the media, politicians, and health experts were frequently poorly designed, incorrect, insensitive to mathematics education research, or a combination of the three. Complicating the matter, through a literature review we realized that we, as a field, know very little about how citizens? perceive QDRs for pandemic data.     This project, titled RAPID: Creating Opportunities for Visualization of Data: Applying STEM Education Research (COVID-TASER), addressed the aforementioned situation by investigating citizens? understandings of QDRs conveying COVID-19 Pandemic data. The project team, consisting of health and education experts, focused on citizens in multiple countries including the United States, South Korea, and Kenya. In doing so, the project extended prior work in the areas of mathematics education, public health, and statistics education in order to better understand and respond to citizens? data interpretations and risk assessment. Three interrelated research questions guided the project: RQ1: How do people understand media and non-media QDRs of COVID-19 data? QDRs include graphs, charts with percentages, videos, and epidemiological models. RQ2: What reasons do people give to explain their choices about social distancing, and what data do they report as important for social distancing behavior choices?  RQ3: What improvements can be made to QDRs so as to better convey epidemic and pandemic data?     COVID-TASER addressed these questions by enacting an iterative, multi-phase study with United States, South Korean, and Kenyan citizens. The first phase of the study implemented a series of clinical interviews that produced knowledge on citizens? perceptions of QDRs. This knowledge, in combination with the project team?s expertise, was used to design QDRs that are more sensitive to citizens? perceptions of QDRs and risk. The second phase of the study implemented a series of clinical interviews and surveys to gain insights into citizens? perceptions of the project-designed QDRs. Furthermore, during this phase the project team shifted its focus to increase attention on vaccine data as compared to a focus restricted to pandemic mortality and infection rates. As this phase of the study progressed, the project team refined the project-based QDRs to incorporate ongoing findings and better support citizens in making accurate assessments of their vaccine, infection, and mortality risks. By situating the project with citizens from multiple countries, COVID-TASER produces research-based and public health driven deliverables that improve citizens? risk assessment and behavior.     COVID-TASER contributed important knowledge to mathematics education, statistics education, and public health. More specifically, the project advanced attempts to translate mathematics and statistics education research in ways that impacts society at a broader level. The generated products which include research knowledge and project-designed QDRs fill a pressing need for academic work that spreads beyond the classroom or lab settings. For example, COVID-TASER helped clarify the manner in which individuals assess risk as it relates to pandemic data, and it produced QDRs that incorporated such knowledge so that society can be better prepared to respond to future pandemics. Beyond its research and societal contributions, the project generated knowledge and products have been disseminated to broader communities through numerous media outlets, a project website, and scholarly publications and presentations geared toward research and practitioner communities. The accessible project products (see: www.covidtaser.com) provide a model program for translating academic research in mathematics and statistics education to the public health arena.          Last Modified: 10/26/2022       Submitted by: Kevin C Moore]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
