<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[EAGER: Integrating Genotype, Phenotype, and Environment to Identify Biomarkers of Coronavirus Disease Severity and Transmission]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>297382.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>297382</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08090300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IOS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joanna Shisler</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jshisler@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925368</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Proposed in response to a “Dear colleague letter” to fund research to fight the coronavirus pandemic, this project will study the impact of obesity, diabetes, and gender on disease severity and transmission in a mouse model of coronavirus disease. Mouse models must be used to study this disease since humans cannot be infected due to ethical reasons. Obese and diabetic people, along with males, are at a higher risk for severe coronavirus disease, which is concerning since 42% of Americans are obese, 30% are pre-diabetic, and 9.4% have diabetes, while 49.2% are male. It is currently unknown why these groups of people are at higher risk for severe disease, a question that must be answered to develop effective treatments and public health campaigns. The value of this research to the taxpayers is that the information gained will generate data necessary to create effective vaccines and antivirals and identify ways to control coronavirus transmission. In addition, this model will have broad interest to researchers studying the modeling of transmission dynamics, virus-host interactions, immunology, antivirals, and understanding basic virus biology. If successful, these studies will provide a model with the potential to transform the way research with these  SARS-CoV-2  is currently done.   The borader impacts of this work include mentoring a graduate student and undergraduate students in infectious disease research to train the next generation of STEM researchers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Currently, no models to study the impacts of co-morbidities or identify biomarkers of disease severity or transmission on COVID-19 exist. The goals of this project are to define the impact of obesity, diabetes, and sex on disease severity and transmission in the context of different viral and host genotypes using a natural model of mouse infection with the murine hepatitis virus (MHV). The two strains of mice display differential susceptibility to severe disease to the two strains of mouse coronavirus—from asymptomatic to 80% mortality. Furthermore, MHV is highly transmissible mouse-to-mouse, which is unlikely to occur with SARS-CoV-2 infection in mice. Accordingly, this is an excellent model system with which to gather immunological, viral, and other data from infected mice to identify potential biomarkers of severe disease or transmission. Levels of MHV in the blood and oral passages, gene expression, cytokine levels, blood parameters, clinical disease, tissue pathology, and mortality will be the phenotypes used to compare to disease severity and transmission to identify associations. The hypothesis is that pro-inflammatory cytokines (notably interleukin-6, tumor necrosis factor-alpha, and CXCL10) and concentration of virus in the blood or oral passages can be used to predict disease severity and transmission, respectively. These studies will increase understanding of the underlying biology of coronaviruses, virus and host interactions, the genotype, phenotype, and environmental factors influencing coronavirus disease and transmission, and may identify biomarkers to predict disease severity and transmission in people with COVID-19. This RAPID award is made by the Physiological and Structural Systems Cluster in the BIO Division of Integrative Organismal Systems, using funds from the Coronavirus Aid, Relief, and Economic Security (CARES) Act.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/28/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/28/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2032166</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Weger</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME>Jr</PI_SUFX_NAME>
<PI_FULL_NAME>James Weger</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[weger@vt.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000826782</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/28/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lin</FirstName>
<LastName>Kang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lin Kang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[lkang@ulm.vcom.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000826793</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/28/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tanya</FirstName>
<LastName>LeRoith</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Tanya LeRoith</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[TLEROITH@VT.EDU]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000826794</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/28/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sheryl</FirstName>
<LastName>Coutermarsh-Ott</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sheryl Coutermarsh-Ott</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[slc2003@vt.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000826831</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/28/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University</Name>
<CityName>BLACKSBURG</CityName>
<ZipCode>240603359</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5402315281</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>300 TURNER ST NW</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[STE 4200]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>VA09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>QDE5UHE5XD16</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>VIRGINIA POLYTECHNIC INSTITUTE &amp; STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>X6KEFGLHSJX7</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Blacksburg</CityName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>240610001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[360 W Campus Dr, Fralin Life Sci]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>VA09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>158y</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>1N20</Code>
<Name>R&amp;RA CARES Act DEFC N</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>010N2021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[R&RA CARES Act DEFC N]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~297382</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The COVID-19 pandemic has profoundly impacted lives globally, revealing disparities in health outcomes based on various factors, including body weight. With funding generously provided by the National Science Foundation (NSF), we conducted comprehensive research to explore the relationship between obesity and susceptibility to coronavirus disease, including identifying biomarkers associated with severe disease outcomes. Our project used the Murine Hepatitis Virus (MHV) as a close model for the SARS-CoV-2 virus responsible for COVID-19 to help us draw parallels and understand how obesity can influence the course of the disease.</p> <p><strong>Intellectual Merit</strong></p> <p>Our research used a natural infection system involving MHV and two strains of mice with different susceptibility to disease--C57BL/6 (mild disease) and C3H (severe disease). We used a relevant diet-induced model of obesity and used both male and female mice to draw comparisons based on mouse strain, sex, and metabolic status. We also collected blood two days following infection to identify biomarkers associated with severe disease outcomes.</p> <p>The following key outcomes were observed:</p> <p>1.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Increased Disease Severity: Obese C3H mice demonstrated higher mortality than lean mice, indicating increased susceptibility to severe disease. As expected, C3H mice experienced worse disease than C57BL/6 mice.</p> <p>2.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Severe pathology similar to human COVID-19: Obese mice exhibited increased pathology in the liver compared to lean mice, indicative of multi-organ involvement similar to what is observed clinically in humans with severe COVID-19. Importantly, we observed signs of diffuse alveolar damage (DAD), which is the major pathology observed in humans with COVID-19; other mouse models using SARS-CoV-2 do not recapitulate this important clinical finding, suggesting this model is highly relevant to study coronavirus disease.</p> <p>3.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Biomarker identification: We used RNAseq from whole blood to identify thousands of highly differentially expressed genes in MHV-infected mice compared to mock-infected controls. Significantly, many of the genes and pathways overlapped with human COVID-19. Finally, we identified several genes that correlated with disease severity, suggesting these can be used as potential markers for severe disease, potentially allowing critical medical resources to be prioritized for these patients.</p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts</strong></p> <p><strong>1.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </strong><strong>Public Health: </strong>Understanding the link between obesity and COVID-19 has critical public health implications. Our research can help inform guidelines on how different sub-populations should protect themselves against COVID-19 and could lead to targeted therapeutic approaches for obese individuals.<strong></strong></p> <p><strong>2.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </strong><strong>Policy: </strong>The findings from this study could inform public health policies, including vaccination strategies and guidelines for healthcare resource allocation by identifying obesity as a significant risk factor that needs attention.<strong></strong></p> <p><strong>3.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </strong><strong>Education: </strong>Our work can be transformed into an educational module for biology and health sciences students to understand the impact of lifestyle factors like obesity on infectious diseases, fostering a more scientifically literate society.<strong></strong></p> <p><strong>4.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </strong><strong>Equity: </strong>Obesity disproportionately affects certain socio-economic and racial/ethnic groups. By understanding the extra risks these groups may face regarding COVID-19, interventions can be designed more equitably.<strong></strong></p> <p><strong>Conclusion</strong></p> <p>Our research offers valuable insights into how obesity modulates the severity of coronavirus infections. Not only does this have intellectual merit in advancing our scientific understanding of the virus and its interactions with comorbidities like obesity, but it also has broader societal impacts in shaping public health initiatives, education, and equitable healthcare delivery.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/20/2023<br>      Modified by: James&nbsp;Weger</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The COVID-19 pandemic has profoundly impacted lives globally, revealing disparities in health outcomes based on various factors, including body weight. With funding generously provided by the National Science Foundation (NSF), we conducted comprehensive research to explore the relationship between obesity and susceptibility to coronavirus disease, including identifying biomarkers associated with severe disease outcomes. Our project used the Murine Hepatitis Virus (MHV) as a close model for the SARS-CoV-2 virus responsible for COVID-19 to help us draw parallels and understand how obesity can influence the course of the disease.  Intellectual Merit  Our research used a natural infection system involving MHV and two strains of mice with different susceptibility to disease--C57BL/6 (mild disease) and C3H (severe disease). We used a relevant diet-induced model of obesity and used both male and female mice to draw comparisons based on mouse strain, sex, and metabolic status. We also collected blood two days following infection to identify biomarkers associated with severe disease outcomes.  The following key outcomes were observed:  1.     Increased Disease Severity: Obese C3H mice demonstrated higher mortality than lean mice, indicating increased susceptibility to severe disease. As expected, C3H mice experienced worse disease than C57BL/6 mice.  2.     Severe pathology similar to human COVID-19: Obese mice exhibited increased pathology in the liver compared to lean mice, indicative of multi-organ involvement similar to what is observed clinically in humans with severe COVID-19. Importantly, we observed signs of diffuse alveolar damage (DAD), which is the major pathology observed in humans with COVID-19; other mouse models using SARS-CoV-2 do not recapitulate this important clinical finding, suggesting this model is highly relevant to study coronavirus disease.  3.     Biomarker identification: We used RNAseq from whole blood to identify thousands of highly differentially expressed genes in MHV-infected mice compared to mock-infected controls. Significantly, many of the genes and pathways overlapped with human COVID-19. Finally, we identified several genes that correlated with disease severity, suggesting these can be used as potential markers for severe disease, potentially allowing critical medical resources to be prioritized for these patients.  Broader Impacts  1.     Public Health: Understanding the link between obesity and COVID-19 has critical public health implications. Our research can help inform guidelines on how different sub-populations should protect themselves against COVID-19 and could lead to targeted therapeutic approaches for obese individuals.  2.     Policy: The findings from this study could inform public health policies, including vaccination strategies and guidelines for healthcare resource allocation by identifying obesity as a significant risk factor that needs attention.  3.     Education: Our work can be transformed into an educational module for biology and health sciences students to understand the impact of lifestyle factors like obesity on infectious diseases, fostering a more scientifically literate society.  4.     Equity: Obesity disproportionately affects certain socio-economic and racial/ethnic groups. By understanding the extra risks these groups may face regarding COVID-19, interventions can be designed more equitably.  Conclusion  Our research offers valuable insights into how obesity modulates the severity of coronavirus infections. Not only does this have intellectual merit in advancing our scientific understanding of the virus and its interactions with comorbidities like obesity, but it also has broader societal impacts in shaping public health initiatives, education, and equitable healthcare delivery.       Last Modified: 09/20/2023       Submitted by: James Weger]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
