<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Examining the Innovative Ecosystem During the COVID-19 Pandemic]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>200000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>200000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SMA</Abbreviation>
<LongName>SBE Off Of Multidisciplinary Activities</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Mary Feeney</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mfeeney@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927197</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The onset of the COVID-19 pandemic not only threatens the health and safety of communities but also the operation and survival of firms and industries that provide essential products and services to the innovative ecosystem. This crisis has hit small businesses (firms with fewer than 500 employees) particularly hard. Obtaining access to emergency financial resources such as the Paycheck Protection Program and forgivable loans offered by federal and state government agencies remains extremely difficult for many U.S. small firms. This holds especially for firms owned by members of underrepresented groups that include minorities, women, and veterans. This project has two primary aims in tracking the different types of small high-tech firms. First, we aim to understand the unique challenges and opportunities that small high-tech firms face in adapting to this unexpected shift and in introducing innovations designed to combat COVID-19. Second, we aim to evaluate state and federal responses to the pandemic by estimating their impacts on the activity of small high-tech firms that drive U.S. innovation. We plan to construct a comprehensive and scalable nationwide database that tracks U.S. small high-tech firms that are current or potential suppliers of critical public heath technologies related to pandemic response. We will make this database publicly available to accelerate broad systematic research. Our results will include detailed insights on the impacts of the pandemic on small business performance. Moreover, the resulting public databases and interactive dashboard will enable policymakers and businesses to identify new opportunities to empower small high-tech firms to grow and supply much needed expertise and resources during the pandemic.   &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;We examine the impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on the U.S. innovative ecosystem. We focus on small high-tech firms (with fewer than 500 employees), including firms owned by members of underrepresented groups (minorities, women, and veterans). Small firms are potential sources of innovation in combating COVID-19, but remain especially vulnerable to the unprecedented health, social, and economic risks arising from this pandemic. We have two primary research aims. First, we seek to characterize changes in the landscape of small high-tech firms resulting from the ongoing pandemic and policy responses. We will build a comprehensive, interactive database to capture shifts in the spatial and temporal patterns of the innovation ecosystem. Second, we seek to use this database for econometric analysis to evaluate the differential impact of state and federal pandemic policies on the performance of small high-tech firms. Specific deliverables include: (i) detailed descriptive statistics characterizing changes in concentrations of business activity in different sectors with geographic precision; (ii) a public dashboard with an interactive map for visualizing changes in the innovative ecosystem at state- and sector-levels; (iii) a public data repository providing access to all aggregated data files used to create our visualization tool; and (iv) econometric models exploiting variation in state policies to determine the causal impacts of these policies on small firms. Our intended broader impact is a clearer picture of which areas of the innovative ecosystem are most susceptible to the effects of COVID-19. We will identify firm-level characteristics that indicate which firms are most and least resilient, as well as those best positioned to assist with government countermeasures against the pandemic. This will illuminate priorities for public and private sector efforts to rebuild innovative activity and allocate support resources more effectively.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/10/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/10/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2032914</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Amol</FirstName>
<LastName>Joshi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Amol M Joshi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[joshia@wfu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000697188</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lauren</FirstName>
<LastName>Lanahan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lauren Lanahan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[llanahan@uoregon.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000697695</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Oregon Eugene</Name>
<CityName>EUGENE</CityName>
<ZipCode>974031657</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5413465131</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1585 E 13TH AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OR04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>Z3FGN9MF92U2</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF OREGON</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>L17DBQFXJVJ6</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Oregon]]></Name>
<CityName>Eugene</CityName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<ZipCode>974035219</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5219 University of Oregon]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OR04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>125Y</Code>
<Text>Science of Science</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~200000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>High-tech ventures play a central role not only in producing scientific contributions, but also in translating innovations to yield economic value. Yet, tracing such activity in a rigorous and systematic manner is challenging. This is most notably due to data constraints in tracking the activity of young ventures.</p> <p>With support from the National Science Foundation, we drew upon rich and heretofore relatively untapped data to identify a critical population of young firms &ndash; specifically, ventures that seek to transact with the U.S. federal government. As our core data, we pulled administrative federal records available via the System for Awards Management (SAM) and their procurement activity as reported in USASpending.gov. We augmented this granular data with an extensive set of economic and demographic indicators (collected at the firm, census tract, county, state, and national levels). With this data, we have been able not only to examine a unique and valuable angle of the U.S. innovative ecosystem, but also to unpack changes in the landscape and trace the contributions of high-tech ventures.</p> <p>For this project, we achieved the following aims: (i) characterizing the national ecosystem of innovative U.S. high-tech ventures; (ii) evaluating the impacts of policy decisions on that ecosystem; and (iii) publishing a comprehensive, flexible database tracing the population of U.S. ventures that are part of the innovative ecosystem. The public platform includes a dashboard with customizable mapping functionalities designed as a reference for scientists and policymakers, as well as interested citizens (APPRISE Platform website: https://appriseplatform.org).</p> <p>The results from this project are manifold. As a baseline, we examine the antecedent factors that motivate ventures to initiate engagement with the government. Paying attention to a range of external and internal factors to the firm, we find evidence that areas with greater access to capital infrastructure decrease the rate of firm-government engagement, while firm-based growth capabilities increase such choice. Figure 1 illustrates the geographic distribution of all U.S. high-tech ventures in contrast to the sub-set of ventures that initiated firm-government engagement.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>Building upon this work, we examine the interactions of such ventures with the U.S. federal government. Prior work chiefly emphasizes firm-government transactions involving the government providing resources as a key <em>input</em> for firms via grants, subsidies, and loans. Yet, the scale and nature of interactions of ventures with their governments suggest that such characterization of firm-government relationships is missing or overlooking a different, but critical form of engagement. Governments can also serve as customers for ventures<em> </em>(i.e., purchasing key <em>output</em> from firms)<em>. </em>Our empirical analyses of over 200,000 ventures reveal intriguing performance trends. We observe a significant financial upside for these firms. Moreover, these firms tend to provide services and support <em>to </em>the federal government rather than seek services and support <em>from </em>the federal government.</p> <p>Furthermore, in tracing broader trends of the innovative ecosystem, we turn to U.S. cities. While the number and activity of high-tech ventures are important metrics in determining the overall health of surrounding innovative and economic conditions, ecosystems benefit from having higher levels of equity in the distribution of entrepreneurial resources. Yet current conditions are far from equitable. We document resource disparities, most notably among financial lending institutions in supporting minority-owned high-tech ventures.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/28/2023<br>      Modified by: Lauren&nbsp;Lanahan</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2032914/2032914_10695067_1682714457575_Figure1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2032914/2032914_10695067_1682714457575_Figure1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Geographic Distribution of U.S. High-tech Startups and Firm-Government Engagement"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2032914/2032914_10695067_1682714457575_Figure1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Geographic Distribution of U.S. High-tech Startups and Firm-Government Engagement"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Maps illustrate aggregate count of high-tech U.S. ventures by FIPS founded from 2015 ? 2017. Panel A reports the population of high-tech ventures (1,075,021 firms); Panel B reports high-tech ventures entering SAM by firm age 3 (25,661 firms).</div> <div class="imageCredit">Lanahan, L., Hemmatian, I., Johnson, E. and Joshi, A.</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Lauren&nbsp;Lanahan</div> <div class="imageTitle">Geographic Distribution of U.S. High-tech Startups and Firm-Government Engagement</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ High-tech ventures play a central role not only in producing scientific contributions, but also in translating innovations to yield economic value. Yet, tracing such activity in a rigorous and systematic manner is challenging. This is most notably due to data constraints in tracking the activity of young ventures.  With support from the National Science Foundation, we drew upon rich and heretofore relatively untapped data to identify a critical population of young firms &ndash; specifically, ventures that seek to transact with the U.S. federal government. As our core data, we pulled administrative federal records available via the System for Awards Management (SAM) and their procurement activity as reported in USASpending.gov. We augmented this granular data with an extensive set of economic and demographic indicators (collected at the firm, census tract, county, state, and national levels). With this data, we have been able not only to examine a unique and valuable angle of the U.S. innovative ecosystem, but also to unpack changes in the landscape and trace the contributions of high-tech ventures.  For this project, we achieved the following aims: (i) characterizing the national ecosystem of innovative U.S. high-tech ventures; (ii) evaluating the impacts of policy decisions on that ecosystem; and (iii) publishing a comprehensive, flexible database tracing the population of U.S. ventures that are part of the innovative ecosystem. The public platform includes a dashboard with customizable mapping functionalities designed as a reference for scientists and policymakers, as well as interested citizens (APPRISE Platform website: https://appriseplatform.org).  The results from this project are manifold. As a baseline, we examine the antecedent factors that motivate ventures to initiate engagement with the government. Paying attention to a range of external and internal factors to the firm, we find evidence that areas with greater access to capital infrastructure decrease the rate of firm-government engagement, while firm-based growth capabilities increase such choice. Figure 1 illustrates the geographic distribution of all U.S. high-tech ventures in contrast to the sub-set of ventures that initiated firm-government engagement.    Building upon this work, we examine the interactions of such ventures with the U.S. federal government. Prior work chiefly emphasizes firm-government transactions involving the government providing resources as a key input for firms via grants, subsidies, and loans. Yet, the scale and nature of interactions of ventures with their governments suggest that such characterization of firm-government relationships is missing or overlooking a different, but critical form of engagement. Governments can also serve as customers for ventures (i.e., purchasing key output from firms). Our empirical analyses of over 200,000 ventures reveal intriguing performance trends. We observe a significant financial upside for these firms. Moreover, these firms tend to provide services and support to the federal government rather than seek services and support from the federal government.  Furthermore, in tracing broader trends of the innovative ecosystem, we turn to U.S. cities. While the number and activity of high-tech ventures are important metrics in determining the overall health of surrounding innovative and economic conditions, ecosystems benefit from having higher levels of equity in the distribution of entrepreneurial resources. Yet current conditions are far from equitable. We document resource disparities, most notably among financial lending institutions in supporting minority-owned high-tech ventures.             Last Modified: 04/28/2023       Submitted by: Lauren Lanahan]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
