<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Understanding the Process of Social Change through the Transitional Period of the COVID-19 Pandemic]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>19015.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>19015</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jeffrey Mantz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jmantz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927783</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Effective management of COVID-19 requires public adherence to directives reliant on behavior change. This research will investigate how diverse groups of individuals understand, process, and react to risk and uncertainty posed by COVID-19, at both a personal and a collective level.  It examines how social changes are impacted by the complex, often contradictory and emotion-laden communications about the pandemic.  Special attention will be given to impacts of a perceived change in the projected course of the pandemic amidst concern about the future. Under these conditions, how do people modify their life projects or demonstrate resiliency? Results from the work will be communicated directly to health experts to ensure that insights will be relevant to current and subsequent waves of the pandemic. The research will provide training for a graduate and an undergraduate student in social epidemiological research. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research augments processual models of social change through the addition of large-scale data from a diverse population during the pandemic. This theory posits a sequence of changes involving a period of break-down, followed by a transitional period that is navigated through human relationships, and culminating with the establishment of new social orders and structures. Using media analysis, and repeated waves of ethnographic observation and interviewing, the researchers will collect data that address how individual variation in the consumption of knowledge, affective states, and ideologies affect the timing and sequential elements of social change, and how such variation ultimately drives the behaviors that affect disease transmission (e.g., wearing masks, observing social distancing). The work provides a novel test of this sequence in communities displaying varying levels of commitment to collectivist ideologies and social order.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/05/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/05/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2032407</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Katherine</FirstName>
<LastName>Mason</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Katherine A Mason</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[katherine_mason@brown.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000727791</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/05/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yifeng</FirstName>
<LastName>Cai</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Yifeng Cai</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[yifeng_cai@brown.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000792204</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/05/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Brown University</Name>
<CityName>PROVIDENCE</CityName>
<ZipCode>029129127</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4018632777</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1 PROSPECT ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>RI01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>E3FDXZ6TBHW3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>BROWN UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>E3FDXZ6TBHW3</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Brown Univesity]]></Name>
<CityName>Providence</CityName>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>029129002</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[350 Eddy Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>RI01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>158Y</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1390</Code>
<Text>CULTURAL ANTHROPOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~19015</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><div class="page" title="Page 2"> <div class="layoutArea"> <div class="column"> <div class="page" title="Page 2"> <div class="layoutArea"> <div class="column"> <p>We conducted over two years of ethnographic research in Shanghai and online between June 2020 and December 2022, interviewing dozens of people, observing social spaces, and closely following online communities. We observed two main phases of popular compliance with Covid-19 control measures in urban China.&nbsp;</p> <p>The first phase, which lasted from January 2020 through mid-2022, was characterized by a high level of willfull, relatively enthusiastic compliance among Chinese citizens in urban China. We found that mass compliance was driven by a combination of self-interest, nationalistic pride, and trust in the competence of the central government. These factors grew out of urban Chinese citizens&rsquo; appreciation for the ways in which effective infectious disease control relies on a symbiosis between what our interlocutors called the &ldquo;big environment&rdquo; (<em>dahuanjing</em>) and the actions and interests of &ldquo;ordinary people&rdquo; (<em>laobaixing</em>).&nbsp;<em>Dahuanjing</em>&nbsp;refers both to the natural environment and to the social, political, and economic en- vironments.&nbsp;<em>Laobaixing</em>&nbsp;refers to those who see themselves as &ldquo;typical&rdquo; citizens in relation to the Chinese Party-state. Popular understandings of how a healthy &ldquo;big environment&rdquo; benefits &ldquo;ordinary people&rdquo; are key to understanding Chinese compliance with COVID-19 controls.</p> </div> </div> </div> <p>Beginning in mid-2022, however, this high-level of compliance was relaced by growing discontent with, and doubts in, the government's strict zero-Covid policy. This discontent culminated in a series of unusual public protests in late 2022 and the termination of zero-Covid. However, we found that despite a dramatic change in people&rsquo;s opinions about their government&rsquo;s actions, the principles guiding those attitudes have remained remarkably consistent. Those we spoke with are still driven by self-interest and pride in their nation. They still understand and appreciate that the individual actions of ordinary people are intimately intertwined with the health and stability of their society. What changed was the trust that our interlocutors once had in the competence and good intentions of the central government. Without that trust, the public&rsquo;s understandings of what was in their own self-interest and the interest of their nation was turned on its head.</p> <p>Our interlocutors no longer trusted that the state had the people&rsquo;s best interests in mind, and they no longer felt that the state&rsquo;s Covid control measures were or should be a source of national pride. Instead, they felt hopeless about a life filled with uncertainty and fear and had growing doubts about the legitimacy of China&rsquo;s pandemic control measures. This hopelessness and doubt produced dynamic discussions and debates about power, authority, class, and the legitimacy of the state.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> </div> </div> </div><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/29/2023<br>      Modified by: Katherine&nbsp;A&nbsp;Mason</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[       We conducted over two years of ethnographic research in Shanghai and online between June 2020 and December 2022, interviewing dozens of people, observing social spaces, and closely following online communities. We observed two main phases of popular compliance with Covid-19 control measures in urban China.   The first phase, which lasted from January 2020 through mid-2022, was characterized by a high level of willfull, relatively enthusiastic compliance among Chinese citizens in urban China. We found that mass compliance was driven by a combination of self-interest, nationalistic pride, and trust in the competence of the central government. These factors grew out of urban Chinese citizens’ appreciation for the ways in which effective infectious disease control relies on a symbiosis between what our interlocutors called the "big environment" (dahuanjing) and the actions and interests of "ordinary people" (laobaixing). Dahuanjing refers both to the natural environment and to the social, political, and economic en- vironments. Laobaixing refers to those who see themselves as "typical" citizens in relation to the Chinese Party-state. Popular understandings of how a healthy "big environment" benefits "ordinary people" are key to understanding Chinese compliance with COVID-19 controls.     Beginning in mid-2022, however, this high-level of compliance was relaced by growing discontent with, and doubts in, the government's strict zero-Covid policy. This discontent culminated in a series of unusual public protests in late 2022 and the termination of zero-Covid. However, we found that despite a dramatic change in people’s opinions about their government’s actions, the principles guiding those attitudes have remained remarkably consistent. Those we spoke with are still driven by self-interest and pride in their nation. They still understand and appreciate that the individual actions of ordinary people are intimately intertwined with the health and stability of their society. What changed was the trust that our interlocutors once had in the competence and good intentions of the central government. Without that trust, the public’s understandings of what was in their own self-interest and the interest of their nation was turned on its head.  Our interlocutors no longer trusted that the state had the people’s best interests in mind, and they no longer felt that the state’s Covid control measures were or should be a source of national pride. Instead, they felt hopeless about a life filled with uncertainty and fear and had growing doubts about the legitimacy of China’s pandemic control measures. This hopelessness and doubt produced dynamic discussions and debates about power, authority, class, and the legitimacy of the state.                   Last Modified: 08/29/2023       Submitted by: Katherine A Mason]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
