<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>RAPID: Collaborative Research: Low-Cost, Non-invasive, Fast Sample Collection System for COVID-19 Viral Load Level Diagnosis: Point-of-Care and Environmental Testing</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>30000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>30000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ron Joslin</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rjoslin@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927030</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Pandemics can have a devastating impact on societies: collapsing local economies, halting trade, weakening national security and overwhelming healthcare capacity. To combat infectious pandemics, rapid, effective diagnostic testing combined with contact tracing and quarantine is needed. This will help officials manage infections while minimizing the effect of the disease on the economy, on society, and on our healthcare system. Further, effective sentinel monitoring of local environments can detect the presence of dangerous levels of virus, preventing mass spreading events. Unfortunately, the COVID-19 pandemic has exposed a critical weakness in health care security infrastructure: the deficiency in our ability to conduct rapid, simple, point-of-care diagnostic and environmental sample collection and testing. The goal in this research is to develop inexpensive, massively deployable rapid diagnostic and sentinel systems for detecting respiratory illness and airborne viral threats. Because the virus is transmitted through droplets in the breath, this system is expected to collect enough sample from one minute of breathing to be used in existing testing units. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This technology is based on continuous dropwise condensation (CDC) which is capable of efficiently extracting particulate (viral) loads from humidified air within a minute. The collection system and supporting instrumentation is simple and can be readily integrated with a well-designed patient interface that is non-invasive, compatible with current rt-PCR sampling and which can be mass produced cheaply. Additionally, CDC, due to its surface collection method, can be modified readily into either a point-of-care, rapid diagnostic test, or into an environmental sentinel sampling/testing system.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/20/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/20/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2032501</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jeffrey</FirstName>
<LastName>Ruberti</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jeffrey W Ruberti</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>j.ruberti@neu.edu</EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000099263</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/20/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Northeastern University</Name>
<CityName>BOSTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>021155005</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6173733004</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>360 HUNTINGTON AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[177-500]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>001423631</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORTHEASTERN UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001423631</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Northeastern University]]></Name>
<CityName>Boston</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021155005</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[360 Huntington Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1443</Code>
<Text>FD-Fluid Dynamics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~30000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Award Title</strong>:</p> <p><em>RAPID: Collaborative Research: Low-Cost, Non-invasive, Fast Sample Collection System for COVID-19 Viral Load Level Diagnosis: Point-of-Care and Environmental Testing</em></p> <p><strong>Purpose:</strong></p> <p>The research conducted was designed to advance our ability to collect and detect COVID-19 directly from the exhaled breath from human lungs. Breath collection methods remove the need to perform deep nasal swabbing and sample directly from the source of the contagious airborn infection.&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Our project: Task 4</strong>: <em>Design in compatibility with current diagnostic testing and the potential for testing in situ</em>.</p> <p>The part of the work performed by our team at Northeastern University was to design methods that can immobilize the virus on glass and to determine if we can identify the virus through an advanced labelling technique that will enable rapid testing that is equivalent in accuracy to PCR and potentially much faster.&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Intellectual Merit</strong>&nbsp;Part 1: <em>Virus Capture and Labelling</em>.</p> <p>We learned from our project that we can capture and label virus on a glass plate. This work demonstrated the feasibility of our fundamental approach which requires immobilizing, cracking open the viral coat and labelling the virus RNA affirmatively. To accomplish the task, we used a pseudotyped virus which expresses the same viral coat proteins that are found on the SARS-CoV-2 virus. The virus was exposed to a plated coated with cell receptors and a cheaper aptamer and its genome was labelled. There was some difficulty transferring our capture method from a plastic to glass plate, but further optimization should solve that problem. In summary, this part of the project was successful</p> <p><br /><strong>Part 2.</strong> <em>Demonstrate the feasibility of detecting the labelled virus</em>.</p> <p>To accomplish part 2, a group of students attempted to produce a system based on Blu-Ray technology to rapidly scan and read the glass plate after the virus was captured and labelled. The student team spent 6 months designing a fluid transfer system to "develop" the viral signal and then they designed a prototype scanning system which has the potential to detect the virus in under 10 minutes. While we did not have adequate funding to fully test the system, the student demonstrated theoretical viability and designed a solution which could literally solve the testing problems facing the US.&nbsp; &nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts</strong></p> <p><strong></strong>The work naturally could have enormous impact by producing a non-invasive system that can detect if individuals are COVID positive. In addition, our project was performed primarily by undergraduates who are working towards STEM degrees. The Capstone design team comprised six female undergraduate bioengineers who completed their training with this project and have all now graduated from the University and moving on to STEM careers.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/14/2022<br>      Modified by: Jeffrey&nbsp;W&nbsp;Ruberti</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Award Title:  RAPID: Collaborative Research: Low-Cost, Non-invasive, Fast Sample Collection System for COVID-19 Viral Load Level Diagnosis: Point-of-Care and Environmental Testing  Purpose:  The research conducted was designed to advance our ability to collect and detect COVID-19 directly from the exhaled breath from human lungs. Breath collection methods remove the need to perform deep nasal swabbing and sample directly from the source of the contagious airborn infection.   Our project: Task 4: Design in compatibility with current diagnostic testing and the potential for testing in situ.  The part of the work performed by our team at Northeastern University was to design methods that can immobilize the virus on glass and to determine if we can identify the virus through an advanced labelling technique that will enable rapid testing that is equivalent in accuracy to PCR and potentially much faster.   Intellectual Merit Part 1: Virus Capture and Labelling.  We learned from our project that we can capture and label virus on a glass plate. This work demonstrated the feasibility of our fundamental approach which requires immobilizing, cracking open the viral coat and labelling the virus RNA affirmatively. To accomplish the task, we used a pseudotyped virus which expresses the same viral coat proteins that are found on the SARS-CoV-2 virus. The virus was exposed to a plated coated with cell receptors and a cheaper aptamer and its genome was labelled. There was some difficulty transferring our capture method from a plastic to glass plate, but further optimization should solve that problem. In summary, this part of the project was successful   Part 2. Demonstrate the feasibility of detecting the labelled virus.  To accomplish part 2, a group of students attempted to produce a system based on Blu-Ray technology to rapidly scan and read the glass plate after the virus was captured and labelled. The student team spent 6 months designing a fluid transfer system to "develop" the viral signal and then they designed a prototype scanning system which has the potential to detect the virus in under 10 minutes. While we did not have adequate funding to fully test the system, the student demonstrated theoretical viability and designed a solution which could literally solve the testing problems facing the US.      Broader Impacts  The work naturally could have enormous impact by producing a non-invasive system that can detect if individuals are COVID positive. In addition, our project was performed primarily by undergraduates who are working towards STEM degrees. The Capstone design team comprised six female undergraduate bioengineers who completed their training with this project and have all now graduated from the University and moving on to STEM careers.        Last Modified: 01/14/2022       Submitted by: Jeffrey W Ruberti]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
