<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Investigating Public Health and Social Information Disparities During the COVID-19 Pandemic]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>200000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>232000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sara Kiesler</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>skiesler@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928643</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Studying differential COVID-19 responses to trustworthy information will contribute new perspectives and improve our fundamental understanding of the human aspects of information trustworthiness during a pandemic. Although many U.S. residents are heeding restrictive COVID-19 orders and warnings from both official guidance and public health information sources, some individuals are not following official guidance. Simultaneously, the pandemic has spread through major U.S. cities and states in an uneven manner. Moreover, COVID-19 messaging is complicated by evolving guidance and contagion information, and media framing complicates information transmission, shifting public understanding of official guidance. Understanding and evaluating how a population is reacting to these multiple sources of information is a crucial scientific challenge with implications for improving future public policy and more effective crisis mitigation. To better understand differential population responses to this crisis, this interdisciplinary research project will gather Twitter data in Louisiana and Washington State to analyze differential sentiment and language use in responses to health information and public guidance, across assumed age and linked geographic conditions. It will also assess how these differences change given time, location, health, economic, social conditions, and sources of information. Assessing the systematic variation of sentiment and language use across age and then across time, space, context, and information sources will provide vital insight to targeting effective public messaging by public health and government officials during a crisis.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will collect three waves of Twitter and associated data to study differential sentiment and language use in responses to health information and public health guidance concerning COVID-19. This interdisciplinary project seeks to advance knowledge about how disparities in information consumption, as represented by sentiment and language use, vary across sources of information and guidance, across time, geography, socio-demographic characteristics, and health conditions. This project will compare sentiment and language use patterns among a population of Twitter users based on the content of their tweets, and analyze how these characteristics evolve through the recognition of the emergency, the peak of the crisis, and the mitigation of the pandemic in the U.S. The project will use computational methods to understand sentiment patterns and language use on Twitter and link tweets and relevant entities to corresponding longitudinal data about trustworthy information sources, including news media sources and official emergency guidance, policies, and orders. The tweets and entities will be classified for relevance (individual, organization, or bot) with derived age and location. Using timestamps and derived location, the project will associate tweets with daily disease-specific rates and annual demographic and socio-economic information. Data about the surrounding information context, including reporting trends and framing of the crisis, sources of health information, and information-seeking behavior about COVID-19 will provide tools for assessing the validity and reliability of our inferences about the patterns of sentiment and language use. Project findings will contribute to the literature on computational methods, disaster communication, misinformation during crisis events, and disaster resilience, informing future guidance on policy and emergency messaging during a crisis.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/10/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/07/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2032745</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nina</FirstName>
<LastName>Lam</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nina S Lam</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[nlam@lsu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000276929</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kisung</FirstName>
<LastName>Lee</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kisung Lee</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[klee76@lsu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000716270</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sara</FirstName>
<LastName>Curran</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sara Curran</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[scurran@uw.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000738616</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Louisiana State University</Name>
<CityName>BATON ROUGE</CityName>
<ZipCode>708030001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2255782760</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>202 HIMES HALL</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
<StateCode>LA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>LA06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>ECQEYCHRNKJ4</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>LOUISIANA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Louisiana State University and A&M College]]></Name>
<CityName>Baton Rouge</CityName>
<StateCode>LA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>708032701</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>LA06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8060</Code>
<Text>Secure &amp;Trustworthy Cyberspace</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>025Z</Code>
<Text>SaTC: Secure and Trustworthy Cyberspace</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>065Z</Code>
<Text>Human factors for security research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>075Z</Code>
<Text>Artificial Intelligence (AI)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7434</Code>
<Text>CNCI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7913</Code>
<Text>PREM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9102</Code>
<Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002223DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~200000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~16000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2022~16000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This interdisciplinary RAPID project has collected three waves of Twitter and associated time-sensitive data to study differential sentiment and language use in responses to health information and public health guidance concerning COVID-19.</p> <p>The intellectual merits of the project are:</p> <p>(1) The project has collected more than 100 million tweets for three study periods covering the first two COVID-19 surges in Louisiana (LA) and Washington State (WA). To avoid selection bias during data collection, we used geospatial filters instead of specifying certain keywords related to COVID-19. In addition, we have collected entire tweets of selected accounts related to COVID-19 public health messaging, such as media outlets, state public health agencies, and offices of emergency management.</p> <p>(2) The project has compiled various databases including 1) COVID-19 policy data in LA and WA, 2) media outlet sources coded for credibility and political bias, 3) county-level COVID-19 case and death counts in LA and WA, 4) city and county demographics in LA and WA, and 5) academic and think tank initiatives that produced COVID-19 information.&nbsp;</p> <p>(3) The project has coded tweets on tweet function and recommended behaviors to understand health communication from WA/LA health and emergency management agencies during the first two surges of COVID-19 in 2020.&nbsp;</p> <p>(4) The project has analyzed and compared tweeting patterns including sentiment and word usage in the two states to understand inter-state disparities. We have also analyzed and visualized tweeting patterns and sentiment variations across counties or parishes to identify intra-state disparities. In addition, we have examined the public health messaging of governmental accounts in the two states and public engagement related to the messages.</p> <p>(5) The project has created a dataset of fact-checked misinforming claims from the beginning of COVID-19 and is in the process of checking these claims against tweets written in the 48-hours before and after a major policy announcement in WA and LA (e.g., mask mandates) to see 1) what misinformation was spreading and 2) whether there are changes related to policy announcements. This work contributes to conversations about misinformation as well as the relationship between misinformation and policy.</p> <p>(6) The project has used the Ad Fontes Media bias chart to understand what news sources were being shared during the initial stages of COVID-19 as related to political bias. This work contributes to conversations about news consumption during a crisis event, considerations of partisan echo chambers during a crisis event, and overall questions of information trustworthiness.</p> <p>(7) The project has built a dataset of evangelical Protestant churches? and church leaders? Twitter accounts, gathered the tweets put out by these accounts between 2020 and 2022, and is analyzing tweets related to COVID-19 for their content. This work attempts to understand messaging from important religious figures during a crisis.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The broader impacts of the project are:</p> <p>(1) We have built a multi-disciplinary and multi-institution research team to collaboratively work on the proposed research. The team includes computer and environmental scientists at Louisiana State University (LSU) and social scientists at the University of Washington (UW).</p> <p>(2) We have built a project website (https://sites.google.com/view/covid19twitter) to disseminate project outcomes. The website provides basic information of the project, publications from the project, and sample datasets available for download. We have also built an interactive dashboard for data visualization in collaboration with UW?s eSciences Institute.</p> <p>(3) From the collaboration process of our interdisciplinary team, we have designed research questions and hypotheses and published our first group paper in IEEE Access that examines tweeting patterns and public engagement on Twitter related to public health messaging in WA and LA during the early stage of the COVID-19 pandemic. In addition, we proposed a session at the Pacific Sociological Association (PSA) 2023 conference and got accepted to present our various research projects.</p> <p>(4) The project has provided research opportunities for one postdoctoral researcher, six graduate students, and nine undergraduate and post-baccalaureate students including REU students. The undergraduates gained experience producing literature reviews, writing for an academic audience, presenting findings to an interdisciplinary research group, data analysis, and other skills. All the student researchers from the UW are from demographic groups underrepresented in science, engineering, and technology. Their inclusion in the project and our close mentoring creates pathways for them to enter professional positions related to these three areas.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/08/2023<br>      Modified by: Kisung&nbsp;Lee</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2032745/2032745_10676228_1691525502895_psa--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2032745/2032745_10676228_1691525502895_psa--rgov-800width.jpg" title="PSA session"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2032745/2032745_10676228_1691525502895_psa--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="PSA session"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Photos of our session at the Pacific Sociological Association (PSA) 2023 conference</div> <div class="imageCredit">Project team</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Kisung&nbsp;Lee</div> <div class="imageTitle">PSA session</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2032745/2032745_10676228_1691525443647_AverageSentimentScore_WO_RT--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2032745/2032745_10676228_1691525443647_AverageSentimentScore_WO_RT--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Average sentiment scores"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2032745/2032745_10676228_1691525443647_AverageSentimentScore_WO_RT--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Average sentiment scores"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Daily average sentiment scores excluding retweets in Washington and Louisiana</div> <div class="imageCredit">Project Team</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Kisung&nbsp;Lee</div> <div class="imageTitle">Average sentiment scores</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2032745/2032745_10676228_1691525341864_TweetDensity_COVID--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2032745/2032745_10676228_1691525341864_TweetDensity_COVID--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Tweet Density"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2032745/2032745_10676228_1691525341864_TweetDensity_COVID--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Tweet Density"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">County-level COVID-19 tweet density in Washington and Louisiana</div> <div class="imageCredit">Project Team</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Kisung&nbsp;Lee</div> <div class="imageTitle">Tweet Density</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2032745/2032745_10676228_1691525580405_dashboard--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2032745/2032745_10676228_1691525580405_dashboard--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Dashboard"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2032745/2032745_10676228_1691525580405_dashboard--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Dashboard"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">A screenshot of our interactive dashboard</div> <div class="imageCredit">Project Team</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Kisung&nbsp;Lee</div> <div class="imageTitle">Dashboard</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This interdisciplinary RAPID project has collected three waves of Twitter and associated time-sensitive data to study differential sentiment and language use in responses to health information and public health guidance concerning COVID-19.  The intellectual merits of the project are:  (1) The project has collected more than 100 million tweets for three study periods covering the first two COVID-19 surges in Louisiana (LA) and Washington State (WA). To avoid selection bias during data collection, we used geospatial filters instead of specifying certain keywords related to COVID-19. In addition, we have collected entire tweets of selected accounts related to COVID-19 public health messaging, such as media outlets, state public health agencies, and offices of emergency management.  (2) The project has compiled various databases including 1) COVID-19 policy data in LA and WA, 2) media outlet sources coded for credibility and political bias, 3) county-level COVID-19 case and death counts in LA and WA, 4) city and county demographics in LA and WA, and 5) academic and think tank initiatives that produced COVID-19 information.   (3) The project has coded tweets on tweet function and recommended behaviors to understand health communication from WA/LA health and emergency management agencies during the first two surges of COVID-19 in 2020.   (4) The project has analyzed and compared tweeting patterns including sentiment and word usage in the two states to understand inter-state disparities. We have also analyzed and visualized tweeting patterns and sentiment variations across counties or parishes to identify intra-state disparities. In addition, we have examined the public health messaging of governmental accounts in the two states and public engagement related to the messages.  (5) The project has created a dataset of fact-checked misinforming claims from the beginning of COVID-19 and is in the process of checking these claims against tweets written in the 48-hours before and after a major policy announcement in WA and LA (e.g., mask mandates) to see 1) what misinformation was spreading and 2) whether there are changes related to policy announcements. This work contributes to conversations about misinformation as well as the relationship between misinformation and policy.  (6) The project has used the Ad Fontes Media bias chart to understand what news sources were being shared during the initial stages of COVID-19 as related to political bias. This work contributes to conversations about news consumption during a crisis event, considerations of partisan echo chambers during a crisis event, and overall questions of information trustworthiness.  (7) The project has built a dataset of evangelical Protestant churches? and church leaders? Twitter accounts, gathered the tweets put out by these accounts between 2020 and 2022, and is analyzing tweets related to COVID-19 for their content. This work attempts to understand messaging from important religious figures during a crisis.     The broader impacts of the project are:  (1) We have built a multi-disciplinary and multi-institution research team to collaboratively work on the proposed research. The team includes computer and environmental scientists at Louisiana State University (LSU) and social scientists at the University of Washington (UW).  (2) We have built a project website (https://sites.google.com/view/covid19twitter) to disseminate project outcomes. The website provides basic information of the project, publications from the project, and sample datasets available for download. We have also built an interactive dashboard for data visualization in collaboration with UW?s eSciences Institute.  (3) From the collaboration process of our interdisciplinary team, we have designed research questions and hypotheses and published our first group paper in IEEE Access that examines tweeting patterns and public engagement on Twitter related to public health messaging in WA and LA during the early stage of the COVID-19 pandemic. In addition, we proposed a session at the Pacific Sociological Association (PSA) 2023 conference and got accepted to present our various research projects.  (4) The project has provided research opportunities for one postdoctoral researcher, six graduate students, and nine undergraduate and post-baccalaureate students including REU students. The undergraduates gained experience producing literature reviews, writing for an academic audience, presenting findings to an interdisciplinary research group, data analysis, and other skills. All the student researchers from the UW are from demographic groups underrepresented in science, engineering, and technology. Their inclusion in the project and our close mentoring creates pathways for them to enter professional positions related to these three areas.       Last Modified: 08/08/2023       Submitted by: Kisung Lee]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
