<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Collaborative Research: Immunological adaptations in bats to moderate the effect of coronavirus infection]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>21310.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>21310</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08090300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IOS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joanna Shisler</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jshisler@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925368</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[All aspects of society have been upended by COVID-19. While most research has understandably focused on clinical applications, how the ancestors of SARS-CoV2 survive and circulate in nature is vital to both prevent future epidemics and help health professionals develop therapeutic treatments. Because some bat species are natural carriers of many coronaviruses, including the closest known relatives of SARS-CoV-2, the team supported by this award will identify consistent differences between bats and other mammals likely involved in moderating infection by regulating virus entry and mounting an effective immune response. This project will address how bats escape illness despite carrying a wide range of viruses. As part of this work, the research team will develop educational displays related to the bat immunology for public display at the Museum of Texas Tech. Results for the study will also be published in peer-reviewed journals, presented at scientific meetings, and posted to shared data repositories.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Researchers supported by this award hypothesize there are consistent differences in the genes involved in the immune response pathways of bats compared to other mammals, such that: a) bats show disproportionate numbers of unique genomic adaptations; b) there is higher expression of immune system genes in bats than in comparable mouse and human tissues, and c) expression of genes involved in coronavirus cell entry in bats differs in RNA profile, limiting the extent pathogenesis when compared to humans and mice. To test these hypotheses, the team will analyze genome structure across diverse bats species, and differential expression analysis of different tissues, in the context of viral tropism and immune response. Resulting data will inform researchers and clinicians as they anticipate and treat these respiratory syndromes. This RAPID award is made by the Physiological and Structural Systems Cluster in the BIO Division of Integrative Organismal Systems, using funds from the Coronavirus Aid, Relief, and Economic Security (CARES) Act.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/08/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/08/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2032011</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>angelique</FirstName>
<LastName>corthals</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>p</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>angelique p corthals</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[acorthals@jjay.cuny.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000594190</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/08/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>CUNY John Jay College of Criminal Justice</Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<ZipCode>100191007</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2122378449</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>524 W 59TH ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NGK8GHNABTB8</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH FOUNDATION OF THE CITY UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>U7WPB7AFN7M2</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[CUNY John Jay College of Criminal Justice]]></Name>
<CityName>New York</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>100191069</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[524 West 59th Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>158Y</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>1N20</Code>
<Name>R&amp;RA CARES Act DEFC N</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>010N2021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[R&RA CARES Act DEFC N]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~21310</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>SARS-CoV2, and other pathogenic coronaviruses (MERS, SARS), have their close relatives circulating in bats who remain unaffected by any of them. What makes bats so tolerant of these deadly viruses in humans? Our project sought to answer one side of this question by comparing the genome of bats and other mammals. The outcome of our research can help prevent the next pandemic as well as discover new treatments for COVID-19, SARS and MERS. By making humans more tolerant of these viruses, indeed more like bats, we can combat infection before it even starts.</p> <p>To achieve our goals, our team performed an exhaustive comparative analysis with 37 bat genomes, the largest sampling to date, and six non-bat mammals as outgroups. Although we found several unique adaptations in bats involved in the immune response regulation, the most important findings were gene losses. We corroborated the loss of the entire PYHIN family, previously reported for a few bat species, with 37 species. PYHIN is one of several pathways of inflammation. In addition to the PYHIN family loss, we discovered losses in more genes involved in the inflammasome pathway, such as the ligands for the NKG2D activation, and losses of epithelial alpha and beta defensins. This is the first report of epithelial defensins contraction in bats. In contrast, we found gene expansions and evidence of positive selection on genes involved in pathogen defense and recognition, such as the MHC-I, cytokines, and APOBEC3. We propose these gene expansions and adaptive evolution may compensate for the shortcomings of a system-wide dampened inflammatory response, thus preventing the now unfortunately famous 'cytokine storm'.&nbsp;Based on the results obtained with the comparative genome analysis, we are currently performing a detailed analysis of bats antimicrobial peptides, which includes alpha and beta defensins, which will gives us an even more refine understanding of how virus tolerance can be achieved.</p> <p>A publication detailing the findings listed above is already in press in Molecular Ecology and available for reading through early release. We are planning a series of publications that have this project as the starting point for further detailed analyses.</p> <p>Postdoctoral students Diana Moreno&nbsp;Santillan (Texas Tech) and Tanya Lama (SBU) mentored undergraduate students and PhD student Alexis Brown (SBU)</p> <p>This grant allowed the participation of 3 undergradaute students from a primarily minority-serving institution, the CIty University of New York John Jay College of Criminal Justice. These students were Francesca Yalong, Mateo Saenz and Rintaro Kato. The students mostly participated in the last steps of analyses and in preparation of the manuscript. It provided them with an invaluable experience into becoming principal investigator and working on a collaborative project.</p> <p>Finally, this project has led to many science communication projects, such as podcasts and talks for general audiences, to bring scientific knowledge to the general public. A NOVA PBS documentrary, Bat Superpowers, featuring PIs Davalos and Corthals talking, in part, about this project, was released on September 15 2021. Thus, this project has also left a lasting impact on evolutionary biology through education and science communication.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/29/2021<br>      Modified by: Angelique&nbsp;P&nbsp;Corthals</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ SARS-CoV2, and other pathogenic coronaviruses (MERS, SARS), have their close relatives circulating in bats who remain unaffected by any of them. What makes bats so tolerant of these deadly viruses in humans? Our project sought to answer one side of this question by comparing the genome of bats and other mammals. The outcome of our research can help prevent the next pandemic as well as discover new treatments for COVID-19, SARS and MERS. By making humans more tolerant of these viruses, indeed more like bats, we can combat infection before it even starts.  To achieve our goals, our team performed an exhaustive comparative analysis with 37 bat genomes, the largest sampling to date, and six non-bat mammals as outgroups. Although we found several unique adaptations in bats involved in the immune response regulation, the most important findings were gene losses. We corroborated the loss of the entire PYHIN family, previously reported for a few bat species, with 37 species. PYHIN is one of several pathways of inflammation. In addition to the PYHIN family loss, we discovered losses in more genes involved in the inflammasome pathway, such as the ligands for the NKG2D activation, and losses of epithelial alpha and beta defensins. This is the first report of epithelial defensins contraction in bats. In contrast, we found gene expansions and evidence of positive selection on genes involved in pathogen defense and recognition, such as the MHC-I, cytokines, and APOBEC3. We propose these gene expansions and adaptive evolution may compensate for the shortcomings of a system-wide dampened inflammatory response, thus preventing the now unfortunately famous 'cytokine storm'. Based on the results obtained with the comparative genome analysis, we are currently performing a detailed analysis of bats antimicrobial peptides, which includes alpha and beta defensins, which will gives us an even more refine understanding of how virus tolerance can be achieved.  A publication detailing the findings listed above is already in press in Molecular Ecology and available for reading through early release. We are planning a series of publications that have this project as the starting point for further detailed analyses.  Postdoctoral students Diana Moreno Santillan (Texas Tech) and Tanya Lama (SBU) mentored undergraduate students and PhD student Alexis Brown (SBU)  This grant allowed the participation of 3 undergradaute students from a primarily minority-serving institution, the CIty University of New York John Jay College of Criminal Justice. These students were Francesca Yalong, Mateo Saenz and Rintaro Kato. The students mostly participated in the last steps of analyses and in preparation of the manuscript. It provided them with an invaluable experience into becoming principal investigator and working on a collaborative project.  Finally, this project has led to many science communication projects, such as podcasts and talks for general audiences, to bring scientific knowledge to the general public. A NOVA PBS documentrary, Bat Superpowers, featuring PIs Davalos and Corthals talking, in part, about this project, was released on September 15 2021. Thus, this project has also left a lasting impact on evolutionary biology through education and science communication.       Last Modified: 09/29/2021       Submitted by: Angelique P Corthals]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
