<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[EAGER: Applying Paleoecosystem-Mass Extinction Theory to Socio-Economic Systems During COVID-19]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>242627.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>242627</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Yurena Yanes</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>yyanes@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922649</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The project will apply a developing theory regarding the behavior of paleoecosystems as complex adaptive systems during mass extinctions, to the response of human and socio-economic systems (SESs) during the COVID-19 pandemic. Socio-economic systems and ecosystems are examples of complex, adaptive systems. Such systems underlie much of our world’s complexity, including human genetic systems, and the global economy. System behavior depends on the number of agents, their interactions, external influences, and how agents are organized into sub-groups. In ecosystems, the agents are species, interacting through mechanisms like predation or competition, and groups of species form when they have overlapping interactions. The behavior of a complex system is difficult to understand and forecast because of structural complexity, but a lot may be learned if the system is subjected to extreme stress. This has been the case when ecosystems in the past suffered mass extinctions, driven by enormous events such as asteroid impact. It is also the case for human SESs stressed by the COVID-19 pandemic and its socio-economic fallout. Studies have shown that ecosystem resilience during mass extinctions was determined by structural complexity, and that proper recovery depended on how structural complexity was re-evolved. This project will use similarities between ecosystems and SESs to model the impact of pandemic-driven mortality, morbidity, and economics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will develop network models of Californian and national SESs, relating employment organized by industrial sectors to system dynamics. The pandemic’s impact on selected SESs are modeled with numbers of persons employed in sectors, and we will identify critical sectors, forecasting future system dynamics. SES recovery will be modeled as employment recovery, comparing three recovery strategies: opportunistic recovery distributed randomly among sectors (random recovery), distributed fairly among sectors (equitable recovery), or distributed unevenly to maximize recovery rate and magnitude (strategic recovery). The latter strategy will be modeled using a Markov Chain Monte Carlo Metropolis-Hastings machine learning method.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/01/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/01/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2032769</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
<LastName>Roopnarine</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Peter D Roopnarine</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[proopnarine@calacademy.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000483117</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/01/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>California Academy of Sciences</Name>
<CityName>SAN FRANCISCO</CityName>
<ZipCode>941184503</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4153795146</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>55 MUSIC CONCOURSE DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>11</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA11</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>N7NRRBNKM5P3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CALIFORNIA ACADEMY OF SCIENCES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>F57PLAKLFQL3</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[California Academy of Sciences]]></Name>
<CityName>San Francisco</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>941184503</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[55 Music Concourse]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>11</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA11</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7459</Code>
<Text>Sedimentary Geo &amp; Paleobiology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~242627</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p style="line-height: 100%; margin-bottom: 0in;">The goal of this project was to explore what the economic consequences would have been if no lockdown or shelter in place orders had been issued during the first year of the COVID-19 pandemic in California. We refer to this sort of question as a counterfactual, that is, something that did not happen but that could have happened. Our intention is to provide an answer to whether economic shutdown was more or less harmful than allowing the economy to remain open. We did this by building a mathematical model of how various economic sectors interact in California, for example, the economic dependencies and exchanges between Agriculture and Manufacturing. The model, termed CASES (Complex Adaptive Socio-Economic Systems), was then applied to 10 Californian socio-economic systems (SESs), ranging from the very large and coastal (e.g. Lost Angeles) to smaller and inland (e.g. Fresno). The conventional SIR (Susceptible, Infected, Removed) epidemiological model provided the disease dynamics for each SES, and a broad range of outbreak and infection scenarios were simulated for each SES, including the actual outbreak scenarios in March, 2020. A simulation begins with the loss of workers due to severe illness or death. The resulting loss of productivity in a sector has a cascading effect throughout the entire economic network, and the model forecasts the resulting levels of unemployment. We then compared those forecasts to real unemployment during 2020-2021 for each SES.</p> <p style="line-height: 100%; margin-bottom: 0in;">&nbsp;</p> <p style="line-height: 100%; margin-bottom: 0in;">We found that the severity of a cascade depends on four factors. First, the intensity of an outbreak. The higher the initial transmission rate, the more workers who become severely ill (or die) and the more rapid the acceleration of a cascade. Second, the age demographics of a sector determine the primary impact of an outbreak on the sector. The greater the number of workers 50 years and older, the greater the primary or direct impact of the disease, because COVID-19 is a more severe disease in older indiviuals. Third, although all economic sectors are connected to each other by supply and demand exchanges, the extent to which an outbreak in one sector will cascade to another is mediated by the strengths of the exchanges between those sectors. Thus, sectors with stronger interactions, e.g. Manufacturing on which most other sectors depend, will both transmit and receive stronger secondary</p> <p style="line-height: 100%; margin-bottom: 0in;">cascades. Fourth, cascades are affected by the overall structure of an SES, notably the total number of</p> <p style="line-height: 100%; margin-bottom: 0in;">workers, and how those workers are divided among sectors. Agriculture is more important</p> <p style="line-height: 100%; margin-bottom: 0in;">in smaller or inland systems, with an increasing dominance of services-providing sectors (e.g. Finance) as SES size and proximity to the coast increase. This reflects the general trend of coastal socio-economic systems in California being both larger than inland systems, and having relatively larger service sectors, such as Information and Financial Services, or larger sectors that are dominated by services, such as Leisure and Hospitality.</p> <p style="line-height: 100%; margin-bottom: 0in;">&nbsp;</p> <p style="line-height: 100%; margin-bottom: 0in;">Model predictions of job losses for the seven large, coastal Californian socio-economic systems with economies dominated by services, such as financial and recreational, were lower than actual job losses. Those economies would therefore have benefited by maintaining an open economy. In contrast, smaller and/or more inland systems, where goods production is a larger economic component, would have suffered more, having both older workforces, and being dominated by goods-production, such as Agriculture. Overall, California may have experienced lower pandemic-driven unemployment under an open economy, but the experience would have been geographically heterogeneous, and it would have come at a cost; significantly greater disability and fatality rates. Simplistic prioritization of the economy over the health emergency, while possibly lessening economic losses, would nevertheless have resulted in an economic downturn, coupled with greatly increased health consequences of the disease. Fewer jobs would have been lost, but at the expense of the health and lives of tens of thousands of workers. In addition to the moral and societal costs of that impact, future recovery would be hampered by a smaller, younger and less experienced post-pandemic labour force.</p> <p style="line-height: 100%; margin-bottom: 0in;">&nbsp;</p> <p style="line-height: 100%; margin-bottom: 0in;">The variability of predicted outcomes among SESs subjected to the counterfactual scenario, suggests that combining local structural economic data with dynamic epidemiological and economic models could form a basis for flexible policies going forward that are strategically designed to disrupt the spread of pandemics and simultaneously adhere to the highest and most compassionate moral and societal standards, even while minimizing inevitable economic damage. California eventually developed a county by county re-opening strategy based on positive case counts, an approach that appears to be epidemiologically effective. Our work supports the adoption of similarly nuanced strategies to manage economic impacts.</p> <!-- p { line-height: 115%; margin-bottom: 0.1in; background: transparent } --><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/27/2023<br>      Modified by: Peter&nbsp;D&nbsp;Roopnarine</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[The goal of this project was to explore what the economic consequences would have been if no lockdown or shelter in place orders had been issued during the first year of the COVID-19 pandemic in California. We refer to this sort of question as a counterfactual, that is, something that did not happen but that could have happened. Our intention is to provide an answer to whether economic shutdown was more or less harmful than allowing the economy to remain open. We did this by building a mathematical model of how various economic sectors interact in California, for example, the economic dependencies and exchanges between Agriculture and Manufacturing. The model, termed CASES (Complex Adaptive Socio-Economic Systems), was then applied to 10 Californian socio-economic systems (SESs), ranging from the very large and coastal (e.g. Lost Angeles) to smaller and inland (e.g. Fresno). The conventional SIR (Susceptible, Infected, Removed) epidemiological model provided the disease dynamics for each SES, and a broad range of outbreak and infection scenarios were simulated for each SES, including the actual outbreak scenarios in March, 2020. A simulation begins with the loss of workers due to severe illness or death. The resulting loss of productivity in a sector has a cascading effect throughout the entire economic network, and the model forecasts the resulting levels of unemployment. We then compared those forecasts to real unemployment during 2020-2021 for each SES.   We found that the severity of a cascade depends on four factors. First, the intensity of an outbreak. The higher the initial transmission rate, the more workers who become severely ill (or die) and the more rapid the acceleration of a cascade. Second, the age demographics of a sector determine the primary impact of an outbreak on the sector. The greater the number of workers 50 years and older, the greater the primary or direct impact of the disease, because COVID-19 is a more severe disease in older indiviuals. Third, although all economic sectors are connected to each other by supply and demand exchanges, the extent to which an outbreak in one sector will cascade to another is mediated by the strengths of the exchanges between those sectors. Thus, sectors with stronger interactions, e.g. Manufacturing on which most other sectors depend, will both transmit and receive stronger secondary cascades. Fourth, cascades are affected by the overall structure of an SES, notably the total number of workers, and how those workers are divided among sectors. Agriculture is more important in smaller or inland systems, with an increasing dominance of services-providing sectors (e.g. Finance) as SES size and proximity to the coast increase. This reflects the general trend of coastal socio-economic systems in California being both larger than inland systems, and having relatively larger service sectors, such as Information and Financial Services, or larger sectors that are dominated by services, such as Leisure and Hospitality.   Model predictions of job losses for the seven large, coastal Californian socio-economic systems with economies dominated by services, such as financial and recreational, were lower than actual job losses. Those economies would therefore have benefited by maintaining an open economy. In contrast, smaller and/or more inland systems, where goods production is a larger economic component, would have suffered more, having both older workforces, and being dominated by goods-production, such as Agriculture. Overall, California may have experienced lower pandemic-driven unemployment under an open economy, but the experience would have been geographically heterogeneous, and it would have come at a cost; significantly greater disability and fatality rates. Simplistic prioritization of the economy over the health emergency, while possibly lessening economic losses, would nevertheless have resulted in an economic downturn, coupled with greatly increased health consequences of the disease. Fewer jobs would have been lost, but at the expense of the health and lives of tens of thousands of workers. In addition to the moral and societal costs of that impact, future recovery would be hampered by a smaller, younger and less experienced post-pandemic labour force.   The variability of predicted outcomes among SESs subjected to the counterfactual scenario, suggests that combining local structural economic data with dynamic epidemiological and economic models could form a basis for flexible policies going forward that are strategically designed to disrupt the spread of pandemics and simultaneously adhere to the highest and most compassionate moral and societal standards, even while minimizing inevitable economic damage. California eventually developed a county by county re-opening strategy based on positive case counts, an approach that appears to be epidemiologically effective. Our work supports the adoption of similarly nuanced strategies to manage economic impacts.        Last Modified: 02/27/2023       Submitted by: Peter D Roopnarine]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
