<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  AK-423: A broad-spectrum antiviral and immunomodulatory agent (COVID-19)]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>256000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>256000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Erik Pierstorff</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>epiersto@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922165</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact /commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project stems from the development of an efficient broad-spectrum antiviral agent addressing the current COVID-19 pandemic. The approach can also address future outbreaks of other viruses. The project is targeting the group of COVID-19 patients who will develop severe illness featuring multiple organ dysfunction.  Those patients need ICU units and ventilators in amounts that can overwhelm the health care system. This project will develop an antiviral agent to mitigate the social distancing measures and improve quality of life. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project focuses on the development AK-423, a potential efficient antiviral and immunomodulatory agent against COVID-19. The technical objectives focus on testing AK-423 (in-vitro and in-vivo) against COVID-19. Recent reports suggest that the multi-organ damage that occurs during COVID-19 infection is characterized by an exaggerated inflammatory response indicative of cytokine storm, auto-immunity, and a sepsis syndrome caused by complex abnormal immune reactions. An ideal treatment would not only suppress viral replication but would also regulate the abnormal immune response. AK-423 targets a host metabolic process that the virus hijacks. It is also a key process in the differentiation of lymphocytes. Inhibition of such process is proven to dampen the immune response, minimize immune response-induced tissue damage, inhibit production of pro-inflammatory cytokines, and efficiently shut down viral replication. This strategy will deliver an efficient broad-spectrum antiviral agent.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/22/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/11/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041, 47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2032097</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sherine</FirstName>
<LastName>Abdelmawla</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sherine Abdelmawla</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[sabdelmawla@akanocure.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000825098</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/22/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Akanocure Pharmaceuticals, Inc.</Name>
<CityName>WEST LAFAYETTE</CityName>
<ZipCode>479061074</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7654096062</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3495 KENT AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IN04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>QMU8ZFLN2A34</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>AKANOCURE PHARMACEUTICALS INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>QMU8ZFLN2A34</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Akanocure Pharmaceuticals, Inc.]]></Name>
<CityName>West Lafayette</CityName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>479064170</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3495 Kent Avenue, Suite E-100]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IN04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1982</Code>
<Text>BIOLOGICAL CHEMISTRY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~256000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This Small Business Innovation Research Phase I project focused on COVID-19 (SARS-CoV-2) infections and its post infection sequalae. COVID-19 infections are characterized by hyperinflammation and autoimmunity leading to multi-organ damage (lungs, heart, blood vessels, brain) even with a mild infection. The damage is cumulative as it gets worse with every new infection, and repeat infections increase the risk of Long COVID (persistent symptoms that last for months after infections). The virus also damages the DNA and impairs the ability of the body to correct that damage causing the cells to age faster and eventually develop cancer. All the damage and clinical manifestations are caused by a persistent chronic infection and a dysregulated immune response. An ideal treatment would not only suppress viral replication but would also restore the immune system homeostasis and healthy immune response. In Phase I, Akanocure tackled the dysregulated immune response through designing and testing AK-423 as an efficient immunomodulatory agent to prevent immune-mediated organ damage. AK-423 was tested for the reduction of key cytokines/chemokines that are markers for disease severity and fatality and are implicated in the persistence of inflammation, organ damage, lung fibrosis, acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS), and cardiovascular complications. In addition, these chemokines/cytokines recruit immune suppressive cells (monocytic myeloid-derived suppressor cells (M-MDSCs)) that decrease the effectiveness of vaccines and disrupt the host?s proper antiviral responses by the immune system. Consequently, such chemokines/cytokines are important therapeutic targets for restoring immune homeostasis and reducing plasma viral load. AK-423 reduced the secretion of such key chemokines in a dose dependent manner. In addition, AK-423 was proven to be effective at inhibiting viral replication in a host-directed, broad-spectrum, virus/strain agnostic manner. AK-423 inhibited the replication of SARS-CoV-2 at single digit nanomolar ranges, was 150X more effective than favipiravir against Sudan Ebolavirus, 80X more effective against Nipah virus, and completely shut down replication of Influenza A compared to oseltamivir. The virus has been mutating and evolving unexpectedly fast; where every new variant is better at immune evasion, is increasingly more transmissible; and resistant to treatments which caused vaccines to progressively offer less and less protection against breakthrough infections and long term sequalae. Current antiviral therapies against COVID-19 either have not shown definitive effectiveness, have severe side effects, and/or are starting to suffer from resistance. In contrast, AK-423 targets the host (known, well-studied, genetically stable) rather than the virus (mutates constantly) which decreases the chances of resistance and provides a broader spectrum efficacy.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Since 2020, the research community has been chasing the virus and chasing variants by reformulating the vaccines and developing more antibodies and direct-acting antivirals, but the virus has been ahead, mutating so fast to make those approaches obsolete. Because COVID-19 is not going away, and because chronic infections and a dysregulated immune response is not unique to COVID-19, and because viral threats will not stop at COVID-19, host-directed, virus and variant agnostic, broad spectrum antiviral and immunomodulatory agents that are easy to administer in an outpatient or pandemic setting (oral) and can be given anytime early or late in the infection cycle like AK-423 are highly needed to get ahead of viral threats and truly advance the health and welfare of the American public. Such an approach can control the<strong> current </strong>pandemic and any<strong> future </strong>pandemic caused by a<strong> </strong>yet<strong> unknown virus </strong>so society would not be caught unprepared again. AK-423 showed efficient antiviral activity against a representative virus from each of the four virus families that have caused pandemics in the past 100 years and are expected to cause the next pandemic (COVID-19, Influenza A, Sudan Ebolavirus, Nipah virus). In addition to the positive effect on pandemic preparedness and decreasing the pressure on the healthcare system, AK-423 can positively impact the economy. The devastating health effects that COVID-19 has caused, especially on the cardiovascular and nervous systems have led to disability claims sharply rising among working age group. Preventing those devastating effects will favorably impact the economy.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/30/2023<br>      Modified by: Sherine&nbsp;Abdelmawla</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This Small Business Innovation Research Phase I project focused on COVID-19 (SARS-CoV-2) infections and its post infection sequalae. COVID-19 infections are characterized by hyperinflammation and autoimmunity leading to multi-organ damage (lungs, heart, blood vessels, brain) even with a mild infection. The damage is cumulative as it gets worse with every new infection, and repeat infections increase the risk of Long COVID (persistent symptoms that last for months after infections). The virus also damages the DNA and impairs the ability of the body to correct that damage causing the cells to age faster and eventually develop cancer. All the damage and clinical manifestations are caused by a persistent chronic infection and a dysregulated immune response. An ideal treatment would not only suppress viral replication but would also restore the immune system homeostasis and healthy immune response. In Phase I, Akanocure tackled the dysregulated immune response through designing and testing AK-423 as an efficient immunomodulatory agent to prevent immune-mediated organ damage. AK-423 was tested for the reduction of key cytokines/chemokines that are markers for disease severity and fatality and are implicated in the persistence of inflammation, organ damage, lung fibrosis, acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS), and cardiovascular complications. In addition, these chemokines/cytokines recruit immune suppressive cells (monocytic myeloid-derived suppressor cells (M-MDSCs)) that decrease the effectiveness of vaccines and disrupt the host?s proper antiviral responses by the immune system. Consequently, such chemokines/cytokines are important therapeutic targets for restoring immune homeostasis and reducing plasma viral load. AK-423 reduced the secretion of such key chemokines in a dose dependent manner. In addition, AK-423 was proven to be effective at inhibiting viral replication in a host-directed, broad-spectrum, virus/strain agnostic manner. AK-423 inhibited the replication of SARS-CoV-2 at single digit nanomolar ranges, was 150X more effective than favipiravir against Sudan Ebolavirus, 80X more effective against Nipah virus, and completely shut down replication of Influenza A compared to oseltamivir. The virus has been mutating and evolving unexpectedly fast; where every new variant is better at immune evasion, is increasingly more transmissible; and resistant to treatments which caused vaccines to progressively offer less and less protection against breakthrough infections and long term sequalae. Current antiviral therapies against COVID-19 either have not shown definitive effectiveness, have severe side effects, and/or are starting to suffer from resistance. In contrast, AK-423 targets the host (known, well-studied, genetically stable) rather than the virus (mutates constantly) which decreases the chances of resistance and provides a broader spectrum efficacy.     Since 2020, the research community has been chasing the virus and chasing variants by reformulating the vaccines and developing more antibodies and direct-acting antivirals, but the virus has been ahead, mutating so fast to make those approaches obsolete. Because COVID-19 is not going away, and because chronic infections and a dysregulated immune response is not unique to COVID-19, and because viral threats will not stop at COVID-19, host-directed, virus and variant agnostic, broad spectrum antiviral and immunomodulatory agents that are easy to administer in an outpatient or pandemic setting (oral) and can be given anytime early or late in the infection cycle like AK-423 are highly needed to get ahead of viral threats and truly advance the health and welfare of the American public. Such an approach can control the current pandemic and any future pandemic caused by a yet unknown virus so society would not be caught unprepared again. AK-423 showed efficient antiviral activity against a representative virus from each of the four virus families that have caused pandemics in the past 100 years and are expected to cause the next pandemic (COVID-19, Influenza A, Sudan Ebolavirus, Nipah virus). In addition to the positive effect on pandemic preparedness and decreasing the pressure on the healthcare system, AK-423 can positively impact the economy. The devastating health effects that COVID-19 has caused, especially on the cardiovascular and nervous systems have led to disability claims sharply rising among working age group. Preventing those devastating effects will favorably impact the economy.          Last Modified: 03/30/2023       Submitted by: Sherine Abdelmawla]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
