<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Virtual Workshops for GEO REU Students and PIs During COVID-19</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>48449.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>48449</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06040100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OCE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Elizabeth Rom</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>elrom@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927709</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>In response to the COVID-19 national emergency, many Research Experiences for Undergraduates (REU) Site programs have cancelled their programs for the summer 2020 due to a lack of housing and travel restrictions. Some REU sites that are funded by the Division of Ocean Sciences have created virtual internships for students who will be able to access and analyze data remotely. The University Corporation for Atmospheric Research (UCAR) will organize an on-line professional development workshop that is designed to support about sixty undergraduates and faculty mentors who are participating in virtual REU internships during the summer 2020.  This professional development workshop series will ensure that students who are participating in the virtual internships have the professional development opportunities that are normally part of an in-person REU program.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will support a workshop series that will focus on two topics. 1. Student Professional Development: providing a series of weekly professional development seminars for students participating in the virtual REUs. These seminars will serve the dual purpose of developing a sense of cohort amongst students, and 2. Faculty Support and Materials: supporting faculty mentors in preparing to run a virtual REU, providing faculty with seminars on facilitating professional development topics, and providing some webinar recordings and materials for guided student activities. The project will also be a model for future virtual internship programs.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/15/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/15/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2032481</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Valerie</FirstName>
<LastName>Sloan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Valerie Sloan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>vsloan@ucar.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3034972572</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000666178</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/15/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University Corporation For Atmospheric Res</Name>
<CityName>BOULDER</CityName>
<ZipCode>803012252</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3034971000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3090 CENTER GREEN DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>YEZEE8W5JKA3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY CORPORATION FOR ATMOSPHERIC RESEARCH</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>YEZEE8W5JKA3</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[National Center for Atmospheric Research]]></Name>
<CityName>Boulder</CityName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>803013000</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1850 Table Mesa Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1690</Code>
<Text>EDUCATION/HUMAN RESOURCES,OCE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9250</Code>
<Text>REU SITE-Res Exp for Ugrd Site</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~48449</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project provided much needed support for people managing summer research internships in the broader geosciences, including the ocean, Earth, atmospheric, and geospace sciences, as well as workshops for 50 undergraduate students in research internships.</p> <p>These students had originally been expecting to do another REU internship, but when their programs were canceled, they were selected to participate in three pop-up internship programs; this workshop series provided them with the professional training they would have had in a regular REU. Several of these students co-authored an abstract for a major conferene, AGU, and presented on their experiences doing a virtual internship online during a summer of heightened racist violence and issues of working in isolation at home. Some of the students were located in Puerto Rico, which was still recovering from Hurricane Maria, and others were in Guam, where they had to get up at 4 am to attend workshops. Nonetheless, 50 the students were very grateful for the opportunities provided.&nbsp;</p> <p>The events provided for the internship managers included training on how to move a program like this to be online, how to train students on anti-harassment and anti-discrimination, and a discussion on approaching DEI in running an internship.&nbsp; The student events included a career panel, a grad school panel, and six workshops on how to create a good poster, how to find jobs and network, creating strong job application materials. The feedback in the program evaluation was extremely positive.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/30/2021<br>      Modified by: Valerie&nbsp;F&nbsp;Sloan</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project provided much needed support for people managing summer research internships in the broader geosciences, including the ocean, Earth, atmospheric, and geospace sciences, as well as workshops for 50 undergraduate students in research internships.  These students had originally been expecting to do another REU internship, but when their programs were canceled, they were selected to participate in three pop-up internship programs; this workshop series provided them with the professional training they would have had in a regular REU. Several of these students co-authored an abstract for a major conferene, AGU, and presented on their experiences doing a virtual internship online during a summer of heightened racist violence and issues of working in isolation at home. Some of the students were located in Puerto Rico, which was still recovering from Hurricane Maria, and others were in Guam, where they had to get up at 4 am to attend workshops. Nonetheless, 50 the students were very grateful for the opportunities provided.   The events provided for the internship managers included training on how to move a program like this to be online, how to train students on anti-harassment and anti-discrimination, and a discussion on approaching DEI in running an internship.  The student events included a career panel, a grad school panel, and six workshops on how to create a good poster, how to find jobs and network, creating strong job application materials. The feedback in the program evaluation was extremely positive.       Last Modified: 10/30/2021       Submitted by: Valerie F Sloan]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
