<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Doctoral Dissertation Improvement Grant:  The Construction of Monumental Architecture]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>31493.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>31493</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>John Yellen</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jyellen@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928759</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This project investigates how the nature of coalescence and emergence of social complexity results in the creation of monuments and artificial landscapes. Multidisciplinary scholars have approached the emergence of social complexity, particularly in early urban centers, as a phenomenon conditioned by process and agency, whereby monuments are built conspicuously as representations of the social order. Archaeology is well positioned to examine the social conditions that gave rise to early urban centers and explain how monumental construction was undertaken with respect to social organization, material resources, and mobility of surplus labor. To what extent does the charismatic authority of prominent leaders or longstanding adherence to tradition shape the increasingly artificial landscapes of the world’s earliest cities and how? For US moundbuilding societies the creation of earthworks held both religious and socio-political significance, as a means of creating a common identity at the place where monuments were built. As such, the energetics of their construction and organization of their internal architectures provide critical insights into their social environments. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will focus on the largest US Pre-Columbian ceremonial center, by examining the nature and pace of monumental earthwork construction within the site’s central precinct. Existing interpretations of the site’s development into an urban center are divided between models that emphasize rapid or slow-paced monumental construction. Rapid pace models claim that hegemonic authority was exercised within a highly stratified social order at the site to direct monumental construction projects, while slower pace models portray such monumental architectures as byproducts of community nucleation and aggregation that carried over extended time periods. With the aid of accelerated mass spectrometry dating and Bayesian statistical models that reference exposed earthwork contexts, this project will assess what labor investments and construction strategies were employed for plaza and mound building at the site. Excavations into a suspected plaza compound with previously undocumented earthworks will be undertaken to acquire datable samples and record new forms of architecture. In this way, the pace and nature of moundbuilding as an expression of the existing social order will be more effectively interpreted. Consequently, the material history of this early urban center can be framed within the larger narratives about incipient urbanism and society at a global scale.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/07/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/07/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2032113</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Stauffer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>G</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John G Stauffer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[g.stauffer@wustl.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000802586</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/07/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tristram</FirstName>
<LastName>Kidder</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Tristram R Kidder</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[trkidder@wustl.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000102240</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/07/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Washington University</Name>
<CityName>SAINT LOUIS</CityName>
<ZipCode>63110</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3147474134</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>ONE BROOKINGS DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MO01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>L6NFUM28LQM5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WASHINGTON UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Cahokia Mounds State Historic Site]]></Name>
<CityName>Collinsville</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>622340501</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[30 Ramey Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7606</Code>
<Text>Archaeology DDRI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1391</Code>
<Text>ARCHAEOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~31493</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Investigations supported through the DDIG: The Construction of Monumental Architecture Award (ID 2032113) sought to discover buried monumental architecture at Cahokia Mounds State Historic Site and World Heritage Center in Collinsville, Illinois. Considered the largest settlement north of Mexico and Native America's first city, Cahokia represents the earliest known urban phenomenon in the North American continent. It grew into a city between 800-1400 CE that boasted the largest earthen monument in North America (Monks Mound), hosting an estimated 20,000 inhabitants. To get a sense of the scale of the site's transformation over time, the pace of its transformation, cultural context of earthwork construction, and population estimates linked to a specific earthwork (the Bareis Mound #17), this NSF award funded the processing of 27 radiocarbon dates, two field seasons in the center of the Cahokia site, material analysis costs, and micromorphology (soil thin section) analysis. The findings were pivotal in understanding the nature of urban transformation in the midcontinental United States before the arrival of Columbus. To contextualize our study of the nature and pace of the Bareis Mound's construction, the nearly 200 existant radiocarbon dates sampled from the Cahokia site were statistically modelled to better understand the nature and timing of previously exavated monuments, houses, and activity areas on site.</p> <p>Upon examining the field notes and artifact collections amassed by Charles Bareis, after his 1969 field season next to Monks Mound that were never published or explained to the academic community, the PI and Co-PI used initial funds from Washington University and the Divided City (Mellon Foundation) to conduct excavations at Bareis's previous field work location to discover a buried earthen monument that lies beneath extensive plaza fills, corresponding to an East Plaza compound off the eastern slope of Monks Mound. Using this discovery to secure the present NSF Award funds, excavations, sediment coring, and geophysical prospection work at the Bareis Mound (#17) revealed the monument to be a multistaged platform mound, built in four stages and amassing 2,736 cubic meters of construction fills that were intentionally mixed to achieve desired engineering qualities. A wall trench house structure was found atop the plaza fills burying the Bareis Mound (#17), and a large submound pit was found beneath it; both containing a variety of informative materials for analysis. Before field work was complete, multiple radiocarbon samples were taken from each construction stage of the mound and soil thin sections were taken from the junctions between each mound construction stage to study the extent of erosion that occurred between each building phase of the mound. 24 sampled radiocarbon dates were statistically modeled to measure the pace of construction, and revealed it to be within 19 to 94 years. However, the soil thin sections revealed that little to no erosion occurred between each building stage of the mound. Most notably, there was no water borne erosion caused by rain. Considering that the longest drought documented in the meteorological records for the state of Illinois lasted no more than 4 weeks, the soil thin sections make the case for the mound being built within a months time. Labor estimates based on the mound's overall construction fill volume (2,736 cubic meters) were related to multiple field experiements that measured the amount of persons and days required to build similar sized earthworks in the 1950s and more recently. Our findings concluded that the mound was built by as many as 228 people within a month's time, sometime between 1050-1200 CE.</p> <p>A pit beneath the earliest stage of the platform mound was also discovered that contained a variety of animal, plant, and man-made materials (artifacts) that, together, represented the deposited refuse of a "labor party." More specifically, diverse remains of edible animals (waterfowl, deer, fish, rabbit, dog, black bear, freshwater shellfish, and rodents) and plants (goosefoot, chenopodium, american lotus, grape, and gourds). Artifacts included varieties of decorated and undecorated pottery, and their analysis revealed a high percentage of decorated serving wares that included nonlocal varieties resembling assemblages from the Lower Mississippi River Valley and Caddo regions. A variety of stone tools and stone tools fragments were also recovered from this pit that suggested their use in processing these animal and plant remains, as well as microlithics that have been demonstrably linked to shell bead and pendant production in other areas of the Cahokia site. Artifacts recovered from house atop the Bareis Mound contained elaborate local and nonlocal ceramics,&nbsp;a ceremonial "friendship blade" fragment chipped from Smoky Hills jasper (mined from the flint hills of Kansas), microlithics, marine whelk shell fragments, and a partial marine shell bead fragments, basalt celt fragments, bone ear plug, galena, mica, hixton, quartz, and pigments (limonite and hematite). Altogether, these provide insights into the performances that took place in the plaza, after plaza construction buried the Bareis Mound.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/01/2023<br>      Modified by: John&nbsp;G&nbsp;Stauffer</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2032113/2032113_10683204_1690932468600_MappingTheBareisMound--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2032113/2032113_10683204_1690932468600_MappingTheBareisMound--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Mapping The Bareis Mound (#17)"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2032113/2032113_10683204_1690932468600_MappingTheBareisMound--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Mapping The Bareis Mound (#17)"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Field assistants (Ann and Julia) meticulously map the Bareis Mound's extensive construction fills, underneath the plaza fills that bury it. Monks Mound, North America's largest earthen monument, lies in the background.</div> <div class="imageCredit">John Grant Stauffer (CoPI)</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">John&nbsp;G&nbsp;Stauffer</div> <div class="imageTitle">Mapping The Bareis Mound (#17)</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2032113/2032113_10683204_1690933231355_Micromorph_10.23.2020--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2032113/2032113_10683204_1690933231355_Micromorph_10.23.2020--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Racing Groundwater"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2032113/2032113_10683204_1690933231355_Micromorph_10.23.2020--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Racing Groundwater"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Grant Stauffer races to collect soil thin sections and radiocarbon samples from the sub-mound pit, as groundwater rises within the excavation trench. A simple pump that has died once again lies in the foreground, suspended on a yellow polyethylene rope.</div> <div class="imageCredit">John Grant Stauffer</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">John&nbsp;G&nbsp;Stauffer</div> <div class="imageTitle">Racing Groundwater</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2032113/2032113_10683204_1690933918886_11.06.2020--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2032113/2032113_10683204_1690933918886_11.06.2020--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Backfilling Day"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2032113/2032113_10683204_1690933918886_11.06.2020--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Backfilling Day"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Field assistant, Ann Merkle, stands in the background, feet planted in the third trench of the project. The field crew is taking in the amount of excavation that took place in 2020 before their trenches are filled back in by site staff.</div> <div class="imageCredit">John Grant Stauffer</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">John&nbsp;G&nbsp;Stauffer</div> <div class="imageTitle">Backfilling Day</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2032113/2032113_10683204_1690934113210_03.03.2021--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2032113/2032113_10683204_1690934113210_03.03.2021--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Caddo Friendship Blade"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2032113/2032113_10683204_1690934113210_03.03.2021--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Caddo Friendship Blade"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">A "Caddo Friendship Blade" recovered from fills of the Bareis Mound is shown, chipped out of smoky hills jasper from the Flint Hills of Kansas by an occupant of the Cahokia site in the 11th century. It was snapped in half before being discarded in the mound fills, later to be recovered by our crew.</div> <div class="imageCredit">John Grant Stauffer</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">John&nbsp;G&nbsp;Stauffer</div> <div class="imageTitle">Caddo Friendship Blade</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2032113/2032113_10683204_1690934284824_10.02.2020--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2032113/2032113_10683204_1690934284824_10.02.2020--rgov-800width.jpg" title="American Lotus at Cahokia"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2032113/2032113_10683204_1690934284824_10.02.2020--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="American Lotus at Cahokia"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The image shows the seed receptacle of an American Lotus (Lily), recovered from the pit beneath the Bareis Mound. This is a rarely preserved example of the American Lotus being used as food. The plant is considered a sacred object by the Osage, who consider Cahokia ancestral territory.</div> <div class="imageCredit">John Grant Stauffer</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">John&nbsp;G&nbsp;Stauffer</div> <div class="imageTitle">American Lotus at Cahokia</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2032113/2032113_10683204_1690934439781_02.19.21--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2032113/2032113_10683204_1690934439781_02.19.21--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Strong Fingers"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2032113/2032113_10683204_1690934439781_02.19.21--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Strong Fingers"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">A tiny, bifurcated Cahokia Point is shown in the lab, after the 2020 field season. It is difficult to imagine the skill required to chip such a small, yet beautiful, projectile point out of Burlington chert mined from the Crescent Hills southwest of St. Louis.</div> <div class="imageCredit">John Grant Stauffer</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">John&nbsp;G&nbsp;Stauffer</div> <div class="imageTitle">Strong Fingers</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Investigations supported through the DDIG: The Construction of Monumental Architecture Award (ID 2032113) sought to discover buried monumental architecture at Cahokia Mounds State Historic Site and World Heritage Center in Collinsville, Illinois. Considered the largest settlement north of Mexico and Native America's first city, Cahokia represents the earliest known urban phenomenon in the North American continent. It grew into a city between 800-1400 CE that boasted the largest earthen monument in North America (Monks Mound), hosting an estimated 20,000 inhabitants. To get a sense of the scale of the site's transformation over time, the pace of its transformation, cultural context of earthwork construction, and population estimates linked to a specific earthwork (the Bareis Mound #17), this NSF award funded the processing of 27 radiocarbon dates, two field seasons in the center of the Cahokia site, material analysis costs, and micromorphology (soil thin section) analysis. The findings were pivotal in understanding the nature of urban transformation in the midcontinental United States before the arrival of Columbus. To contextualize our study of the nature and pace of the Bareis Mound's construction, the nearly 200 existant radiocarbon dates sampled from the Cahokia site were statistically modelled to better understand the nature and timing of previously exavated monuments, houses, and activity areas on site.  Upon examining the field notes and artifact collections amassed by Charles Bareis, after his 1969 field season next to Monks Mound that were never published or explained to the academic community, the PI and Co-PI used initial funds from Washington University and the Divided City (Mellon Foundation) to conduct excavations at Bareis's previous field work location to discover a buried earthen monument that lies beneath extensive plaza fills, corresponding to an East Plaza compound off the eastern slope of Monks Mound. Using this discovery to secure the present NSF Award funds, excavations, sediment coring, and geophysical prospection work at the Bareis Mound (#17) revealed the monument to be a multistaged platform mound, built in four stages and amassing 2,736 cubic meters of construction fills that were intentionally mixed to achieve desired engineering qualities. A wall trench house structure was found atop the plaza fills burying the Bareis Mound (#17), and a large submound pit was found beneath it; both containing a variety of informative materials for analysis. Before field work was complete, multiple radiocarbon samples were taken from each construction stage of the mound and soil thin sections were taken from the junctions between each mound construction stage to study the extent of erosion that occurred between each building phase of the mound. 24 sampled radiocarbon dates were statistically modeled to measure the pace of construction, and revealed it to be within 19 to 94 years. However, the soil thin sections revealed that little to no erosion occurred between each building stage of the mound. Most notably, there was no water borne erosion caused by rain. Considering that the longest drought documented in the meteorological records for the state of Illinois lasted no more than 4 weeks, the soil thin sections make the case for the mound being built within a months time. Labor estimates based on the mound's overall construction fill volume (2,736 cubic meters) were related to multiple field experiements that measured the amount of persons and days required to build similar sized earthworks in the 1950s and more recently. Our findings concluded that the mound was built by as many as 228 people within a month's time, sometime between 1050-1200 CE.  A pit beneath the earliest stage of the platform mound was also discovered that contained a variety of animal, plant, and man-made materials (artifacts) that, together, represented the deposited refuse of a "labor party." More specifically, diverse remains of edible animals (waterfowl, deer, fish, rabbit, dog, black bear, freshwater shellfish, and rodents) and plants (goosefoot, chenopodium, american lotus, grape, and gourds). Artifacts included varieties of decorated and undecorated pottery, and their analysis revealed a high percentage of decorated serving wares that included nonlocal varieties resembling assemblages from the Lower Mississippi River Valley and Caddo regions. A variety of stone tools and stone tools fragments were also recovered from this pit that suggested their use in processing these animal and plant remains, as well as microlithics that have been demonstrably linked to shell bead and pendant production in other areas of the Cahokia site. Artifacts recovered from house atop the Bareis Mound contained elaborate local and nonlocal ceramics, a ceremonial "friendship blade" fragment chipped from Smoky Hills jasper (mined from the flint hills of Kansas), microlithics, marine whelk shell fragments, and a partial marine shell bead fragments, basalt celt fragments, bone ear plug, galena, mica, hixton, quartz, and pigments (limonite and hematite). Altogether, these provide insights into the performances that took place in the plaza, after plaza construction buried the Bareis Mound.       Last Modified: 08/01/2023       Submitted by: John G Stauffer]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
