<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Epidemiology of COVID-19 based on Surveillance of Deceased Donors in the United States]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>198244.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>198244</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Katharina Dittmar</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kdittmar@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927799</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[A novel coronavirus, Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome Coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2), emerged at the end of 2019, causing the clinical illness of Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID-19). The symptoms of COVID-19 can vary dramatically in both presentation and severity. Individuals infected with COVID-19 may be asymptomatic while still able to transmit the virus. Population-based studies suggest the rate of asymptomatic cases of COVID-19 may be high, but data is lacking. In order to evaluate the true prevalence of the virus, characterize individuals that are affected and express severe symptoms and assess the effects of interventions to attenuate the proliferation of the spread of the virus, data regarding both the symptomatic and asymptomatic cases are critically important. Measurement of rates of COVID-19 are important for surveillance and predictive modeling in the general population as well as to inform scientific inquiry regarding the potential biological mechanisms underlying the expression of symptoms among select individuals. The current project will provide novel insights about COVID-19 by assessing test results of decedents referred for tissue or organ donation across the United States in an epidemiological framework. Broad dissemination of these results will inform ongoing national policy and will continue to expand the scope and accuracy of predictive modeling.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research project will provide unique insights into the epidemiology of COVID-19 in the United States. This will be accomplished by aggregating systematic test results of COVID-19 among decedents referred for tissue and organ donation. Organ procurement organizations (OPOs) are responsible for recovering deceased donors for transplantation in the United States. OPOs are now utilizing tests of COVID-19 for decedents referred as potential donors to assess risk prior to allocation to a potential recipient. Importantly, this includes donor tissue and organs from decedents with and without symptoms or known exposure to COVID-19. This process provides a unique opportunity to evaluate the incidence, progression and characteristic of COVID-19 including decedents from unrelated causes. These data will further be analyzed via statistics and predictive models to model the trajectory of COVID-19 in the general population based on demographic and clinical characteristics of the general population in different regions of the country. This RAPID award is made by the Ecology and Evolution of Infectious Disease Program in the Division of Environmental Biology, using funds from the Coronavirus Aid, Relief, and Economic Security (CARES) Act.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/26/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/26/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2032726</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jesse</FirstName>
<LastName>Schold</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jesse D Schold</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[scholdj@ccf.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000826770</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/26/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Cleveland Clinic Foundation</Name>
<CityName>CLEVELAND</CityName>
<ZipCode>441950001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2164456440</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>9500 EUCLID AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>11</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OH11</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>TDGUJ1WA4UJ9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>THE CLEVELAND CLINIC FOUNDATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>TDGUJ1WA4UJ9</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Cleveland Clinic Foundation]]></Name>
<CityName>Cleveland</CityName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>441950001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[9500 Euclid Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>11</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OH11</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>158Y</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>1N20</Code>
<Name>R&amp;RA CARES Act DEFC N</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>010N2021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[R&RA CARES Act DEFC N]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~198244</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The COVID-19 pandemic has detrimentally affected all portions of the global population. The devastating effects include increases in mortality, morbidity, economic disruptions and mental health disorders. Patients with End-Stage Kidney Disease (ESKD) are particularly vulnerable to the impacts of COVID-19 due to pre-existing morbidity, challenges to maintain social distancing due to ongoing care and immunological susceptibility due to health conditions and ongoing treatments. Our project evaluated the impact of COVID-19 on processes of care and outcomes for patients with ESKD who were awaiting a kidney transplant (transplant candidates) and transplant recipients in the United States.&nbsp;</p> <p>We addressed our project Aims in three distinct studies which are now published (1,2,3). In our first study, we examined factors associated with mortality among kidney transplant candidates in the United States using a national database (1). The primary findings illustrated a high mortality rate overall including approximately 11% of deaths due to COVID-19.&nbsp; Increased age, male gender, elevated BMI, and diabetes were associated with increased rates of COVID-19 mortality. In addition, there was a strong association of increased mortality among Blacks and Hispanics, patients with lower educational attainment, patients with public health insurance and patients residing in more distressed communities. Overall, the findings demonstrated that the impact of COVID-19 in this population was associated with both demographic and clinical factors as well as social determinants of health.&nbsp;</p> <p>In our second study we evaluated the impact of COVID-19 on the utilization of potential deceased donor kidneys for transplantation (2). We examined changes in the utilization of these organs over time and rates of organs discarded related to different surges of COVID-19 over the first year of the pandemic. The primary findings indicated significant changes in the procurement and availability of deceased donor kidney during different surges in 2020. Discard rates of organs that could not be accepted by transplant centers also changed over time and the quality of the organs accepted were associated with COVID-19 surge periods. These effects were variable by different regions of the country and individual transplant center. In summary, COVID-19 had a marked impact on the processes associated with deceased donor kidney transplantation in the United States and the availability of organs for potential transplant recipients.&nbsp;</p> <p>In our third study we examined the impact of COVID-19 on kidney transplant candidates and recipients in the United States (3). The primary findings indicated that both candidates and kidney transplant recipients were significantly impacted by the pandemic including 16% of deaths among transplant recipients attributed to COVID-19. Compared to 2019, there was a 20% increase in mortality among kidney transplant recipients in 2020 during the pandemic. There was a disproportionately higher mortality rate among recipients that were Black and Hispanic and peaks of mortality during the years consistent with national rises in COVID-19 attributed deaths. Overall, the study provided a national depiction of the broad detrimental impact of COVID-19 on the kidney transplant population in the United States.</p> <p>We are grateful to the National Science Foundation for support for our project and are hopeful that our work has contributed to the understanding of the impact of COVID-19 in the United States and to inform prospective interventions.</p> <p>1. Schold JD, King KL, Husain SA, Poggio ED, Buccini LD, Mohan S. COVID-19 Mortality among Kidney Transplant Candidates is strongly associated with Social Determinants of Health. American Journal of Transplantation. 2021; Jul; 21(7): 2563-72.</p> <p>2. Miah TL, King KL, Husain SA, Schold JD, Mohan S. Deceased Donor Kidneys Utilization and Discard Rates During COVID-19 Pandemic in the United States. Kidney International Reports (in press).</p> <p>3.Mohan S, King KL, Husain SA, Schold JD. COVID-19 associated Mortality among Kidney Transplant Recipients and Candidates in the United States. Clinical Journal of the American Society of Nephrology (in press).</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/31/2021<br>      Modified by: Jesse&nbsp;D&nbsp;Schold</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The COVID-19 pandemic has detrimentally affected all portions of the global population. The devastating effects include increases in mortality, morbidity, economic disruptions and mental health disorders. Patients with End-Stage Kidney Disease (ESKD) are particularly vulnerable to the impacts of COVID-19 due to pre-existing morbidity, challenges to maintain social distancing due to ongoing care and immunological susceptibility due to health conditions and ongoing treatments. Our project evaluated the impact of COVID-19 on processes of care and outcomes for patients with ESKD who were awaiting a kidney transplant (transplant candidates) and transplant recipients in the United States.   We addressed our project Aims in three distinct studies which are now published (1,2,3). In our first study, we examined factors associated with mortality among kidney transplant candidates in the United States using a national database (1). The primary findings illustrated a high mortality rate overall including approximately 11% of deaths due to COVID-19.  Increased age, male gender, elevated BMI, and diabetes were associated with increased rates of COVID-19 mortality. In addition, there was a strong association of increased mortality among Blacks and Hispanics, patients with lower educational attainment, patients with public health insurance and patients residing in more distressed communities. Overall, the findings demonstrated that the impact of COVID-19 in this population was associated with both demographic and clinical factors as well as social determinants of health.   In our second study we evaluated the impact of COVID-19 on the utilization of potential deceased donor kidneys for transplantation (2). We examined changes in the utilization of these organs over time and rates of organs discarded related to different surges of COVID-19 over the first year of the pandemic. The primary findings indicated significant changes in the procurement and availability of deceased donor kidney during different surges in 2020. Discard rates of organs that could not be accepted by transplant centers also changed over time and the quality of the organs accepted were associated with COVID-19 surge periods. These effects were variable by different regions of the country and individual transplant center. In summary, COVID-19 had a marked impact on the processes associated with deceased donor kidney transplantation in the United States and the availability of organs for potential transplant recipients.   In our third study we examined the impact of COVID-19 on kidney transplant candidates and recipients in the United States (3). The primary findings indicated that both candidates and kidney transplant recipients were significantly impacted by the pandemic including 16% of deaths among transplant recipients attributed to COVID-19. Compared to 2019, there was a 20% increase in mortality among kidney transplant recipients in 2020 during the pandemic. There was a disproportionately higher mortality rate among recipients that were Black and Hispanic and peaks of mortality during the years consistent with national rises in COVID-19 attributed deaths. Overall, the study provided a national depiction of the broad detrimental impact of COVID-19 on the kidney transplant population in the United States.  We are grateful to the National Science Foundation for support for our project and are hopeful that our work has contributed to the understanding of the impact of COVID-19 in the United States and to inform prospective interventions.  1. Schold JD, King KL, Husain SA, Poggio ED, Buccini LD, Mohan S. COVID-19 Mortality among Kidney Transplant Candidates is strongly associated with Social Determinants of Health. American Journal of Transplantation. 2021; Jul; 21(7): 2563-72.  2. Miah TL, King KL, Husain SA, Schold JD, Mohan S. Deceased Donor Kidneys Utilization and Discard Rates During COVID-19 Pandemic in the United States. Kidney International Reports (in press).  3.Mohan S, King KL, Husain SA, Schold JD. COVID-19 associated Mortality among Kidney Transplant Recipients and Candidates in the United States. Clinical Journal of the American Society of Nephrology (in press).             Last Modified: 08/31/2021       Submitted by: Jesse D Schold]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
