<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[EAGER: STEM Identity &amp; Computer Education: Overcoming the Intersectionality of Culture, Poverty &amp; Disability]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>292467.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>292467</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Allyson Kennedy</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>aykenned@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928905</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Information technology and coding can be made accessible to people with various types of physical disabilities as a path to higher-wage employment. Companies need computing and coding talent. These skills can be applied to a variety of careers, provide advantages in a competitive job market, and offer opportunities for creativity and innovation. People with disabilities are underrepresented in STEM fields including computer science and this creates a barrier to their inclusion in careers in STEM. The goals of this project align with the NSF goal of increasing education and diversity by connecting disabled youth to STEM professionals who will serve as mentors and introducing students to various careers and opportunities. The project intends to identify specific barriers that prevent underrepresented disabled students from fully engaging in STEM education (specifically computer science) and will identify the most effective methods and tools for teaching coding to persons with various disabilities.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project proposes to engage students who live at the intersection marginalized identities such as race, gender, and disability status. The project will select 24 students in grades 8-12 with congenital or acquired physical disabilities from an urban school district in Connecticut to participate in the project, which will consist of a series of introductory discussions, exercises (computer-based and unplugged), projects, and concurrent mentoring with STEM professionals with disabilities. A combination of in-class lectures, training videos, online tools, and practical exercises will teach the foundations of computer science and programming, emphasizing logical thinking and problem-solving skills.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/03/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/14/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2032020</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Crystal</FirstName>
<LastName>Emery</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Crystal Emery</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[r.starr@uruglobal.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000791599</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/03/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Belinda</FirstName>
<LastName>Carberry</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Belinda M Carberry</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[belinda_carberry@yahoo.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000826710</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/03/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sandra</FirstName>
<LastName>Bulmer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sandra Bulmer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[bulmers1@southernct.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000831149</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/03/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>URU THE RIGHT TO BE INC</Name>
<CityName>HAMDEN</CityName>
<ZipCode>065181813</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2033898829</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>305 HILLFIELD RD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CT03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>H9Y6Z37BLQH5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>URU THE RIGHT TO BE INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[URU THE RIGHT TO BE INC]]></Name>
<CityName>Hamden</CityName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>065181813</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[305 HILLFIELD RD]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CT03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>055y</Code>
<Text>CISE Education and Workforce</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7361</Code>
<Text>EDUCATION AND WORKFORCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~292467</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">EAGER: STEM Identity &amp; Computer Education: Overcoming the Intersectionality of Culture, Poverty &amp; Disability </span>developed and implemented a coding program for 27 students, ages ranging of 13.5 years to 20.25 years. Students represented a variety of physical disabilities, neurodiversity, and behavioral disorders and were primarily Black and Latinx. The cohort of students represented a range of accommodations and needs. The program trained local mentors with shared-identities to support students throughout the program. The research was to better understand the needs of this student population ? students who come from low-income backgrounds, identify as students of color (predominantly Black and Latinx) and have a disability. This research leaves opportunity for future study on other student demographic groups such as individuals with sensory-based disabilities such as those with hearing or vision loss. We were interested in understanding what instructional design considerations were needed to best support student participation and understanding. We also wanted to understand what underlying motivations contributed to student interest in participation in the program, and if this influenced their desire to continue further technical study. Students participated in day-long Saturday sessions for a period of 12-weeks that focused on a range of technical topics including Scratch and game design. The project utilized a range of teaching and facilitation techniques with a focus on students completing development steps through real-time instruction. Over the course of the program, students applied concepts and skills working towards a final technical project which was presented at a showcase for parents and community members at the end of the semester.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Findings indicated that students primary challenges in traditional academic settings is organization (62%), listening and attention (57%) and math (52%). This informed our approach to facilitating day-long sessions of the program including pacing of instruction, integration of breaks throughout the day, reiteration of examples and application of hands-on exercises. Participants expressed their primary reason for interest in participating was to build skills that would ?help in life? at 38% of respondents. 22% of students specifically participated with the goal of preparation for their future, including possible job opportunities. This indicates that students were largely self-motivated to participate with a desire to build technical capabilities and with an interest in potentially pursuing a career in the computer science discipline.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Parents and guardians indicated through surveys and interviews that minimal programming existed that was tailored specifically to the needs of their students. Guardians expressed that the program provided a positive exposure to shared-identity mentors, and observed a consistent enthusiasm among participants throughout the duration of the program. Findings indicated the mentoring component was a significant contributing factor to the programs success and led to the students developing meaningful relationships and improved self-identity as it pertains to their capacity to succeed in computing. This proved to be a mutually-beneficial experience for both student participants and mentors who cited engaging with students to be a generative experience. Another key finding that leaves opportunity for further examination was the lack of training provided to classroom educators for working with students of color with disabilities. To implement this project, URU developed a curriculum for coding, and teaching strategies that were tailored to the needs of the student population.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>As it stands, still limited educational models exist currently to address teaching rigorous coding and technical skills to individuals with disabilities tailored to the unique needs of each student. Further, few of these have been designed through the lens of connecting to students who identify as a racial or ethnic minority and those with behavior disorders. As such, this project served to establish the key elements that must be considered when working with students who hold intersecting identities across disability and racial/ethnic minority, in order to expand the design of intentional learning programs to connect more effectively with students. This initial program was effective in providing initial insight that can be developed in future programming to support this excluded group and broaden the diversity of future computing professionals.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/08/2023<br>      Modified by: Crystal&nbsp;Emery</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ EAGER: STEM Identity &amp; Computer Education: Overcoming the Intersectionality of Culture, Poverty &amp; Disability developed and implemented a coding program for 27 students, ages ranging of 13.5 years to 20.25 years. Students represented a variety of physical disabilities, neurodiversity, and behavioral disorders and were primarily Black and Latinx. The cohort of students represented a range of accommodations and needs. The program trained local mentors with shared-identities to support students throughout the program. The research was to better understand the needs of this student population ? students who come from low-income backgrounds, identify as students of color (predominantly Black and Latinx) and have a disability. This research leaves opportunity for future study on other student demographic groups such as individuals with sensory-based disabilities such as those with hearing or vision loss. We were interested in understanding what instructional design considerations were needed to best support student participation and understanding. We also wanted to understand what underlying motivations contributed to student interest in participation in the program, and if this influenced their desire to continue further technical study. Students participated in day-long Saturday sessions for a period of 12-weeks that focused on a range of technical topics including Scratch and game design. The project utilized a range of teaching and facilitation techniques with a focus on students completing development steps through real-time instruction. Over the course of the program, students applied concepts and skills working towards a final technical project which was presented at a showcase for parents and community members at the end of the semester.     Findings indicated that students primary challenges in traditional academic settings is organization (62%), listening and attention (57%) and math (52%). This informed our approach to facilitating day-long sessions of the program including pacing of instruction, integration of breaks throughout the day, reiteration of examples and application of hands-on exercises. Participants expressed their primary reason for interest in participating was to build skills that would ?help in life? at 38% of respondents. 22% of students specifically participated with the goal of preparation for their future, including possible job opportunities. This indicates that students were largely self-motivated to participate with a desire to build technical capabilities and with an interest in potentially pursuing a career in the computer science discipline.     Parents and guardians indicated through surveys and interviews that minimal programming existed that was tailored specifically to the needs of their students. Guardians expressed that the program provided a positive exposure to shared-identity mentors, and observed a consistent enthusiasm among participants throughout the duration of the program. Findings indicated the mentoring component was a significant contributing factor to the programs success and led to the students developing meaningful relationships and improved self-identity as it pertains to their capacity to succeed in computing. This proved to be a mutually-beneficial experience for both student participants and mentors who cited engaging with students to be a generative experience. Another key finding that leaves opportunity for further examination was the lack of training provided to classroom educators for working with students of color with disabilities. To implement this project, URU developed a curriculum for coding, and teaching strategies that were tailored to the needs of the student population.     As it stands, still limited educational models exist currently to address teaching rigorous coding and technical skills to individuals with disabilities tailored to the unique needs of each student. Further, few of these have been designed through the lens of connecting to students who identify as a racial or ethnic minority and those with behavior disorders. As such, this project served to establish the key elements that must be considered when working with students who hold intersecting identities across disability and racial/ethnic minority, in order to expand the design of intentional learning programs to connect more effectively with students. This initial program was effective in providing initial insight that can be developed in future programming to support this excluded group and broaden the diversity of future computing professionals.          Last Modified: 02/08/2023       Submitted by: Crystal Emery]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
