<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Energy-Efficient Disinfection of Viral Bioaerosols in Public Spaces: Vital for Lifting of the “Stay-at-Home” Orders during the Covid-19 Outbreak]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>200000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>200000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Bruce Hamilton</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bhamilto@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032920000</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This project will provide an analytical framework to assess potential reduction of infection risks from COVID-19 viral bioaerosols in public spaces, including school buses, classrooms, and retail stores. Viral bioaerosols may cause infection for occupants staying both near and far away from infected people, whether staying indoors at the same time or not. Upper-room germicidal ultraviolet (UR-GUV) light can provide a real-time air disinfection solution with a relatively small energy footprint if its light effectively interacts with the bioaerosol both in the air and on surfaces. This project will develop and disseminate an open-source numerical analytical framework including assessment of UR-GUV disinfection and make it publicly available online to provide a free resource useful for helping to control the spread of airborne COVID-19 infections in public spaces. An effective, real-time, and sustainable engineering solution for air indoor space disinfection is an important precaution to help prevent the spread of COVID-19, particularly in the context of efforts to restart the nation's economy. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will develop numerical methods based on Computational Fluid Dynamics (CFD) to reproduce the processes for viral bioaerosols spread by indoor airflow, removed by exhaust, inactivated by UR-GUV, inhaled by the occupants, and deposited onto surfaces in public spaces of varied spatial scales, ventilation systems, as well as population size and density. This project will also optimize the application of ceiling fans to improve UR-GUV disinfection efficacy. The investigation will provide new insight on infection risk due to viral aerosols and infection control by UR-GUV for surfaces contaminated by viral bioaerosols. In addition, the project will consider two UV-C sources, one by traditional mercury vapor UV-C lamps (UV-C-MV) and another by UV-C-LED for their energy efficiency. The comparison of the two UV-C sources in terms of disinfection, energy efficiencies, and operation cost holds promise for a sustainable UR-GUV solution for minimizing infection risk in public spaces.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/11/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/11/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2032107</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jelena</FirstName>
<LastName>Srebric</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jelena Srebric</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jsrebric@umd.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000106470</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/11/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Maryland, College Park</Name>
<CityName>College Park</CityName>
<ZipCode>207420001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3014056269</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3112 LEE BLDG 7809 REGENTS DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MD04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NPU8ULVAAS23</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MARYLAND, COLLEGE PARK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>KMGEN62NKEM9</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Maryland]]></Name>
<CityName>College Park</CityName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>207403809</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5000 College Ave.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MD04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7643</Code>
<Text>EnvS-Environmtl Sustainability</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~200000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>COVID-19 will redefined the concept of acceptable indoor air quality, as well as the required ventilation design / operation. Thsi project results provided the knowledge for the future development of ASHRAE Standard on ventilation and indoor air quality with respect to indoor aerosol infection control. Moreover, our result on 222-nm GUV application in the airport bus also shows the needs for the development of 222-nm UV technology with focus on UV fixture and its operation, and the knowledge on the exposure limit to 222-nm UV light.</p> <p>Our research team has provided the first insightd into the UR-GUV application in the two specific indoor settings, the bus with low ceiling and high occupancy, and the rehearsal room with a high ceiling. In this project, we developed a procedure including the generation of realistic UV fluence rate distribution, a Matlab code for the format conversion of UV fluence rate dataset, and a tool account for all the physical processes related to ventilation and air cleaning. Furthermore, we investigated the application of 222-nm UV light in the airport bus, where indicated inappropriate to apply the traditional UR-GUV with 254-nm UV light. We also showed the advantage of UR-GUV air disinfection technology in energy saving for air cleaning, with the whole building energy modeling and analysis. Our work has made City@UMD a national leading research unit on UR-GUV technologies, especially on its numerical modeling and analysis. The results will provide scientific and technological understanding on the application of UR-GUV, and help the policy makers to determine the occupancy rules for different indoor settings.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/21/2022<br>      Modified by: Jelena&nbsp;Srebric</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ COVID-19 will redefined the concept of acceptable indoor air quality, as well as the required ventilation design / operation. Thsi project results provided the knowledge for the future development of ASHRAE Standard on ventilation and indoor air quality with respect to indoor aerosol infection control. Moreover, our result on 222-nm GUV application in the airport bus also shows the needs for the development of 222-nm UV technology with focus on UV fixture and its operation, and the knowledge on the exposure limit to 222-nm UV light.  Our research team has provided the first insightd into the UR-GUV application in the two specific indoor settings, the bus with low ceiling and high occupancy, and the rehearsal room with a high ceiling. In this project, we developed a procedure including the generation of realistic UV fluence rate distribution, a Matlab code for the format conversion of UV fluence rate dataset, and a tool account for all the physical processes related to ventilation and air cleaning. Furthermore, we investigated the application of 222-nm UV light in the airport bus, where indicated inappropriate to apply the traditional UR-GUV with 254-nm UV light. We also showed the advantage of UR-GUV air disinfection technology in energy saving for air cleaning, with the whole building energy modeling and analysis. Our work has made City@UMD a national leading research unit on UR-GUV technologies, especially on its numerical modeling and analysis. The results will provide scientific and technological understanding on the application of UR-GUV, and help the policy makers to determine the occupancy rules for different indoor settings.       Last Modified: 11/21/2022       Submitted by: Jelena Srebric]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
