<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Effects of COVID-19 on Community Solidarity]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>67146.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>67146</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joseph Whitmeyer</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jwhitmey@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927808</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[In this project, how health pandemics affect levels of community solidarity, how these levels differ from other tragedies, and whether solidarity can be generated and sustained using virtual means are explored.  Tragedies, such as mass shootings and natural disasters, often bring communities together in solidarity as their residents gather to mourn and comfort one another.  While the COVID-19 tragedy has created an environment ripe for solidarity, coming together in mutual support – the typical method for generating and sustaining solidarity –  has not been possible because of the widely adopted social distancing guidelines that has prevented being physically close.  Findings promote national health and welfare by furthering understanding of how feelings of community and belonging are promoted even when we cannot be in physical proximity. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The fundamental goals of the project are to explore whether the solidarity-generating effects of natural disasters are similar to those of man-made disasters, if and how communicating virtually can promote and sustain solidarity in a way comparable to interaction in the physical world, and what role culture-building institutions can play in buffering the effects of a pandemic. Four waves of survey panel data from students from one particular university and a national sample of college-aged students are used (1) to compare current levels of community solidarity in at the university to levels of community solidarity before and after a tragic event that occurred on the campus; (2) to document changes in levels of solidarity over time to determine if trajectories are similar to those witnessed after other tragedies; (3) to track the various types of virtual communication that are associated with higher levels of community solidarity and sustained levels of solidarity; (4) to explore the relationships between sociodemographic variables and feelings of solidarity; (5) to map respondents’ involvement in and commitment to the campus culture and their feelings of community solidarity over time; and (6) to compare levels of solidarity among this university’s students with those of other college-aged Americans over time.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/29/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/29/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2032452</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ashley</FirstName>
<LastName>Reichelmann</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ashley Reichelmann</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[avr@vt.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000767049</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/29/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Hawdon</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>James Hawdon</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[hawdonj@vt.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000223725</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/29/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University</Name>
<CityName>BLACKSBURG</CityName>
<ZipCode>240603359</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5402315281</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>300 TURNER ST NW</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[STE 4200]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>VA09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>QDE5UHE5XD16</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>VIRGINIA POLYTECHNIC INSTITUTE &amp; STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>X6KEFGLHSJX7</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Blacksburg</CityName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>240600137</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[225 Stanger St]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>VA09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1331</Code>
<Text>Sociology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~67146</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Mass tragedies and natural disasters often bring communities together in solidarity as their residents gather to mourn and comfort each other. Evidence indicates that this solidarity helps both communities and individuals as they recover from these events.&nbsp; This project investigated if the COVID-19 pandemic resulted in solidarity since coming together in mutual support -- the typical method for generating and sustaining solidarity -- was not possible due to social distancing guidelines that discouraged people from being physically close. Did interacting virtually generate and sustain solidarity in a similar way that interacting physically does?&nbsp;</p> <p>We used survey data to compare levels of solidarity on Virginia Tech's campus after two tragedies: the 2007 Virginia Tech school shooting and the COVID-19 pandemic.&nbsp; We found that solidarity increased by 18% after the 2007 murders and by 12% after the onset of COVID-19.&nbsp; We also compared the trajectories of solidarity after the two tragedies.&nbsp; Not only was the increase in solidarity greater after the shooting than after the onset of COVID-19, the heightened levels of solidarity normalized more quickly after the pandemic than after the shooting.&nbsp; Unlike in 2007 when levels of solidarity remained elevated for approximately twelve months, levels of solidarity decreased below normal levels nine months after the pandemic began and did not return to normal until one year after the pandemic's onset.&nbsp; Thus, unlike in 2007, the initial increase in solidarity witnessed at the early stages of the pandemic was not sustained.&nbsp; The finding highlights the importance of in-person interactions for sustaining solidarity.&nbsp; Since the pandemic resulted in the forced termination of nearly all interaction beyond one's small primary group or "pod," the group could not collectively grieve and its solidarity suffered as a result.</p> <p>We also studied how the different types of interactions people engaged in after the tragedy relate to levels of solidarity.&nbsp; We investigated if personal relations (interacting with friends/family), public relations (interacting with Virginia Tech employees/students), and parochial relations (interacting with community members in religious institutions, social clubs, schools, or local businesses) influenced solidarity.&nbsp; Similar to the 2007 tragedy, private relations generated solidarity and parochial relations sustained solidarity.&nbsp; Engaging with fellow community members were correlated with high levels of solidarity even a year after the pandemic's onset.&nbsp; Two differences between the tragedies were observed, however. First, public relations were related to lower levels of solidarity during the pandemic, but this was not the case in 2007.&nbsp; This difference is likely due to how these interactions occurred. In 2020, these interactions occurred virtually since the university had moved most classes online.&nbsp; These virtual interactions likely reminded people of what had been lost due to the pandemic. Unlike in 2007 when pubic interactions reinforced the group's sense of community, those of 2020 simply reminded students that their group was still&nbsp;experiencing the trauma. A second difference is that private relations were also important in sustaining levels of solidarity during the pandemic; these did not sustain solidarity after the 2007 tragedy. This finding is likely due to that fact that students were able to remain engaged with their community through social media. These findings again highlight the importance of relations that immerse individuals in their community.</p> <p>&nbsp;Additionally, we observed that levels of solidarity followed similar patterns of increasing immediately after the tragedy and then slowly returning to pre-tragedy levels for all racial, ethnic, and age groups studied, but solidarity decreased more rapidly for females compared to males. This finding suggests the pandemic affected females more profoundly than it did males.&nbsp; Finally, comparing students at Virginia Tech with students at other four-year public universities revealed that levels of solidarity at other universities followed a similar trajectory as at Virginia Tech; however, Virginia Tech students consistently expressed higher levels of solidarity.</p> <p>These research outcomes advance the theoretical model of community solidarity that has been applied to numerous tragedies.&nbsp; The findings indicate that virtual interactions can generate solidarity, but these are not as effective as face-to-face interactions for sustaining solidarity. Moreover, the research demonstrates one way that the pandemic more profoundly affected women. Finally, these outcomes inform scholars about how recovery may differ depending on if a tragedy occurs suddenly or if it unfolds slowly as the COVID-19 pandemic did.&nbsp;</p> <p>The research has broader impacts and advances the nation's welfare by documenting how virtual interactions can effectively generate feelings of solidarity after tragedies.&nbsp; These interactions can assist communities and individuals as they recover from tragedies.&nbsp; These interactions appear to be effective regardless of the nature of the tragedy, be it human-made or naturally occurring.&nbsp; However, a community's wellbeing cannot be sustained solely with virtual interactions. Face-to-face interactions are needed for continued wellbeing. Therefore, the research informs scholars as well as community leaders and those engaged in recovery work about how communities recover after disasters and mass tragedies.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/01/2022<br>      Modified by: James&nbsp;Hawdon</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2032452/2032452_10681284_1669827537206_SolidarityafterTwoTragedies--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2032452/2032452_10681284_1669827537206_SolidarityafterTwoTragedies--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Solidarity after Two Tragedies"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2032452/2032452_10681284_1669827537206_SolidarityafterTwoTragedies--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Solidarity after Two Tragedies"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The 2006 and 2009 surveys are from separate projects. August 2007, and the 2008 surveys are from a NSF project studying solidarity after the 2007 murders. April 2020, October 2020, February 2021, and April 2021 surveys were collected to investigate solidarity after the onset of the COVID-19.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Hawdon and Reichelmann</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">James&nbsp;Hawdon</div> <div class="imageTitle">Solidarity after Two Tragedies</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Mass tragedies and natural disasters often bring communities together in solidarity as their residents gather to mourn and comfort each other. Evidence indicates that this solidarity helps both communities and individuals as they recover from these events.  This project investigated if the COVID-19 pandemic resulted in solidarity since coming together in mutual support -- the typical method for generating and sustaining solidarity -- was not possible due to social distancing guidelines that discouraged people from being physically close. Did interacting virtually generate and sustain solidarity in a similar way that interacting physically does?   We used survey data to compare levels of solidarity on Virginia Tech's campus after two tragedies: the 2007 Virginia Tech school shooting and the COVID-19 pandemic.  We found that solidarity increased by 18% after the 2007 murders and by 12% after the onset of COVID-19.  We also compared the trajectories of solidarity after the two tragedies.  Not only was the increase in solidarity greater after the shooting than after the onset of COVID-19, the heightened levels of solidarity normalized more quickly after the pandemic than after the shooting.  Unlike in 2007 when levels of solidarity remained elevated for approximately twelve months, levels of solidarity decreased below normal levels nine months after the pandemic began and did not return to normal until one year after the pandemic's onset.  Thus, unlike in 2007, the initial increase in solidarity witnessed at the early stages of the pandemic was not sustained.  The finding highlights the importance of in-person interactions for sustaining solidarity.  Since the pandemic resulted in the forced termination of nearly all interaction beyond one's small primary group or "pod," the group could not collectively grieve and its solidarity suffered as a result.  We also studied how the different types of interactions people engaged in after the tragedy relate to levels of solidarity.  We investigated if personal relations (interacting with friends/family), public relations (interacting with Virginia Tech employees/students), and parochial relations (interacting with community members in religious institutions, social clubs, schools, or local businesses) influenced solidarity.  Similar to the 2007 tragedy, private relations generated solidarity and parochial relations sustained solidarity.  Engaging with fellow community members were correlated with high levels of solidarity even a year after the pandemic's onset.  Two differences between the tragedies were observed, however. First, public relations were related to lower levels of solidarity during the pandemic, but this was not the case in 2007.  This difference is likely due to how these interactions occurred. In 2020, these interactions occurred virtually since the university had moved most classes online.  These virtual interactions likely reminded people of what had been lost due to the pandemic. Unlike in 2007 when pubic interactions reinforced the group's sense of community, those of 2020 simply reminded students that their group was still experiencing the trauma. A second difference is that private relations were also important in sustaining levels of solidarity during the pandemic; these did not sustain solidarity after the 2007 tragedy. This finding is likely due to that fact that students were able to remain engaged with their community through social media. These findings again highlight the importance of relations that immerse individuals in their community.   Additionally, we observed that levels of solidarity followed similar patterns of increasing immediately after the tragedy and then slowly returning to pre-tragedy levels for all racial, ethnic, and age groups studied, but solidarity decreased more rapidly for females compared to males. This finding suggests the pandemic affected females more profoundly than it did males.  Finally, comparing students at Virginia Tech with students at other four-year public universities revealed that levels of solidarity at other universities followed a similar trajectory as at Virginia Tech; however, Virginia Tech students consistently expressed higher levels of solidarity.  These research outcomes advance the theoretical model of community solidarity that has been applied to numerous tragedies.  The findings indicate that virtual interactions can generate solidarity, but these are not as effective as face-to-face interactions for sustaining solidarity. Moreover, the research demonstrates one way that the pandemic more profoundly affected women. Finally, these outcomes inform scholars about how recovery may differ depending on if a tragedy occurs suddenly or if it unfolds slowly as the COVID-19 pandemic did.   The research has broader impacts and advances the nation's welfare by documenting how virtual interactions can effectively generate feelings of solidarity after tragedies.  These interactions can assist communities and individuals as they recover from tragedies.  These interactions appear to be effective regardless of the nature of the tragedy, be it human-made or naturally occurring.  However, a community's wellbeing cannot be sustained solely with virtual interactions. Face-to-face interactions are needed for continued wellbeing. Therefore, the research informs scholars as well as community leaders and those engaged in recovery work about how communities recover after disasters and mass tragedies.           Last Modified: 12/01/2022       Submitted by: James Hawdon]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
