<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research: RAPID: Integrative Modeling of Intervention Serology and the Role of Shield Immunity in Reducing COVID-19 Epidemic Spread]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>99430.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>99430</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Katharina Dittmar</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kdittmar@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927799</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Developing intervention strategies that can reduce transmission and alleviate the impacts of social distancing is an essential goal of near- and long-term public health responses to the ongoing COVID-19 pandemic. This project combines epidemic models of COVID-19 with serological testing modules to develop actionable policies to robustly identify recovered individuals who have protective antibodies to SARS-CoV-2019 as a means to (i) reduce infection transmission; (ii) facilitate interaction substitution that can reduce transmission risk (the basis for ‘shield immunity’); (iii) enable safer return to normal economic activity.  Findings from shield immunity modeling studies will be released via open-source software, disseminated via policy-making documents that guide the design, interpretation, and action-taking from serological testing initiatives, and communicated with local, state, and national decision makers (e.g. CDC) via rapid response reports. The project will help assess feasibility of scaling up targeted serological testing and shield immunity-based interventions for the public good and economic re-engagement. Additionally, this project will provide training opportunities for graduate students and a postdoctoral scholar.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Mitigation and suppression have emerged as the primary means to control and contain local spread of COVID-19. Public health interventions including lockdowns and shelter-in-place orders both reduce infections and raise questions of sustainability and long-term tactics, given the drastic consequences for socio-economic health and well-being. This project expands intervention approaches by extending the conceptual and practical foundations for ‘shield immunity’, i.e., the identification and deployment of recovered individuals as focal points for sustaining safer interactions via interaction substitution of otherwise risky contacts between individuals of unknown disease status. This project evaluates the practical potential of shield immunity by combining realistic scale-out of test capacity and reliability into an integrated framework with explicit consideration of individual status both with respect to disease status and with respect to serological test status. Altogether, the research integrates epidemiological dynamics, nonlinear dynamics, and statistical test analytics. The analysis of combined effects of interaction substitution, test scale, and test reliability will help inform efforts to prudently leverage information on seroconversion and immunity to help control COVID-19 spread while facilitating the safer return of individuals back to economic and social activities. This RAPID award is made by the Ecology and Evolution of Infectious Disease Program in the Division of Environmental Biology, using funds from the Coronavirus Aid, Relief, and Economic Security (CARES) Act.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/28/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/28/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2032082</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Joshua</FirstName>
<LastName>Weitz</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Joshua S Weitz</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jsweitz@umd.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000477951</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/28/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Georgia Tech Research Corporation</Name>
<CityName>ATLANTA</CityName>
<ZipCode>30332</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4048944819</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>926 DALNEY ST NW</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>EMW9FC8J3HN4</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GEORGIA TECH RESEARCH CORPORATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>EMW9FC8J3HN4</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Georgia Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>303320230</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[310 Ferst Dr.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>158Y</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>1N20</Code>
<Name>R&amp;RA CARES Act DEFC N</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>010N2021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[R&RA CARES Act DEFC N]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~99430</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-d8324001-7fff-fcbd-ec8d-2020a7ba8003">&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Overview: </span><span>This project developed and assessed potential intervention strategies to reduce transmission and alleviate the impacts of social distancing amidst the ongoing COVID-19 pandemic. In doing so, realistic models of testing - for both disease and immunization status - were integrated as control components of epidemic models of COVID-19 as a means to (i) reduce infection transmission; (ii) facilitate interaction substitution (the basis for &lsquo;shield immunity&rsquo;); (iii) enable safer return to normal economic activity.&nbsp; The results of this project led to new networked intervention models, proof-of-principle analyses for how to switch from lockdowns to personalized pandemic policies, and the deployment of multiple websites that advanced both conceptual and practical understanding of the risk of exposure and the baseline level of population immunity in the US.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Intellectual Merit: </span><span>Mitigation and suppression have emerged as the primary means to control and contain local spread of the COVD-19 pandemic. Public health interventions including lockdowns and shelter-in-place orders reduce infections but also raise questions of sustainability and long-term tactics, given the drastic consequences for socio-economic health and well-being.&nbsp; This project expanded intervention approaches by extending the conceptual and practical foundations for `shield immunity&rsquo;, i.e., changing the interaction rates of immune individuals. By combining our own primary sero-epidemiology data with computational models, this project showed how shield immunity is robust to inclusion of realistic features of test capacity, test characteristics, and in applications to health care settings. The extension of shield immunity principles to networked interactions provides an actionable opportunity to leverage disease and immune status to change cohorting, scheduling, and interaction behaviours in real-world settings (with an emphasis on vulnerable communities in health-care and long-term care facilities). Additional work revealed the impacts of heterogeneity in terms of the accumulation of population immunity while highlighting the risk of transmission in large events - in both cases connecting policy decisions to ongoing risk and opportunities to reduce transmission via non-pharmaceutical interventions. Moving forward, the analysis of interaction substitution, test scale, and test reliability will help inform efforts to leverage existing immunity - ideally derived from vaccination - to help control COVID-19 spread while facilitating the safe return of individuals back to economic and social activities.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Broader Impacts: </span><span>The research impacts of this proposal integrated epidemiological dynamics, network theory, control theory, nonlinear dynamics, and statistical test analytics.&nbsp; The findings will impact multiple fields, given the integrated and multi-disciplinary responses necessary to establish conceptual models of interventions and to translate those interventions into actionable policies. The dissemination impacts</span><span> </span><span>of this proposal included multiple releases of public-facing websites powered by open-source code.&nbsp; These websites include a Covid-19 Event Risk Assessment Planning Tool (</span><a href="https://covid19risk.biosci.gatech.edu/"><span>https://covid19risk.biosci.gatech.edu</span></a><span>; accessed by more than 8M individuals since launch in July 2020), a conceptual introduction to shield immunity concepts (</span><a href="https://shieldimmunity.biosci.gatech.edu/"><span>https://shieldimmunity.biosci.gatech.edu/</span></a><span>), and a real-time estimator of state level variation in population immunity (</span><a href="https://popimmunity.biosci.gatech.edu/"><span>https://popimmunity.biosci.gatech.edu</span></a><span>). Results from these studies have been distributed via journal articles, brief reports, Op-Eds, blogs, press interviews, interactions with policy makers and public health officials, and communicated directly to the public via interactive website dashboards and social media campaigns. Multiple undergraduate students, graduate students, postdoctoral researchers, and software engineers contributed to both the science and dissemination components of the project.</span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/27/2021<br>      Modified by: Joshua&nbsp;S&nbsp;Weitz</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   Overview: This project developed and assessed potential intervention strategies to reduce transmission and alleviate the impacts of social distancing amidst the ongoing COVID-19 pandemic. In doing so, realistic models of testing - for both disease and immunization status - were integrated as control components of epidemic models of COVID-19 as a means to (i) reduce infection transmission; (ii) facilitate interaction substitution (the basis for ‘shield immunity’); (iii) enable safer return to normal economic activity.  The results of this project led to new networked intervention models, proof-of-principle analyses for how to switch from lockdowns to personalized pandemic policies, and the deployment of multiple websites that advanced both conceptual and practical understanding of the risk of exposure and the baseline level of population immunity in the US.   Intellectual Merit: Mitigation and suppression have emerged as the primary means to control and contain local spread of the COVD-19 pandemic. Public health interventions including lockdowns and shelter-in-place orders reduce infections but also raise questions of sustainability and long-term tactics, given the drastic consequences for socio-economic health and well-being.  This project expanded intervention approaches by extending the conceptual and practical foundations for `shield immunity’, i.e., changing the interaction rates of immune individuals. By combining our own primary sero-epidemiology data with computational models, this project showed how shield immunity is robust to inclusion of realistic features of test capacity, test characteristics, and in applications to health care settings. The extension of shield immunity principles to networked interactions provides an actionable opportunity to leverage disease and immune status to change cohorting, scheduling, and interaction behaviours in real-world settings (with an emphasis on vulnerable communities in health-care and long-term care facilities). Additional work revealed the impacts of heterogeneity in terms of the accumulation of population immunity while highlighting the risk of transmission in large events - in both cases connecting policy decisions to ongoing risk and opportunities to reduce transmission via non-pharmaceutical interventions. Moving forward, the analysis of interaction substitution, test scale, and test reliability will help inform efforts to leverage existing immunity - ideally derived from vaccination - to help control COVID-19 spread while facilitating the safe return of individuals back to economic and social activities.   Broader Impacts: The research impacts of this proposal integrated epidemiological dynamics, network theory, control theory, nonlinear dynamics, and statistical test analytics.  The findings will impact multiple fields, given the integrated and multi-disciplinary responses necessary to establish conceptual models of interventions and to translate those interventions into actionable policies. The dissemination impacts of this proposal included multiple releases of public-facing websites powered by open-source code.  These websites include a Covid-19 Event Risk Assessment Planning Tool (https://covid19risk.biosci.gatech.edu; accessed by more than 8M individuals since launch in July 2020), a conceptual introduction to shield immunity concepts (https://shieldimmunity.biosci.gatech.edu/), and a real-time estimator of state level variation in population immunity (https://popimmunity.biosci.gatech.edu). Results from these studies have been distributed via journal articles, brief reports, Op-Eds, blogs, press interviews, interactions with policy makers and public health officials, and communicated directly to the public via interactive website dashboards and social media campaigns. Multiple undergraduate students, graduate students, postdoctoral researchers, and software engineers contributed to both the science and dissemination components of the project.       Last Modified: 09/27/2021       Submitted by: Joshua S Weitz]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
