<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Developing and Researching Youth-Driven Media that Highlights Science as an Act of Service During a Public Health Crisis]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>151040.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>151040</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DRL</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Alicia Santiago Gonzalez</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>asantiag@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924546</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[During the COVID-19 pandemic, numerous media sources have placed a spotlight on the critical role of science and scientists in promoting public health. In contrast to many existing media sources that portray images of adult scientists, this project will develop media that portrays youth scientists as they conduct scientific research related to COVID-19. This media will be developed based on the findings from focus groups with youth of color, and it will include features that are designed to encourage youth to see the value of science while envisioning themselves as participants in science. These features include showing first-person narratives of youth of color; portraying science as a team endeavor; and framing science as an act of service to local communities and to society at large. After developing a video with these features, researchers at the University of Oregon Eugene will share the video with youth of color who will share their responses in focus groups. This project will broaden participation in science career pathways by advancing knowledge of the features of media that motivate youth to pursue science careers and career pathways. This project is funded by the Innovative Technology Experiences for Students and Teachers (ITEST) program, which supports projects that build understandings of practices, program elements, contexts and processes contributing to increasing students' knowledge and interest in science, technology, engineering, and mathematics (STEM) and information and communication technology (ICT) careers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Researchers at the University of Oregon Eugene will conduct focus groups with 30 high school students who identify with races or ethnicities that are underrepresented in STEM careers. These focus groups will include reflections related to the COVID-19 pandemic and the purpose of science. Informed by data from these focus groups, undergraduate students in the University of Oregon’s School of Journalism and Communication will use footage from professional and student scientists conducting research related to COVID-19, as well as first-person narratives from high school students, to produce a new video titled “Science as Service.” This video will highlight the global, community-focused, service-oriented nature of science as conducted by diverse teams. The research team will then conduct a qualitative study to determine how youth from underrepresented groups respond to this new video by conducting focus groups with 30 high school students who identify with races or ethnicities that are underrepresented in STEM careers. These focus groups, conducted after the students watched the video, will be designed to elicit aspects of the students’ perceptions of science, science identities, and motivations to pursue science. A constant comparative analysis will illustrate how youth perceived science and their motivations to pursue science careers and career pathways relative to the video. Empirical findings will be shared in empirical journals, while the video will be disseminated widely through existing national networks and organizations.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/16/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/16/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2032226</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jenefer</FirstName>
<LastName>Husman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jenefer E Husman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jhusman@uoregon.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000392620</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/16/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ross</FirstName>
<LastName>Anderson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ross C Anderson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[rossa@uoregon.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000712910</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/16/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ed</FirstName>
<LastName>Madison</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ed Madison</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[madison2@uoregon.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000724439</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/16/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Matthew</FirstName>
<LastName>Kim</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Matthew Kim</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[matthew.kim@uky.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000728827</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/16/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Oregon Eugene</Name>
<CityName>EUGENE</CityName>
<ZipCode>974031657</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5413465131</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1585 E 13TH AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OR04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>Z3FGN9MF92U2</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF OREGON</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>L17DBQFXJVJ6</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Oregon]]></Name>
<CityName>Eugene</CityName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<ZipCode>974035219</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5219 University of Oregon]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OR04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7227</Code>
<Text>ITEST-Inov Tech Exp Stu &amp; Teac</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>13XX</Code>
<Name>H-1B FUND, EHR, NSF</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>045176</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>1300XXXXDB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[H-1B FUND, EDU, NSF]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>045176</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~151040</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-ef6789e1-7fff-6515-92a9-15ed05aae82a"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><strong>Project Outcomes</strong></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Building on a concurrent NSF-funded ?My STEM Story? study (DRL 1759442) and informed by a global pandemic, the researchers learned about students? engagement with an educational video that highlighted science as an act of service to one?s community and broader society.&nbsp;</span>The video featured a mentoring relationship between a graduate researcher studying marine ecology at a four-year university and a high school student with an interest in science.</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>A key aim of this study was to examine how students' personal and cultural perspectives and identities might influence how they experienced the COVID-19 pandemic and its role in informing their motivational beliefs and values related to science.</span><span><br /></span><span><br /></span><span>The researchers conducted 11 focus groups with 36 students and found three prominent themes regarding emerging science identity:</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span><strong>1)</strong> Seeing other students of similar ages in the videos helped focus group participants identify with a future science identity, reflecting the importance of peer influence.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span><strong>2)</strong> Students? reflections about their future identity related to science were often uncertain and couched in abstract terms, but were sometimes connected to a purpose with a communal benefit to the broader world and agentic (expressing control on one's own behalf) benefit to their own lives.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span><strong>3)</strong> Students? pandemic experiences reflected the multifaceted nature of adolescent identity exploration beyond science identity.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><span>Two studies completed to date applied integrative theoretical frameworks. Findings from the first study, titled </span><em>Adolescent identity development in sociohistorical context: Interpersonal connections, social goals, and perceptions of time and agency during a pandemic</em><span>,</span><span> </span><span>incorporated ecological systems theory, identity-based motivation theory, and socioemotional selectivity theory. This approach helped frame and the ideas students carry about their future directions in science and other domains. </span></p> <p><span id="docs-internal-guid-ef6789e1-7fff-6515-92a9-15ed05aae82a"><span>Findings from the second study, titled</span><span><em> Implicit theories and interest development in science: An integrative theoretical perspective</em>,</span><span> examined how racially diverse high school students understand science interest through three theoretical lenses: implicit theories, interest development theory, and identity-based motivation theory. </span></span></p> <p><span id="docs-internal-guid-ef6789e1-7fff-6515-92a9-15ed05aae82a"><span>Analysis of the focus group data for the second study revealed:</span></span></p> <ol> <li><span id="docs-internal-guid-ef6789e1-7fff-6515-92a9-15ed05aae82a"><span>Students perceive interests as hierarchical (arranged in order of rank) and nested (existing inside another).</span></span></li> <li><span><span>Incremental-entity theories and situational-individual interest map on in complex ways.</span></span></li> <li><span><span>The individual?s social ecology exerts strong influence on the development of and beliefs about science interest.&nbsp;</span></span>Exposure to the firsthand perspectives of diverse near-peers who have developed their own paths beyond high school in science reinforced the importance of following one?s interests and values no matter the challenges or discouragement from others.</li> </ol> <p><span id="docs-internal-guid-253c4428-7fff-c3ff-c19d-0ace8a61b3dd"><strong>Additional Information</strong><span><br /></span><span><br /></span><span>The video produced for this study was included in an online curriculum called ?My STEM Story? (</span><a href="https://app.mystemstoryproject.org/"><span>https://app.mystemstoryproject.org</span></a><span>) that was used in a larger study focused on the effects of digital storytelling featuring near-peer (peers who are close in age and educational attainment) mentorships on adolescent science identity and science motivation. A website with a modified version of the curriculum will be made available to educators at no cost. The purpose of the curriculum is to amplify diverse voices in science to improve adolescent engagement in STEM (Science, Technology, Engineering, and Math) career pathways, with a particular focus on under-represented students in STEM. </span></span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/28/2022<br>      Modified by: Ed&nbsp;Madison</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   Project Outcomes Building on a concurrent NSF-funded ?My STEM Story? study (DRL 1759442) and informed by a global pandemic, the researchers learned about students? engagement with an educational video that highlighted science as an act of service to one?s community and broader society. The video featured a mentoring relationship between a graduate researcher studying marine ecology at a four-year university and a high school student with an interest in science. A key aim of this study was to examine how students' personal and cultural perspectives and identities might influence how they experienced the COVID-19 pandemic and its role in informing their motivational beliefs and values related to science.  The researchers conducted 11 focus groups with 36 students and found three prominent themes regarding emerging science identity: 1) Seeing other students of similar ages in the videos helped focus group participants identify with a future science identity, reflecting the importance of peer influence. 2) Students? reflections about their future identity related to science were often uncertain and couched in abstract terms, but were sometimes connected to a purpose with a communal benefit to the broader world and agentic (expressing control on one's own behalf) benefit to their own lives. 3) Students? pandemic experiences reflected the multifaceted nature of adolescent identity exploration beyond science identity.     Two studies completed to date applied integrative theoretical frameworks. Findings from the first study, titled Adolescent identity development in sociohistorical context: Interpersonal connections, social goals, and perceptions of time and agency during a pandemic, incorporated ecological systems theory, identity-based motivation theory, and socioemotional selectivity theory. This approach helped frame and the ideas students carry about their future directions in science and other domains.   Findings from the second study, titled Implicit theories and interest development in science: An integrative theoretical perspective, examined how racially diverse high school students understand science interest through three theoretical lenses: implicit theories, interest development theory, and identity-based motivation theory.   Analysis of the focus group data for the second study revealed:  Students perceive interests as hierarchical (arranged in order of rank) and nested (existing inside another). Incremental-entity theories and situational-individual interest map on in complex ways. The individual?s social ecology exerts strong influence on the development of and beliefs about science interest. Exposure to the firsthand perspectives of diverse near-peers who have developed their own paths beyond high school in science reinforced the importance of following one?s interests and values no matter the challenges or discouragement from others.   Additional Information  The video produced for this study was included in an online curriculum called ?My STEM Story? (https://app.mystemstoryproject.org) that was used in a larger study focused on the effects of digital storytelling featuring near-peer (peers who are close in age and educational attainment) mentorships on adolescent science identity and science motivation. A website with a modified version of the curriculum will be made available to educators at no cost. The purpose of the curriculum is to amplify diverse voices in science to improve adolescent engagement in STEM (Science, Technology, Engineering, and Math) career pathways, with a particular focus on under-represented students in STEM.        Last Modified: 10/28/2022       Submitted by: Ed Madison]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
