<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[The Thermodynamic Properties of Rare Earth Element (REE) Minerals: A Solid Solution Model for Xenotime-(Y) and Monazite-(Ce)]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>52453.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>52453</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jennifer Wade</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jwade@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924739</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The Rare-Earth Elements (REE) are among the most critical elements used in a variety of new technological applications. The minerals xenotime-(Y) and monazite-(Ce) are common minerals that contain these rare earth elements (REE) in the Earth's crust. In addition to their societal relevance, REE bearing minerals (phosphates) have proven to be important geological tracers for constraining timing and temperatures of crustal processes. The full potential for retrieving information from REE phosphates in different geological settings has just begun to be explored, and the properties of REE minerals have gained an increased economic interest in the search for critical metals, which play this major role in emerging high technology and green industries. The proposed study combines laboratory experiments with numerical modeling for building a new thermodynamic fluid-mineral solid solution model that can be applied to the study of ore deposits and metamorphic/metasomatic processes in geological settings.  This research will be disseminated by implementing the resulting data in the open access MINES thermodynamic database (http://tdb.mines.edu/), and a set of educational modeling projects will be provided on a dedicated webpage. A short course on REE mineral deposits and numerical modeling will be organized at the Colorado School of Mines (CSM) to introduce the application of this database. This project will also promote an early career scientist by supporting the investigator's new crustal fluid-rock laboratory, where he will train 2 graduate students and involve summer undergraduate students from CSM and/or the Brazil Scientific Mobility program. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Using numerical simulations, the team will predict the stability of minerals and fluids in the Earth's crust as a function of pressure and temperature, and expand these capabilities based on experiments and new theoretical models. Our current understanding of the behavior of REE in aqueous fluids and minerals is limited by the paucity of available thermodynamic data for REE mineral solid solutions. The proposed work will combine laboratory mineral solubility and calorimetric experiments to determine the enthalpy of mixing of binary REE phosphate solid solutions, the solubility of end members and their heat capacities. This will permit building an internally consistent thermodynamic dataset that will be implemented in the Gibbs energy minimization program GEMS, and applied to study the genesis of hydrothermal REE mineral deposits. The project will attempt to cross boundaries between metamorphic petrology and geochemistry, and is expected to have an impact for the interpretation of the behavior of REE in crustal fluids. This knowledge can be extended to determine the effects of major ligands on the mobility of metals in the crust, and may be applied to systems were the composition of accessory mineral solid solutions could be used to track metasomatic stages during metamorphism.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/19/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/19/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2032761</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alexander</FirstName>
<LastName>Gysi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alexander Gysi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[Alexander.Gysi@nmt.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000678831</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/19/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>New Mexico Institute of Mining and Technology</Name>
<CityName>SOCORRO</CityName>
<ZipCode>878014681</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5758355496</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>801 LEROY PL</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Mexico</StateName>
<StateCode>NM</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NM02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>HZJ2JZUALWN4</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NEW MEXICO INSTITUTE OF MINING AND TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>HZJ2JZUALWN4</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[New Mexico Institute of Mining and Technology]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NM</StateCode>
<ZipCode>878014681</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Mexico</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NM02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1573</Code>
<Text>Petrology and Geochemistry</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01001920DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~52453</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p style="line-height: 100%; margin-bottom: 0in;">The rare earth elements (REE) are important for society because of their use in the high-tech and green technology industries. These critical elements can be enriched through magmatic-hydrothermal processes that form mineral deposits in natural systems. The REE phosphates monazite and xenotime as well as their hydrated variants (i.e. rhabdophane and churchite) are common hosts to REE in these deposits, but are also found in many other geologic systems. The major problem this project addresses, is to determine the stability of these minerals in hydrothermal aqueous fluids and the stability of solid solutions with mixed compositions of the form Ce<sub>1-x</sub>REE<sub>x</sub>PO<sub>4</sub> (x= mole fraction from 0 to 1; REE = La, Pr, Nd, Sm, Eu, and Gd). The overarching goal of the project is to develop a thermodynamic model that enables simulating the stability of these minerals in hydrothermal systems. The hypothesis followed is that the REE compositions of these phosphates are useful indicators of fluid chemistry and temperature in natural ore-forming systems.</p> <p style="line-height: 100%; margin-bottom: 0in;">&nbsp;</p> <p style="line-height: 100%; margin-bottom: 0in;">For this purpose, we conducted a series of mineral solubility experiments between 100 and 250 &deg;C with synthetic REE phosphates in acidic aqueous solution with a pH of 2. These experiments were used to determine the solubility products of all the monazite (La to Gd phosphates) and xenotime (Tb to Lu phosphates) endmembers. A series of solid solution compositions and pure endmembers were synthesized at room temperature using a solution calorimeter. The enthalpy of precipitation was measured and used to determine the ideal/non-ideal mixing properties of the solid solutions. The precipitated minerals were further analyzed using X-ray diffraction to determine their crystal structure and excess volume of mixing.</p> <p style="line-height: 100%; margin-bottom: 0in;">&nbsp;</p> <p style="line-height: 100%; margin-bottom: 0in;">The major outcomes from the monazite and xenotime solubility experiments are: 1) the solubility of REE is controlled by metastable hydrated REE phosphates (i.e., rhabdophane) &lt;100 &deg;C and monazite/xenotime between 100 and 250 &deg;C; 2) the experimentally derived monazite/xenotime solubilities can display several orders of magnitude higher values in comparison to the predicted solubility using previously available literature data for minerals and aqueous species; 3) major discrepancies between previous predictions and our new solubility experiments can be explained by a need to revise the thermodynamic properties of REE aqueous species controlling the solubility at acidic pH (i.e., REE<sup>3+</sup> and REEOH<sup>2+</sup>). The major outcomes from the solid solution precipitation experiments are: 1) rhabdophane solid solutions display a non-ideal behavior; 2) the excess volume of mixing is positive and becomes asymmetric with larger discrepancies in ionic radii between Ce and the substituting REE (i.e., Sm, Eu, and Gd); 3) the enthalpy of mixing is positive for La-Ce and Pr-Ce solid solutions, whereas the enthalpy of mixing becomes negative and display an asymmetric behavior for the smaller and heavier REE substituting for Ce (i.e., Nd, Sm, Eu and Gd).</p> <p style="line-height: 100%; margin-bottom: 0in;">&nbsp;</p> <p style="line-height: 100%; margin-bottom: 0in;">This work enabled us to revise thermodynamic data for all the REE phosphates and generate an internally consistent thermodynamic database for the REE-P-O-H-Na-Cl system. The MINES thermodynamic database includes these and future updates from the experiments and can be downloaded open access (<a href="https://geoinfo.nmt.edu/mines-tdb/">https://geoinfo.nmt.edu/mines-tdb/</a>). Further, a free tutorials gitbook (<a href="https://apgysi.github.io/gems-mines-tutorial/">https://apgysi.github.io/gems-mines-tutorial/</a>) was developed for this project, which can be used for education and professional development to learn geochemical modeling of fluid-rock interaction using the GEMS code package and the MINES database. We organized a total of five geochemical modeling workshops worldwide and the project has supported the training of four undergraduate students and four graduate students. The experimental equipment provided through this project will be used to continue training students in our Ore Deposits and Critical Minerals laboratory at New Mexico Tech.</p> <!-- p { line-height: 115%; margin-bottom: 0.1in; background: transparent }a:link { color: #000080; so-language: zxx; text-decoration: underline } --><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/07/2022<br>      Modified by: Alexander&nbsp;Gysi</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[The rare earth elements (REE) are important for society because of their use in the high-tech and green technology industries. These critical elements can be enriched through magmatic-hydrothermal processes that form mineral deposits in natural systems. The REE phosphates monazite and xenotime as well as their hydrated variants (i.e. rhabdophane and churchite) are common hosts to REE in these deposits, but are also found in many other geologic systems. The major problem this project addresses, is to determine the stability of these minerals in hydrothermal aqueous fluids and the stability of solid solutions with mixed compositions of the form Ce1-xREExPO4 (x= mole fraction from 0 to 1; REE = La, Pr, Nd, Sm, Eu, and Gd). The overarching goal of the project is to develop a thermodynamic model that enables simulating the stability of these minerals in hydrothermal systems. The hypothesis followed is that the REE compositions of these phosphates are useful indicators of fluid chemistry and temperature in natural ore-forming systems.   For this purpose, we conducted a series of mineral solubility experiments between 100 and 250 &deg;C with synthetic REE phosphates in acidic aqueous solution with a pH of 2. These experiments were used to determine the solubility products of all the monazite (La to Gd phosphates) and xenotime (Tb to Lu phosphates) endmembers. A series of solid solution compositions and pure endmembers were synthesized at room temperature using a solution calorimeter. The enthalpy of precipitation was measured and used to determine the ideal/non-ideal mixing properties of the solid solutions. The precipitated minerals were further analyzed using X-ray diffraction to determine their crystal structure and excess volume of mixing.   The major outcomes from the monazite and xenotime solubility experiments are: 1) the solubility of REE is controlled by metastable hydrated REE phosphates (i.e., rhabdophane) &lt;100 &deg;C and monazite/xenotime between 100 and 250 &deg;C; 2) the experimentally derived monazite/xenotime solubilities can display several orders of magnitude higher values in comparison to the predicted solubility using previously available literature data for minerals and aqueous species; 3) major discrepancies between previous predictions and our new solubility experiments can be explained by a need to revise the thermodynamic properties of REE aqueous species controlling the solubility at acidic pH (i.e., REE3+ and REEOH2+). The major outcomes from the solid solution precipitation experiments are: 1) rhabdophane solid solutions display a non-ideal behavior; 2) the excess volume of mixing is positive and becomes asymmetric with larger discrepancies in ionic radii between Ce and the substituting REE (i.e., Sm, Eu, and Gd); 3) the enthalpy of mixing is positive for La-Ce and Pr-Ce solid solutions, whereas the enthalpy of mixing becomes negative and display an asymmetric behavior for the smaller and heavier REE substituting for Ce (i.e., Nd, Sm, Eu and Gd).   This work enabled us to revise thermodynamic data for all the REE phosphates and generate an internally consistent thermodynamic database for the REE-P-O-H-Na-Cl system. The MINES thermodynamic database includes these and future updates from the experiments and can be downloaded open access (https://geoinfo.nmt.edu/mines-tdb/). Further, a free tutorials gitbook (https://apgysi.github.io/gems-mines-tutorial/) was developed for this project, which can be used for education and professional development to learn geochemical modeling of fluid-rock interaction using the GEMS code package and the MINES database. We organized a total of five geochemical modeling workshops worldwide and the project has supported the training of four undergraduate students and four graduate students. The experimental equipment provided through this project will be used to continue training students in our Ore Deposits and Critical Minerals laboratory at New Mexico Tech.        Last Modified: 12/07/2022       Submitted by: Alexander Gysi]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
