<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: How social norms impact COVID-19 transmission behaviors]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>66882.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>66882</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jeffrey Mantz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jmantz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927783</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Until a vaccine is developed, behavior change is the only way to stem the transmission of COVID-19 and safely resume economic activities. Social norms – aggregate behaviors, private preferences, judgments of behaviors, etc. – affect individuals' likelihood of adopting behavior change and must be understood in order to model effectively the impact of behavior-based interventions on disease transmission. This project investigates how community norms and normative pressures, in conjunction with population demographic composition, government policies, and information that people receive, determine behaviors targeted by COVID-19 health interventions. The results of the research will be disseminated quickly and broadly to facilitate efforts to stem disease transmission. The research trains a U.S. based graduate student and undergraduate students.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The study evaluates two causal relationships: 1) how government policies and individual traits (e.g., socio-economic position, personality) cause an individual to adopt a behavior (e.g., interpersonal distance, mask wearing); and 2) how aggregate patterns at the community level cause differences in transmission patterns. Surveys will be administered in five populations, one rural with limited exposure, and four urban with differences in the control measures that have been implemented. The researchers will collect longitudinal and time-series cross-sectional survey data to document 1) how people make interpersonal interaction and personal hygiene behavioral decisions; 2) how interpersonal interaction and personal hygiene norms change in each community during the pandemic; and 3) how the prevailing norms and shifts in those norms impact COVID-19 transmission patterns.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/05/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/05/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2032513</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Minhua</FirstName>
<LastName>Yan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Minhua Yan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[myan18@asu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000818724</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/05/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sarah</FirstName>
<LastName>Mathew</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sarah Mathew</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[sarah.mathew@asu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000498720</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/05/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Arizona State University</Name>
<CityName>TEMPE</CityName>
<ZipCode>852813670</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4809655479</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>660 S MILL AVENUE STE 204</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AZ04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NTLHJXM55KZ6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ARIZONA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Arizona State University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>852876011</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AZ04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>158Y</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1390</Code>
<Text>CULTURAL ANTHROPOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~66882</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="p1"><span class="s1">A longitudinal study was conducted to document changes in behaviors and attitudes that could impact COVID-19 prevention and transmission. The study focused on three preventive behaviors, mask wearing, interpersonal distancing, and greeting style, and was conducted in 3 US states, Oklahoma, Kansas and Idaho, and in a rural horticultural ethnic minority population in the Yunnan province of China, the Derung. Information was collected on subjects' perceived risk of contracting Covid-19, their individual characteristics, social pressures they perceive, and a variety of demographic factors, to examine factors associated with the adoption and retention of Covid-19 preventive behaviors.&nbsp;Over a 14 month period from August 2020 to Nov 2021, we conducted 10 rounds of data collection in the US, and 5 rounds in China, to track how people&rsquo;s attitudes and behaviors changed as the pandemic progressed, new variants emerged, vaccines became available, and as guidelines changed.&nbsp;The resulting dataset can be used to probe the dynamics of how norms shift. It can be analyzed to examine variability in pandemic responses between individuals, between populations within the US, and between the US and China. The the role of normative pressures in influencing behavior is important for understanding human behavioral and cultural change. By contributing data from the novel context of the pandemic, the dataset can inform theories of human behavior more broadly. The data can additionally inform public health responses to future pandemics. Differences between how individuals responded based on their demographic characteristics, political leaning, risk perception, and social environment can help in developing individually-tailored public health interventions in future pandemics, that can be more effective than interventions that assume homogeneous behavioral responses to pandemic prevention guidelines.</span></p> <p class="p1">&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/08/2022<br>      Modified by: Sarah&nbsp;Mathew</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[A longitudinal study was conducted to document changes in behaviors and attitudes that could impact COVID-19 prevention and transmission. The study focused on three preventive behaviors, mask wearing, interpersonal distancing, and greeting style, and was conducted in 3 US states, Oklahoma, Kansas and Idaho, and in a rural horticultural ethnic minority population in the Yunnan province of China, the Derung. Information was collected on subjects' perceived risk of contracting Covid-19, their individual characteristics, social pressures they perceive, and a variety of demographic factors, to examine factors associated with the adoption and retention of Covid-19 preventive behaviors. Over a 14 month period from August 2020 to Nov 2021, we conducted 10 rounds of data collection in the US, and 5 rounds in China, to track how people’s attitudes and behaviors changed as the pandemic progressed, new variants emerged, vaccines became available, and as guidelines changed. The resulting dataset can be used to probe the dynamics of how norms shift. It can be analyzed to examine variability in pandemic responses between individuals, between populations within the US, and between the US and China. The the role of normative pressures in influencing behavior is important for understanding human behavioral and cultural change. By contributing data from the novel context of the pandemic, the dataset can inform theories of human behavior more broadly. The data can additionally inform public health responses to future pandemics. Differences between how individuals responded based on their demographic characteristics, political leaning, risk perception, and social environment can help in developing individually-tailored public health interventions in future pandemics, that can be more effective than interventions that assume homogeneous behavioral responses to pandemic prevention guidelines.         Last Modified: 04/08/2022       Submitted by: Sarah Mathew]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
