<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research/GOALI: Fully Continuous Downstream Processing Enabled by Coupled Precipitation-Filtration Capture Operations]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>224996.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>70052</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Robert McCabe</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rmccabe@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924826</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The goal of this research project is to develop a highly efficient purification method for therapeutic biopharmaceuticals that has the potential to facilitate the transition of the biomanufacturing industry from batch to continuous processing. The use of continuous processing has the potential for improved product uniformity, lower cost production of drugs, and more flexible manufacturing operations. The research project involves designing, building, operating, evaluating, and optimizing an integrated demonstration process for biopharmaceutical purification.  The research is being performed in collaboration with an industrial partner, so the project is providing a unique training environment for graduate students and should facilitate successful career entry into the domestic biopharmaceutical industry. Additionally, knowledge gained from the research project can be rapidly transferred to industry. Outreach efforts are leveraging an existing program at the university to develop, deploy and assess bioseparations learning modules and lab experiments for use in secondary school chemistry curricula.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of this research project is the development of a continuous coupled precipitation-filtration biomanufacturing process for protein therapeutics that offers significant performance and cost advantages relative to traditional column chromatography-based capture. This purification process is based on staged pairings of static mixers and hollow fiber filters for efficient dewatering, washing, and re-dissolution of the target product. The use of synergistic and generalizable cross-linking and excluded volume precipitant pairs results in reversible, non-denatured precipitates at low precipitant concentrations, relieving the traditional limitations of precipitation. Data-driven models are being developed and validated for protein solubility, precipitation kinetics, and precipitate morphology to provide a quantitative description of the precipitation process. This research project is being performed in collaboration with an industrial partner who, in conjunction with the project researchers, are designing, building, operating, evaluating, and optimizing an integrated demonstration process for biopharmaceutical purification.  Consequently, knowledge gained from the research project can be rapidly transferred to industry.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/03/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/03/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2032261</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Todd</FirstName>
<LastName>Przybycien</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Todd M Przybycien</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[przybt3@rpi.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000179521</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/03/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute</Name>
<CityName>Troy</CityName>
<ZipCode>121803522</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5182766000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>110 8TH ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>U5WBFKEBLMX3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RENSSELAER POLYTECHNIC INSTITUTE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute]]></Name>
<CityName>Troy</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>121803522</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1417</Code>
<Text>Interfacial Engineering Progra</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1504</Code>
<Text>GOALI-Grnt Opp Acad Lia wIndus</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1504</Code>
<Text>GRANT OPP FOR ACAD LIA W/INDUS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01001718DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~70051</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This GOALI proposal was focused on the development of a highly efficient continuous coupled precipitation-filtration process for initial capture / purification of monoclonal antibodies and other high value biopharmaceuticals that can facilitate the transition of the biomanufacturing industry from batch to continuous processing. The use of continuous processing has been recognized as having the potential for improved product uniformity, lower cost of production for novel drugs, and more flexible biomanufacturing operations.&nbsp;</p> <p>The precipitation process developed in this project uses specially selected precipitants to achieve high yield of the monoclonal antibody product with minimal precipitation of the host cell proteins. The process exploits countercurrent staging of static mixers and hollow fiber membrane modules to achieve highly efficient washing of the precipitated antibody to enhance the removal of soluble host cell proteins. The hollow fiber membrane modules were operated below the critical flux to enable long-term operation without fouling. Several strategies were used to increase the conversion in the membrane modules, including the development of a novel feed-and-bleed strategy. This allowed us to achieve very effective concentration and washing of the precipitated protein using commercially available hollow fiber modules.</p> <p>The effectiveness of the continuous precipitation process was demonstrated through work directly performed with our industrial collaborator at Boehringer Ingelheim. This not only allowed us to work with industrial process streams, it also provided the two PhD students who worked on this project to obtain significant industrial / practical experience &ndash; both of these students have now graduated and are working at leading biopharmaceutical companies. This project also provided important learning experiences for several undergraduate research assistants who are now pursuing their PhD degrees at leading graduate programs in chemical engineering.</p> <p>The optimized precipitation-filtration process provided host cell protein removal and antibody yield that were comparable to what is currently achieved in commercial biomanufacturing using Protein A affinity chromatography but with much lower manufacturing costs. In addition, the precipitation process was operated continuously using a completely single-use flow path, which will greatly facilitate the implementation of this technology in flexible biomanufacturing facilities that can handle multiple product purification trains.&nbsp; The work conducted in this project has significantly advanced the development of an integrated continuous precipitation-filtration for the purification of important biopharmaceuticals with much lower cost of goods.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/16/2022<br>      Modified by: Todd&nbsp;M&nbsp;Przybycien</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This GOALI proposal was focused on the development of a highly efficient continuous coupled precipitation-filtration process for initial capture / purification of monoclonal antibodies and other high value biopharmaceuticals that can facilitate the transition of the biomanufacturing industry from batch to continuous processing. The use of continuous processing has been recognized as having the potential for improved product uniformity, lower cost of production for novel drugs, and more flexible biomanufacturing operations.   The precipitation process developed in this project uses specially selected precipitants to achieve high yield of the monoclonal antibody product with minimal precipitation of the host cell proteins. The process exploits countercurrent staging of static mixers and hollow fiber membrane modules to achieve highly efficient washing of the precipitated antibody to enhance the removal of soluble host cell proteins. The hollow fiber membrane modules were operated below the critical flux to enable long-term operation without fouling. Several strategies were used to increase the conversion in the membrane modules, including the development of a novel feed-and-bleed strategy. This allowed us to achieve very effective concentration and washing of the precipitated protein using commercially available hollow fiber modules.  The effectiveness of the continuous precipitation process was demonstrated through work directly performed with our industrial collaborator at Boehringer Ingelheim. This not only allowed us to work with industrial process streams, it also provided the two PhD students who worked on this project to obtain significant industrial / practical experience &ndash; both of these students have now graduated and are working at leading biopharmaceutical companies. This project also provided important learning experiences for several undergraduate research assistants who are now pursuing their PhD degrees at leading graduate programs in chemical engineering.  The optimized precipitation-filtration process provided host cell protein removal and antibody yield that were comparable to what is currently achieved in commercial biomanufacturing using Protein A affinity chromatography but with much lower manufacturing costs. In addition, the precipitation process was operated continuously using a completely single-use flow path, which will greatly facilitate the implementation of this technology in flexible biomanufacturing facilities that can handle multiple product purification trains.  The work conducted in this project has significantly advanced the development of an integrated continuous precipitation-filtration for the purification of important biopharmaceuticals with much lower cost of goods.       Last Modified: 02/16/2022       Submitted by: Todd M Przybycien]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
