<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID/Collaborative Research: Implications of Social Distancing Policies on Water Infrastructure Systems]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>20661.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>20661</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Siqian Shen</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>siqshen@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927048</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This Rapid Response Research (RAPID) grant will demonstrate how drinking water services provided by water utilities have been impacted by the social distancing policies undertaken by much of the nation during the 2020 coronavirus pandemic. By design, social distancing policies have caused immense change in human behavior, as families shelter in place and industrial and commercial sectors pause operations. One of the many consequences of these changes is a significant spatial, temporal, and volumetric change in water use within municipal water distribution systems. These changes have the potential to substantially impact water age and water quality both within the distribution system and within homes and other buildings.  In addition, utilities are facing unprecedented workforce, financial, and logistical challenges because of the pandemic as they respond to the unknown and emerging consequences of social distancing policies.  As such, this research has the potential to prevent infrastructure asset damage and negative public health impacts in communities with piped water that have undertaken social distancing.  Accordingly, and, as warranted by results, this project will create technical guidance for utilities to proactively mitigate these potential negative consequences.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In this research, existing water meter data and new interview data will be used to identify changes in water use patterns associated with various social distancing regimes. Next, the impacts of these changes on the pressure and water quality in distribution systems will be evaluated via hydraulic modeling and water quality sampling and analysis. The hydraulic modeling will identify and locate potential water distribution problems in a university campus, a residential neighborhood, and a primarily commercial, urban downtown. These data, coupled with  physical, chemical, and microbiological water quality analyses, will provide vital new empirical knowledge of water infrastructure performance under social distancing conditions. Interview data from utilities around the nation will further validate findings and enable the generalization of results and potential mitigation strategies. In partnership with collaborating water utilities, these combined datasets will be integrated to create a range of possible future Impact Scenarios of social distancing for water distribution systems. The empirically validated hydraulic models will be used to determine the implications of each Impact Scenario on distribution system performance, and to test mitigation strategies that utilities can implement during anticipated future waves of the pandemic and social distancing.  Broadly, this research builds engineering theory to link human patterns of water use to the performance and resilience of water distribution infrastructure.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/18/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/18/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2032429</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jessica</FirstName>
<LastName>Kaminsky</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jessica Kaminsky</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jkaminsk@uw.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000666861</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/18/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Washington</Name>
<CityName>SEATTLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>981951016</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2065434043</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4333 BROOKLYN AVE NE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>HD1WMN6945W6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF WASHINGTON</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Washington]]></Name>
<CityName>Seattle</CityName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>981952700</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4333 Brooklyn Ave NE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>158Y</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>029E</Code>
<Text>INFRASTRUCTURE SYSTEMS MGT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>036E</Code>
<Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9102</Code>
<Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>1N20</Code>
<Name>R&amp;RA CARES Act DEFC N</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>010N2021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[R&RA CARES Act DEFC N]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~20661</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The COVID-19 pandemic changed the way society operates. Social distancing policies (SDPs) enacted to prevent disease spread caused immense changes in human behavior, as families sheltered in place and industrial and commercial sectors paused operations. These SDPs caused spatial, temporal, and volumetric change in water use, impacting utility operations. Utilities had to ensure continuous services and the safety of their staff, while in many cases operating beyond their budgets and design conditions.</p> <p>In response to the pandemic, this project built new knowledge of the ways in which pandemics impact water infrastructure systems, leading to practical, technical, and policy recommendations useful during the COVID-19 pandemic and future pandemics. The research objectives of this project were to (1) empirically assess how water consumption and water quality changed due to social distancing policies using both newly collected and existing data, (2) document sociotechnical challenges faced by water utilities, as well as their responses to those challenges, (3) conduct hydraulic modeling to determine the type and scale of impacts on water distribution systems during SDPs, and (4) test Impact Scenarios. In summary, we ask how SDPs impacts our water systems, and how utilities are mitigating emerging challenges.</p> <p>Results show that water infrastructure systems were notably impacted by the COVID-19 pandemic. The research team discovered that water demand changed during the pandemic?buildings on a university campus experienced significant water demand changes, both in magnitude and patterns, which were tied to SDPs (Research Objective 1). Such demand changes can have operational, technical, and managerial impacts on water systems. For instance, the decreased water use might lead to water stagnation in premise plumbing, and as a result, water quality challenges.</p> <p>A qualitative analysis of semi-structured interviews with water utilities across the United States was conducted to understand how the COVID-19 impacted operations (Research Objective 2). These interviews revealed vulnerabilities in organizations due to lack of pandemic preparation in their emergency response plans. We identified components that should be included such as increased provisions for workforce management (e.g., ensuring operators are able to work) and supply chain (e.g., becoming a priority customer). Further, our findings revealed gaps in infrastructure policy, and we provided practical policy solutions. For instance, qualitative results showed that utilities were experiencing a decrease in financial capacity due to the pandemic, resulting in capital project delays. We recommend an increase in federal and state policy to provide funding for operational expenses and revenue deficits that occurred during the pandemic. Additionally, the team interviewed small utilities throughout the US to understand how the COVID-19 pandemic impacted water utilities of varying sizes, our study provides additional insights on the different experiences of water utilities with contrasting customer bases, financial capacity, and locations.</p> <p>Using the altered water demand data, the research team developed and ran a hydraulic model to understand changes to hydraulic performance (Research Objective 3-4). While developing the model, several barriers and opportunities in the widespread adoption of hydraulic modeling by utilities were revealed. This led to recommendations for utilities and policy makers to better support the creation and effective use of models (e.g., coordinated, centralized data collection efforts, policy initiatives to support model development).</p> <p>This project assessed how water infrastructure systems were impacted by the COVID-19 pandemic, and the associated SDPs. Using this knowledge, this work provided technical guidance to utilities to proactively mitigate negative consequences and made practical policy recommendations to increase pandemic preparedness.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/09/2023<br>      Modified by: Jessica&nbsp;Kaminsky</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The COVID-19 pandemic changed the way society operates. Social distancing policies (SDPs) enacted to prevent disease spread caused immense changes in human behavior, as families sheltered in place and industrial and commercial sectors paused operations. These SDPs caused spatial, temporal, and volumetric change in water use, impacting utility operations. Utilities had to ensure continuous services and the safety of their staff, while in many cases operating beyond their budgets and design conditions.  In response to the pandemic, this project built new knowledge of the ways in which pandemics impact water infrastructure systems, leading to practical, technical, and policy recommendations useful during the COVID-19 pandemic and future pandemics. The research objectives of this project were to (1) empirically assess how water consumption and water quality changed due to social distancing policies using both newly collected and existing data, (2) document sociotechnical challenges faced by water utilities, as well as their responses to those challenges, (3) conduct hydraulic modeling to determine the type and scale of impacts on water distribution systems during SDPs, and (4) test Impact Scenarios. In summary, we ask how SDPs impacts our water systems, and how utilities are mitigating emerging challenges.  Results show that water infrastructure systems were notably impacted by the COVID-19 pandemic. The research team discovered that water demand changed during the pandemic?buildings on a university campus experienced significant water demand changes, both in magnitude and patterns, which were tied to SDPs (Research Objective 1). Such demand changes can have operational, technical, and managerial impacts on water systems. For instance, the decreased water use might lead to water stagnation in premise plumbing, and as a result, water quality challenges.  A qualitative analysis of semi-structured interviews with water utilities across the United States was conducted to understand how the COVID-19 impacted operations (Research Objective 2). These interviews revealed vulnerabilities in organizations due to lack of pandemic preparation in their emergency response plans. We identified components that should be included such as increased provisions for workforce management (e.g., ensuring operators are able to work) and supply chain (e.g., becoming a priority customer). Further, our findings revealed gaps in infrastructure policy, and we provided practical policy solutions. For instance, qualitative results showed that utilities were experiencing a decrease in financial capacity due to the pandemic, resulting in capital project delays. We recommend an increase in federal and state policy to provide funding for operational expenses and revenue deficits that occurred during the pandemic. Additionally, the team interviewed small utilities throughout the US to understand how the COVID-19 pandemic impacted water utilities of varying sizes, our study provides additional insights on the different experiences of water utilities with contrasting customer bases, financial capacity, and locations.  Using the altered water demand data, the research team developed and ran a hydraulic model to understand changes to hydraulic performance (Research Objective 3-4). While developing the model, several barriers and opportunities in the widespread adoption of hydraulic modeling by utilities were revealed. This led to recommendations for utilities and policy makers to better support the creation and effective use of models (e.g., coordinated, centralized data collection efforts, policy initiatives to support model development).  This project assessed how water infrastructure systems were impacted by the COVID-19 pandemic, and the associated SDPs. Using this knowledge, this work provided technical guidance to utilities to proactively mitigate negative consequences and made practical policy recommendations to increase pandemic preparedness.       Last Modified: 05/09/2023       Submitted by: Jessica Kaminsky]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
