<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Rapid disinfection using compact plasma reactors for COVID-19]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>255945.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>255945</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anna Brady</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>abrady@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927077</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) project is a convenient, effective, green and economical disinfection solution for everyday items contaminated with pathogens, specifically SARS-CoV-2. This project will develop a portable, compact, and low-power disinfection product using ozone. The proposed solution will address items otherwise difficult to treat with conventional methods such as wipes, UV exposure, and autoclave. Furthermore, it is free of long-term toxic residuals, with excess ozone converted back to oxygen. This will support the mitigation of social distancing policies and applications include personal protection equipment such as disinfecting masks, gloves, suits, equipment, etc., as well as household items.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This SBIR Phase I project proposes to develop a convenient, effective, green and economical disinfection unit, based on Dielectric Barrier Discharge (DBD) generated ozone, to remove pathogen contamination. The solution uses embedded compact plasma reactor systems to generate ozone in-situ from atmospheric air and simultaneously distributing it within the box. This eliminates the need for external gas tanks or mixing agents. The proposed project will advance the Active Plasma Module (APM) - a compact, energy-efficient DBD generation device. Research objectives include testing DBD plasma against SARS CoV-2, determining optimum operating conditions (exposure times, ozone concentrations, surface to volume ratios, input power), and testing disinfection on commonly used materials like fabric, latex, etc. This entails designing DBD reactors for APMs and for their integration in an enclosed system, as well as testing of SARS-CoV-2 inactivation under varying operating conditions. This system is expected to rapidly inactivate SARS-CoV-2 while overcoming limitations of conventional disinfection technologies like high temperatures, material incompatibility and ineffective disinfection of obstructed surfaces.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/10/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/14/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2032575</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Bhaswati</FirstName>
<LastName>Choudhury</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Bhaswati Choudhury</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[bhaswati@surfplasma.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000826951</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>SurfPlasma, Inc.</Name>
<CityName>GAINESVILLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>326067156</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8105160991</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>8722 NW 9TH PL</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>Y96ESVKCPTE9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SURFPLASMA INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[SurfPlasma, Inc.]]></Name>
<CityName>GAINESVILLE</CityName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>326016591</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[101 SE 2 Pl, Suite 201 – Room]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8030</Code>
<Text>Chemical Technology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~255945</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p style="text-align: left;">This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) project resulted in the development of a convenient, effective, green, and economical disinfection and sterilization device - <strong>SterBox</strong>, for everyday items as well as medical tools contaminated with killer pathogens like SARS CoV-2. The SterBox is a non-thermal, efficient, and safe practical solution which addresses disinfection of items otherwise difficult to treat with conventional methods such as wipes, UV exposure, and autoclave. Furthermore, it is free of long-term toxic residuals. Applications include personal protection equipment such as disinfecting masks, gloves, suits, equipment, etc., as well as household items. SterBox uses SurfPlasma core patented technology -&nbsp;<strong>APM (Active Plasma Module)</strong> which is a compact (~inch cube), portable, green, energy-efficient, and modularly scalable disinfection device based on DBD (dielectric barrier discharge) generated ozone for killing pathogens like bacteria, virus and fungi. The APM uses embedded compact plasma reactor systems to generate ozone in-situ from atmospheric air and simultaneously distributing it within the box. This eliminates the need for external gas tanks or mixing agents.</p> <p style="text-align: left;">With successful completion of this project, SurfPlasma has accomplished the following: (a) demonstrated <strong>killing of SARS CoV&#8209;2 and its surrogate (HCoV-OC43)</strong> using APM, (b) demonstrated <strong>sterilization of virus contaminated porous (KN95 mask material) and non-porous (Aluminum and Polycarbonate)</strong> materials using APM, (c) performed scaling studies (e) obtained ozone requirements for sterilization of virus, (f) obtained APM power requirements, (g) demonstrated <strong>material compatibility</strong> of APM with 3 material types: <strong>metal, plastic and fabric</strong>, and (h) identified required product specifications and corresponding <strong>design modifications</strong> for customers requiring sterilization solutions. These accomplishments set the baseline to advance the SterBox toward commercial deployment in healthcare facilities, common households, medical device companies and food &amp;beverage companies across the country with a team of committed investor, manufacturer, distributor, and industry level field testing partners.</p> <p style="text-align: left;">This NSF SBIR project has addressed the <strong>broader societal need</strong> of a non-thermal, economical, and efficient solution for sterilizing pathogen contaminated surfaces. The major impact of the established feasibility of the technology - APM, against SARS CoV-2, allows for development of the SterBox - a non-thermal, safe, economical, and convenient sterilization device for different material types contaminated with virus, bacteria, and fungi. <strong>Applications</strong> include sterilizing PPE, personal effects, surgical tools, medical tools, food, beverages, etc. from harmful pathogens. The SterBox can help improve safety by preventing spreading of harmful pathogens in households, healthcare facilities, medical device companies and food &amp;beverage companies. The major impact will be in crowded facilities and community settings where rapid disinfection of objects is required. This project also helped <strong>develop human resources</strong> in science, engineering, and technology by providing opportunities to graduates and undergraduates to actively participate in a research project. Specifically, SurfPlasma created jobs by hiring four engineers of diverse disciplines to work on various aspects of this project. Further, the project has encouraged women participation in STEM.&nbsp;</p> <p style="text-align: left;">The <strong>technical impact</strong> of this NSF SBIR project lies in advancing scientific knowledge in the following fields: plasma engineering [plasma engineering literature for decontamination], mechanical and aerospace engineering [design and manufacturing knowledge for plasma reactors used in mechanical and aerospace engineering], electrical engineering [knowledge in creating efficient electrical power supplies for plasma reactors] and biotechnology [innovative decontamination solutions]. In summary, successful conclusion of SurfPlasma's Phase I NSF project established the efficacy and feasibility of an affordable, low energy budget, compact, ready-to-use, superior safety, portable DBD reactor-based high throughput sterilization system for rapid inactivation of deadly pathogens like SARS CoV-2 and its surrogate HCoV-OC43 on common materials like metal, plastic, and fabric. The innovation has impacted multiple disciplines and has the potential to be help both medical industry and everyday lives.</p> <p style="text-align: left;">&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/10/2021<br>      Modified by: Bhaswati&nbsp;Choudhury</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2032575/2032575_10706330_1631216895024_APM.png--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2032575/2032575_10706330_1631216895024_APM.png--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Active Plasma Module"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2032575/2032575_10706330_1631216895024_APM.png--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Active Plasma Module"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">SurfPlasma patented technology - Active Plasma Module (APM)</div> <div class="imageCredit">Subrata Roy</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Bhaswati&nbsp;Choudhury</div> <div class="imageTitle">Active Plasma Module</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) project resulted in the development of a convenient, effective, green, and economical disinfection and sterilization device - SterBox, for everyday items as well as medical tools contaminated with killer pathogens like SARS CoV-2. The SterBox is a non-thermal, efficient, and safe practical solution which addresses disinfection of items otherwise difficult to treat with conventional methods such as wipes, UV exposure, and autoclave. Furthermore, it is free of long-term toxic residuals. Applications include personal protection equipment such as disinfecting masks, gloves, suits, equipment, etc., as well as household items. SterBox uses SurfPlasma core patented technology - APM (Active Plasma Module) which is a compact (~inch cube), portable, green, energy-efficient, and modularly scalable disinfection device based on DBD (dielectric barrier discharge) generated ozone for killing pathogens like bacteria, virus and fungi. The APM uses embedded compact plasma reactor systems to generate ozone in-situ from atmospheric air and simultaneously distributing it within the box. This eliminates the need for external gas tanks or mixing agents. With successful completion of this project, SurfPlasma has accomplished the following: (a) demonstrated killing of SARS CoV&#8209;2 and its surrogate (HCoV-OC43) using APM, (b) demonstrated sterilization of virus contaminated porous (KN95 mask material) and non-porous (Aluminum and Polycarbonate) materials using APM, (c) performed scaling studies (e) obtained ozone requirements for sterilization of virus, (f) obtained APM power requirements, (g) demonstrated material compatibility of APM with 3 material types: metal, plastic and fabric, and (h) identified required product specifications and corresponding design modifications for customers requiring sterilization solutions. These accomplishments set the baseline to advance the SterBox toward commercial deployment in healthcare facilities, common households, medical device companies and food &amp;beverage companies across the country with a team of committed investor, manufacturer, distributor, and industry level field testing partners. This NSF SBIR project has addressed the broader societal need of a non-thermal, economical, and efficient solution for sterilizing pathogen contaminated surfaces. The major impact of the established feasibility of the technology - APM, against SARS CoV-2, allows for development of the SterBox - a non-thermal, safe, economical, and convenient sterilization device for different material types contaminated with virus, bacteria, and fungi. Applications include sterilizing PPE, personal effects, surgical tools, medical tools, food, beverages, etc. from harmful pathogens. The SterBox can help improve safety by preventing spreading of harmful pathogens in households, healthcare facilities, medical device companies and food &amp;beverage companies. The major impact will be in crowded facilities and community settings where rapid disinfection of objects is required. This project also helped develop human resources in science, engineering, and technology by providing opportunities to graduates and undergraduates to actively participate in a research project. Specifically, SurfPlasma created jobs by hiring four engineers of diverse disciplines to work on various aspects of this project. Further, the project has encouraged women participation in STEM.  The technical impact of this NSF SBIR project lies in advancing scientific knowledge in the following fields: plasma engineering [plasma engineering literature for decontamination], mechanical and aerospace engineering [design and manufacturing knowledge for plasma reactors used in mechanical and aerospace engineering], electrical engineering [knowledge in creating efficient electrical power supplies for plasma reactors] and biotechnology [innovative decontamination solutions]. In summary, successful conclusion of SurfPlasma's Phase I NSF project established the efficacy and feasibility of an affordable, low energy budget, compact, ready-to-use, superior safety, portable DBD reactor-based high throughput sterilization system for rapid inactivation of deadly pathogens like SARS CoV-2 and its surrogate HCoV-OC43 on common materials like metal, plastic, and fabric. The innovation has impacted multiple disciplines and has the potential to be help both medical industry and everyday lives.         Last Modified: 09/10/2021       Submitted by: Bhaswati Choudhury]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
