<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[EAGER: Community Building and Workflows for Data Sharing with Publicly Accessible and Consumable Metadata]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>298998.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>298998</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OAC</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure (OAC)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Martin Halbert</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mhalbert@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928516</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[In this exploratory activity, the Center for Open Science (COS) will create and pilot a result-reporting workflow for with Open Science Framework (OSF) study registration that includes reporting study outcomes, archiving study data and materials with permanent identifiers, and availability of metadata in a public API such as could be used by a federal agency for consumption (e.g., NSF Public Access Repository (PAR)).    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The team will conduct community building around data sharing in the product development process and in the review and evolution of data sharing standards established with the Transparency and Openness Promotion (TOP) Guidelines and badges for acknowledging open practices.  The project anticipates maximizing the discoverability of metadata of NSF-funded research, and increasing scientific rigor by helping link the products of research (data and software) to their associated publications through a user experience that supports transformative behavior change towards open-science aligned research.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/22/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/22/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2032650</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Brian</FirstName>
<LastName>Nosek</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Brian Nosek</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[nosek@cos.io]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000693651</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/22/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Center for Open Science</Name>
<CityName>CHARLOTTESVILLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>229035083</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4343521024</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>210 RIDGE MCINTIRE RD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[STE 500]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>VA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>N1SSK43FCY13</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CENTER FOR OPEN SCIENCE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Center for Open Science]]></Name>
<CityName>Charlottesville</CityName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>229035083</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[210 Ridge McIntire]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>VA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7414</Code>
<Text>NSF Public Access Initiative</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~298998</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-2c515bc0-7fff-6c84-c606-003bce94a9d7"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr">Data, software, and other research outputs are essential to the scientific community but are too often lost or disconnected from the origin of the work. The outcomes of this project were to align community-driven standards and expectations for research outputs with open source software for managing the research lifecycle, the OSF (<a href="https://osf.io/">https://osf.io/</a>). A deeper understanding of community and stakeholder perceptions, attitudes, and needs was incorporated into the workflow design through user research studies and outcomes available at <a href="https://osf.io/9b27q/"><span>osf.io/9b27q</span></a>. The open source software code is available at <a href="https://github.com/CenterForOpenScience/osf.io/tree/feature/registration_resources"><span>https://github.com/CenterForOpenScience/osf.io/tree/feature/registration_resources</span></a> and <a href="https://github.com/centerforopenscience/ember-osf-web/tree/feature/output-reporting"><span>https://github.com/centerforopenscience/ember-osf-web/tree/feature/output-reporting</span></a>.</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Along with existing badges for Open Data and Open Materials, preregistrations can now indicate if there is analytic code associated with the study. This indicator relies on the new Open Analytic Code Badge criteria (&#8203;&#8203;</span><a href="https://osf.io/fntgb"><span>https://osf.io/fntgb</span></a><span>) that will soon appear with badges for data, materials, and preregistrations in other scholarly outputs, namely journal articles. The OSF registry also enables authors to indicate if papers or other supplementary materials are available for the project in the same new, clean interface. This workflow is accompanied by clear documentation and instructions for researchers (</span><a href="https://help.osf.io/article/452-open-practice-badges"><span>https://help.osf.io/article/452-open-practice-badges</span></a><span>).&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span>An example of a project with all badges is included to demonstrate this new workflow (</span><a href="https://osf.io/scayl/resources"><span>https://osf.io/scayl/resources</span></a><span>). The metadata provided in this new workflow and available in the OSF public API will enable discovery of research data and other resources across platforms. This discoverability and increased transparency of research outputs will provide more avenues to incentivizing best practices in open and rigorous research, such as allowing journals or funders to quickly verify that all research outputs are available from relevant work. </span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/08/2022<br>      Modified by: Brian&nbsp;Nosek</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   Data, software, and other research outputs are essential to the scientific community but are too often lost or disconnected from the origin of the work. The outcomes of this project were to align community-driven standards and expectations for research outputs with open source software for managing the research lifecycle, the OSF (https://osf.io/). A deeper understanding of community and stakeholder perceptions, attitudes, and needs was incorporated into the workflow design through user research studies and outcomes available at osf.io/9b27q. The open source software code is available at https://github.com/CenterForOpenScience/osf.io/tree/feature/registration_resources and https://github.com/centerforopenscience/ember-osf-web/tree/feature/output-reporting. Along with existing badges for Open Data and Open Materials, preregistrations can now indicate if there is analytic code associated with the study. This indicator relies on the new Open Analytic Code Badge criteria (&#8203;&#8203;https://osf.io/fntgb) that will soon appear with badges for data, materials, and preregistrations in other scholarly outputs, namely journal articles. The OSF registry also enables authors to indicate if papers or other supplementary materials are available for the project in the same new, clean interface. This workflow is accompanied by clear documentation and instructions for researchers (https://help.osf.io/article/452-open-practice-badges).   An example of a project with all badges is included to demonstrate this new workflow (https://osf.io/scayl/resources). The metadata provided in this new workflow and available in the OSF public API will enable discovery of research data and other resources across platforms. This discoverability and increased transparency of research outputs will provide more avenues to incentivizing best practices in open and rigorous research, such as allowing journals or funders to quickly verify that all research outputs are available from relevant work.              Last Modified: 09/08/2022       Submitted by: Brian Nosek]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
