<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Handheld Detection of COVID-19 With Simple Biosensor Devices for Environmental Monitoring]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>256000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>276000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rajesh Mehta</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rmehta@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922174</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is to develop an inexpensive, easy-to-use, and portable test for the detection of SARS-CoV-2 in the environment. A portable test kit for the environmental detection of SARS-CoV-2 would enable widespread and proactive identification where the virus is present, allowing for informed decisions regarding social distancing and related COVID-19 pandemic mitigation measures. The proposed device will be battery-powered, support easy operation, and will report results directly.The technology can be extended to other pathogens in the future. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This SBIR Phase I project will develop a rapid, on-site SARS-CoV-2 environmental detection technology that can be performed by non-technical users with a portable handheld device. The technology integrates a simple-to-use and one-pot assay for the simultaneous isothermal amplification and detection of ribonucleic acids.  This project will establish an assay that can specifically detect SARS-CoV-2 genomic RNA, be freeze-dried to eliminate cold chain logistics, and can be run in an hour; and refine a battery-powered handheld device to provide temperature control, report on assay test results, and allow tests to be performed in the field. The proposal will address technical hurdles related to assay handling, sensitivity, specificity, shelf-stability, run time and device design through a technical plan that involves assay component optimizations and device design and testing cycles.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/10/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/10/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2032825</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Khalid</FirstName>
<LastName>Alam</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>K</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Khalid K Alam</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[khalid@stemloop.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000824431</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>STEMLOOP, INC.</Name>
<CityName>EVANSTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>602013193</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3144971984</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1801 MAPLE AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>DB19KLCTUZ47</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>STEMLOOP, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[STEMLOOP, INC.]]></Name>
<CityName>Lemont</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>604394801</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[9700 S Cass Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8091</Code>
<Text>SBIR Outreach &amp; Tech. Assist</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1238</Code>
<Text>TECH FOR SUSTAINABLE ENVIRONMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5383</Code>
<Text>HUMAN &amp;/OR BIOLOGICAL</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8040</Code>
<Text>Energy and Environment</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~256000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~20000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The goal of this project was to develop a portable and rapid testing kit for the on-site detection of pathogens, such as SARS-CoV-2, in the environment. It sought to address the lack of tools for pathogen detection in the environment that are easy-to-use, inexpensive, rapid, and do not require laboratory infrastructure.</p> <p>The project had two overarching objectives. The first objective was to develop a test that was sensitive and specific, while being fast, shelf-stable, and easy-to-use. The second objective was to integrate the enviornmental pathogen test into a device for portable on-site detection.</p> <p>Project objectives were accomplished. We developed a highly sensitive (low femtomolar detection), specific (no cross-reactivity with closely related samples), and quick (detection within minutes) test for environmental pathogens. Additonally,&nbsp;we demonstrated that our detection approach could be implemented in a simple and inexpensive lateral flow device format. Finally,&nbsp;we showed the generalizability of the platform for the detection of different pathogens.</p> <p>Broadly, this work is important by demonstrating that recent advances in the field of synthetic biology can be applied to environmental testing of pathogens. It offers a new paradigm that supplements traditional medical diagnostics and supports public health efforts such as global pathogen surveillance in the enviornment.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/10/2022<br>      Modified by: Khalid&nbsp;K&nbsp;Alam</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The goal of this project was to develop a portable and rapid testing kit for the on-site detection of pathogens, such as SARS-CoV-2, in the environment. It sought to address the lack of tools for pathogen detection in the environment that are easy-to-use, inexpensive, rapid, and do not require laboratory infrastructure.  The project had two overarching objectives. The first objective was to develop a test that was sensitive and specific, while being fast, shelf-stable, and easy-to-use. The second objective was to integrate the enviornmental pathogen test into a device for portable on-site detection.  Project objectives were accomplished. We developed a highly sensitive (low femtomolar detection), specific (no cross-reactivity with closely related samples), and quick (detection within minutes) test for environmental pathogens. Additonally, we demonstrated that our detection approach could be implemented in a simple and inexpensive lateral flow device format. Finally, we showed the generalizability of the platform for the detection of different pathogens.  Broadly, this work is important by demonstrating that recent advances in the field of synthetic biology can be applied to environmental testing of pathogens. It offers a new paradigm that supplements traditional medical diagnostics and supports public health efforts such as global pathogen surveillance in the enviornment.          Last Modified: 03/10/2022       Submitted by: Khalid K Alam]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
