<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Preliminary Design Planning for the Leadership-Class Computing Facility]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>3500000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>3500000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Cooperative Agreement</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OAC</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure (OAC)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Edward Walker</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>edwalker@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924863</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Over the past decades, the role of computational and data science in advancing discovery has increased tremendously.  NSF has played a central role in this transformation of scientific research as a funder of pioneering research activities and as a leader in enabling the use of High-Performance Computing (HPC), with Computation-based methods now becoming central to research in diverse areas of Science and Engineering (S&amp;E).  The NSF leadership-class computing facility (LCCF) program is intended to provide unique services and resources to enable discoveries in the largest and most computationally intensive S&amp;E research frontiers that could not advance otherwise.  This award supports the design and planning activities associated with the Preliminary Design (PD) of LCCF after successful completion of Conceptual Design (CD). &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The LCCF project proposes an advanced computing facility to enable discoveries in all fields of S&amp;E requiring leadership computing capabilities, delivering a facility that will not only deal with the very largest challenges in S&amp;E simulation, but also in Artificial Intelligence (AI), as well as the analysis of data from experimental and observational facilities.  To deliver this goal, the LCCF project will provide a large-scale computing platform, called Horizon, with a ten-fold increase in the time-to-solution capability of the NSF's current largest system (Frontera), as well as a complete environment for managing data throughout the research lifecycle. The LCCF will also provide a software environment, supporting services, and training to ensure that researchers can effectively use the facility for maximum impact to enhance the scientific discovery process.  Extensive plans for Education and Public Outreach are also planned which includes developing existing high impact formal learning programs for students, teachers, and parents, as well as construction for an informal learning environment that will be part of LCCF called the Computarium.  The PD process will continue many of the activities from CD, but with a focus on improving the project plans and estimates sufficiently to make important decisions moving forward.  Important PD goals are to make the final site selection for the facility, refine the science use cases into specific application targets with defined Figure of Merit performance increases, and choose the general direction of the Horizon system architecture.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/17/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/17/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>CoopAgrmnt</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2033468</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Omar</FirstName>
<LastName>Ghattas</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>N</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Omar N Ghattas</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[omar@ices.utexas.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000249850</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/17/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
<LastName>Stanzione</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME>Jr</PI_SUFX_NAME>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Daniel Stanzione</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[dan@tacc.utexas.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000193108</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/17/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>West</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John E West</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[john@tacc.utexas.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000760987</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/17/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Texas at Austin</Name>
<CityName>AUSTIN</CityName>
<ZipCode>787121139</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5124716424</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>110 INNER CAMPUS DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>25</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX25</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>V6AFQPN18437</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT AUSTIN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>X5NKD2NFF2V3</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Texas at Austin]]></Name>
<CityName>Austin</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>787595316</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3925 West Braker Lane]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>37</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX37</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7781</Code>
<Text>Leadership-Class Computing</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~3500000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>NSF has played a central role in the transformation of scientific research and as a leader in enabling the use of High-Performance Computing (HPC) to advance discovery for almost four decades. The leadership-class computing program is intended to provision advanced computational capabilities to enable transformative research for all of Science and Engineering (S&amp;E) that would not otherwise be possible. NSF's current leadership-class computing investment is the support of the Frontera project at the Texas Advanced Computing Center (TACC) at The University of Texas at Austin. Frontera is the Phase 1 system of a two-phase approach to eventual deployment of a much more capable Leadership-Class Computing Facility (LCCF) in approximately 2024. This award will supported the conceptual design of a Phase 2 system and facility. This award delivered a conceptual design that was successfully reviewed and recommended to advance to the preliminary design phase.</p> <p>The project's preliminary design approach extended best practices in the design/operate/evaluate cycle that TACC has used to successfully deploy some of the largest computing systems in the world for open scientific research. This process has four keystones: science user requirements, future technology assessment, alternative design evaluation, as well as risk management for cost, scope and schedule. Testbeds are an important part of the design process and offered system designers quantitative insights into the effectiveness of these technologies. Testbed partners included major technology vendors, emerging technology vendors, and early exascale computing technology adopters. In addition, the design process was guided by science inputs and technology drivers identified by science and technology engagement teams. These teams were composed of distinguished scientists representing a broad range of expertise and experience to guide the Phase 2 system design. The team members also served as community leaders to bring together colleagues in workshops, meetings, and other engagement venues to inform the process further. The project resulted in a successful preliminary design and a recommendation to proceed to final system design.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/02/2023<br>      Modified by: John&nbsp;E&nbsp;West</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ NSF has played a central role in the transformation of scientific research and as a leader in enabling the use of High-Performance Computing (HPC) to advance discovery for almost four decades. The leadership-class computing program is intended to provision advanced computational capabilities to enable transformative research for all of Science and Engineering (S&amp;E) that would not otherwise be possible. NSF's current leadership-class computing investment is the support of the Frontera project at the Texas Advanced Computing Center (TACC) at The University of Texas at Austin. Frontera is the Phase 1 system of a two-phase approach to eventual deployment of a much more capable Leadership-Class Computing Facility (LCCF) in approximately 2024. This award will supported the conceptual design of a Phase 2 system and facility. This award delivered a conceptual design that was successfully reviewed and recommended to advance to the preliminary design phase.  The project's preliminary design approach extended best practices in the design/operate/evaluate cycle that TACC has used to successfully deploy some of the largest computing systems in the world for open scientific research. This process has four keystones: science user requirements, future technology assessment, alternative design evaluation, as well as risk management for cost, scope and schedule. Testbeds are an important part of the design process and offered system designers quantitative insights into the effectiveness of these technologies. Testbed partners included major technology vendors, emerging technology vendors, and early exascale computing technology adopters. In addition, the design process was guided by science inputs and technology drivers identified by science and technology engagement teams. These teams were composed of distinguished scientists representing a broad range of expertise and experience to guide the Phase 2 system design. The team members also served as community leaders to bring together colleagues in workshops, meetings, and other engagement venues to inform the process further. The project resulted in a successful preliminary design and a recommendation to proceed to final system design.       Last Modified: 05/02/2023       Submitted by: John E West]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
