<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:Automatic Touch Screen Disinfection (COVID-19)]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>255730.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>255730</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anna Brady</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>abrady@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927077</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I is to equip any personal and public touch screen displays with self-disinfection capabilities. Touch-screen technology is an integral part of everyday life in applications such as personal smartphones, industrial and medical equipment, and public touch screen stations. These screens are convenient but become a hotspot for harmful germs and bacteria. The use of touch screens could mitigate the social distancing policies of the COVID-19 pandemic. This project will develop an ultrasonic disinfection method to mitigate the spread of pathogens across such surfaces.  A wide array of applications could follow including:  banks (ATMs), retail (groceries POS stations, vending machines, restaurant order stations), transportation (self-check kiosks, border control stations, plane’s infotainment systems, automotive dashboards), medical equipment, government buildings, museums and tourist attractions, art and entertainment (interactive kiosks), and consumer electronics (smartphones, smartwatches, tablets, laptops, touch screen equipped appliances). Primary benefits of the methods would include speed and ability to disinfect with high frequency, elimination of need for manual labor to disinfect by this method, and expected safety to the user.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;This SBIR Phase I project will demonstrate the efficiency of ultrasonic disinfection process using discrete piezoelectric transducers. Because these elements are not transparent, they could be integrated with touch screen only by attachment at the periphery of the display glass. This configuration will allow a basic feasibility study for a proposed disinfection method. The project will use a novel thin film piezoelectric technology where transducers are fabricated across an entire display glass surface using thin film deposition and patterning method.  This configuration is beneficial since it would not require additional device area or thickness beyond the current display glass product dimensions. Moreover, this design is not limited to small display form-factors and could be scaled to a larger display size. A thin film piezoelectric system is energy efficient in operation. The disinfection process will be characterized at wide ranges of ultrasonic frequencies and powers, and illustrated for coronavirus (SARS-CoV-2) and bacterium (E. coli).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/22/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/22/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2033314</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Boris</FirstName>
<LastName>Kobrin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Boris Kobrin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[boris@innovasonic.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000765419</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/22/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Innovasonic</Name>
<CityName>DUBLIN</CityName>
<ZipCode>945684580</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9255486064</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4292 KEEGAN ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>15</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA15</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>PHNNFYZ9YGS1</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>INNOVASONIC, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Innovasonic]]></Name>
<CityName>Dublin</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>945684580</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4292 Keegan Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>15</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA15</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8034</Code>
<Text>Hardware Components</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8609</Code>
<Text>Other Energy Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~255730</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Touch screens improve our convenience but become a hotspot for harmful germs and bacteria and an effective infection transmitter, if not disinfected very frequently (continuously or, at least after each customer).</p> <p>Today touch screens are mostly cleaned/disinfected manually. Manual cleaning requires labor, wipes and non-environmentally friendly chemicals (i.e., alcohol). Most importantly, it is impossible to do it after each customer when device is used by many people only minutes apart. Thus, this method, being widely used, still <strong>fails to protect public</strong>.<strong> &ldquo;</strong>Anti-bacterial coatings&rdquo; and &ldquo;anti-microbial glass&rdquo; are not <strong>relevant</strong> in preventing contamination in high-traffic areas since require 3-4 hours to drop pathogens to acceptable levels. UV-based disinfection <strong>devices are very dangerous to public. Thus, the need for a safe, effective, and relevant disinfection method for public touch screens has not been met and a better solution is urgently required.</strong></p> <p>Thermal treatment is known to be an effective disinfection method (medical tools. food). It is typically done through some media (liquid, air): immersing products in hot liquid or placing in an oven. Disinfecting surfaces of electronics devices <strong>in-operation</strong> using embedded heaters is a novel concept, which will open significant opportunities in enhancing public biosafety.</p> <p>Phase-I has demonstrated feasibility of the 2 methods of touch screen thermal disinfection: In-situ Hot Surface Disinfection (HSD) and Thermal Pulse Disinfection (TPD). Per IEC&rsquo;s 60950-1 and Telcordia GR-63 standards glass parts in consumer electronics devices can be touched at 70 C for up to 10s. In HSD touch screen is kept at 70&deg;C continuously during operation: to save the energy heating starts only when touch sensor detects the first touch event, and terminated, when no touch events detected within 1-2 min. In TPD touch screen operation interrupts after each customer for a short maintenance-disinfection cycle (&lt;1min). Glass heats up to &gt;120&deg;C and then quickly cools down to safe-to-use temperatures (&lt;70&deg;C).&nbsp; We have confirmed LOG2-LOG7 reduction of E-Coli bacteria and Phi6 corona-virus (COVID-19) surrogate at different peak temperatures (90-149&deg;C) within ~1 min and LOG3-LOG4 reduction for E-Coli for 5 min continuous heating at 70-77&deg;C.</p> <p>To further optimize the process, we suggested implementing local disinfection by heating only a small portion of an entire glass screen, just where potentially contaminated fingerprints are left on the surface. The information about fingerprints position is obtained from an existing touch sensor.</p> <p>This technology could be integrated in new touch screen products by using touch sensor&rsquo;s transparent conductor layer (resistive or capacitive) as a heater. Alternatively, existing touch screen/kiosk can be retrofitted by laminating transparent conductive film on top of existing display glass. Power could be provided through flex cable or inductively.</p> <p>We have checked basic compatibility of this technology to touch screen display operation (prolong heating, touch sensitivity) and suggested improvements for seamless integration (to be developed during Phase-II MVP project).</p> <p>COVID-19 pandemic has changed the public attitude towards touch screens, at least in public spaces. Just 12% of individuals surveyed in April 2020 believed that touchscreens in public places were safe. The technology suggested in this project could <strong>change this perception and provide public a piece of mind</strong> when operating public touch screens. Our disinfection method can automatically give customers a confirmation/proof of action through tactile feeling of a worm surface. The proposed technology can significantly <strong>advance the health and welfare of the American public</strong>: &nbsp;<strong><em>remove one of the most notorious routs for pathogen spread </em></strong>through hospitals and medical facilities, ATMs, self-order kiosks, gas pumps; help to <strong><em>stop the spread of contamination into US soil through transportation vehicles and facilities (airports, planes, boats, passport control and fingerprinting stations, etc.), which is a matter of national defense and security.</em></strong></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/09/2021<br>      Modified by: Boris&nbsp;Kobrin</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Touch screens improve our convenience but become a hotspot for harmful germs and bacteria and an effective infection transmitter, if not disinfected very frequently (continuously or, at least after each customer).  Today touch screens are mostly cleaned/disinfected manually. Manual cleaning requires labor, wipes and non-environmentally friendly chemicals (i.e., alcohol). Most importantly, it is impossible to do it after each customer when device is used by many people only minutes apart. Thus, this method, being widely used, still fails to protect public. "Anti-bacterial coatings" and "anti-microbial glass" are not relevant in preventing contamination in high-traffic areas since require 3-4 hours to drop pathogens to acceptable levels. UV-based disinfection devices are very dangerous to public. Thus, the need for a safe, effective, and relevant disinfection method for public touch screens has not been met and a better solution is urgently required.  Thermal treatment is known to be an effective disinfection method (medical tools. food). It is typically done through some media (liquid, air): immersing products in hot liquid or placing in an oven. Disinfecting surfaces of electronics devices in-operation using embedded heaters is a novel concept, which will open significant opportunities in enhancing public biosafety.  Phase-I has demonstrated feasibility of the 2 methods of touch screen thermal disinfection: In-situ Hot Surface Disinfection (HSD) and Thermal Pulse Disinfection (TPD). Per IEC’s 60950-1 and Telcordia GR-63 standards glass parts in consumer electronics devices can be touched at 70 C for up to 10s. In HSD touch screen is kept at 70&deg;C continuously during operation: to save the energy heating starts only when touch sensor detects the first touch event, and terminated, when no touch events detected within 1-2 min. In TPD touch screen operation interrupts after each customer for a short maintenance-disinfection cycle (&lt;1min). Glass heats up to &gt;120&deg;C and then quickly cools down to safe-to-use temperatures (&lt;70&deg;C).  We have confirmed LOG2-LOG7 reduction of E-Coli bacteria and Phi6 corona-virus (COVID-19) surrogate at different peak temperatures (90-149&deg;C) within ~1 min and LOG3-LOG4 reduction for E-Coli for 5 min continuous heating at 70-77&deg;C.  To further optimize the process, we suggested implementing local disinfection by heating only a small portion of an entire glass screen, just where potentially contaminated fingerprints are left on the surface. The information about fingerprints position is obtained from an existing touch sensor.  This technology could be integrated in new touch screen products by using touch sensor’s transparent conductor layer (resistive or capacitive) as a heater. Alternatively, existing touch screen/kiosk can be retrofitted by laminating transparent conductive film on top of existing display glass. Power could be provided through flex cable or inductively.  We have checked basic compatibility of this technology to touch screen display operation (prolong heating, touch sensitivity) and suggested improvements for seamless integration (to be developed during Phase-II MVP project).  COVID-19 pandemic has changed the public attitude towards touch screens, at least in public spaces. Just 12% of individuals surveyed in April 2020 believed that touchscreens in public places were safe. The technology suggested in this project could change this perception and provide public a piece of mind when operating public touch screens. Our disinfection method can automatically give customers a confirmation/proof of action through tactile feeling of a worm surface. The proposed technology can significantly advance the health and welfare of the American public:  remove one of the most notorious routs for pathogen spread through hospitals and medical facilities, ATMs, self-order kiosks, gas pumps; help to stop the spread of contamination into US soil through transportation vehicles and facilities (airports, planes, boats, passport control and fingerprinting stations, etc.), which is a matter of national defense and security.       Last Modified: 09/09/2021       Submitted by: Boris Kobrin]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
