<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[I-Corps: Stretchable Lightguides for Multimodal Sensing]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ruth Shuman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rshuman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922160</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this I-Corps project is the development of multifunctional, stretchable sensors. These sensors may be used to measure deformations such as pressing, stretching and bending. When integrated into garments or clothes, they may have an impact in a variety of different industries. For example, in the fitness wearables market, they may be used to measure muscle fatigue and to monitor muscle growth over time, in the healthcare market they may be used as bed sheets to prevent pressure ulcers.  In the virtual reality/augmented reality the sensors may be used to improve training by measuring contact forces as well as offering motion tracking, and in the automotive industry as part of car seats to monitor in-vehicle passenger behavior as well as to indicate child presence in the car.  Finally, in robotics  industry the stretchable sensors may give robots the sense of touch.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project is based on the development of multifunctional stretchable sensors termed Stretchable Lightguides for Multimodal Sensing (SLIMS). SLIMS technology improves the functionalities of a single stretchable sensor by using an optical approach. By using intensity and chromaticity changes of wavelengths throughout a broad spectrum input, these sensors can differentiate the mode of a mechanical deformation such as stretching, pressing and bending, as well as detect the magnitude and location of such deformations. Since these sensors are soft and rely on photonics, rather than electronics as the sensing modality, they are washable and insensitive to electromagnetic interference unlike their competitors. SLIMS’ ability to decouple complex deformations has been demonstrated through integration on a wireless 3D printed glove, where each finger has one SLIMS. The glow (signal) was able to reconstruct in real time the three joint angles on the finger as well as simultaneously detect the location and force of external pressure on the finger.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/13/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/14/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2033773</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
<LastName>Shepherd</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Robert Shepherd</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[rfs247@cornell.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000644350</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/13/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Cornell University</Name>
<CityName>ITHACA</CityName>
<ZipCode>148502820</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6072555014</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>341 PINE TREE RD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>23</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY23</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>G56PUALJ3KT5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CORNELL UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>EQA8NBEN9WD5</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Cornell University]]></Name>
<CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>148502820</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[124 Hoy Rd]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>23</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY23</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project outcome for the&nbsp;<span>I-Corps: Stretchable Lightguides for Multimodal Sensing, Award ID 2033773 was a "go." This means that the Entrepreneurial Lead's hypothesis that technology they were evaluating is relevant commercially was not invalidated. In particular, after over 100 industry stakeholder interviews, the application of their technology has a potential for commercial success in the area of kinematic analysis in sports science.&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span>The technology that was under investigation for potential commercialization are stretchable fiberoptics that use intensity and wavelength modulation to estimate shape change and magnitude of force interactions. The stiffness of these sensing fibers is very low, and so they can be worn without discomfort. By placing these fibers on gloves, it was previously shown by the entrepreneurial lead that the glove/computer interface can reconstruct the joint angles of the hand as well as the interaction forces in which the glove interacts. </span></p> <p><span>Our hypothesis was that kinematics and force reaction monitoring in a wearable format will provide valuable supplementary information to vision based motion capture systems. As we found that the motion capture systems do not record force, are constrained to a laboratory like environment, and some motions are occluded and reduce accuracy of motion capture predictions, the investigated wearable technology does provide value. The magnitude of this value seems to be a commercially viable opportunity, but only actually testing it in the market will reveal the truth.</span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/11/2022<br>      Modified by: Robert&nbsp;Shepherd</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project outcome for the I-Corps: Stretchable Lightguides for Multimodal Sensing, Award ID 2033773 was a "go." This means that the Entrepreneurial Lead's hypothesis that technology they were evaluating is relevant commercially was not invalidated. In particular, after over 100 industry stakeholder interviews, the application of their technology has a potential for commercial success in the area of kinematic analysis in sports science.   The technology that was under investigation for potential commercialization are stretchable fiberoptics that use intensity and wavelength modulation to estimate shape change and magnitude of force interactions. The stiffness of these sensing fibers is very low, and so they can be worn without discomfort. By placing these fibers on gloves, it was previously shown by the entrepreneurial lead that the glove/computer interface can reconstruct the joint angles of the hand as well as the interaction forces in which the glove interacts.   Our hypothesis was that kinematics and force reaction monitoring in a wearable format will provide valuable supplementary information to vision based motion capture systems. As we found that the motion capture systems do not record force, are constrained to a laboratory like environment, and some motions are occluded and reduce accuracy of motion capture predictions, the investigated wearable technology does provide value. The magnitude of this value seems to be a commercially viable opportunity, but only actually testing it in the market will reveal the truth.       Last Modified: 06/11/2022       Submitted by: Robert Shepherd]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
