<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Desktop Plug-and-Play Vaporized Hydrogen Peroxide Sterilizers for Personal Protective Equipment (COVID-19)]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>255998.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>255998</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anna Brady</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>abrady@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927077</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) project is to enable sterilization of personal protective equipment (PPE).  Global response measures to the COVID-19 pandemic have highlighted severe shortages of N95 masks and PPE, which could be alleviated by sterilizing the equipment. This has been demonstrated effectively in large trailers and room-size facilities, but these large units are cost more than $1 M each, require substantive facility modifications, and have strict operational requirements. An alternative approach is to provide desktop sterilizers resembling the ubiquitous steam sterilizers typically used in hospitals and clinical settings.  This project will develop a desktop plug-and-play vaporized hydrogen peroxide sterilizer unit to decontaminate PPE within 30 minutes at low cost.  These could be deployed throughout a medical facility without requiring substantive room remodeling or restricted access rooms. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This SBIR Phase I project proposes to develop and demonstrate a desktop plug-and-play vaporized hydrogen peroxide sterilizer. Vaporized hydrogen peroxide (VHP) is a proven sterilant that exhibits broad-spectrum efficacy against viruses, bacteria, yeasts and bacterial spores. Conventional VHP sterilizers are large units that use concentrated H2O2 cartridges to produce the requisite 750 ppm VHP concentration. Because these units use concentrated H2O2 canisters, the resulting systems have significant process controls and operations to maintain safe operation, design consequences that make it difficult to scale the technology to smaller economical desktop units. Toward producing safer desktop sterilization units, a new chemical reactor will be developed in this program that can produce hydrogen peroxide directly in the vapor state without using hazardous compounds or dangerous reaction conditions. Optimization of the catalysts, reaction area, and operating conditions will be conducted to produce vaporized hydrogen peroxide at concentrations upwards of 750 ppm. Additional components will be developed to safely operate the sterilizer including H2O2 concentration and relative humidity sensors, and a catalytic H2O2 decomposition reactor to breakdown residual H2O2 to water and oxygen.  These components will be integrated into a desktop sterilizer unit, along with new control algorithms for safe operation.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/04/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/04/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2033865</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Kimble</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael C Kimble</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mkimble@skyhavensystems.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000779496</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/04/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>SKYHAVEN SYSTEMS, LLC</Name>
<CityName>STEAMBOAT SPRINGS</CityName>
<ZipCode>80487</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9708460547</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>25557 BELLA VISTA CIR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>YW31GV8ZEM14</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SKYHAVEN SYSTEMS, LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Skyhaven Systems, LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>Steamboat Springs</CityName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>804770252</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[25557 Bella Vista Circle]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8030</Code>
<Text>Chemical Technology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~255998</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Purpose of the Research</span></p> <p>Skyhaven Systems has previously developed an electrochemical reactor that reacts water and air to produce vaporized hydrogen peroxide (VHP) on-site and on-demand. VHP is an effective sterilant mostly used in large, room-size facilities for medical equipment sterilization including the sterilization of COVID-19 infected N95 masks and personal protective equipment. The purpose of this present research project is to apply VHP sterilization within a smaller, desktop sterilizer unit similar to the ubiquitous steam sterilizers used throughout medical and dental offices. Via using Skyhaven&rsquo;s electrochemical VHP generator instead of using the industrial standard of concentrated liquid hydrogen peroxide sources, a simpler and safer desktop sterilizer is possible. This offers the value of the large room size sterilizer effectiveness, yet packaged into a smaller unit suitable for desktop operation without requiring facility modifications. Operational logistics is extremely simplified with these sterilization units requiring only water, air, and a source of DC power, thus enabling rapid set up and usage throughout medical facilities.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Brief Description of the Conducted Research</span></p> <p>A Phase I project initially examined the commercial marketplace defining the needs for a desktop VHP sterilizer. This led to defining a process flow schematic to meet the sterilization needs of medical/dental offices. From this, the various components for the VHP sterilizer were either procured or produced in-house. This included the VHP generator and VHP decomposer units that were produced in-house since these items are not commercially available. Other system components were procured including water and air pumps, solenoid valves, and control electronics all retrofitted into a steam sterilizer unit converting it to a VHP sterilizer.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Research Findings</span></p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; During this project, a desktop plug-and-play prototype sterilizer was developed where concentrated VHP could be generated within minutes. This VHP stream is subsequently directed to a sterilizer chamber for a rapid, room-temperature and dry sterilization process. Variations of the VHP generator were examined and developed showing effective kill action on biological indicators showing the efficacy of the VHP process. A VHP decomposition unit was also developed and shown &nbsp;to break down VHP to oxygen and water once the sterilization process was complete. A control system was developed for the VHP sterilizer prototype that controls the initial generation of VHP, the dwelling of VHP in the sterilizer chamber, and the decomposition of VHP post sterilization. This control system and prototype unit will enable the firm to continue developing and assessing key components of the sterilizer, namely, the VHP generator and VHP decomposer, along with operational modalities to meet desktop VHP sterilizer needs for the medical and dental industries. Extensions of the VHP generator may also be used for pharmaceutical production operations to replace the use of concentrated VHP sources enabling safer operation with vaporized hydrogen peroxide.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/19/2022<br>      Modified by: Michael&nbsp;C&nbsp;Kimble</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Purpose of the Research  Skyhaven Systems has previously developed an electrochemical reactor that reacts water and air to produce vaporized hydrogen peroxide (VHP) on-site and on-demand. VHP is an effective sterilant mostly used in large, room-size facilities for medical equipment sterilization including the sterilization of COVID-19 infected N95 masks and personal protective equipment. The purpose of this present research project is to apply VHP sterilization within a smaller, desktop sterilizer unit similar to the ubiquitous steam sterilizers used throughout medical and dental offices. Via using Skyhaven’s electrochemical VHP generator instead of using the industrial standard of concentrated liquid hydrogen peroxide sources, a simpler and safer desktop sterilizer is possible. This offers the value of the large room size sterilizer effectiveness, yet packaged into a smaller unit suitable for desktop operation without requiring facility modifications. Operational logistics is extremely simplified with these sterilization units requiring only water, air, and a source of DC power, thus enabling rapid set up and usage throughout medical facilities.     Brief Description of the Conducted Research  A Phase I project initially examined the commercial marketplace defining the needs for a desktop VHP sterilizer. This led to defining a process flow schematic to meet the sterilization needs of medical/dental offices. From this, the various components for the VHP sterilizer were either procured or produced in-house. This included the VHP generator and VHP decomposer units that were produced in-house since these items are not commercially available. Other system components were procured including water and air pumps, solenoid valves, and control electronics all retrofitted into a steam sterilizer unit converting it to a VHP sterilizer.     Research Findings        During this project, a desktop plug-and-play prototype sterilizer was developed where concentrated VHP could be generated within minutes. This VHP stream is subsequently directed to a sterilizer chamber for a rapid, room-temperature and dry sterilization process. Variations of the VHP generator were examined and developed showing effective kill action on biological indicators showing the efficacy of the VHP process. A VHP decomposition unit was also developed and shown  to break down VHP to oxygen and water once the sterilization process was complete. A control system was developed for the VHP sterilizer prototype that controls the initial generation of VHP, the dwelling of VHP in the sterilizer chamber, and the decomposition of VHP post sterilization. This control system and prototype unit will enable the firm to continue developing and assessing key components of the sterilizer, namely, the VHP generator and VHP decomposer, along with operational modalities to meet desktop VHP sterilizer needs for the medical and dental industries. Extensions of the VHP generator may also be used for pharmaceutical production operations to replace the use of concentrated VHP sources enabling safer operation with vaporized hydrogen peroxide.          Last Modified: 09/19/2022       Submitted by: Michael C Kimble]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
