<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Exploring the Effects of Parent-Child Interactions on Children’s Learning about Handwashing Behavior and Disease Prevention]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>103596.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>103596</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DRL</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Catherine L. Eberbach</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ceberbac@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924960</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This RAPID project will study connections between children's hygiene habits and learning about science, such as the science of disease transmission.  It builds upon findings from the investigator’s prior research of parent-child interactions observed in children’s museums and will extend this research to home settings. This research will focus on understanding how goal-setting, whether it is parent-directed, child-directed, or jointly-directed, affects children’s engagement with a handwashing activity and their subsequent learning about handwashing behavior and preventing the spread of disease. More specifically, the intent is to examine how goal-setting during an interactive demonstration between parents and children relates to children’s recollection of the activity and their handwashing behavior afterwards. This project is funded by the Advancing Informal STEM Learning (AISL) program which seeks to advance new approaches to, and evidence-based understanding of, the design and development of STEM learning in informal environments. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;During a pandemic, it is vital that children establish good hygiene habits and understand the importance of handwashing for the prevention of disease transmission. What is most important is that young children wash their hands frequently and follow good hygiene habits, such as using soap, when doing so. This study examines the role parents might play in engaging children to wash their hands. The project team has developed a short 10 minute intervention that parents and children can participate in while using everyday household items. Utilizing remote technology, parents and children will be guided through this intervention while video recording their behavior. Families will be presented with a structured activity for parents and children to participate in together. This activity will be focused on how handwashing, and particularly the use of soap during handwashing, helps prevent the spread of germs. Parent-child interactions will be coded using schemes for goal setting that the investigator developed in prior work. Directly after their participation and one week later, children will be asked to reflect on the activity to understand what they remember about it, and to understand whether they have encoded the importance of handwashing for preventing the transmission of disease. Parents will also be asked to track their children’s handwashing to see whether aspects of these reflections, as well as individual differences in how parents and children interact during the activity, promote better engagement with handwashing. The data generated will allow researchers to develop best practices for interventions centered on children’s handwashing and the prevention of disease transmission. Knowing such practices is critical for reintegrating children into social settings such as schools and children's museums.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/12/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/12/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2033368</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Sobel</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David M Sobel</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[David_Sobel_1@brown.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000569913</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/12/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Brown University</Name>
<CityName>PROVIDENCE</CityName>
<ZipCode>029129127</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4018632777</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1 PROSPECT ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>RI01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>E3FDXZ6TBHW3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>BROWN UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>E3FDXZ6TBHW3</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Brown University]]></Name>
<CityName>Providence</CityName>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>029129067</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[190 Thayer St. Room 103, Box 182]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>RI01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7259</Code>
<Text>AISL</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0420</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~103596</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Overview</p> <p>The goal of the project was to examine the relation between parent-child interaction during an at-home activity demonstrating the importance of using soap during handwashing and children's reflections on that activity, their handwashing behaviors, and understanding of disease transmission over the course of the following week after their participation.&nbsp;Children between the ages of 4-7 and a parent either participated in or watch a video of a demonstration designed to articulate the importance of soap during handwashing. Children reflected on the experience immediately afterwards and approximately a week later. During that time, parents were asked to report children&rsquo;s handwashing behaviors. Independent of age and children&rsquo;s knowledge of disease transmission, how parents and children interacted during the activity related to children&rsquo;s unprompted use of soap during handwashing. Parents who set more goals and directed their children&rsquo;s behavior during the activity reported that their children washed their hands with soap unprompted less frequently, compared with both children whose parents were more collaborative and with those who merely watched the activity. Not only are these results relevant to preventing the spread of disease in children, but they are a first step in describing how parent-child interaction can affect children&rsquo;s autonomy and internalization of STEM content to their everyday lives.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Intellectual Merits</p> <p>Given concerns about reduced numbers of students in STEM fields (President&rsquo;s Council of Advisors on Science &amp; Technology, 2012), there is an urgent need to improve STEM learning and engagement among young children. In the research literature, there is a fundamental tension the role of direct instruction and guided exploration for children&rsquo;s STEM learning and engagement, and that tension has been translated to informal learning environments, such as museums and the home. Of import is the role parents have in fostering children&rsquo;s STEM learning and engagement. The present study showed that parent-child interaction, particularly overly-directed instruction and parental goal setting, had negative relations to children&rsquo;s engagement with the content of the activity (in this case, soap-use during handwashing, which is of importance to the prevention of disease transmission). This project uncovered patterns and connections in how diverse families can engage in STEM-related activities in the home and how that interaction may facilitate children&rsquo;s autonomy and internalization of the importance of the STEM content. More generally, this project suggested numerous ways we can consider how parent-child interaction affects STEM learning and engagement. This can be applied in both formal educational settings, as well as informal, everyday activities in the home.</p> <p>Broader Impacts</p> <p>The study presented here not only contributes to our basic knowledge of how parent-child interaction in the home relates to children&rsquo;s behavior and understanding of STEM content, but also translates research performed in informal learning environments (in particular children&rsquo;s museums) to the home environment. Thus, the project advances both the basic research goals of improving our understanding of how children learn STEM content, but also the educational goal of developing new strategies for introducing STEM content within meaningful educational activities that can easily be done in the home. Moreover, the specific content of this project involves an at-home intervention that can facilitate children&rsquo;s understanding of the importance of handwashing for disease prevention. This allows us to describe practices for how parents can facilitate children&rsquo;s internalization of the importance of using soap during handwashing and more generally, preventing the spread of disease. This will not only increase children&rsquo;s awareness of the importance of hygiene, but can better prepare children to interact with others while cognizant of the need to reduce disease transmission.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/12/2022<br>      Modified by: David&nbsp;M&nbsp;Sobel</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Overview  The goal of the project was to examine the relation between parent-child interaction during an at-home activity demonstrating the importance of using soap during handwashing and children's reflections on that activity, their handwashing behaviors, and understanding of disease transmission over the course of the following week after their participation. Children between the ages of 4-7 and a parent either participated in or watch a video of a demonstration designed to articulate the importance of soap during handwashing. Children reflected on the experience immediately afterwards and approximately a week later. During that time, parents were asked to report children’s handwashing behaviors. Independent of age and children’s knowledge of disease transmission, how parents and children interacted during the activity related to children’s unprompted use of soap during handwashing. Parents who set more goals and directed their children’s behavior during the activity reported that their children washed their hands with soap unprompted less frequently, compared with both children whose parents were more collaborative and with those who merely watched the activity. Not only are these results relevant to preventing the spread of disease in children, but they are a first step in describing how parent-child interaction can affect children’s autonomy and internalization of STEM content to their everyday lives.     Intellectual Merits  Given concerns about reduced numbers of students in STEM fields (President’s Council of Advisors on Science &amp; Technology, 2012), there is an urgent need to improve STEM learning and engagement among young children. In the research literature, there is a fundamental tension the role of direct instruction and guided exploration for children’s STEM learning and engagement, and that tension has been translated to informal learning environments, such as museums and the home. Of import is the role parents have in fostering children’s STEM learning and engagement. The present study showed that parent-child interaction, particularly overly-directed instruction and parental goal setting, had negative relations to children’s engagement with the content of the activity (in this case, soap-use during handwashing, which is of importance to the prevention of disease transmission). This project uncovered patterns and connections in how diverse families can engage in STEM-related activities in the home and how that interaction may facilitate children’s autonomy and internalization of the importance of the STEM content. More generally, this project suggested numerous ways we can consider how parent-child interaction affects STEM learning and engagement. This can be applied in both formal educational settings, as well as informal, everyday activities in the home.  Broader Impacts  The study presented here not only contributes to our basic knowledge of how parent-child interaction in the home relates to children’s behavior and understanding of STEM content, but also translates research performed in informal learning environments (in particular children’s museums) to the home environment. Thus, the project advances both the basic research goals of improving our understanding of how children learn STEM content, but also the educational goal of developing new strategies for introducing STEM content within meaningful educational activities that can easily be done in the home. Moreover, the specific content of this project involves an at-home intervention that can facilitate children’s understanding of the importance of handwashing for disease prevention. This allows us to describe practices for how parents can facilitate children’s internalization of the importance of using soap during handwashing and more generally, preventing the spread of disease. This will not only increase children’s awareness of the importance of hygiene, but can better prepare children to interact with others while cognizant of the need to reduce disease transmission.          Last Modified: 01/12/2022       Submitted by: David M Sobel]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
