<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Building Research Cyberinfrastructure in EPSCoR Jurisdictions: Assessment, Planning and Partnerships]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>9635.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>9635</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01060100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OIA</Abbreviation>
<LongName>OIA-Office of Integrative Activities</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Andrea Johnson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>andjohns@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925164</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The University of Hawaii, in collaboration with Montana State University and the University of Nevada Reno, will host a workshop to gather the necessary baseline data to characterize cyberinfrastructure (CI) capabilities across EPSCoR jurisdictions and institutions. As these resources are required to drive data and compute-intensive science forward, this workshop will address the issues of historical underinvestment in CI resources and services in EPSCoR jurisdictions and the uneven distribution and availability of these resources across the nation. Activities and deliverables of this workshop aim to enhance CI access and capability for research and education across EPSCoR jurisdictions, including under-resourced institutions. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goals of this workshop are to increase knowledge of, and aid access to, CI capabilities across EPSCoR jurisdictions and beyond. Data generated by participants will allow insights into existing gaps, priorities, and challenges at local and national levels. First, participants will use the Research Computing and Data Capabilities Model (RCDCM) assessment tool paired with trainings to generate baseline CI data and ideas on how to increase CI access, planning, and partnerships. The workshop will include facilitated discussion, a case-study panel on regional collaboration, and group working sessions. The resulting open access report, publication, and related outreach activities will present aggregated and analyzed baseline data, interpreted findings, and planning and partnership initiatives to advance knowledge and understanding of participating EPSCoR institutions’ CI capabilities and intentions. The workshop will be co-located with the EPSCoR Project Directors and Project Administrators meeting in Portland, Maine (or online, per circumstances).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/06/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/06/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.083</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2033514</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Venice</FirstName>
<LastName>Bayrd</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Venice Bayrd</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[venice.bayrd@montana.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000818768</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/06/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Montana State University</Name>
<CityName>BOZEMAN</CityName>
<ZipCode>59717</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4069942381</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>216 MONTANA HALL</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Montana</StateName>
<StateCode>MT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MT01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>EJ3UF7TK8RT5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MONTANA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>HD5YDTPGA865</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Montana State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Bozeman</CityName>
<StateCode>MT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>597173320</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[P.O. Box 173320 / Renne Library]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Montana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MT01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9168</Code>
<Text>EPSCoR Outreach and Workshops</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9168</Code>
<Text>EPSCOR OUTREACH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~9635</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-5a23b054-7fff-34fb-4644-3dcbff12c11f"> </span></p> <p><span id="docs-internal-guid-c1c04965-7fff-b9bd-f82a-2c4f92b12a3d"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Improving research and related education capabilities across under-represented and under-resourced parts of the United States is central to the National Science Foundation's Established Program to Stimulate Competitive Research (NSF EPSCoR) mission. Modern research and education rely on cyberinfrastructure (CI): networks, data, computers, software, and the people who support them. However, the rapid rate of technological change poses significant challenges to researchers and traditional institutional Information Technology (IT) organizations. Any lack of access to research-focused professional technology support results in researchers making difficult time management decisions between working on their science or solving the associated technology integration problems. In contrast, access to robust technology support can translate to improvements in areas including knowledge development and transfer, research impact, cross-disciplinary workforce development, and cybersecurity, thereby accelerating shifts in the quality of education and research competitiveness.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The EPSCoR CI Working Group formed with funding support from NSF EPSCoR via a collaborative workshop award for the dual purpose of responding to the lack of data characterizing technology capabilities across EPSCoR-associated states, and to Loretta Moore's "Call to Action" to increase CI access in these under-resourced geographies in her 2019 presentation to the National Research Platform Conference. The EPSCoR CI Working Group facilitated community generation of unprecedented baseline technology capabilities data characterizing CI distribution and availability across EPSCoR-associated institutions. Those data then framed community workshop discussions focused on prioritizing identified gaps and generating solutions. Assessment data and workshop discussions suggest that the gaps in data-centric areas alone will leave EPSCoR institutions struggling to be competitive in the national research/education arena if there are not purposeful companion efforts to improve already lagging CI. The report resulting from this workshop series makes 11 recommendations to NSF and to EPSCoR institutions, all intended as actionable steps to increase the capability and presence of CI in EPSCoR, and thereby increase EPSCoR institutions' competitiveness. Our report can be accessed by the public at: </span><a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.8097562"><span>https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.8097562</span></a><span>.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Both the Intellectual Merit and Broader Impacts of this project center on the project's overarching goal to leverage CI to support all science and engineering disciplines. If the recommendations of our workshop outcomes are followed by NSF and the EPSCoR regions, there will be significant impact in the areas of research, teaching, and education related to science and technology in geographically diverse regions. The scalability of research, teaching, and education is reliant on use of advanced, well-supported technology (networks, security, identity management, virtual systems, instructional facilitation, IT mission focus). The gaps in institutional and national cyberinfrastructure that have been identified by the higher education community in our workshop report directly affect the scalability and impact of research-related education. Our recommendations originate from current knowledge across the community of research computing, data, networking, and team science best-practices. These intended outcomes focus on the Broader Impacts of technology workforce development across the entire country and match those impacts with current capability gaps in higher-education cyberinfrastructure.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>&nbsp;</span></p> <div><span><br /></span></div> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr">&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/14/2023<br>      Modified by: Venice&nbsp;Bayrd</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2033514/2033514_10732279_1689361410520_title-screenshot--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2033514/2033514_10732279_1689361410520_title-screenshot--rgov-800width.jpg" title="&quot;Minding the Gap&quot; Report Title Page"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2033514/2033514_10732279_1689361410520_title-screenshot--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="&quot;Minding the Gap&quot; Report Title Page"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The cover image of the "Minding the Gap: Leveraging Cyberinfrastructure to Transform EPSCoR Jurisdictions" report.</div> <div class="imageCredit">EPSCoR CI Working Group</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Venice&nbsp;Bayrd</div> <div class="imageTitle">"Minding the Gap" Report Title Page</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2033514/2033514_10732279_1689361222910_table-1-screenshot--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2033514/2033514_10732279_1689361222910_table-1-screenshot--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Workshop recommendations to NSF and EPSCoR jurisdictions and institutions"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2033514/2033514_10732279_1689361222910_table-1-screenshot--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Workshop recommendations to NSF and EPSCoR jurisdictions and institutions"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">11 recommendations to the NSF and EPSCoR jurisdictions and institutions resulting from the workshop discussions.</div> <div class="imageCredit">EPSCoR CI Working Group</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Venice&nbsp;Bayrd</div> <div class="imageTitle">Workshop recommendations to NSF and EPSCoR jurisdictions and institutions</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[      Improving research and related education capabilities across under-represented and under-resourced parts of the United States is central to the National Science Foundation's Established Program to Stimulate Competitive Research (NSF EPSCoR) mission. Modern research and education rely on cyberinfrastructure (CI): networks, data, computers, software, and the people who support them. However, the rapid rate of technological change poses significant challenges to researchers and traditional institutional Information Technology (IT) organizations. Any lack of access to research-focused professional technology support results in researchers making difficult time management decisions between working on their science or solving the associated technology integration problems. In contrast, access to robust technology support can translate to improvements in areas including knowledge development and transfer, research impact, cross-disciplinary workforce development, and cybersecurity, thereby accelerating shifts in the quality of education and research competitiveness. The EPSCoR CI Working Group formed with funding support from NSF EPSCoR via a collaborative workshop award for the dual purpose of responding to the lack of data characterizing technology capabilities across EPSCoR-associated states, and to Loretta Moore's "Call to Action" to increase CI access in these under-resourced geographies in her 2019 presentation to the National Research Platform Conference. The EPSCoR CI Working Group facilitated community generation of unprecedented baseline technology capabilities data characterizing CI distribution and availability across EPSCoR-associated institutions. Those data then framed community workshop discussions focused on prioritizing identified gaps and generating solutions. Assessment data and workshop discussions suggest that the gaps in data-centric areas alone will leave EPSCoR institutions struggling to be competitive in the national research/education arena if there are not purposeful companion efforts to improve already lagging CI. The report resulting from this workshop series makes 11 recommendations to NSF and to EPSCoR institutions, all intended as actionable steps to increase the capability and presence of CI in EPSCoR, and thereby increase EPSCoR institutions' competitiveness. Our report can be accessed by the public at: https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.8097562. Both the Intellectual Merit and Broader Impacts of this project center on the project's overarching goal to leverage CI to support all science and engineering disciplines. If the recommendations of our workshop outcomes are followed by NSF and the EPSCoR regions, there will be significant impact in the areas of research, teaching, and education related to science and technology in geographically diverse regions. The scalability of research, teaching, and education is reliant on use of advanced, well-supported technology (networks, security, identity management, virtual systems, instructional facilitation, IT mission focus). The gaps in institutional and national cyberinfrastructure that have been identified by the higher education community in our workshop report directly affect the scalability and impact of research-related education. Our recommendations originate from current knowledge across the community of research computing, data, networking, and team science best-practices. These intended outcomes focus on the Broader Impacts of technology workforce development across the entire country and match those impacts with current capability gaps in higher-education cyberinfrastructure.                Last Modified: 07/14/2023       Submitted by: Venice Bayrd]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
