<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Income and Poverty in the COVID-19 Pandemic]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>199723.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>199723</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Nancy Lutz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>nlutz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927280</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In nine weeks at the start of the COVID-19 pandemic 39 million people filed for unemployment insurance, while GDP for the first quarter of 2020 was down 4.8%. The federal government responded with unprecedented stimulus legislation that committed more than two trillion dollars to countering the effects of the pandemic. Effectively targeting and calibrating the government's fiscal response requires tracking changes in income and poverty by demographic group and geography in a timely way, which there is extremely limited ability to do. Official estimates of income and poverty for 2020 will not be available until September of 2021. This project responds directly to this need to develop new processes to help address the economic impact of the COVID-19 pandemic by providing timely and accurate information on the impact of the current pandemic on income and poverty to inform the targeting of resources to those most affected. The project aims to construct new measures of the income distribution and poverty with a lag of only a few weeks using high frequency data for a large, representative sample of U.S. families. This project will have immediate impact in advancing basic knowledge in the fields of economics and related social sciences and providing tools for policy makers by constructing new, near real-time estimates of income and poverty. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will validate new, timely measure of income by comparing historical estimates that rely on these data to estimates from data on income and consumption that have been used much more broadly. Importantly, these validation exercises will utilize new data that links survey data to tax and program data at the individual level. The validation will help researchers understand the advantages and limitations of using more timely income data to study changes in economic well-being. This project will also address key questions regarding the impacts of large economic shocks and survey income measurement, both critical elements of much economic research.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/22/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/22/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2033893</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Bruce</FirstName>
<LastName>Meyer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Bruce D Meyer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[bdmeyer@uchicago.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000382419</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/22/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Sullivan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>James Sullivan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[sullivan.197@nd.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000299965</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/22/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Chicago</Name>
<CityName>CHICAGO</CityName>
<ZipCode>606375418</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7737028669</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5801 S ELLIS AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>ZUE9HKT2CLC9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CHICAGO</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>ZUE9HKT2CLC9</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Chicago]]></Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>606372612</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[6054 South Drexel Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1320</Code>
<Text>Economics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1320</Code>
<Text>ECONOMICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~199723</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="Default">Our project has provided critical, real-time information on the state of the economy that was useful during the pandemic and continues to be used by policymakers and researchers.&nbsp; We constructed new measures of the income distribution and income-based poverty with a lag of only a few weeks using high frequency data for a large, representative sample of U.S. families and individuals, and we validated these new measures by comparing them to other measures based on well-established data sources. The main results of our research are contained in our published article in the journal <em>Brookings Papers on Economic Activity</em> and an interactive dashboard that provides updates of the results from the published article on a monthly basis. We have produced these updates from August 2020 through April 2022. And with each monthly update, we produce a report summarizing the key findings to date, which we post on our webpage dedicated to this project. We also actively engage in dissemination activities to ensure that our real-time poverty measure reaches a broad audience of researchers, policy makers and service providers. In addition to the dashboard, these activities include a monthly eblast that is broadly distributed, a monthly press release.&nbsp; We have also presented our work at professional conferences including the Brookings Papers on Economic Activity conference in Washington, DC and the Annual Meeting of the Association for Public Policy and Management in Austin, Texas.&nbsp; We have also disseminated our work to broader audiences.&nbsp; These dissemination efforts have resulted in our work being featured in many major media outlets including the New York Times, the Economist, the Washington Post, NBC News, Bloomberg News, NPR, CNN, and others.</p> <p class="Default">Several individuals have further developed their research skills through working on the project, including several undergraduate and graduate students who have helped write the statistical programs and conduct the data analysis; and a research associate (pre-doc) has helped design and launch the online dashboard and update the results for this dashboard each month.</p> <p class="Default">&nbsp;We have also shared the results of our project with researchers at government agencies interested in poverty measurement, and these efforts have informed recommendations from these agencies. For example, a recent Inter-agency Technical Working Group report on poverty measurement by the federal government encouraged the federal statistical system to follow up on our work and consider more timely updates to poverty measures. The Census Bureau has an ongoing project that first replicated our results and then has begun to consider permanently adopting a measure such as the one we created.&nbsp;</p> <p class="Default">&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/11/2022<br>      Modified by: Bruce&nbsp;D&nbsp;Meyer</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[Our project has provided critical, real-time information on the state of the economy that was useful during the pandemic and continues to be used by policymakers and researchers.  We constructed new measures of the income distribution and income-based poverty with a lag of only a few weeks using high frequency data for a large, representative sample of U.S. families and individuals, and we validated these new measures by comparing them to other measures based on well-established data sources. The main results of our research are contained in our published article in the journal Brookings Papers on Economic Activity and an interactive dashboard that provides updates of the results from the published article on a monthly basis. We have produced these updates from August 2020 through April 2022. And with each monthly update, we produce a report summarizing the key findings to date, which we post on our webpage dedicated to this project. We also actively engage in dissemination activities to ensure that our real-time poverty measure reaches a broad audience of researchers, policy makers and service providers. In addition to the dashboard, these activities include a monthly eblast that is broadly distributed, a monthly press release.  We have also presented our work at professional conferences including the Brookings Papers on Economic Activity conference in Washington, DC and the Annual Meeting of the Association for Public Policy and Management in Austin, Texas.  We have also disseminated our work to broader audiences.  These dissemination efforts have resulted in our work being featured in many major media outlets including the New York Times, the Economist, the Washington Post, NBC News, Bloomberg News, NPR, CNN, and others. Several individuals have further developed their research skills through working on the project, including several undergraduate and graduate students who have helped write the statistical programs and conduct the data analysis; and a research associate (pre-doc) has helped design and launch the online dashboard and update the results for this dashboard each month.  We have also shared the results of our project with researchers at government agencies interested in poverty measurement, and these efforts have informed recommendations from these agencies. For example, a recent Inter-agency Technical Working Group report on poverty measurement by the federal government encouraged the federal statistical system to follow up on our work and consider more timely updates to poverty measures. The Census Bureau has an ongoing project that first replicated our results and then has begun to consider permanently adopting a measure such as the one we created.          Last Modified: 05/11/2022       Submitted by: Bruce D Meyer]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
