<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Uncovering the Effects of COVID-19 on Stress, Well-being and Economic Decision-Making]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>82273.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>82273</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kwabena Gyimah-Brempong</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kgyimahb@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927466</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Measures taken to slow the spread of COVID-19, such as social distancing and “stay-at-home” orders  have generated the fear of income and employment losses in addition to  possibility of the individual, friends and family getting infected.  COVID-19 therefore increases burdens on mental well-being and stress levels.  Such increased stress levels affect individuals’ decision-making in risky environments, choices over time-dated payments, willingness to donate to charities, and honesty when provided the opportunity to cheat for personal gain. The increased stress levels can impact preferences and choices and a range of outcomes such as health, borrowing and savings, and human capital formation.  It therefore has long-term consequences for individual well-being.  This research project will use survey and field experiments to study the impact of COVID-19. Specifically, it investigates three questions: (i) What are the effects of COVID-19 on stress, mental and physical health, and preferences? (ii) Do individuals believe in the effectiveness of strategies to slow the spread of COVID-19 and do individuals have  confidence in institutions responsible for these strategies? and (iii) What are the welfare effects of the COVID-19 pandemic? In addition, how much money or how many years of life would individuals give up in order to avoid exposure to a future pandemic similar to COVID-19? The results of this study have important policy implications for strategies to reduce the spread of, as well as reducing the effects of COVID-19 on the welfare of households.  This research also will help establish the US as the global leader in policies to reduce the effects of pandemics on households.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project uses a survey and field experiment, built on an existing project, to study the impact of COVID-19 induced stress on economic preferences and decision-making. The survey has several unique features that allows the PIs to quantify non-monetary costs of COVID-19. The survey measures how exposure to COVID-19 affects self-reported levels of stress, life satisfaction, and mental well-being. In addition, the field experiment elicits individual specific measures of time and risk preference, honesty, and pro-social/altruistic behavior, to examine whether and how stress induced by COVID-19 affects economic preferences and decision-making. The study will compare the effects of COVID-19, which may affect both stress and income through changes in employment, to the effects of traffic and congestion, which impact stress, but not income. Results from the study will inform the on-going debate on stability of preferences and how preferences respond to temporary shocks, such as the COVID-19 pandemic. The results will also provide important inputs into policy formulation and implementation to reduce the spread of, as well as mitigate the welfare effects of COVID-19.  The research will provide insights into which organizations are most trusted during a national crisis, and therefore guide information strategies to prevent the spread of pandemics.  This research also will help establish the US as the global leader in policies to reduce the effects of pandemics on households.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/25/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/25/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2033425</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Laura</FirstName>
<LastName>Razzolini</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Laura Razzolini</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[lrazzolini@cba.ua.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000367040</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/25/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Price</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael Price</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mkprice2@cba.ua.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000196277</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/25/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Alabama Tuscaloosa</Name>
<CityName>TUSCALOOSA</CityName>
<ZipCode>354870001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2053485152</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>301 ROSE ADMIN BLDG</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Alabama</StateName>
<StateCode>AL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>RCNJEHZ83EV6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ALABAMA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>TWJWHYEM8T63</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Alabama]]></Name>
<CityName>Tuscaloosa</CityName>
<StateCode>AL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>354040005</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Box 870224, 361 Stadium Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Alabama</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1320</Code>
<Text>Economics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~82273</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>In this project we conducted two surveys in Birmingham, AL metropolitan statistical area to quantify the impact of COVID-19 on individual?s well-being and economic decision-making. We combined these data with data from two previous surveys conducted between August and December of 2019 in the same parts of the Birmingham, AL metropolitan area.&nbsp; Throughout 2019, a one-mile stretch of the Interstate 59/20 through downtown Birmingham was closed for a bridge replacement. By combining these data, we were able to compare the effects of two different stressors - traffic induced&nbsp;commute strain&nbsp;and a pandemic ? on stress, mental well-being, and individual decision making.</p> <p>In all four surveys we collected information on risk attitudes, time preference and present bias, altruism, and propensity to lie.&nbsp; In each survey, we also collected standard socio-demographic characteristics and individual specific measures of stress levels, satisfaction with physical health and mental wellbeing, and overall life-satisfaction.&nbsp; For the two survey waves conducted during the COVID-19 pandemic, we also collected data on perceived health risks associated with the pandemic ? like the risk of contracting COVID-19 or the risk of becoming hospitalized because of the virus ? and information about whether the respondent?s life had been impacted by the pandemic ? like if the person reduced physical contact with other people, whether the person?s employment status or earnings had been impacted, or if the person increased the propensity of shopping online or ordering food for delivery. For the two survey waves conducted during the closure of I59/20, we also collected data on whether the person?s daily commute to and from work was impacted by the closure.&nbsp;</p> <p>Analysis of the data from these surveys suggest the following:</p> <p>Outcome one: Both events, commute strain and pandemic, were perceived by the individuals as stressful events.&nbsp; Both events lead to lower life satisfaction, lower levels of happiness and job satisfaction, lower levels of mental well-being, and less balance between work and life.</p> <p>Outcome two:&nbsp; Both events, commute strain and pandemic, impacted decision-making.&nbsp; Individuals reacted to both events by becoming more impatient, more risk-seeking, and less altruistic.</p> <p>Outcome three: The effects of commute strain on stress and our various measures of happiness and well-being are moderated when employers allow for flexible work arrangements.&nbsp; Flexible work arrangements also moderate the effect of commute strain on decision-making.</p> <p>Outcome four: While flexible work schedules moderate the negative effects of commute strain, the effect of flexible work arrangements on impacts associated with the pandemic are more nuanced.&nbsp; Flexible work schedules allow individuals to worry less about the impact of the pandemic on employment and, thus, moderate the effects on work/life balance and job satisfaction.&nbsp; However, the effect of flexible work arrangements on stress levels and individual decision-making during the pandemic is limited.&nbsp;</p> <p>The third and forth outcomes highlight a potential benefit of flexible work arrangements for businesses.&nbsp; Such arrangements can reduce the stress levels of employees and enhance job satisfaction, especially when employees face traffic induced&nbsp;commute strain.</p> <p>Outcome five: Both events, lead to reductions in altruism.&nbsp; However, the reasons for reduced generosity across the two events was different. Commute strain had little impact on the likelihood of sharing money with the selected charity, but did lead to reduced amounts donated.&nbsp; The pandemic, induces lower propensity to give to the selected charity.&nbsp; However, conditioned on giving, the amount shared with the charitable organization increased.</p> <p>Outcome six: The pandemic caused a shift in the types of charitable causes selected by potential donors.&nbsp; Specifically, we find that donors were less likely to select international causes. We register instead an increase in the likelihood of selecting domestic causes providing support to children and families in need.&nbsp;</p> <p>Outcome seven: The changes in patterns of giving during the pandemic is not driven by income shocks and economic hardship.&nbsp; Rather the changes in patterns of giving are driven by reluctant donors, for whom the pandemic provides ?moral wiggle room? that helps reducing the psychological costs of not giving when asked to do so.</p> <p>Outcome eight:&nbsp; The degree of pessimism expressed by a donor ?measured by the greatest chance they believe they will wind up hospitalized by COVID ? is negatively associated with observed generosity. This suggests that pessimistic views about future incomes will lead to less giving today.&nbsp;</p> <p>For charitable organizations, these last four outcomes underline the importance of understanding donors? motives for giving, and how moral propensity to give is impacted by shocks, such as the COVID-19 pandemic, that provide for an uncertain future.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/18/2023<br>      Modified by: Laura&nbsp;Razzolini</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ In this project we conducted two surveys in Birmingham, AL metropolitan statistical area to quantify the impact of COVID-19 on individual?s well-being and economic decision-making. We combined these data with data from two previous surveys conducted between August and December of 2019 in the same parts of the Birmingham, AL metropolitan area.  Throughout 2019, a one-mile stretch of the Interstate 59/20 through downtown Birmingham was closed for a bridge replacement. By combining these data, we were able to compare the effects of two different stressors - traffic induced commute strain and a pandemic ? on stress, mental well-being, and individual decision making.  In all four surveys we collected information on risk attitudes, time preference and present bias, altruism, and propensity to lie.  In each survey, we also collected standard socio-demographic characteristics and individual specific measures of stress levels, satisfaction with physical health and mental wellbeing, and overall life-satisfaction.  For the two survey waves conducted during the COVID-19 pandemic, we also collected data on perceived health risks associated with the pandemic ? like the risk of contracting COVID-19 or the risk of becoming hospitalized because of the virus ? and information about whether the respondent?s life had been impacted by the pandemic ? like if the person reduced physical contact with other people, whether the person?s employment status or earnings had been impacted, or if the person increased the propensity of shopping online or ordering food for delivery. For the two survey waves conducted during the closure of I59/20, we also collected data on whether the person?s daily commute to and from work was impacted by the closure.   Analysis of the data from these surveys suggest the following:  Outcome one: Both events, commute strain and pandemic, were perceived by the individuals as stressful events.  Both events lead to lower life satisfaction, lower levels of happiness and job satisfaction, lower levels of mental well-being, and less balance between work and life.  Outcome two:  Both events, commute strain and pandemic, impacted decision-making.  Individuals reacted to both events by becoming more impatient, more risk-seeking, and less altruistic.  Outcome three: The effects of commute strain on stress and our various measures of happiness and well-being are moderated when employers allow for flexible work arrangements.  Flexible work arrangements also moderate the effect of commute strain on decision-making.  Outcome four: While flexible work schedules moderate the negative effects of commute strain, the effect of flexible work arrangements on impacts associated with the pandemic are more nuanced.  Flexible work schedules allow individuals to worry less about the impact of the pandemic on employment and, thus, moderate the effects on work/life balance and job satisfaction.  However, the effect of flexible work arrangements on stress levels and individual decision-making during the pandemic is limited.   The third and forth outcomes highlight a potential benefit of flexible work arrangements for businesses.  Such arrangements can reduce the stress levels of employees and enhance job satisfaction, especially when employees face traffic induced commute strain.  Outcome five: Both events, lead to reductions in altruism.  However, the reasons for reduced generosity across the two events was different. Commute strain had little impact on the likelihood of sharing money with the selected charity, but did lead to reduced amounts donated.  The pandemic, induces lower propensity to give to the selected charity.  However, conditioned on giving, the amount shared with the charitable organization increased.  Outcome six: The pandemic caused a shift in the types of charitable causes selected by potential donors.  Specifically, we find that donors were less likely to select international causes. We register instead an increase in the likelihood of selecting domestic causes providing support to children and families in need.   Outcome seven: The changes in patterns of giving during the pandemic is not driven by income shocks and economic hardship.  Rather the changes in patterns of giving are driven by reluctant donors, for whom the pandemic provides ?moral wiggle room? that helps reducing the psychological costs of not giving when asked to do so.  Outcome eight:  The degree of pessimism expressed by a donor ?measured by the greatest chance they believe they will wind up hospitalized by COVID ? is negatively associated with observed generosity. This suggests that pessimistic views about future incomes will lead to less giving today.   For charitable organizations, these last four outcomes underline the importance of understanding donors? motives for giving, and how moral propensity to give is impacted by shocks, such as the COVID-19 pandemic, that provide for an uncertain future.          Last Modified: 05/18/2023       Submitted by: Laura Razzolini]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
