<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Psychosocial Determinants of Successful Remote Learning During the Covid-19 Pandemic: A Study of Promoters and Barriers faced by HBCU Students]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>199997.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>199997</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Michelle Rogers</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mlrogers@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032920000</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The unprecedented and fast evolving nature of the COVID-19 pandemic disrupted STEM education, negatively impacting students’ persistence and success. Social aspects of race and class predict health and education outcomes.  Public health crises, like COVID-19, disproportionately impact African Americans (AAs), lower income Americans, and individuals with psychosocial risk factors. This disparate impact has been linked to poor baseline health and environmental factors that make it difficult to adhere to social distancing orders. National education-related disparities show similar patterns across sociodemographic groups. Low-income college students have unequal access to computers, electronic devices, and internet service. They also encounter, higher instances of barriers, such as family violence and hunger, and greater concerns around stress and coping. At North Carolina A&amp;T State University (NC A&amp;T), the nation’s largest Historically Black College and University (HBCU), over 1,700 students failed to show up for classes when COVID-19 forced transition of all classes to online instruction modes in March 2020, placing them at risk for dropping out of college or extending their time in school; an additional financial burden. Furthermore, many of the students at HBCUs work part-time while attending school, mostly in the essential services sector. This places them at greater risk for exposure to COVID-19, exacerbating their anxieties and stress levels. A multidisciplinary team of investigators from NC A&amp;T seeks to understand the risk factors for these college students and use the information to develop effective interventions to prevent disruptions in remote learning success in preparation for fall 2020 and subsequent semesters. This is critical because resumption of classes using “normal” face-to-face formats is unlikely to happen until a drug or vaccine for COVID-19 is developed, a scenario that could take years. If the barriers to online and remote learning are not addressed, these students will literally be left behind. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This study seeks to highlight the extent to which psychosocial risk factors, including poor access to technology resources, related to the current COVID-19 pandemic and extenuating circumstances are having an impact on student learning outcomes. To better understand the correlations between psychosocial risk factors and remote learning success in times of crisis, this study will utilize a mixed-methods approach for students at NC A&amp;T. An online survey will be administered to collect data on various metrics: sociodemographic characteristics, experience with COVID-19, attitudes and behaviors in response to COVID-19, perceived stress and coping, depression, family violence perpetration and victimization, food insecurity and self-efficacy, and familiarity with computers and technology. This will be followed by interviews with randomly selected survey respondents to contextualize quantitative findings and uncover additional barriers and promoters. Survey data will be analyzed using regression modeling, and interview data will be analyzed using content analyses. The survey and interview data will be triangulated by comparing and contrasting findings to develop a comprehensive understanding of psychosocial risk factors that impact remote learning success. The outcomes will inform development of a mobile Application (App) to engage these students and connect them to resources needed to sustain their learning in these disruptive conditions. Findings from this study will produce new knowledge regarding psychosocial determinants of successful remote learning during a critical disruption in the academic journey. As the nation’s largest HBCU and top producer of African American STEM undergraduates, NC A&amp;T is positioned to evaluate how the COVID-19 pandemic has impacted vulnerable students and develop suitable interventions for academic success. This work will inform future policy and development of prevention strategies so that institutions are better prepared for future pandemics that make remote and online learning necessary for all students. This work will produce insights that may be applied more generally to how HBCU students’ and students from similar backgrounds transition to online learning. This research will aid intervention development by identifying factors impacting student success under extreme disruptive conditions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/09/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/09/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2033926</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Anna</FirstName>
<LastName>Lee</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Anna Lee</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[aklee1@ncat.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000710313</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/09/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jeannette</FirstName>
<LastName>Wade</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jeannette M Wade</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jmwade1@ncat.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000828035</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/09/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Adrienne</FirstName>
<LastName>Morgan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Adrienne A Morgan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[adrienne_aikenmorgan@med.unc.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000770970</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/09/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Christopher</FirstName>
<LastName>Doss</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Christopher Doss</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[cdoss@ncat.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000058181</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/09/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Stephanie</FirstName>
<LastName>Teixeira-Poit</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Stephanie M Teixeira-Poit</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[steixeirapoit@ncat.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000788293</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/09/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>North Carolina Agricultural &amp; Technical State University</Name>
<CityName>GREENSBORO</CityName>
<ZipCode>274110002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3363347995</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1601 E MARKET ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>SKH5GMBR9GL3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORTH CAROLINA AGRICULTURAL AND TECHNICAL STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[North Carolina Agricultural & Technical State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Greensboro</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>274110001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>158Y</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>1N20</Code>
<Name>R&amp;RA CARES Act DEFC N</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>010N2021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[R&RA CARES Act DEFC N]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~199997</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>When we think of higher education, student support tends to focus on improving what happens IN the classroom rather than outside of the classroom, yet the environment in which a student lives, studies, and works can greatly impact their success in the classroom. As COVID-19 ravaged our community, many students were required to transition to remote learning regardless of their needs for institutional, interpersonal, and community-based supports. We surveyed students to learn more about the impacts of COVID-19 on their education and mental wellbeing as well their need for institutional and community-based psychosocial supports. We found that 10% of respondents withdrew from 1 or more classes after we transitioned to remote learning because of COVID-19 and 22% of respondents indicated that their mental health was poor after COVID-19 (compared to only 5% of respondents before COVID-19). These findings help elevate the pressing need for addressing student mental health, promoting self-care, and educational institutions? changing roles in connecting students with psychosocial resources that may help foster student success in these rapidly changing, challenging times. This led our team to the development of the Student Hangar App, which is a resource app developed specifically for students at NC A&amp;T but has the potential to be widely applicable and disseminated to students at other college (HBCUs) campuses. By leveraging the ubiquity of smartphone technology to connect students with local community-based resources, the Student Hangar App provides support outside the classroom to help students have the best opportunity for success within the classroom.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/14/2022<br>      Modified by: Anna&nbsp;Lee</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ When we think of higher education, student support tends to focus on improving what happens IN the classroom rather than outside of the classroom, yet the environment in which a student lives, studies, and works can greatly impact their success in the classroom. As COVID-19 ravaged our community, many students were required to transition to remote learning regardless of their needs for institutional, interpersonal, and community-based supports. We surveyed students to learn more about the impacts of COVID-19 on their education and mental wellbeing as well their need for institutional and community-based psychosocial supports. We found that 10% of respondents withdrew from 1 or more classes after we transitioned to remote learning because of COVID-19 and 22% of respondents indicated that their mental health was poor after COVID-19 (compared to only 5% of respondents before COVID-19). These findings help elevate the pressing need for addressing student mental health, promoting self-care, and educational institutions? changing roles in connecting students with psychosocial resources that may help foster student success in these rapidly changing, challenging times. This led our team to the development of the Student Hangar App, which is a resource app developed specifically for students at NC A&amp;T but has the potential to be widely applicable and disseminated to students at other college (HBCUs) campuses. By leveraging the ubiquity of smartphone technology to connect students with local community-based resources, the Student Hangar App provides support outside the classroom to help students have the best opportunity for success within the classroom.          Last Modified: 01/14/2022       Submitted by: Anna Lee]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
