<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[EAGER: Temporal Occurrence, Spatial Dynamics, and Host Diversity of Betacoronaviruses, including SARS-CoV-2, with Implications for Mitigating Covid-19 Re-emergence]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>199652.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>199652</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Katharina Dittmar</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kdittmar@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927799</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Frozen museum collections provide a largely untapped biodiversity infrastructure that would potentially allow for the study of pandemics, like that caused by SARS-CoV-2, in substantially new and different ways. This project will leverage a vast set of frozen samples from wild mammals and engage new expertise to develop powerful interdisciplinary approaches to studying pathogens that emerge from wildlife. This study will examine the frozen tissue collections of the Museum of Southwestern Biology’s Division of Genomic Resources (DGR) with specimens collected from Asian countries near China that are ideal for testing for SARS-CoV-2 virus. Detailed understanding of the distribution of pathogens in the wild and how they cross species boundaries, including switching to infect humans, could provide a critical foundation for prevention and mitigation of future zoonotic infections or reinfections. New workflows that fully leverage this biodiversity and zoonotic pathogen infrastructure will be developed. This project also provides training opportunities for students, including from underrepresented minorities, as well as outreach to the public.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;During the last few decades, disease ecologists and evolutionary biologists have identified key factors involved in the spillover of pathogens from reservoir host species into human populations. Understanding the distribution of the virus in wild mammals will contribute to a better assessment of the potential for direct contact between human populations and the virus. Pathogen detection will be carried out via molecular methods in tissues from 1,000 target (bar-coded) mammal specimens from eastern Asia with a special focus on SARS-CoV-2 and its coronavirus relatives. For positive tissues, sequencing of whole genomes of viruses will be conducted using established techniques for coronaviruses optimized for downstream comparative analyses. Phylogeographic methods will be used to characterize the geographic variation and historical demography of viruses and associated mammalian hosts. These efforts will leverage already existing natural history collection materials to inform SARS-CoV-2 evolution, Covid-19 emergence, and more generally pathogen emergence and epidemiological models.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/20/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/20/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2033482</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daryl</FirstName>
<LastName>Domman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Daryl Domman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ddomman@salud.unm.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000827757</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/20/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Helen</FirstName>
<LastName>Wearing</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Helen Wearing</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[hwearing@unm.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000584202</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/20/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Joseph</FirstName>
<LastName>Cook</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Joseph A Cook</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[cookjose@unm.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000420185</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/20/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Darrell</FirstName>
<LastName>Dinwiddie</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Darrell L Dinwiddie</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[dldinwiddie@salud.unm.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000827323</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/20/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Steven</FirstName>
<LastName>Bradfute</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Steven B Bradfute</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[sbradfute@salud.unm.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000827306</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/20/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of New Mexico</Name>
<CityName>ALBUQUERQUE</CityName>
<ZipCode>871063837</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5052774186</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1700 LOMAS BLVD NE STE 2200</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Mexico</StateName>
<StateCode>NM</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NM01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>F6XLTRUQJEN4</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF NEW MEXICO, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>C16BGHA4MLJ6</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of New Mexico]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NM</StateCode>
<ZipCode>871310001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Mexico</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NM01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7374</Code>
<Text>Systematics &amp; Biodiversity Sci</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~199652</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>In the MuseVirome Project, a total of 1039 tissue samples representing nearly 100 distinct mammalian species (primarily bats and rats) collected from 7 countries (but primarily from Asia) were selected from the frozen biorepository at the University of New Mexico?s Museum of Southwestern Biology to test for SARS-CoV2 and related coronaviruses. RNA was extracted and 978 quality samples were screened using a PCR strategy, <strong>but no samples were found to be positive for coronavirus</strong> by this strategy. All isolated RNA is available for future testing using alternative and optimized virus detection protocols (see below).&nbsp;</p> <p>To assess the ability to detect host microbial flora and potential bacterial, fungal, and viral pathogens in host mammalian tissues, we explored broader screening techniques using metagenomic and metatranscriptomic approaches. We conducted metagenomic DNA sequencing on eight shrew samples and matched metatranscriptomic RNA sequencing on four of the eight samples.&nbsp; For example, using this approach, we found substantial signals of both DNA (662,871 reads) and RNA (1,822,801 sequencing reads) signatures of bacterial origin, respectively (Figure 1). In the DNA sequencing, 26% of all bacterial reads were classified as <em>Firmicutes</em>, and 18% as <em>Gammaproteobacteria</em>. As expected, in the RNA sequencing one of the most prevalent bacteria detected was <em>Staphylococcus aureus</em> (a member of the Firmicutes) with 275,361 reads classified to the species level.&nbsp; Furthermore, in sample MSB288595 the DNA sequencing had 8,166 and 10,858 RNA sequencing reads classified as of viral origin, respectively (Figure 2). In the DNA sequencing results, the majority of classified viral sequences were bacterial phage viruses, as expected. Importantly, the detected phages were recognized viruses of the bacteria that were classified as in the sample.&nbsp;</p> <p>In addition, several pathogens that are of known importance in human infection were found in the analyzed samples.&nbsp; These include <em>Staphylococcus aureus</em> (from museum specimens MSB288595, MSB288596, MSB288622, MSB293217, and MSB417), which, although often part of the normal flora, can cause a range of deadly infections in humans.&nbsp; Furthermore, <em>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</em> was found in MSB288596 and MSB288595; this bacterium is often antibiotic resistant and can cause sepsis, pneumonia, and urinary tract, gastrointestinal, and soft tissue infections in humans; it is also associated with biofilm formation.&nbsp; <em>Clostridium botulinum</em> was found in two samples (MSB293217 and MSB 293417), which is concerning due to its neurotoxin production.&nbsp; Other human pathogens found in our samples included <em>Klebsiella pneumoniae</em> (MSB293417, MSB288595, and MSB288596), <em>Leptospirosa</em> (MSB288595 and MSB288596), and <em>Clostridium perfringens</em> (MSB293417).</p> <p>It remains difficult to say if any of the potential pathogens are causing disease in their wild mammalian hosts or if they are part of the normal microbiome.&nbsp; Additional broad-scale sequencing of multiple host individuals across a wide geographic and seasonal time course is needed to establish an understanding of normal microbiome of these wild mammals, which can be used as a comparative to detect possible abnormal infections or colonization with pathogenic microorganisms.&nbsp;</p> <p>Overall, the preliminary metagenomic and metatranscriptomic results were promising and provide evidence for more detailed future analyses of particular pathogens and for the potential value of screening additional museums samples using these approaches or working with engineers to develop more economical technologies for higher throughput procedures (e.g., chip-based analyses).</p> <p><em>Education</em>--We developed a new educational module on hantavirus for advanced college courses (e.g., Biol 419/519 Modeling Infectious Disease) in parasitology, biogeography, evolution, and ecology, and for high school teachers in advanced placement courses. This module provides hands-on quantitative training in mathematical modeling by linking the epidemiology of Sin Nombre hantavirus with dynamical processes involved in emerging zoonotic pathogens. This module is now available at online http://aimup.unm.edu/.</p> <p><em>Collaborations with biomedical communities---</em>We initiated and continued to build collaborations across the public health arena in the US, Latin America, and Central Asia through efforts related to identifying pathogens from wild mammals and studying the ecology of zoonotic diseases through the Museums and Emerging Pathogens in the Americas (MEPA) Community of Practice. Beginning in early 2020 through UNM?s Project ECHO, we have now reached more than 200 participants representing &gt;35 institutions (biweekly average attendance about 40) and is spread across 12 countries in North, South, and Central America. Participants include biorepositories, universities, government agencies, veterinarians, bioinformaticians, and public health officials, among others. The group meets virtually every other week to troubleshoot barriers to the successful integration of biorepositories into biomedical workflows to facilitate the detection, monitoring, and prevention of emerging zoonotic diseases. Regular MEPA sessions serve as a soundboard for the feasibility of international scaling of our newly developed sequencing and bioinformatic methods.</p> <p><em>Training---</em> Two graduate students (1 woman), including a completed doctoral student now a postdoc at University of Montana with Jeff Good and Zac Cheviron) Three undergrads and a recently graduated student were also supported (all women, 2 Hispanic, 1 Pacific Islander). Of the two staff supported, Robert Nofchissey, is Navajo.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/28/2022<br>      Modified by: Joseph&nbsp;A&nbsp;Cook</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2033482/2033482_10686953_1669680025431_MuseViromeSampling--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2033482/2033482_10686953_1669680025431_MuseViromeSampling--rgov-800width.jpg" title="MuseVirome Mammals"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2033482/2033482_10686953_1669680025431_MuseViromeSampling--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="MuseVirome Mammals"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The 978 screened mammalian hosts include 4 mammalian orders, 11 families, and 84 species from 7 countries that cover the temporal range 1981-2016 and 7 countries.</div> <div class="imageCredit">JA Cook</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Joseph&nbsp;A&nbsp;Cook</div> <div class="imageTitle">MuseVirome Mammals</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2033482/2033482_10686953_1669680154163_MuseViromeFigure2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2033482/2033482_10686953_1669680154163_MuseViromeFigure2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="MuseVirome Figure 2"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2033482/2033482_10686953_1669680154163_MuseViromeFigure2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="MuseVirome Figure 2"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 2. Comparison of reads classified as bacterial from DNA and RNA library preps from shrew museum sample MSB288595.</div> <div class="imageCredit">JA Cook</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Joseph&nbsp;A&nbsp;Cook</div> <div class="imageTitle">MuseVirome Figure 2</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2033482/2033482_10686953_1669680252715_MuseviromeFigure3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2033482/2033482_10686953_1669680252715_MuseviromeFigure3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="MuseVirome Figure 3"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2033482/2033482_10686953_1669680252715_MuseviromeFigure3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="MuseVirome Figure 3"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 3. Comparison of reads classified as viral from DNA and RNA library preps from shrew museum sample MSB288595.</div> <div class="imageCredit">JA Cook</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Joseph&nbsp;A&nbsp;Cook</div> <div class="imageTitle">MuseVirome Figure 3</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2033482/2033482_10686953_1669680613145_MEPAUNM--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2033482/2033482_10686953_1669680613145_MEPAUNM--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Museums &amp; Emerging Pathogens"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2033482/2033482_10686953_1669680613145_MEPAUNM--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Museums &amp; Emerging Pathogens"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Museums and Emerging Pathogens in the Americas is a Community of Practice that meets biweekly and was initiated to bring diverse stakeholders together to assess emerging pathogens.</div> <div class="imageCredit">JA Cook</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Joseph&nbsp;A&nbsp;Cook</div> <div class="imageTitle">Museums & Emerging Pathogens</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ In the MuseVirome Project, a total of 1039 tissue samples representing nearly 100 distinct mammalian species (primarily bats and rats) collected from 7 countries (but primarily from Asia) were selected from the frozen biorepository at the University of New Mexico?s Museum of Southwestern Biology to test for SARS-CoV2 and related coronaviruses. RNA was extracted and 978 quality samples were screened using a PCR strategy, but no samples were found to be positive for coronavirus by this strategy. All isolated RNA is available for future testing using alternative and optimized virus detection protocols (see below).   To assess the ability to detect host microbial flora and potential bacterial, fungal, and viral pathogens in host mammalian tissues, we explored broader screening techniques using metagenomic and metatranscriptomic approaches. We conducted metagenomic DNA sequencing on eight shrew samples and matched metatranscriptomic RNA sequencing on four of the eight samples.  For example, using this approach, we found substantial signals of both DNA (662,871 reads) and RNA (1,822,801 sequencing reads) signatures of bacterial origin, respectively (Figure 1). In the DNA sequencing, 26% of all bacterial reads were classified as Firmicutes, and 18% as Gammaproteobacteria. As expected, in the RNA sequencing one of the most prevalent bacteria detected was Staphylococcus aureus (a member of the Firmicutes) with 275,361 reads classified to the species level.  Furthermore, in sample MSB288595 the DNA sequencing had 8,166 and 10,858 RNA sequencing reads classified as of viral origin, respectively (Figure 2). In the DNA sequencing results, the majority of classified viral sequences were bacterial phage viruses, as expected. Importantly, the detected phages were recognized viruses of the bacteria that were classified as in the sample.   In addition, several pathogens that are of known importance in human infection were found in the analyzed samples.  These include Staphylococcus aureus (from museum specimens MSB288595, MSB288596, MSB288622, MSB293217, and MSB417), which, although often part of the normal flora, can cause a range of deadly infections in humans.  Furthermore, Pseudomonas aeruginosa was found in MSB288596 and MSB288595; this bacterium is often antibiotic resistant and can cause sepsis, pneumonia, and urinary tract, gastrointestinal, and soft tissue infections in humans; it is also associated with biofilm formation.  Clostridium botulinum was found in two samples (MSB293217 and MSB 293417), which is concerning due to its neurotoxin production.  Other human pathogens found in our samples included Klebsiella pneumoniae (MSB293417, MSB288595, and MSB288596), Leptospirosa (MSB288595 and MSB288596), and Clostridium perfringens (MSB293417).  It remains difficult to say if any of the potential pathogens are causing disease in their wild mammalian hosts or if they are part of the normal microbiome.  Additional broad-scale sequencing of multiple host individuals across a wide geographic and seasonal time course is needed to establish an understanding of normal microbiome of these wild mammals, which can be used as a comparative to detect possible abnormal infections or colonization with pathogenic microorganisms.   Overall, the preliminary metagenomic and metatranscriptomic results were promising and provide evidence for more detailed future analyses of particular pathogens and for the potential value of screening additional museums samples using these approaches or working with engineers to develop more economical technologies for higher throughput procedures (e.g., chip-based analyses).  Education--We developed a new educational module on hantavirus for advanced college courses (e.g., Biol 419/519 Modeling Infectious Disease) in parasitology, biogeography, evolution, and ecology, and for high school teachers in advanced placement courses. This module provides hands-on quantitative training in mathematical modeling by linking the epidemiology of Sin Nombre hantavirus with dynamical processes involved in emerging zoonotic pathogens. This module is now available at online http://aimup.unm.edu/.  Collaborations with biomedical communities---We initiated and continued to build collaborations across the public health arena in the US, Latin America, and Central Asia through efforts related to identifying pathogens from wild mammals and studying the ecology of zoonotic diseases through the Museums and Emerging Pathogens in the Americas (MEPA) Community of Practice. Beginning in early 2020 through UNM?s Project ECHO, we have now reached more than 200 participants representing &gt;35 institutions (biweekly average attendance about 40) and is spread across 12 countries in North, South, and Central America. Participants include biorepositories, universities, government agencies, veterinarians, bioinformaticians, and public health officials, among others. The group meets virtually every other week to troubleshoot barriers to the successful integration of biorepositories into biomedical workflows to facilitate the detection, monitoring, and prevention of emerging zoonotic diseases. Regular MEPA sessions serve as a soundboard for the feasibility of international scaling of our newly developed sequencing and bioinformatic methods.  Training--- Two graduate students (1 woman), including a completed doctoral student now a postdoc at University of Montana with Jeff Good and Zac Cheviron) Three undergrads and a recently graduated student were also supported (all women, 2 Hispanic, 1 Pacific Islander). Of the two staff supported, Robert Nofchissey, is Navajo.       Last Modified: 11/28/2022       Submitted by: Joseph A Cook]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
