<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Translating Basic Research Into Actionable Guidance Through the Societal Experts Action Network (SEAN)]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>198000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>198000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Nancy Lutz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>nlutz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927280</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Decision-makers at the state, national and local level are facing a range of complex issues as they lead the COVID-19 recovery efforts in their communities. These issues include increased unemployment, disruption of schools and education, unhealthy practices, increased domestic violence and many other critical problems affecting the well-being of virtually every person in the U.S. In order to make informed decisions on how to mitigate these issues, decision-makers need rapid access to the best possible evidence and information. That evidence and information can be provided by experts in the social, behavioral, and economic sciences through the newly formed Societal Experts Action Network (SEAN). SEAN will include researchers from leading social and behavioral science institutions and will be guided by an executive committee that will coordinate with the National Academies’ Standing Committee on Emerging Infectious Diseases and 21st Century Health Threats.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;SEAN is a multi-faceted effort and will include a number of organizations collaborating together while each managing different components. The purpose of this project is to create and manage the SEAN component responsible for rapidly translating the wealth of scholarly research, data and other materials provided by social, behavioral and economic science experts into actionable guidance that can be used immediately by decision-makers, businesses and other community leaders. The translation component of SEAN will be based at the Federation for American Scientists and will be home to consultants who are skilled at translating scholarly research and data into plain-language guidance that can be applied to current real-world events. Using the model of “Rapid Expert Consultations,” SEAN will provide expert guidance on a range of issues to decision-makers, while also making the same guidance available to the general public. We expect SEAN to greatly expand the use of “Rapid Expert Consultations” beyond medicine and virology into a broad range of subjects, such as how to best use remote-learning technology to teach children, how to bolster our supply chains and small businesses, how to address social isolation and domestic violence and many other public issues facing our communities now and into the future.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/10/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/10/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2033924</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kerry</FirstName>
<LastName>Duggan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kerry C Duggan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[kerry@sustainabilid.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000827151</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Stebbins</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael Stebbins</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[Mike@MikeStebbins.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000827073</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Federation of American Scientists</Name>
<CityName>WASHINGTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>200364814</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2024544689</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1112 16TH ST NW</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[STE 600]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>KHMQUXDA2K33</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>FEDERATION OF AMERICAN SCIENTISTS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Federation of American Scientists]]></Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>200362824</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1397</Code>
<Text>Cross-Directorate  Activities</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~198000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-d9b49e6e-7fff-89b6-debc-f971a05c72ab"> <p dir="ltr"><span>The damage that the global pandemic has wreaked on the world is unprecedented in modern times.&nbsp; While biochemistry and other biomedical research hold key roles in ameliorating the pandemic, human behavior, as a factor in the spread, must be taken seriously. Established in 2020, the Societal Experts Action Network (SEAN) is a network of social scientists, survey professionals, and institutions in the social, behavioral, and economic sciences available to provide actionable responses to urgent policy questions. The purpose of the network is to harness social science knowledge in the fight against the global pandemic of COVID-19.&nbsp; Its mission is to be a bridge between the social sciences and real decisions that must be made day-to-day by local and state government leaders, public health administrators, and hosts of other public servants who are charged with confronting the pandemic.</span></p> <span id="docs-internal-guid-94e4c517-7fff-b8f8-d359-11f2cf18a6da"> <p dir="ltr"><span>SEAN has successfully created an infrastructure through which subject matter experts can translate relevant reports into more accessible language for decision-makers. By establishing relationships with local and state decision maker groups (e.g. &#8203;&#8203;National Governors Association, National Conference of State Legislatures, National League of Cities, International City/County Management Association, National Association of City and County Health Officials, local public health agencies, and National Association of Counties) and understanding high priority questions related to COVID-19, SEAN was able to prioritize questions and mechanisms for response in a timely manner.</span></p> </span> <p dir="ltr"><span>In less than a year of operation, SEAN has produced nine rapid expert consultations, eight webinars, and contributed to one consensus study report of the National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine. SEAN&rsquo;s products are short, rapid, and evidence-based, translating technical concepts into actionable guidance for decision makers. SEAN reports have drawn&nbsp;<span id="docs-internal-guid-510f6d11-7fff-a236-ebfe-5c4d02baf020"><span>21,975 readers from all 50 states, 133 countries, and all sectors of society. 11 briefings have been conducted with decision makers at the state, local, and federal levels, and&nbsp;<span id="docs-internal-guid-eb9ff38b-7fff-1aeb-b9a3-620a90ed0c16"><span>SEAN&rsquo;s work has been referenced in</span><span> 20</span><span> articles ranging from the Washington Post, New York Times, Bloomberg News, and Politico, to the Journal of the American Medical Association.</span></span></span></span></span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span><span><span><span><span><span id="docs-internal-guid-e7cb0406-7fff-a240-adcb-6b60b6d261aa"><span>SEAN&rsquo;s rapid consultations with subject matter experts in social, behavioral, and economic sciences created actionable, easily accessible and legible guidance for addressing questions raised during the COVID-19 pandemic. Various decision makers and policy advisors from departments of public health, universities, governors offices, and the CDC have been quoted citing SEAN&rsquo;s rapid expert consultations as &lsquo;</span><span>a vital resource to state and local leaders as they seek to implement an evidence-informed response to the pandemic.&rsquo; </span></span><br /></span></span></span></span></span></p> </span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/22/2021<br>      Modified by: Kerry&nbsp;C&nbsp;Duggan</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  The damage that the global pandemic has wreaked on the world is unprecedented in modern times.  While biochemistry and other biomedical research hold key roles in ameliorating the pandemic, human behavior, as a factor in the spread, must be taken seriously. Established in 2020, the Societal Experts Action Network (SEAN) is a network of social scientists, survey professionals, and institutions in the social, behavioral, and economic sciences available to provide actionable responses to urgent policy questions. The purpose of the network is to harness social science knowledge in the fight against the global pandemic of COVID-19.  Its mission is to be a bridge between the social sciences and real decisions that must be made day-to-day by local and state government leaders, public health administrators, and hosts of other public servants who are charged with confronting the pandemic.  SEAN has successfully created an infrastructure through which subject matter experts can translate relevant reports into more accessible language for decision-makers. By establishing relationships with local and state decision maker groups (e.g. &#8203;&#8203;National Governors Association, National Conference of State Legislatures, National League of Cities, International City/County Management Association, National Association of City and County Health Officials, local public health agencies, and National Association of Counties) and understanding high priority questions related to COVID-19, SEAN was able to prioritize questions and mechanisms for response in a timely manner.  In less than a year of operation, SEAN has produced nine rapid expert consultations, eight webinars, and contributed to one consensus study report of the National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine. SEAN’s products are short, rapid, and evidence-based, translating technical concepts into actionable guidance for decision makers. SEAN reports have drawn 21,975 readers from all 50 states, 133 countries, and all sectors of society. 11 briefings have been conducted with decision makers at the state, local, and federal levels, and SEAN’s work has been referenced in 20 articles ranging from the Washington Post, New York Times, Bloomberg News, and Politico, to the Journal of the American Medical Association. SEAN’s rapid consultations with subject matter experts in social, behavioral, and economic sciences created actionable, easily accessible and legible guidance for addressing questions raised during the COVID-19 pandemic. Various decision makers and policy advisors from departments of public health, universities, governors offices, and the CDC have been quoted citing SEAN’s rapid expert consultations as ‘a vital resource to state and local leaders as they seek to implement an evidence-informed response to the pandemic.’          Last Modified: 09/22/2021       Submitted by: Kerry C Duggan]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
