<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[I-Corps: A Multi-Antigen Vaccine Delivery System for the Effective Induction of Mucosal Immunity]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ruth Shuman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rshuman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922160</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this I-Corps project is the development of a novel vaccine discovery platform. The COVID-19 pandemic has opened our eyes to the urgent need for technologies capable of effectively delivering vaccines that combat mucosal infections. Mucosal infections, such as influenza and rotavirus, make up more than 70% of the yearly cases of infectious diseases recorded in the US, and more than 50% of all infections worldwide. This high infection rate is because most pathogens either infect mucosal tissues directly or begin their invasion at mucosal sites throughout the body (i.e., the nose, intestines, and mouth).  The proposed technology solves the need to effectively deliver vaccines to mucosal tissue, providing a robust immune response, and can be rapidly developed and scaled up to respond to emerging pandemics, saving potentially hundreds of thousands of lives. In addition to being rapid response, the proposed vaccine delivery system can be used with multiple antigens at once, potentially reducing the number of vaccinations required throughout a patient’s lifetime. The proposed vaccine platform is needle-free, allowing it to be administered outside of clinics, reducing the need for highly skilled personnel and administration costs especially in low-income countries.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project is based on the development of outer cell membrane vesicles as a vaccine delivery platform. Outer membrane vesicles (OMVs) are spherical lipid bilayers naturally produced by bacteria that possess the ability to modulate the immune system. Previously, OMVs were engineered to display antigens on their exterior surface, thereby acting as a self-adjuvanted vaccine platform that has shown promise in animal models as an injectable vaccine. Further modification of the OMV platform to enable the co-delivery of multiple different antigens has been investigated for its immunological potential in a mouse model. Preliminary work has shown this feature to yield potential benefits for vaccine engineering. Additionally, through buccal vaccination in swine, OMVs were shown to induce robust mucosal immunity, without the need for injection.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/06/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/06/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2033559</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tom</FirstName>
<LastName>Schryver</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Tom Schryver</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[tps1@cornell.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000673743</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/06/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Cornell University</Name>
<CityName>ITHACA</CityName>
<ZipCode>148502820</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6072555014</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>341 PINE TREE RD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>23</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY23</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>G56PUALJ3KT5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CORNELL UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>EQA8NBEN9WD5</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Cornell University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>148502820</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>23</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY23</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p style="text-align: center;"><strong><span>A Multi-Antigen Vaccine Delivery System for the Effective Induction of Mucosal Immunity</span></strong></p> <p>We engineered a <span style="text-decoration: underline;">multi-antigen vaccine delivery platform</span> that effectively induces mucosal immunity by a simple swab of the cheek with a cotton swab. The platform is based on <span style="text-decoration: underline;">outer membrane vesicles</span> (OMVs) &ndash; <span style="text-decoration: underline;">a self-adjuvanted </span>delivery technology very amenable to recombinant <span style="text-decoration: underline;">subunit vaccines</span>. The IP for OMVs capable of delivering <span style="text-decoration: underline;">single antigen</span> subunit vaccines is currently in development for human phase I clinical trials at the small biotech company - Versatope. Our team has developed a <span style="text-decoration: underline;">multiple antigen</span> OMV co-delivery technology. Our OMV technology was successful in inducing both a systemic immune response in mice models through needle injection and <span style="text-decoration: underline;">mucosal immunity</span> in swine through buccal vaccination via a Q-tip. Patent application 62/992,490 was filed for this innovative vaccine delivery platform through Cornell University&rsquo;s Office of Technology Licensing. Through participation in the regional I-Corps program in the Spring 2020, we identified both commercial and not-for-profit vaccine development organizations as potential customers for this technology.&nbsp; At the national I-Corps program in the summer 2020, we further determined, through a robust customer discovery process, the first product for our vaccine pipeline to be a pediatric RSV vaccine to be marketed to the ACIP, the initial vaccine customers in the United States.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Intellectual Merit: </strong>Our engineered multi-antigen vaccine delivery platform will <em><span style="text-decoration: underline;">enable researchers to answer both vaccine engineering and basic immunological questions</span></em>. In fact, while many researchers have advocated for pathogen-mimetic vaccines, the immunological questions surrounding the possible differential interactions between innate immune cells and these multi-antigen delivery platforms remains unanswered. Many questions abound such as: mechanistically, are the antigens processed by the immune system in a similar way? Does the platform induce a synergistic or competitive immune response to each antigen? Which antigens should be co-delivered, and which immune cells do they interact with? The answers that the use of the multi-antigen vaccine technology would provide may have huge implications for vaccine engineering, including cementing the place of pathogen-mimetic vaccines in the vaccine pipeline.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts: </strong>Infectious diseases affect an estimated one-third of the human population every year, causing significant economic losses in both direct and indirect costs for hospitalization and treatment of affected individuals. For example, in the U.S. alone, the current COVID-19 pandemic has resulted in over 1 million infections, caused more than 56,000 deaths, forced over 25 million people to file for unemployment, and cost the U.S. government more than $2.5 trillion in spending to relieve the economy, with these numbers still increasing. Due to the rise in the number of novel zoonotic pathogens, more infectious diseases continue to appear, making vaccines essential to protect the population. However, with significant development and manufacturing costs outweighing commercialization benefits, vaccines are often not a lucrative investment. The OMV technology we developed reduces the upfront capital cost, as well as cost associated with single-use needles necessary for current vaccination regimens. We envisage the successful commercialization of this product to help reduce time and costs associated with vaccine development and clinical trials, and result in a viable vaccine in months rather than years. Furthermore, adoption of this technology will help to prepare healthcare systems for future pandemics, allowing manufacturers to scale up quickly. Finally, with simple manufacturing, vaccination programs could expand towards less lucrative disease markets, such as neglected tropical diseases.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/24/2022<br>      Modified by: Tom&nbsp;Schryver</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[A Multi-Antigen Vaccine Delivery System for the Effective Induction of Mucosal Immunity  We engineered a multi-antigen vaccine delivery platform that effectively induces mucosal immunity by a simple swab of the cheek with a cotton swab. The platform is based on outer membrane vesicles (OMVs) &ndash; a self-adjuvanted delivery technology very amenable to recombinant subunit vaccines. The IP for OMVs capable of delivering single antigen subunit vaccines is currently in development for human phase I clinical trials at the small biotech company - Versatope. Our team has developed a multiple antigen OMV co-delivery technology. Our OMV technology was successful in inducing both a systemic immune response in mice models through needle injection and mucosal immunity in swine through buccal vaccination via a Q-tip. Patent application 62/992,490 was filed for this innovative vaccine delivery platform through Cornell University’s Office of Technology Licensing. Through participation in the regional I-Corps program in the Spring 2020, we identified both commercial and not-for-profit vaccine development organizations as potential customers for this technology.  At the national I-Corps program in the summer 2020, we further determined, through a robust customer discovery process, the first product for our vaccine pipeline to be a pediatric RSV vaccine to be marketed to the ACIP, the initial vaccine customers in the United States.     Intellectual Merit: Our engineered multi-antigen vaccine delivery platform will enable researchers to answer both vaccine engineering and basic immunological questions. In fact, while many researchers have advocated for pathogen-mimetic vaccines, the immunological questions surrounding the possible differential interactions between innate immune cells and these multi-antigen delivery platforms remains unanswered. Many questions abound such as: mechanistically, are the antigens processed by the immune system in a similar way? Does the platform induce a synergistic or competitive immune response to each antigen? Which antigens should be co-delivered, and which immune cells do they interact with? The answers that the use of the multi-antigen vaccine technology would provide may have huge implications for vaccine engineering, including cementing the place of pathogen-mimetic vaccines in the vaccine pipeline.     Broader Impacts: Infectious diseases affect an estimated one-third of the human population every year, causing significant economic losses in both direct and indirect costs for hospitalization and treatment of affected individuals. For example, in the U.S. alone, the current COVID-19 pandemic has resulted in over 1 million infections, caused more than 56,000 deaths, forced over 25 million people to file for unemployment, and cost the U.S. government more than $2.5 trillion in spending to relieve the economy, with these numbers still increasing. Due to the rise in the number of novel zoonotic pathogens, more infectious diseases continue to appear, making vaccines essential to protect the population. However, with significant development and manufacturing costs outweighing commercialization benefits, vaccines are often not a lucrative investment. The OMV technology we developed reduces the upfront capital cost, as well as cost associated with single-use needles necessary for current vaccination regimens. We envisage the successful commercialization of this product to help reduce time and costs associated with vaccine development and clinical trials, and result in a viable vaccine in months rather than years. Furthermore, adoption of this technology will help to prepare healthcare systems for future pandemics, allowing manufacturers to scale up quickly. Finally, with simple manufacturing, vaccination programs could expand towards less lucrative disease markets, such as neglected tropical diseases.       Last Modified: 02/24/2022       Submitted by: Tom Schryver]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
