<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Mapping Integral Human Behavior Changes and Resiliency in Response to COVID-19]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>9977.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>9977</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jeffrey Mantz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jmantz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927783</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[During the COVID-19 pandemic, encouraged human behaviors such as social distancing and wearing of masks have become key methods to control the spread of the disease. While individuals may be presented with suggested behavioral changes and prompts daily, how individuals perceive these recommendations within their local, national, and global context can influence how they assess disease risk and whether they respond to recommendations in their daily lives. By pairing variability in individual and community disease perception with news data, this research aims to model efficacy and success of different human behaviors to halt the spread of disease. This project uses social network analysis to understand what networks help or hinder behavioral changes during a pandemic, with the aim of identifying adaptations that impact stress resistance and resiliency. The project provides training for graduate and undergraduate students in methods of rigorous, scientific data collection and analysis. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research will be conducted in three main phases to address two issues: (1) how human behavioral changes are affecting the spread of COVID-19, and (2) what integral behavioral changes appear to have the greatest influence on resiliency to a pandemic disaster. In the first phase, researchers in a major metropolitan area will conduct an observation-based analysis using picture and field note evidence at open essential businesses. This phase will provide a basis for local and national trends. In the second phase, researchers will recruit from a range of more remote locations for the purposes of understanding larger social networks. Participants will fill out a risk-perception survey, schedule an interview with researchers, and, if interested, will participate in forwarding their own photographic evidence and field notes following research guidelines. In the third phase, a systematic news media analysis will be conducted from November 2019 through the continuation of the project. Such a review will focus on a pool of accessible news sources that will provide a way of tracking human behavioral changes and recommendations from the beginning of the pandemic, onwards. Using frameworks from disaster, anthropology, identity, and social network research, this study will provide information that may be actively utilized in epidemiological efforts to address the spread of COVID-19. Additionally, this research project aims to develop a functioning dynamic model of identified effective human behaviors to be useful in planning pandemic responses currently and in the future.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/05/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/16/2023</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2033008</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jonathan</FirstName>
<LastName>Maupin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jonathan Maupin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jonathan.maupin@asu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000571661</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/05/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Julia</FirstName>
<LastName>Ivanova</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Julia Ivanova</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jivanova@asu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000743732</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/05/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alyssa</FirstName>
<LastName>Hart</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>N</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alyssa N Hart</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[alyssanhart@gmail.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000826650</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/05/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gage</FirstName>
<LastName>Reitzel</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gage A Reitzel</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[gareitzel@gmail.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000826654</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/05/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Arizona State University</Name>
<CityName>TEMPE</CityName>
<ZipCode>852813670</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4809655479</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>660 S MILL AVENUE STE 204</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AZ04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NTLHJXM55KZ6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ARIZONA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Arizona State University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>852876011</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AZ04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1390</Code>
<Text>Cultural Anthropology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1390</Code>
<Text>CULTURAL ANTHROPOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~9977</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>On March 11, 2020 the World Health Organization (WHO) declared COVID-19 a pandemic. By that time the disease had spread to 114 countries and resulted in 4,291 deaths. While global health organizations, like the WHO, worked to gather information on the spread, prevention, and possible treatments for COVID-19, national governments implemented a range of prevention and mitigation efforts, from police-enforced curfews in Guatemala to limited restrictions in Sweden. Public information about the disease was rapidly changing and social media offered counter-narratives a space to contest and question established sources of information such as the WHO or the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) in the United States of America. During the first year of the pandemic, in particular, individuals in every country were faced with variations in global, national and local policy; conflicting narratives about the severity, spread, and prevention of COVID-19; and concerns about the political, economic, and social impacts of the disease and health policies.</p> <p>This research examined public perceptions of COVID-19 throughout the second half of 2020. To understand the role of socio-cultural and political contexts in shaping perceptions of COVID-19 and health responses, we recruited residents in the United States of America as well as expatriates living abroad. Using a mixed-methods approach, we surveyed 268 individuals in 25 countries from June 2020 through February 2021. These surveys focused on perceptions of COVID-19 severity, risk, and prevention. We additionally conducted qualitative interviews with 36 participants in 15 countries between July 2020 and February 2021. In addition to discussions of COVID-19 severity, risk, and prevention, these interviews focused on expatriates&rsquo; perceptions of local interactions, national policies, and international guidelines.</p> <p>Results of the survey show general trends across participants in all countries during the second half of 2020, including uncertainty about the severity and transmissibility of COVID-19. The majority of participants agreed that social distancing could help prevent COVID-19, and many reported that they would socially distance if advised to do so due to a feeling of responsibility for the health of themselves and others. Yet, many reported that they did not believe that other people in their neighborhoods would follow social distance guidelines and limit the effectiveness of prevention guidelines, emphasizing the importance of social networks as well as (dis)trust in the wider communities that individuals are embedded in.</p> <p>Follow-up semi-structured interviews with participants over Zoom allowed participants to expand on the factors influencing their perceptions of COVID-19 severity, risk, and prevention. Interviews with expatriates inevitably turned into a comparison between the participants&rsquo; countries of residence and their country of origin, the United States of America. Four primary themes emerged during in the interviews: the political influence of national COVID-19 responses; states&rsquo; rights versus individual rights; comparing media representations of COVID-19 with information gathered through social networks at home and abroad; and the influence of cultural orientations in responding to global, national, and local COVID-19 policies, particularly the differences between individualism in the USA and collectivism in South Asian contexts. Expatriates&rsquo; comparisons of COVID-19 policies in the USA and their countries of residence involve a process of self-identifying as participants linked COVID-19 responses to political and cultural processes that either connected them to, or separated them from, their countries of origin and residence. COVID-19 narratives thus serve not only to express uncertainty about the severity and spread of the disease itself, but as a way for individuals to contrast the political and socio-cultural contexts of the USA with other countries, and thereby individuals&rsquo; own sense of identity and values.</p> <p>The findings of this research have implications for cultural and medical anthropology as well as epidemiology and global health. Specifically, the data show that individuals interpret COVID-19 prevention efforts in the contexts of national political systems and cultural contexts. (Dis)Trust in political administrations or systems can influence individuals&rsquo; willingness to participate in prevention behaviors. Similarly, distrust in community members&rsquo; willingness to participate in prevention behaviors, such as social distancing, may reduce individual behaviors even if they feel a sense of individual and social responsibility. These findings can contribute to understanding public response to global and public health initiatives in different political and socio-cultural contexts.</p> <p>This research served as training for graduate and undergraduate students. One graduate student served as the Co-Principal Investigator. Graduate student training emphasized how to run and manage a funded grant process, how to teach project-related lessons in data management, recruitment, methodology, theory, and teamwork. Four undergraduate students participated in the project. Undergraduate student training focused on methodological skills including sampling, survey design, interview methodologies, and qualitative and qualitative analysis.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/04/2023<br>      Modified by: Jonathan&nbsp;Maupin</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ On March 11, 2020 the World Health Organization (WHO) declared COVID-19 a pandemic. By that time the disease had spread to 114 countries and resulted in 4,291 deaths. While global health organizations, like the WHO, worked to gather information on the spread, prevention, and possible treatments for COVID-19, national governments implemented a range of prevention and mitigation efforts, from police-enforced curfews in Guatemala to limited restrictions in Sweden. Public information about the disease was rapidly changing and social media offered counter-narratives a space to contest and question established sources of information such as the WHO or the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) in the United States of America. During the first year of the pandemic, in particular, individuals in every country were faced with variations in global, national and local policy; conflicting narratives about the severity, spread, and prevention of COVID-19; and concerns about the political, economic, and social impacts of the disease and health policies.  This research examined public perceptions of COVID-19 throughout the second half of 2020. To understand the role of socio-cultural and political contexts in shaping perceptions of COVID-19 and health responses, we recruited residents in the United States of America as well as expatriates living abroad. Using a mixed-methods approach, we surveyed 268 individuals in 25 countries from June 2020 through February 2021. These surveys focused on perceptions of COVID-19 severity, risk, and prevention. We additionally conducted qualitative interviews with 36 participants in 15 countries between July 2020 and February 2021. In addition to discussions of COVID-19 severity, risk, and prevention, these interviews focused on expatriates’ perceptions of local interactions, national policies, and international guidelines.  Results of the survey show general trends across participants in all countries during the second half of 2020, including uncertainty about the severity and transmissibility of COVID-19. The majority of participants agreed that social distancing could help prevent COVID-19, and many reported that they would socially distance if advised to do so due to a feeling of responsibility for the health of themselves and others. Yet, many reported that they did not believe that other people in their neighborhoods would follow social distance guidelines and limit the effectiveness of prevention guidelines, emphasizing the importance of social networks as well as (dis)trust in the wider communities that individuals are embedded in.  Follow-up semi-structured interviews with participants over Zoom allowed participants to expand on the factors influencing their perceptions of COVID-19 severity, risk, and prevention. Interviews with expatriates inevitably turned into a comparison between the participants’ countries of residence and their country of origin, the United States of America. Four primary themes emerged during in the interviews: the political influence of national COVID-19 responses; states’ rights versus individual rights; comparing media representations of COVID-19 with information gathered through social networks at home and abroad; and the influence of cultural orientations in responding to global, national, and local COVID-19 policies, particularly the differences between individualism in the USA and collectivism in South Asian contexts. Expatriates’ comparisons of COVID-19 policies in the USA and their countries of residence involve a process of self-identifying as participants linked COVID-19 responses to political and cultural processes that either connected them to, or separated them from, their countries of origin and residence. COVID-19 narratives thus serve not only to express uncertainty about the severity and spread of the disease itself, but as a way for individuals to contrast the political and socio-cultural contexts of the USA with other countries, and thereby individuals’ own sense of identity and values.  The findings of this research have implications for cultural and medical anthropology as well as epidemiology and global health. Specifically, the data show that individuals interpret COVID-19 prevention efforts in the contexts of national political systems and cultural contexts. (Dis)Trust in political administrations or systems can influence individuals’ willingness to participate in prevention behaviors. Similarly, distrust in community members’ willingness to participate in prevention behaviors, such as social distancing, may reduce individual behaviors even if they feel a sense of individual and social responsibility. These findings can contribute to understanding public response to global and public health initiatives in different political and socio-cultural contexts.  This research served as training for graduate and undergraduate students. One graduate student served as the Co-Principal Investigator. Graduate student training emphasized how to run and manage a funded grant process, how to teach project-related lessons in data management, recruitment, methodology, theory, and teamwork. Four undergraduate students participated in the project. Undergraduate student training focused on methodological skills including sampling, survey design, interview methodologies, and qualitative and qualitative analysis.       Last Modified: 08/04/2023       Submitted by: Jonathan Maupin]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
