<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[I-Corps: Restorative cement for remineralization in tooth decay following minimal invasive restoration]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ruth Shuman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rshuman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922160</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this I-Corps project is the development of a dental restorative addressing dental cavities. Dental caries remains the most common chronic disease in humans, children (25%), teenagers (59%), and adults (92%); it consumes 5-10% of healthcare budgets in high-income countries. The proposed technology provides a low-cost solution to functionally repair and mineralize the damaged tooth, instead of merely removing the tissue, reducing the time and costs associated with surgical intervention. It may be readily adopted by dental professionals as it requires only minor modifications to the existing restorative workflow, and as a minimally invasive approach, it may simplify and shorten surgical interventions compared to conventional restorations. The core technology of mineralization opens a significant potential for the in vitro synthesis as well as in vivo repair of mineralized tissues like bone, and cementum.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project is based on the development of a dental restorative to address dentin incipient cavities.  The proposed technology is based on the incorporation of the polymer induced liquid precursor (PILP)-method into a dental restorative. This material releases biomimetic molecules that transport calcium and phosphate ions to collagen fibrils in the damaged dentin tissue and facilitates mechanical reinforcement by functional remineralization. The proposed approach introduces a remineralization agent for the dentin and can augment the standard restorative protocol in dental procedures. This treatment restores the function of dentin through the recovery of the elastic modulus and hardness of the damaged tissue, thus facilitating repair through remineralization. In addition, the technology enables a special cement liner to deliver targeted and sustained mineralizing agents to repair and reverse caries in dentin. The final formulation will be developed by tuning bioactive compositions mixed with biomimetic compounds.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/09/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/09/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2033171</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Stefan</FirstName>
<LastName>Habelitz</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Stefan Habelitz</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[stefan.habelitz@ucsf.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000705948</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/09/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-San Francisco</Name>
<CityName>SAN FRANCISCO</CityName>
<ZipCode>941434249</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4154762977</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1855 FOLSOM ST STE 425</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>KMH5K9V7S518</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, SAN FRANCISCO, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-San Francisco]]></Name>
<CityName>San Francisco</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>941432210</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[707 Parnassus Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This NSF award explored new formulations of a dental cement to be used as a liner on the surface of a deep dental cavity. The cement releases poly-aspartic acid (pAsp), which has shown to be critical in the mineralization process of collagen, as it facilitates the formation of apatite within collagen fibrils through a process term the "Polymer-Induced Liquid Precursor (PILP)" process. Our novel cements are able to release pAsp and to remineralize significant portions of a caries lesion that has reached dentin. Through this award we improved the formulation of the dental cement by using calcium phosphate cements in combination with pAsp which made the cement more chemically stable compared to the previous version which relied on bioglass. Our solution showed significant repair through remineralization in dentin cavities with significant recovery of mineral and reduction in lesion size over time, which we disseminated in a recent publication: Babaie et al. J Dent 2021 Jun;109:103659.&nbsp;</p> <p>Primary goals of this project were to conduct interviews with dentists and to evaluate possible acceptance of product, while also exploring pathways of distribution of the product to dental offices. 100 interviews with dentists across the United States were conducted.</p> <p>According to our customer discovery surveys, we found out that independent general dentists want reduced chair time, reduced follow up visits while also maintaining the patient care in their office without having to refer outside, in order to increase the revenue and profitability of their office</p> <p>We quantified the value and confirmed our solution reduces the chair time by 30% for the independent general dentist who performs tooth restorations, mostly due to the different caries management and the minimal removal of the caries lesion that is part of our method.</p> <p>Furthermore, since our approach aims at extending the lifespan of the natural tooth, it is expected that even in the case of recurring caries, our approach will delay pulp exposure and possible root canal treatment very significantly. Thus referral to an endodontist will be delayed or may even be completely avoided, which was very attractive to the general dental practitioner. &nbsp;</p> <p>We also have identified channels to get our product to the customers. There are two ways for general dentists: a) direct from manufacturers or b) from distributors. Dentists will be made aware of the product by advertisement by the company through channels such as continuing education courses, magazines, tradeshows and scientific meetings and publications. The distributors get the standard 30% of revenue for dental devices with a two-years exclusivity.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/11/2022<br>      Modified by: Stefan&nbsp;Habelitz</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This NSF award explored new formulations of a dental cement to be used as a liner on the surface of a deep dental cavity. The cement releases poly-aspartic acid (pAsp), which has shown to be critical in the mineralization process of collagen, as it facilitates the formation of apatite within collagen fibrils through a process term the "Polymer-Induced Liquid Precursor (PILP)" process. Our novel cements are able to release pAsp and to remineralize significant portions of a caries lesion that has reached dentin. Through this award we improved the formulation of the dental cement by using calcium phosphate cements in combination with pAsp which made the cement more chemically stable compared to the previous version which relied on bioglass. Our solution showed significant repair through remineralization in dentin cavities with significant recovery of mineral and reduction in lesion size over time, which we disseminated in a recent publication: Babaie et al. J Dent 2021 Jun;109:103659.   Primary goals of this project were to conduct interviews with dentists and to evaluate possible acceptance of product, while also exploring pathways of distribution of the product to dental offices. 100 interviews with dentists across the United States were conducted.  According to our customer discovery surveys, we found out that independent general dentists want reduced chair time, reduced follow up visits while also maintaining the patient care in their office without having to refer outside, in order to increase the revenue and profitability of their office  We quantified the value and confirmed our solution reduces the chair time by 30% for the independent general dentist who performs tooth restorations, mostly due to the different caries management and the minimal removal of the caries lesion that is part of our method.  Furthermore, since our approach aims at extending the lifespan of the natural tooth, it is expected that even in the case of recurring caries, our approach will delay pulp exposure and possible root canal treatment very significantly. Thus referral to an endodontist will be delayed or may even be completely avoided, which was very attractive to the general dental practitioner.    We also have identified channels to get our product to the customers. There are two ways for general dentists: a) direct from manufacturers or b) from distributors. Dentists will be made aware of the product by advertisement by the company through channels such as continuing education courses, magazines, tradeshows and scientific meetings and publications. The distributors get the standard 30% of revenue for dental devices with a two-years exclusivity.          Last Modified: 03/11/2022       Submitted by: Stefan Habelitz]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
