<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Reimagined Virtual STEM Laboratory Experiences in Response to COVID-19 Pandemic Impacts on Undergraduate Education]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>197870.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>197870</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Michael Davis</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mdavis@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032920000</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[With support from the Improving Undergraduate STEM Education: Hispanic-Serving Institutions (HSI Program), this RAPID project will address critical instructional challenges in undergraduate STEM education that result from the COVID-19 pandemic.  Specifically, it will produce and deploy virtual labs in upper-division chemistry, physics, and math courses. The rush to online course delivery in response to COVID-19 has revealed limitations of commercially available online virtual labs. Existing virtual lab experiences are generally poorly focused on student exploration.  In addition, the effectiveness of virtual lab activities is not well understood, particularly for specific student populations such as Hispanic/Latinx students.  To address these opportunities, the California State University system will design three virtual labs that focus on community building, are culturally responsive, and relate to real life events brought about by the pandemic. The project will also study the effectiveness of these virtual labs, thus adding to the body of knowledge about effective online instruction.  The creation and delivery of the proposed labs have the potential to positively affect many students, as well as increase equitable access to high-quality learning opportunities. Beyond its immediate impact on improving online laboratory instruction in a time of crisis, this work may provide models for other STEM education initiatives and contribute to institutional and educational changes to better support STEM learning.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project aims to develop and test three virtual labs that are purposely designed to create and sustain a culture of inclusion and equity that supports the success of all students, particularly the large population of Hispanic/Latinx students served within the California State University system. The project seeks to increase opportunity and achievement by providing students with avenues to grow STEM identity, self-efficacy, and sense of belonging. The design criteria for the three virtual labs will be informed by culturally responsive and trauma-informed teaching practices. The virtual labs will support instruction across the California State University campuses and beyond, beginning as early as Fall 2020.  The overall goal is to directly improve students’ knowledge and ability, STEM identity, and integration of identities. The project plans to examine disciplinary best practices in student learning through an informed equity perspective. The project will investigate how to best implement culturally responsive and relevant teaching in virtual science and math laboratory environments and gather and analyze data about the shift to online teaching/learning modalities. Data will be collected every three months from students participating in the virtual labs via pre/post assessments to provide insight into the role of metacognition in their learning. Results of the research will be disseminated through peer-reviewed scholarship, virtual and face-to-face workshops, and reports. This RAPID award is made by the Hispanic-Serving Institutions Program in the Division of Undergraduate Education, Directorate of Education and Human Resources. The HSI Program aims to enhance undergraduate STEM education and build capacity at HSIs.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/01/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/29/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2033488</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Frank</FirstName>
<LastName>Gomez</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Frank A Gomez</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[fgomez@calstate.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000468452</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/01/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Gillespie</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David B Gillespie</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[blake.gillespie@csuci.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000073517</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/29/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>California State University Channel Islands</Name>
<CityName>CAMARILLO</CityName>
<ZipCode>930128599</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8054378808</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1 UNIVERSITY DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>26</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA26</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>FGK7C4BSUVK3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CALIFORNIA STATE UNIVERSITY, CHANNEL ISLANDS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>NUDGYLBB4S99</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[California State University, Channel Islands]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>930128559</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>26</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA26</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>077Y</Code>
<Text>HSI-Hispanic Serving Instituti</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>097Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Impacts on Existing Activities</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8209</Code>
<Text>Improv Undergrad STEM Ed(IUSE)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0420</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~197870</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Project Outcomes Report</strong></p> <p><strong>Award Title:&nbsp;</strong>RAPID: Reimagined Virtual STEM Laboratory Experiences in Response to COVID-19 Pandemic Impacts on Undergraduate Education</p> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p><strong>Federal Award ID:&nbsp;</strong>2033488</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>PI: Frank A. Gomez (California State University, Office of the Chancellor), co-PIs, Blake Gillespie (CSU Channel Islands), Sara Callori (CSU San Bernardino), Shirley Yap (CSU East Bay), Jane Lehr (Cal Poly San Luis Obispo)</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>In 2020, the California State University (CSU) Office of the Chancellor and CSU Channel Islands received a $197,780) RAPID award entitled<strong> &ldquo;</strong><strong>Reimagined Virtual STEM Laboratory Experiences in Response to COVID-19 Pandemic Impacts on Undergraduate Education&rdquo;.</strong> This project addressed critical instructional challenges in undergraduate STEM education that resulted from the COVID-19 pandemic. Specifically, its goal was to produce and deploy virtual labs in upper-division chemistry, physics, and math courses. Three exemplar virtual laboratory experiences were developed, implemented, and data collected at CSU San Bernardino, East Bay, and Cal Poly. The project provides the necessary foundation from which further virtual laboratories can be developed to meet the rapidly expanding needs of a diverse student population. The projects spanned the disciplines of chemistry, mathematics and physics. They not only integrated student learning, but dimensions of context, choice, affect, community, and equity that are cornerstones of sound pedagogy.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>At CSU East Bay online, interactive, data-intensive learning math modules, related to the coronavirus pandemic, were created. COVID-19 data (cases, deaths, hospitalizations, and economic, demographic data) was collected from a variety of repositories and obtained demographic information from the US census bureau. The data was used to generate a variety of 2D and 3D plots to model the data. A set of questions were then developed &ndash; many of which are explorative and open-ended, related to the graphs. At CSU San Bernardino, a student-designed laboratory project was implemented in several sections of Intermediate Lab, the upper division laboratory course generally taken by third-year physics majors. During the latter part of the course students worked in teams to select, design, and carry out an experimental investigation using easily accessible materials and free online and smartphone applications. At CSU Channel Islands, a current classic experiment (the Wittig experiment) already in the Chemistry Department&rsquo;s organic chemistry curriculum, was adapted.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Resources, lab experience, and course organization were common themes from the findings of the virtual STEM laboratory experiences. The students who indicated that they needed more technical resources voiced that they felt discouraged about their technical abilities as they had no prior experience working with data analysis using Python or Excel in the capacity that it was being done in this course. All students voiced a desire for an integrated calendar to view deadlines and shared that they experienced frustration keeping up with due dates and their schedule along with other courses due to virtual instruction and the lack of overall cohesiveness. For those completing a final project, students appreciated that they had ownership and choice. Minoritized students voiced the need for more support at a slightly higher rate than other students. All students voiced that the combination of virtual courses and personal stressors made their experiences in classes and beyond more difficult.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>While the outcomes are mixed, the work provides insight into the impact of virtual laboratory experiences on student learning, their attitudes, choice, and performance. This work will serve as a foundation for future educators when developing virtual experiences for students.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/29/2022<br>      Modified by: Frank&nbsp;A&nbsp;Gomez</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Project Outcomes Report  Award Title: RAPID: Reimagined Virtual STEM Laboratory Experiences in Response to COVID-19 Pandemic Impacts on Undergraduate Education     Federal Award ID: 2033488     PI: Frank A. Gomez (California State University, Office of the Chancellor), co-PIs, Blake Gillespie (CSU Channel Islands), Sara Callori (CSU San Bernardino), Shirley Yap (CSU East Bay), Jane Lehr (Cal Poly San Luis Obispo)     In 2020, the California State University (CSU) Office of the Chancellor and CSU Channel Islands received a $197,780) RAPID award entitled "Reimagined Virtual STEM Laboratory Experiences in Response to COVID-19 Pandemic Impacts on Undergraduate Education". This project addressed critical instructional challenges in undergraduate STEM education that resulted from the COVID-19 pandemic. Specifically, its goal was to produce and deploy virtual labs in upper-division chemistry, physics, and math courses. Three exemplar virtual laboratory experiences were developed, implemented, and data collected at CSU San Bernardino, East Bay, and Cal Poly. The project provides the necessary foundation from which further virtual laboratories can be developed to meet the rapidly expanding needs of a diverse student population. The projects spanned the disciplines of chemistry, mathematics and physics. They not only integrated student learning, but dimensions of context, choice, affect, community, and equity that are cornerstones of sound pedagogy.     At CSU East Bay online, interactive, data-intensive learning math modules, related to the coronavirus pandemic, were created. COVID-19 data (cases, deaths, hospitalizations, and economic, demographic data) was collected from a variety of repositories and obtained demographic information from the US census bureau. The data was used to generate a variety of 2D and 3D plots to model the data. A set of questions were then developed &ndash; many of which are explorative and open-ended, related to the graphs. At CSU San Bernardino, a student-designed laboratory project was implemented in several sections of Intermediate Lab, the upper division laboratory course generally taken by third-year physics majors. During the latter part of the course students worked in teams to select, design, and carry out an experimental investigation using easily accessible materials and free online and smartphone applications. At CSU Channel Islands, a current classic experiment (the Wittig experiment) already in the Chemistry Department’s organic chemistry curriculum, was adapted.     Resources, lab experience, and course organization were common themes from the findings of the virtual STEM laboratory experiences. The students who indicated that they needed more technical resources voiced that they felt discouraged about their technical abilities as they had no prior experience working with data analysis using Python or Excel in the capacity that it was being done in this course. All students voiced a desire for an integrated calendar to view deadlines and shared that they experienced frustration keeping up with due dates and their schedule along with other courses due to virtual instruction and the lack of overall cohesiveness. For those completing a final project, students appreciated that they had ownership and choice. Minoritized students voiced the need for more support at a slightly higher rate than other students. All students voiced that the combination of virtual courses and personal stressors made their experiences in classes and beyond more difficult.     While the outcomes are mixed, the work provides insight into the impact of virtual laboratory experiences on student learning, their attitudes, choice, and performance. This work will serve as a foundation for future educators when developing virtual experiences for students.          Last Modified: 08/29/2022       Submitted by: Frank A Gomez]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
