<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Thermal Compression Device for Maintenance of Perioperative Normothermia]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>255713.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>255713</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Henry Ahn</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>hahn@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927069</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact and commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is to reduce the risk of patients experiencing a severe drop in body temperature during surgery, known as inadvertent perioperative hypothermia (IPH). In the United States, 57.5 million procedures are performed annually with significant risk of IPH and an estimated 22 million surgical patients develop clinical complications associated with IPH. IPH leads to increased wound infections, blood loss, cardiac problems, increased use of mechanical ventilation, and longer stays in hospital, contributing to 1 million excess inpatient days and $1.6 billion in yearly costs. The proposed technology will develop a novel device to prevent IPH, saving an estimated $2,000-$3,500 per patient or $1 billion.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project aims to create a body heat transfer model that accurately integrates the novel device with a tissue model of the lower limb. The resulting model will enable in silico evaluation of device performance (heat output), efficacy (heat transfer), and safety (burn risk) across a broad clinical setting (expanded surgical procedures and patient demographics). We will collect clinical data from a proof-of-concept feasibility study to create and validate a model.  Further simulation in support of prototype development efforts enable the optimization of critical parameters. Physical prototypes (including sub-components) will be developed and manufactured based on the optimized design. Prototypes will be evaluated for thermal performance under controlled bench-top tests, with empirical results compared to expected values generated by the model.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/24/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/24/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2034065</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jeffrey</FirstName>
<LastName>Thompson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jeffrey P Thompson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jeff@pattondesign.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000827841</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/24/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Flotherm Inc</Name>
<CityName>LOS ANGELES</CityName>
<ZipCode>900171950</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9182843544</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1100 WILSHIRE BLVD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[APT 2105]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>34</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA34</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>R9ATAM2N22L3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>FLOTHERM INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Flotherm Inc]]></Name>
<CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>900171916</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1100 Wilshire Blvd #2105]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>34</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA34</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5345</Code>
<Text>BIOMEDICAL ENGINEERING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~255713</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p id="docs-internal-guid-b87aabbb-7fff-3981-3e97-a5803f844060" style="line-height: 1.38; margin-top: 0pt; margin-bottom: 6pt;" dir="ltr"><span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Raleway,sans-serif; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">Supported by the NSF SBIR award, Flotherm has completed its Phase I objective in the creation of a body heat transfer model for lower limb thermal compression devices. Numerical simulation with the product enabled predictions evaluating the effects of size, shape, material selection, and positioning on the device's ability to transfer heat into targeted tissue areas of the lower limb. Model-driven development allowed the team to rapidly iterate on design concepts and identify a final concept with which we have now entered formal product development.</span></p> <p style="line-height: 1.38; margin-top: 12pt; margin-bottom: 12pt;" dir="ltr"><span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Raleway,sans-serif; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">Flotherm accomplished its technical goals in the SBIR Phase I project by completing four tasks critical to risk reduction of the thermal compression concept: A) development of a body-heat transfer model for numerical simulation of heat transfer from the device into the body, B) produced multiple prototype concepts (manufacture and test) based on model insights, C) completed a burn risk safety assessment identifying safe thermal dose from the product, and D) developed a robust patient temperature control algorithm using thermal dose safety thresholds.</span></p> <p style="line-height: 1.38; margin-top: 12pt; margin-bottom: 12pt;" dir="ltr"><span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Raleway,sans-serif; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">The reduced risk of the concept combined with improved functional performance from the final prototype provided Flotherm with a straightforward path to complete product development during Phase II. Our Phase I project outcomes affirm that the product will be a safe and effective solution for managing perioperative patient normothermia.</span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/16/2022<br>      Modified by: Jeffrey&nbsp;P&nbsp;Thompson</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[Supported by the NSF SBIR award, Flotherm has completed its Phase I objective in the creation of a body heat transfer model for lower limb thermal compression devices. Numerical simulation with the product enabled predictions evaluating the effects of size, shape, material selection, and positioning on the device's ability to transfer heat into targeted tissue areas of the lower limb. Model-driven development allowed the team to rapidly iterate on design concepts and identify a final concept with which we have now entered formal product development. Flotherm accomplished its technical goals in the SBIR Phase I project by completing four tasks critical to risk reduction of the thermal compression concept: A) development of a body-heat transfer model for numerical simulation of heat transfer from the device into the body, B) produced multiple prototype concepts (manufacture and test) based on model insights, C) completed a burn risk safety assessment identifying safe thermal dose from the product, and D) developed a robust patient temperature control algorithm using thermal dose safety thresholds. The reduced risk of the concept combined with improved functional performance from the final prototype provided Flotherm with a straightforward path to complete product development during Phase II. Our Phase I project outcomes affirm that the product will be a safe and effective solution for managing perioperative patient normothermia.       Last Modified: 09/16/2022       Submitted by: Jeffrey P Thompson]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
