<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I: Auto Pairing Direct to Cellular Telehealth Gateway for Improved COVID-19 Home Health Monitoring Adherence]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>255430.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>255430</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Muralidharan Nair</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mnair@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927059</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovative Research (SBIR) Phase I project includes the ability to eliminate two of the primary barriers in dealing with seniors and technology: user interfaces and internet availability. The  approach makes use of recent (2019) national network coverage for Narrow-Band Internet of Things (NB-IoT) enabling low power, low cost access for direct to cellular low bandwidth applications. The auto pairing direct to cellular gateway provides COVID-19 diagnosed patients with the capability to effectively monitor symptoms from home resulting in improved disease impact tracking and monitoring adherence while reducing hospital demand, disease spread, and system costs over current smart phone-based system. Current systems require lengthy user training and account setup as well as cumbersome measurement data transfers using an app during each reading. This currently challenging interface would be replaced with a single device requiring no set up or direct interaction with the user. The approach greatly simplifies and streamlines the disease related measurements while reducing the time and cost of getting devices provisioned and into the end users’ hands.  Although focused on COVID-19 monitoring, the technology also provides broad application for effective telemedicine adoption by seniors for chronic care monitoring. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovative Research (SBIR) Phase I project seeks to provide a solution which is more cost effective and enables greater adoption and compliance for long-term, in-home, self-monitoring of seniors and at-risk populations diagnosed with COVID-19. The research goals of this project include demonstrating an auto pairing direct to cellular device that meets the requirements for COVID-19 monitoring under the global COVID-19 Emergency Response Solution. The research approach includes: demonstrating a design with optimized narrow band performance; demonstrating FCC/IC end unit certification; and demonstrating testing required for network certifications.  The anticipated technical results of this Phase I project enable smartphone-based monitoring systems and a gateway into senior populations for chronic care monitoring.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/21/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/21/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2034020</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Fitch</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John E Fitch</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[john.fitch@birkelandcurrent.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000594165</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/21/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Birkeland Current LLC</Name>
<CityName>WACO</CityName>
<ZipCode>767043024</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2547321537</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>100 RESEARCH PKWY</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[#3285]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>V1CLA4KM5WA5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>BIRKELAND CURRENT LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Birkeland Current LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>Waco</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>767043024</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[100 Research Parkway, Ste. 2265]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>4080</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED COMP RESEARCH PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>Health Care Enterprise Systems</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8033</Code>
<Text>Hardware Software Integration</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~255430</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This award resulted in the development of an auto pairing direct to cellular medical device data system (MDDS) which is now available for commercialization in support of improved home health monitoring care plan adherence.&nbsp; The device provides a direct connection to home health monitoring devices without the need for indivdual interaction to capture or transfer readings.&nbsp; For certain populations that lack technology skills or access to internet options, this device enables home heath monitoring that may not have been possible otherwise.&nbsp; Orignially intended to simplify Covid-19 recovery monitoring in senior and rural populations, this device has secondary applications supporting in-home chronic care managment.&nbsp; A third societal benefit has been identified which reduces the need for in home and assisted living health workers by enabling self monitoring.&nbsp; Given the current gap in available home health workers, this may help to alleviate this societal need.&nbsp; The gateway device is fully certified for use on ATT networks with T-Mobile approvals pending and Verizon approvals expected later in 2022.&nbsp; Medical devices currently supported by the certified Gateway include IHealth Labs digital scales, blood pressure devices, digital thermometers, blood glucose monitors, and pulse oximeters. The intellectual merit includes the optimization of the cellular communication to make use of recently available nationwide Narrow Band Internet of Things (NBIoT) low bandwidth communications protocols.&nbsp; The Gateway is certified for both NBIoT and CATM1 communications.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/13/2022<br>      Modified by: John&nbsp;E&nbsp;Fitch</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This award resulted in the development of an auto pairing direct to cellular medical device data system (MDDS) which is now available for commercialization in support of improved home health monitoring care plan adherence.  The device provides a direct connection to home health monitoring devices without the need for indivdual interaction to capture or transfer readings.  For certain populations that lack technology skills or access to internet options, this device enables home heath monitoring that may not have been possible otherwise.  Orignially intended to simplify Covid-19 recovery monitoring in senior and rural populations, this device has secondary applications supporting in-home chronic care managment.  A third societal benefit has been identified which reduces the need for in home and assisted living health workers by enabling self monitoring.  Given the current gap in available home health workers, this may help to alleviate this societal need.  The gateway device is fully certified for use on ATT networks with T-Mobile approvals pending and Verizon approvals expected later in 2022.  Medical devices currently supported by the certified Gateway include IHealth Labs digital scales, blood pressure devices, digital thermometers, blood glucose monitors, and pulse oximeters. The intellectual merit includes the optimization of the cellular communication to make use of recently available nationwide Narrow Band Internet of Things (NBIoT) low bandwidth communications protocols.  The Gateway is certified for both NBIoT and CATM1 communications.        Last Modified: 03/13/2022       Submitted by: John E Fitch]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
