<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Catalyzing Electrochemical Data Sciences: Education and Research Opportunities Workshop]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>49967.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>49967</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Carole Read</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cread@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922418</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[A workshop, titled "Catalyzing Electrochemical Data Sciences: Education and Research Opportunities," will be held at the Spring 2021 Electrochemical Society (ECS) Meeting in Chicago, with contingencies for a potential virtual meeting.  The workshop will focus on data sciences for the electrochemical community.  A key objective will be to identify research priorities and strategies for promoting open electrochemical data repositories and software.  Such systems will accelerate research progress in electrochemical science and engineering. To assure a diversity of participation at the workshop, participants will be nominated by the steering committee and by relevant ECS Division Executive Committees. The two-day agenda includes a series of presentations on the creation and analysis of labeled datasets in electrochemical science and engineering.  The agenda also contains seminars on open source software of significance to the electrochemical community.  Discussions will be guided by steering committee participants, and a report on priorities and research gaps will be drafted by steering committee members. An associated educational activity, entitled Hackweek, will be aimed at the electrochemical software developer community through online teaching and project work.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Analysis, aggregation and use of different electrochemical datasets from multiple labs are limited by a lack of standardized file structures, a lack of data quality standards, and a lack of long-lived, scalable, and searchable open data repositories. Extensive dataset archives are critical to machine learning, statistical analysis methods, and validation and parameter estimation in physics-based modeling. The lack of such data slows progress in electrochemical fields. The objective of this workshop is to identify promising research directions in data science focused on providing accessible repositories of electrochemical data for the research community. This workshop will ascertain research gaps in the processes of storing and integrating big data in electrochemical research. Members of the steering committee will lead critical activities of the workshop including selecting participants and drafting the report. The workshop leaders have significant experience in educational and management aspects of the workshop as well as in research topics pertaining to data science.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/18/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/18/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2034796</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
<LastName>Schwartz</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>T</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Daniel T Schwartz</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[dts@u.washington.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000381503</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/18/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Beck</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David A Beck</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[dacb@uw.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000565805</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/18/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Washington</Name>
<CityName>SEATTLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>981951016</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2065434043</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4333 BROOKLYN AVE NE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>HD1WMN6945W6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF WASHINGTON</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Washington]]></Name>
<CityName>Seattle</CityName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>981951750</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4333 Brooklyn Ave NE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7644</Code>
<Text>EchemS-Electrochemical Systems</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~49967</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>The goal was to develop and host a workshop "Catalyzing Electrochemical Data Sciences: Education and Research Opportunities," at the Spring 2022 Electrochemical Society (ECS) Meeting in Vancouver. </span><span>Due to the major disruption of the COVID-19 pandemic <span>on university research and education</span>, we were unable to develop the workshop or an online alternative during the funded period, and all funds were returned to NSF.&nbsp; Nonetheless, <span>there remains an opportunity to coordinate research and  education across global research groups, set community data and software  standards, and build educational materials.</span> Electrochemical research remains a field dominated by a classic bench science model, where many distributed scholars generate datasets in their labs, analyze the data using proprietary or lab-specific software, and then disseminate results as peer reviewed publication. This model for distributed experimentation and dissemination has resulted in a dearth of well-labeled electrochemical datasets that can be reused, reanalyzed, and combined with data from several laboratories.&nbsp; Progress is being made in sub-fields of electrochemical science, for example, with the concept of a "Battery Data Genome" recently introduced. But data sharing is nascent, and without extensive well-labeled data, it is difficult to develop and validate new physics-based models, machine learning approaches, and statistical analysis methods. Likewise, the electrochemical research community has only a few examples of widely adopted open source software dedicated to their problems, which slows the pace that new models and analysis concepts can be assimilated in electrochemical science and engineering. <br /></span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/07/2023<br>      Modified by: Daniel&nbsp;T&nbsp;Schwartz</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The goal was to develop and host a workshop "Catalyzing Electrochemical Data Sciences: Education and Research Opportunities," at the Spring 2022 Electrochemical Society (ECS) Meeting in Vancouver. Due to the major disruption of the COVID-19 pandemic on university research and education, we were unable to develop the workshop or an online alternative during the funded period, and all funds were returned to NSF.  Nonetheless, there remains an opportunity to coordinate research and  education across global research groups, set community data and software  standards, and build educational materials. Electrochemical research remains a field dominated by a classic bench science model, where many distributed scholars generate datasets in their labs, analyze the data using proprietary or lab-specific software, and then disseminate results as peer reviewed publication. This model for distributed experimentation and dissemination has resulted in a dearth of well-labeled electrochemical datasets that can be reused, reanalyzed, and combined with data from several laboratories.  Progress is being made in sub-fields of electrochemical science, for example, with the concept of a "Battery Data Genome" recently introduced. But data sharing is nascent, and without extensive well-labeled data, it is difficult to develop and validate new physics-based models, machine learning approaches, and statistical analysis methods. Likewise, the electrochemical research community has only a few examples of widely adopted open source software dedicated to their problems, which slows the pace that new models and analysis concepts can be assimilated in electrochemical science and engineering.         Last Modified: 03/07/2023       Submitted by: Daniel T Schwartz]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
