<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID Collaborative Research: Mitigating the Impact of Forced Remote Learning of ECS Due to COVID-19]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>95196.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>95196</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jeffrey Forbes</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jforbes@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925301</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The Learning Partnership,  in collaboration with the Chicago Public Schools (CPS), and Education Development Center (EDC), will conduct research and develop teacher support programs that will mitigate the impact that the global COVID pandemic is having on high school computer science students in CPS. There are significant concerns that the variability in implementation of remote learning policies in response to COVID-19 school closures could exacerbate educational inequities in access and quality of experience for students taking Exploring Computer Science (ECS). These concerns are particularly acute in CPS where computer science is a graduation requirement and ECS is the primary course that students take to fulfill the requirement. Inequalities in access and implementation of computer science in CPS can have consequences for students’ high school graduation.  In order to develop effective teaching materials for the 2020-2021 academic year, the project team will study the overall impact of remote learning by comparing outcomes for the 2019-20 implementation of ECS in CPS relative to the previous three years of ECS implementation as well as whether inequities have emerged within CPS by examining differences in school plans for remote learning, student access to technology, participation in remote learning experiences by race and ethnicity and whether those differences correlate with differences in learning outcomes. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project extends the work of the Chicago Alliance for Equity in Computer Science (CAFECS), a long-standing partnership between university computer science faculty, educational researchers, and CPS teachers and administrators,  to ensure that all CPS high school students engage in high quality, engaging computer science education.  CAFECS will develop strategies develop strategies on how to emulate effective high-touch teacher facilitation strategies online from their experience with face-to-face classrooms. The project will be guided by three research questions: (1) How can we design online professional development to support ECS teachers’ transition to teach the course fully or partially online during the 2020-21 school year? (2) How can the CAFÉCS coaching model be adapted to support teachers in moving ECS to a remote learning format and to provide remote coaching when school access is restricted? (3) What are the characteristics of remote learning policies that foster student engagement and best support student online collaboration? The teacher professional development model will be guided by the Desimone and Garet framework to provide a structure for drawing conclusions about the contribution of the professional development in mitigating the impact COVID-19 school building closures have on student outcomes.  The results of this research will have a direct impact on hundreds of CPS teachers and, ultimately, thousands of CPS high school students. The results will significantly contribute to the knowledge base of how to effectively teach computer science for underserved students in computer science and how schools can mitigate the impacts of COVID-19.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/08/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/08/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2034145</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Steven</FirstName>
<LastName>McGee</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Steven M McGee</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mcgee@lponline.net]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000277387</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/08/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>The Learning Partnership</Name>
<CityName>WESTERN SPRINGS</CityName>
<ZipCode>605581522</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7087105963</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4617 WOLF RD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>DA9LBJCRS8F3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>LEARNING PARTNERSHIP LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[The Learning Partnership]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>605581522</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>158Y</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>1N20</Code>
<Name>R&amp;RA CARES Act DEFC N</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>010N2021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[R&RA CARES Act DEFC N]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~95196</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-1701fe87-7fff-6700-ab7f-d29dc8cf1a9f"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The COVID-19 pandemic caused an unprecedented closure of K-12 school buildings across the United States and introduced uncertainty on the modality of instruction for the 2020-21 and 2021-2022 school years. The policies for addressing remote learning in the context of school closures varied across states as well as among schools within each state. There were significant concerns that these remote learning policies in response to COVID-19 school closures could exacerbate educational inequities in access and quality of experience for computer science students. These concerns were particularly acute in the Chicago Public Schools (CPS) where computer science (CS) is a graduation requirement. Inequalities in access to and implementation of CS in CPS can have consequences for students&rsquo; high school graduation.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The goal of this RAPID project was to inform strategies to immediately mitigate the impact of this global challenge on school children. </span><span>The </span><span>Chicago Alliance for Equity in Computer Science (CAF&Eacute;CS), a long-standing partnership between university computer science faculty, educational researchers, and CPS teachers and administrators, </span><span>designed a series of professional development (PD) workshops for teachers, a coaching model with various one-on-one and group coaching options, and a professional learning community (PLC) to build coaches&rsquo; capacities to support teachers during the pandemic.&nbsp;</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The project was guided by three research questions:</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>1. </span><span><span> </span></span><span>How can we design online professional development to support ECS teachers&rsquo; transition to teach the course fully or partially online during the 2020-21 school year?&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>2. </span><span><span> </span></span><span>How can the CAF&Eacute;CS coaching model be adapted to support teachers in moving ECS to a remote learning format and to provide remote coaching when school access is restricted?&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>3. </span><span><span> </span></span><span>What was the impact of remote learning on student outcomes in ECS?&nbsp;</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><strong>Broader Impacts</strong></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Drawing on qualitative data, we analyzed instructional coaches&rsquo; and teachers&rsquo; experiences with remote PD during COVID-19. The instructional coaching team designed PD workshops and coaching structures around key ECS instructional strategies and prioritized teachers&rsquo; emotional needs throughout the pandemic-impacted school year. To understand the impact of these professional learning opportunities on instructional coaching and teaching in the remote context, we analyzed several sources of qualitative data, including PLC meeting notes, teacher interviews and focus groups, and teacher feedback surveys. We found that the instructional coaching team designed professional development workshops and coaching structures around key instructional strategies and made efforts to address teachers&rsquo; emotional needs. Teachers reported that focusing on key instructional strategies helped (re)ground them in the ECS framework and build community with and among students in the remote environment. Teachers also expressed feeling emotionally supported by their coaches and gaining a sense of community with other CS teachers throughout workshops and group coaching models. While more research is needed to understand the full effect of remote instruction on CS instructional coaching, teaching, and learning, our findings highlight the importance of devising instructional coaching and professional development models that are responsive to teachers&rsquo; different needs and allowing instructional coaches to continually reflect on their own practice.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Drawing on quantitative data, we compared performance on the ECS end of course assessment between the last complete school year before the pandemic (2018-19) and the first full year of the pandemic (2020-21). After controlling for student-level and teacher-level factors, students performed about 1 point less (on a scale of 25 points) on the posttest than students prior to the pandemic. The pandemic also negatively affected students&rsquo; perceptions of expectancy of success in ECS, which in turn correlated with student posttest performance. There was no statistically significant main effect difference in posttest performance by gender or race/ethnicity nor was there an interaction of gender and race/ethnicity by pandemic year. In other words, there was not a differential impact of the pandemic on posttest performance by gender or race/ethnicity. There was not a direct effect of the Next PD on student posttest performance.&nbsp; However, there was an indirect effect of ECS professional development on student posttest performance. Teachers who had participated in the ECS professional development program reduced the impact of the pandemic on students&rsquo; perceptions of expectancy of success.&nbsp; Although there was not a direct or indirect effect of the Next PD on student posttest performance in the pandemic year, the fact that the Next PD (re)grounded teachers in the ECS framework learned in the ECS PD points to the potentially longer-term benefits of the Next PD.</span></p> <p><strong>Intellectual Merit</strong></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Our findings add to the literature on effective professional development by showing what professional development structures and practices best support teachers in times of crisis. Specifically, this research points to the need to account for the humanistic side of professional development, as both teachers and instructional coaches discussed the importance of providing and receiving emotional &ndash; in addition to instructional &ndash; support.</span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/08/2022<br>      Modified by: Steven&nbsp;M&nbsp;Mcgee</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   The COVID-19 pandemic caused an unprecedented closure of K-12 school buildings across the United States and introduced uncertainty on the modality of instruction for the 2020-21 and 2021-2022 school years. The policies for addressing remote learning in the context of school closures varied across states as well as among schools within each state. There were significant concerns that these remote learning policies in response to COVID-19 school closures could exacerbate educational inequities in access and quality of experience for computer science students. These concerns were particularly acute in the Chicago Public Schools (CPS) where computer science (CS) is a graduation requirement. Inequalities in access to and implementation of CS in CPS can have consequences for students’ high school graduation. The goal of this RAPID project was to inform strategies to immediately mitigate the impact of this global challenge on school children. The Chicago Alliance for Equity in Computer Science (CAF&Eacute;CS), a long-standing partnership between university computer science faculty, educational researchers, and CPS teachers and administrators, designed a series of professional development (PD) workshops for teachers, a coaching model with various one-on-one and group coaching options, and a professional learning community (PLC) to build coaches’ capacities to support teachers during the pandemic.     The project was guided by three research questions: 1.  How can we design online professional development to support ECS teachers’ transition to teach the course fully or partially online during the 2020-21 school year?  2.  How can the CAF&Eacute;CS coaching model be adapted to support teachers in moving ECS to a remote learning format and to provide remote coaching when school access is restricted?  3.  What was the impact of remote learning on student outcomes in ECS?     Broader Impacts Drawing on qualitative data, we analyzed instructional coaches’ and teachers’ experiences with remote PD during COVID-19. The instructional coaching team designed PD workshops and coaching structures around key ECS instructional strategies and prioritized teachers’ emotional needs throughout the pandemic-impacted school year. To understand the impact of these professional learning opportunities on instructional coaching and teaching in the remote context, we analyzed several sources of qualitative data, including PLC meeting notes, teacher interviews and focus groups, and teacher feedback surveys. We found that the instructional coaching team designed professional development workshops and coaching structures around key instructional strategies and made efforts to address teachers’ emotional needs. Teachers reported that focusing on key instructional strategies helped (re)ground them in the ECS framework and build community with and among students in the remote environment. Teachers also expressed feeling emotionally supported by their coaches and gaining a sense of community with other CS teachers throughout workshops and group coaching models. While more research is needed to understand the full effect of remote instruction on CS instructional coaching, teaching, and learning, our findings highlight the importance of devising instructional coaching and professional development models that are responsive to teachers’ different needs and allowing instructional coaches to continually reflect on their own practice. Drawing on quantitative data, we compared performance on the ECS end of course assessment between the last complete school year before the pandemic (2018-19) and the first full year of the pandemic (2020-21). After controlling for student-level and teacher-level factors, students performed about 1 point less (on a scale of 25 points) on the posttest than students prior to the pandemic. The pandemic also negatively affected students’ perceptions of expectancy of success in ECS, which in turn correlated with student posttest performance. There was no statistically significant main effect difference in posttest performance by gender or race/ethnicity nor was there an interaction of gender and race/ethnicity by pandemic year. In other words, there was not a differential impact of the pandemic on posttest performance by gender or race/ethnicity. There was not a direct effect of the Next PD on student posttest performance.  However, there was an indirect effect of ECS professional development on student posttest performance. Teachers who had participated in the ECS professional development program reduced the impact of the pandemic on students’ perceptions of expectancy of success.  Although there was not a direct or indirect effect of the Next PD on student posttest performance in the pandemic year, the fact that the Next PD (re)grounded teachers in the ECS framework learned in the ECS PD points to the potentially longer-term benefits of the Next PD.  Intellectual Merit Our findings add to the literature on effective professional development by showing what professional development structures and practices best support teachers in times of crisis. Specifically, this research points to the need to account for the humanistic side of professional development, as both teachers and instructional coaches discussed the importance of providing and receiving emotional &ndash; in addition to instructional &ndash; support.       Last Modified: 11/08/2022       Submitted by: Steven M Mcgee]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
