<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Doctoral Dissertation Improvement Award: Variable Household Use of Space]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>11/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>29400.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>29400</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>John Yellen</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jyellen@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928759</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Researchers have long been interested in understanding how culture changes over time.  Understanding one particular type of cultural shift, the creation and perpetuation of social inequality, is particularly pertinent to modern-day social realities. This project builds on previous ethnographic and archaeological research into how complex fisher-hunter-gatherer groups shift from an egalitarian to a non-egalitarian society. Understanding the expression and experience of such social change by members of households is the primary focus of this research. How might a society go from a cultural ethos of sharing access to resources to one promoting restricted access? How is access to resources and power defined and who is included (or not included)? This research investigates these questions by analyzing changes in household-based interactions to unravel the roles gender, kinship, and agency play in defining access to power and resources within an emerging social hierarchy.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This doctoral dissertation project examines previously collected material from a site which contains a sequence of 15 anthropogenic floors.  The researchers will conduct new macrobotanical analyses and examine lithic artifacts from four occupations using a wide array of cutting-edge analytical techniques (geo-chemical sourcing, residue studies, and ancient DNA analysis) to understand what types of activities constituted social identities during different times within the housepit.  Spatial and statistical analysis of these data will be used to understand, reconstruct, and interpret changes in past household interactions over time.  This research will thus create new frameworks for understanding the interplay between social identity and the emergence of institutionalized inequality at the household level.  The research will actively include First Nation perspectives and cultural knowledge to interpret and contribute to ongoing public memory projects in the region.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/02/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/02/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2034651</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Anna</FirstName>
<LastName>Prentiss</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Anna M Prentiss</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[anna.prentiss@umontana.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000263893</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/02/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ashley</FirstName>
<LastName>Hampton</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ashley E Hampton</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ashley.hampton@umontana.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000815100</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/02/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Montana</Name>
<CityName>MISSOULA</CityName>
<ZipCode>598120003</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4062436670</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>32 CAMPUS DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Montana</StateName>
<StateCode>MT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MT01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>DAY7Z8ZD48Q3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MONTANA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Montana]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>MT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>598120001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Montana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MT01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7606</Code>
<Text>Archaeology DDRI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1391</Code>
<Text>ARCHAEOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~29400</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The NSF-funded project Doctoral Dissertation Improvement Grant "Variable Household Use of Space" (NSF-BCS DDRI # 2034651, PI Prentiss, co-PI Hampton) used spatial and statistical analysis to examine change and continuity across four occupational floors from Housepit 54 located at the Bridge River site (<em>K'etxelkna'z</em>), British Columbia, Canada.&nbsp; The pithouse village site is located in the traditional territory of the interior Salish-speaking St<em>'</em>at'imc, situated near the confluence of the Bridge and Fraser rivers within the Mid-Fraser Canyon and consists of over 80 housepits that date from 1800 cal. BP to 145 cal BP.&nbsp; The Bridge River site (<em>K'etxelkna'z</em>) is composed of four occupationally distinct time periods, noted as Bridge River (BR) 1 ca. 1800-1600 cal. BP, BR 2 ca. 1600-1300 cal. BP, BR 3 ca. 1300-1000 cal. BP, and BR 4 ca. 600/800-145 cal. BP.&nbsp; During BR 1 and BR2, there was a slow village expansion followed by the emergence of circular "neighborhoods" during BR 3.&nbsp; Between BR 2 and BR 3 occupations, the site reached a population of at least 30 occupied houses during a time of marine resource productivity and increasing inter-household wealth inequality.&nbsp; By the end of BR3, climatic variability and declining resources contributed to a period of abandonment until reoccupation during BR 4 though the overall number of occupied pithouses was fairly low and no longer formed the previously established neighborhoods.&nbsp;</p> <p>Housepit 54 was one of the few pithouses with almost continual occupation throughout the BR 2 to BR 4 time periods and includes 15 occupational floors spanning the BR 2 to BR 3 time periods.&nbsp; Each occupational floor in Housepit 54 is designated as Stratum II followed by a letter corresponding to the floor?s position in the overall floor sequence.&nbsp; Seven occupational floors date to the BR 2 time period (IIo-IIi) and seven occupational floors date to the BR 3 time period (IIg-IIa) with the IIh floor being a transitional occupation.&nbsp; This project examined four floors (IId, IIe, IIh, IIL) to understand how household use of space embodied social-identity and cultural change, testing three hypotheses about the nature of the emergence of inequality.</p> <p>This project sheds light on the interplay between the division of household labor, kinship connections, and individual agency in access to prestige over time.&nbsp; Understanding how these mechanisms influence household use of space helps us better explain and examine variation in archaeological assemblages.&nbsp; Each floor was examined for evidence of spatial division of labor around individual hearths, variation in raw material sources associated with tool use/production, and variation in food material.&nbsp; Utilizing funding from the National Science Foundation, collaborative teams analyzed botanical material to recreate subsistence practices, sourced raw material to understand landscape access and kinship networks, and extracted animal/plant ancient DNA from stone tools to understand variation in uses of different tool forms.</p> <p>Based on analysis of these data, access to prestige items, as they became more restricted to specific locations/households per floor, was not connected to the prevalence of a certain type of labor (such as hide-working or tool production) nor one type of kinship network as captured by restricted access to nonlocal raw material.&nbsp; If past social identities were tied to resource-extraction activities (for instance, hunting individuals have identities based around their hunting practices, gathering individuals have identities based around their gathering practices) then prestige access is not clearly aligned with a social identity before or after subsistence shifts from low intensities of salmon/deer to higher intensities of salmon processing or the spatial re-arrangement of plant processing locations.&nbsp; If social identities were more tired/defined by kinship networks represented through access to particular nonlocal raw material, then access to prestige does not appear to be correlated to these raw material sources.&nbsp;</p> <p>Access to prestige appears to not be tied to these individualized aspects of social identity but rather to household-level identities, where regardless of gender or kinship connections, certain households are able to obtain higher status/prestige compared to other households.&nbsp; A households? ability to obtain high-quality subsistence foods is consistent with a particular household having access to prestige items, especially as resource scarcity increased during BR 3, indicating the ability to procure, store, and redistribute food resources is a primary influencer in how inequality emerged.</p> <p>Understanding what mechanisms of social distinction in the past functioned as justification for unequal access to particular material goods is essential to understanding current manifestations of inequality.&nbsp; By finding labor to be uncorrelated to prestige material, this research demonstrates how the emergence of inequality may inherently be tied to some form of inheritable social qualities, in this case, long-term membership within Housepit 54.&nbsp; This project was able to explore nuances in the fine-grained spatial distribution of raw material, artifacts, and subsistence material and provides promising new avenues for future examinations of the emergence of inequality.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/10/2023<br>      Modified by: Ashley&nbsp;E&nbsp;Hampton</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The NSF-funded project Doctoral Dissertation Improvement Grant "Variable Household Use of Space" (NSF-BCS DDRI # 2034651, PI Prentiss, co-PI Hampton) used spatial and statistical analysis to examine change and continuity across four occupational floors from Housepit 54 located at the Bridge River site (K'etxelkna'z), British Columbia, Canada.  The pithouse village site is located in the traditional territory of the interior Salish-speaking St'at'imc, situated near the confluence of the Bridge and Fraser rivers within the Mid-Fraser Canyon and consists of over 80 housepits that date from 1800 cal. BP to 145 cal BP.  The Bridge River site (K'etxelkna'z) is composed of four occupationally distinct time periods, noted as Bridge River (BR) 1 ca. 1800-1600 cal. BP, BR 2 ca. 1600-1300 cal. BP, BR 3 ca. 1300-1000 cal. BP, and BR 4 ca. 600/800-145 cal. BP.  During BR 1 and BR2, there was a slow village expansion followed by the emergence of circular "neighborhoods" during BR 3.  Between BR 2 and BR 3 occupations, the site reached a population of at least 30 occupied houses during a time of marine resource productivity and increasing inter-household wealth inequality.  By the end of BR3, climatic variability and declining resources contributed to a period of abandonment until reoccupation during BR 4 though the overall number of occupied pithouses was fairly low and no longer formed the previously established neighborhoods.   Housepit 54 was one of the few pithouses with almost continual occupation throughout the BR 2 to BR 4 time periods and includes 15 occupational floors spanning the BR 2 to BR 3 time periods.  Each occupational floor in Housepit 54 is designated as Stratum II followed by a letter corresponding to the floor?s position in the overall floor sequence.  Seven occupational floors date to the BR 2 time period (IIo-IIi) and seven occupational floors date to the BR 3 time period (IIg-IIa) with the IIh floor being a transitional occupation.  This project examined four floors (IId, IIe, IIh, IIL) to understand how household use of space embodied social-identity and cultural change, testing three hypotheses about the nature of the emergence of inequality.  This project sheds light on the interplay between the division of household labor, kinship connections, and individual agency in access to prestige over time.  Understanding how these mechanisms influence household use of space helps us better explain and examine variation in archaeological assemblages.  Each floor was examined for evidence of spatial division of labor around individual hearths, variation in raw material sources associated with tool use/production, and variation in food material.  Utilizing funding from the National Science Foundation, collaborative teams analyzed botanical material to recreate subsistence practices, sourced raw material to understand landscape access and kinship networks, and extracted animal/plant ancient DNA from stone tools to understand variation in uses of different tool forms.  Based on analysis of these data, access to prestige items, as they became more restricted to specific locations/households per floor, was not connected to the prevalence of a certain type of labor (such as hide-working or tool production) nor one type of kinship network as captured by restricted access to nonlocal raw material.  If past social identities were tied to resource-extraction activities (for instance, hunting individuals have identities based around their hunting practices, gathering individuals have identities based around their gathering practices) then prestige access is not clearly aligned with a social identity before or after subsistence shifts from low intensities of salmon/deer to higher intensities of salmon processing or the spatial re-arrangement of plant processing locations.  If social identities were more tired/defined by kinship networks represented through access to particular nonlocal raw material, then access to prestige does not appear to be correlated to these raw material sources.   Access to prestige appears to not be tied to these individualized aspects of social identity but rather to household-level identities, where regardless of gender or kinship connections, certain households are able to obtain higher status/prestige compared to other households.  A households? ability to obtain high-quality subsistence foods is consistent with a particular household having access to prestige items, especially as resource scarcity increased during BR 3, indicating the ability to procure, store, and redistribute food resources is a primary influencer in how inequality emerged.  Understanding what mechanisms of social distinction in the past functioned as justification for unequal access to particular material goods is essential to understanding current manifestations of inequality.  By finding labor to be uncorrelated to prestige material, this research demonstrates how the emergence of inequality may inherently be tied to some form of inheritable social qualities, in this case, long-term membership within Housepit 54.  This project was able to explore nuances in the fine-grained spatial distribution of raw material, artifacts, and subsistence material and provides promising new avenues for future examinations of the emergence of inequality.         Last Modified: 07/10/2023       Submitted by: Ashley E Hampton]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
