<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID:  Characterization of the shear stress enhanced electric field gradients in MOF/Polymers composite thin films and multilayered fibers.]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>200000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>211867</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Birgit Schwenzer</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bschwenz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924771</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Non-technical Summary: This RAPID project, supported by the Solid State and Materials Chemistry Program in the Division of Materials Research, is focused on fundamental investigations, aimed at advancing our knowledge about materials with nanoscale-level filtration capabilities that have possible applications in the development of longer lasting respirators with increased ease-of-wear. This type of research has become necessary due to the current coronavirus (COVID-19) pandemic, of which the loss of lives, reduced financial livelihoods and reduced quality of lives are just a few of the already manifested consequences. In order to regain safe living and working environments, one of the main things needed is personal protective equipment such as facemasks and respirators. Unfortunately, there are worldwide shortages which have resulted in excessive reuse of these protective equipment, oftentimes to the detriment of not only the wearer, but others. Additionally, respirators are also uncomfortable to wear for most people, due to the inherent large pressure gradients and relatively low water vapor transmission. This project provides researchers in academia and industries involved in the development and application of filtration media with specific tuning procedures, which will in turn advance the welfare of society through improvements in our health, living and environmental conditions. Beyond personal protective equipment, the benefits of better nanoscale filtration media also extend to applications including water membrane treatments, nanoreactors, and chemical catalysis. The project involves the participation of students from various socioeconomic and education levels, and because of its interdisciplinary nature, they gain the knowledge and research experience involving aspects of chemistry, engineering, physics and material science.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical Summary: With support from the Solid State and Materials Chemistry Program in the Division of Materials Research, this RAPID research project focuses on fundamentally characterizing the variable shear stress enhanced local electric field gradients in composite polymers/metal organic frameworks (MOFs) thin films, and multilayered electrospun fibrous materials. The principal investigator and her research group study whether materials that have greater electric fields gradients (EFGs) exhibit superior filtration/adsorption properties. Generally, the filtration properties of composite polymers can be tuned by modification of their surface morphology (diameter, surface roughness, etc.) and one way to accomplish this is by the incorporation of MOFs. To further increase nano-filtration properties, the electrostatic characteristics must be enhanced, and this project accomplishes this by the directional alignment and enhancement of the local electric field gradients using variable sheer stresses. Multinuclear (1H, 2H, and 17O) Magnetic Resonance (NMR) and Scanning Electron Microscopy (SEM) provide information about the local interactions between the various polymers, as well as between the MOFs and the polymers. Information about the electric field gradients is accessed through the quadrupole 2H and 17O nuclei and their magnitudes correlated with the degree of shear stress applied. Polymer type, crystallinity and morphology are also investigated, along with different MOF types and content as well as the order of layering used to construct the multilayered fibrous composites.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/18/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/05/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2034643</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sophia</FirstName>
<LastName>Suarez</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sophia Suarez</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[SNSuarez@brooklyn.cuny.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000587628</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/18/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>CUNY Brooklyn College</Name>
<CityName>BROOKLYN</CityName>
<ZipCode>112102850</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7189515622</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2900 BEDFORD AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>XNAKYW3FTSE1</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH FOUNDATION OF THE CITY UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[CUNY Brooklyn College]]></Name>
<CityName>Brooklyn</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>112102889</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2900 Bedford Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1253</Code>
<Text>OFFICE OF MULTIDISCIPLINARY AC</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1762</Code>
<Text>SOLID STATE &amp; MATERIALS CHEMIS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8614</Code>
<Text>Nanomaterials</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002223DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~200000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2022~11867</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Summary</strong>: The&nbsp;<strong>main objectives</strong>&nbsp;of this project were to characterize the various interactions (MOF-polymer, polymer-polymer, etc.) in electrospun polymer fibers and thin films. In this project, we synthesized various polymer solutions, as well as mixtures of individual polymers, polymer blends and composites comprised of nanoparticles, which were then electrospun to create fibers and thin films. These materials were designed with filtration applications and various variables of interest were investigated, all for the purpose of effecting the fiber or thin film pore size and resulting filtration characteristics. For example, the type of nanoparticle (size, shape, etc.), and the polymer (molecular weight, crystallinity, etc.).&nbsp;&nbsp;Outside of these, additional tuning can be accomplished through the resulting composite&rsquo;s characteristics (component concentrations, polymer-nanoparticle interactions, etc.).&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;Our&nbsp;<strong><em>hypothesis</em></strong>&nbsp;was that materials having greater microscopic electric fields gradients (EFGs) will have smaller pore diameters, ergo better filtration adsorption properties. To investigate our hypothesis,&nbsp;we will apply quantifiable variable sheer stresses to the composite materials and determine their corresponding EFGs.</p> <p>What was accomplished:</p> <p><em>1. We purchased the electrospinner and spent time modifying the equipment to ensure&nbsp;</em><em>moisture free environment during the electrospinning of materials.</em></p> <p><em>2. We synthesized the ZIF-8 and ZIF-67 MOFs with both in a 1% w/w proportion&nbsp;</em><em>relative to a polymer and DMF or 1-Propanol solution. We also synthesized various&nbsp;</em><em>polymer solutions and tested the appropriateness of various dissolution solvents.</em></p> <p><em>3. We successfully electrospun various polymers, polymer blends and polymer&nbsp;</em><em>composites. The polymers used included Polyacrylonitrile (PAN), Polyvinyl Chloride&nbsp;</em><em>(PVC), Polystyrene (PS), Polyvinylpyrrolidone (PVP), polyvinylidene difluoride&nbsp;</em><em>hexafluoropropylene (PVDF-HFP), and others.</em></p> <p><em>4. We performed 1H and 13C solid state NMR studies including MAS and HETCOR on&nbsp;</em><em>selected materials.</em></p> <p><em>5.&nbsp;</em><em>We also explored incorporating various ionic liquids (ILs) and deep eutectic solvents </em><em>(DESs) into the polymer solutions to electrospin these composites.</em></p> <p><em>6. Through a successful user proposal submitted in 2022, we were able to get SEM&nbsp;</em><em>micrographs of selected electrospun materials at the Center for Functional&nbsp;</em><em>Nanomaterials (CFN) at Brookhaven National Laboratory (BNL).</em></p> <p><em>7. We trained three undergraduates, one graduate and five high school students the&nbsp;</em><em>process of electrospinning, thin film battery assembly and testing, cyclic voltammetry,&nbsp;</em><em>electrochemistry. Some also learned NMR and SEM.</em></p> <p><em><br /></em></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/10/2023<br>      Modified by: Sophia&nbsp;Suarez</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Summary: The main objectives of this project were to characterize the various interactions (MOF-polymer, polymer-polymer, etc.) in electrospun polymer fibers and thin films. In this project, we synthesized various polymer solutions, as well as mixtures of individual polymers, polymer blends and composites comprised of nanoparticles, which were then electrospun to create fibers and thin films. These materials were designed with filtration applications and various variables of interest were investigated, all for the purpose of effecting the fiber or thin film pore size and resulting filtration characteristics. For example, the type of nanoparticle (size, shape, etc.), and the polymer (molecular weight, crystallinity, etc.).  Outside of these, additional tuning can be accomplished through the resulting composite’s characteristics (component concentrations, polymer-nanoparticle interactions, etc.).    Our hypothesis was that materials having greater microscopic electric fields gradients (EFGs) will have smaller pore diameters, ergo better filtration adsorption properties. To investigate our hypothesis, we will apply quantifiable variable sheer stresses to the composite materials and determine their corresponding EFGs.  What was accomplished:  1. We purchased the electrospinner and spent time modifying the equipment to ensure moisture free environment during the electrospinning of materials.  2. We synthesized the ZIF-8 and ZIF-67 MOFs with both in a 1% w/w proportion relative to a polymer and DMF or 1-Propanol solution. We also synthesized various polymer solutions and tested the appropriateness of various dissolution solvents.  3. We successfully electrospun various polymers, polymer blends and polymer composites. The polymers used included Polyacrylonitrile (PAN), Polyvinyl Chloride (PVC), Polystyrene (PS), Polyvinylpyrrolidone (PVP), polyvinylidene difluoride hexafluoropropylene (PVDF-HFP), and others.  4. We performed 1H and 13C solid state NMR studies including MAS and HETCOR on selected materials.  5. We also explored incorporating various ionic liquids (ILs) and deep eutectic solvents (DESs) into the polymer solutions to electrospin these composites.  6. Through a successful user proposal submitted in 2022, we were able to get SEM micrographs of selected electrospun materials at the Center for Functional Nanomaterials (CFN) at Brookhaven National Laboratory (BNL).  7. We trained three undergraduates, one graduate and five high school students the process of electrospinning, thin film battery assembly and testing, cyclic voltammetry, electrochemistry. Some also learned NMR and SEM.                   Last Modified: 09/10/2023       Submitted by: Sophia Suarez]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
