<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[EAGER: Stable iRNA Vectors for Production of Proteins in Pumpkin Sap]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>300000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>300000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>MCB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Manju Hingorani</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mhingora@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927323</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The project tackles the ongoing need to develop new technology for rapid, large-scale and cost-effective production of therapeutic peptides/proteins such as vaccines – now made even more acute by the COVID-19 pandemic. Using plants to produce biological products offers advantages of speed, low cost and low toxicity, but also disadvantages of low yields and complex purification processes. The PI will investigate a novel RNA vector for molecular determinants of stability that can hinder protein expression, and develop pumpkin as a host for producing large amounts of proteins encoded by this RNA vector. Overcoming hurdles to vaccine production in plants has potential for immense broader impact. The project also offers research training and career development opportunities to a post-doctoral scholar.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research builds on substantive preliminary data indicating that a novel virus-like RNA vector (CYVaV) can be manipulated to control its stability and related properties in host plants. The PI’s team plans to modify CYVaV RNA sequence and secondary structure with the goal of optimizing stable versions of the vector for over-expression of engineered proteins in host plants. Development of a vector platform that can serve to infect a variety of plants for large-scale production of biologics will have broad biotechnological and biomedical applications.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is funded by the Genetic Mechanisms cluster in the Division of Molecular and Cellular Biosciences.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/09/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/09/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2034359</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Anne</FirstName>
<LastName>Simon</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Anne E Simon</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[simona@umd.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000451829</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/09/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Maryland, College Park</Name>
<CityName>College Park</CityName>
<ZipCode>207420001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3014056269</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3112 LEE BLDG 7809 REGENTS DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MD04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NPU8ULVAAS23</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MARYLAND, COLLEGE PARK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>KMGEN62NKEM9</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Maryland]]></Name>
<CityName>COLLEGE PARK</CityName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>207425141</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4062 Campus Drive, 1109 Microbio]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MD04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1112</Code>
<Text>Genetic Mechanisms</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7465</Code>
<Text>NANOSCALE BIO CORE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~300000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Long lived trees and vines are under serious assault by numerous pathogens that threaten entire industries. &nbsp;Most scientists agree that using harmless plant viruses as vehicles to deliver anti-pathogenic small RNAs and peptides to a plant infected by the virus could be the solution to this massive problem. This method, known as &ldquo;VIGS&rdquo; for virus-induced gene silencing has been used in laboratories for over 20 years but has a serious problem before it can be used in the field in long-lived plants.&nbsp; Addition of extra RNA segments toa viral genome is required and to date, no one has been able to keep the inserted fragement stable in the virus for more than a few weeks.&nbsp; After that time, virus is always recovered that has &ldquo;spit out&rdquo; all or a portion of the inserted sequence, implying that the virus is much more fit in the absence of the artificial sequence.&nbsp; This grant was to generate, for the first time, stable VIGS vectors that can be used to protect trees.&nbsp; Although we were not successful at inserting large sequences capable of coding for large proteins, we did solve why viruses with inserted sequences are not stable.&nbsp; We determined that every nucleotide in every natural folded &ldquo;hairpin&rdquo; structure of an RNA virus has evolved to have thermodynamic properties that allow for seamless replication by the virus&rsquo;s replicating enzyme.&nbsp; Artificial hairpin sequences that are not engineered to have the same thermodynamic properties impede seamless replication, causing the replicating enzyme to remove the impediment.&nbsp; With this new understanding, we can now design hairpins that the virus views as "normal" and 200 nucleotides can be inserted into two locations in our VIGS vector, which can be used to control fungi, viruses, and (hopefully bacteria) in citrus and other plants.&nbsp; The inserted fragments are either converted by the plant into small RNAs that are taken up by the pathogens and rendered harmless, or can be joined to regions that encode proteins to product a new small protein (a peptide). &nbsp;&nbsp;The major broader impact implications can be seen with using this vector to protect citrus trees against citrus greening disease, which in a decade will impact every citrus tree grown outside of a greenhouse worldwide. &nbsp;A new proposal has been submitted based on this work to see if these thermodynamic parameters of hairpins are unique to a particular virus (e.g., our CYVaV VIGS vector) or if they are universal, with the goal of stabilizing additional plant virus VIGS vectors and animal virus vectors that can then be used as vaccine strains.&nbsp; A patent application based on these findings has been submitted.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/23/2023<br>      Modified by: Anne&nbsp;E&nbsp;Simon</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Long lived trees and vines are under serious assault by numerous pathogens that threaten entire industries.  Most scientists agree that using harmless plant viruses as vehicles to deliver anti-pathogenic small RNAs and peptides to a plant infected by the virus could be the solution to this massive problem. This method, known as "VIGS" for virus-induced gene silencing has been used in laboratories for over 20 years but has a serious problem before it can be used in the field in long-lived plants.  Addition of extra RNA segments toa viral genome is required and to date, no one has been able to keep the inserted fragement stable in the virus for more than a few weeks.  After that time, virus is always recovered that has "spit out" all or a portion of the inserted sequence, implying that the virus is much more fit in the absence of the artificial sequence.  This grant was to generate, for the first time, stable VIGS vectors that can be used to protect trees.  Although we were not successful at inserting large sequences capable of coding for large proteins, we did solve why viruses with inserted sequences are not stable.  We determined that every nucleotide in every natural folded "hairpin" structure of an RNA virus has evolved to have thermodynamic properties that allow for seamless replication by the virus’s replicating enzyme.  Artificial hairpin sequences that are not engineered to have the same thermodynamic properties impede seamless replication, causing the replicating enzyme to remove the impediment.  With this new understanding, we can now design hairpins that the virus views as "normal" and 200 nucleotides can be inserted into two locations in our VIGS vector, which can be used to control fungi, viruses, and (hopefully bacteria) in citrus and other plants.  The inserted fragments are either converted by the plant into small RNAs that are taken up by the pathogens and rendered harmless, or can be joined to regions that encode proteins to product a new small protein (a peptide).   The major broader impact implications can be seen with using this vector to protect citrus trees against citrus greening disease, which in a decade will impact every citrus tree grown outside of a greenhouse worldwide.  A new proposal has been submitted based on this work to see if these thermodynamic parameters of hairpins are unique to a particular virus (e.g., our CYVaV VIGS vector) or if they are universal, with the goal of stabilizing additional plant virus VIGS vectors and animal virus vectors that can then be used as vaccine strains.  A patent application based on these findings has been submitted.          Last Modified: 06/23/2023       Submitted by: Anne E Simon]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
