<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Broadening the Academic Data Science Community]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>60000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>60000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sylvia Spengler</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sspengle@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927347</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The Academic Data Science Alliance (ADSA) was created to enable the broad dissemination of new approaches and best practices in data science to colleges and universities nationwide. ADSA’s goals are to provide community resources and events for academic data scientists at any level to share research advances and educational approaches. ADSA also provides a collaboration space for university leadership to share their challenges and success stories around programs for data science. ADSA supports a peer network of early career academic data scientists to forge collaborations and implement novel training approaches on their campuses.  This project supports the ADSA Annual Meeting and the Data Science Leadership Summit. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The ADSA Annual Meeting provides an opportunity for academic researchers at any level (graduate students, postdocs, staff researchers and faculty) to collectively address common issues in data science research, education and training, program administration, and advocacy for data scientist career paths in higher education. The Data Science Leadership Summit convenes heads of current and nascent data science programs, and faculty interested in creating new initiatives on their campuses: to form an academic community for data science; to share best practices where they face similar challenges and opportunities; and to take collective responsibility in preparing next-generation data scientists to contribute in the best interests of society. The ADSA Career Development Network provides a peer-network for early career academic data scientists to support each other in their professional development.  Outcomes from these meetings are provided online for public consideration.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/10/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/30/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2034493</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Micaela</FirstName>
<LastName>Parker</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Micaela S Parker</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[micaela@academicdatascience.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000826765</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Ronin Institute for Independent Scholarship Incorporated</Name>
<CityName>MONTCLAIR</CityName>
<ZipCode>070432314</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9737072485</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>127 HADDON PL</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>11</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NJ11</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>JC6MG997HEK8</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RONIN INSTITUTE FOR INDEPENDENT SCHOLARSHIP INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Academic Data Science Alliance]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>981156655</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7484</Code>
<Text>IIS Special Projects</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7364</Code>
<Text>INFO INTEGRATION &amp; INFORMATICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~60000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-a88ac1c1-7fff-8fbd-8a41-ab933f374c02"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span><span id="docs-internal-guid-2c1d2265-7fff-14da-c8cd-566c99195d1b"><span>The</span><a href="https://academicdatascience.org/"><span> Academic Data Science Alliance</span></a></span> convenes in-person and virtual events, such the ADSA Annual Meeting, the Data Science Leadership Summit, and various workshops, to collectively address common challenges in data science research, education and training in higher education.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><strong>The major goal of this NSF funded project was to broaden participation in data science by inviting and supporting members of small colleges, Minority Serving Institutions, and under-represented groups in data science to participate in our annual events and workshops.&nbsp;</strong></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Due to the pandemic, <span id="docs-internal-guid-1aeb93b4-7fff-ae18-2317-49699d91b168"><span>our </span><a href="https://academicdatascience.org/adsa-meetings/"><span>2020 and 2021 meetings</span></a></span> were moved to virtual. With NSF funding, we supported accessibility of these virtual meetings by using event facilitators and offering free admission to all ADSA Annual Meeting registrants. We also supported travel and participation of students, postdocs, and faculty from Minority Serving Institutions (MSIs) and small colleges, or who self-identified as under-represented in data science, in two in-person meetings: our Spring ADSA Meeting in March 2022, and a Fall Career Workshop in October 2022.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>We encouraged and accepted research talks, breakout sessions, and keynote talks on topics that address issues of racial and gender bias in data science.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><strong><em>Attendees</em></strong></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The 2020 ADSA Annual Meeting attracted 241 attendees (566 registrations from 21 countries, and 37 U.S. states). Just under 1/4 of the registrants who responded to the question (23%) self-identified as part of an under-represented group in data science, some identified with more than one category. The dominant axis along which these registrants self-identified as under-represented was ethnicity/nationality/race (72 respondents), followed by gender identity (50 respondents), and sexual orientation (22 respondents).</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Despite the work/life challenges of 2020, the Data Science Leadership Summit also attracted 57 attendees from 40 academic institutions, in addition to representatives of federal agencies, foundations, and other professional societies. Here again, we collected optional demographic information at registration. Just over 33% of respondents self-identified as part of an under-represented group in data science, with nearly equal numbers identifying themselves as part of an underrepresented group based on ethnicity/nationality/race (17) and/or gender identity (16).</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Recognizing zoom burnout, we did not run a full conference in 2021. Instead we hosted a series of short virtual engagements, including panel discussions and lightning talks. See next section on Content.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The fully in-person ADSA Spring Meeting in March 2022 attracted attendees from 41 different schools, including 5 HBCUs, 4 HSIs, two 2yr community colleges, one small liberal arts school. In terms of demographic diversity, 44% identified as a race or ethnicity other than White and a different 44% identified as women (2 survey respondents preferred not to list their genders).&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>In October 2022, we ran an in-person </span><a href="https://academicdatascience.org/adsa-meetings/2022-fall-workshop"><span>Career Workshop</span></a><span> together with the US Research Software Engineers association (US-RSE). In total, 40 individuals from 31 institutions/organizations (12 from Minority Serving Institutions, 8 supported directly with this grant) attended to co-create a guidebook for hiring, retention, promotion, and professional development of data scientists and research software engineers in academia.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><strong><em>Content</em></strong></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Our outreach and community building efforts with under-represented or marginalized groups in data science, funded in part by this grant, led to:</span></p> <ul> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>High profile keynote speakers: Dr. Ruha Benjamin on "Race and Technology"; Dr. Desmond Upton Patton on "Impacted Communities";</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Amazing student keynote speakers: a team of two Black women from an HBCU who presented on "Using Data Analysis to Solve Human Trafficking", and a gay Hispanic man who is a Dreamer (DACA) student and first in his family to go to college who presented on "Enabling Exploratory Large Scale Graph Analytics through Arkouda";</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>A panel on Indigenous Data Sovereignty;</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Contributions from researchers who self-identified as under-represented and/or tackled ethical challenges in data science, for example Charreau Bell's&nbsp; "Growing Diversity in Data Science with a Hands-On Deep Learning Workshop for Students Exploring Racial Bias in Facial Recognition";</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Virtual breakout sessions covering topics on increasing diversity and accessibility in data science, including: Data science for social impact in university-based programs, Emerging AI Technologies for Inclusion of Underserved Populations, Non-Ableist Data Science, Community-Centered Benefit Sharing and New Data Equities.&nbsp;</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Recorded lightning talks with topics that included democratizing data, empowering people through data science, empowering humanities students with their first Python experience, a new community of practice for data creatives, and data driven approaches to maximizing the reach of public art. Four of these talks were led by early career researchers.</span></p> </li> </ul> <p dir="ltr"><span>The Career workshop had breakout sessions focused on predetermined topics pertinent to academic careers for RSEs and data scientists that form the chapters of the book. Participants were expected to actively engage in content creation throughout the workshop and participate in writing, review, and editing of the end product(s) after the workshop concluded. A draft of the Guidebook is currently being edited, with expected public release in Summer 2022.&nbsp;</span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/30/2023<br>      Modified by: Micaela&nbsp;S&nbsp;Parker</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   The Academic Data Science Alliance convenes in-person and virtual events, such the ADSA Annual Meeting, the Data Science Leadership Summit, and various workshops, to collectively address common challenges in data science research, education and training in higher education.  The major goal of this NSF funded project was to broaden participation in data science by inviting and supporting members of small colleges, Minority Serving Institutions, and under-represented groups in data science to participate in our annual events and workshops.  Due to the pandemic, our 2020 and 2021 meetings were moved to virtual. With NSF funding, we supported accessibility of these virtual meetings by using event facilitators and offering free admission to all ADSA Annual Meeting registrants. We also supported travel and participation of students, postdocs, and faculty from Minority Serving Institutions (MSIs) and small colleges, or who self-identified as under-represented in data science, in two in-person meetings: our Spring ADSA Meeting in March 2022, and a Fall Career Workshop in October 2022. We encouraged and accepted research talks, breakout sessions, and keynote talks on topics that address issues of racial and gender bias in data science. Attendees The 2020 ADSA Annual Meeting attracted 241 attendees (566 registrations from 21 countries, and 37 U.S. states). Just under 1/4 of the registrants who responded to the question (23%) self-identified as part of an under-represented group in data science, some identified with more than one category. The dominant axis along which these registrants self-identified as under-represented was ethnicity/nationality/race (72 respondents), followed by gender identity (50 respondents), and sexual orientation (22 respondents). Despite the work/life challenges of 2020, the Data Science Leadership Summit also attracted 57 attendees from 40 academic institutions, in addition to representatives of federal agencies, foundations, and other professional societies. Here again, we collected optional demographic information at registration. Just over 33% of respondents self-identified as part of an under-represented group in data science, with nearly equal numbers identifying themselves as part of an underrepresented group based on ethnicity/nationality/race (17) and/or gender identity (16). Recognizing zoom burnout, we did not run a full conference in 2021. Instead we hosted a series of short virtual engagements, including panel discussions and lightning talks. See next section on Content. The fully in-person ADSA Spring Meeting in March 2022 attracted attendees from 41 different schools, including 5 HBCUs, 4 HSIs, two 2yr community colleges, one small liberal arts school. In terms of demographic diversity, 44% identified as a race or ethnicity other than White and a different 44% identified as women (2 survey respondents preferred not to list their genders).  In October 2022, we ran an in-person Career Workshop together with the US Research Software Engineers association (US-RSE). In total, 40 individuals from 31 institutions/organizations (12 from Minority Serving Institutions, 8 supported directly with this grant) attended to co-create a guidebook for hiring, retention, promotion, and professional development of data scientists and research software engineers in academia.  Content Our outreach and community building efforts with under-represented or marginalized groups in data science, funded in part by this grant, led to:   High profile keynote speakers: Dr. Ruha Benjamin on "Race and Technology"; Dr. Desmond Upton Patton on "Impacted Communities";   Amazing student keynote speakers: a team of two Black women from an HBCU who presented on "Using Data Analysis to Solve Human Trafficking", and a gay Hispanic man who is a Dreamer (DACA) student and first in his family to go to college who presented on "Enabling Exploratory Large Scale Graph Analytics through Arkouda";   A panel on Indigenous Data Sovereignty;   Contributions from researchers who self-identified as under-represented and/or tackled ethical challenges in data science, for example Charreau Bell's  "Growing Diversity in Data Science with a Hands-On Deep Learning Workshop for Students Exploring Racial Bias in Facial Recognition";   Virtual breakout sessions covering topics on increasing diversity and accessibility in data science, including: Data science for social impact in university-based programs, Emerging AI Technologies for Inclusion of Underserved Populations, Non-Ableist Data Science, Community-Centered Benefit Sharing and New Data Equities.    Recorded lightning talks with topics that included democratizing data, empowering people through data science, empowering humanities students with their first Python experience, a new community of practice for data creatives, and data driven approaches to maximizing the reach of public art. Four of these talks were led by early career researchers.   The Career workshop had breakout sessions focused on predetermined topics pertinent to academic careers for RSEs and data scientists that form the chapters of the book. Participants were expected to actively engage in content creation throughout the workshop and participate in writing, review, and editing of the end product(s) after the workshop concluded. A draft of the Guidebook is currently being edited, with expected public release in Summer 2022.        Last Modified: 04/30/2023       Submitted by: Micaela S Parker]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
