<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Highly Customizable, Breathable N95 Mask Design Utilizing Kirigami-enabled Filters and Sensor Platforms to Maximize Comfort and Monitor usage Patterns]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>200000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>200000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EFMA</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Emerging Frontiers &amp; Multidisciplinary Activities</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Alias Smith</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>alismith@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928367</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Intellectual Merit: &lt;br/&gt;This project proposes to develop a rapidly manufacturable novel N95 class respirator design platform that decouples the relationship between comfort and filtering efficiency. The majority of N95 respirator masks are worn improperly even by trained medical personnel, caused by improper donning and fit when optimizing for comfort instead of filtering efficacy.  The proposed N95 respirators would enable the monitoring and minimization of face touching and track cleaning cycles and usage patterns. The project will circumvent several fundamental shortcomings in the design of current N95 style respirator masks, as well as their fit and wear protocols. The proposed design maximizes compactness, comfort, and manufacturability, while enabling real-time monitoring of face-touch events. The research team will use the latest advances in knitting technology that controllably place stiff and compliant elements in a seamless and semi-customized manner, sensing algorithms that can run on widely deployed wearable technology, as well as novel kirigami/origami-inspired sensor platforms and mechanical enhancement for filter effectiveness. Despite the advanced nature of these elements, the project will use current hardware and manufacturing capacity and plans to quickly transition to cost-effective implementation.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact:&lt;br/&gt;Studies have implied that gaps (as caused by an improper fit of the mask) can result in over a 60% decrease in the filtration efficiency, implying the need for future cloth mask design studies to take into account issues of "fit" and leakage, while allowing the exhaled air to vent efficiently.  The knitting-enabled approach used in this project allows for N-95 class of masks to be manufactured with a wider variety of size and fit options, using industrial capacity that has not been used to date for medical-grade masks.  Successful implementation of these designs will result in greater numbers of PPE produced and made available to healthcare workers. Although the proposed manufacturing process will be more costly initially, the mask construction will meet the necessary standards to allow for reusability and continued fit over time; significantly reducing its per-use cost. Furthermore, this approach to achieving semi- or fully customized fit of something as varied as the human face can be more broadly adapted to a variety of wearable garments and devices.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/30/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/30/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2034626</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sean</FirstName>
<LastName>Ahlquist</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sean Ahlquist</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ahlquist@umich.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000642855</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/30/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Max</FirstName>
<LastName>Shtein</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Max Shtein</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mshtein@umich.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000486532</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/30/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alanson</FirstName>
<LastName>Sample</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alanson P Sample</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[apsample@umich.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000828357</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/30/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Regents of the University of Michigan - Ann Arbor</Name>
<CityName>ANN ARBOR</CityName>
<ZipCode>481091079</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1109 GEDDES AVE, SUITE 3300</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>GNJ7BBP73WE9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MICHIGAN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Regents of the University of Michigan]]></Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3003 S. State Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7633</Code>
<Text>EFRI Research Projects</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7633</Code>
<Text>EFRI RESEARCH PROJECTS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~200000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>1. Intellectual Merit: </strong>This project recognized several fundamental shortcomings in the design of N-95 style respirator masks, as well as their fit and wear protocols. Such shortcomings arise in part from a trade-off between breathability and filtering efficiency inherent in the filter being placed directly in the inhalation and exhalation path, with an optimal porosity and size limited by the constraints of mask size, weight, and mechanical stability. To test these ideas, we built a specialized apparatus that allowed us to precicely measure mask filtering performance, deconvolving the filtering efficiency of the filter material used to construct the mask, its permeabilit to flow (i.e., intrinsic breathing comfort), and also when happens when a given mask is put on a face (in our case, using a specially configured mannikin head, with flow ducts connected to the aerosol and particle generation and detection chambers, and flow and pressure drop sensors to indicate breathing comfort). Our work clearly showed that commercially available N95 / KN95 masks that are commonly purchased by the general population, as well as medical professionals, result in breathing difficulty&nbsp;and uncomfortable fit. While this is by now common experience of the vast majority of people, we set out to also quantify the extent of improper fitting, which in the majority of cases even for trained personnel, and subsequent constant, conscious and sub-conscious readjustment that introduces pathogens and contamination.&nbsp;</p> <p>Our findings supported these qualitative notions, and also showed for several products where reductions in overall filtering efficacy were dramatics, and where masks performed well. Based on these results, we are preparing publications discussing the methods used, the results obtained, and recommendations for purchasing and future (re)designs.&nbsp;</p> <p>In addition to the above, we used the latest advances in knitting technology that controllably place stiff and compliant elements in a seamless and semi-customized manner to design masks maximizing wearing comfort and minimizing leakage paths, making and testing several designs.</p> <p>Finally, we also incorporated sensing algorithms that can detect face-touching and mask-adjustment events in use. They can run on widely deployed wearable technology (e.g., smart watches) and be incorporated into the masks, either <em>via</em> post-manufacturing add-ons, or via novel kirigami-based inserts that can be used to help maintain mechanical integrity of the masks to prevent collapse under heavy breathing.&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>2. Broader Impacts:&nbsp;</strong> The approach used here allows for effective and comfortable masks to be manufactured with a wider variety of size and fit options. In the case of knitted structures, industrial capacity could be leveraged that has not been used to date for medical-grade masks, which can result in greater numbers of PPE produced domestically and made available to healthcare workers. Mask selection protocols can also now be augmented with testing of performance of N95 class masks when worn, based on a larger set of parameters that includes extent of leakage created by improper fit, and long-term breathing comfort, not just based on the quality of the filter itself used to construct the mask. Finally, our preliminary designs for kirigami-based inserts for personalizing mask fit can also serve as a vehicle for embedding novel sensing modalities (e.g. pathogen detection, breathing frequency and depth, breath analysis, etc.) and embedding sophisticated algorithms in new classes of wearable devices. The touch sensing algorithms running on the now-ubiquitous wrist-worn or pocketable devices will become more power efficient and portable to more applications.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/18/2022<br>      Modified by: Max&nbsp;Shtein</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ 1. Intellectual Merit: This project recognized several fundamental shortcomings in the design of N-95 style respirator masks, as well as their fit and wear protocols. Such shortcomings arise in part from a trade-off between breathability and filtering efficiency inherent in the filter being placed directly in the inhalation and exhalation path, with an optimal porosity and size limited by the constraints of mask size, weight, and mechanical stability. To test these ideas, we built a specialized apparatus that allowed us to precicely measure mask filtering performance, deconvolving the filtering efficiency of the filter material used to construct the mask, its permeabilit to flow (i.e., intrinsic breathing comfort), and also when happens when a given mask is put on a face (in our case, using a specially configured mannikin head, with flow ducts connected to the aerosol and particle generation and detection chambers, and flow and pressure drop sensors to indicate breathing comfort). Our work clearly showed that commercially available N95 / KN95 masks that are commonly purchased by the general population, as well as medical professionals, result in breathing difficulty and uncomfortable fit. While this is by now common experience of the vast majority of people, we set out to also quantify the extent of improper fitting, which in the majority of cases even for trained personnel, and subsequent constant, conscious and sub-conscious readjustment that introduces pathogens and contamination.   Our findings supported these qualitative notions, and also showed for several products where reductions in overall filtering efficacy were dramatics, and where masks performed well. Based on these results, we are preparing publications discussing the methods used, the results obtained, and recommendations for purchasing and future (re)designs.   In addition to the above, we used the latest advances in knitting technology that controllably place stiff and compliant elements in a seamless and semi-customized manner to design masks maximizing wearing comfort and minimizing leakage paths, making and testing several designs.  Finally, we also incorporated sensing algorithms that can detect face-touching and mask-adjustment events in use. They can run on widely deployed wearable technology (e.g., smart watches) and be incorporated into the masks, either via post-manufacturing add-ons, or via novel kirigami-based inserts that can be used to help maintain mechanical integrity of the masks to prevent collapse under heavy breathing.   2. Broader Impacts:  The approach used here allows for effective and comfortable masks to be manufactured with a wider variety of size and fit options. In the case of knitted structures, industrial capacity could be leveraged that has not been used to date for medical-grade masks, which can result in greater numbers of PPE produced domestically and made available to healthcare workers. Mask selection protocols can also now be augmented with testing of performance of N95 class masks when worn, based on a larger set of parameters that includes extent of leakage created by improper fit, and long-term breathing comfort, not just based on the quality of the filter itself used to construct the mask. Finally, our preliminary designs for kirigami-based inserts for personalizing mask fit can also serve as a vehicle for embedding novel sensing modalities (e.g. pathogen detection, breathing frequency and depth, breath analysis, etc.) and embedding sophisticated algorithms in new classes of wearable devices. The touch sensing algorithms running on the now-ubiquitous wrist-worn or pocketable devices will become more power efficient and portable to more applications.       Last Modified: 06/18/2022       Submitted by: Max Shtein]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
