<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[STTR Phase I:  COVID-19 - High-Brightness Fluorescent Probes for Quantitative Polymerase Chain Reaction]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>256000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>276000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Erik Pierstorff</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>epiersto@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922165</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Technology Transfer (STTR) Phase I project is to develop a new probe to detect low levels of viral load, such as that causing COVID-19.  Rapid and reliable kits are not currently readily available. This project will provide rapid detection of viral material using exsiting cost-effective techniques with fewer detection errors. Being able to quantify and track viral loads at low concentration and high accuracy will expedite tests, reduce false negatives, and accelerate vaccine and drug development to combat COVID-19, and future pandemics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This STTR Phase I project will develop innovative fluorescent probes based on high-brightness fluorophores/dyes (HBFs) that offer tunable extinction coefficients up to several thousand times higher than commercial dyes. Based on this HBF platform technology, we will be able to create high-brightness qPCR probes that can specifically quantify viral RNAs by strong and tunable fluorescent signals at fewer amplification cycles and minimum replication errors. The activity, efficiency, and specificity of high-brightness qPCR probes will be evaluated in the project.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/02/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/29/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041, 47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2034693</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dongyan</FirstName>
<LastName>Zhang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Dongyan Zhang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[dozhang@mtu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000641711</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/02/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Xiuling</FirstName>
<LastName>Liu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Xiuling Liu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[xiulingliu@stabiluxbiosciences.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000795606</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/02/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>StabiLux Biosciences, Inc</Name>
<CityName>HOUGHTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>499319010</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9064872900</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>22151 RIDGE RD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>TGVWGK6GC341</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>STABILUX BIOSCIENCES INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[StabiLux Biosciences, Inc]]></Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>481039002</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[600 S. Wagner Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1505</Code>
<Text>STTR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8091</Code>
<Text>SBIR Outreach &amp; Tech. Assist</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>066E</Code>
<Text>INSTRUMENTATION &amp; DIAGNOSTICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8038</Code>
<Text>Biotechnology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~256000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~20000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="Pa3">&nbsp;</p> <p class="Default"><strong>Project Title</strong>: High-brightness fluorophore application in qPCR probe</p> <p class="Default"><strong>Recipient Organization</strong>: StabiLux Biosciences, Inc., and Michigan Technological University&nbsp;</p> <p class="Default"><strong>Project Period</strong>: 09/01/2020-08/31/2022</p> <p class="Default"><strong>PI</strong>: Xiuling Liu &amp;&nbsp;<strong>Co-PI</strong>: Dongyan Zhang&nbsp;</p> <p class="Default"><strong>NSF Award ID</strong>: #2034693</p> <p class="Default">The novel coronavirus (COVID-19) has infected more than 630 million people and caused 6.5 million deaths worldwide. Our original project proposed to develop high-brightness fluorescent probes for quantitative polymerase chain reaction (qPCR) to allow researchers and clinicians to rapidly detect trace amounts of viral genes with minimum amplification cycles and errors. Such high-brightness probes (HBPs) allow scientists to perform in-depth virology studies to combat this and future pandemics.</p> <p class="Default">&nbsp;After performing ~150 customer interviews as part of our NSF Bootcamp and I-Corps team project, we decided to pivot our target market from qPCR to fluorescence in situ hybridization (FISH) and the associated spatial omics (multiplexed genomic, transcriptomic, and proteomic detection on tissues). The new markets have many substantial unmet needs that our technology can solve and are larger in size. Furthermore, the technical design of the qPCR and FISH probes are compatible. Therefore, we switched our focus to developing HBPs as secondary FISH probes for detectionof messenger ribonucleic acids (mRNAs).</p> <p class="Default">After the pivot, we developed HBPs to target mRNAs in cancerous HeLa cells and discovered the following features: StabiLux HBPs are more than 10X brighter than commercial probes without signal amplification and yet small in size (~10nm). These unique features are significant: (1) HBPs enable more accurate quantification of gene molecules by avoiding uncertainties arising in the amplification processes. (2) HBPs allow the detection of short and rare genes, which is currently not possible with existing FISH probes. Detecting such genes will lead to new biomedical discoveries in cancer, immunological, and genomics research. (3) HBPs eliminate or reduce the signal amplification steps needed for tissue imaging. This will reduce the reagent cost and sample preparation time by at least 2-4X. (4) The high brightness could increase tissue sample mapping speed by 1000X. (5) HBPs is a drop-in technology that allows scientists to perform FISH research using existing fluorescent microscopes without the need for expensive detectors. Therefore, HBPs can increase the market size by promoting FISH research in institutes and countries where high-performance fluorescent microscopes are not widely accessible. (6) Our phase I research engaged collaboration between three female research scientists, a female lab assistant, and a female graduate student, coinciding with our efforts in promoting STEM (Science, Technology, Engineering, and Mathematics) careers among under-represented groups.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/29/2022<br>      Modified by: Xiuling&nbsp;Liu</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Project Title: High-brightness fluorophore application in qPCR probe Recipient Organization: StabiLux Biosciences, Inc., and Michigan Technological University  Project Period: 09/01/2020-08/31/2022 PI: Xiuling Liu &amp; Co-PI: Dongyan Zhang  NSF Award ID: #2034693 The novel coronavirus (COVID-19) has infected more than 630 million people and caused 6.5 million deaths worldwide. Our original project proposed to develop high-brightness fluorescent probes for quantitative polymerase chain reaction (qPCR) to allow researchers and clinicians to rapidly detect trace amounts of viral genes with minimum amplification cycles and errors. Such high-brightness probes (HBPs) allow scientists to perform in-depth virology studies to combat this and future pandemics.  After performing ~150 customer interviews as part of our NSF Bootcamp and I-Corps team project, we decided to pivot our target market from qPCR to fluorescence in situ hybridization (FISH) and the associated spatial omics (multiplexed genomic, transcriptomic, and proteomic detection on tissues). The new markets have many substantial unmet needs that our technology can solve and are larger in size. Furthermore, the technical design of the qPCR and FISH probes are compatible. Therefore, we switched our focus to developing HBPs as secondary FISH probes for detectionof messenger ribonucleic acids (mRNAs). After the pivot, we developed HBPs to target mRNAs in cancerous HeLa cells and discovered the following features: StabiLux HBPs are more than 10X brighter than commercial probes without signal amplification and yet small in size (~10nm). These unique features are significant: (1) HBPs enable more accurate quantification of gene molecules by avoiding uncertainties arising in the amplification processes. (2) HBPs allow the detection of short and rare genes, which is currently not possible with existing FISH probes. Detecting such genes will lead to new biomedical discoveries in cancer, immunological, and genomics research. (3) HBPs eliminate or reduce the signal amplification steps needed for tissue imaging. This will reduce the reagent cost and sample preparation time by at least 2-4X. (4) The high brightness could increase tissue sample mapping speed by 1000X. (5) HBPs is a drop-in technology that allows scientists to perform FISH research using existing fluorescent microscopes without the need for expensive detectors. Therefore, HBPs can increase the market size by promoting FISH research in institutes and countries where high-performance fluorescent microscopes are not widely accessible. (6) Our phase I research engaged collaboration between three female research scientists, a female lab assistant, and a female graduate student, coinciding with our efforts in promoting STEM (Science, Technology, Engineering, and Mathematics) careers among under-represented groups.          Last Modified: 11/29/2022       Submitted by: Xiuling Liu]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
