<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[STTR Phase I:  A therapeutic molecule for COVID-19]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>256000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>256000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Erik Pierstorff</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>epiersto@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922165</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact of this Small Business Technology Transfer (STTR) Phase I project is to provide a therapeutic solution for coronavirus pandemics.  Coronaviruses have been implicated in several outbreaks, including prior SARS and MERS. The proposed therapeutic will inhibit the virus’s ability to replicate and elicit the body's immune system to kill the virus.  In addition, this research can be applied to solutions for other viruses including RSV, hepatitis B and HIV/AIDS.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed project will advance a method integrating vaccines, small molecule inhibitors, and antibodies. This project will identify a small molecule that targets and binds to the virus, then link it to a small payload that signals the body's immune system.  This project will identify and develop a targeting molecule that can bind effectively to multiple strains of the coronavirus and a payload that promotes an appropriate immune response.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/05/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/05/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2035422</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Martin</FirstName>
<LastName>Low</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Martin Low</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[martin.low@eradivir.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000826726</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/05/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Madduri</FirstName>
<LastName>Srinivasarao</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Madduri Srinivasarao</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[msriniva@purdue.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000828728</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/05/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>ERADIVIR, INC.</Name>
<CityName>WEST LAFAYETTE</CityName>
<ZipCode>479064335</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4847441500</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1281 WIN HENTSCHEL BLVD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IN04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>QGDJNUMU9VR6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ERADIVIR INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[ERADIVIR, INC.]]></Name>
<CityName>West Lafayette</CityName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>479064182</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1281 Win Hentschel]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IN04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1505</Code>
<Text>STTR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>6883</Code>
<Text>CHEMISTRY OF LIFE PROCESSES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~256000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Eradivir, Inc. (2035422)</p> <p>Eradivir?s technology targets the immune system to kill viruses and the cells that host them.&nbsp; By linking a molecule that finds and binds to the surface of infected cells and free viruses (targeting ligand) to a small unique payload that elicits help from the immune system, the body can quickly respond and eliminate the infection with minimal side effects (see figure for influenza example).&nbsp; Initial work successfully used this technology to treat influenza.&nbsp; The results in animals demonstrated that the window to successfully treat the virus doubled from 48 hours post initial symptoms (limit for current standard of care) to 96 hours, and that the viral burden was reduced much faster.&nbsp;</p> <p>Eradivir used the proceeds from the NSF phase 1 grant to leverage this technology in order to find a treatment for COVID-19.&nbsp; As a result, multiple targeting ligands that securely bind to the spike protein found on the COVID-19 virus and infected host were identified and two payloads were developed that effectively call on Natural Killer (NK) cells, dendritic cells and activated macrophages to eliminate the infection.&nbsp; Work is still ongoing to choose the best targeting ligand, optimize it and link it to the appropriate payload to treat COVID-19. &nbsp;However, two separate unique immunological payloads were developed and successfully tested.&nbsp; These payloads can now be linked to various targeting ligands that bind to different diseased cells and viruses.&nbsp; Work has now begun to find treatments for other viruses including RSV, HIV and hepatitis B.&nbsp; This work also provides a ?toolkit? of solutions for any future new viruses that will certainly come.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/03/2022<br>      Modified by: Martin&nbsp;Low</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2035422/2035422_10716020_1646335573318_2022-03-03(2)--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2035422/2035422_10716020_1646335573318_2022-03-03(2)--rgov-800width.jpg" title="How Eradivir's Technology Works"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2035422/2035422_10716020_1646335573318_2022-03-03(2)--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="How Eradivir's Technology Works"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Eradivir will use similar technology as influenza to treat other viral infections</div> <div class="imageCredit">Eradivir</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Martin&nbsp;Low</div> <div class="imageTitle">How Eradivir's Technology Works</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Eradivir, Inc. (2035422)  Eradivir?s technology targets the immune system to kill viruses and the cells that host them.  By linking a molecule that finds and binds to the surface of infected cells and free viruses (targeting ligand) to a small unique payload that elicits help from the immune system, the body can quickly respond and eliminate the infection with minimal side effects (see figure for influenza example).  Initial work successfully used this technology to treat influenza.  The results in animals demonstrated that the window to successfully treat the virus doubled from 48 hours post initial symptoms (limit for current standard of care) to 96 hours, and that the viral burden was reduced much faster.   Eradivir used the proceeds from the NSF phase 1 grant to leverage this technology in order to find a treatment for COVID-19.  As a result, multiple targeting ligands that securely bind to the spike protein found on the COVID-19 virus and infected host were identified and two payloads were developed that effectively call on Natural Killer (NK) cells, dendritic cells and activated macrophages to eliminate the infection.  Work is still ongoing to choose the best targeting ligand, optimize it and link it to the appropriate payload to treat COVID-19.  However, two separate unique immunological payloads were developed and successfully tested.  These payloads can now be linked to various targeting ligands that bind to different diseased cells and viruses.  Work has now begun to find treatments for other viruses including RSV, HIV and hepatitis B.  This work also provides a ?toolkit? of solutions for any future new viruses that will certainly come.          Last Modified: 03/03/2022       Submitted by: Martin Low]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
