<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Doctoral Dissertation Research: Do Government Regulations Drive Product Features? The Case of the Global Commercial Drone Industry]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>15638.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>15638</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Mary Feeney</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mfeeney@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927197</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This dissertation research advances a novel way to link government science and technology regulation directly to product features by focusing on the global commercial drone/UAV (Unmanned Aerial Vehicle) industry. This industry was chosen as an example of a globally diverse high-tech market where multiple product features and parameters are possible.  The intent of this work is to understand what product features are most crucial to the drone industry and how differing standards affect them, as well as what features are most crucial for affecting both the safety and trajectory of a technology. This work has relevance to regulators and other decision-makers who must ascertain how best to strike a balance in their standard specifications to support nascent markets while protecting people from the potential harms of unregulated technologies.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This dissertation will use web scraping and other archival analyses to collect fine-grained product feature data to reveal the relationship between type of institutional support available to a firm (e.g., universities, public-private institutions, science parks) and the types of product innovations that it produces. We will also examine the impact of government standards on product features around weight, height, fuel mileage, and other relevant performance dimensions. Besides having granular product specifications, governments across the world have diverged as to what regulatory standards they use. We will examine differences between the U.S. and China around weight requirements for pilot licensing and drone registration and investigate how this affects product features. Overall, this research will improve our understanding of the effects of government regulations directly on the product features of firms in nascent markets.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/22/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/20/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2035625</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dian</FirstName>
<LastName>Yu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Dian Yu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[dia.yu@northeastern.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000823045</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/22/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
<LastName>Armanios</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Daniel Armanios</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[darmanios@cmu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000702814</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/22/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Carnegie-Mellon University</Name>
<CityName>PITTSBURGH</CityName>
<ZipCode>152133815</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4122688746</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5000 FORBES AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>U3NKNFLNQ613</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CARNEGIE MELLON UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>U3NKNFLNQ613</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Carnegie-Mellon University]]></Name>
<CityName>Pittsburgh</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>152133815</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5000 Forbes Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>125Y</Code>
<Text>Science of Science</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7626</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE OF SCIENCE POLICY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~15638</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>When considering social systems in innovation, the prevailing approach revolves around the pre- and post-acceptance of a dominant design. This view focuses on "convergence," or how social systems lead to progressive acceptance around a standard that underlies the technological paradigm. But how do we explain divergence? More specifically, when and where does divergence in product innovation occur? This is an important question because more and more high-potential technologies are emerging whose trajectory and impact are not clear. Therefore, a better prediction of where the disruptive innovation might occur can help managers make decisions and can help government officials better prepare for such occurrences.&nbsp;</p> <p>Intellectual Merit: Through this award, we have developed granular product feature data for the drone/UAV (Unmanned Aerial Vehicle) industry to provide a more detailed view of how innovation can be influenced by institutions. This project proposes links between product innovation and various dimensions of the institutional environment. Specifically, we investigate whether reforms in product specification guidelines (regulatory), trade association membership (normative), and drone knowledge providers (cognitive) lead to more product experimentation. We find that proximity to cognitive institutions (i.e., knowledge providers such as agricultural extension offices) may increase divergence, while proximity to normative institutions (i.e., trade associations such as the National Agricultural Aviation Association) may increase convergence. Knowing that divergence may come from local institutions could help firms identify or anticipate potential disruption, rather than being caught off guard by it.</p> <p>Broader Impacts: For policymakers, this research could serve as a policy playbook for what features are most important in influencing the safety and trajectory of a technology. The case of the commercial drone industry could serve as a baseline for similar general-purpose technologies (such as AI) that have the potential for use by a large population, and thus have a need for regulation. This research could be useful for engineers in a variety of fields in terms of understanding the potential impact of changes in standards on design.</p> <p>With the NSF Dissertation Improvement Grant, the Co-PI completed data collection for her dissertation "Do Government Regulations Drive Product Features? The Case of the Global Commercial Drone Industry." During the grant period, she worked with two research assistants to collect product feature-level data from the drone industry, traveled to the AUVSI trade show to conduct interviews, and purchased LexisNexis news archival data. The first chapter of the dissertation is currently being revised and resubmitted to the Strategic Management Journal, and the second chapter is ready for submission. The results of this research have been disseminated through a series of seminar and conference presentations, academic workshops, and industry trade shows. The Co-PI's dissertation is expected to be completed in 2023. It will be an important contribution at the nexus between institutional theory, engineering design, and technology and innovation management</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/19/2023<br>      Modified by: Daniel&nbsp;Armanios</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ When considering social systems in innovation, the prevailing approach revolves around the pre- and post-acceptance of a dominant design. This view focuses on "convergence," or how social systems lead to progressive acceptance around a standard that underlies the technological paradigm. But how do we explain divergence? More specifically, when and where does divergence in product innovation occur? This is an important question because more and more high-potential technologies are emerging whose trajectory and impact are not clear. Therefore, a better prediction of where the disruptive innovation might occur can help managers make decisions and can help government officials better prepare for such occurrences.   Intellectual Merit: Through this award, we have developed granular product feature data for the drone/UAV (Unmanned Aerial Vehicle) industry to provide a more detailed view of how innovation can be influenced by institutions. This project proposes links between product innovation and various dimensions of the institutional environment. Specifically, we investigate whether reforms in product specification guidelines (regulatory), trade association membership (normative), and drone knowledge providers (cognitive) lead to more product experimentation. We find that proximity to cognitive institutions (i.e., knowledge providers such as agricultural extension offices) may increase divergence, while proximity to normative institutions (i.e., trade associations such as the National Agricultural Aviation Association) may increase convergence. Knowing that divergence may come from local institutions could help firms identify or anticipate potential disruption, rather than being caught off guard by it.  Broader Impacts: For policymakers, this research could serve as a policy playbook for what features are most important in influencing the safety and trajectory of a technology. The case of the commercial drone industry could serve as a baseline for similar general-purpose technologies (such as AI) that have the potential for use by a large population, and thus have a need for regulation. This research could be useful for engineers in a variety of fields in terms of understanding the potential impact of changes in standards on design.  With the NSF Dissertation Improvement Grant, the Co-PI completed data collection for her dissertation "Do Government Regulations Drive Product Features? The Case of the Global Commercial Drone Industry." During the grant period, she worked with two research assistants to collect product feature-level data from the drone industry, traveled to the AUVSI trade show to conduct interviews, and purchased LexisNexis news archival data. The first chapter of the dissertation is currently being revised and resubmitted to the Strategic Management Journal, and the second chapter is ready for submission. The results of this research have been disseminated through a series of seminar and conference presentations, academic workshops, and industry trade shows. The Co-PI's dissertation is expected to be completed in 2023. It will be an important contribution at the nexus between institutional theory, engineering design, and technology and innovation management       Last Modified: 01/19/2023       Submitted by: Daniel Armanios]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
