<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID:  Surveying the American Public in the Time of COVID-19: Comparing Video to Face-to-Face Interviews]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>74963.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>74963</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SMA</Abbreviation>
<LongName>SBE Off Of Multidisciplinary Activities</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jan Leighley</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The National Science Foundation has typically funded face-to-face survey interviews with nationally representative samples of Americans. It has seemed inconceivable that face-to-face interviewing might not be possible. But then in 2020, the COVID-19 (coronavirus) pandemic arrived. States issued stay-at-home orders, required social distancing, and brought most in-person research to a standstill. In light of these circumstances, this project develops a mixed-mode design for surveys that will facilitate rigorous data collection in a period of viral pandemic and public uncertainty. We conduct multiple experiments and simulations that address the feasibility and logistics for the use of remote, live interviewing by video conference.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project builds on a small but powerful mode experiment that shows promising results. A previous experiment allowed within- and between-subject experimental design features to assess differences across modes, with randomization occurring after interviewees have consented to participate in this survey study. While we observed only minimal, statistically insignificant differences in the available data quality metrics—non-differentiation, non-response, don’t know responses, and length of response to open-ended questions—across modes, this may have resulted in part because it was conducted in a controlled environment to maximize internal validity, with all respondents participating in a central on-site location.  The experiments and simulations of this project extend the experimental designs to a more externally valid field environment to further test for data quality of video interviewing.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/24/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/24/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2035095</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ted</FirstName>
<LastName>Brader</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ted Brader</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[tbrader@umich.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000392655</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/24/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Regents of the University of Michigan - Ann Arbor</Name>
<CityName>ANN ARBOR</CityName>
<ZipCode>481091079</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1109 GEDDES AVE, SUITE 3300</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>GNJ7BBP73WE9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MICHIGAN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Michigan Ann Arbor]]></Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>481041248</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[426 Thompson St., Suite 4200]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>158Y</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~74963</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The 2020 election was a defining and historic moment for American democracy. To study that moment, the National Science Foundation provided funding to the University of Michigan to conduct survey interviews with a national sample of American citizens before and after the 2020 presidential election in the United States. That study, the American National Election Studies (ANES), conducted in-person interviews from 1948 to the present. But then, in 2020, the COVID-19 pandemic arrived. As a result, states issued stay-at-home orders, required social distancing, and brought most in-person research to a standstill. However, it was critically important that the project continued to provide this essential research project and its resulting data to the scholarly community and public, despite the inability to visit households in person.&nbsp;</p> <p>In response, ANES identified video interviewing as a possible alternative to in-person interviewing for the 2020 study. Video interviewing is relatively new, however, to large nationally representative surveys such as the ANES. Therefore, the ANES, under a very tight timeframe, used this new funding to conduct multiple experiments and simulations to learn how to successfully implement video interviewing in the 2020 ANES study and to the project&rsquo;s high standards of quality. The ANES developed training to conduct survey interviews using video, developed technology and instructions so that respondents could comfortably participate by video, and tested how to collect the highest quality data possible using video. These efforts resulted in a very successful 2020 ANES data collection whose data is being used, at no cost, by thousands of researchers, students, journalists, and the public, to study the moment of the 2020 election and its place in history. The effort has also produced valuable information for academic and government researchers who may need or wish to rely on remote, live interviewing by video conference in the future.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/03/2021<br>      Modified by: Ted&nbsp;Brader</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The 2020 election was a defining and historic moment for American democracy. To study that moment, the National Science Foundation provided funding to the University of Michigan to conduct survey interviews with a national sample of American citizens before and after the 2020 presidential election in the United States. That study, the American National Election Studies (ANES), conducted in-person interviews from 1948 to the present. But then, in 2020, the COVID-19 pandemic arrived. As a result, states issued stay-at-home orders, required social distancing, and brought most in-person research to a standstill. However, it was critically important that the project continued to provide this essential research project and its resulting data to the scholarly community and public, despite the inability to visit households in person.   In response, ANES identified video interviewing as a possible alternative to in-person interviewing for the 2020 study. Video interviewing is relatively new, however, to large nationally representative surveys such as the ANES. Therefore, the ANES, under a very tight timeframe, used this new funding to conduct multiple experiments and simulations to learn how to successfully implement video interviewing in the 2020 ANES study and to the project’s high standards of quality. The ANES developed training to conduct survey interviews using video, developed technology and instructions so that respondents could comfortably participate by video, and tested how to collect the highest quality data possible using video. These efforts resulted in a very successful 2020 ANES data collection whose data is being used, at no cost, by thousands of researchers, students, journalists, and the public, to study the moment of the 2020 election and its place in history. The effort has also produced valuable information for academic and government researchers who may need or wish to rely on remote, live interviewing by video conference in the future.       Last Modified: 12/03/2021       Submitted by: Ted Brader]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
