<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Improved Catalysts for Sanitizer Ethanol Production (COVID-19)]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>256000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>256000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anna Brady</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>abrady@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927077</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) project is to scale a renewable technology.  The proposed system uses renewable energy to convert carbon dioxide and water into value-added chemicals with the only byproduct being oxygen. This approach has the potential to make chemicals and fuels that consume and prevent greenhouse gas emissions. Unique to this process is production of the world’s first carbon-negative alcohols. These can be used as feedstock for materials including consumer goods, bioplastics, and fuel, both more sustainably and at a cost potentially lower than any other technologies in use today. The system’s most critical component is a proprietary catalyst that transforms carbon dioxide into alcohols, namely ethanol, using only earth-abundant elements and avoiding the use of precious metals. This SBIR project will focus on significantly improving these earth-abundant catalysts to reduce the cost of sustainable chemical production. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This SBIR project proposes to make transformative improvements to heterogeneous catalyst efficiency and yield for ethanol production. In doing so, it will improve understanding of how carbon dioxide interacts with the metals in novel heterogeneous catalysts. The new industrial chemical process produces ethanol from carbon dioxide in a single step. This process produces the first and only lifecycle carbon-negative ethanol to date, with the potential to be more energy efficient than legacy and state-of-the-art renewable ethanol processes.  The proposed novel catalysts enable new conversion phenomena not observed previously, which presents a challenge toward improving and scaling catalyst production. This project will study variants of the catalyst under varied pressure, temperature, flow rate, and other conditions along with chemical characterization to better understand how carbon dioxide and hydrogen bind to the catalyst surface. This data will be used to iterate and improve rate and selectivity toward production of USP grade ethanol.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/13/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/13/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2035588</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Stafford</FirstName>
<LastName>Sheehan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Stafford W Sheehan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[staff@aircompany.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000714964</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/13/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>AIR COMPANY HOLDINGS, INC.</Name>
<CityName>BROOKLYN</CityName>
<ZipCode>112062805</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3479274255</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>407 JOHNSON AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>MJU8VSEWNX85</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>AIR COMPANY HOLDINGS, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[AIR COMPANY HOLDINGS, INC.]]></Name>
<CityName>Brooklyn</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>112062805</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[407 Johnson Ave.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8030</Code>
<Text>Chemical Technology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~256000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Air Company converts CO<sub>2</sub> to products that are used for commodity chemicals and fuels. In our process, we use our proprietary catalysts to combine captured CO<sub>2</sub> with hydrogen (produced by splitting water using renewable electricity) to form alcohols, such as methanol or ethanol, as major products and oxygen as a side product. We are source-agnostic as a CO<sub>2</sub> utilization company, but ultimately plan to source our CO<sub>2</sub> using direct air capture (diagram showing process flows shown in Fig. 1). To date we have used high purity ethanol that is produced by our process for carbon negative consumer products (hand sanitizer, spirits, and most recently, fragrance).</p> <p>The main purpose of the Phase 1 proposal was to gain a better understanding of our proprietary family of catalysts and improve their performance for producing high purity ethanol to be used in our consumer products, namely hand sanitizer. Since the beginning of Phase 1, we have tested our existing catalyst under varying conditions, such as varied temperatures, pressures, and flow conditions, to understand their performance at our pilot-scale facility (reactor skid shown in Fig. 2). Additionally, we have improved and streamlined our bench-scale testing capabilities to synthesize, screen and identify best performing catalysts faster (photograph of synthesis underway in Fig. 3). Based on the data we collected form large- and small-scale testing and as a direct outcome of the SBIR funding, we have subsequently synthesized and further screened over 50 catalysts (exemplary catalyst shown in Fig. 4). This includes both modified versions of our existing and commercial catalysts, as well as new ones, and identified candidates with improved catalytic activity to improve our CO<sub>2</sub>-to-ethanol conversion.</p> <p>As a direct result of synthesis and testing, we have identified a new champion catalyst that shows higher activity for ethanol production than our previous champion catalyst. As an added outcome, we have also observed further activity toward CO<sub>2</sub> conversion to aviation fuel hydrocarbons, opening avenues for us to contribute to carbon capture and conversion at a much larger scale. The outcome of this research has demonstrated that our novel catalysts show catalytic phenomenon that have not yet been reported in the literature, and we plan to report our findings in scientific journals in the near future. Based on the outcomes of Phase 1, we continue our efforts to gain further mechanistic understanding of catalysts and to optimize our process by targeting specific products streams (e.g., jet fuel) that would allow us to make significant impact to advance carbon capture and utilization technologies.&nbsp;</p> <p>During this funding period, we have hired and trained technical staff and more than quadrupled the outcome of our synthetic and testing capabilities. Efforts to scale up the synthesis of our new champion catalysts are underway for use at our pilot scale facility. Having found a catalyst with significantly improved ethanol yield the outcomes of this project will benefit our commercial technology and prodcut output. In addition to our contribution to advancing scientific research to improve carbon conversion efficiency and yields, Air Company is also committed to participating in efforts to bring awareness pertaining to global climate issues to our consumers. We continue to bring awareness through our targeted campaigns to educate our consumers about climate change issues as well as how we are combating it through our processes and products. Inspired to support our community in a time of great need at the height of the COVID-19 lockdown, we had pivoted to producing and donating carbon negative hand sanitizers to hospitals and essential services in New York City in 2020. As part of our continued dedication to this effort, we have donated 15,000 bottles of hand sanitizer to date, to communities in need across the country.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/22/2021<br>      Modified by: Stafford&nbsp;W&nbsp;Sheehan</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2035588/2035588_10733774_1639860056616_Figure_2_Reactor--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2035588/2035588_10733774_1639860056616_Figure_2_Reactor--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 2: Air Company Carbon Dioxide Reactor"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2035588/2035588_10733774_1639860056616_Figure_2_Reactor--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 2: Air Company Carbon Dioxide Reactor"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Air Company's large prototype carbon dioxide conversion reactor at our test facility in Brooklyn, New York.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Air Company</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Stafford&nbsp;W&nbsp;Sheehan</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 2: Air Company Carbon Dioxide Reactor</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2035588/2035588_10733774_1639860144916_Figure_3_Synthesis--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2035588/2035588_10733774_1639860144916_Figure_3_Synthesis--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 3: Air Company Catalyst Synthesis"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2035588/2035588_10733774_1639860144916_Figure_3_Synthesis--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 3: Air Company Catalyst Synthesis"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Photograph of one of Air Company's chemists during catalyst synthesis in our laboratory facility.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Air Company</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Stafford&nbsp;W&nbsp;Sheehan</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 3: Air Company Catalyst Synthesis</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2035588/2035588_10733774_1639859885987_Figure_1_Process--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2035588/2035588_10733774_1639859885987_Figure_1_Process--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 1: Air Company Process"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2035588/2035588_10733774_1639859885987_Figure_1_Process--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 1: Air Company Process"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Air Company's vision for an integrated system that makes commodity products from air, water, and sunlight.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Air Company</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Stafford&nbsp;W&nbsp;Sheehan</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 1: Air Company Process</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2035588/2035588_10733774_1640154828913_Figure_4_Catalyst--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2035588/2035588_10733774_1640154828913_Figure_4_Catalyst--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 4: Photograph of Catalyst"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2035588/2035588_10733774_1640154828913_Figure_4_Catalyst--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 4: Photograph of Catalyst"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Catalyst material is synthesized as a black powder and pressed into pellets, as shown in this photograph.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Air Company</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Stafford&nbsp;W&nbsp;Sheehan</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 4: Photograph of Catalyst</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Air Company converts CO2 to products that are used for commodity chemicals and fuels. In our process, we use our proprietary catalysts to combine captured CO2 with hydrogen (produced by splitting water using renewable electricity) to form alcohols, such as methanol or ethanol, as major products and oxygen as a side product. We are source-agnostic as a CO2 utilization company, but ultimately plan to source our CO2 using direct air capture (diagram showing process flows shown in Fig. 1). To date we have used high purity ethanol that is produced by our process for carbon negative consumer products (hand sanitizer, spirits, and most recently, fragrance).  The main purpose of the Phase 1 proposal was to gain a better understanding of our proprietary family of catalysts and improve their performance for producing high purity ethanol to be used in our consumer products, namely hand sanitizer. Since the beginning of Phase 1, we have tested our existing catalyst under varying conditions, such as varied temperatures, pressures, and flow conditions, to understand their performance at our pilot-scale facility (reactor skid shown in Fig. 2). Additionally, we have improved and streamlined our bench-scale testing capabilities to synthesize, screen and identify best performing catalysts faster (photograph of synthesis underway in Fig. 3). Based on the data we collected form large- and small-scale testing and as a direct outcome of the SBIR funding, we have subsequently synthesized and further screened over 50 catalysts (exemplary catalyst shown in Fig. 4). This includes both modified versions of our existing and commercial catalysts, as well as new ones, and identified candidates with improved catalytic activity to improve our CO2-to-ethanol conversion.  As a direct result of synthesis and testing, we have identified a new champion catalyst that shows higher activity for ethanol production than our previous champion catalyst. As an added outcome, we have also observed further activity toward CO2 conversion to aviation fuel hydrocarbons, opening avenues for us to contribute to carbon capture and conversion at a much larger scale. The outcome of this research has demonstrated that our novel catalysts show catalytic phenomenon that have not yet been reported in the literature, and we plan to report our findings in scientific journals in the near future. Based on the outcomes of Phase 1, we continue our efforts to gain further mechanistic understanding of catalysts and to optimize our process by targeting specific products streams (e.g., jet fuel) that would allow us to make significant impact to advance carbon capture and utilization technologies.   During this funding period, we have hired and trained technical staff and more than quadrupled the outcome of our synthetic and testing capabilities. Efforts to scale up the synthesis of our new champion catalysts are underway for use at our pilot scale facility. Having found a catalyst with significantly improved ethanol yield the outcomes of this project will benefit our commercial technology and prodcut output. In addition to our contribution to advancing scientific research to improve carbon conversion efficiency and yields, Air Company is also committed to participating in efforts to bring awareness pertaining to global climate issues to our consumers. We continue to bring awareness through our targeted campaigns to educate our consumers about climate change issues as well as how we are combating it through our processes and products. Inspired to support our community in a time of great need at the height of the COVID-19 lockdown, we had pivoted to producing and donating carbon negative hand sanitizers to hospitals and essential services in New York City in 2020. As part of our continued dedication to this effort, we have donated 15,000 bottles of hand sanitizer to date, to communities in need across the country.       Last Modified: 12/22/2021       Submitted by: Stafford W Sheehan]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
