<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Transdisciplinary Convergence to Accelerate Strategies to Mitigate Institutional Racism in Criminal Justice, Education, and Health Systems]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>99855.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>99855</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ITE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Innovation and Technology Ecosystems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Linda Molnar</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lmolnar@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928316</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The NSF Convergence Accelerator supports use-inspired, team-based, multidisciplinary efforts that address challenges of national importance and will produce deliverables of value to society in the near future. The broader impact and potential societal benefit of this Convergence Accelerator conference proposal is to address institutional racism by utilizing advanced technologies that have the potential to disrupt institutional racism in ways that have not been experienced previously. The disparate burden of the COVID-19 pandemic on Black communities, the recent high profile police involved murders of Black people in Minneapolis and Louisville, and the longstanding racial achievement gaps in education underscore the need for the proposed project. Institutional racism currently manifests&lt;br/&gt;heavily within criminal justice, education, and healthcare. The project seeks to explore the use of technology in building more socially conscious systems to mitigate institutional racism. Leading experts in this project will leverage their talents, perspectives, and resources to help the project document technology-infused ideas that have potential to disrupt institutional racism in ways that have not been experienced in the past. Ending institutional racism will only be advanced by visionaries across academic disciplines and sectors who can see a universe of opportunity that is not distant or unattainable. The field experts who will commit to this project have the capacity to converge efforts to advance human technology in addressing racial inequities in criminal justice, education, and health systems. The PIs have plan to broadly disseminate findings included in the technical report across sectors including academia, non-profits, government, and especially the technology industry. Finally, this project also has the potential to broaden the scope and influence of research by including HBCU scholars.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will advance knowledge of technologically-informed systems  at the Human Technology Frontier that have the potential to mitigate institutional racism in the criminal justice, education, and health workforce. The virtual workshops will bring together transdisciplinary and cross-sector thought leaders from social, behavioral and computational sciences and industry with demonstrated capacity to propose technological innovations that have the most potential to create the humanistic agency necessary to advance racial equity within the criminal justice, education, and health systems. The plan for the workshops optimizes and builds upon prior identified cutting-edge research that will be foundational to achieving the project’s ultimate goal of developing a technical report that provides solutions to existing gaps affecting the Black community in criminal justice, education, and healthcare. Our plan to distribute relevant major studies prior to the workshops for the leaders to review and evaluate will ensure that ensuing discussions at the workshop are informed by the current landscape. Further, final reports from each workshop session will have the potential to form the basis for a NSF Convergence Accelerator Track topic. The PIs organization, Quality Education for Minorities Network (QEM)  has 30 years of experience with research and programs that have assembled technical advisors necessary to conduct the proposed activities. The project will also strategically use HBCU researchers for their time-honored expertise with advancing African American progress.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/12/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/29/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.083, 47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2035321</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>IVORY</FirstName>
<LastName>TOLDSON</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>IVORY A TOLDSON</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[itoldson@qem.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000727410</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/12/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate>10/29/2021</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mercy</FirstName>
<LastName>Mugo</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mercy W Mugo</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mmugo@qem.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000730946</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/12/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate>10/29/2021</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mercy</FirstName>
<LastName>Mugo</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mercy W Mugo</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mmugo@qem.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000730946</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>10/29/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>QUALITY EDUCATION FOR MINORITIES NETWORK</Name>
<CityName>WASHINGTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>200362406</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2026591818</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1818 N ST NW STE 350</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>M1LSMGM4J768</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>QUALITY EDUCATION FOR MINORITIES NETWORK (INC)</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[QUALITY EDUCATION FOR MINORITIES NETWORK]]></Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>200362406</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1818 N Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>131Y</Code>
<Text>Convergence Accelerator Resrch</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~99855</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Project Overview</strong></p> <p>Under this award, QEM Network planned and conducted a town hall meeting and facilitated two think tank sessions (October 2020 and April 2022) to gather insights from thought leaders from multiple disciplines and sectors&nbsp;about the human-technology mechanisms that can mitigate institutional racism in education system.&nbsp;A total of 40 individuals representing a range of institutions such as k-12 school districts, community colleges, higher education institutions, industries, nonprofits, government agencies, and scientific professional societies provided their perspectives on&nbsp;mechanisms to maximize technology to dismantle systemic educational inequities.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;Table 1. Institutions Represented at the Think Tanks</p> <table border="1" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="0" width="616"> <tbody> <tr> <td colspan="2" width="616" valign="top"> <p>Institutions Represented at the October 2020 Think Tank</p> </td> </tr> <tr> <td width="358"> <p>American University&nbsp;</p> </td> <td width="258"> <p>IBM&nbsp;</p> </td> </tr> <tr> <td width="358"> <p>Association of American Colleges &amp; Universities</p> </td> <td width="258"> <p>National Education Association&nbsp;</p> </td> </tr> <tr> <td width="358"> <p>Atlanta University Center Consortium&nbsp;</p> </td> <td width="258"> <p>Stanford University&nbsp;</p> </td> </tr> <tr> <td width="358"> <p>Broward County Public Schools&nbsp;</p> </td> <td width="258"> <p>Tennessee State University&nbsp;</p> </td> </tr> <tr> <td width="358"> <p>California State, Monterey Bay</p> </td> <td width="258"> <p>The Learning Agency&nbsp;</p> </td> </tr> <tr> <td width="358"> <p>Center for Curriculum Redesign&nbsp;</p> </td> <td width="258"> <p>University of Maryland&nbsp;</p> </td> </tr> <tr> <td width="358"> <p>Executive Technology, Inc&nbsp;</p> </td> <td width="258"> <p>University of Missouri-Kansas City</p> </td> </tr> <tr> <td width="358"> <p>Fielding University&nbsp;</p> </td> <td width="258"> <p>&nbsp;</p> </td> </tr> <tr> <td colspan="2" width="616" valign="top"> <p>Institutions Represented at the April 2022 Think Tank</p> </td> </tr> <tr> <td width="358" valign="top"> <p>Amazon</p> </td> <td width="258" valign="top"> <p>Jackson State University</p> </td> </tr> <tr> <td width="358" valign="top"> <p>American Association of College for Teacher Education</p> </td> <td width="258" valign="top"> <p>Lawson State Community College</p> </td> </tr> <tr> <td width="358" valign="top"> <p>Atlanta University Center Consortium&nbsp;</p> </td> <td width="258" valign="top"> <p>Microsoft TEALS Program</p> </td> </tr> <tr> <td width="358" valign="top"> <p>Basic Commerce and Industries, Inc.</p> </td> <td width="258" valign="top"> <p>National Society of Black Engineers</p> </td> </tr> <tr> <td width="358" valign="top"> <p>Broward Public County Schools</p> </td> <td width="258" valign="top"> <p>STEM Funders Network</p> </td> </tr> <tr> <td width="358" valign="top"> <p>Coahoma Community College</p> </td> <td width="258" valign="top"> <p>The Edtech Equity Project</p> </td> </tr> <tr> <td width="358" valign="top"> <p>Florida A&amp;M University</p> </td> <td width="258" valign="top"> <p>Tougaloo College</p> </td> </tr> <tr> <td width="358" valign="top"> <p>Hinds Community College</p> </td> <td width="258" valign="top"> <p>Tuskegee University</p> </td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Think Tank Discussion Framework</strong></p> <p>QEM consultants with expertise in facilitation moderated small group discussions. The facilitators employed a structured approach to generating ideas that provided an opportunity for participants to contribute perspectives on the following topical areas:&nbsp;</p> <ul> <li><strong>Expanded Cognition and Humanistic Reprioritization</strong>: How can we use technology strategically to focus on cognitive tasks in the classrooms so that educators can reprioritize efforts around humanistic tasks?</li> </ul> <ul> <li><strong>Humanistic Distributed Agency</strong>: How do we use technology to democratize knowledge to give humanistic educators the necessary agency to make decisions that can positively impact learners?</li> </ul> <ul> <li><strong>From Standards in Practice to Standards in Principle</strong>: How do we use technology to eliminate rigid&nbsp;standards of practice&nbsp;to create a system that rewards innovation and recorded strategies to shape professional practice in accordance with a larger mission and higher-level ideas and principles?</li> </ul> <ul> <li><strong>Using Data Science to Glean Best Practice:&nbsp;</strong>How do we implement data systems to allow the education system to learn from variations (deviations) in practice?<strong>&nbsp;</strong></li> </ul> <ul> <li><strong>Post-Reform Education Era, Education at the Human-Technology Frontier:&nbsp;</strong>How will the next 40 years look, and how much does this statement comport with reality? and what kind of changes are you looking to see? How does technology affect lifelong learning? How can educators affirm lifelong learning<strong><em>?</em></strong></li> </ul> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p><strong>Key Findings</strong></p> <p>The&nbsp;following&nbsp;themes&nbsp;emerged&nbsp;from the collective feedback&nbsp;on&nbsp;ways to&nbsp;utilize technology&nbsp;support equitable systems change&nbsp;in education:&nbsp;&nbsp;<em>&nbsp;</em><em>increasing accessibility to resources and opportunities, democratizing data and using data to inform decision making, providing training opportunities (upskilling/reskilling teachers and students), establishing authentic partnerships with key stakeholders, </em>and<em>&nbsp;</em><em> influencing policy changes</em>. The findings can advance knowledge of technological-informed systems that have the potential to mitigate institutional racism in education.&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p><strong>Publication</strong></p> <p>The&nbsp;findings&nbsp;from the think tank were documented in the whitepaper below:&nbsp;</p> <p>Toldson, Ivory A. (2020).&nbsp;Humanistic Distributed Agency: Remaking Education at the Human Technology Frontier.<a href="https://qem.org/wp-content/uploads/Convergence-Accelerator-Report.pdf">https://qem.org/wp-content/uploads/Convergence-Accelerator-Report.pdf</a></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/14/2022<br>      Modified by: Mercy&nbsp;W&nbsp;Mugo</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Project Overview  Under this award, QEM Network planned and conducted a town hall meeting and facilitated two think tank sessions (October 2020 and April 2022) to gather insights from thought leaders from multiple disciplines and sectors about the human-technology mechanisms that can mitigate institutional racism in education system. A total of 40 individuals representing a range of institutions such as k-12 school districts, community colleges, higher education institutions, industries, nonprofits, government agencies, and scientific professional societies provided their perspectives on mechanisms to maximize technology to dismantle systemic educational inequities.      Table 1. Institutions Represented at the Think Tanks      Institutions Represented at the October 2020 Think Tank      American University     IBM       Association of American Colleges &amp; Universities    National Education Association       Atlanta University Center Consortium     Stanford University       Broward County Public Schools     Tennessee State University       California State, Monterey Bay    The Learning Agency       Center for Curriculum Redesign     University of Maryland       Executive Technology, Inc     University of Missouri-Kansas City      Fielding University            Institutions Represented at the April 2022 Think Tank      Amazon    Jackson State University      American Association of College for Teacher Education    Lawson State Community College      Atlanta University Center Consortium     Microsoft TEALS Program      Basic Commerce and Industries, Inc.    National Society of Black Engineers      Broward Public County Schools    STEM Funders Network      Coahoma Community College    The Edtech Equity Project      Florida A&amp;M University    Tougaloo College      Hinds Community College    Tuskegee University            Think Tank Discussion Framework  QEM consultants with expertise in facilitation moderated small group discussions. The facilitators employed a structured approach to generating ideas that provided an opportunity for participants to contribute perspectives on the following topical areas:   Expanded Cognition and Humanistic Reprioritization: How can we use technology strategically to focus on cognitive tasks in the classrooms so that educators can reprioritize efforts around humanistic tasks?   Humanistic Distributed Agency: How do we use technology to democratize knowledge to give humanistic educators the necessary agency to make decisions that can positively impact learners?   From Standards in Practice to Standards in Principle: How do we use technology to eliminate rigid standards of practice to create a system that rewards innovation and recorded strategies to shape professional practice in accordance with a larger mission and higher-level ideas and principles?   Using Data Science to Glean Best Practice: How do we implement data systems to allow the education system to learn from variations (deviations) in practice?    Post-Reform Education Era, Education at the Human-Technology Frontier: How will the next 40 years look, and how much does this statement comport with reality? and what kind of changes are you looking to see? How does technology affect lifelong learning? How can educators affirm lifelong learning?      Key Findings  The following themes emerged from the collective feedback on ways to utilize technology support equitable systems change in education:   increasing accessibility to resources and opportunities, democratizing data and using data to inform decision making, providing training opportunities (upskilling/reskilling teachers and students), establishing authentic partnerships with key stakeholders, and  influencing policy changes. The findings can advance knowledge of technological-informed systems that have the potential to mitigate institutional racism in education.      Publication  The findings from the think tank were documented in the whitepaper below:   Toldson, Ivory A. (2020). Humanistic Distributed Agency: Remaking Education at the Human Technology Frontier.https://qem.org/wp-content/uploads/Convergence-Accelerator-Report.pdf          Last Modified: 12/14/2022       Submitted by: Mercy W Mugo]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
