<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[STTR Phase I: Nanoparticulate metal oxide electrodes for fast charging lithium ion batteries]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>256000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>256000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anna Brady</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>abrady@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927077</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this project is to develop and commercialize a fast charging battery which offers better safety with long cycle life compared to today’s lithium (Li)-ion batteries. In traditional batteries, fast charging can cause the battery to become dangerously hot (more than 60°C/140°F) and reduce the life of the battery to one or two charges. The proposed batteries utilize novel electrode materials that can be charged rapidly while generating no/little heat. Safe, fast-charging batteries have strong economic benefits for a variety of applications. Generally speaking, for mobile applications (cars, scooters, etc.), fast-charging batteries allows electrification of these devices by removing the main obstacle to acceptance - long charge times. For automated robots, power tools, and small electric vehicles, using the new generation batteries is expected to reduce the cost of ownership by increasing the battery life by at least a factor of 3. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This STTR Phase I project seeks to develop ultrafast charging batteries using mesoporous electrode materials. The materials are made into a sponge-like electrodes with the pores many times smaller than a human hair.  These sponge-like electrodes allow very close contact between the energy storage material and energy transport liquid, the electrolyte, decreasing ion transport distance.  The project will further develop the material into commercial fast charge batteries that allow: 1) charging in less than 10 minutes, 2) minimal heating upon fast charging, and 3) three times the cycle life compared to traditional Li-ion batteries. Additional effort will be put on process development to scale the materials production cost effectively.  Detailed performance studies at the better cell level will aid in understanding the effect of mesoporosity on fast-charging and heat generation using oxide nanostructured materials. These results will aid in the future development of high rate oxide materials in practical and fast charge Li-ion batteries with improved safety characteristics and minimized heat management requirements.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/04/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/04/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2035681</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sarah</FirstName>
<LastName>Tolbert</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sarah H Tolbert</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[tolbert@chem.ucla.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000419902</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/04/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Chun-Han</FirstName>
<LastName>Lai</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Chun-Han Lai</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[laich@batterystreak.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000826584</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/04/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>BATTERY STREAK, INC.</Name>
<CityName>CAMARILLO</CityName>
<ZipCode>930128534</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8054024088</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4770 CALLE QUETZAL</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>26</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA26</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>CH74MCMN7BK7</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>BATTERY STREAK INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Battery Streak]]></Name>
<CityName>Newbury Park</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>913206186</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3537 Old Conejo Rd, Suite 111]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>26</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA26</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1505</Code>
<Text>STTR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8399</Code>
<Text>Energy Storage or Transmission</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~256000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The goal of this project was to develop improved high-power lithium-ion batteries.&nbsp; The work was a joint effort of Battery Streak, Inc. (BSI) and UCLA, and including material synthesis, electrode optimization for commercial battery cell, and initial battery prototype implementation. The project specifically developed and explored new pathways to nanostructured lithium vanadium fluorophosphate (nanoLVPF). This new positive electrode material has pores on the nanoscale that are beneficial for fast charging.&nbsp; The material is also free of critical minerals such as nickel and cobalt. Initial work on the fabrication, characterization, and battery testing of nanoLVPF was carried out at UCLA, where researchers were able to achieve a superior energy density of&nbsp; 660 Wh/kg with a reasonable capacity of 150 Ah/kg at a Li-referenced voltage of 4.2 V. In addition, a newly developed synthesis route to nanoLVPF was verified as scalable and compatible with industrial standard processes without compromising material performance; the synthetic methods were successfully transferred to BSI for pilot scale production.</p> <p>With the scaled production of nanoLVPF, BSI further developed the material into commercial fast charge batteries that allow charging to 80% in 10 minute with minimal heating. The synthesized material was then successfully used to create commercial high-loading electrodes which were implemented in a prototype pouch cell developed by BSI. The BSI prototype uses titanium niobium oxide (TNO), and is an ideal fast-charging platform with numerous benefits over traditional battery chemistries because it can be charged rapidly while generating no/little heat. In this project, a commercial 1 Ah prototype cell of nanoLVPF//TNO was first built and demonstrated to charge in 10 minute with a nominal cell voltage of 2.6 V.</p> <p>While the main focus of this work was on material development, students working on this project at UCLA were provided with both industry experience and interdisciplinary training in the design and development of batteries and in battery manufacturing. BSI was also able get the technology exposed to local business partners through regional conferences and trade shows, and students were able to understand how their work could be directly translated into a product.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/22/2023<br>      Modified by: Sarah&nbsp;H&nbsp;Tolbert</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The goal of this project was to develop improved high-power lithium-ion batteries.  The work was a joint effort of Battery Streak, Inc. (BSI) and UCLA, and including material synthesis, electrode optimization for commercial battery cell, and initial battery prototype implementation. The project specifically developed and explored new pathways to nanostructured lithium vanadium fluorophosphate (nanoLVPF). This new positive electrode material has pores on the nanoscale that are beneficial for fast charging.  The material is also free of critical minerals such as nickel and cobalt. Initial work on the fabrication, characterization, and battery testing of nanoLVPF was carried out at UCLA, where researchers were able to achieve a superior energy density of  660 Wh/kg with a reasonable capacity of 150 Ah/kg at a Li-referenced voltage of 4.2 V. In addition, a newly developed synthesis route to nanoLVPF was verified as scalable and compatible with industrial standard processes without compromising material performance; the synthetic methods were successfully transferred to BSI for pilot scale production.  With the scaled production of nanoLVPF, BSI further developed the material into commercial fast charge batteries that allow charging to 80% in 10 minute with minimal heating. The synthesized material was then successfully used to create commercial high-loading electrodes which were implemented in a prototype pouch cell developed by BSI. The BSI prototype uses titanium niobium oxide (TNO), and is an ideal fast-charging platform with numerous benefits over traditional battery chemistries because it can be charged rapidly while generating no/little heat. In this project, a commercial 1 Ah prototype cell of nanoLVPF//TNO was first built and demonstrated to charge in 10 minute with a nominal cell voltage of 2.6 V.  While the main focus of this work was on material development, students working on this project at UCLA were provided with both industry experience and interdisciplinary training in the design and development of batteries and in battery manufacturing. BSI was also able get the technology exposed to local business partners through regional conferences and trade shows, and students were able to understand how their work could be directly translated into a product.          Last Modified: 03/22/2023       Submitted by: Sarah H Tolbert]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
