<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[STTR Phase I:  Feasibility Study of Chip-Scale Iodine Vapor Cell Fabrication]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>255916.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>255916</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Benaiah Schrag</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bschrag@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928323</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Technology Transfer (STTR) Phase I project is to improve measurement science.  Currently, special low-pressure chambers known as "vapor cells" are made by hand in a select number of precision glassblowing shops and suffer from poor dimensional reproducibility, low production capacity, irregular sizes, and variable vapor composition leading to a multifaceted limitation in the marketplace. Optical frequency references on the market today are large, costly, and power-hungry, but are used in a variety of commercial opportunities throughout industrial metrology markets. This study aims to produce a repeatable recipe suitable for high-volume production of miniature vapor cells. The results of this study will lead to the scalable production of references that would be intrinsically trustworthy and perform well in a continuous manner over many years.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This STTR Phase I project will leverage micromachining of glass and silicon to enable a new fabrication method for a traditionally handmade component: a glass-blown vapor cell. The research objective of this study is to test if such a method can yield a compact and reproducible vapor cell. Research will employ semiconductor processing techniques and optical frequency metrology to deduce the long-term stability and accuracy of these vapor cells in order to assess their suitability as optical frequency references. The anticipated technical results of this study include a potential pathway to a mass-produced optical frequency standard suitable for optical clocks, interferometers, and wavemeters. Such a technology would underpin accurate measurement science in high-performance optical measurement equipment.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/03/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/06/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041, 47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2035963</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Leo</FirstName>
<LastName>Hollberg</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Leo Hollberg</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[leoh@stanford.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000792635</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/03/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Douglas</FirstName>
<LastName>Bopp</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>G</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Douglas G Bopp</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[dougbopp@gmail.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000828319</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/03/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>VAPOR CELL TECHNOLOGIES LLC</Name>
<CityName>BOULDER</CityName>
<ZipCode>803024606</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6024306907</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2237 PINE ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>JBL9ZKN6S8K8</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>VAPOR CELL TECHNOLOGIES LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[VAPOR CELL TECHNOLOGIES LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>Boulder</CityName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>803024606</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2237 pine street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1505</Code>
<Text>STTR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8035</Code>
<Text>Hardware Devices</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~255916</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Vapor Cell Technologies is pleased to report the successful and  repeatable fabrication of chip-scale Iodine vapor cells using  semiconductor micromachining and bonding techniques and the invention of  two novel methods to control the mass of deposited Iodine. Multiple  cells were fabricated repeatedly using an optimized process recipe  distinct from traditional bonding recipes.</p> <p>In collaboration with Professor Leo Hollberg of Stanford University, optical  frequency measurements were performed on vapor cells which were shown to  have no observable change in optical absorption depth over 7+ months at  elevated temperatures of 60 C and having undergone multiple thermal  cyclings from 20 to 100 C. Cycled vapor cells indicate strong bonds and  survive dicing. Optical measurements indicate a high signal to noise ratio (SNR) over 4,000 in a  1 s bandwidth suitable for optical frequency references. Integration  with ultra-miniature circuitry enabled reproducible results and  easy integration into optical systems.</p> <p>These results indicate successful demonstration of Iodine  vapor cell construction using semiconductor bonding techniques. As  Iodine is a molecule with many well-characterized optical resonances  across the visible and is used as one of the major constituents of  standard frequencies listed by the <span class="yKMVIe">International Bureau of Weights and Measures</span> (BIPM), these results indicate the  potential to disseminate accurate and stable optical frequencies  throughout compact and mass-producible photonic technologies with  mm-scale characteristic geometries. Use of Iodine spectra enables optical sensing technologies such as spectrometers to be calibrated continuously and with high certitude even in the presence of environmental disturbances.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/23/2023<br>      Modified by: Douglas&nbsp;G&nbsp;Bopp</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2035963/2035963_10720347_1677111924893_I2Vaporcellzoomcircle--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2035963/2035963_10720347_1677111924893_I2Vaporcellzoomcircle--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Chip-scale I2 Vapor Cell Variant 1"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2035963/2035963_10720347_1677111924893_I2Vaporcellzoomcircle--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Chip-scale I2 Vapor Cell Variant 1"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Chip-scale I2 Vapor Cell Variant 1 pictured next to a dime. Cell is mm-scale and indicates exceptional bond quality.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Douglas Bopp</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Douglas&nbsp;G&nbsp;Bopp</div> <div class="imageTitle">Chip-scale I2 Vapor Cell Variant 1</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Vapor Cell Technologies is pleased to report the successful and  repeatable fabrication of chip-scale Iodine vapor cells using  semiconductor micromachining and bonding techniques and the invention of  two novel methods to control the mass of deposited Iodine. Multiple  cells were fabricated repeatedly using an optimized process recipe  distinct from traditional bonding recipes.  In collaboration with Professor Leo Hollberg of Stanford University, optical  frequency measurements were performed on vapor cells which were shown to  have no observable change in optical absorption depth over 7+ months at  elevated temperatures of 60 C and having undergone multiple thermal  cyclings from 20 to 100 C. Cycled vapor cells indicate strong bonds and  survive dicing. Optical measurements indicate a high signal to noise ratio (SNR) over 4,000 in a  1 s bandwidth suitable for optical frequency references. Integration  with ultra-miniature circuitry enabled reproducible results and  easy integration into optical systems.  These results indicate successful demonstration of Iodine  vapor cell construction using semiconductor bonding techniques. As  Iodine is a molecule with many well-characterized optical resonances  across the visible and is used as one of the major constituents of  standard frequencies listed by the International Bureau of Weights and Measures (BIPM), these results indicate the  potential to disseminate accurate and stable optical frequencies  throughout compact and mass-producible photonic technologies with  mm-scale characteristic geometries. Use of Iodine spectra enables optical sensing technologies such as spectrometers to be calibrated continuously and with high certitude even in the presence of environmental disturbances.       Last Modified: 02/23/2023       Submitted by: Douglas G Bopp]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
