<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Self-defense wristband]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>256000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>256000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Muralidharan Nair</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mnair@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927059</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research Phase I project may lead to an innovative self-defense wristband so that users will not have to remember to carry additional items. The potential users may already be wearing a Fitbit, Apple Watch, etc. This device will address the limitations of current devices, which include: charging a separate device, placing a device in the current purse or grabbing it before leaving the house, being alert when walking around, fumbling for a device if attacked, remembering how to use a security device, pointing the device in the right direction, or activating the device in a surprise attack.  The wristband will sense the user struggling and activate automatically. The wearable self-defense wristband will benefit current self-defense product owners, college students, concerned spouses and family members, people who exercise or work alone. etc.. The goal of this project is to enable self-protection for the public and achieve swift and sustained support.  It is anticipated that the wearable, threat-protection product could deter 1 million attacks by 2030.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project will develop the first Internet of Things (IoT), hands-free, and wrist-worn self-defense device. The device will be motion-activated. A gyro/accelerometer will be programmed to activate defense features when the correct motion is applied.  This wearable self-defense device will be easy and quick to activate, reliable to respond, safe to use, and comfortable for the wearer, as well as aesthetically pleasing. For the Phase I project, the features that will be enabled in the self-defense wristband include a siren, a strobe light, and a GPS ping to designated contacts and/or a 24/7 security firm that will call the user back and call emergency responders, if needed. The key technical hurdles are combining all targeted features in one compact device, while triggering the self-defense wristband consistently and safely.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/21/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/08/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041, 47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2035671</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Troy</FirstName>
<LastName>Dugo</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>F</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Troy F Dugo</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[tfdugo@gmail.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000824266</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/21/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>WEARABLE DEFENSE, LLC</Name>
<CityName>CHARLOTTE</CityName>
<ZipCode>282084872</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7049957938</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1749 LELA AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>X3EUXRKVLD25</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WEARABLE DEFENSE LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[WEARABLE DEFENSE, LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>CHARLOTTE</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>282084872</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1749 LELA AVE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1185</Code>
<Text>SENSORY SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8033</Code>
<Text>Hardware Software Integration</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~256000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-461d39ba-7fff-3c90-e58e-01030de55908"><strong>The Problem</strong><span>: Despite the FBI statistics of 24 sexual assaults every hour, less than 4% of the 200 women interviewed actually carry any type of self-defense device. "It's in the other purse, I forgot it at home, it's in the car, it's too bulky" in summary - lack of convenience.&nbsp;</span></span></p> <p><strong>Solution:</strong>&nbsp;<span id="docs-internal-guid-63931b74-7fff-f986-47ed-2a9ebe6d2132"><span>Wearable Defense, LLC will&nbsp;produce the world's most convenient self-defense device. It is a wristband that is truly hands-free that will offer the quickest response over anything else on the market.&nbsp;</span></span></p> <p><span id="docs-internal-guid-63931b74-7fff-f986-47ed-2a9ebe6d2132"><span>https://youtu.be/tL4x0IxalHc</span></span></p> <p>If you feel threatened, <strong>two quick twists of the wrist</strong> is all it takes to activate 5 built-in features:</p> <ol> <li>A stun gun for immediate protection</li> <li>A loud siren and a&nbsp;</li> <li>Bright Strobe light to cause a scene</li> <li>Through IoT technology it will send out a GPS ping to your friends &amp; family you choose from the app and&nbsp;</li> <li>Place a call into an established 24/7 call center so they can determine the level of help you need</li> </ol> <p><strong>Moreover</strong>,<span id="docs-internal-guid-f3ef13d9-7fff-a2e9-343a-a07b93ebc853"><span>&nbsp;i</span><span>f attacked from behind</span><span>, the wristband's internal gyro will sense your arms flailing about and the wristband</span><span>&nbsp;will <strong>automatically</strong> turn on all the features and notify 911. So <strong>"When you're not ready, you're ready".&nbsp;</strong></span></span></p> <p><span><span><span id="docs-internal-guid-24b07df8-7fff-db13-3fba-8a065b1c53b1"><span>Our cool looking wristbands are&nbsp;so convenient that you will actually </span><strong>want </strong><span>to wear them. The </span><span>patented wristband</span><span>&nbsp;can be worn by itself and future models will accomodate&nbsp;</span><strong>the wrist bands on the fitness trackers or Apple Watches you are already wearing</strong><span> (A $64 Billion market) our blue ocean opportunity! Therer will be nothing to have to remember to carry. Nothing else to charge up. No need to to remember to be alert when out and about.&nbsp;</span></span></span></span></p> <p><strong>In Phase I</strong>&nbsp;we successfully produced a workig alpha model. In Phase II we will make it smaller yet, and make models to accomodate Apple Watches and other wrist-worn devices.&nbsp;</p> <p>We plan on rolling this out to the 10 million American college women as we will be partnering up with women's campus advocacy groups returning some of the proceeds to their cause. Other groups that will benefit are the more than 1 million women Realtors, women joggers, as well as other well-defined groups. We are creating a whole new wearable IoT tech niche. As the first player in this space, Wearable Defense, LLC will be setting the standard and owning this market through continued innovation.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Statement of purpose:</strong> Until the world is a safer place for our loved ones, Wearable Defense will be <strong>the </strong>recognized leader in chic wearable threat deterrents and will deter 1 million attacks over the next 10 years.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/21/2021<br>      Modified by: Troy&nbsp;F&nbsp;Dugo</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2035671/2035671_10711605_1640035277371_refinement5--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2035671/2035671_10711605_1640035277371_refinement5--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Rendering #1"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2035671/2035671_10711605_1640035277371_refinement5--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Rendering #1"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Stand-alone model #1</div> <div class="imageCredit">Wearable Defense, LLC</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Troy&nbsp;F&nbsp;Dugo</div> <div class="imageTitle">Rendering #1</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2035671/2035671_10711605_1640035366242_Refinement3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2035671/2035671_10711605_1640035366242_Refinement3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Rendering #2"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2035671/2035671_10711605_1640035366242_Refinement3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Rendering #2"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Black with copper fittings</div> <div class="imageCredit">Wearable Defense, LLC</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Troy&nbsp;F&nbsp;Dugo</div> <div class="imageTitle">Rendering #2</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2035671/2035671_10711605_1640035465681_refinement4--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2035671/2035671_10711605_1640035465681_refinement4--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Working Out"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2035671/2035671_10711605_1640035465681_refinement4--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Working Out"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Always available</div> <div class="imageCredit">Wearable Defense, LLC</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Troy&nbsp;F&nbsp;Dugo</div> <div class="imageTitle">Working Out</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2035671/2035671_10711605_1640038846410_Alpha1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2035671/2035671_10711605_1640038846410_Alpha1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Alpha Larger Model"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2035671/2035671_10711605_1640038846410_Alpha1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Alpha Larger Model"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Larger gray version</div> <div class="imageCredit">Wearable Defense, LLC</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Troy&nbsp;F&nbsp;Dugo</div> <div class="imageTitle">Alpha Larger Model</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2035671/2035671_10711605_1640115140691_Alpha2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2035671/2035671_10711605_1640115140691_Alpha2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Small Alpha"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2035671/2035671_10711605_1640115140691_Alpha2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Small Alpha"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Smaller size</div> <div class="imageCredit">Wearable Defense, LLC</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Troy&nbsp;F&nbsp;Dugo</div> <div class="imageTitle">Small Alpha</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Problem: Despite the FBI statistics of 24 sexual assaults every hour, less than 4% of the 200 women interviewed actually carry any type of self-defense device. "It's in the other purse, I forgot it at home, it's in the car, it's too bulky" in summary - lack of convenience.   Solution: Wearable Defense, LLC will produce the world's most convenient self-defense device. It is a wristband that is truly hands-free that will offer the quickest response over anything else on the market.   https://youtu.be/tL4x0IxalHc  If you feel threatened, two quick twists of the wrist is all it takes to activate 5 built-in features:  A stun gun for immediate protection A loud siren and a  Bright Strobe light to cause a scene Through IoT technology it will send out a GPS ping to your friends &amp; family you choose from the app and  Place a call into an established 24/7 call center so they can determine the level of help you need   Moreover, if attacked from behind, the wristband's internal gyro will sense your arms flailing about and the wristband will automatically turn on all the features and notify 911. So "When you're not ready, you're ready".   Our cool looking wristbands are so convenient that you will actually want to wear them. The patented wristband can be worn by itself and future models will accomodate the wrist bands on the fitness trackers or Apple Watches you are already wearing (A $64 Billion market) our blue ocean opportunity! Therer will be nothing to have to remember to carry. Nothing else to charge up. No need to to remember to be alert when out and about.   In Phase I we successfully produced a workig alpha model. In Phase II we will make it smaller yet, and make models to accomodate Apple Watches and other wrist-worn devices.   We plan on rolling this out to the 10 million American college women as we will be partnering up with women's campus advocacy groups returning some of the proceeds to their cause. Other groups that will benefit are the more than 1 million women Realtors, women joggers, as well as other well-defined groups. We are creating a whole new wearable IoT tech niche. As the first player in this space, Wearable Defense, LLC will be setting the standard and owning this market through continued innovation.    Statement of purpose: Until the world is a safer place for our loved ones, Wearable Defense will be the recognized leader in chic wearable threat deterrents and will deter 1 million attacks over the next 10 years.       Last Modified: 12/21/2021       Submitted by: Troy F Dugo]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
