<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Development of High Efficiency Thermoelectric Materials for Sub 200K Space Applications]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>256000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>256000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anna Brady</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>abrady@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927077</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovative Research (SBIR) Phase I project will advance the state-of-the-art in low temperature thermoelectric devices for space applications enabling advanced space travel as well as improvements to satellite wireless and worldwide mobile internet availability.  With the increased interest in space exploration from industrial efforts, a significantly improved low temperature thermoelectric module could capture a sizable portion of the rapidly growing thermoelectric module market which is estimated to be ~$1 Billion by 2024.  Significantly improved low temperature thermoelectrics would also open the door for the use of these devices in other low temperature thermal management systems, where the poor efficiency of cooling technologies operating in the cryogenic regime have been a major challenge.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovative Research Phase I project aims to improve the efficiency (ZT) of thermoelectric cooling modules using advanced materials and a novel module design concept.  Bismuth-antimony (BiSb)-based single crystal materials with applied magnetic fields have long been known as the highest performance materials for sub 100K applications but they have not yet found commercial utility due to a variety of challenges.  The research effort aims to address these challenges and develop both p-type and n-type single crystal BiSb based alloys with ZT &gt; 0.4 at 90 K and application of less than 1 Tesla magnetic field, which would be a four-fold improvement in efficiency at sub 100 K compared to current state of the art.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/23/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/20/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041, 47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2035074</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Robin</FirstName>
<LastName>Ihnfeldt</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>V</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Robin V Ihnfeldt</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[rihnfeldt@geandr.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000550785</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/23/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>General Engineering &amp; Research, L.L.C.</Name>
<CityName>SAN DIEGO</CityName>
<ZipCode>921211527</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8587365069</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>10459 ROSELLE ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[STE A]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>50</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA50</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>GKKUTN2NGXJ5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GENERAL ENGINEERING &amp; RESEARCH, L.L.C.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[General Engineering & Research LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>San Diego</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>921211527</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[10459 Roselle St Ste A]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>50</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA50</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>024E</Code>
<Text>MATERIALS DESIGN</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1218</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED TECHNOLOGIES &amp; INSTRM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~256000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Thermoelectric (TE) modules, also known as Peltier coolers or thermoelectric coolers (TEC), are a key component that provide stabilized temperature control of electronics, such as UV/Vis detectors and sensors.&nbsp; For space applications, the desirable characteristics are their small size and solid-state structure.&nbsp; With no moving parts, TE modules are highly durable and have no maintenance requirements.&nbsp; Unfortunately, the current commercially available TE modules have a thermal cooling lower limit of ~140K (or -130<sup>o</sup>C).&nbsp; Very little progress has been made in improving TE modules for this low temperature regime due to a variety of challenges.&nbsp; The difficulty in synthesizing new TE materials and characterizing their properties at low temperature, obtaining/maintaining the regulatory compliance to supply into the space/defense industry, and the lack of competition due to supply chain and manufacturing limitations that exist in the US market, are just a few named challenges.&nbsp; Currently the only commercial suppliers of low temperature TE modules utilize similar Bismuth Tellurium (BiTe) based materials as room temperature TE modules.&nbsp;</p> <p>According to the 2020 NASA Technology Taxonomy Report, &ldquo;the future thermal control needs for spacecraft will require development of technologies that can more effectively transfer heat, as well as methods to advance robustness, life, efficiency, and temperature range of operability.&rdquo;&nbsp; While the need for low temperature TE modules has existed for decades, the past several years this need has been intensified by new developments in UV/IR/Vis detector and CCD sensor technologies used in satellites and other space applications, as well as terrestrial defense articles, which function optimally when cooled to extreme temperatures (i.e. maintaining these sensors at low temperatures reduces noise generation and improves sensitivities/performance).&nbsp; In fact, when cooled to cryogenic temperatures (down to ~80-100K), the performance of these sensors can be significantly improved and/or their functionality enabled.&nbsp;</p> <p>The properties of TE materials are typically characterized by a dimensionless parameter known as the figure of merit, <em>ZT</em>,<em> </em>where <em>T</em> is the absolute temperature, and<em> Z</em> is given as <em>Z</em> = <em>S<sup>2</sup></em><em>s</em> /<em>k</em>, where <em>S</em> is the Seebeck coefficient, <em>s</em> is the electrical conductivity, and <em>k</em> is the thermal conductivity.&nbsp; To improve the efficiency of TE devices, the development of materials with higher <em>ZT</em> is required.&nbsp; A TE cooling device requires coupled <em>n</em>-type and <em>p</em>-type cooling legs with similar thermoelectric characteristics to function optimally.&nbsp; In practice, ZT values for both the n- and p-type pellets need to be ~0.2 or higher over the entire desired temperature range of use for the TE module to function.&nbsp; For the BiTe alloys used in current TE modules, the temperature range where ZT&gt;0.2 is ~140-500K, hence the lower thermal limit of 140K.&nbsp;</p> <p>Finding a suitable TE material set for low temperature is not trivial.&nbsp; Synthesizing TE materials in useful quantities typically requires complicated heat treatment processing in specialty furnaces to achieve homogeneous crystal structures with high ZT.&nbsp; Additionally, accurately characterizing TE properties at low temperature requires special equipment (we have this equipment in-house).&nbsp;</p> <p>The goal of the Phase I SBIR effort was to discover a TE material set with a feasible path to provide high efficiency functionality at sub 200K temperatures and significantly improve current state-of-the-art. This goal was accomplished.&nbsp; We successfully developed an n-type TE composition which provides high efficiency performance at sub 200K temperatures compared to current known TE materials, scalable synthetic methods, and utilizes economical elemental compositions that can be obtained from US or US allied countries (i.e. no Tellurium).&nbsp; With further TE process optimization and development of module manufacturing capabilities we expect to double the ZT for sub 150K, significantly improving the performance of current state-of-the-art TE modules for applications at 140K which is the current temperature limitation for TECs.&nbsp; Further, if successful our low temperature TE modules would enable the use of TE technology for applications down to 80K, which would open an array of new high performance possibilities for IR/UV/Visible detectors, CCD sensors, and other electronic components both terrestrially and in space environments.&nbsp;&nbsp; Our Phase II SBIR application has been prepared and submitted which details our Phase I results and potential future work.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/01/2023<br>      Modified by: Robin&nbsp;V&nbsp;Ihnfeldt</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Thermoelectric (TE) modules, also known as Peltier coolers or thermoelectric coolers (TEC), are a key component that provide stabilized temperature control of electronics, such as UV/Vis detectors and sensors.  For space applications, the desirable characteristics are their small size and solid-state structure.  With no moving parts, TE modules are highly durable and have no maintenance requirements.  Unfortunately, the current commercially available TE modules have a thermal cooling lower limit of ~140K (or -130oC).  Very little progress has been made in improving TE modules for this low temperature regime due to a variety of challenges.  The difficulty in synthesizing new TE materials and characterizing their properties at low temperature, obtaining/maintaining the regulatory compliance to supply into the space/defense industry, and the lack of competition due to supply chain and manufacturing limitations that exist in the US market, are just a few named challenges.  Currently the only commercial suppliers of low temperature TE modules utilize similar Bismuth Tellurium (BiTe) based materials as room temperature TE modules.   According to the 2020 NASA Technology Taxonomy Report, "the future thermal control needs for spacecraft will require development of technologies that can more effectively transfer heat, as well as methods to advance robustness, life, efficiency, and temperature range of operability."  While the need for low temperature TE modules has existed for decades, the past several years this need has been intensified by new developments in UV/IR/Vis detector and CCD sensor technologies used in satellites and other space applications, as well as terrestrial defense articles, which function optimally when cooled to extreme temperatures (i.e. maintaining these sensors at low temperatures reduces noise generation and improves sensitivities/performance).  In fact, when cooled to cryogenic temperatures (down to ~80-100K), the performance of these sensors can be significantly improved and/or their functionality enabled.   The properties of TE materials are typically characterized by a dimensionless parameter known as the figure of merit, ZT, where T is the absolute temperature, and Z is given as Z = S2s /k, where S is the Seebeck coefficient, s is the electrical conductivity, and k is the thermal conductivity.  To improve the efficiency of TE devices, the development of materials with higher ZT is required.  A TE cooling device requires coupled n-type and p-type cooling legs with similar thermoelectric characteristics to function optimally.  In practice, ZT values for both the n- and p-type pellets need to be ~0.2 or higher over the entire desired temperature range of use for the TE module to function.  For the BiTe alloys used in current TE modules, the temperature range where ZT&gt;0.2 is ~140-500K, hence the lower thermal limit of 140K.   Finding a suitable TE material set for low temperature is not trivial.  Synthesizing TE materials in useful quantities typically requires complicated heat treatment processing in specialty furnaces to achieve homogeneous crystal structures with high ZT.  Additionally, accurately characterizing TE properties at low temperature requires special equipment (we have this equipment in-house).   The goal of the Phase I SBIR effort was to discover a TE material set with a feasible path to provide high efficiency functionality at sub 200K temperatures and significantly improve current state-of-the-art. This goal was accomplished.  We successfully developed an n-type TE composition which provides high efficiency performance at sub 200K temperatures compared to current known TE materials, scalable synthetic methods, and utilizes economical elemental compositions that can be obtained from US or US allied countries (i.e. no Tellurium).  With further TE process optimization and development of module manufacturing capabilities we expect to double the ZT for sub 150K, significantly improving the performance of current state-of-the-art TE modules for applications at 140K which is the current temperature limitation for TECs.  Further, if successful our low temperature TE modules would enable the use of TE technology for applications down to 80K, which would open an array of new high performance possibilities for IR/UV/Visible detectors, CCD sensors, and other electronic components both terrestrially and in space environments.   Our Phase II SBIR application has been prepared and submitted which details our Phase I results and potential future work.        Last Modified: 04/01/2023       Submitted by: Robin V Ihnfeldt]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
