<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  A high-efficiency filter for endotoxin removal]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>235506.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>235506</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Henry Ahn</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>hahn@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927069</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is to develop a system to improve pharmaceutical manufacturing and sepsis treatment. A toxic substance known as endotoxin is a common contaminant in many types of therapeutics, and it is the primary cause of batch rejection in pharmaceutical manufacturing. The economic impact of pharmaceutical batch failure due to contamination is high due to loss of product and facility closure for cleaning. The endotoxin removal market within drug manufacturing was valued at $315 million in 2018 and is expected to grow due to the increase in biopharmaceutical products. Additionally, endotoxins are dangerous when they enter patients’ bloodstream and can cause various medical complications, including sepsis.  The technology has the potential to remove endotoxins from patients’ bloodstream more effectively than current solutions  This project will develop a universal high-efficiency endotoxin removal filter that has the potential to not only improve drug manufacturing but also provide a life-saving treatment for sepsis.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project will develop a high-affinity, high-specificity filter for endotoxin removal by using a protein that specifically binds endotoxin and has been shown to remove 99.9% of endotoxin from protein preparations. Traditionally, the use of proteins for product separations cause problems with durability and protein density, stability, and activity. These problems are overcome with unique materials that allow 100% incorporation of active proteins via a stable fusion with substantially increased protein stability. The binding capacity of the materials for endotoxin similar to current solutions (5,000,000 EU/mL) would be considered successful, although the binding capacity is expected to greatly exceed the current standard. Current solutions are compatible with only specific types of therapeutics. A prototype filter will be evaluated for endotoxin separation and protein recovery for three protein therapeutics. An 80% recovery of each therapeutic is expected, with simultaneous removal of 5,000,000 EU/mL of endotoxin. These tests will prove the technical feasibility of the prototype filter by showing the materials have a significantly higher binding capacity for endotoxin than current methods and that they are compatible with multiple types of therapeutics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/30/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/26/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041, 47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2035882</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Howell</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David W Howell</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[dwhowell11@gmail.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000761292</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/30/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>BONDWELL TECHNOLOGIES LP</Name>
<CityName>COLLEGE STATION</CityName>
<ZipCode>778459660</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9794754545</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>415 GRAHAM RD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>KC2RGD3DS457</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>BONDWELL TECHNOLOGIES LP</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Bondwell Technologies]]></Name>
<CityName>College Station</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>778459662</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[415 Graham Rd]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>004E</Code>
<Text>BIOMEDICAL ENG AND DIAGNOSTICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~235506</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Bacterial endotoxin produced by Gram-negative bacteria can enter the bloodstream and cause sepsis, a leading and increasing cause of mortality worldwide. There is currently no adequate therapy for sepsis. An effective method to remove endotoxins would have two critical uses: first, contamination of biopharmaceutical products during production poses a significant risk because endotoxin is so prevalent, toxic, and stable. Current strategies significantly lower product yields and/or increase the operational burden. Second, hemoperfusion in which the circulating endotoxins in blood is removed by selective adsorption, could be a promising sepsis therapy. However, the available methods to remove endotoxin through hemoperfusion therapy lack the capacity and specificity to significantly reduce mortality.</p> <p>All current techniques for both biomanufacturing and sepsis therapy adsorb endotoxin to small molecules bound to the surface of a support, such as polystyrene beads. In this project we will develop a universal high-capacity, low-cost endotoxin removal filter that could not only revolutionize the bioprocessing industry, but also provide a life-saving treatment for sepsis in future studies.</p> <p><span>The following objectives will test feasibility of our anticipated technical advantages: 1)&nbsp;Demonstrate that our materials can bind more endotoxin than current standard capacity (5,000,000 EU/mL) solutions in a single step.&nbsp;2) Evaluate endotoxin separation and protein recovery for a variety of protein therapeutics.</span></p> <p>The first objective was to optimize production of our protein based materials in <em>P. pichia</em>. This first required cloning the protein sequence into a new vector for expression in <em>P. pichia. </em>Once transfected, the yeast should secrete the protein into the media for collection and purification. We determined that the protein was not being secreted as expected. Therefore, we developed a process for lysing the yeast cells and purifying the protein. This took considerable time and effort before we learned that proteases in the yeast were cleaving the protein and removing the function of binding endotoxin. The protein was the correct size using standard test however mass spec analysis showed that several amino acids were being cleaved.</p> <p>Therefore, we engaged Genscript Scientific to design secretary tags so that the protein could be secreted into the media as originally planned. However, after 2 months a trying Genscript reported that the protein cannot be expressed in <em>P. pichia.</em> To complete Objective 1, we plan to use cell free protein synthesis (see changes in approach section). We are currently in talks with a CMO and will pursue this method at our own expense as we prepare for a Phase II submission.</p> <p>To complete Objective 2, we are currently expressing in <em>E. coli</em> ClearColi however, we discovered that endotoxin from other projects in the lab was contaminating the material. The material was already saturated with endotoxin prior to conducting experiments so we saw no binding of Endotoxin to our materials. One way to solve this would be to manufacture under GMP conditions however, that is not feasible at this early stage of production. Therefore, we created a proprietary equilibrating buffer that strips the material of endotoxin and allows us to bind endotoxin as shown in the preliminary data. We didn&rsquo;t discover this issue during the preliminary experiments because there were no other projects in the lab and therefore not a significant source of endotoxin to contaminate the experiments. We have replicated binding experiments demonstrated in the preliminary data after the endotoxin is stripped from the material however, the project time has ended. We are currently undertaking the experiments described in Objective 2 at our own expense.</p> <p>This project has encountered both technical problems and real-world delays. First, we have had to shut down the lab twice during this project due to employee COVID protocols. Additionally, the supply chain shortages have impacted both general lab efficiency but also this project specifically. Endotoxin test kits, reagents, and endotoxin free water are all required for this project and are also crucial to larger player&rsquo;s roles in fighting the pandemic. This led to significant delays in being able to complete this project on time. We now have enough supplies in hand to finish the proposed experiments.</p> <p>From a technical perspective, there were multiple unforseen problems that forced us to invent solutions before being able to complete the proposed experiments. The data generated in this project shows feasibility of this technology for endotoxin filtration however, we must complete the proposed experiments at our own cost before submitting a Phase II application.</p> <p><span><br /></span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/15/2022<br>      Modified by: David&nbsp;W&nbsp;Howell</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Bacterial endotoxin produced by Gram-negative bacteria can enter the bloodstream and cause sepsis, a leading and increasing cause of mortality worldwide. There is currently no adequate therapy for sepsis. An effective method to remove endotoxins would have two critical uses: first, contamination of biopharmaceutical products during production poses a significant risk because endotoxin is so prevalent, toxic, and stable. Current strategies significantly lower product yields and/or increase the operational burden. Second, hemoperfusion in which the circulating endotoxins in blood is removed by selective adsorption, could be a promising sepsis therapy. However, the available methods to remove endotoxin through hemoperfusion therapy lack the capacity and specificity to significantly reduce mortality.  All current techniques for both biomanufacturing and sepsis therapy adsorb endotoxin to small molecules bound to the surface of a support, such as polystyrene beads. In this project we will develop a universal high-capacity, low-cost endotoxin removal filter that could not only revolutionize the bioprocessing industry, but also provide a life-saving treatment for sepsis in future studies.  The following objectives will test feasibility of our anticipated technical advantages: 1) Demonstrate that our materials can bind more endotoxin than current standard capacity (5,000,000 EU/mL) solutions in a single step. 2) Evaluate endotoxin separation and protein recovery for a variety of protein therapeutics.  The first objective was to optimize production of our protein based materials in P. pichia. This first required cloning the protein sequence into a new vector for expression in P. pichia. Once transfected, the yeast should secrete the protein into the media for collection and purification. We determined that the protein was not being secreted as expected. Therefore, we developed a process for lysing the yeast cells and purifying the protein. This took considerable time and effort before we learned that proteases in the yeast were cleaving the protein and removing the function of binding endotoxin. The protein was the correct size using standard test however mass spec analysis showed that several amino acids were being cleaved.  Therefore, we engaged Genscript Scientific to design secretary tags so that the protein could be secreted into the media as originally planned. However, after 2 months a trying Genscript reported that the protein cannot be expressed in P. pichia. To complete Objective 1, we plan to use cell free protein synthesis (see changes in approach section). We are currently in talks with a CMO and will pursue this method at our own expense as we prepare for a Phase II submission.  To complete Objective 2, we are currently expressing in E. coli ClearColi however, we discovered that endotoxin from other projects in the lab was contaminating the material. The material was already saturated with endotoxin prior to conducting experiments so we saw no binding of Endotoxin to our materials. One way to solve this would be to manufacture under GMP conditions however, that is not feasible at this early stage of production. Therefore, we created a proprietary equilibrating buffer that strips the material of endotoxin and allows us to bind endotoxin as shown in the preliminary data. We didn’t discover this issue during the preliminary experiments because there were no other projects in the lab and therefore not a significant source of endotoxin to contaminate the experiments. We have replicated binding experiments demonstrated in the preliminary data after the endotoxin is stripped from the material however, the project time has ended. We are currently undertaking the experiments described in Objective 2 at our own expense.  This project has encountered both technical problems and real-world delays. First, we have had to shut down the lab twice during this project due to employee COVID protocols. Additionally, the supply chain shortages have impacted both general lab efficiency but also this project specifically. Endotoxin test kits, reagents, and endotoxin free water are all required for this project and are also crucial to larger player’s roles in fighting the pandemic. This led to significant delays in being able to complete this project on time. We now have enough supplies in hand to finish the proposed experiments.  From a technical perspective, there were multiple unforseen problems that forced us to invent solutions before being able to complete the proposed experiments. The data generated in this project shows feasibility of this technology for endotoxin filtration however, we must complete the proposed experiments at our own cost before submitting a Phase II application.          Last Modified: 07/15/2022       Submitted by: David W Howell]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
