<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[NSF Convergence Accelerator: Workshop for the Development of Infrastructure for Distributed Bio-Manufacturing and Bio-Readiness]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>33561.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>33561</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01060500</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OIA</Abbreviation>
<LongName>OIA-Office of Integrative Activities</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Linda Molnar</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lmolnar@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928316</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Our ability to rapidly manufacture bio-based solutions like therapeutics, materials, and bio-energy is crucial to our national economic advantage and national security. An agile national infrastructure to distribute the manufacturing of biological materials as well as provide the nation with a level of “bio-readiness” to address global pandemics and bio-threats is crucial in the 21st century. This research area will produce a distributed network of facilities, equipment, software, protocols, techniques, and personnel to develop applications and technology as well as to respond to bio-threats such as global warming and international pandemics. Sharing resources, software, training, personnel, and expertise will allow new centers to be created quickly in the face of national threats or economic needs. This effort will be inherently interdisciplinary and require computer scientists, material scientists, molecular biologists, government officials, legal expertise, and business leaders. It will include academic, government, and commercial partners at all scales. It will be a truly unique effort.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This proposal is to organize a six-session virtual workshop series to develop a coherent set of Needs, Opportunities, and Challenges for Bio-Manufacturing and Bio-Readiness. This workshop series will result in a set of interdisciplinary reports that will be communicated to the National Science Foundation for consideration as a “Convergence Accelerator” Future Topic. The ideas generated during this workshop series will impact commercial as well as academic developments and research in bio-manufacturing, bio-security, and bio-readiness. Workforce development will require new training and create new personnel positions as a response. Models of collaboration between academic research and commercial business will be altered along with the legal and government agencies required to make these connections happen. If successful, this effort will change how the United States views its national manufacturing abilities as well as how it responds to potential global threats in the future. As a result, a well-defined, accessible, and continuously evolving set of tools, techniques, software, hardware, and personnel will be available to the United States and, as appropriate, globally.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/12/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/12/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.083</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2035346</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Douglas</FirstName>
<LastName>Densmore</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Douglas Densmore</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[doug.densmore@gmail.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000566028</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/12/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Trustees of Boston University</Name>
<CityName>BOSTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>022151703</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6173534365</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1 SILBER WAY</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>THL6A6JLE1S7</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF BOSTON UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Trustees of Boston University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>022151300</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>066Y</Code>
<Text>Program Planning and Policy De</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~33561</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This award sponsored five virtual workshops held September 29th, 30th, October 1st, 6th, and 8th 2020.&nbsp;&nbsp; Over 250 people expressed interest and registered for one of the workshop sessions. These sessions discussed broadly the topics of "Distributed Bio-Manufacturing and Bio-Readiness". &nbsp;Participants included academics, industry representatives, and community leaders. Fields represented included bioengineering, computer science, chemistry, economics, microbiology, and other STEM fields. The first 3 workshops were broad in scope and audience and the final 2 meetings narrowed the scope and participants. Topics included needs, challenges, and opportunities in the following four areas:</p> <ul> <li>Bioengineering Perspective</li> <li>Infrastructure Engineering Perspective</li> <li>Industry Perspective</li> <li>Law/Policy Perspective</li> </ul> <p>Breakout groups also included discussions of other resources such as DOE's Agile Biofoundry, the DARPA SD2 program, the DoD Manufacturing Innovation Institute, and the Global Biofoundries Alliance.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>Stakeholders and future participants were also identified during these workshops. &nbsp;Three sample programs were identified:</p> <ol> <li><em>Sample      Program 1:</em><strong> Infrastructure Development, Standards,      Knowledge Curation</strong> - Projects      in this classification would develop various manufacturing workflows and      identify the infrastructure needed to support them.</li> <li><em>Sample      Program 2:</em> <strong>Brokering Service Development </strong>- Projects in this      classification would help to create workflows and processes that help to      connect existing services and infrastructure to "customer" needs.</li> <li><em>Sample      Program 3:</em> <strong>Specific Manufacturing Challenges</strong> - Projects in this      classification would address specific bio-manufacturing grand challenges      to demonstrate the viability and effectiveness of particular approaches to      the topics in this area.</li> </ol> <p>The workshops themselves were also captured in a summary report made available to NSF.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/04/2022<br>      Modified by: Douglas&nbsp;Densmore</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This award sponsored five virtual workshops held September 29th, 30th, October 1st, 6th, and 8th 2020.   Over 250 people expressed interest and registered for one of the workshop sessions. These sessions discussed broadly the topics of "Distributed Bio-Manufacturing and Bio-Readiness".  Participants included academics, industry representatives, and community leaders. Fields represented included bioengineering, computer science, chemistry, economics, microbiology, and other STEM fields. The first 3 workshops were broad in scope and audience and the final 2 meetings narrowed the scope and participants. Topics included needs, challenges, and opportunities in the following four areas:  Bioengineering Perspective Infrastructure Engineering Perspective Industry Perspective Law/Policy Perspective   Breakout groups also included discussions of other resources such as DOE's Agile Biofoundry, the DARPA SD2 program, the DoD Manufacturing Innovation Institute, and the Global Biofoundries Alliance.    Stakeholders and future participants were also identified during these workshops.  Three sample programs were identified:  Sample      Program 1: Infrastructure Development, Standards,      Knowledge Curation - Projects      in this classification would develop various manufacturing workflows and      identify the infrastructure needed to support them. Sample      Program 2: Brokering Service Development - Projects in this      classification would help to create workflows and processes that help to      connect existing services and infrastructure to "customer" needs. Sample      Program 3: Specific Manufacturing Challenges - Projects in this      classification would address specific bio-manufacturing grand challenges      to demonstrate the viability and effectiveness of particular approaches to      the topics in this area.   The workshops themselves were also captured in a summary report made available to NSF.              Last Modified: 01/04/2022       Submitted by: Douglas Densmore]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
