<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[NSF Convergence Accelerator: Re-Think Nature for Innovative Solutions to Grand Challenges]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>66596.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>66596</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01060500</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OIA</Abbreviation>
<LongName>OIA-Office of Integrative Activities</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Nakhiah Goulbourne</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This grant provides financial support for the workshop entitled, "NSF Convergence Accelerator: Re-think Nature for Innovative Solutions to Grand Challenges", to be held virtually in the Fall 2020.  The workshop will bring together and expand collaboration among key stakeholders from academia, industry, and government with the charge of exploring grand challenges for the future of humanity and planet by leveraging nature-inspired solutions.  The workshop will focus on three areas: (1) nature-inspired solutions to petroleum-based plastics, (2) natural material-based solutions to clean water, and (3) advanced materials for sustainable infrastructure.  The proposed workshop will explore sustainable and nature-abundant materials by synthesizing new ideas, approaches, and technologies from diverse fields of knowledge to achieve scientific breakthroughs and exceptional innovation, with the ultimate goal to seek innovative solutions to grand challenges. By successfully integrating diverse disciplines in chemistry, materials science, engineering, data sciences, plant science, and public policy, the proposed convergence approach is poised to achieve cutting-edge discoveries in nature-abundant resources and unprecedented innovation in sustainable utilization of natural materials toward a wide range of potential applications.  For example, newly discovered properties of wood-sourced materials could be exploited for more sustainable and in many cases superior materials for products and processes that directly impact society, which is an excellent example of re-thinking nature-inspired solutions for humans and the planet.  While tremendous research possibilities exist, center to these opportunities is use-inspired convergence and building partnerships to transition discoveries into practice. The objective of this workshop is to review the recent progress and identify new directions and opportunities ripe for convergence research. Funding from this grant will go towards web hosting services for the workshop, and personnel support for organizing the workshop as well as the production of a report. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In this virtual workshop, invited leaders, researchers, innovators, and stake-holders with a diverse range of disciplinary expertise from across academia, government, and industry will discuss present and future challenges and opportunities for convergence related to nature-inspired solutions to grand challenges. The workshop will be comprised of three tracks, with a mixed format of invited talks, lightning talks, break out groups, and moderated discussions.  The format is intended to foster brain-storming discussions around the most important technical challenges in each topic and opportunities for future convergence research. This workshop will also feature panel discussions that will integrate the topics and discussions from the three sessions. The outcome of these presentations and discussions will be documented in a final report and will be widely disseminated across academia, government, and industry.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/12/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/12/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.083</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2035307</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Teng</FirstName>
<LastName>Li</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Teng Li</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[lit@umd.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000200610</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/12/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Liangbing</FirstName>
<LastName>Hu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Liangbing Hu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[binghu@umd.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000606296</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/12/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Maryland, College Park</Name>
<CityName>College Park</CityName>
<ZipCode>207420001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3014056269</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3112 LEE BLDG 7809 REGENTS DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MD04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NPU8ULVAAS23</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MARYLAND, COLLEGE PARK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>KMGEN62NKEM9</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Maryland College Park]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>207425103</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MD04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>066Y</Code>
<Text>Program Planning and Policy De</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~66596</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The workshop brought together 82 participants from academic institutions, national laboratories, government agencies, industries and non-profit organizations. It featured 20 lightning talks by leading experts and key stakeholders from multiple disciplines and sectors, and it held in-depth discussions among the participants. The workshop attendees discussed extensively the complexity and severity of the grand challenges associated with environmental pollution, energy sustainability, access to clean and safe water, and climate change, and the participants brainstormed the topics and solutions for addressing such grand challenges in near and intermediate terms through convergence research on two major topics:</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <ul> <li>Convergence research for nature-inspired solutions to replacement for petroleum-based plastics</li> <li>Convergence research for innovative solutions in the advanced materials space for sustainable infrastructure applicable to buildings, transportation, and water.</li> </ul> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Intellectual merit:</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The intellectual merit of the workshop includes an array of findings, such as:</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <ul> <li>There exists tremendous yet largely unexplored potential to explore nature-inspired solutions as a promising approach to address the grand challenges of petroleum-based plastics pollution and sustainable infrastructures.</li> <li>There have been groundbreaking research discoveries in the last several years to epitomize the remarkable potential of leveraging natural resources toward paradigm-shifting solutions to grand challenges in science and technology.</li> <li>A prioritization of research objectives alongside an array of clearly defined multi-dimensional criteria is needed to assess potential of replacement for petroleum-based plastics on sustainability and scalability.</li> <li>With the prioritization of research objectives and well-defined criteria as a key deliverable to Phase I, a more robust research agenda can be developed to enable the exploration of nature-inspired solutions for petroleum-based plastics with the greatest impact/most traction in Phase II.</li> <li>On the topic of advanced materials for sustainable infrastructure, three themes of research are needed: new functional materials<strong> </strong>based on natural materials;<strong> </strong>new applications<strong> </strong>based on natural materials (e.g., water, automotive), and<strong> </strong>new analytical tools (e.g., modeling, manufacturing, etc.).</li> <li>In designing complex composite materials based on hybridization of nature-inspired, renewable, and recycled resources meant to minimize environmental and social impacts, the participants identified great potentials and opportunities for convergent and interdisciplinary research toward a promising solution.</li> <li>Key disciplines and stakeholders are identified for the convergent research needed to address the above two grand challenges.</li> <li>The societal impacts of the proposed convergence research are expected to be multifaceted and far-reaching, with the widespread carbon-neutral applications in addressing an array of global challenges on sustainability.</li> <li>The proposed convergence research is expected to initiate an innovation-cultivating ecosystem through collaboration among academia, industrial and government partners at regional, national and global scales.</li> <li>The proposed convergence research will also train future workforce with the mindset of harnessing nature to solve global challenges of humankind.</li> </ul> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Broader impacts:</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The findings of this workshop will have broader impacts, including</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&#9679;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; depicting the current understanding of the grand challenges stemming from the ever-growing environmental pollution due to petroleum-based plastics and the non-sustainable nature of traditional infrastructure materials;</p> <p>&#9679;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; presenting key challenges and opportunities for convergence in exploring nature-inspired solutions to address the two focal topics described above; and&nbsp;</p> <p>&#9679;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; identifying the disciplines needed to understand and address the key challenges, and the stakeholders needed to be engaged and form integrated and coherent partnerships to form convergent teams in developing nature-inspired solutions for these grand challenges.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/01/2021<br>      Modified by: Teng&nbsp;Li</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The workshop brought together 82 participants from academic institutions, national laboratories, government agencies, industries and non-profit organizations. It featured 20 lightning talks by leading experts and key stakeholders from multiple disciplines and sectors, and it held in-depth discussions among the participants. The workshop attendees discussed extensively the complexity and severity of the grand challenges associated with environmental pollution, energy sustainability, access to clean and safe water, and climate change, and the participants brainstormed the topics and solutions for addressing such grand challenges in near and intermediate terms through convergence research on two major topics:     Convergence research for nature-inspired solutions to replacement for petroleum-based plastics Convergence research for innovative solutions in the advanced materials space for sustainable infrastructure applicable to buildings, transportation, and water.      Intellectual merit:     The intellectual merit of the workshop includes an array of findings, such as:     There exists tremendous yet largely unexplored potential to explore nature-inspired solutions as a promising approach to address the grand challenges of petroleum-based plastics pollution and sustainable infrastructures. There have been groundbreaking research discoveries in the last several years to epitomize the remarkable potential of leveraging natural resources toward paradigm-shifting solutions to grand challenges in science and technology. A prioritization of research objectives alongside an array of clearly defined multi-dimensional criteria is needed to assess potential of replacement for petroleum-based plastics on sustainability and scalability. With the prioritization of research objectives and well-defined criteria as a key deliverable to Phase I, a more robust research agenda can be developed to enable the exploration of nature-inspired solutions for petroleum-based plastics with the greatest impact/most traction in Phase II. On the topic of advanced materials for sustainable infrastructure, three themes of research are needed: new functional materials based on natural materials; new applications based on natural materials (e.g., water, automotive), and new analytical tools (e.g., modeling, manufacturing, etc.). In designing complex composite materials based on hybridization of nature-inspired, renewable, and recycled resources meant to minimize environmental and social impacts, the participants identified great potentials and opportunities for convergent and interdisciplinary research toward a promising solution. Key disciplines and stakeholders are identified for the convergent research needed to address the above two grand challenges. The societal impacts of the proposed convergence research are expected to be multifaceted and far-reaching, with the widespread carbon-neutral applications in addressing an array of global challenges on sustainability. The proposed convergence research is expected to initiate an innovation-cultivating ecosystem through collaboration among academia, industrial and government partners at regional, national and global scales. The proposed convergence research will also train future workforce with the mindset of harnessing nature to solve global challenges of humankind.         Broader impacts:     The findings of this workshop will have broader impacts, including     &#9679;      depicting the current understanding of the grand challenges stemming from the ever-growing environmental pollution due to petroleum-based plastics and the non-sustainable nature of traditional infrastructure materials;  &#9679;      presenting key challenges and opportunities for convergence in exploring nature-inspired solutions to address the two focal topics described above; and   &#9679;      identifying the disciplines needed to understand and address the key challenges, and the stakeholders needed to be engaged and form integrated and coherent partnerships to form convergent teams in developing nature-inspired solutions for these grand challenges.             Last Modified: 09/01/2021       Submitted by: Teng Li]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
