<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Catalyzing Systemic Change in Undergraduate Mathematics: A Convening of Mathematics Leaders]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>49135.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>49135</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Mike Ferrara</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mferrara@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922635</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Mathematics serves as a gateway to most STEM majors.  As a result, improving college mathematics contributes to preparation of the future STEM workforce. Based on research results, student outcomes in mathematics could be improved by using approaches such as interactive pedagogies, co-requisite courses, and enrichment and support programs.  However, entrenched practices and systemic challenges currently limit widespread adoption of these and other promising approaches. This multi-day virtual workshop will develop a comprehensive account of these challenges and begin exploring productive ways to move forward.  Leaders and researchers from a broad group of institutions and professional societies will discuss challenges to expanding the reach of high-impact programs.  They will share positive outcomes, strategies, and lessons learned and brainstorm how these results can be used to promote equity in the mathematical sciences.  A major outcome of the workshop will be a public report detailing the challenges that were identified within the mathematics higher education community. The report will also discuss how addressing those challenges might lead to more positive and equitable student outcomes.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This four-day virtual convening will bring together professional organization and community leaders to share their successes and challenges to achieve three main goals: (1) Sharing successful departmental, institutional, and professional society strategies and programs as a means for improving existing programs; (2) Identifying institutional and individual issues that limit the broader impact of existing strategies and programs; and (3) Formulating recommendations for how to move forward on the institutional and cultural change needed to address the identified issues. Each of the four workshop days will be approximately two to four weeks apart, allowing participants to engage in interim discussions and other work. The first session of the first workshop day will focus on detailing successful departmental, institutional, and professional society strategies and programs, including how equity issues are being addressed.  Participants will also discuss approaches to evaluate the reach of programs and benchmarks for moving forward. The remainder of the first day will focus on challenges to scaling programs and identifying forces that keep promising strategies and programs from having a broader impact. The second workshop day will have two working group sessions on systemic barriers, one structured by program type and the second structured across program type. The first session of the third day will focus on models of change that might be effective in different settings and discuss strategies that different participant groups might use to overcome specific challenges. The second session will focus on how the recommendations presented in the workshop report might address the identified challenges across different program types. The final day of the workshop, approximately one month after the third day, will allow participants to discuss and suggest improvements to a draft of the public report.   This award is funded through the NSF IUSE: EHR Program, which supports research and development projects to improve the effectiveness of STEM education for all students.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/16/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/20/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2035375</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Chris</FirstName>
<LastName>Rasmussen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Chris L Rasmussen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[crasmussen@mail.sdsu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000237247</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/22/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Kung</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>T</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David T Kung</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[david.kung@austin.utexas.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000339782</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/16/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>April</FirstName>
<LastName>Strom</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>April D Strom</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[april.strom@scottsdalecc.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000516412</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/16/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kiera</FirstName>
<LastName>Edwards</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kiera L Edwards</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[kedwards@maa.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000805110</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/16/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Mathematical Association of America</Name>
<CityName>WASHINGTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>200361206</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2023875200</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>11 DUPONT CIRCLE NW</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[STE 200]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>TY44D55D6B65</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>THE MATHEMATICAL ASSOCIATION OF AMERICA (INCORPORATED)</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Mathematical Association of Am]]></Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>200361385</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1529 18th Street, NW]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1998</Code>
<Text>IUSE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8209</Code>
<Text>Improv Undergrad STEM Ed(IUSE)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0421</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~49135</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p dir="ltr">Research suggests that there are many changes that would help mitigate the challenges facing students&rsquo; success in gateway mathematics, such as interactive pedagogies, teaching with inquiry, co-requisites, multiple measures of placement, and widespread enrichment programs for marginalized populations. While hosts of students experience innovative teaching and improved programs in small doses, the larger programmatic systems they return to afterwards are still entrenched in traditional thinking &ndash; which has produced the high drop/fail/withdrawal rates, low completion rates, and inequities we see today. Real systemic change cannot happen until we start addressing the wider, structural problems that pervade the mathematics community in post-secondary education.<br /><br />For this project, we envisioned a three-day virtual convening where community leaders will share their successes and challenges with following three main goals in mind:</p> <ul> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><em><strong>Sharing</strong></em>&nbsp;successful departmental, institutional, and professional society strategies and programs as a means for improving existing programs.</p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><em><strong>Identifying</strong></em>&nbsp;institutional and individual forces that keep existing strategies and programs from having a broader impact.</p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><em><strong>Formulating</strong></em>&nbsp;recommendations for how to move forward on the institutional and cultural change needed to address the identified issues.</p> </li> </ul> <p dir="ltr">Invited participants for this convening would include leaders of projects, programs, organizations, and institutions with experience in both creating progressive change in the higher education mathematics community and struggling against an entrenched system that holds these changes static in having a greater impact. The culmination of the convening will take shape in a report to be made public and widely available detailing the infrastructure challenges within the higher education community (with an eye specifically on mathematics) and how addressing those issues might lead to greater and more equitable student outcomes.</p> <p dir="ltr"><strong>Intellectual Merit</strong><br />The organizing committee for this planned convening has experience in planning, implementing, and disseminating conferences. In addition, the broad reach of each committee member facilitated the recruitment of the most prominent and vital leaders of the mathematics community that helped meet the goals of this convening. This new compilation of recommendations that was created will address a need in the community to better understand the ways in which institutions can connect and leverage networks to advance the field.</p> <p dir="ltr"><strong>Broader Impact</strong><br />After spending time listening to fellow peers and building awareness of the barriers and levers that are associated with quality math instuction, the leaders of this convening were inspired to enact change at the institutional and individual levels where decisions about student success are motivated by convincing data. Our work in this project aimed to compile and synthesize not only the critical challenges that have prevented broad uptake of progressive reform efforts in mathematics education, but also the recommendations for moving the needle across the spectrum vertically and horizontally. Many institutions are already aware of the systemic challenges their departments face; this project&rsquo;s goal was to bring those barriers to the table, discuss how to break them down and implement change and share the process in its entirety to a national audience.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/28/2022<br>      Modified by: Kiera&nbsp;L&nbsp;Edwards</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[Research suggests that there are many changes that would help mitigate the challenges facing students’ success in gateway mathematics, such as interactive pedagogies, teaching with inquiry, co-requisites, multiple measures of placement, and widespread enrichment programs for marginalized populations. While hosts of students experience innovative teaching and improved programs in small doses, the larger programmatic systems they return to afterwards are still entrenched in traditional thinking &ndash; which has produced the high drop/fail/withdrawal rates, low completion rates, and inequities we see today. Real systemic change cannot happen until we start addressing the wider, structural problems that pervade the mathematics community in post-secondary education.  For this project, we envisioned a three-day virtual convening where community leaders will share their successes and challenges with following three main goals in mind:   Sharing successful departmental, institutional, and professional society strategies and programs as a means for improving existing programs.   Identifying institutional and individual forces that keep existing strategies and programs from having a broader impact.   Formulating recommendations for how to move forward on the institutional and cultural change needed to address the identified issues.   Invited participants for this convening would include leaders of projects, programs, organizations, and institutions with experience in both creating progressive change in the higher education mathematics community and struggling against an entrenched system that holds these changes static in having a greater impact. The culmination of the convening will take shape in a report to be made public and widely available detailing the infrastructure challenges within the higher education community (with an eye specifically on mathematics) and how addressing those issues might lead to greater and more equitable student outcomes. Intellectual Merit The organizing committee for this planned convening has experience in planning, implementing, and disseminating conferences. In addition, the broad reach of each committee member facilitated the recruitment of the most prominent and vital leaders of the mathematics community that helped meet the goals of this convening. This new compilation of recommendations that was created will address a need in the community to better understand the ways in which institutions can connect and leverage networks to advance the field. Broader Impact After spending time listening to fellow peers and building awareness of the barriers and levers that are associated with quality math instuction, the leaders of this convening were inspired to enact change at the institutional and individual levels where decisions about student success are motivated by convincing data. Our work in this project aimed to compile and synthesize not only the critical challenges that have prevented broad uptake of progressive reform efforts in mathematics education, but also the recommendations for moving the needle across the spectrum vertically and horizontally. Many institutions are already aware of the systemic challenges their departments face; this project’s goal was to bring those barriers to the table, discuss how to break them down and implement change and share the process in its entirety to a national audience.          Last Modified: 04/28/2022       Submitted by: Kiera L Edwards]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
