<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Two-Dimensional Quantum Materials Out of Equilibrium]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>10000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>10000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Germano Iannacchione</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>giannacc@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924431</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This proposal mainly seeks to partially support 20+ undergraduate students, graduate students, post-docs, and under-represented, female, junior and retired faculty to attend and present at the symposium on Two-Dimensional Quantum Materials out of Equilibrium at the 2020 MRS Spring and Fall Virtual Meeting.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/23/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/20/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2035783</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>J. Ardie Butch</FirstName>
<LastName>Dillen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>J. Ardie Butch Dillen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[dillen@mrs.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000602561</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/23/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Srinivasa Rao</FirstName>
<LastName>Singamaneni</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Srinivasa Rao Singamaneni</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[srao@utep.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000759990</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/23/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Materials Research Society</Name>
<CityName>WARRENDALE</CityName>
<ZipCode>150867537</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7247792732</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>506 KEYSTONE DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>MFPJGRD1NWE3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MATERIALS RESEARCH SOCIETY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Materials Research Society]]></Name>
<CityName>Warrendale</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>150867573</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[506 Keystone Dr]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1710</Code>
<Text>CONDENSED MATTER PHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~10000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>MRS 2020 Virtual Spring/Fall Meeting</strong></p> <p><strong>Symposium S. NM07</strong>, Two-Dimensional Quantum Materials Out of Equilibrium</p> <p><strong>Award ID</strong>: 2035783<strong>&nbsp;&nbsp;</strong></p> <p>This symposium focussed on investigations into the physical properties (magnetic, optical, and electronic) of 2D quantum materials upon application of external perturbations, using a wide range of experimental and computational tools. The principal goal of this symposium was to bring together both experimentalists and theoreticians investigating the physics, chemistry, materials science and engineering aspects of quantum materials. With a mix of young scientists and established leaders in the field as invited speakers, the symposium captured the new and most impactful developments in the field, and simultaneously enabled researchers to receive a deeper perception of this emerging field and its grand challenges and opportunities. The development of understanding, knowledge, new methodologies and tools is expected to accelerate the discovery of new quantum materials and advance the ability to probe, predict, and exploit their remarkable properties.</p> <p>The symposium had received more than 67 abstracts.</p> <p>To manipukate the propoerties of quantum materials, this symposium covered a wide variety of approaches such as time- and spatially-resolved optical techniques, and employing the high-energy particles including protons, neutrons and electrons, and voltage/electric-field/electrostatic gating. In addition, this symposium presented the latest advances on the control of physical properties of quantum materials by in-situ application of pressure and high magnetic fields. Significant effort was also focused on the prediction of the fundamental properties of quantum materials upon external stimuli by employing the state-of-the-art theoretical calculations as well as on the optically and electrically controlled device concepts and demonstration. With a mix of young scientists and established leaders in the field as invited speakers, the symposium captured the new and most impactful developments and simultaneously, enabled researchers to receive a deeper perception of this rich field and outline the grand challenges and opportunities. This symposium provided greater opportunity for underrepresented Hispanic young scholars to advance their research in the rapidly growing field of research.</p> <p><strong>Activities/Findings/Highlights</strong></p> <p>This symposium was held at the 2020 Virtual Spring/Fall Meeting of the Materials Research Society, from Nov 27th &ndash; Dec 4th. The symposium was composed of 10 sessions over 3 days. It also had a Young Scientist Tutorial session on Nov 27th, 2020.</p> <p><strong>Highlights and findings include:</strong></p> <p>The tutorial (Electronic, Optical, and Magnetic Properties of Quantum Materials) was very useful for young and emerging researchers in this field as it is the first of its kind in MRS Spring Meetings on 2D materials. The success of this tutorial was reflected in the record number (143) of The technical program and abstracts may be viewed here:</p> <p><a href="https://www.mrs.org/meetings-events/spring-meetings-exhibits/past-spring-meetings/2020-mrs-spring-meeting/call-for-papers/detail/2020_mrs_spring_meeting/nm07/Symposium_NM07">https://www.mrs.org/meetings-events/spring-meetings-exhibits/past-spring-meetings/2020-mrs-spring-meeting/call-for-papers/detail/2020_mrs_spring_meeting/nm07/Symposium_NM07</a></p> <p>An article was published in MRS Advances&nbsp; MRS Advances (2021) 6:221&ndash;233</p> <p>A snapshot review&mdash;Fluctuations in quantum materials: from Skyrmions to superconductivity</p> <p><a href="https://doi.org/10.1557/s43580-021-00051-y">https://doi.org/10.1557/s43580-021-00051-y</a><strong></strong></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/20/2021<br>      Modified by: J. Ardie Butch&nbsp;Dillen</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ MRS 2020 Virtual Spring/Fall Meeting  Symposium S. NM07, Two-Dimensional Quantum Materials Out of Equilibrium  Award ID: 2035783    This symposium focussed on investigations into the physical properties (magnetic, optical, and electronic) of 2D quantum materials upon application of external perturbations, using a wide range of experimental and computational tools. The principal goal of this symposium was to bring together both experimentalists and theoreticians investigating the physics, chemistry, materials science and engineering aspects of quantum materials. With a mix of young scientists and established leaders in the field as invited speakers, the symposium captured the new and most impactful developments in the field, and simultaneously enabled researchers to receive a deeper perception of this emerging field and its grand challenges and opportunities. The development of understanding, knowledge, new methodologies and tools is expected to accelerate the discovery of new quantum materials and advance the ability to probe, predict, and exploit their remarkable properties.  The symposium had received more than 67 abstracts.  To manipukate the propoerties of quantum materials, this symposium covered a wide variety of approaches such as time- and spatially-resolved optical techniques, and employing the high-energy particles including protons, neutrons and electrons, and voltage/electric-field/electrostatic gating. In addition, this symposium presented the latest advances on the control of physical properties of quantum materials by in-situ application of pressure and high magnetic fields. Significant effort was also focused on the prediction of the fundamental properties of quantum materials upon external stimuli by employing the state-of-the-art theoretical calculations as well as on the optically and electrically controlled device concepts and demonstration. With a mix of young scientists and established leaders in the field as invited speakers, the symposium captured the new and most impactful developments and simultaneously, enabled researchers to receive a deeper perception of this rich field and outline the grand challenges and opportunities. This symposium provided greater opportunity for underrepresented Hispanic young scholars to advance their research in the rapidly growing field of research.  Activities/Findings/Highlights  This symposium was held at the 2020 Virtual Spring/Fall Meeting of the Materials Research Society, from Nov 27th &ndash; Dec 4th. The symposium was composed of 10 sessions over 3 days. It also had a Young Scientist Tutorial session on Nov 27th, 2020.  Highlights and findings include:  The tutorial (Electronic, Optical, and Magnetic Properties of Quantum Materials) was very useful for young and emerging researchers in this field as it is the first of its kind in MRS Spring Meetings on 2D materials. The success of this tutorial was reflected in the record number (143) of The technical program and abstracts may be viewed here:  https://www.mrs.org/meetings-events/spring-meetings-exhibits/past-spring-meetings/2020-mrs-spring-meeting/call-for-papers/detail/2020_mrs_spring_meeting/nm07/Symposium_NM07  An article was published in MRS Advances  MRS Advances (2021) 6:221&ndash;233  A snapshot review&mdash;Fluctuations in quantum materials: from Skyrmions to superconductivity  https://doi.org/10.1557/s43580-021-00051-y          Last Modified: 12/20/2021       Submitted by: J. Ardie Butch Dillen]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
