<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Experimental validation of an innovative lift-generating mechanism for use in future VTOL Aircraft.]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>230311.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>230311</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ela Mirowski</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>emirowsk@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922936</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact of this Small Business Innovation Research SBIR Phase I project is that it will answer the quest for developing a new type of vertical take-off and landing (VTOL) aircraft combining the competitive advantages of winged aircraft with those of helicopters.  Accordingly, this project will enable the production of a new type of VTOL aircraft that will be able to cruise at 640 mph; to operate at altitudes up to 35,000 feet; will be cheaper to build and maintain, easier to fly and less prone to accidents; and will provide the comfort and low noise level winged aircraft enjoy. These competitive advantages will make this new type of VTOL aircraft more attractive to Helicopter and Business Aircraft manufacturers and customers, which will boost the $55 Billion/year helicopter and business aircraft Industry.  In addition, this project will enable the production of small/medium-sized, electric, VTOL Aircraft for use in metropolitan areas, which will provide U.S. communities with a fast, convenient, low-noise means of transportation for use in metropolitan areas. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The current SBIR Phase I project aims at confirming the feasibility of an innovative lift-generating mechanism to enable the production of a new type of VTOL Aircraft. The lift-generating mechanism employs two novel components, a compound propeller having a cascade of specially-designed low angle-of-attack blades positioned in close proximity to one another, and an airflow pattern modifier. The feasibility of these two components was suggested with a multi-element airfoil CFD analysis tool, motivating the prototype proposed here.  This project will broaden our understanding of blades operating at low angle-of-attack and positioned in close proximity to one another. The main objectives of this project are to assess the performance of the compound propeller and the effect of using the airflow pattern modifiers on the performance; and to estimate the overall disc loading and hover lift efficiency of this proposed lift-generating mechanism.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/01/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/26/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041, 47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2035620</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Essam</FirstName>
<LastName>Marcus</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>T</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Essam T Marcus</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[marcuse@novoaerotech.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000786855</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/01/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>NOVO AERO TECHNOLOGY, INC.</Name>
<CityName>RALEIGH</CityName>
<ZipCode>276065512</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9196055306</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1017 MAIN CAMPUS DR STE 2300</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NLWQZR4RJWG3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NOVO AERO TECHNOLOGY, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[NOVO AERO TECHNOLOGY, INC.]]></Name>
<CityName>RALEIGH</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>276065512</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1017 MAIN CAMPUS DRIVE, STE 2300]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8091</Code>
<Text>SBIR Outreach &amp; Tech. Assist</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>059P</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE IN MOTION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~230311</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Due to the recent advancement in battery and electric motor technologies, numerous electric Vertical Take-Off and Landing (VTOL) configurations are currently investigated. The current research effort was undertaken to investigate the feasibility through experimental validation of an innovative lift-generating (LG) mechanism intended for use in future VTOL vehicles, which was believed to have some competitive advantages compared to currently in use technologies. The proposed LG mechanism configuration includes flow directing (FD) blades placed at strategic locations to increase the net thrust generated. A sub-scale technology demonstrator was designed, built, and tested. Following the experimental investigation, design optimization was performed leveraging CFD simulation, and the net thrust generated was increased by 3 to 5 times the initial design.</p> <p>The prototype assembly was tested at the North Carolina State University (NCSU) FREEDM Systems Center. The prototype was designed to enable investigating the performance of three main components of the LG mechanism individually and in combination with one another. The prototype was tested with several configurations to properly evaluate the value added to the LG mechanism by each of the three components. Collected performance data included values from sensor recordings (i.e., the load cell, the AC/DC Clamp Meter, AC/DC Multimeter, and Digital Sound Level Meter). Performance data was recorded at various blade tip speeds ranging between 180-270 meters/second. Collected raw data was processed and used to calculate the lift-generating mechanism?s disc loading, hover lift efficiency, and intensity of noise generated at various operating speeds for all the cases. The net thrust produced by the system was relatively lower than the initial predictions. It is believed that due to the negative camber of the FD blades, a force is produced downstream of the rotor blades. Consequently, the net thrust produced by the system is decreased as observed during the experiment.</p> <p>An effort was made by leveraging CFD analysis of the system to further understand the phenomena and to optimize the system. ANSYS Fluent was used to predict the flow conditions during the experiment. To model the rotating blades and the stationary duct, a frozen rotor in a moving reference frame approach was chosen. The methodology was validated by performing an analysis to the NACA 4-(3)(08)-03 propeller for which experimental values are available. Numerous designs including FD blades were analyzed. Although the net thrust was increased 3 to 5 times compared to the initial design, the FD blades had adverse effects on thrust on all designs considered. Therefore, the FD blades were disregarded moving forward. To further investigate the applicability of an upgraded, innovative lift generating mechanism as a means of propulsion system for a new proposed type of hybrid/electric VTOL aircraft, several ducted thrusters with an equivalent disk area of 3.1415 ft<sup>2</sup> were designed and investigated.</p> <p>Based on the knowledge acquired from this Phase I R&amp;D work, we were able to design an upgraded, innovative, plug-and-fly, lift-generating mechanism for use in future hybrid/electric VTOL aircraft. The upgraded lift-generating mechanism is projected to enable producing hybrid/electric VTOL aircraft having decreased rate of energy consumption and improved performance, when compared to currently in use helicopters and other proposed types of VTOL aircraft, while reducing the aircraft maintenance requirements almost to zero, apart from routine inspections and major overhauls every 3,000 to 5,000 hours of flight.</p> <p>Although the performance of this upgraded lift-generating mechanism was assessed using ANSYS simulation, and although the used ANSYS simulation methodology was validated by performing an analysis to a comparable propeller for which experimental values are available; proof-of-concept prototype experimental validation data for the upgraded lift-generating mechanism are still needed before further investing in this technology.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/04/2022<br>      Modified by: Essam&nbsp;T&nbsp;Marcus</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2035620/2035620_10715225_1641327412750_fig.2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2035620/2035620_10715225_1641327412750_fig.2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Prototype and Test station in SOLIDWORKS"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2035620/2035620_10715225_1641327412750_fig.2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Prototype and Test station in SOLIDWORKS"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Prototype and test station SOLIDWORKS model</div> <div class="imageCredit">Joel Jacobson</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Essam&nbsp;T&nbsp;Marcus</div> <div class="imageTitle">Prototype and Test station in SOLIDWORKS</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2035620/2035620_10715225_1641327168830_FIG.1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2035620/2035620_10715225_1641327168830_FIG.1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Rotating Components of the Prototype"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2035620/2035620_10715225_1641327168830_FIG.1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Rotating Components of the Prototype"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">ANSYS simulation of the rotating components of the prototype</div> <div class="imageCredit">Budhyant Venepalli</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Essam&nbsp;T&nbsp;Marcus</div> <div class="imageTitle">Rotating Components of the Prototype</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2035620/2035620_10715225_1641327531886_fig.3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2035620/2035620_10715225_1641327531886_fig.3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Assembly of the Test Prototype"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2035620/2035620_10715225_1641327531886_fig.3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Assembly of the Test Prototype"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The prototype rotor and stationary components before assembling them</div> <div class="imageCredit">Essam T Marcus</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Essam&nbsp;T&nbsp;Marcus</div> <div class="imageTitle">Assembly of the Test Prototype</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Due to the recent advancement in battery and electric motor technologies, numerous electric Vertical Take-Off and Landing (VTOL) configurations are currently investigated. The current research effort was undertaken to investigate the feasibility through experimental validation of an innovative lift-generating (LG) mechanism intended for use in future VTOL vehicles, which was believed to have some competitive advantages compared to currently in use technologies. The proposed LG mechanism configuration includes flow directing (FD) blades placed at strategic locations to increase the net thrust generated. A sub-scale technology demonstrator was designed, built, and tested. Following the experimental investigation, design optimization was performed leveraging CFD simulation, and the net thrust generated was increased by 3 to 5 times the initial design.  The prototype assembly was tested at the North Carolina State University (NCSU) FREEDM Systems Center. The prototype was designed to enable investigating the performance of three main components of the LG mechanism individually and in combination with one another. The prototype was tested with several configurations to properly evaluate the value added to the LG mechanism by each of the three components. Collected performance data included values from sensor recordings (i.e., the load cell, the AC/DC Clamp Meter, AC/DC Multimeter, and Digital Sound Level Meter). Performance data was recorded at various blade tip speeds ranging between 180-270 meters/second. Collected raw data was processed and used to calculate the lift-generating mechanism?s disc loading, hover lift efficiency, and intensity of noise generated at various operating speeds for all the cases. The net thrust produced by the system was relatively lower than the initial predictions. It is believed that due to the negative camber of the FD blades, a force is produced downstream of the rotor blades. Consequently, the net thrust produced by the system is decreased as observed during the experiment.  An effort was made by leveraging CFD analysis of the system to further understand the phenomena and to optimize the system. ANSYS Fluent was used to predict the flow conditions during the experiment. To model the rotating blades and the stationary duct, a frozen rotor in a moving reference frame approach was chosen. The methodology was validated by performing an analysis to the NACA 4-(3)(08)-03 propeller for which experimental values are available. Numerous designs including FD blades were analyzed. Although the net thrust was increased 3 to 5 times compared to the initial design, the FD blades had adverse effects on thrust on all designs considered. Therefore, the FD blades were disregarded moving forward. To further investigate the applicability of an upgraded, innovative lift generating mechanism as a means of propulsion system for a new proposed type of hybrid/electric VTOL aircraft, several ducted thrusters with an equivalent disk area of 3.1415 ft2 were designed and investigated.  Based on the knowledge acquired from this Phase I R&amp;D work, we were able to design an upgraded, innovative, plug-and-fly, lift-generating mechanism for use in future hybrid/electric VTOL aircraft. The upgraded lift-generating mechanism is projected to enable producing hybrid/electric VTOL aircraft having decreased rate of energy consumption and improved performance, when compared to currently in use helicopters and other proposed types of VTOL aircraft, while reducing the aircraft maintenance requirements almost to zero, apart from routine inspections and major overhauls every 3,000 to 5,000 hours of flight.  Although the performance of this upgraded lift-generating mechanism was assessed using ANSYS simulation, and although the used ANSYS simulation methodology was validated by performing an analysis to a comparable propeller for which experimental values are available; proof-of-concept prototype experimental validation data for the upgraded lift-generating mechanism are still needed before further investing in this technology.          Last Modified: 01/04/2022       Submitted by: Essam T Marcus]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
