<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Bridging the STEM Entrepreneurial Gap for Under-Represented Minority Women By Using the NSF I-Corps' Program Methodology]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>300000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>300000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rebecca Shearman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rshearma@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927403</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The Julian C. Madison Building, LLC (JCMB) project includes the research, evaluation, and reporting of the STEM Entrepreneurial Excellence Program (STEEP) – a pilot initiative to enhance cultural and contextual relevancy for a proven STEM entrepreneurship support program using the NSF I-Corps™ framework as the model program methodology.  In service to national interests promoting the progress of science, this project targets under-represented minority (URM) women interested in advancing their STEM education and experience for business ownership.  By increasing diversity in STEM-related career options, this project provides broad societal benefits and advances in education for marginalized sectors of the US population.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The STEEP Training Initiative goal is to broaden participation in the NSF I-Corps™ program  for URM women interested in entrepreneurship. This project’s scope focuses on evaluating readiness activities that collectively utilize STEEP’s entrepreneurial planning and NSF program methodology for maximum efficacy. The project team tracks STEEP participants’ engagement with corporate partners to leverage mentoring opportunities. Utilizing pre-, interim, and post-training surveys and interviews, data is collected across the project timeline to analyze its intended results.  The approach serves as a solid research model for long-term sustainability for STEM-focused entrepreneurship, as well as NSF I-Corps™ program participation for URM women.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will create a broader-access community in this innovative research area by capturing critical data (e.g. obstacles – real or perceived) on URM women participants with entrepreneurial spirits; engaging the national and international community through academic, professional development and mentorship networks; and establishing new and/or improved interdisciplinary programs among the participating academic institutions.  This project is scalable and transferable across the NSF Innovation Network (NIN) where Nodes, Hubs, Teams, and participating institutions of higher education (IHE) can implement the expected research findings to improve diversity and participation for URM women across STEM programs that encourage innovation and entrepreneurism.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;JCMB maintains an internal repository of survey data and interviews that is processed, then summarized to protect confidentiality (biographical information from the respondents).  Summarized project survey and individual interview results are assigned pseudonyms prior to any publication (i.e. scientific or managerial journals).  Once collected and analyzed, JCMB will present all data in aggregate form ensuring that the identity of respondents is maintained.  Personally-identifiable data is access-controlled during the project and for three years after the study is complete; then destroyed.  JCMB intends to distribute sanitized/summarized results to a broad audience concerned with the lack of diversity in STEM entrepreneurship.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/31/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/14/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2035165</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tonya</FirstName>
<LastName>Matthews</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Tonya M Matthews</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[tonya.matthews@wayne.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000507501</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/31/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sharon</FirstName>
<LastName>Madison</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sharon Madison</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[sharonmadison1971@gmail.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000826992</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/31/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>JULIAN C. MADISON BUILDING LLC, THE</Name>
<CityName>DETROIT</CityName>
<ZipCode>482261718</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3139636110</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1420 WASHINGTON BOULEVARD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>N8VHE12L1K58</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>THE JULIAN C. MADISON BUILDING LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[JULIAN C. MADISON BUILDING LLC, THE]]></Name>
<CityName>Detroit</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>482261718</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1420 Washington Boulevard]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8046</Code>
<Text>I-Corps-Sites</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~300000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Overview</strong></p> <p>The Julian C. Madison Building?s STEM Entrepreneurial Excellence Program (STEEP) is a pilot, funded by the National Science Foundation?s (NSF), Early Concept Grants for Exploratory Research, (EAGER).</p> <p>The 18-month program invited two cohorts of underrepresented minority (URM) African American women, to participate in an innovative concept, utilizing principles and training from the NSF I-Corps model integrated with STEEP. The design includes culturally relevant, context sensitive training to measurably improve business outcomes and prepare URM women for sustainable, growth. The research looked at how I- Corps can be utilized more effectively to support URM women STEM entrepreneurs. The program featured three components: pre-training exposure, training, and post-training development. It was organized by the following five principles:</p> <ol> <li>Raising awareness to address barriers to entrepreneurial success in STEM fields for URM women.</li> <li>Expanding participant access to and understanding of the NSF I-Corp program and benefits.</li> <li>Augmenting the NSF I-Corp program infrastructure to increase URM women participation.</li> <li>Establishing a scalable, repeatable process to build entrepreneurial networks for URM women.</li> <li>Create a network of aspiring and practicing of URM women, STEM-based business owners.&nbsp;</li> </ol> <p>Pre-training included media and introductory coverage showcasing the program's offerings and use of I-Corps. Results were general public exposure, 150 direct inquiries, and 100 applications. Two cohorts of 50 participants were admitted from the applicant pool. Thirty one women completed the program. Each cohort met weekly for 16 weeks. Participants&nbsp;explored strategies supporting their early and mid-stage businesses with intensive training in customer discovery and refinement, business branding, sales traction, and operational strategies.&nbsp;Weekly sessions included collaborations between academics, business leaders and industry professionals to spur an understanding of the connection between the further development of the specific products, technologies and services in each business/concept while addressing the skill and knowledge gap needed to connect the I-Corps model of experiential learning, customer discovery, and industry knowledge. &nbsp;Entrepreneurship skills, product mastery and issues specific to race and gender in technology were components. A virtual pitch competition showcased the cumulative business concepts and transformative learning.&nbsp;</p> <p>Each cohort began with an introductory overview and culminated with a final celebration.</p> <p>The composition of the two Cohorts included STEM Savvy women who have traditional or well aligned experience in STEM &nbsp;&nbsp;but little or no business experience and Business experienced women who have business experience but no formal STEM background. Our findings provided several useful insights.</p> <p>The NSF I-Corps instrument features two core pre-survey measures ? confidence and commercialization. Confidence assessed the perception of one?s ability to 1) identify the need for new products or services, 2), design customer-centric products or services, 3) garner support for one?s business plans, 4) contact and exchange information with others for the purpose of networking, and 5) clearly explain one?s business idea to laypersons. Cohort I participants were most confident in their ability to network and garner support for their business but least confident in their ability to clearly explain their business to laypersons. Cohort II participants were most confident in their ability to identify the need for new products or services and clearly explain their business ideas. These participants were least confident in their ability to garner support for their business and network.</p> <p>Both cohorts reported interests in gaining recognition, need for funding, and intrinsic interests in technology as the lesser reasons for wanting to commercialize their products or services. Cohort I reported motivation to satisfy a need in the market as their leading reason, whereas Cohort II?s leading reason was an intrinsic interest in creating something of their own. Out of the seven commercialization reasons, increasing personal income was fourth from a ranking standpoint.&nbsp; The broader impacts were similar for both groups.</p> <p><strong>Intellectual Merit</strong></p> <p>The evaluation used a multi-component process including 1) integration of existing NSF I-Corps evaluation methodology in Cohorts I and II, 2) integration of evaluation methodology developed specifically for STEEP, and 3) integration of multiple evaluation time points to track participant experiences over the 18-month program period. Data was collected via pre- and post-training surveys utilizing the NSF I-Corps pre-survey instrument. It suggests that traditional I-Corps methodology is more effective when incorporating contextual support and information.</p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts;</strong></p> <p>Data accumulated throughout the program suggest that STEEP provided a meaningful learning experience and acquisition of new competencies and skills as well as social contextual information crucial to the intersectional experiences and needs particular to Black women. Sociopolitical issues specifically experienced by URM African American women were integrated. Participants successfully enhanced competencies without sacrificing individual efficacy beliefs. Participants reported intentions to transfer trained skills as behaviors. Unlike the traditional NSF I-Corps program, STEEP included psychosocial phenomena associated with entrepreneurship and provided guidance for building one?s network. This pilot will be used as a basis for further developing programs and understanding of the special needs specific to black and other URM women entrepreneurs in STEM businesses .</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/28/2022<br>      Modified by: Sharon&nbsp;Madison</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2035165/2035165_10703340_1659037649065_Cover--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2035165/2035165_10703340_1659037649065_Cover--rgov-800width.jpg" title="STEEP Final Report Cover"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2035165/2035165_10703340_1659037649065_Cover--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="STEEP Final Report Cover"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Steep Detroit Final Report Cover and Image</div> <div class="imageCredit">Juan Sifuentes</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Sharon&nbsp;Madison</div> <div class="imageTitle">STEEP Final Report Cover</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2035165/2035165_10703340_1659037929480_STEEPVideoPage--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2035165/2035165_10703340_1659037929480_STEEPVideoPage--rgov-800width.jpg" title="STEEP Introduction and Final Celebration"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2035165/2035165_10703340_1659037929480_STEEPVideoPage--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="STEEP Introduction and Final Celebration"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">There were 2 public events for the participants and the general public. Over 100 people attended  each virtually, giving widespread recognition to the program and its participants.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Sharon Madison</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Sharon&nbsp;Madison</div> <div class="imageTitle">STEEP Introduction and Final Celebration</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2035165/2035165_10703340_1659038460371_STEEPparticipants--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2035165/2035165_10703340_1659038460371_STEEPparticipants--rgov-800width.jpg" title="STEEP Participants"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2035165/2035165_10703340_1659038460371_STEEPparticipants--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="STEEP Participants"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">There were over 50 women who participated in the STEEP program. This a representation of some of participant entrepreneurs.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Juan Sifuentes</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Sharon&nbsp;Madison</div> <div class="imageTitle">STEEP Participants</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[    Overview  The Julian C. Madison Building?s STEM Entrepreneurial Excellence Program (STEEP) is a pilot, funded by the National Science Foundation?s (NSF), Early Concept Grants for Exploratory Research, (EAGER).  The 18-month program invited two cohorts of underrepresented minority (URM) African American women, to participate in an innovative concept, utilizing principles and training from the NSF I-Corps model integrated with STEEP. The design includes culturally relevant, context sensitive training to measurably improve business outcomes and prepare URM women for sustainable, growth. The research looked at how I- Corps can be utilized more effectively to support URM women STEM entrepreneurs. The program featured three components: pre-training exposure, training, and post-training development. It was organized by the following five principles:  Raising awareness to address barriers to entrepreneurial success in STEM fields for URM women. Expanding participant access to and understanding of the NSF I-Corp program and benefits. Augmenting the NSF I-Corp program infrastructure to increase URM women participation. Establishing a scalable, repeatable process to build entrepreneurial networks for URM women. Create a network of aspiring and practicing of URM women, STEM-based business owners.    Pre-training included media and introductory coverage showcasing the program's offerings and use of I-Corps. Results were general public exposure, 150 direct inquiries, and 100 applications. Two cohorts of 50 participants were admitted from the applicant pool. Thirty one women completed the program. Each cohort met weekly for 16 weeks. Participants explored strategies supporting their early and mid-stage businesses with intensive training in customer discovery and refinement, business branding, sales traction, and operational strategies. Weekly sessions included collaborations between academics, business leaders and industry professionals to spur an understanding of the connection between the further development of the specific products, technologies and services in each business/concept while addressing the skill and knowledge gap needed to connect the I-Corps model of experiential learning, customer discovery, and industry knowledge.  Entrepreneurship skills, product mastery and issues specific to race and gender in technology were components. A virtual pitch competition showcased the cumulative business concepts and transformative learning.   Each cohort began with an introductory overview and culminated with a final celebration.  The composition of the two Cohorts included STEM Savvy women who have traditional or well aligned experience in STEM   but little or no business experience and Business experienced women who have business experience but no formal STEM background. Our findings provided several useful insights.  The NSF I-Corps instrument features two core pre-survey measures ? confidence and commercialization. Confidence assessed the perception of one?s ability to 1) identify the need for new products or services, 2), design customer-centric products or services, 3) garner support for one?s business plans, 4) contact and exchange information with others for the purpose of networking, and 5) clearly explain one?s business idea to laypersons. Cohort I participants were most confident in their ability to network and garner support for their business but least confident in their ability to clearly explain their business to laypersons. Cohort II participants were most confident in their ability to identify the need for new products or services and clearly explain their business ideas. These participants were least confident in their ability to garner support for their business and network.  Both cohorts reported interests in gaining recognition, need for funding, and intrinsic interests in technology as the lesser reasons for wanting to commercialize their products or services. Cohort I reported motivation to satisfy a need in the market as their leading reason, whereas Cohort II?s leading reason was an intrinsic interest in creating something of their own. Out of the seven commercialization reasons, increasing personal income was fourth from a ranking standpoint.  The broader impacts were similar for both groups.  Intellectual Merit  The evaluation used a multi-component process including 1) integration of existing NSF I-Corps evaluation methodology in Cohorts I and II, 2) integration of evaluation methodology developed specifically for STEEP, and 3) integration of multiple evaluation time points to track participant experiences over the 18-month program period. Data was collected via pre- and post-training surveys utilizing the NSF I-Corps pre-survey instrument. It suggests that traditional I-Corps methodology is more effective when incorporating contextual support and information.  Broader Impacts;  Data accumulated throughout the program suggest that STEEP provided a meaningful learning experience and acquisition of new competencies and skills as well as social contextual information crucial to the intersectional experiences and needs particular to Black women. Sociopolitical issues specifically experienced by URM African American women were integrated. Participants successfully enhanced competencies without sacrificing individual efficacy beliefs. Participants reported intentions to transfer trained skills as behaviors. Unlike the traditional NSF I-Corps program, STEEP included psychosocial phenomena associated with entrepreneurship and provided guidance for building one?s network. This pilot will be used as a basis for further developing programs and understanding of the special needs specific to black and other URM women entrepreneurs in STEM businesses .          Last Modified: 07/28/2022       Submitted by: Sharon Madison]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
