<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Using a novel RNA therapy to immunize trees and vines against deadly bacteria]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>255990.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>255990</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Erik Pierstorff</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>epiersto@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922165</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is to develop the first small RNA-based vaccination approach for mature trees, vines, and bushes against Xylella fastidiosa (XF), one of agriculture’s most devastating bacterial diseases. XF diseases include (1) Olive Quick Decline Syndrome, which is currently threatening the entire Southern Europe olive industry and killing trees that are over 1,000 years old; (2) Pierce’s Disease, which has severely damaged Southern California vineyards; and (3) Citrus Variegated Chlorosis, which is one of several diseases threatening the citrus industry. This project is based on a novel infectious RNA discovered by the Company’s team that can be used as a delivery vehicle for anti-pathogenic agents to target XF. A single inoculation can potentially provide lifetime protection while not harming the tree. As of today, there is no vaccination or cure for XF. If successful, this would represent a new platform potentially capable of vaccinating most trees against most fungal, bacterial, and viral diseases. In the absence of treatment, in a few decades, citrus, olives, and many other valuable crops that produce food for millions of people may cease to exist outside of insect-protective structures like greenhouses. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed project has four key milestones required to defeat XF: (1) identify small interfering RNAs (siRNAs) capable of targeting gene expression in a Gram-negative bacterium like XF, which has never been accomplished commercially, and integrate these siRNAs into a novel delivery vector, which can systemically infect plants with no apparent host range; (2) demonstrate that sufficient siRNAs are generated in phloem companion cells in a laboratory host to reduce titers of XF in the xylem where it exclusively resides; (3) show that the Company’s novel RNA vector, which can systemically infect all commercial varieties of citrus, can also systemically infect olive trees and/or grapevines; (4) amplify the RNA vector in trees susceptible to XF and demonstrate efficacy against XF in greenhouse trials. The proposed work will address the first two objectives in the model plant N. bethamiana and the third objective in olive and grapevines.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/05/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/05/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2035639</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>FENG</FirstName>
<LastName>GAO</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>FENG GAO</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[feng_gao@subr.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000816256</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/05/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate>03/27/2022</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Feng</FirstName>
<LastName>Gao</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Feng Gao</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[fgao@silvec.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000846290</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/28/2022</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>SILVEC BIOLOGICS, INC.</Name>
<CityName>GAITHERSBURG</CityName>
<ZipCode>208773490</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3104636625</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>200 GIRARD ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[STE 200]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MD06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>ZH7KBVHXP1C3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SILVEC BIOLOGICS INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Silvec Biologics Inc.]]></Name>
<CityName>Rockville</CityName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>208503467</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[9600 Gudelsky Dr]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MD08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9109</Code>
<Text>AGRICULTURAL BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~255990</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Fruit trees such as grapevines and citrus represent around 20% of global agriculture production value. One of the most dangerous plant bacterial pathogens worldwide, Xylella fastidiosa (Xf), capable of infecting economically important trees like olives (Olive Quick Decline Syndrome) and grapevine (Pierce's Disease), is currently spreading at alarming rates. There is a lack of biological control strategies available to protect trees and vines against Xf and many other microbial pathogens. In this context, Silvec Biologics has developed an RNA-based technology that can be used to defeat microbial pathogens currently threatening the fruit tree industry in the USA and worldwide. This method works by delivering RNA molecules inside trees designed to target invasive pathogens for degradation and to aid the plant's immune system.</p> <p><br />Silvec has spent several years optimizing methods to ensure an efficient and economically viable means of delivering small anti-pathogenic RNA molecules into trees to protect against Xf as well as several viral and fungal pathogens. It has focused to date on model plant systems and is now scaling up to demonstrate it technology by silencing a pathogen in its natural host tree.</p> <p><br />In this NSF-SBIR project, Silvec's goal is to defeat Xf, as well as potentially other microbial pathogens, in trees starting with grapevines. Silvec had identified 3 milestones in its phase I project that needed to be overcome to defeat Xf: (1) develop an siRNA able to target gene expression in a gram negative bacterium like Xf; (2) demonstrate that sufficient siRNAs are generated in phloem companion cells by its vector to reach the xylem where Xf resides; and (3) show that its vector can systemically infect trees and/or grapevines. This was to then be followed by a Phase II project to optimize the process and scale up to immunizing grapevines against Xf and demonstrating efficacy in growth rooms / greenhouse trials.</p> <p><br />In phase I conducted between Feb 2021 to Jan 2022, Silvec has 1) developed multiple small RNAs (siRNAs) targeting Xf and have demonstrated the ability to substantially silence Xf colonizing the xylem of model plant N. benthamiana. It has also demonstrated an inoculation process to introduce the vector into grapevines and have detected it in systemic tissue and new leaves (including minus strands), indicating that the vector is moving systemically and replicating.</p> <p><br />These highly encouraging results position us well for Phase II of this project where Silvec expects to not only be able to target a bacterial target like Xf, but also to immunize grapevines against other economically important microbial targets including viruses and fungi using its vector.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/30/2022<br>      Modified by: Feng&nbsp;Gao</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Fruit trees such as grapevines and citrus represent around 20% of global agriculture production value. One of the most dangerous plant bacterial pathogens worldwide, Xylella fastidiosa (Xf), capable of infecting economically important trees like olives (Olive Quick Decline Syndrome) and grapevine (Pierce's Disease), is currently spreading at alarming rates. There is a lack of biological control strategies available to protect trees and vines against Xf and many other microbial pathogens. In this context, Silvec Biologics has developed an RNA-based technology that can be used to defeat microbial pathogens currently threatening the fruit tree industry in the USA and worldwide. This method works by delivering RNA molecules inside trees designed to target invasive pathogens for degradation and to aid the plant's immune system.   Silvec has spent several years optimizing methods to ensure an efficient and economically viable means of delivering small anti-pathogenic RNA molecules into trees to protect against Xf as well as several viral and fungal pathogens. It has focused to date on model plant systems and is now scaling up to demonstrate it technology by silencing a pathogen in its natural host tree.   In this NSF-SBIR project, Silvec's goal is to defeat Xf, as well as potentially other microbial pathogens, in trees starting with grapevines. Silvec had identified 3 milestones in its phase I project that needed to be overcome to defeat Xf: (1) develop an siRNA able to target gene expression in a gram negative bacterium like Xf; (2) demonstrate that sufficient siRNAs are generated in phloem companion cells by its vector to reach the xylem where Xf resides; and (3) show that its vector can systemically infect trees and/or grapevines. This was to then be followed by a Phase II project to optimize the process and scale up to immunizing grapevines against Xf and demonstrating efficacy in growth rooms / greenhouse trials.   In phase I conducted between Feb 2021 to Jan 2022, Silvec has 1) developed multiple small RNAs (siRNAs) targeting Xf and have demonstrated the ability to substantially silence Xf colonizing the xylem of model plant N. benthamiana. It has also demonstrated an inoculation process to introduce the vector into grapevines and have detected it in systemic tissue and new leaves (including minus strands), indicating that the vector is moving systemically and replicating.   These highly encouraging results position us well for Phase II of this project where Silvec expects to not only be able to target a bacterial target like Xf, but also to immunize grapevines against other economically important microbial targets including viruses and fungi using its vector.       Last Modified: 03/30/2022       Submitted by: Feng Gao]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
