<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Reconstruction of Hurricane Florence Flood Hydrographs (HF2Hs) for South Carolina's Critical Infrastructures Using Data Analytics Algorithms and In-situ Field Measurements]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/16/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>30432.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>85432</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Bruce Hamilton</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bhamilto@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032920000</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[In the wake of Hurricane Florence in South Carolina, this research aims to collect high water marks (HWMs) data across flooded/damaged critical infrastructures, and perishable images and video footage from traffic cameras and social media outlets. The investigators will then reconstruct Hurricane Florence flood hydrographs (HF2Hs) using data analytics algorithms as well as HWMs data to estimate flood elevation and inundation extent over overtopped roads and bridges. Using the eastern portion of South Carolina (SC) as a case study, this RAPID project will address the following questions: Do reconstructed flood hydrographs over critical infrastructures provide valuable insight into flooding thresholds and frequencies? If so, how? To address these questions, the team consists of members with expertise in engineering hydrology and computer sciences and engineering who are positioned to deliver the needed collecting, examining, and archiving of perishable datasets. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The methodology for collecting perishable data merges the broader objectives of enhancing perishable data collection through the use of traditional (tape measure, engineer's rule, etc.) and data analytics techniques, both of which depend on the timely collection of data. The reconstructed flood hydrographs for overtopped routes/roads and bridges will help understanding of how critical infrastructures respond to hurricane-induced flooding that presents persistent widespread challenges in many regions worldwide. The collected data will benefit the development of new numerical models for flood prediction that will deal with the unique needs and concepts of the U.S.'s southeast catchments (shallow aquifer parameterization). The data analytics algorithm is targeted be flexible and scalable to collect and analyze large sets of data which will be disseminated through open-source public repositories (e.g., GitHub). The collection and integration of data is targeted to facilitate communication/ collaboration between decision makers and technically-focused institutions. This project is intended to have an immediate impact on South Carolina, a state which is very vulnerable to repeated hurricane events and is under the threat of increasing floods.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/19/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/14/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2035685</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Vidya</FirstName>
<LastName>Samadi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Vidya Samadi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[SAMADI@clemson.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000651827</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/19/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Clemson University</Name>
<CityName>CLEMSON</CityName>
<ZipCode>296340001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8646562424</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>201 SIKES HALL</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>South Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>SC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>SC03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>H2BMNX7DSKU8</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CLEMSON UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>H2BMNX7DSKU8</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Clemson University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>SC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>296340001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>South Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>SC03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1504</Code>
<Text>GOALI-Grnt Opp Acad Lia wIndus</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7643</Code>
<Text>EnvS-Environmtl Sustainability</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>019Z</Code>
<Text>Grad Prep APG:Enhan. Experience</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>080Z</Code>
<Text>Research related to Hurricane Florence</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1504</Code>
<Text>GRANT OPP FOR ACAD LIA W/INDUS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01001920DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~30432</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~55000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p style="text-align: left;">This project started in 2018 and was the first attempt to use Big Data analytics approaches and machine learning along with&nbsp;Natural Language Processing (NLP) of tweets for flood assessment and decision making.&nbsp;Overall, 12 python packages were developed and integrated within the Flood Analytics Information System (FAIS). FAIS workflow includes the use of IoTs-APIs and various machine learning approaches for transmitting, processing, and loading big data through which the application gathers information from various data servers and replicates it to a data warehouse (IBM database service). Users are allowed to directly stream and download flood related images/videos from the USGS and DOT and save the data on a local storage.&nbsp; The outcome of the river measurement, imagery, and tabular data is displayed on a web based remote dashboard and the information can be plotted in real-time. FAIS proved to be a robust and user-friendly tool for flood data analysis at regional scale that could help stakeholders for rapid assessment of flood situation and damages. FAIS also provides flood frequency analysis (FFA) to estimate extreme flood quantiles including the associated uncertainties that combine elements of observational analysis, stochastic probability distribution and design return periods. FFA techniques predict how flow values corresponding to specific return periods or probabilities along a river could change over different design periods. FAIS currently uses multiple probability distributions such as Normal, Lognormal, Gamma, Gumbel, Pearson Type III, Weibull, and Loglogistic distributions to compute FFA for any given flood gauging station in the US. The tool also provides a .CSV report file of the FFA computation that is downloadable from the interface. The use of FFA for any given USGS station provides an easy assessment for the design of engineering structures such as culverts, bridges, and dams. With the many challenges facing existing probability distribution fitting and performance calculation, FAIS FFA functions, numerical estimation and uncertainty calculation, and graphical capabilities together with its flexibility to fit multiple distributions, can go a long way. This makes the FAIS application an ideal tool to assess flood frequencies for any USGS gauging station. This project provided support for 4 graduate students and 1 undergraduate student in Civil Engineering and Computer Sciences, and 2 high school students in mathematics and sciences.&nbsp;FAIS is publicly available and deployed at the Clemson-IBM cloud service.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/08/2021<br>      Modified by: Seyedehzahra Vi&nbsp;V&nbsp;Samadi</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[This project started in 2018 and was the first attempt to use Big Data analytics approaches and machine learning along with Natural Language Processing (NLP) of tweets for flood assessment and decision making. Overall, 12 python packages were developed and integrated within the Flood Analytics Information System (FAIS). FAIS workflow includes the use of IoTs-APIs and various machine learning approaches for transmitting, processing, and loading big data through which the application gathers information from various data servers and replicates it to a data warehouse (IBM database service). Users are allowed to directly stream and download flood related images/videos from the USGS and DOT and save the data on a local storage.  The outcome of the river measurement, imagery, and tabular data is displayed on a web based remote dashboard and the information can be plotted in real-time. FAIS proved to be a robust and user-friendly tool for flood data analysis at regional scale that could help stakeholders for rapid assessment of flood situation and damages. FAIS also provides flood frequency analysis (FFA) to estimate extreme flood quantiles including the associated uncertainties that combine elements of observational analysis, stochastic probability distribution and design return periods. FFA techniques predict how flow values corresponding to specific return periods or probabilities along a river could change over different design periods. FAIS currently uses multiple probability distributions such as Normal, Lognormal, Gamma, Gumbel, Pearson Type III, Weibull, and Loglogistic distributions to compute FFA for any given flood gauging station in the US. The tool also provides a .CSV report file of the FFA computation that is downloadable from the interface. The use of FFA for any given USGS station provides an easy assessment for the design of engineering structures such as culverts, bridges, and dams. With the many challenges facing existing probability distribution fitting and performance calculation, FAIS FFA functions, numerical estimation and uncertainty calculation, and graphical capabilities together with its flexibility to fit multiple distributions, can go a long way. This makes the FAIS application an ideal tool to assess flood frequencies for any USGS gauging station. This project provided support for 4 graduate students and 1 undergraduate student in Civil Engineering and Computer Sciences, and 2 high school students in mathematics and sciences. FAIS is publicly available and deployed at the Clemson-IBM cloud service.        Last Modified: 11/08/2021       Submitted by: Seyedehzahra Vi V Samadi]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
