<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Higher Order Beliefs during a Pandemic: Theory and Evidence to Test the Effects of Public Health Campaigns]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>198852.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>198852</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kwabena Gyimah-Brempong</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kgyimahb@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927466</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Social distancing is critical to slowing the spread of COVID-19 pandemic, which threatens the nation’s health, economy, and national defense.  This research project studies people’s strategic behavior in deciding to follow public health rules or not.  The project uses sophisticated economic theory and empirical methods to study strategic considerations that may hamper or facilitate compliance with public health guidelines to reduce the spread of COVID-19.  One person’s choice to comply with social distancing regulation influences the costs and benefits to others doing so.  As a result, individual behavior depends on beliefs about others’ compliance and on social norms regarding compliance. This project increases understanding of individual behavior in group settings and highlights the conditions under which benefits of publicity in mass media campaigns, and provides hundreds of thousands of public health mailers to American residents may be beneficial.   The results of this research project will help public health authorities to craft more efficient public information campaigns.   &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research project uses theory and empirical methods based on a large data set from Cook county to investigate how beliefs in other peoples’ response influence one’s decision to comply with public health rules.  The theory extends previous research on two strategic considerations, conformity, and free-riding, that influence behavior by incorporating the related phenomenon of publicity. Publicity is found to amplify pro-social behavior only when conformity dominates free-riding; otherwise publicity will lessen the effectiveness of an informational campaign. The empirics analyze a vast public health campaign in Cook County, Illinois. The campaign will provide public health best practices directly to hundreds of thousands of Cook County households. Using a mix of public information and a voluntary survey, we will evaluate the effectiveness of the public health campaign in promoting behaviors identified as decreasing the risk of transmitting COVID-19.  The results of this research project will help public health authorities to craft more efficient public information campaigns.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/09/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/09/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2035682</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ethan</FirstName>
<LastName>Bueno de Mesquita</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ethan Bueno de Mesquita</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[bdm@uchicago.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000084768</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/09/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Adam</FirstName>
<LastName>Zelizer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Adam P Zelizer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[zelizer@uchicago.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000829538</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/09/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Chicago</Name>
<CityName>CHICAGO</CityName>
<ZipCode>606375418</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7737028669</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5801 S ELLIS AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>ZUE9HKT2CLC9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CHICAGO</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>ZUE9HKT2CLC9</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Chicago]]></Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>606373298</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1307 E 60th Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1320</Code>
<Text>Economics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~198852</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Social distancing was a key public health effort to slow the spread of COVID-19, but it was implemented haphazardly and with limited public acceptance. Like many other activities of interest to social scientists, engaging in social distancing or any pro-social health behavior confronts strategic considerations that complicate individual behavior. One person&rsquo;s choice to comply with social distancing influences the costs and benefits to others. As a result, individual behavior depends on higher-order beliefs about others&rsquo; compliance as well as social norms regarding compliance. Through a combination of theory and empirics, we explore the strategic considerations that may hamper, or facilitate, compliance with public health guidelines. Our theory extends previous research on two strategic considerations, conformity and free-riding, that influence behavior by incorporating the related phenomenon of publicity, which is found to amplify pro-social behavior only when conformity dominates free-riding.&nbsp;</p> <p>We sent mailers to approximately 125,000 households in Cook County, Illinois, with guidance from the University of Chicago Medicine's chief epidemiologist Dr. Emily Landon. The guidance was sent in November 2020 in advance of the holiday season. It informed recipients of the risks of travel, that congregating over the holidays posed a substantial health risk. Some of the mailers included supplemental information about what percentage of recipients' neighbors were also receiving the information.&nbsp;</p> <p>We used two data sources to determine if the mailers had a meaningful impact on individuals' travel over the 2020 holiday. First, anonymized, aggregated cell phone mobility data captured travel outside the home over the period; measures included time spent out of the house, distance travelled, and time spent out of the house. The second data source was an original survey conducted of Cook County residents in early January 2021. This survey was placed to individuals with valid phone numbers as provided by a commercial data vendor. We obtained over 3,300 respondents to the survey.&nbsp;</p> <p><span>We aimed to understand 1) whether messages from health experts influenced individuals' behavior during the COVID-19 epidemic, and 2) the extent to which social distancing behavior was subject to strategic considerations and social dynamics.&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span>We estimate that guidance from a credible local health expert had minimal impact on travel during the 2020 holiday season. While some outcome measures suggest that the expert effectively reduced travel or gatherings, the preponderence of evidence points to null effects from the health campaign. Mailer recipients were substantially more likely to remember the public health campaign when it publicized the percentage of the neighborhood sent the messages, which suggests that publicity and social dynamics do have an important role in such campaigns. However, we find no evidence of a role of publicity in mediating messages' influence through strategic considerations.&nbsp;</span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/29/2022<br>      Modified by: Adam&nbsp;P&nbsp;Zelizer</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Social distancing was a key public health effort to slow the spread of COVID-19, but it was implemented haphazardly and with limited public acceptance. Like many other activities of interest to social scientists, engaging in social distancing or any pro-social health behavior confronts strategic considerations that complicate individual behavior. One person’s choice to comply with social distancing influences the costs and benefits to others. As a result, individual behavior depends on higher-order beliefs about others’ compliance as well as social norms regarding compliance. Through a combination of theory and empirics, we explore the strategic considerations that may hamper, or facilitate, compliance with public health guidelines. Our theory extends previous research on two strategic considerations, conformity and free-riding, that influence behavior by incorporating the related phenomenon of publicity, which is found to amplify pro-social behavior only when conformity dominates free-riding.   We sent mailers to approximately 125,000 households in Cook County, Illinois, with guidance from the University of Chicago Medicine's chief epidemiologist Dr. Emily Landon. The guidance was sent in November 2020 in advance of the holiday season. It informed recipients of the risks of travel, that congregating over the holidays posed a substantial health risk. Some of the mailers included supplemental information about what percentage of recipients' neighbors were also receiving the information.   We used two data sources to determine if the mailers had a meaningful impact on individuals' travel over the 2020 holiday. First, anonymized, aggregated cell phone mobility data captured travel outside the home over the period; measures included time spent out of the house, distance travelled, and time spent out of the house. The second data source was an original survey conducted of Cook County residents in early January 2021. This survey was placed to individuals with valid phone numbers as provided by a commercial data vendor. We obtained over 3,300 respondents to the survey.   We aimed to understand 1) whether messages from health experts influenced individuals' behavior during the COVID-19 epidemic, and 2) the extent to which social distancing behavior was subject to strategic considerations and social dynamics.   We estimate that guidance from a credible local health expert had minimal impact on travel during the 2020 holiday season. While some outcome measures suggest that the expert effectively reduced travel or gatherings, the preponderence of evidence points to null effects from the health campaign. Mailer recipients were substantially more likely to remember the public health campaign when it publicized the percentage of the neighborhood sent the messages, which suggests that publicity and social dynamics do have an important role in such campaigns. However, we find no evidence of a role of publicity in mediating messages' influence through strategic considerations.        Last Modified: 10/29/2022       Submitted by: Adam P Zelizer]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
