<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Identifying New Community-Driven Science Themes for National Science Foundation (NSF)’s Support of Paleo Perspectives on Climate Change (P2C2): A Workshop]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>214309.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>214309</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06020100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AGS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Soumaya Belmecheri</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine will organize a workshop that seeks to identify potential future paleoclimate research directions that will help advance understanding of current and potential future change in the Earth’s climate system. Drawing upon broad community input collected via an online questionnaire, workshop discussions will address gaps in the current understanding of past climate variability and processes, and new research strategies and technological capabilities that could practically be undertaken to effectively fill these knowledge gaps. In preparation for an update of the research themes and goals of the Paleo perspectives on Climate Change (P2C2) annual competition, this project plans to engage the broad science community via online questionnaire and a workshop to identify potential priority areas for research in a possible follow-on call for proposals and beyond. Engagement with the science community at the outset will help identify themes with high potential to advance the field and that are feasible for NSF to support and for the community to tackle. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project seeks input from a broad community with efforts to achieve diversity in geographic representation, institutional affiliation, career stage, gender, and race.  Additionally, identifying future research themes in paleoclimate has inherent broader impact related to the scientific and socioeconomic applications of paleoclimate research and their relevance to decision making on issues such as water management, biodiversity, infrastructure adaptation, etc. Other broader impacts include a report of the workshop and questionnaire activities, available in paper (limited quantities) and free PDF, which will be disseminated to NSF and other interested stakeholders as appropriate. The Workshop report will be made available to the public without restriction and will be posted on the National Academies Press website. The National Academies will conduct extensive outreach and engagement to ensure that the results are widely disseminated. This outreach could include briefings for agencies, briefings for Congressional offices, continued facilitation of on-line discussion forums with the broader community, briefings and webinars, presentations and sessions at relevant conferences, and other related activities.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/07/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/07/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2035238</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Amanda</FirstName>
<LastName>Staudt</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Amanda Staudt</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[AStaudt@nas.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000657530</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/07/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>National Academy of Sciences</Name>
<CityName>WASHINGTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>204180007</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2023342254</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2101 CONSTITUTION AVE NW</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>PKFJZHG2MLG9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NATIONAL ACADEMY OF SCIENCES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>PKFJZHG2MLG9</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[National Academy of Sciences]]></Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>200012721</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[500 5th Street NW]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1530</Code>
<Text>Paleoclimate</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1577</Code>
<Text>GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1620</Code>
<Text>Marine Geology and Geophysics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>4444</Code>
<Text>INTERDISCIPLINARY PROPOSALS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~214309</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Paleoclimate science aims to understand how Earth?s climate has varied over time by integrating a broad range of evidence from the natural and human world. Over the last decades, paleoclimate research has advanced understanding of the magnitudes, rates, and drivers of past climate variability on a range of timescales, providing a baseline and understanding for use in assessing current and future climate variability and change. These advances reflect progress in developing and understanding new proxies?indirect indicators of past climates preserved in climate archives?as well as in integrating these proxy records with numerical models.</p> <p>The National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine convened a workshop on June 21-23, 2021, to identify potential future paleoclimate research directions that will help advance the understanding of past, current, and future change in the Earth?s climate system. Using broad community input that was collected through an online questionnaire, workshop participants discussed gaps in current understanding of past climate variability and processes and new research strategies and technological capabilities that could practically be undertaken to effectively fill these knowledge gaps.</p> <p>Workshop discussions highlighted both emerging areas of research and relevant questions that the community is currently trying to address. Participants highlighted the interest of the community in translating the global emphasis of paleoclimate research into regional connections. The attention to regional scales is motivated by the interest in making policy connections to explore regional vulnerabilities to climate change?for example, to understand extreme events, such as drought and wildfires. A focus on regional scales would involve more records at different resolutions to elucidate these connections. Emerging scientific areas of interest included hydroclimate during past warm periods; connections between the biosphere, marine, and terrestrial ecosystems; and the carbon cycle. These research questions indicate the importance of also understanding large-scale processes in combination with the interest in shorter temporal and smaller spatial scales.</p> <p>Participants paid much attention to the ways the paleoclimate community can develop geologic models for a no-analog future, leveraging data from the past to better understand, for example, fires, permafrost thaw, and carbon release in a warming climate. Interest in better understanding past extreme events in order to inform present and future climate and communicate with the public and decision makers was also a repeated theme.</p> <p>Tools and strategies to advance these new research directions were also an essential part of the workshop discussions. Participants discussed sample and data archiving and sharing and the lack of community infrastructure was noted as a potential barrier to the accessibility of paleoclimate records. There was interest among some participants in putting resources behind building community databases that would serve as dynamic resources and facilitate synthesis work, instead of relying on the current volunteer-based model.</p> <p>Issues around belonging, accessibility, justice, equity, diversity, and inclusion were central to the workshop discussions on advancing paleoclimate research questions. In addition to strategies around skillset and equity-minded training, and tracking metrics for progress to enhance diversity and inclusion in the paleoclimate field (particularly for early career researchers), discussions also centered on knowledge coproduction. Some participants suggested that programmatic and financial support for efforts to engage and establish long-term relationships with local communities may be necessary in order to inform the development of new science questions.</p> <p>The community questionnaire conducted as part of this activity received 96 thoughtful responses that informed the workshop. The June 2021 workshop was attended by 200-250 participants each day in addition to over 200 viewers of the plenary session webcast. The workshop proceedings have been downloaded or viewed 875 times and the Academies has distributed and sold 33 copies. Since the workshop and release of the workshop proceedings, NSF has announced a new solicitation, Paleo Perspectives on Present and Projected Climate (P4CLIMATE) that draws on many of the themes raised throughout the workshop.</p> <p>The workshop recordings and additional information are available on the project website: <a href="https://www.nationalacademies.org/event/06-21-2021/identifying-new-community-driven-science-themes-for-nsfs-support-of-paleo-perspectives-on-climate-change-p2c2-a-workshop">https://www.nationalacademies.org/event/06-21-2021/identifying-new-community-driven-science-themes-for-nsfs-support-of-paleo-perspectives-on-climate-change-p2c2-a-workshop</a></p> <p>The workshop proceedings can be downloaded for free from the National Academies: <a href="https://nap.nationalacademies.org/catalog/26377/identifying-new-community-driven-science-themes-for-nsfs-support-of-paleoclimate-research">https://nap.nationalacademies.org/catalog/26377/identifying-new-community-driven-science-themes-for-nsfs-support-of-paleoclimate-research</a></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/28/2022<br>      Modified by: Amanda&nbsp;Staudt</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Paleoclimate science aims to understand how Earth?s climate has varied over time by integrating a broad range of evidence from the natural and human world. Over the last decades, paleoclimate research has advanced understanding of the magnitudes, rates, and drivers of past climate variability on a range of timescales, providing a baseline and understanding for use in assessing current and future climate variability and change. These advances reflect progress in developing and understanding new proxies?indirect indicators of past climates preserved in climate archives?as well as in integrating these proxy records with numerical models.  The National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine convened a workshop on June 21-23, 2021, to identify potential future paleoclimate research directions that will help advance the understanding of past, current, and future change in the Earth?s climate system. Using broad community input that was collected through an online questionnaire, workshop participants discussed gaps in current understanding of past climate variability and processes and new research strategies and technological capabilities that could practically be undertaken to effectively fill these knowledge gaps.  Workshop discussions highlighted both emerging areas of research and relevant questions that the community is currently trying to address. Participants highlighted the interest of the community in translating the global emphasis of paleoclimate research into regional connections. The attention to regional scales is motivated by the interest in making policy connections to explore regional vulnerabilities to climate change?for example, to understand extreme events, such as drought and wildfires. A focus on regional scales would involve more records at different resolutions to elucidate these connections. Emerging scientific areas of interest included hydroclimate during past warm periods; connections between the biosphere, marine, and terrestrial ecosystems; and the carbon cycle. These research questions indicate the importance of also understanding large-scale processes in combination with the interest in shorter temporal and smaller spatial scales.  Participants paid much attention to the ways the paleoclimate community can develop geologic models for a no-analog future, leveraging data from the past to better understand, for example, fires, permafrost thaw, and carbon release in a warming climate. Interest in better understanding past extreme events in order to inform present and future climate and communicate with the public and decision makers was also a repeated theme.  Tools and strategies to advance these new research directions were also an essential part of the workshop discussions. Participants discussed sample and data archiving and sharing and the lack of community infrastructure was noted as a potential barrier to the accessibility of paleoclimate records. There was interest among some participants in putting resources behind building community databases that would serve as dynamic resources and facilitate synthesis work, instead of relying on the current volunteer-based model.  Issues around belonging, accessibility, justice, equity, diversity, and inclusion were central to the workshop discussions on advancing paleoclimate research questions. In addition to strategies around skillset and equity-minded training, and tracking metrics for progress to enhance diversity and inclusion in the paleoclimate field (particularly for early career researchers), discussions also centered on knowledge coproduction. Some participants suggested that programmatic and financial support for efforts to engage and establish long-term relationships with local communities may be necessary in order to inform the development of new science questions.  The community questionnaire conducted as part of this activity received 96 thoughtful responses that informed the workshop. The June 2021 workshop was attended by 200-250 participants each day in addition to over 200 viewers of the plenary session webcast. The workshop proceedings have been downloaded or viewed 875 times and the Academies has distributed and sold 33 copies. Since the workshop and release of the workshop proceedings, NSF has announced a new solicitation, Paleo Perspectives on Present and Projected Climate (P4CLIMATE) that draws on many of the themes raised throughout the workshop.  The workshop recordings and additional information are available on the project website: https://www.nationalacademies.org/event/06-21-2021/identifying-new-community-driven-science-themes-for-nsfs-support-of-paleo-perspectives-on-climate-change-p2c2-a-workshop  The workshop proceedings can be downloaded for free from the National Academies: https://nap.nationalacademies.org/catalog/26377/identifying-new-community-driven-science-themes-for-nsfs-support-of-paleoclimate-research          Last Modified: 11/28/2022       Submitted by: Amanda Staudt]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
