<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Open Vascular Surgical Training System for Skill Acquisition and Evaluation]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>253462.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>273462</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Alastair Monk</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>amonk@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924392</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is to streamline surgical training and reduce the burden of surgical complications by creating a device that can train and evaluate surgeons.  The proposed project will demonstrate the feasibility of progressive skills education and quantitative assessment on a simulated open surgery system. This project will develop a high-fidelity modular system and synthetic vasculature to effectively train surgeons in open vascular surgery.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project will advance development of an educational tool to support surgical training.  The device must provide progressive skills education, expose users to a comprehensive range of open surgical procedures, and provide objective feedback metrics. The proposed research will first investigate the feasibility of developing a variety of simulated vascular components, including those with abnormalities, and subsequently integrating them into the benchtop system. The synthetic training models will be evaluated by practicing surgeons using a bipolar scaling method. The mechanical properties of the synthetic vascular tissue will be measured and compared to live tissue. This project will additionally develop components to measure surgical performance. The metrics will be evaluated in a pilot study of a panel of experienced and inexperienced surgeons. The anticipated results are a synthetic vascular material with similar mechanical properties as live tissue, surgical models that are validated as realistic by a panel of expert surgeons, and a system with sensors and components that are capable of differentiating between user skill levels.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/05/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/16/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2035945</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Hannah</FirstName>
<LastName>Eherenfeldt</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Hannah Eherenfeldt</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[heherenfeldt@gmail.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000828960</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/05/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Resuture Inc.</Name>
<CityName>Surprise</CityName>
<ZipCode>853789022</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6197849777</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>12425 W BELL RD STE 110</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AZ09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>DD4NZFP3KVW8</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESUTURE INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[RESUTURE LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>Surprise</CityName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>853789799</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[12425 W Bell Rd, Suite 110]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AZ09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8091</Code>
<Text>SBIR Outreach &amp; Tech. Assist</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>066E</Code>
<Text>INSTRUMENTATION &amp; DIAGNOSTICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8035</Code>
<Text>Hardware Devices</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~273462</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-74fd79ce-7fff-16b7-6575-bb4fb9c5d162"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project enabled ReSuture to develop a high-fidelity modular system to train surgeons in open vascular surgery. Over the course of this project, a robust method to manufacture synthetic vasculature with significantly divergent morphological and mechanical properties was devised. Four mechanical properties of this synthetic vasculature were evaluated and compared to bovine aortic tissue in partnership with the Neithalath and Rajan Labs at Arizona State University. Additionally, a set of sensors capable of providing quantitative feedback on surgical performance have been designed and integrated into the surgical simulation system to improve assessment of user skill. A pilot study was conducted in partnership with the Mayo Clinic to determine the efficacy of the chosen evaluation metrics. The system developed in Phase I allows for the progressive development of psychomotor skills that separates operative learning from patient care, providing valuable tools to surgeons who wish to improve patient outcomes.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The redesigned manufacturing method for customized operable vasculature is a significant development that has the potential to transform the fields of both surgical education and medical device development. ReSuture is the only company to offer operable vasculature that can reproduce the true anatomical complexity of </span><span>in vivo</span><span> structures. This capability extends to developing models that can be based on patient-specific data or procedure-specific models, with abnormalities customized for device development or clinician training. The models are currently being used by medical device manufacturers for aortic device development, clinician education, and sales in multiple vascular device specialties. The models developed during this grant period, unlike the current standard of cadaver or porcine labs, help accelerate medical device companies' product development processes and streamline market adoption through enhanced physician education.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Another noteworthy outcome of the R&amp;D conducted during this grant period are the results of the pilot validation study of preliminary surgical evaluation sensors. ReSuture is the first company to pair high-fidelity procedure-based simulations with capacitive sensing. The results both demonstrate the efficacy of products developed as part of the Phase I grant and emphasize the need for more extensive R&amp;D to provide robust surgical skill quantification. The development of a substantial database of recorded procedures, as performed by operators with different skill levels, to be used for training and testing a robust algorithm will be the logical next goal of subsequent development. The initial results have attracted the interest of leading research institutions, and further industry recognition of this sensor development and the corresponding pilot study will ensue with a presentation of our results at the American College of Surgeons (ACS) and Engineers conference occurring in March 2022.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>ReSuture's sensing technology, developed under this Phase I award, has potential applications across the field of surgery, from surgical evaluation to surgical robotic training. Compared to the conventional methods for data collection, which rely primarily on computer vision, capacitive sensor-derived data could offer a much deeper perspective on surgical operations. While computer vision tracks movement in two-dimensional space and derives depth by means of an algorithm, properly developed capacitive sensing has the potential to track movement in three-dimensional space and allows one to accurately measure the force being applied. This sensing&nbsp; technology can provide a more robust understanding of how surgeons and surgical devices interact with surrounding tissue, and has the potential to generate critical data for medical device manufacturers, surgical instructors, and practicing surgeons.</span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/15/2022<br>      Modified by: Hannah&nbsp;Eherenfeldt</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2035945/2035945_10716028_1644960157599_CarotidPlaqueRemoval--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2035945/2035945_10716028_1644960157599_CarotidPlaqueRemoval--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Synthetic Carotid Plaque Elevation"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2035945/2035945_10716028_1644960157599_CarotidPlaqueRemoval--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Synthetic Carotid Plaque Elevation"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">ReSuture carotid endarterectomy training model with plaque elevation conducted by a surgeon.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Hannah Eherenfeldt</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Hannah&nbsp;Eherenfeldt</div> <div class="imageTitle">Synthetic Carotid Plaque Elevation</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2035945/2035945_10716028_1644959293334_20210709_122843--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2035945/2035945_10716028_1644959293334_20210709_122843--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Synthetic Fistula Creation"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2035945/2035945_10716028_1644959293334_20210709_122843--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Synthetic Fistula Creation"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">ReSuture synthetic trainer for arteriovenous fistula creation.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Hannah Eherenfeldt</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Hannah&nbsp;Eherenfeldt</div> <div class="imageTitle">Synthetic Fistula Creation</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2035945/2035945_10716028_1644960072435_CarotidAngioplasty--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2035945/2035945_10716028_1644960072435_CarotidAngioplasty--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Synthetic Carotid Patch Angioplasty"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2035945/2035945_10716028_1644960072435_CarotidAngioplasty--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Synthetic Carotid Patch Angioplasty"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">This is a photo of ReSuture's synthetic carotid model after a patch angioplasty completed by a surgeon.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Hannah Eherenfeldt</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Hannah&nbsp;Eherenfeldt</div> <div class="imageTitle">Synthetic Carotid Patch Angioplasty</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2035945/2035945_10716028_1644959055352_saphenousvein--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2035945/2035945_10716028_1644959055352_saphenousvein--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Synthetic Saphenous Vein"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2035945/2035945_10716028_1644959055352_saphenousvein--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Synthetic Saphenous Vein"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Synthetic saphenous vein model created by ReSuture using novel manufacturing method</div> <div class="imageCredit">Benjamin M Knapp</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Hannah&nbsp;Eherenfeldt</div> <div class="imageTitle">Synthetic Saphenous Vein</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2035945/2035945_10716028_1644960298877_MayoClinicStudyLowPressure--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2035945/2035945_10716028_1644960298877_MayoClinicStudyLowPressure--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Capacitive Sensing Technology - Low Pressure"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2035945/2035945_10716028_1644960298877_MayoClinicStudyLowPressure--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Capacitive Sensing Technology - Low Pressure"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Graph of force applied by a surgeon when making a skin incision using ReSuture's capacitive sensing technology.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Benjamin Knapp</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Hannah&nbsp;Eherenfeldt</div> <div class="imageTitle">Capacitive Sensing Technology - Low Pressure</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2035945/2035945_10716028_1644960371654_MayoClinicStudyPeak--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2035945/2035945_10716028_1644960371654_MayoClinicStudyPeak--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Capacitive Sensing Technology - Peak Pressure"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2035945/2035945_10716028_1644960371654_MayoClinicStudyPeak--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Capacitive Sensing Technology - Peak Pressure"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Peak pressure when making a surgeon is making a skin incision as measured by ReSuture's capacitive sensing technology.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Benjamin Knapp</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Hannah&nbsp;Eherenfeldt</div> <div class="imageTitle">Capacitive Sensing Technology - Peak Pressure</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project enabled ReSuture to develop a high-fidelity modular system to train surgeons in open vascular surgery. Over the course of this project, a robust method to manufacture synthetic vasculature with significantly divergent morphological and mechanical properties was devised. Four mechanical properties of this synthetic vasculature were evaluated and compared to bovine aortic tissue in partnership with the Neithalath and Rajan Labs at Arizona State University. Additionally, a set of sensors capable of providing quantitative feedback on surgical performance have been designed and integrated into the surgical simulation system to improve assessment of user skill. A pilot study was conducted in partnership with the Mayo Clinic to determine the efficacy of the chosen evaluation metrics. The system developed in Phase I allows for the progressive development of psychomotor skills that separates operative learning from patient care, providing valuable tools to surgeons who wish to improve patient outcomes.  The redesigned manufacturing method for customized operable vasculature is a significant development that has the potential to transform the fields of both surgical education and medical device development. ReSuture is the only company to offer operable vasculature that can reproduce the true anatomical complexity of in vivo structures. This capability extends to developing models that can be based on patient-specific data or procedure-specific models, with abnormalities customized for device development or clinician training. The models are currently being used by medical device manufacturers for aortic device development, clinician education, and sales in multiple vascular device specialties. The models developed during this grant period, unlike the current standard of cadaver or porcine labs, help accelerate medical device companies' product development processes and streamline market adoption through enhanced physician education. Another noteworthy outcome of the R&amp;D conducted during this grant period are the results of the pilot validation study of preliminary surgical evaluation sensors. ReSuture is the first company to pair high-fidelity procedure-based simulations with capacitive sensing. The results both demonstrate the efficacy of products developed as part of the Phase I grant and emphasize the need for more extensive R&amp;D to provide robust surgical skill quantification. The development of a substantial database of recorded procedures, as performed by operators with different skill levels, to be used for training and testing a robust algorithm will be the logical next goal of subsequent development. The initial results have attracted the interest of leading research institutions, and further industry recognition of this sensor development and the corresponding pilot study will ensue with a presentation of our results at the American College of Surgeons (ACS) and Engineers conference occurring in March 2022. ReSuture's sensing technology, developed under this Phase I award, has potential applications across the field of surgery, from surgical evaluation to surgical robotic training. Compared to the conventional methods for data collection, which rely primarily on computer vision, capacitive sensor-derived data could offer a much deeper perspective on surgical operations. While computer vision tracks movement in two-dimensional space and derives depth by means of an algorithm, properly developed capacitive sensing has the potential to track movement in three-dimensional space and allows one to accurately measure the force being applied. This sensing  technology can provide a more robust understanding of how surgeons and surgical devices interact with surrounding tissue, and has the potential to generate critical data for medical device manufacturers, surgical instructors, and practicing surgeons.       Last Modified: 02/15/2022       Submitted by: Hannah Eherenfeldt]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
