<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[EAGER: Collaborative Research: Networking Faculty Seeds for Collective Change in the Geosciences]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>11/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>29055.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>29055</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>RISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div of Res, Innovation, Synergies, &amp; Edu</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Brandon Jones</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mbjones@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924713</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The PIs plan to create a professional development curriculum that is highly tailorable to an individual's particular institutional context. They seek to recruit 10 Seeding Diversity Fellows from 10 different universities who will then bring on board another two partners to join the team. Each team of three will then identify gatekeeping mechanisms that impede the ability of their particular institution to recruit, retain, and include diverse faculty and students in the geosciences. The proposed curriculum will implement and research an innovative use of social network analysis as a tool for participants to identify potential collaborators so that, together, they can collectively change departmental beliefs and behaviors. The PIs will also develop and research three, new, mixed-reality simulations that combine artificial intelligence with human conversational intuition to teach participants how to manage conflicts while advocating for systemic changes in university and departmental procedures. Building off of the work from the pilot GOLD:GeoDES project, these new simulations will extend beyond individual actions and move more toward coordinating and leveraging social networks to effect institutional change.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The PI's proposed professional development curriculum includes the following two innovations: 1. Helping participants to identify and analyze their social networks to select two additional key individuals with whom to collaborate to change collective behaviors in a department. In the pilot GeoDES project, the PIs recognized that changing collective behaviors of a department is a heavier lift than changing individual behaviors and beliefs. 2. Making use of innovative mixed-reality simulations that combine artificial intelligence with human conversational intuition to teach participants how to manage conflicts while advocating for systemic changes in university and departmental procedures. The project's innovation rests on the idea that changing the behavior of many people within a department requires a robust intervention grounded in strong theoretical foundations that have shown promising results.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/02/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/14/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2035816</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Brian</FirstName>
<LastName>Teppen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Brian J Teppen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[teppen@msu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000335293</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/02/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Michigan State University</Name>
<CityName>EAST LANSING</CityName>
<ZipCode>488242600</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5173555040</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>426 AUDITORIUM RD RM 2</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>R28EKN92ZTZ9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MICHIGAN STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>VJKZC4D1JN36</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Michigan State University]]></Name>
<CityName>East Lansing</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>488246270</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1066 Bogue Street, Room 538]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7699</Code>
<Text>Integrat &amp; Collab Ed &amp; Rsearch</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~29055</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="Default">The goal of this project is to test new methods of professional development that increase the effectiveness of geoscience faculty members to lead social change in their institutions. The collaborative group recruited seven participants (team leaders) to act as faculty 'seeds for change' at each of seven different U.S. geoscience institutions. With a goal of adding power to their social networks, each of these team leaders recruited two allies to promote diversity, equity, and inclusion (DEI) at their institution and each team collaboratively developed DEI goals tailored to their own institutional contexts. The resulting 21 people were surveyed regarding their motivations, and their social networks were also analyzed gto help understand their influences. The project provided three rounds of coaching sessions to help leaders strategize and manage relationships in their departments. The project also created mixed-reality simulations to give participants realistic yet safe and non-threatening practice in DEI advocacy and managing common conflicts that arise while advocating for systemic change. As of November 2022, participants had engaged in one round of mixed-reality simulations with two more piloted and being adapted during a no-cost extension. An exciting innovation is that the PI and co-PI at William &amp; Mary purchased their own license for the simulations to gain full control over designing, producing, and running these simulations. They have hired and trained three simulation specialists to build capacity for running simulations at a larger scale. These mixed-reality simulations have shown great promise for increasing the skills and confidence of geoscience faculty to engage in DEI-positive social change at their institutions.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/21/2023<br>      Modified by: Brian&nbsp;J&nbsp;Teppen</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[The goal of this project is to test new methods of professional development that increase the effectiveness of geoscience faculty members to lead social change in their institutions. The collaborative group recruited seven participants (team leaders) to act as faculty 'seeds for change' at each of seven different U.S. geoscience institutions. With a goal of adding power to their social networks, each of these team leaders recruited two allies to promote diversity, equity, and inclusion (DEI) at their institution and each team collaboratively developed DEI goals tailored to their own institutional contexts. The resulting 21 people were surveyed regarding their motivations, and their social networks were also analyzed gto help understand their influences. The project provided three rounds of coaching sessions to help leaders strategize and manage relationships in their departments. The project also created mixed-reality simulations to give participants realistic yet safe and non-threatening practice in DEI advocacy and managing common conflicts that arise while advocating for systemic change. As of November 2022, participants had engaged in one round of mixed-reality simulations with two more piloted and being adapted during a no-cost extension. An exciting innovation is that the PI and co-PI at William &amp; Mary purchased their own license for the simulations to gain full control over designing, producing, and running these simulations. They have hired and trained three simulation specialists to build capacity for running simulations at a larger scale. These mixed-reality simulations have shown great promise for increasing the skills and confidence of geoscience faculty to engage in DEI-positive social change at their institutions.       Last Modified: 02/21/2023       Submitted by: Brian J Teppen]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
