<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Development of a Novel Biosensor to Accelerate Investigations of COVID-19 and the Gut Microbiome.]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/15/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>255658.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>255658</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Erik Pierstorff</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>epiersto@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922165</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project will be advanced understanding of the interaction between SARS-CoV-2, COVID-19, and the human gut microbiome, potentially resulting in new treatment approaches for COVID-19 patients.  This project will develop a novel biosensor to enable low-cost, highly standardized studies of links between the human gut microbiome and COVID-19 to help evaluate the performance of different therapeutic approaches, drugs, vaccines, and other clinical interventions. Finally, once this project is successfully completed, there is a longer-term opportunity to add detection capability to the technology, enabling real-time, at-home tracking of SARS-CoV-2 prevalence in stool samples of high-risk patients and their caretakers. This would enable the technology to become a continuous viral detection tool.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed project will advance a sensor to allow isolation and preservation of microbial RNA from stool samples.  Existing technique preserve microbial DNA but are not sensitive enough to preserve the far less stable RNA. The project will evaluate candidate extraction and fixative reagents based on technical performance, length of RNA stability, reagent cost, and storage requirements. Simultaneously, the project will develop an advanced systems architecture enabling a scalable solution for widespread use.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/06/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/11/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2035981</AwardID>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>BiomeSense&rsquo;s goals with this SBIR Phase I award was to develop proof of concept procedures for the isolation and storage of COVID-19 RNA from human stool samples that have a low per-sample cost and are mechanically simple enough to feasibly integrate into BiomeSense&rsquo;s GutLab technology. GutLab is an automated human stool collection and DNA processing system capable of sustained use by participants of human gut microbiome studies. &nbsp;</p> <p>During our award timeframe we successfully developed two feasible protocols for RNA isolation. One protocol was selected for priority development based on our evaluation criteria of quality, quantity and cost. Additionally, we identified multiple commercially viable storage solutions that were successful in keeping RNA integrity high over several weeks of room temperature storage. Finally, we combined the priority extraction protocol and storage solutions in a single proof-of-concept experiment and successfully demonstrated the ability to extract and store SARS-Cov-2 RNA for 4 weeks at room temperature.</p> <p>Our next steps are to #1) continue optimizing the proof of concept protocols to further improve performance, as defined by quality and quantity of RNA, #2) broaden scope of RNA studies to explore whether identified protocols can support other use cases such as RNA-seq, and #3) begin engineering design work to integrate identified protocols into the GutLab technology. These steps would allow for unprecedented wealth of information to be gathered during human gut microbiome studies via DNA and RNA extraction and sequencing and contribute significantly to unlocking the clinical potential of the gut microbiome.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/28/2021<br>      Modified by: Dylan&nbsp;Nichols</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ BiomeSense’s goals with this SBIR Phase I award was to develop proof of concept procedures for the isolation and storage of COVID-19 RNA from human stool samples that have a low per-sample cost and are mechanically simple enough to feasibly integrate into BiomeSense’s GutLab technology. GutLab is an automated human stool collection and DNA processing system capable of sustained use by participants of human gut microbiome studies.    During our award timeframe we successfully developed two feasible protocols for RNA isolation. One protocol was selected for priority development based on our evaluation criteria of quality, quantity and cost. Additionally, we identified multiple commercially viable storage solutions that were successful in keeping RNA integrity high over several weeks of room temperature storage. Finally, we combined the priority extraction protocol and storage solutions in a single proof-of-concept experiment and successfully demonstrated the ability to extract and store SARS-Cov-2 RNA for 4 weeks at room temperature.  Our next steps are to #1) continue optimizing the proof of concept protocols to further improve performance, as defined by quality and quantity of RNA, #2) broaden scope of RNA studies to explore whether identified protocols can support other use cases such as RNA-seq, and #3) begin engineering design work to integrate identified protocols into the GutLab technology. These steps would allow for unprecedented wealth of information to be gathered during human gut microbiome studies via DNA and RNA extraction and sequencing and contribute significantly to unlocking the clinical potential of the gut microbiome.           Last Modified: 09/28/2021       Submitted by: Dylan Nichols]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
