<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Stress Pathway Inhibition Prevents COVID-19 Infection (COVID-19)]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/15/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>255700.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>255700</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kaitlin Bratlie</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is the pursuit of developing a first-in-class, non-toxic, inexpensive, and effective treatment for COVID-19 for vulnerable patients including the elderly and those at additional risk from cancer, high blood pressure, diabetes and obesity. These conditions produce high levels of stress on diseased cells compared to normal cells. This project leverages insights that COVID-19 uses the same pathway to enhance viral infection as cancer cells use for survival; this process causes immune system weakening which allows tumor cells and viruses to multiply.   The proposed project will create innovative anti-viral therapies by exploring how this survival pathway increases COVID-19 infectivity, weakens the immune system and induces tumor cell resistance. Its use can be expanded to other new targets and therapies. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This SBIR Phase I project leverages insights regarding similarities between tumors and viral infections. This project will advance translation of a novel inhibitor to a survival factor that continually keeps these wounds from healing by increasing tumor survival and enhancing viral infections. This novel inhibitor can potently block the binding of COVID-19 spike protein to this survival factor, which has been shown to be highly expressed on stressed lung cells as a result of cancer and other inflammatory diseases. The goals of this project are to 1) show that the proposed COVID-19 inhibitor can block COVID-19 infection of stressed lung cells; 2) reduce cytokine expression to lessen the cytokine storm associated with COVID-19 infection; 3) prevent immune weakening and 4) inhibit coagulopathy to lessen the “blood clot storm”. The project will use standard in vitro viral infectivity assays and in vivo immune competent tumor-bearing mice models infected with a lethal strain of COVID-19. Together, these studies will demonstrate that the proposed lead survival factor inhibitor can significantly reduce the attachment, entry and replication of COVID-19 virus as well as reduce the immune suppressive nature of infected lung alveolar epithelial cells in vitro and in vivo.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/06/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/06/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2035793</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Donald</FirstName>
<LastName>Davidson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Donald J Davidson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[creativebiotherapeutics@gmail.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000828549</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/06/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>CREATIVE BIOTHERAPEUTICS LLC</Name>
<CityName>GURNEE</CityName>
<ZipCode>600313257</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2246276402</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4835 KINGS WAY W</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>YNJ8ST14PBD8</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CREATIVE BIOTHERAPEUTICS LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Creative BioTherapeutics]]></Name>
<CityName>Gurnee</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>600313257</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[200 South Greenleaf, Suite J]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>6883</Code>
<Text>CHEMISTRY OF LIFE PROCESSES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~255700</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The SARS-CoV-2 virus that results in COVID-19 infection has persisted for nearly two years causing hundreds of thousands of deaths in the US, millions worldwide and untold financial business and personal hardships. Based on the number and rapid spread of the ?wild type? and subsequent mutations, it appears as if the virus may be part of our ongoing medical landscape in the future. The presence of comorbidities such as cancer, diabetes, or obesity for 198 million Americans paired with aging, places them at higher risk for infection and possible death. We are finding that despite vaccination status, when these pre-existing conditions are present the immune system may not be robust enough to fight the infection resulting in permanent lung damage and possible death. As such there is an ongoing, urgent and critical need for an anti-viral therapy that can block SARS-CoV-2 and related mutations in people with pre-existing conditions, leading to a more complete recovery.</p> <p>Creative BioTherapeutics was founded to pursue novel cancer research beginning where other therapies have failed. A key discovery of our research is the role of a protein on the cell surface, that helps tumors survive by hiding from the immune system. Using our extensive experience in drug discovery, we have discovered and invented a novel drug that blocks this protein on the cell surface resulting in tumor death. This identified survival protein, is not only present on tumor cells, it has also been shown to be increased on lung and blood vessels cells in people with comorbidities. Early in the COVID-19 pandemic we identified that our cancer therapies could have an impact on the SARS-CoV-2 virus that was gripping the world. Recently, several researchers have shown that this cell surface protein, protects the ACE2 receptor on the cell allowing the SARS-CoV-2 spike protein to attach. Since the same survival factor used by tumors is also used by viruses to infect cells, we pivoted to include viral research to evaluate our potential for a COVID-19 therapeutic.</p> <p>Tumors have been described as a ?wound that won?t heal?. Since we believe that viral infections are very similar to tumors and could also be described as wounds that won?t heal, this would explain why people with comorbidities have a much higher risk for SARS-CoV-2 infection.&nbsp; As such, the results from this NSF SBIR Phase I grant research show that our lead biologic therapy, CBT300, potently blocks all of the SARS-CoV-2 virus spike proteins including all of the current mutations (wild-type, Alpha, Beta, Delta, Lambda, and Omicron) from binding to this survival protein on the cell surface and the ACE2 receptor on lung cells. When our therapy binds to these cell surface receptors, the virus no longer has a ?docking station? to enter the cell stopping the infection. &nbsp;In fact, we can show that our CBT300 therapy can block not only the spike protein, but also whole SARS-CoV-2 virus, EBOLA virus and Influenza A virus from infecting cells.&nbsp;</p> <p>Our data demonstrates that this cell surface protein enhances SARS-CoV-2 viral infection and is essential for COVID-19 disease.&nbsp; With CBT300, we can reverse the inflammation and clotting around SARS-CoV-2 infected lung cells. By further understanding the binding of SARS-CoV-2 mutations, we can predict which mutations are more infectious and which are more deadly.&nbsp; Finally, by understanding how viruses bind to the cell, we can predict which other viruses can be blocked by CBT300.&nbsp; Currently, we show that the MERS-CoV, EBOLA, Influenza A, Dengue and the common cold (CoV-NL63) spike proteins are all blocked from binding by CBT300.&nbsp;</p> <p>We can also show that besides SARS-CoV-2 virus, whole live viruses of EBOLA and Influenza A can be prevented from infecting human lung or kidney cells with CBT300.&nbsp; With a greater knowledge of this survival protein and how viruses bind, we understand that SARS-CoV-1 will not be inhibited by CBT300 but EBOLA will be inhibited. &nbsp;To validate this understanding, we tested both of these live viruses in mouse models. Our data shows that CBT300 does not inhibit SARS-CoV-1 viral infection, but does inhibit EBOLA virus infection in mice.&nbsp; In fact, all mice infected with a high viral load of EBOLA without treatment &nbsp;died within 5-6 days but about 30% of the mice treated with CBT300 survived past 14 days and were considered cured.&nbsp; As a result of our NSF Phase I funding, our studies show that our lead &nbsp;therapy, CBT300, is effective against SARS-CoV-2 and all variants as wells as against EBOLA and influenza A virus infection.</p> <p>Based on these findings and the need for safe and effective therapies, further study and drug development is critical to move our therapy to the market. &nbsp;As an innovative treatment, our therapy is presenting an exciting and promising opportunity to expand the options for viral treatment with our broad spectrum, anti-viral therapy leading to a healthier future.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/10/2022<br>      Modified by: Donald&nbsp;J&nbsp;Davidson</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The SARS-CoV-2 virus that results in COVID-19 infection has persisted for nearly two years causing hundreds of thousands of deaths in the US, millions worldwide and untold financial business and personal hardships. Based on the number and rapid spread of the ?wild type? and subsequent mutations, it appears as if the virus may be part of our ongoing medical landscape in the future. The presence of comorbidities such as cancer, diabetes, or obesity for 198 million Americans paired with aging, places them at higher risk for infection and possible death. We are finding that despite vaccination status, when these pre-existing conditions are present the immune system may not be robust enough to fight the infection resulting in permanent lung damage and possible death. As such there is an ongoing, urgent and critical need for an anti-viral therapy that can block SARS-CoV-2 and related mutations in people with pre-existing conditions, leading to a more complete recovery.  Creative BioTherapeutics was founded to pursue novel cancer research beginning where other therapies have failed. A key discovery of our research is the role of a protein on the cell surface, that helps tumors survive by hiding from the immune system. Using our extensive experience in drug discovery, we have discovered and invented a novel drug that blocks this protein on the cell surface resulting in tumor death. This identified survival protein, is not only present on tumor cells, it has also been shown to be increased on lung and blood vessels cells in people with comorbidities. Early in the COVID-19 pandemic we identified that our cancer therapies could have an impact on the SARS-CoV-2 virus that was gripping the world. Recently, several researchers have shown that this cell surface protein, protects the ACE2 receptor on the cell allowing the SARS-CoV-2 spike protein to attach. Since the same survival factor used by tumors is also used by viruses to infect cells, we pivoted to include viral research to evaluate our potential for a COVID-19 therapeutic.  Tumors have been described as a ?wound that won?t heal?. Since we believe that viral infections are very similar to tumors and could also be described as wounds that won?t heal, this would explain why people with comorbidities have a much higher risk for SARS-CoV-2 infection.  As such, the results from this NSF SBIR Phase I grant research show that our lead biologic therapy, CBT300, potently blocks all of the SARS-CoV-2 virus spike proteins including all of the current mutations (wild-type, Alpha, Beta, Delta, Lambda, and Omicron) from binding to this survival protein on the cell surface and the ACE2 receptor on lung cells. When our therapy binds to these cell surface receptors, the virus no longer has a ?docking station? to enter the cell stopping the infection.  In fact, we can show that our CBT300 therapy can block not only the spike protein, but also whole SARS-CoV-2 virus, EBOLA virus and Influenza A virus from infecting cells.   Our data demonstrates that this cell surface protein enhances SARS-CoV-2 viral infection and is essential for COVID-19 disease.  With CBT300, we can reverse the inflammation and clotting around SARS-CoV-2 infected lung cells. By further understanding the binding of SARS-CoV-2 mutations, we can predict which mutations are more infectious and which are more deadly.  Finally, by understanding how viruses bind to the cell, we can predict which other viruses can be blocked by CBT300.  Currently, we show that the MERS-CoV, EBOLA, Influenza A, Dengue and the common cold (CoV-NL63) spike proteins are all blocked from binding by CBT300.   We can also show that besides SARS-CoV-2 virus, whole live viruses of EBOLA and Influenza A can be prevented from infecting human lung or kidney cells with CBT300.  With a greater knowledge of this survival protein and how viruses bind, we understand that SARS-CoV-1 will not be inhibited by CBT300 but EBOLA will be inhibited.  To validate this understanding, we tested both of these live viruses in mouse models. Our data shows that CBT300 does not inhibit SARS-CoV-1 viral infection, but does inhibit EBOLA virus infection in mice.  In fact, all mice infected with a high viral load of EBOLA without treatment  died within 5-6 days but about 30% of the mice treated with CBT300 survived past 14 days and were considered cured.  As a result of our NSF Phase I funding, our studies show that our lead  therapy, CBT300, is effective against SARS-CoV-2 and all variants as wells as against EBOLA and influenza A virus infection.  Based on these findings and the need for safe and effective therapies, further study and drug development is critical to move our therapy to the market.  As an innovative treatment, our therapy is presenting an exciting and promising opportunity to expand the options for viral treatment with our broad spectrum, anti-viral therapy leading to a healthier future.             Last Modified: 01/10/2022       Submitted by: Donald J Davidson]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
