<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[I-Corps:  Load bearing ceramic bone scaffolds produced via 3D printing]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ruth Shuman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rshuman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922160</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this I-Corps project is the development of a novel solution for bone repair and replacement scaffolds. In the United States alone, 5-10% of fracture repairs experience delayed healing or non-union, which means close to 800,000 patients suffer from reoperation or complications. 3D printing will make this method of creating bone scaffolds affordable and attainable. The proposed technology provides 3D printed, customizable, ceramic bone scaffolds that are biocompatible and mimic the mechanical properties of native bone. Using 3D printing as an affordable manufacturing process to make the novel scaffold will provide a way for bone repairs to be more accessible and successful.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project is based on the development of a powder preparation technique that produces customizable bone scaffolds via a custom-made powder-based 3D printer. The proposed technology addresses major issues with current methods of repairing or replacing bone injuries. Novel features of the scaffolds produced using the proposed technology include injury-specific geometry, strength as high as native bone, biocompatible ceramic material, and highly tailorable properties.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/08/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/08/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2035370</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Eugene</FirstName>
<LastName>Olevsky</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Eugene Olevsky</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[eolevsky@mail.sdsu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000275415</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/08/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>San Diego State University Foundation</Name>
<CityName>SAN DIEGO</CityName>
<ZipCode>921821901</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6195945731</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5250 CAMPANILE DR MC1947</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>53</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA53</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>H59JKGFZKHL7</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SAN DIEGO STATE UNIVERSITY FOUNDATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[San Diego State University]]></Name>
<CityName>San Diego</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>921821323</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5500 Campanile Dr.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>53</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA53</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>1) The team learned a lot about how to conduct a market research study. The fundamentals were&nbsp;learned on how to identify key stakeholders, important value propositions and critical questions to&nbsp;lead us into a definite conclusion on our technology?s potential.</p> <p>2) More than 150 customer discovery interviews allowed us to gauge the current status of the&nbsp;market and how our product fits into it.</p> <p>3) Through the knowledge gained in the didactic portion of the program and the insight we&nbsp;gained from all interviewees, the team determined there is a high demand and need for this&nbsp;technology in the market.<br />The current gold standard is autologous or allographic bone which is limited in size, shape and&nbsp;availability. This was confirmed by most surgeons the team spoke to.</p> <p>There is potential for implementation in ?niche? surgery types. For example, pediatric surgery. One&nbsp;pediatric surgeon from Rady?s Children?s Hospital stated that at times, he must cut the standard&nbsp;implants in the operating room to fit his small patients.</p> <p>Although there are many metallic implants being used in surgery today, there are no ceramic&nbsp;components being printed and used. When asked, most stakeholders mentioned ceramic materials would&nbsp;be ideal however, manufacturing of ceramics has been too difficult and so there has been no&nbsp;success.</p> <p>4) The team determined that the technology is financially viable by using CMS Reimbursement&nbsp;codes to our advantage. Furthermore, the implementation of our technology would not require&nbsp;significant infrastructure changes or workflow disruption.<br /><br />5) Based on the details provided above, the team believes there is product market fit.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/08/2022<br>      Modified by: Eugene&nbsp;Olevsky</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2035370/2035370_10683525_1644340035565_RapidBonetech--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2035370/2035370_10683525_1644340035565_RapidBonetech--rgov-800width.jpg" title="3D-Printed Bone Implant"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2035370/2035370_10683525_1644340035565_RapidBonetech--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="3D-Printed Bone Implant"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">3D-Printed Bone Implant</div> <div class="imageCredit">Maricruz Carrillo</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Eugene&nbsp;Olevsky</div> <div class="imageTitle">3D-Printed Bone Implant</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ 1) The team learned a lot about how to conduct a market research study. The fundamentals were learned on how to identify key stakeholders, important value propositions and critical questions to lead us into a definite conclusion on our technology?s potential.  2) More than 150 customer discovery interviews allowed us to gauge the current status of the market and how our product fits into it.  3) Through the knowledge gained in the didactic portion of the program and the insight we gained from all interviewees, the team determined there is a high demand and need for this technology in the market. The current gold standard is autologous or allographic bone which is limited in size, shape and availability. This was confirmed by most surgeons the team spoke to.  There is potential for implementation in ?niche? surgery types. For example, pediatric surgery. One pediatric surgeon from Rady?s Children?s Hospital stated that at times, he must cut the standard implants in the operating room to fit his small patients.  Although there are many metallic implants being used in surgery today, there are no ceramic components being printed and used. When asked, most stakeholders mentioned ceramic materials would be ideal however, manufacturing of ceramics has been too difficult and so there has been no success.  4) The team determined that the technology is financially viable by using CMS Reimbursement codes to our advantage. Furthermore, the implementation of our technology would not require significant infrastructure changes or workflow disruption.  5) Based on the details provided above, the team believes there is product market fit.       Last Modified: 02/08/2022       Submitted by: Eugene Olevsky]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
