<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID/Collaborative Research: Digitizing Early Cretaceous dinosaur trackways to preserve the geological heritage of central Texas]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>12070.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>12070</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Dena Smith</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dmsmith@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927431</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Dinosaur tracks and trackways provide invaluable information about ancient lifeforms and are of great interest to the general public. Yet, increasing urbanization jeopardizes their preservation. This is especially true in central Texas where the metropolitan population grows by 1.7% yearly, and puts dinosaur tracksites exposed in rural areas and creeks at risk. Other sources of destruction include transient flood and weathering enhanced by climate change. This proposal will preserve three important sites in a digital format using advanced imagery techniques and will include analysis of collected rock samples to provide information about the landscape where these dinosaurs lived. New data will be integrated into the Witte Museum in San Antonio, Texas, where it can be used for scientific research and to educate the general public on preservation best practice and the ecology of life in central Texas about 110 million years ago. This project will engage researchers from four institutions with a strong track record on the topic and they will mentor non-traditional graduate and undergraduate students to solidify their interest in the geosciences and retain them in the major. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will inform on the depositional environment and the conditions that promoted the preservation of trace fossils. The digitization of each site using photogrammetric techniques will be complemented by detailed analysis of rock samples using microscopy and geochemistry. Results will evaluate whether dinosaur tracks are preferentially preserved in shallow marine sediments deposited during periods of sea-level fall, when their frequent subaerial exposure under a hot and dry climate favored their early lithification and preservation. Alternatively, preservation may be enhanced by rapid burial with clay-rich sediment in a hot and humid environment. Geochemical and petrographic data also will be used to test these hypotheses. The integration of all results in a database available to researchers and the general public will showcase the cultural heritage of Texas and serve as a basis for future research.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/29/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/29/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2035530</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Marina</FirstName>
<LastName>Suarez</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Marina B Suarez</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mb.suarez@ku.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000589998</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/29/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Kansas Center for Research Inc</Name>
<CityName>LAWRENCE</CityName>
<ZipCode>660457552</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7858643441</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2385 IRVING HILL RD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Kansas</StateName>
<StateCode>KS</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>KS01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>SSUJB3GSH8A5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF KANSAS CENTER FOR RESEARCH INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Kansas Center for Research Inc]]></Name>
<CityName>Lawrence</CityName>
<StateCode>KS</StateCode>
<ZipCode>660457568</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2385 IRVING HILL RD]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Kansas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>KS01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7459</Code>
<Text>Sedimentary Geo &amp; Paleobiology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~12070</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Dinosaur tracks and rocks that preserve them provide a window into the past. The physical and geochemical characteristics of these strata and the tracks therein result from the environment at the time of deposition, the behavior of the track makers, and the post-depositional conditions. Dinosaur tracks are common in the Lower Cretaceous Glen Rose Formation of central Texas, and were formed in marine environments representing the ancient shoreline of the Gulf of Mexico. While there have been previous studies of these trackways, a detailed study utilizing multiple geologic and geochemical tools will provide greater insight into these unique traces of ancient life. The opportunity to explore a range of preservation styles occurs in Central Texas, specifically at three sites: Startzville, the Blanco River, and the South Fork of the San Gabriel River (west and east).&nbsp; Many of the sites (especially the site at Startzville) are vulnerable to ongoing climate change and will disappear because of weathering, stream erosion, and urbanization. The goals of this project are to 1) develop digital archives of dinosaur track sites using photogrammetry data, and 2) provide a detailed interpretation of the environments where dinosaurs lived and constrain the conditions that led to the preservation of the tracks using sedimentologic and geochemical data.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>At the Startzville locality, tracks are preserved in limestone and are undertracks (wherein the impressions visible today are the result of registration of the track into the layers underlying the original track surface). The tracks at the Blanco River site are also preserved in limestone but correspond to a true track surface. Tracks at the San Gabriel River site are preserved in dolostone. East San Gabriel River site preserves tracks as true track, while the West San Gabriel River site shows undertracks. All locations are interpreted to have been deposited in shoreline to tidal flat to offshore and open marine environments.</p> <p>The primary aim for this part of the research project was the analysis and interpretation of carbon and oxygen stable isotopes composition of rock samples at these track sites. The Glen Rose Formation has been investigated petrographically and with stable isotopes in the past, and previous work on stable isotopes reveals that potential exposure surfaces (where dinosaur tracks are likely to occur) are characterized by low carbon and oxygen isotope values (Allen and Matthews, 1982), characteristic of lithification under freshwater (groundwater derived from precipitation). The original hypothesis is that the track surfaces would show consistent decreases in carbon and oxygen isotope values compared to strata above and below them. However, this was not the case. Only the Startzville locality shows low values, especially in the remnant traces of what is thought to be the original track surface (Figure 1). While the stable isotope values did not show a consistent pattern of decreased values at the track surface, the elemental geochemistry of the overlying units show a consistent pattern. In all three sites, the track surfaces are overlain by mudrock or clay-rich limestone containing chemical evidence for greater input of silicate material (Al, Si, and Ti) and micronutrients (Ba, Ni, Cu, Fe, P) that are interpreted to have been transported from land. This suggests that burial by silicate sediment input played an important role in the preservation of the tracks, as opposed to just early lithification under the influence of fresh groundwater.</p> <p>The physical and digital data collected as part of this project by co-PIs preserve the evidence of dinosaur behavior. At each locality, measurements of individual track and trackway parameters indicate that theropod and sauropod dinosaurs responsible for these tracks were between 2.1 and 3.3 and 3.8 to 4.6 m high (at the hip) and were moving at a speed ranging from 4.2 to 17.0 and 2.7 to 3.7 kilometer per hour, respectively. The digital archive of this project will be housed at the Witte Museum in San Antonio, showcasing the unique geological wonders of central Texas to the general public.&nbsp; Results from this project have been used in the development of educational materials for teaching high school and introductory college field projects on making observations, gathering data on trackways, and using the data to test hypotheses and to draw conclusions on the size, speed and behavior of the dinosaurs and the paleoenvironments represented in the rock record.&nbsp; This project supported three undergraduate student projects at Trinity University, one undergraduate student project and a Ph.D. project at The University of Texas San Antonio. Students were mentored by a multidisciplinary team of professors and peers from The University of Texas at San Antonio, Trinity University, The University of Kansas, Kansas State University, and the Witte Museum. Activities supported by the project allowed students the opportunity to for networking, peer and traditional mentoring, and ways to learn how to discuss and defend their ideas. In addition, it helped demonstrate the teamwork aspect of science.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/02/2022<br>      Modified by: Marina&nbsp;B&nbsp;Suarez</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2035530/2035530_10681289_1669958068652_VFW_summaryIsotopeData-forNSF-2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2035530/2035530_10681289_1669958068652_VFW_summaryIsotopeData-forNSF-2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Stable Isotope Values of Dinosaur Tracks, Startzville, Texas"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2035530/2035530_10681289_1669958068652_VFW_summaryIsotopeData-forNSF-2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Stable Isotope Values of Dinosaur Tracks, Startzville, Texas"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Stable isotope values that suggests the track layer (light colored rock that has mostly been eroded) has been lithified under the influence of freshwater. Of the three locations studied, only this site shows this pattern.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Marina Suarez</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Marina&nbsp;B&nbsp;Suarez</div> <div class="imageTitle">Stable Isotope Values of Dinosaur Tracks, Startzville, Texas</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Dinosaur tracks and rocks that preserve them provide a window into the past. The physical and geochemical characteristics of these strata and the tracks therein result from the environment at the time of deposition, the behavior of the track makers, and the post-depositional conditions. Dinosaur tracks are common in the Lower Cretaceous Glen Rose Formation of central Texas, and were formed in marine environments representing the ancient shoreline of the Gulf of Mexico. While there have been previous studies of these trackways, a detailed study utilizing multiple geologic and geochemical tools will provide greater insight into these unique traces of ancient life. The opportunity to explore a range of preservation styles occurs in Central Texas, specifically at three sites: Startzville, the Blanco River, and the South Fork of the San Gabriel River (west and east).  Many of the sites (especially the site at Startzville) are vulnerable to ongoing climate change and will disappear because of weathering, stream erosion, and urbanization. The goals of this project are to 1) develop digital archives of dinosaur track sites using photogrammetry data, and 2) provide a detailed interpretation of the environments where dinosaurs lived and constrain the conditions that led to the preservation of the tracks using sedimentologic and geochemical data.     At the Startzville locality, tracks are preserved in limestone and are undertracks (wherein the impressions visible today are the result of registration of the track into the layers underlying the original track surface). The tracks at the Blanco River site are also preserved in limestone but correspond to a true track surface. Tracks at the San Gabriel River site are preserved in dolostone. East San Gabriel River site preserves tracks as true track, while the West San Gabriel River site shows undertracks. All locations are interpreted to have been deposited in shoreline to tidal flat to offshore and open marine environments.  The primary aim for this part of the research project was the analysis and interpretation of carbon and oxygen stable isotopes composition of rock samples at these track sites. The Glen Rose Formation has been investigated petrographically and with stable isotopes in the past, and previous work on stable isotopes reveals that potential exposure surfaces (where dinosaur tracks are likely to occur) are characterized by low carbon and oxygen isotope values (Allen and Matthews, 1982), characteristic of lithification under freshwater (groundwater derived from precipitation). The original hypothesis is that the track surfaces would show consistent decreases in carbon and oxygen isotope values compared to strata above and below them. However, this was not the case. Only the Startzville locality shows low values, especially in the remnant traces of what is thought to be the original track surface (Figure 1). While the stable isotope values did not show a consistent pattern of decreased values at the track surface, the elemental geochemistry of the overlying units show a consistent pattern. In all three sites, the track surfaces are overlain by mudrock or clay-rich limestone containing chemical evidence for greater input of silicate material (Al, Si, and Ti) and micronutrients (Ba, Ni, Cu, Fe, P) that are interpreted to have been transported from land. This suggests that burial by silicate sediment input played an important role in the preservation of the tracks, as opposed to just early lithification under the influence of fresh groundwater.  The physical and digital data collected as part of this project by co-PIs preserve the evidence of dinosaur behavior. At each locality, measurements of individual track and trackway parameters indicate that theropod and sauropod dinosaurs responsible for these tracks were between 2.1 and 3.3 and 3.8 to 4.6 m high (at the hip) and were moving at a speed ranging from 4.2 to 17.0 and 2.7 to 3.7 kilometer per hour, respectively. The digital archive of this project will be housed at the Witte Museum in San Antonio, showcasing the unique geological wonders of central Texas to the general public.  Results from this project have been used in the development of educational materials for teaching high school and introductory college field projects on making observations, gathering data on trackways, and using the data to test hypotheses and to draw conclusions on the size, speed and behavior of the dinosaurs and the paleoenvironments represented in the rock record.  This project supported three undergraduate student projects at Trinity University, one undergraduate student project and a Ph.D. project at The University of Texas San Antonio. Students were mentored by a multidisciplinary team of professors and peers from The University of Texas at San Antonio, Trinity University, The University of Kansas, Kansas State University, and the Witte Museum. Activities supported by the project allowed students the opportunity to for networking, peer and traditional mentoring, and ways to learn how to discuss and defend their ideas. In addition, it helped demonstrate the teamwork aspect of science.           Last Modified: 12/02/2022       Submitted by: Marina B Suarez]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
