<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Multi-Step Sequential Processing of Gas Ions for Identifying Volatile Organic Compounds in Recirculated Air of Energy Efficient Buildings]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>255400.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>255400</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Benaiah Schrag</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bschrag@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928323</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is to improve human health, energy savings, and improved environment.  Increased urbanization worldwide and demand for high quality, comfortable ambient air environments is expected to drive an existing market for improved heating, ventilation, and air conditioning (HVAC) systems estimated at $12 billion nationally and $190 billion worldwide by 2026. Respiratory disease and human illness are attributed to unregulated amounts of these constituents in indoor air. This project will inform users about the concentrations and identities of volatile organic compounds (VOCs) in recirculated indoor air from energy-efficient HVAC systems. &lt;br/&gt;This will inform clinical analyses of disease, industrial process monitoring, screening of food purity and authenticity, and commercial aviation security.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This SBIR Phase I project will leverage discoveries in the chemistry of ion fragmentation in strong electric fields in air at ambient pressure and the association of these fragments with molecular identity.  Additional merit is derived from algorithms for identification of ion spectra, dependences of fragmentation on electric field strength, and processes to handle ions both in the initial step of ion selection and the final stage of fragment ion analysis.  This will be a novel exploration of strong electric field fragmentation of gas ions at ambient pressure.  Research objectives include tasks to establish broad understanding of mechanisms of ion fragmentation of volatile organic compounds as gas ions at ambient pressure and establishing autonomous molecular identification using spectral profiles from mobility analysis.  The research is organized into three phases including the development of efficient, advanced control of ion fragmentation, the discovery of chemical rules governing ion fragmentation, and the integration of artificial intelligence with chemical instrumentation developed in this project.  The key technical result anticipated in this project is a chemical analyzer for autonomous monitoring of the quality of recirculated indoor air in green heating, ventilation, and air conditioning systems in green buildings.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/09/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/25/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041, 47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2035894</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
<LastName>Fowler</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Peter E Fowler</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[petererfowler@gmail.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000829676</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/09/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>GP IONICS LLC</Name>
<CityName>LAS CRUCES</CityName>
<ZipCode>880031223</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4062242726</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1175 N HORSESHOE DR.</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[CHEMISTRY RM 34]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Mexico</StateName>
<StateCode>NM</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NM02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>EQ8JN83A1DU5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GP IONICS LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>M8VKNL9J6BD1</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[GP IONICS LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>Las Cruces</CityName>
<StateCode>NM</StateCode>
<ZipCode>880031239</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3655 Research Dr.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Mexico</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NM02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>090E</Code>
<Text>Chem/Bio and Physical Diagnostics</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8035</Code>
<Text>Hardware Devices</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~255400</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Air quality monitoring is a critical concern in today's world, with implications for public health and safety in indoor, outdoor, and industrial settings. When specific chemical identities and concentrations are necessary, current sensor technologies are often limited to expensive, lab-based instruments, limiting their accessibility and practicality in real-world applications. The IonMPRO instrument was developed by GP Ionics for this grant, and fills a technology gap by providing modern, multi-stage chemical identification at a low cost, on-site, and with rapid identification and concentrations of chemicals in the air.</p> <p>Intellectual Merit:</p> <p>The IonMPRO instrument is based on a multi-stage approach to measurement, using tandem differential mobility spectrometers with electric field fragmentation. Developed through academic labs, this technology has significant real-world applications, and was funded by the NSF Phase I SBIR program to advance the understanding and technology from proof of concept to a fieldable prototype. This was accomplished, with several iterations producing the electronics, software, and hardware for a portable, stand-alone instrument suitable for field trials and a first commercial prototype.</p> <p>Additionally, the project has contributed to the scientific understanding of ion fragmentation in air at ambient pressure by completing development and optimization of designs and methods for the IonMPRO. Improved electronics, novel designs, and models of field and chemical dynamics provided valuable insights into the underlying processes of ion fragmentation and chemical identification. The IonMPRO instrument now boasts increased power and capability for fragmenting ions, expanding the range of possible applications for the technology. This includes the analysis of large molecules previously unattainable. The project has also demonstrated and published spectral features in fragment ion spectra that can be utilized by neural networks for automatic chemical identification. This is used by the early-stage IonMPRO software to allow direct identification of spectra by a trained neural network in real time, enabling rapid, automated chemical identification.</p> <p>Broader/Commercial Impacts:</p> <p>The IonMPRO instrument has progressed from a lab breadboard to a self-contained, portable prototype, filling a gap in sensing capabilities. The prototype instrument has already been selected by clients for development in several real-world applications, notably being assessed for use in air quality monitoring at launch sites to detect highly toxic hydrazine compounds. Future applications are sought in indoor air quality monitoring, where it can detect and quantify individually all chemicals of concern specified in ASHRAE Standard 62.2 for control of HVAC systems. Through these applications and others, the IonMPRO can be used for indoor, outdoor, and industrial settings to give knowledge of our environment, ultimately benefiting public health and safety across many fields.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/27/2023<br>      Modified by: Peter&nbsp;E&nbsp;Fowler</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Air quality monitoring is a critical concern in today's world, with implications for public health and safety in indoor, outdoor, and industrial settings. When specific chemical identities and concentrations are necessary, current sensor technologies are often limited to expensive, lab-based instruments, limiting their accessibility and practicality in real-world applications. The IonMPRO instrument was developed by GP Ionics for this grant, and fills a technology gap by providing modern, multi-stage chemical identification at a low cost, on-site, and with rapid identification and concentrations of chemicals in the air.  Intellectual Merit:  The IonMPRO instrument is based on a multi-stage approach to measurement, using tandem differential mobility spectrometers with electric field fragmentation. Developed through academic labs, this technology has significant real-world applications, and was funded by the NSF Phase I SBIR program to advance the understanding and technology from proof of concept to a fieldable prototype. This was accomplished, with several iterations producing the electronics, software, and hardware for a portable, stand-alone instrument suitable for field trials and a first commercial prototype.  Additionally, the project has contributed to the scientific understanding of ion fragmentation in air at ambient pressure by completing development and optimization of designs and methods for the IonMPRO. Improved electronics, novel designs, and models of field and chemical dynamics provided valuable insights into the underlying processes of ion fragmentation and chemical identification. The IonMPRO instrument now boasts increased power and capability for fragmenting ions, expanding the range of possible applications for the technology. This includes the analysis of large molecules previously unattainable. The project has also demonstrated and published spectral features in fragment ion spectra that can be utilized by neural networks for automatic chemical identification. This is used by the early-stage IonMPRO software to allow direct identification of spectra by a trained neural network in real time, enabling rapid, automated chemical identification.  Broader/Commercial Impacts:  The IonMPRO instrument has progressed from a lab breadboard to a self-contained, portable prototype, filling a gap in sensing capabilities. The prototype instrument has already been selected by clients for development in several real-world applications, notably being assessed for use in air quality monitoring at launch sites to detect highly toxic hydrazine compounds. Future applications are sought in indoor air quality monitoring, where it can detect and quantify individually all chemicals of concern specified in ASHRAE Standard 62.2 for control of HVAC systems. Through these applications and others, the IonMPRO can be used for indoor, outdoor, and industrial settings to give knowledge of our environment, ultimately benefiting public health and safety across many fields.       Last Modified: 04/27/2023       Submitted by: Peter E Fowler]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
