<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Soil and water biogeochemical response to COVID-19: increased stress on septic systems alters soil and water quality]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>99993.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>99993</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Douglas Kowalewski</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dkowalew@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922181</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Early in 2020 northeast Georgia had much higher rainfall than normal placing increased stress on aging septic systems in the region. Additionally, “shelter-in-place” and “social distancing” policies related to the COVID-19 pandemic have increased the time residents spend at home and therefore the use of residential septic wastewater treatment systems. This increased stress on septic systems may change soil properties and pollutant content in septic leach fields. This project will investigate how increased septic system use could lead to pollutant runoff.  Septic systems will be investigated inside and outside of the leach field perimeter and the soil physical, hydrologic, and chemical properties analyzed in the field and with laboratory methods.  The results from this study will inform land managers and local governments on pollutants that need to be managed to protect human health, natural resources, and the environment.  Educational materials will be prepared and distributed at the annual Athens Water Festival.  One graduate student will be directly involved in the project and will be trained in a wide selection of field and laboratory techniques.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The object of this project is to investigate the current period of intensive rainfall and septic system use and how it may generate novel hotspots of biogeochemical activity in both soil and soil water. The core hypothesis is that enhanced nutrient loading in septic leach fields during this period of increased septic stress (COVID-19 and weather related) will drive shifts in quantity and composition of organic matter in soil and soil water, along with shifts in overall biogeochemical cycling. This research project will address three objectives: 1. Estimate the impact of leach fields on soil and soil water biogeochemistry using a comparative approach.  2. Identify potential hotspots of change in nutrients and soil organic matter with enough spatial and temporal resolution to generate larger-scale hotspot predictions. 3. Estimate potential nutrient and organic matter loading being delivered to water bodies from related stress in septic system functioning and to septic system maintenance. By investigating the impacts of extreme weather events and increased septic system demand, this work will provide critical insights to shifts in soil water and related aquatic nutrient loading. Understanding these shifts will provide local governments information related to long-term use of septic systems, and management challenges related to future climate regimes. The PIs anticipate working with local agencies and outreach specialists to develop new septic educational material to be distributed at the annual Athens Water Festival, taking advantage of an on-going collaboration with Clarke County.  The PI is a new researcher, and one graduate student will be directly involved in the project and will be trained in a wide selection of field and laboratory techniques.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/06/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/06/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2035534</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nandita</FirstName>
<LastName>Gaur</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nandita Gaur</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[nandita.gaur@uga.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000826322</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/06/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Krista</FirstName>
<LastName>Capps</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Krista Capps</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[kcapps@uga.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000631624</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/06/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jacob</FirstName>
<LastName>Bateman McDonald</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jacob M Bateman McDonald</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jacob.mcdonald@ung.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000630118</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/06/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rebecca</FirstName>
<LastName>Abney</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Rebecca B Abney</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[Rebecca.Abney@uga.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000786651</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/06/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lori</FirstName>
<LastName>Sutter</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lori A Sutter</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[sutterl@uncw.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000743806</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/06/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Georgia Research Foundation Inc</Name>
<CityName>ATHENS</CityName>
<ZipCode>306021589</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7065425939</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>310 E CAMPUS RD RM 409</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NMJHD63STRC5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF GEORGIA RESEARCH FOUNDATION, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Georgia]]></Name>
<CityName>Athens</CityName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>306025025</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[180 E Green St]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7222</Code>
<Text>XC-Crosscutting Activities Pro</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7295</Code>
<Text>Geobiology &amp; Low-Temp Geochem</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~99993</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>RAPID: Soil and water biogeochemical response to COVID-19: increased stress on septic systems alters soil and water quality</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>In the United States, over 20% of residences utilize a septic, or decentralized, system to treat wastewater<a title=", 2014 #14" href="applewebdata://265126C1-1510-47CC-963A-52C717317A64#_ENREF_1"><sup>1</sup></a>. Previous research has indicated that septic systems can contribute to shifts in nutrient loading and soil functioning in leach field soils and connected aquatic systems<a title="Gilliom, 1983 #15" href="applewebdata://265126C1-1510-47CC-963A-52C717317A64#_ENREF_2"><sup>2-5</sup></a>. This represents a significant mechanism by which anthropogenic activity alters soil biogeochemical and microbial processes, but one that is not considered in global biogeochemical models used to understand ecosystem functioning.</p> <p>We hypothesized that&nbsp;increasing stress on septic systems due to ongoing extreme weather and increased use (from increased teleworking due to COVID-19 pandemic restrictions) would drive shifts in&nbsp;soil properties due to the influx of nutrients and water in the leach field area of residential septic systems. To address this hypothesis, we conducted a study at 21 residences in Athens, GA that currently use septic wastewater treatment systems. We measured soil chemical and physical properties, and nutrient content of septic outflow in pairs inside and outside the septic leach fields at these residences, to compare the difference between them. We found slightly higher nutrient loading inside of leach fields for nitrate, nitrite, and phosphate, but that these were much higher in leach fields from newer built houses (2008 onwards) compared with residences constructed before 2008. The concentrations of nutrient loading from the leach fields varied seasonally, but we found no decrease in nutrient loading with lifting of stay-at-home orders during the COVID-19 pandemic. Interestingly, the concentrations of nutrients varied over four orders of magnitude between different residences. This may be due to the residence time of waste within septic tanks, differences in their efficacy in treating wastewater, and variability in management of residences.</p> <p>We found no significant differences in soil properties when comparing inside and outside of the septic leach fields ? including pH, texture, and measures of compaction (completed via bulk density and penetrometer readings). These results were surprising, because we expected to find a higher impact of the septic effluent on overall soil properties. There was a considerable amount of variability in our data, which reflects the diversity of management strategies in different residences (e.g., use of fertilizer, pesticides, irrigation, type of ground cover, septic system management and stress, etc.).</p> <p>We conducted a survey of tree health at sites with trees inside the leach field and found that bottomland adapted species (e.g. Tulip poplar and White Oak) were not negatively impacted by leach field soil conditions. In this survey, we noted that there were few upland hardwood or pine species in the leach fields, which suggests that they may not have been able to survive the different soil water conditions. It is also important to note that planting trees within septic leach fields is not recommended, and the recommendation for the state of Georgia is to keep tree plantings within 50 feet of a leach field, due to the potential for roots to block or damage drain field structures and functioning.</p> <p>In summary, we found very variable soil and effluent properties between different residences, but there were few significant differences when directly comparing inside and outside of septic leach fields. The biggest differences in nutrient loading were in newer developments, which had higher nutrient concentration in effluent water. This may reflect some settling of leach field drain lines or different styles of drain line installation. Overall, we found that differences in individual residential management strategies lead to considerable variability in soil and septic effluent properties.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>References</p> <p class="EndNoteBibliography">1.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<em>Decentrailzed wastewater management program annual report 2013</em>; Environmental Protection Agency: 2014.</p> <p class="EndNoteBibliography">2.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Gilliom, R. J.; Patmont, C. R., Lake phosphorus loading from septic systems by seasonally perched groundwater.&nbsp;<em>Journal (Water Pollution Control Federation)&nbsp;</em><strong>1983</strong>, 1297-1305.</p> <p class="EndNoteBibliography">3.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Badruzzaman, M.;&nbsp;&nbsp;Pinzon, J.;&nbsp;&nbsp;Oppenheimer, J.; Jacangelo, J. G., Sources of nutrients impacting surface waters in Florida: a review.&nbsp;<em>Journal of Environmental Management&nbsp;</em><strong>2012,</strong>&nbsp;<em>109</em>, 80-92.</p> <p class="EndNoteBibliography">4.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Iverson, G.;&nbsp;&nbsp;Humphrey Jr, C.;&nbsp;&nbsp;O'Driscoll, M.;&nbsp;&nbsp;Sanderford, C.;&nbsp;&nbsp;Jernigan, J.; Serozi, B., Nutrient exports from watersheds with varying septic system densities in the North Carolina Piedmont.&nbsp;<em>Journal of Environmental Management&nbsp;</em><strong>2018,</strong>&nbsp;<em>211</em>, 206-217.</p> <p class="EndNoteBibliography">5.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Mechtensimer, S.; Toor, G. S., Fate, mass balance, and transport of phosphorus in the septic system drainfields.&nbsp;<em>Chemosphere&nbsp;</em><strong>2016,</strong>&nbsp;<em>159</em>, 153-158.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/28/2022<br>      Modified by: Rebecca&nbsp;B&nbsp;Abney</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ RAPID: Soil and water biogeochemical response to COVID-19: increased stress on septic systems alters soil and water quality     In the United States, over 20% of residences utilize a septic, or decentralized, system to treat wastewater1. Previous research has indicated that septic systems can contribute to shifts in nutrient loading and soil functioning in leach field soils and connected aquatic systems2-5. This represents a significant mechanism by which anthropogenic activity alters soil biogeochemical and microbial processes, but one that is not considered in global biogeochemical models used to understand ecosystem functioning.  We hypothesized that increasing stress on septic systems due to ongoing extreme weather and increased use (from increased teleworking due to COVID-19 pandemic restrictions) would drive shifts in soil properties due to the influx of nutrients and water in the leach field area of residential septic systems. To address this hypothesis, we conducted a study at 21 residences in Athens, GA that currently use septic wastewater treatment systems. We measured soil chemical and physical properties, and nutrient content of septic outflow in pairs inside and outside the septic leach fields at these residences, to compare the difference between them. We found slightly higher nutrient loading inside of leach fields for nitrate, nitrite, and phosphate, but that these were much higher in leach fields from newer built houses (2008 onwards) compared with residences constructed before 2008. The concentrations of nutrient loading from the leach fields varied seasonally, but we found no decrease in nutrient loading with lifting of stay-at-home orders during the COVID-19 pandemic. Interestingly, the concentrations of nutrients varied over four orders of magnitude between different residences. This may be due to the residence time of waste within septic tanks, differences in their efficacy in treating wastewater, and variability in management of residences.  We found no significant differences in soil properties when comparing inside and outside of the septic leach fields ? including pH, texture, and measures of compaction (completed via bulk density and penetrometer readings). These results were surprising, because we expected to find a higher impact of the septic effluent on overall soil properties. There was a considerable amount of variability in our data, which reflects the diversity of management strategies in different residences (e.g., use of fertilizer, pesticides, irrigation, type of ground cover, septic system management and stress, etc.).  We conducted a survey of tree health at sites with trees inside the leach field and found that bottomland adapted species (e.g. Tulip poplar and White Oak) were not negatively impacted by leach field soil conditions. In this survey, we noted that there were few upland hardwood or pine species in the leach fields, which suggests that they may not have been able to survive the different soil water conditions. It is also important to note that planting trees within septic leach fields is not recommended, and the recommendation for the state of Georgia is to keep tree plantings within 50 feet of a leach field, due to the potential for roots to block or damage drain field structures and functioning.  In summary, we found very variable soil and effluent properties between different residences, but there were few significant differences when directly comparing inside and outside of septic leach fields. The biggest differences in nutrient loading were in newer developments, which had higher nutrient concentration in effluent water. This may reflect some settling of leach field drain lines or different styles of drain line installation. Overall, we found that differences in individual residential management strategies lead to considerable variability in soil and septic effluent properties.     References 1.         Decentrailzed wastewater management program annual report 2013; Environmental Protection Agency: 2014. 2.         Gilliom, R. J.; Patmont, C. R., Lake phosphorus loading from septic systems by seasonally perched groundwater. Journal (Water Pollution Control Federation) 1983, 1297-1305. 3.         Badruzzaman, M.;  Pinzon, J.;  Oppenheimer, J.; Jacangelo, J. G., Sources of nutrients impacting surface waters in Florida: a review. Journal of Environmental Management 2012, 109, 80-92. 4.         Iverson, G.;  Humphrey Jr, C.;  O'Driscoll, M.;  Sanderford, C.;  Jernigan, J.; Serozi, B., Nutrient exports from watersheds with varying septic system densities in the North Carolina Piedmont. Journal of Environmental Management 2018, 211, 206-217. 5.         Mechtensimer, S.; Toor, G. S., Fate, mass balance, and transport of phosphorus in the septic system drainfields. Chemosphere 2016, 159, 153-158.          Last Modified: 07/28/2022       Submitted by: Rebecca B Abney]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
