<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Studies of Atmospheric Processes Using Imaging Science Techniques]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>500000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>500000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06020200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AGS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Roman Makarevich</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rmakarev@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927207</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Aeronomy is a field robustly interdisciplinary and fundamentally dependent upon multi-diagnostic observations and advanced computer modeling capabilities. This proposal describes networks of existing all-sky-imagers (ASIs) and the contributions they can make to some of the outstanding problems in Space Physics. The term “Imaging Science” is used to describe the avenues of exploration enabled by actual two-dimensional images of emission, as well as the visualization aspects of data analysis, and the pictoral portrayal of modeling results. The infra-structure required for a team science effort is led by an experienced team of PI and senior staff for instrument operations, observations, data transfer, data management and rapid availability to multiple research communities. The effort is conducted in conjunction with research colleagues and students eager to use new observations to further their studies of Ionosphere-Thermosphere-Mesosphere (ITM) physics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/22/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/20/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2035267</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Mendillo</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael Mendillo</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mendillo@bu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000109286</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/22/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Trustees of Boston University</Name>
<CityName>BOSTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>022151703</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6173534365</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1 SILBER WAY</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>THL6A6JLE1S7</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF BOSTON UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Trustees of Boston University]]></Name>
<CityName>Boston</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>022151400</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[881 Commonwealth Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1521</Code>
<Text>AERONOMY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~500000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This grant from the National Science Foundation supported investigations of the physical processes that link solar activity to our near-Earth space environment. In the Earth&rsquo;s upper atmosphere (heights above about 60 miles), the ultraviolet light from the Sun has sufficient energy to separate electrons from atoms and molecules.&nbsp; This results in an electrically-charged gas of oxygen ions (O+ and O2+) and electrons (e-) that is called the ionosphere (and more generally, a plasma).&nbsp; The plasma state is, in fact, the most abundant state of matter in the universe.&nbsp; Thus studies of the Earth&rsquo;s ionosphere are both of practical importance (because they govern radio wave propagation, e.g., for GPS navigation), as well as fundamental science of our physical place in the universe.&nbsp;&nbsp;<br />With support from this grant, Boston University operates a global network of 12 optical observatories with instruments that observe the ionosphere using wide-angle (all-sky) fields of view.&nbsp; These instruments capture ionospheric structure and dynamics in three latitude zones:&nbsp; sub-auroral, mid-latitude, and equatorial domains in two longitude regions (north/south America) and Europe/Africa.&nbsp; The locations of these instruments are at so-called conjugate points---places where the Earth&rsquo;s magnetic field extends from one site (e.g., Asiago, Italy) to the other (Sutherland, South Africa).&nbsp; This Boston University observing network is a unique capability world-wide and our investigations are at the forefront of &ldquo;conjugate point science&rdquo; in the near-Earth environment. Results of our research appear regularly in major refereed journals and in presentations at professional meetings ranging from highly-focused workshops to major&nbsp; international meetings.<br />In addition to the science-focused results, our research is a form of Big-Data science with a data archive that has millions of images spanning several solar cycle cycles.&nbsp; These data are made available to professional scientists and the general public (&ldquo;Citizen Science&rdquo;) via a website updated daily (buimaging.com). Our grant also fosters education and training ranging from professional staff on state-of-the-art data management, to student training in optical observing methods.&nbsp;&nbsp;<br />It is with pleasure that we acknowledge that this grant from the NSF as the key source of support of one of the major research groups in the US and, indeed, world-wide space science.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/05/2023<br>      Modified by: Michael&nbsp;Mendillo</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This grant from the National Science Foundation supported investigations of the physical processes that link solar activity to our near-Earth space environment. In the Earth’s upper atmosphere (heights above about 60 miles), the ultraviolet light from the Sun has sufficient energy to separate electrons from atoms and molecules.  This results in an electrically-charged gas of oxygen ions (O+ and O2+) and electrons (e-) that is called the ionosphere (and more generally, a plasma).  The plasma state is, in fact, the most abundant state of matter in the universe.  Thus studies of the Earth’s ionosphere are both of practical importance (because they govern radio wave propagation, e.g., for GPS navigation), as well as fundamental science of our physical place in the universe.   With support from this grant, Boston University operates a global network of 12 optical observatories with instruments that observe the ionosphere using wide-angle (all-sky) fields of view.  These instruments capture ionospheric structure and dynamics in three latitude zones:  sub-auroral, mid-latitude, and equatorial domains in two longitude regions (north/south America) and Europe/Africa.  The locations of these instruments are at so-called conjugate points---places where the Earth’s magnetic field extends from one site (e.g., Asiago, Italy) to the other (Sutherland, South Africa).  This Boston University observing network is a unique capability world-wide and our investigations are at the forefront of "conjugate point science" in the near-Earth environment. Results of our research appear regularly in major refereed journals and in presentations at professional meetings ranging from highly-focused workshops to major  international meetings. In addition to the science-focused results, our research is a form of Big-Data science with a data archive that has millions of images spanning several solar cycle cycles.  These data are made available to professional scientists and the general public ("Citizen Science") via a website updated daily (buimaging.com). Our grant also fosters education and training ranging from professional staff on state-of-the-art data management, to student training in optical observing methods.   It is with pleasure that we acknowledge that this grant from the NSF as the key source of support of one of the major research groups in the US and, indeed, world-wide space science.       Last Modified: 05/05/2023       Submitted by: Michael Mendillo]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
