<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID/Collaborative Research: Digitizing Early Cretaceous dinosaur trackways to preserve the geological heritage of central Texas]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>111417.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>111417</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Dena Smith</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dmsmith@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927431</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Dinosaur tracks and trackways provide invaluable information about ancient lifeforms and are of great interest to the general public. Yet, increasing urbanization jeopardizes their preservation. This is especially true in central Texas where the metropolitan population grows by 1.7% yearly, and puts dinosaur tracksites exposed in rural areas and creeks at risk. Other sources of destruction include transient flood and weathering enhanced by climate change. This proposal will preserve three important sites in a digital format using advanced imagery techniques and will include analysis of collected rock samples to provide information about the landscape where these dinosaurs lived. New data will be integrated into the Witte Museum in San Antonio, Texas, where it can be used for scientific research and to educate the general public on preservation best practice and the ecology of life in central Texas about 110 million years ago. This project will engage researchers from four institutions with a strong track record on the topic and they will mentor non-traditional graduate and undergraduate students to solidify their interest in the geosciences and retain them in the major. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will inform on the depositional environment and the conditions that promoted the preservation of trace fossils. The digitization of each site using photogrammetric techniques will be complemented by detailed analysis of rock samples using microscopy and geochemistry. Results will evaluate whether dinosaur tracks are preferentially preserved in shallow marine sediments deposited during periods of sea-level fall, when their frequent subaerial exposure under a hot and dry climate favored their early lithification and preservation. Alternatively, preservation may be enhanced by rapid burial with clay-rich sediment in a hot and humid environment. Geochemical and petrographic data also will be used to test these hypotheses. The integration of all results in a database available to researchers and the general public will showcase the cultural heritage of Texas and serve as a basis for future research.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/29/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/29/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2035529</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alexis</FirstName>
<LastName>Godet</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alexis Godet</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[alexis.godet@utsa.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000653526</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/29/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
<LastName>Adams</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Thomas L Adams</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[tladams40@gmail.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000798556</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/29/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Texas at San Antonio</Name>
<CityName>SAN ANTONIO</CityName>
<ZipCode>782491644</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2104584340</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1 UTSA CIRCLE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>U44ZMVYU52U6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT SAN ANTONIO, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>X5NKD2NFF2V3</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[The University of Texas at San Antonio]]></Name>
<CityName>San Antonio</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>782491644</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[One UTSA Circle]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7222</Code>
<Text>XC-Crosscutting Activities Pro</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7459</Code>
<Text>Sedimentary Geo &amp; Paleobiology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~111417</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Dinosaur tracks are common in the Lower Cretaceous Glen Rose Formation of central Texas.&nbsp; The Glen Rose Formation was deposited in marine environments representing the ancient shoreline of the Gulf of Mexico. The track sites record the environments that existed as dinosaurs walked along the shoreline. Many sites are important for the documentation and interpretation of dinosaur behavior. However, previous investigations of these track sites lacked detailed studies of their ancient environments. Furthermore, many of the sites are vulnerable to ongoing climate change and will disappear because of weathering, stream erosion, and urbanization. The goals of this project are to 1) develop digital archives of dinosaur track sites using photogrammetry data, and 2) provide a detailed interpretation of the environments where dinosaurs lived and constrain the conditions that led to the preservation of the tracks using sedimentologic and geochemical data.</p> <p>Our research focused on three sites: the Startzville site, the Blanco River site, and the South Fork of the San Gabriel River site (west and east). &nbsp;In all sites the sedimentary rocks record fluctuations in sea level with shifts from a very shallow shoreline and tidalflat environments to offshore, open marine environments. In the Starzville and the Blanco River sites the track surface is in a limestone containing sedimentary structures, while tracks are preserved in a dolostone at San Gabriel River. These lithologies indicate very shallow marine to tidal flat environments. At Startzville carbon and oxygen isotope ratios in the track surface point to chemical alteration of the sediment during exposure to the atmosphere and rainfall, while isotope data from the two other sites suggest alteration in a marine environment. In all three sites, the track surfaces are overlain by mudrock or clay-rich limestone containing chemical evidence for greater input of silicate material (aluminum, silica, and titanium) and micronutrients (barium, nickel, copper, iron, phosphorus) that are interpreted to have been transported from land into the shoreline by river or wind. These observations indicate that burial by silicate sediment input from land played an important role in the preservation of the tracks. The chemical index of alteration (CIA*), reported &nbsp;as the percent ratio of aluminum to the sum of aluminum, sodium and potassium, is interpreted to reflect intensity of weathering of continental landmasses.&nbsp; The CIA* values for all sites are consistent with a high intensity of chemical weathering indicating a generally hot and humid climate.</p> <p class="Pa4">The track surfaces at the Startzville and the west San Gabriel River localities are undertracks where the impressions preserved today are the result of registration of the track deformation into sediments underlying the actual track surface. The actual track surface was stripped away by erosion. At the Blanco River and the east San Gabriel River sites the presence of pressure rims indicate the preservation of the original track surfaces. The identification of true track layers permits to explore processes that affected the sediments directly after dinosaurs left their footprints, and inform on the ecology of dinosaurs. At each locality, measurements of individual track and trackway parameters indicate that theropod and sauropod dinosaurs responsible for these tracks measured between 2.1 and 3.3 and 3.8 to 4.6 m high (at the hip), and were moving at a speed ranging from 4.2 to 17.0 and 2.7 to 3.7 kilometer per hour, respectively.</p> <p>This project has produced a digital data archive that will be housed at the Witte Museum in San Antonio, showcasing the unique geological wonders of central Texas to the general public.&nbsp; Results from this project have been used in the development of educational materials for teaching high school and introductory college field projects on making observations, gathering data on trackways, and using the data to test hypotheses and to draw conclusions on the size, speed and behavior of the dinosaurs and the paleoenvironments represented in the rock record.&nbsp; New standards for ichnological field-based data collection and digital management practices have been adopted and implemented as a result of these studies. This project supported three undergraduate student projects at Trinity University, one undergraduate student project and a Ph.D. project at The University of Texas San Antonio. Students were mentored by a multidisciplinary team of professors and peers from The University of Texas at San Antonio, Trinity University, The University of Kansas, Kansas State University, and the Witte Museum.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/17/2022<br>      Modified by: Alexis&nbsp;Godet</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Dinosaur tracks are common in the Lower Cretaceous Glen Rose Formation of central Texas.  The Glen Rose Formation was deposited in marine environments representing the ancient shoreline of the Gulf of Mexico. The track sites record the environments that existed as dinosaurs walked along the shoreline. Many sites are important for the documentation and interpretation of dinosaur behavior. However, previous investigations of these track sites lacked detailed studies of their ancient environments. Furthermore, many of the sites are vulnerable to ongoing climate change and will disappear because of weathering, stream erosion, and urbanization. The goals of this project are to 1) develop digital archives of dinosaur track sites using photogrammetry data, and 2) provide a detailed interpretation of the environments where dinosaurs lived and constrain the conditions that led to the preservation of the tracks using sedimentologic and geochemical data.  Our research focused on three sites: the Startzville site, the Blanco River site, and the South Fork of the San Gabriel River site (west and east).  In all sites the sedimentary rocks record fluctuations in sea level with shifts from a very shallow shoreline and tidalflat environments to offshore, open marine environments. In the Starzville and the Blanco River sites the track surface is in a limestone containing sedimentary structures, while tracks are preserved in a dolostone at San Gabriel River. These lithologies indicate very shallow marine to tidal flat environments. At Startzville carbon and oxygen isotope ratios in the track surface point to chemical alteration of the sediment during exposure to the atmosphere and rainfall, while isotope data from the two other sites suggest alteration in a marine environment. In all three sites, the track surfaces are overlain by mudrock or clay-rich limestone containing chemical evidence for greater input of silicate material (aluminum, silica, and titanium) and micronutrients (barium, nickel, copper, iron, phosphorus) that are interpreted to have been transported from land into the shoreline by river or wind. These observations indicate that burial by silicate sediment input from land played an important role in the preservation of the tracks. The chemical index of alteration (CIA*), reported  as the percent ratio of aluminum to the sum of aluminum, sodium and potassium, is interpreted to reflect intensity of weathering of continental landmasses.  The CIA* values for all sites are consistent with a high intensity of chemical weathering indicating a generally hot and humid climate. The track surfaces at the Startzville and the west San Gabriel River localities are undertracks where the impressions preserved today are the result of registration of the track deformation into sediments underlying the actual track surface. The actual track surface was stripped away by erosion. At the Blanco River and the east San Gabriel River sites the presence of pressure rims indicate the preservation of the original track surfaces. The identification of true track layers permits to explore processes that affected the sediments directly after dinosaurs left their footprints, and inform on the ecology of dinosaurs. At each locality, measurements of individual track and trackway parameters indicate that theropod and sauropod dinosaurs responsible for these tracks measured between 2.1 and 3.3 and 3.8 to 4.6 m high (at the hip), and were moving at a speed ranging from 4.2 to 17.0 and 2.7 to 3.7 kilometer per hour, respectively.  This project has produced a digital data archive that will be housed at the Witte Museum in San Antonio, showcasing the unique geological wonders of central Texas to the general public.  Results from this project have been used in the development of educational materials for teaching high school and introductory college field projects on making observations, gathering data on trackways, and using the data to test hypotheses and to draw conclusions on the size, speed and behavior of the dinosaurs and the paleoenvironments represented in the rock record.  New standards for ichnological field-based data collection and digital management practices have been adopted and implemented as a result of these studies. This project supported three undergraduate student projects at Trinity University, one undergraduate student project and a Ph.D. project at The University of Texas San Antonio. Students were mentored by a multidisciplinary team of professors and peers from The University of Texas at San Antonio, Trinity University, The University of Kansas, Kansas State University, and the Witte Museum.          Last Modified: 11/17/2022       Submitted by: Alexis Godet]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
