<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Upgrade of an Infrared Spectrometer (with Electronics Replacement) for Quantitative Analysis, Focusing on H-species and Concentrations at Temperatures]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>69593.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>69593</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>David Lambert</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dlambert@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924736</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This award is funded in whole or in part under the American Rescue Plan Act of 2021 (Public Law 117-2).  It will provide funds to upgrade a Fourier Transform Infrared spectrometer (DA3-FTIR). The instrument covers a wide range of light wavelengths and has accessories for high and low temperatures as well as high pressure which makes the instrument useful in addressing an extensive range of problems. Examples of the breadth of supported research are collaborative studies in medicine (bone growth) and ongoing studies in astronomy (identifying dust ejected from old stars).  However, the primary focus of the instrument has been on problems important to the geological, planetary and materials science. The upgraded instrument will add to the infrastructure and will help advance fundamental issues while providing opportunities for education and training. The instrument has been used by students at all levels plus students of other faculty at Washington U. and at U. Missouri. The laboratory plans to continue probing the fundamental principles that govern the interaction of heat with matter, and to apply these findings to the Earth and beyond.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The existing Fourier Transform Infrared spectrometer (DA3-FTIR) in this laboratory has been used in diverse and numerous research projects since its funding by NSF three decades ago. The DA3-FTIR is a high-end research instrument, with 5 pairs of detectors and beam-splitters that altogether cover the far-IR to the visible.  Accessories include a liquid helium cryostat, heaters, and diamond anvil cells to acquire spectra from ~10 to 700 K or at pressure to 50 GPa. Two IR-microscopes are used for very small samples. This instrument is no longer maintained by its manufacturer. The problems are largely electronic. Due to its popularity and robust mechanical components, a small company has filled the market need by offering an upgrade, electronics replacement, and support for this instrument. The upgraded instrument will add to the infrastructure and will help advance fundamental issues in the geological and planetary sciences. Ongoing and planned projects use this instrument and are important to geophysics, volcanology, petrology, and planetary science. Acquiring quantitative spectra vs frequency and T will permit extrapolating to unattainable conditions and will improve understanding of the thermal state and evolution of planets.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/29/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/29/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2035778</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Anne</FirstName>
<LastName>Hofmeister</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Anne M Hofmeister</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[hofmeist@levee.wustl.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000285030</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/29/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Washington University</Name>
<CityName>SAINT LOUIS</CityName>
<ZipCode>63110</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3147474134</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>ONE BROOKINGS DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MO01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>L6NFUM28LQM5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WASHINGTON UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Washington University]]></Name>
<CityName>Saint Louis</CityName>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>631304899</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MO01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7222</Code>
<Text>XC-Crosscutting Activities Pro</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1580</Code>
<Text>INSTRUMENTATION &amp; FACILITIES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>1V21</Code>
<Name>R&amp;RA ARP Act DEFC V</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>010V2122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[R&RA ARP Act DEFC V]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~69593</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Overview.</strong> The existing Fourier Transform Infrared spectrometer (DA3-FTIR) in the Washington University mineral physics laboratory has been used in diverse and numerous research projects since its funding by NSF 3 decades ago, as exemplified by data in over 85 journal publications, 2 books, and 4 review papers.&nbsp; Spectral data were essential to all postdoctoral, graduate, and undergraduate projects. One recent focus has been to ascertain speciation and concentrations of hydroxyl and water impurities in glasses and melts, and their influence on heat and mass transport properties. Another focus has been obtaining spectra for models of diffusive heat transport. The DA3 instrument is no longer maintained by its manufacturer. The problems are largely electronic. Due to its popularity and robust mechanical components, a small company has filled the market need by offering an upgrade, electronics replacement, software, and support for this instrument. This proposal seeks funds for upgrading, replacing electronics, and repairing a pump.</p> <p><strong>Why upgrade?</strong> The DA3-FTIR is a high-end research instrument that can explore a wide range of light wavelengths, with many accessories. Replacement would require substantial additional funds to reconfigure accessories (the cryostat, heaters and pressure cells) for a different bench. &nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Intellectual benefits.</strong> Ongoing and planned projects use this instrument and are important to geophysics, volcanology, petrology, and planetary science. Examples are: (1) We have shown that hydrous impurities, which can only be quantified with IR spectra, affect heat transport.&nbsp; Funding was recently requested to explore how thermal expansivity is affected. Importantly, modest temperatures convert liquid H<sub>2</sub>O to gas or supercritical fluid, which expands 1000 times more rapidly that do silicate melts. Thus, high gravitational buoyancy of steam outpaces H<sub>2</sub>O diffusion in a melt and should promote planetary differentiation. (2) Examining diverse glasses after heating, and comparing these spectra to previous results, indicates that well-used spectral calibrations of H<sub>2</sub>O and OH for glass or melt may be more uncertain than recognized, so these need revisiting (more spectra are needed). (3) We have shown that heat is conducted at low and high temperatures by diffusion of infrared light inside a material. Acquiring quantitative spectra will permit extrapolating to unattainable conditions and will improve understanding of the thermal state and evolution of planets.</p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts.</strong> The upgraded instrument will add to the infrastructure and will help advance fundamental issues in the geological and planetary sciences. The instrument has been used by students at all levels, not just at Washington university, but also at U. Missouri. The DA3-FTIR was used for collaborative medical and astronomical studies. Our publications centering on spectral data are well cited by workers in several physical sciences, and thus serve diverse purposes. Currently the spectrometer is being used to help a female astronomer restart her career after a long maternity break. Data gathered during the upgrade was submitted and published in 2022. The IR spectrometer has been essential to all endeavors of the Principle Investigator, and has assisted diverse other researchers meet their goals.</p> <p><strong>Outcomes. </strong>The upgrade is now finished, so the above existing projects can be completed, and new projects undertaken.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/04/2023<br>      Modified by: Anne&nbsp;M&nbsp;Hofmeister</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Overview. The existing Fourier Transform Infrared spectrometer (DA3-FTIR) in the Washington University mineral physics laboratory has been used in diverse and numerous research projects since its funding by NSF 3 decades ago, as exemplified by data in over 85 journal publications, 2 books, and 4 review papers.  Spectral data were essential to all postdoctoral, graduate, and undergraduate projects. One recent focus has been to ascertain speciation and concentrations of hydroxyl and water impurities in glasses and melts, and their influence on heat and mass transport properties. Another focus has been obtaining spectra for models of diffusive heat transport. The DA3 instrument is no longer maintained by its manufacturer. The problems are largely electronic. Due to its popularity and robust mechanical components, a small company has filled the market need by offering an upgrade, electronics replacement, software, and support for this instrument. This proposal seeks funds for upgrading, replacing electronics, and repairing a pump.  Why upgrade? The DA3-FTIR is a high-end research instrument that can explore a wide range of light wavelengths, with many accessories. Replacement would require substantial additional funds to reconfigure accessories (the cryostat, heaters and pressure cells) for a different bench.    Intellectual benefits. Ongoing and planned projects use this instrument and are important to geophysics, volcanology, petrology, and planetary science. Examples are: (1) We have shown that hydrous impurities, which can only be quantified with IR spectra, affect heat transport.  Funding was recently requested to explore how thermal expansivity is affected. Importantly, modest temperatures convert liquid H2O to gas or supercritical fluid, which expands 1000 times more rapidly that do silicate melts. Thus, high gravitational buoyancy of steam outpaces H2O diffusion in a melt and should promote planetary differentiation. (2) Examining diverse glasses after heating, and comparing these spectra to previous results, indicates that well-used spectral calibrations of H2O and OH for glass or melt may be more uncertain than recognized, so these need revisiting (more spectra are needed). (3) We have shown that heat is conducted at low and high temperatures by diffusion of infrared light inside a material. Acquiring quantitative spectra will permit extrapolating to unattainable conditions and will improve understanding of the thermal state and evolution of planets.  Broader Impacts. The upgraded instrument will add to the infrastructure and will help advance fundamental issues in the geological and planetary sciences. The instrument has been used by students at all levels, not just at Washington university, but also at U. Missouri. The DA3-FTIR was used for collaborative medical and astronomical studies. Our publications centering on spectral data are well cited by workers in several physical sciences, and thus serve diverse purposes. Currently the spectrometer is being used to help a female astronomer restart her career after a long maternity break. Data gathered during the upgrade was submitted and published in 2022. The IR spectrometer has been essential to all endeavors of the Principle Investigator, and has assisted diverse other researchers meet their goals.  Outcomes. The upgrade is now finished, so the above existing projects can be completed, and new projects undertaken.       Last Modified: 03/04/2023       Submitted by: Anne M Hofmeister]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
