<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[NSF CONVERGENCE ACCELERATOR: Improving Online Education Through Technology, Research, And Data]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>99220.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>99220</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01060500</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OIA</Abbreviation>
<LongName>OIA-Office of Integrative Activities</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Mike Pozmantier</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mpozmant@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924475</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The COVID-19 pandemic has exponentially accelerated the growth of online educational technology. Digital platforms are seeing a 10 fold increase in users. Still, many current educational technologies have weak approaches to instruction, and they do not leverage basic research on learning, have a culture of continuous improvement, meet the needs of diverse learners, or leverage the growing power of &lt;br/&gt;computers. This conference will provide ideas for deliverables around potential use-cases and prototypes as well as lay the groundwork for future collaborations across a variety of disciplines to research, develop, and refine effective and equitable remote educational technologies.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will bring together experts in industry and fields such as education, cognitive science, and technology to identify barriers and solutions to delivering high-quality online education. These collaborations will inform best practices in educational technology design and generate future development and testing. Topics such leveraging AI/ML or new modes of platform design will be key components of the discussions that take place at this conference, along with a look at what types deliverables can be derived from applying these new approaches to online learning.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/25/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/14/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.083</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2035359</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Scott</FirstName>
<LastName>Crossley</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Scott Crossley</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[scrossley@gsu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000624271</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/25/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kathryn</FirstName>
<LastName>McCarthy</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kathryn S McCarthy</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[kmccarthy12@gsu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000828066</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/25/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Georgia State University Research Foundation, Inc.</Name>
<CityName>ATLANTA</CityName>
<ZipCode>303032921</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4044133570</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>58 EDGEWOOD AVE NE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[FL 3]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>MNS7B9CVKDN7</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GEORGIA STATE UNIVERSITY RESEARCH FOUNDATION INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Georgia State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>303032924</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[25 Park Place NE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>066Y</Code>
<Text>Program Planning and Policy De</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~99220</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The increased reliance on online education and educational technologies more generally has laid bare the need to more deeply consider how researchers, designers, and educators can improve the quality of technology-mediated learning. To address this need, more than two dozen experts from a variety of fields came together to discuss the challenges that educational technology must address in the immediate future. These experts were tasked with identifying barriers to and potential solutions for delivering high-quality and equitable online and remote education.&nbsp;</p> <p>The experts acknowledged that the popularity of online learning has grown as policy-makers, researchers, and instructors adapt instruction in response to COVID-19. While the practice of online learning is not new, the convergence of recent developments in educational technologies, the science of learning, AI, and NLP can provide critical contributions to online learning. These collaborations can also promote high quality online instruction in varied contexts and to diverse learners who differ across a wide array of dimensions, such as skills, knowledge, and motivation.</p> <p>True convergence must consider the full ecosystem of those who develop, use, and are affected by educational technology. This means that educational technology needs to be reimagined to include teachers, students, and families as co-designers and partners, rather than merely passive consumers. In order for educational technologies to fully meet their potential, teams of researchers, designers, developers, computer scientists, and educators from a variety of backgrounds and experiences must engage in long-term collaboration and iterative design. Having multiple viewpoints, goals, and expertise can support the development of technologies that can evaluate and assess learners and other end-users across a variety of dimensions and outcomes in order to provide personalized instruction and feedback that keeps students excited, engaged, and optimally learning.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/01/2021<br>      Modified by: Scott&nbsp;Crossley</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The increased reliance on online education and educational technologies more generally has laid bare the need to more deeply consider how researchers, designers, and educators can improve the quality of technology-mediated learning. To address this need, more than two dozen experts from a variety of fields came together to discuss the challenges that educational technology must address in the immediate future. These experts were tasked with identifying barriers to and potential solutions for delivering high-quality and equitable online and remote education.   The experts acknowledged that the popularity of online learning has grown as policy-makers, researchers, and instructors adapt instruction in response to COVID-19. While the practice of online learning is not new, the convergence of recent developments in educational technologies, the science of learning, AI, and NLP can provide critical contributions to online learning. These collaborations can also promote high quality online instruction in varied contexts and to diverse learners who differ across a wide array of dimensions, such as skills, knowledge, and motivation.  True convergence must consider the full ecosystem of those who develop, use, and are affected by educational technology. This means that educational technology needs to be reimagined to include teachers, students, and families as co-designers and partners, rather than merely passive consumers. In order for educational technologies to fully meet their potential, teams of researchers, designers, developers, computer scientists, and educators from a variety of backgrounds and experiences must engage in long-term collaboration and iterative design. Having multiple viewpoints, goals, and expertise can support the development of technologies that can evaluate and assess learners and other end-users across a variety of dimensions and outcomes in order to provide personalized instruction and feedback that keeps students excited, engaged, and optimally learning.          Last Modified: 09/01/2021       Submitted by: Scott Crossley]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
