<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[EAGER: Stable and efficient perovskite solar cells]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>125829.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>125829</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ECCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Leon Shterengas</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Non-technical:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The key challenge in reducing the cost of solar power lies in increasing the conversion efficiency of solar panels. Tandem solar cells are made from sub-cells that respond to different wavelengths of light and could double the efficiency of solar panels. Their deployment, however, has been limited by high fabrication costs. Perovskite solar cells hold promise for use in low-cost tandem solar cells due to ease of processing and chemical tuning of their absorption. Most perovskite solar cells are made from hybrid organic-inorganic materials which decompose at temperatures above 100°C and degrade in the presence of moisture. The aim of this project is to develop a perovskite device that is thermally stable to 300℃, and is relatively insensitive to moisture. The cell will be an all-inorganic structure, thereby potentially improving its stability against photo-induced degradation. The new device is likely to be useful for making tandem junction cells with silicon acting as the bottom cell in a tandem junction arrangement. The technology is likely to increase the efficiency of solar energy conversion and reduce its overall cost. The project will offer a significant opportunity for research to both graduate and undergraduate students, including those from underrepresented groups in STEM.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will develop photovoltaic devices based on a new inorganic perovskite—a bromide based inorganic perovskite alloy, Cs(Pb,Sn)Br3. Bandgap engineering will enable the fabrication of an optimized tandem structure. The bandgap of the CsPbBr3 can be reduced from 2.3 eV to 1.9 eV by incorporating tin, with further reductions possible by mixing cesium and rubidium. Inorganic heterojunction layers will be used to fabricate the devices. The material will be deposited using vacuum deposition processes which are easily scalable. Detailed structural and electronic characterization of the material and the device will be undertaken to understand the photovoltaic performance of the device. The devices will be tested for their stability against moisture and heat and against photoinduced degradation.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/14/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/26/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2035240</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rana</FirstName>
<LastName>Biswas</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Rana Biswas</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[biswasr@iastate.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000160857</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/26/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Vikram</FirstName>
<LastName>Dalal</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Vikram L Dalal</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[vdalal@iastate.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000202814</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/14/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate>08/26/2021</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Iowa State University</Name>
<CityName>AMES</CityName>
<ZipCode>500112103</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5152945225</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1350 BEARDSHEAR HALL</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[515 MORRILL ROAD]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Iowa</StateName>
<StateCode>IA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>DQDBM7FGJPC5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>IOWA STATE UNIVERSITY OF SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Iowa State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Ames</CityName>
<StateCode>IA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>500112207</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Pearson Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Iowa</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT/>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IA"</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1517</Code>
<Text>EPMD-ElectrnPhoton&amp;MagnDevices</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>094E</Code>
<Text>Optoelectronic devices</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>146E</Code>
<Text>Solar energy</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1775</Code>
<Text>ELECTRONIC/PHOTONIC MATERIALS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~125829</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The project has developed environmentally friendly highly stable perovskite solar cells based on&nbsp;CsPbBr<sub>3</sub>&nbsp;absorber materials.</p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Intellectual Merit:</span> We developed an all-bromine inorganic perovskite solar cell, with an absorber layer of the composition CsPBBr<sub>3</sub>, with high voltage, excellent device characteristics that shows stability to high temperatures, moisture, and typical outdoor conditions.</p> <p>Our studies have established that light induced degradation in conventional solar cells with organic based absorber layers is caused by blue and ultra-violet photons in the solar spectrum. This problem is averted by using CsPbBr<sub>3 </sub>based perovskite solar cells.<sub> </sub></p> <p>The perovskite material CsPbBr<sub>3</sub> has a wide band gap material of 2.3 eV. Yet most of the n-i-p solar cells fabricated with the prototypical structure Glass/FTO/ c-TiO2/ CsPbBr<sub>3</sub> /P3HT have poor open circuit voltage Voc~1.4 eV, indicating a 1eV voltage loss in the device. The voltage loss arises from electronic band misalignments and poor interfaces between the intrinsic perovskite layer and the n and p-heterojunctions. We improved the band alignments and the interfaces between the perovskite absorber i-layer and the p and n-transport layers.</p> <p>In our FTO/compact-TiO2/CsPbBr<sub>3</sub>/ PbBr<sub>2</sub> /P3HT/Au solar cell we deposited a PbBr<sub>2</sub> cap layer between the absorber layer and the P3HT. &nbsp;We have achieved highest device performance with n-i-p bromine-based perovskite solar cells with PbBr2 interfacial layers providing power conversion efficiencies of 7.9%, Voc=1.64 eV, Jsc=6.7 mA/cm2, and FF=71%.</p> <p>Virtually no degradation of the cell efficiency and the I-V characteristic was observed after 500 hours of light exposure. Heating the solar cells for 200 C for 12 hours in the atmosphere, showed no degradation of the PCE or the I-V characteristics, indicating excellent thermal stability.&nbsp; By using carbon paste as the hole-transport layer (HTL) we obtained solar cells that were stable in air and reached PCE of over 8%.</p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Broad Impact: </span>The project trained four graduate students completing (2) PhD and (1) MS degrees in cutting edge research, that enabled them to contribute to the technical microelectronics workforce. The graduated PhD students have acquired positions in the microelectronics industry, and are applying the technical skills acquired in this project to the microelectronics industry. Research results from this project have been incorporated into a ECpE graduate course at Iowa State U taught by the PI.&nbsp; Invited talks including research results from this project, have been presented by the PI to broad non-technical audiences at the Central Iowa IEEE chapter, and to high school alumni associations. Three technical papers have been published including one paper in a high impact journal. Two presentations have been made at leading national photovoltaic conferences to experts in this area.&nbsp; &nbsp;Stable perovskite solar cells have great commercial potential in providing clean renewable energy in many parts of the world, and are an alternative to presently available commercial silicon solar cells.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/17/2023<br>      Modified by: Rana&nbsp;Biswas</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The project has developed environmentally friendly highly stable perovskite solar cells based on CsPbBr3 absorber materials.  Intellectual Merit: We developed an all-bromine inorganic perovskite solar cell, with an absorber layer of the composition CsPBBr3, with high voltage, excellent device characteristics that shows stability to high temperatures, moisture, and typical outdoor conditions.  Our studies have established that light induced degradation in conventional solar cells with organic based absorber layers is caused by blue and ultra-violet photons in the solar spectrum. This problem is averted by using CsPbBr3 based perovskite solar cells.   The perovskite material CsPbBr3 has a wide band gap material of 2.3 eV. Yet most of the n-i-p solar cells fabricated with the prototypical structure Glass/FTO/ c-TiO2/ CsPbBr3 /P3HT have poor open circuit voltage Voc~1.4 eV, indicating a 1eV voltage loss in the device. The voltage loss arises from electronic band misalignments and poor interfaces between the intrinsic perovskite layer and the n and p-heterojunctions. We improved the band alignments and the interfaces between the perovskite absorber i-layer and the p and n-transport layers.  In our FTO/compact-TiO2/CsPbBr3/ PbBr2 /P3HT/Au solar cell we deposited a PbBr2 cap layer between the absorber layer and the P3HT.  We have achieved highest device performance with n-i-p bromine-based perovskite solar cells with PbBr2 interfacial layers providing power conversion efficiencies of 7.9%, Voc=1.64 eV, Jsc=6.7 mA/cm2, and FF=71%.  Virtually no degradation of the cell efficiency and the I-V characteristic was observed after 500 hours of light exposure. Heating the solar cells for 200 C for 12 hours in the atmosphere, showed no degradation of the PCE or the I-V characteristics, indicating excellent thermal stability.  By using carbon paste as the hole-transport layer (HTL) we obtained solar cells that were stable in air and reached PCE of over 8%.  Broad Impact: The project trained four graduate students completing (2) PhD and (1) MS degrees in cutting edge research, that enabled them to contribute to the technical microelectronics workforce. The graduated PhD students have acquired positions in the microelectronics industry, and are applying the technical skills acquired in this project to the microelectronics industry. Research results from this project have been incorporated into a ECpE graduate course at Iowa State U taught by the PI.  Invited talks including research results from this project, have been presented by the PI to broad non-technical audiences at the Central Iowa IEEE chapter, and to high school alumni associations. Three technical papers have been published including one paper in a high impact journal. Two presentations have been made at leading national photovoltaic conferences to experts in this area.   Stable perovskite solar cells have great commercial potential in providing clean renewable energy in many parts of the world, and are an alternative to presently available commercial silicon solar cells.                 Last Modified: 05/17/2023       Submitted by: Rana Biswas]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
