<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[NSF Convergence Accelerator: Socioresilient Infrastructure: Precision Materials, Assemblages, and Systems]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>97067.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>97067</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01060500</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OIA</Abbreviation>
<LongName>OIA-Office of Integrative Activities</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Linda Molnar</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lmolnar@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928316</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This project will develop and convene a cross-sector and cross-disciplinary workshop focused on “Socioresilient Infrastructure: Precision Materials, Assemblages, and Systems.”  Infrastructure is foundational to supporting a healthy, inclusive, sustainable, and prosperous nation and society. There is an urgent need for modernization, innovation, maintenance, repair, and replacement of infrastructure, and, in addition, the development of infrastructure which supports the ability of human communities to cope with and adapt to stresses and shocks such as social, political, environmental, or economic change. Currently, there is an acute amplification of new risks and vulnerabilities, and an opportunity to consider infrastructure as a research and design process grounded in equity to shift infrastructure from an extractive (resources and labor) to regenerative (sustainable and equitable) modality. This workshop will involve cross-sector engagement and will bring together leaders from academia, industry (i.e. established and startup companies in the materials, infrastructure, and construction industry, materials and infrastructure-focused venture capital firms), non-profit community-based organizations, philanthropy, and government entities (e.g. municipalities, smart cities initiatives, etc.). The merging of ideas, new computational and manufacturing technologies, research methods, across disparate disciplines will not only lead to innovation and commercialization, but advances in the development of equitable, inclusive, and sustainable innovation and commercialization of socioresilient infrastructure. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This workshop aims to advance a technical framework for the acceleration of use-inspired convergence research in this area of national importance by integrating exciting advances across length scales from materials (materials science and engineering, chemistry, and mechanical engineering) to assemblages (civil, structural, and environmental engineering, architecture, art and design) to systems (engineering systems, computer science and engineering, urban studies and planning including civic design and engagement). Broad technical topic areas will include emerging approaches to socioresilient materials design, structural engineering, and intelligent infrastructure systems. It will also incorporate cross-cutting humanistic and socially-focused research in material culture, social justice, community-based design at the margins, environmental and social life cycle assessment, sociotechnical and sociological analysis (history, social sciences, including science, technology, and society studies). This workshop will advance transformative convergent, inclusive, and cross-disciplinary research and education focused on socioresilient infrastructure.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/12/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/12/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.083</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2035215</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Christine</FirstName>
<LastName>Ortiz</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Christine Ortiz</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[cortiz@mit.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000180177</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/12/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Massachusetts Institute of Technology</Name>
<CityName>CAMBRIDGE</CityName>
<ZipCode>021394301</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6172531000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>77 MASSACHUSETTS AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>E2NYLCDML6V1</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MASSACHUSETTS INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>E2NYLCDML6V1</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Massachusetts Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021394301</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[77 Massachusetts Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>066Y</Code>
<Text>Program Planning and Policy De</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~97067</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-9ef3d0e2-7fff-6542-86dd-a9b041f2f11a"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr">The intellectual merit of this project included the reimagination, reconception, and redesign of infrastructure, the fundamentally entangled physical, digital, and social frameworks and systems that underpin society, hold enormous potential for addressing urgent environmental challenges, global health disparities, economic and social divides.&nbsp; This project developed the concept of socioresilient infrastructure (Ortiz and Spero, 2020) which addresses this imperative by envisioning a future where infrastructure is intentionally designed to empower human communities to cope with, and adapt to stresses and shocks such as social, political, environmental, or economic change. While there is increasing attention to sustainability and environmental issues, the critical integration of emerging infrastructure technologies with humanistic fields, including history, social sciences, including science, technology, and society studies, social justice, diversity, equity, and inclusion, remains fragmented and a significant challenge. A framework was advanced for the acceleration of use-inspired convergence research in this area of national importance that integrates exciting advances across length scales from materials (materials science and engineering, chemistry, and mechanical engineering) to assemblages (civil, structural, and environmental engineering, architecture, art and design) to systems (engineering systems, computer science and engineering, urban studies and planning including civic design and engagement) with cross-cutting research in material culture, social justice, community and equity-based design, environmental and social life cycle assessment, environmental justice, sociotechnical and sociological analysis (history, social sciences, including science, technology, and society studies). This project demonstrated that the merging of ideas, new computational and manufacturing technologies, research methods, across widely disparate disciplines holds great potential for the development of equitable, inclusive, and sustainable research breakthroughs, innovation, and commercialization of socioresilient infrastructure. The broader impacts of this project and continued advancement of the project aims include; the codification of project results into publications for scholarly audiences, contributions to pedagogy and curriculum, influence on emergent research, and the creation of new collaborations between project participants and their organizations which were catalyzed by interaction at the workshop.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <div><span><br /></span></div> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/23/2022<br>      Modified by: Christine&nbsp;Ortiz</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   The intellectual merit of this project included the reimagination, reconception, and redesign of infrastructure, the fundamentally entangled physical, digital, and social frameworks and systems that underpin society, hold enormous potential for addressing urgent environmental challenges, global health disparities, economic and social divides.  This project developed the concept of socioresilient infrastructure (Ortiz and Spero, 2020) which addresses this imperative by envisioning a future where infrastructure is intentionally designed to empower human communities to cope with, and adapt to stresses and shocks such as social, political, environmental, or economic change. While there is increasing attention to sustainability and environmental issues, the critical integration of emerging infrastructure technologies with humanistic fields, including history, social sciences, including science, technology, and society studies, social justice, diversity, equity, and inclusion, remains fragmented and a significant challenge. A framework was advanced for the acceleration of use-inspired convergence research in this area of national importance that integrates exciting advances across length scales from materials (materials science and engineering, chemistry, and mechanical engineering) to assemblages (civil, structural, and environmental engineering, architecture, art and design) to systems (engineering systems, computer science and engineering, urban studies and planning including civic design and engagement) with cross-cutting research in material culture, social justice, community and equity-based design, environmental and social life cycle assessment, environmental justice, sociotechnical and sociological analysis (history, social sciences, including science, technology, and society studies). This project demonstrated that the merging of ideas, new computational and manufacturing technologies, research methods, across widely disparate disciplines holds great potential for the development of equitable, inclusive, and sustainable research breakthroughs, innovation, and commercialization of socioresilient infrastructure. The broader impacts of this project and continued advancement of the project aims include; the codification of project results into publications for scholarly audiences, contributions to pedagogy and curriculum, influence on emergent research, and the creation of new collaborations between project participants and their organizations which were catalyzed by interaction at the workshop.                 Last Modified: 02/23/2022       Submitted by: Christine Ortiz]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
