<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase II:  Intelligent modular vertical farming system]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>999056.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1499004</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Cooperative Agreement</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rajesh Mehta</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rmehta@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922174</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase II project is to improve vertical farms. The global threat to food security and the need to deal with unpredictable climate conditions have opened the doors to advanced precision agriculture and vertical urban farming. Rapidly growing global populations, demand for higher agricultural yields with limited arable farmland drive demand for vertical farming and new technologies to expand access to this method of sustainable crop cultivation. The proposed system will reduce the burden on the environment by decreasing water, fertilizers and pesticides required to grow crops. These micro-farms will boost agricultural profitability by providing a reliable, sustainable food system with fresh, healthy, and eco-friendly produce. This reduces food waste and the environmental impact of the food supply chain while improving yields and nutritional density.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This SBIR Phase II project advances a system with integrated environmental control, consumables management, alerting, and scheduling. Furthermore, the automated controls are continuously improved by using camera vision to estimate yield and machine learning to forecast yield and optimize the environmental variables. To make the system cost-effective, a novel multispectral camera will be developed to collect agricultural data. Using machine learning, the images collected will be correlated to the environmental variables, such as pH and nutrient concentration, so that those variables can be optimized to increase yields. In order to improve scheduling and logistics, the platform will track inputs such as seeds, nutrients, and pH solution, using sensors and QR codes to automate consumable replacement.  Sensors and software checks will determine when component or human failure have occurred, before they lead to crop failure, leading to just-in-time component replacement and maintenance.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/21/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/20/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>CoopAgrmnt</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041, 47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2035792</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Graham</FirstName>
<LastName>Smith</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Graham Smith</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[babylonmicrofarms_grants@outlook.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000783411</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/21/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>BABYLON MICRO-FARMS INC.</Name>
<CityName>RICHMOND</CityName>
<ZipCode>232304301</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5712303923</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3409 CARLTON ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>VA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>Y5JMA8JF8DR5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>BABYLON MICRO-FARMS INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[BABYLON MICRO-FARMS INC.]]></Name>
<CityName>Charlottesville</CityName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>229034584</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[700 Harris Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>VA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5373</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase II</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1238</Code>
<Text>TECH FOR SUSTAINABLE ENVIRONMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>165E</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase IIB</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8028</Code>
<Text>Sensor Technology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002324DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~999056</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2023~499948</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><div class="WordSection1"> <p>The primary objective of Babylon&rsquo;s NSF Phase II SBIR work was to develop and commercialize a remote management platform for onsite hydroponic farms. Because of climate and supply chain disruption, produce will increasingly need to be grown closer to the consumer, and indoors in hoop houses, green houses, and vertical farms. Onsite farming, where produce is grown at the point of consumption, can be part of the solution to those stated problems, but has received a fraction of the investment as the other areas. While it has numerous additional benefits including reduced food waste and increased nutrition due to requiring no transport, improved biodiversity, and engagement of the end consumer, it brings many additional challenges. Farming onsite must be so simple that anyone without a green thumb can do so with little time investment, which Babylon endeavored to solve through user-friendly hardware and a remote management platform.</p> <p>Babylon&rsquo;s NSF research has resulted in successfully launching the Galleri, the world&rsquo;s easiest to use onsite farm, which hundreds of people like chefs and facilities workers are operating using less than an hour a week. To enable this, Babylon has developed several technologies that allow the hardware to automate the growth cycle of dozens of crop varieties. A mobile app was developed that streamlines operator interactions with their farm, dashboards and alerting allow Babylon to understand exactly how the hardware and operator are performing to fix problems before they arise, and a computer vision and machine learning platform was built using novel cameras to automatically detect plant health to tweak and improve the growing environment over time. The result is a scalable platform that will support multiple and lower cost hardware configurations with tens of thousands of users.</p> </div> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/21/2023<br>      Modified by: Graham&nbsp;Smith</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  The primary objective of Babylon’s NSF Phase II SBIR work was to develop and commercialize a remote management platform for onsite hydroponic farms. Because of climate and supply chain disruption, produce will increasingly need to be grown closer to the consumer, and indoors in hoop houses, green houses, and vertical farms. Onsite farming, where produce is grown at the point of consumption, can be part of the solution to those stated problems, but has received a fraction of the investment as the other areas. While it has numerous additional benefits including reduced food waste and increased nutrition due to requiring no transport, improved biodiversity, and engagement of the end consumer, it brings many additional challenges. Farming onsite must be so simple that anyone without a green thumb can do so with little time investment, which Babylon endeavored to solve through user-friendly hardware and a remote management platform.  Babylon’s NSF research has resulted in successfully launching the Galleri, the world’s easiest to use onsite farm, which hundreds of people like chefs and facilities workers are operating using less than an hour a week. To enable this, Babylon has developed several technologies that allow the hardware to automate the growth cycle of dozens of crop varieties. A mobile app was developed that streamlines operator interactions with their farm, dashboards and alerting allow Babylon to understand exactly how the hardware and operator are performing to fix problems before they arise, and a computer vision and machine learning platform was built using novel cameras to automatically detect plant health to tweak and improve the growing environment over time. The result is a scalable platform that will support multiple and lower cost hardware configurations with tens of thousands of users.              Last Modified: 08/21/2023       Submitted by: Graham Smith]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
