<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[NSF Convergence Accelerator: Symposium on Predicting Extremes by Data-Driven Analytics]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>99998.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>99998</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01060500</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OIA</Abbreviation>
<LongName>OIA-Office of Integrative Activities</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Chaitanya Baru</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cbaru@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924596</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The NSF Convergence Accelerator supports use-inspired, team-based, multidisciplinary efforts that address challenges of national importance and will produce deliverables of value to society in the near future. This symposium on Predicting Extremes by Data-Driven Analytics will help identify topic areas for new tracks in the NSF Convergence Accelerator. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Extreme events and associated hazards in natural, commercial, and security systems underlie the most devastating catastrophes in society. The societal risks arising from extreme events are very high both in terms of likelihood and impact on society. The increasing impact of disasters and the consequent risks have led leading organizations and institutions around the world to develop new approaches to mitigate the impacts and develop strategies for resilience. Improved predictive capability for extreme events is a critical scientific need in order to achieve effective disaster risk assessment, which is a product of three factors: the probability of the underlying events, vulnerability of the system and consequences therein. The understanding and modeling of extreme events contributes towards developing the probabilities of occurrence. This symposium will bring together participants from academia, government and industry to develop data-driven analytics as a pathway for predicting extreme events in natural and anthropogenic systems, including applications in terrestrial and space weather, finance and economics, and cybersecurity. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The symposium is planned as a 3-day event to be run as a virtual meeting. It will emphasize participation by researchers and students from underrepresented communities that may be especially vulnerable to the effects of extreme events.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;An essential step toward achieving better predictability is uncertainty quantification, which is an inherently interdisciplinary endeavor, requiring convergence across multiple disciplines and participation by multiple stakeholders across academia, industry and government. A Convergence Accelerator track on this theme would benefit multiple sectors. Developing a framework for predicting extremes requires the harnessing of massive data from a variety of sources. The symposium will discuss the idea of developing a common platform for stakeholders in government, industry and nonprofits as part of this potential new track in the Convergence Accelerator. The themes of the symposium are of general interest due to their potential for high impact on society. A symposium proceedings will be produced, which will provide broad exposure to the potential outcomes of convergence research in this topic area.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/27/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/14/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.083</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2035365</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>A Surjalal</FirstName>
<LastName>Sharma</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>A Surjalal Sharma</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ssh@umd.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000175045</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/27/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Maryland, College Park</Name>
<CityName>College Park</CityName>
<ZipCode>207420001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3014056269</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3112 LEE BLDG 7809 REGENTS DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MD04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NPU8ULVAAS23</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MARYLAND, COLLEGE PARK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>KMGEN62NKEM9</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Maryland College Park]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>207423370</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MD04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>066y</Code>
<Text>Program Planning and Policy De</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~99998</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Extreme events and natural hazards cause increasing devastation worldwide and there is an urgent need for enhancing the predictive capability and for developing a comprehensive system for their prediction. Improved capability for extreme events prediction is a critical scientific need for effective disaster risk assessment and resilience. In disaster risk estimation the likelihood of the underlaying events are usually derived from the understanding of the extreme events based on the first-principles of the specific phenomena. However, because of the complicated set of processes interacting across disparate scales in space and time, reliable redictions of extremes based on the disciplinary approaches are continuing challenges. The data-driven modeling in the complex systems framework is based on extracting the leading features inherent in the data, independent of modeling assumptions, and provide a direct approach for prediction of extreme events. The key components of the Prediction of Extremes by Data analytics (PrExDa) are its foundation based on dynamical systems theory and complexity science, availability and accessibility of extensive data, and methodologies and techniques for extreme event modeling and prediction. The data-driven analytics, with its system-based approach, provides a natural framework for harnessing the unprecedented and massive data of multiple systems to yield improved predictive capability for extreme events. Further, the complex systems approach provides a transdisciplinary framework for integrating the theories, models and data across disciplines for convergence research of extreme events. The project bridges the scientific advances to the societal need for enhancing predictive capability for extreme events in a comprehensive system. A critical task for accelerating convergence in this framework is a closer collaboration with the stakeholders and user communities to develop clear pathways for an effective prediction system for increasing resilience to extreme events and for developing mitigation strategies.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/28/2022<br>      Modified by: A. Surjalal&nbsp;Sharma</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2035365/2035365_10702770_1672266017429_PrExDAIntegrativeFrameworkProjectOutcomes--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2035365/2035365_10702770_1672266017429_PrExDAIntegrativeFrameworkProjectOutcomes--rgov-800width.jpg" title="PrExDa - Predicting Extreme Events by Data Analytics in the Complex Systems Framework"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2035365/2035365_10702770_1672266017429_PrExDAIntegrativeFrameworkProjectOutcomes--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="PrExDa - Predicting Extreme Events by Data Analytics in the Complex Systems Framework"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The framework for prediction of extremes events in an integrative platform is built on the advances in data-driven modeling in thecomplex systems framework. Extensive data from multiple sources are used to model dynamical behavior, make predictions and quantify predictability.</div> <div class="imageCredit">A Surjalal Sharma</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">A. Surjalal&nbsp;Sharma</div> <div class="imageTitle">PrExDa - Predicting Extreme Events by Data Analytics in the Complex Systems Framework</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2035365/2035365_10702770_1672267032428_PrexdaComponents--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2035365/2035365_10702770_1672267032428_PrexdaComponents--rgov-800width.jpg" title="PrExDa Components"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2035365/2035365_10702770_1672267032428_PrexdaComponents--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="PrExDa Components"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">PrExDa optimizes the integration of the three components: 1) Harnessing of the data of the phenomena, 2) Complex SystemsFramework for Modeling, prediction and quantifying Predictability, and3) Extreme event Characterization.</div> <div class="imageCredit">A Surjalal Sharma</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">A. Surjalal&nbsp;Sharma</div> <div class="imageTitle">PrExDa Components</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Extreme events and natural hazards cause increasing devastation worldwide and there is an urgent need for enhancing the predictive capability and for developing a comprehensive system for their prediction. Improved capability for extreme events prediction is a critical scientific need for effective disaster risk assessment and resilience. In disaster risk estimation the likelihood of the underlaying events are usually derived from the understanding of the extreme events based on the first-principles of the specific phenomena. However, because of the complicated set of processes interacting across disparate scales in space and time, reliable redictions of extremes based on the disciplinary approaches are continuing challenges. The data-driven modeling in the complex systems framework is based on extracting the leading features inherent in the data, independent of modeling assumptions, and provide a direct approach for prediction of extreme events. The key components of the Prediction of Extremes by Data analytics (PrExDa) are its foundation based on dynamical systems theory and complexity science, availability and accessibility of extensive data, and methodologies and techniques for extreme event modeling and prediction. The data-driven analytics, with its system-based approach, provides a natural framework for harnessing the unprecedented and massive data of multiple systems to yield improved predictive capability for extreme events. Further, the complex systems approach provides a transdisciplinary framework for integrating the theories, models and data across disciplines for convergence research of extreme events. The project bridges the scientific advances to the societal need for enhancing predictive capability for extreme events in a comprehensive system. A critical task for accelerating convergence in this framework is a closer collaboration with the stakeholders and user communities to develop clear pathways for an effective prediction system for increasing resilience to extreme events and for developing mitigation strategies.          Last Modified: 12/28/2022       Submitted by: A. Surjalal Sharma]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
