<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Automated DOAC assay to determine coagulation status in emergent care]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>256000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>256000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Henry Ahn</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>hahn@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927069</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial impact potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase 1 project is a diagnostic product that addresses patient safety and clinical decision-making for physicians managing patients taking Direct Oral Anticoagulants (DOACs). DOACs are becoming the preferred drugs to reduce the risk of blood clots that can lead to significant adverse events, such as stroke. However, DOACs are part of the leading class of drugs implicated in adverse event-related emergency department visits. These adverse events place a significant burden on the healthcare system in the form of transfusions, exposure to blood products, platelet repletion, reversal therapies, and additional complications (e.g. infection, sepsis, multiple organ failure) driving longer hospitalizations, higher mortality rates, and escalating healthcare costs. In emergency situations, the rapid detection of DOAC anticoagulation is needed when planning for urgent care for surgery, serious trauma, drug overdose, emergency procedures, or monitoring for drug accumulation in cases of renal and liver failure.  This project proposes a diagnostic at the point of care. With an estimated 21 M patients globally taking DOACs, this technology could significantly reduce the $2.5 B in costs related to treating and correcting adverse events caused by the absence of DOAC information in emergency care situations.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I Project will demonstrate the feasibility of a point-of-care (POC) diagnostic chip for emergency room clinicians to manage bleeding risk and avoid overuse of drug reversal therapies, thereby improving patient outcomes while reducing healthcare costs. Currently there is no approved rapid diagnostic POC test that accurately identifies the type of DOAC drug a patient is using, nor how much of the drug is in the patient’s blood. An integrated microfluidic cartridge is proposed developed to manage blood distribution within the device, mix the blood with DOAC detection reagents, and provide an integrated assay result that evaluates the three important clotting factors in clot formation (fibrin/thrombin/platelets). The technology is unique in that, unlike other coagulation tests, it re-creates the blood clotting physiology, and characteristic blood flow, that happens within the body. With DOAC-reversing drugs, the diagnostic can determine DOAC type (Factor Xa or Factor IIa), and the level of DOAC in the blood, allowing emergency room physicians to make more informed care decisions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/24/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/04/2023</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041, 47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2035983</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
<LastName>Kunkel</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mark Kunkel</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ma-consulting@comcast.net]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000729804</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Megan</FirstName>
<LastName>Farrell</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Megan Farrell</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mfarrell@flobiollc.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000828106</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/24/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate>12/10/2020</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>FLOBIO LLC</Name>
<CityName>PHILADELPHIA</CityName>
<ZipCode>191462701</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6105054392</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3401 GRAYS FERRY AVE BLDG 176-10</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>YPEYKCYZB837</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>FLOBIO LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[FLOBIO LLC]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>191462701</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5345</Code>
<Text>BIOMEDICAL ENGINEERING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~256000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This Phase I NSF SBIR project focused on the feasibility of a rapid diagnostic device for detecting the presence of direct oral anticoagulants (DOAC) in whole blood. The project was meant to demonstrate the feasibility of a continuous flow based method of determining DOAC drug presence, and effects, on coagulation and platelet function. The purpose of the project was to evaluate potential microfluidic technology for creating a novel diagnostic assay for use in emergency medicine, to rapidly evaluate coagulation dysfunction as a result of patient DOAC use. The assay was evaluated to determine if coagulation dysfunction could be detected in as little as 10 minutes.</p> <p>DOAC drugs represent a major complication of bleeding emergencies in emergency care. To date no existing technology can comprehensively determine DOAC drug class, or estimated drug levels, as well as platelet and coagulation function, rapidly, in one test. This delays care decisions that can be critical to preventing further injury, or death, from bleeding complications. The continuous flow device under study was unique to evaluating bleeding risk from DOACs, in real time, in a format consistent with developing a rapid point of care diagnostic.</p> <p>The outcome of this work was a device that could analyze whole human blood in less than 15 minutes for both platelet and coagulation function, under continuous blood flow. The device was able to demonstrate the proportionate distribution of labeling reagents into the blood, control the rate of blood flow over a coagulation site within the device, and allow for the direct fluorescent measurement of clotting within the device. The rate of development of a clot within the device was indicative of the relative concentration of DOAC drug present within the device. The device also showed for the first time, that key platelet and coagulation functions within human blood could react within seconds to the addition of DOAC reversal drugs. This was accomplished by a non-destructive, in-line, continuous flow mixing process developed within the device that did not disrupt or significantly modify blood clotting function. This process may be useful in future iterations of the device to modify blood behavior, to re-calcify citrated blood, or to create other blood tests where rapid mixing of reagent with blood is needed.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/24/2023<br>      Modified by: Mark&nbsp;Kunkel</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This Phase I NSF SBIR project focused on the feasibility of a rapid diagnostic device for detecting the presence of direct oral anticoagulants (DOAC) in whole blood. The project was meant to demonstrate the feasibility of a continuous flow based method of determining DOAC drug presence, and effects, on coagulation and platelet function. The purpose of the project was to evaluate potential microfluidic technology for creating a novel diagnostic assay for use in emergency medicine, to rapidly evaluate coagulation dysfunction as a result of patient DOAC use. The assay was evaluated to determine if coagulation dysfunction could be detected in as little as 10 minutes.  DOAC drugs represent a major complication of bleeding emergencies in emergency care. To date no existing technology can comprehensively determine DOAC drug class, or estimated drug levels, as well as platelet and coagulation function, rapidly, in one test. This delays care decisions that can be critical to preventing further injury, or death, from bleeding complications. The continuous flow device under study was unique to evaluating bleeding risk from DOACs, in real time, in a format consistent with developing a rapid point of care diagnostic.  The outcome of this work was a device that could analyze whole human blood in less than 15 minutes for both platelet and coagulation function, under continuous blood flow. The device was able to demonstrate the proportionate distribution of labeling reagents into the blood, control the rate of blood flow over a coagulation site within the device, and allow for the direct fluorescent measurement of clotting within the device. The rate of development of a clot within the device was indicative of the relative concentration of DOAC drug present within the device. The device also showed for the first time, that key platelet and coagulation functions within human blood could react within seconds to the addition of DOAC reversal drugs. This was accomplished by a non-destructive, in-line, continuous flow mixing process developed within the device that did not disrupt or significantly modify blood clotting function. This process may be useful in future iterations of the device to modify blood behavior, to re-calcify citrated blood, or to create other blood tests where rapid mixing of reagent with blood is needed.          Last Modified: 04/24/2023       Submitted by: Mark Kunkel]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
