<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase II:  A novel 3D bioprinting system for rapid high-throughput tissue fabrication]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>997692.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>997692</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Cooperative Agreement</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ela Mirowski</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>emirowsk@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922936</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase II project is to provide a high-throughput biofabrication platform that can create physiologically relevant in vitro tissue models for diverse applications including drug testing, assay development, therapeutics, and biomedical research. The current drug development process is lengthy, inefficient, and expensive. It costs about $1.8 billion and takes 12-15 years to launch a single drug. Approximately 92% of the drugs that passed preclinical testing failed in subsequent human trials, highlighting the lack of adequate preclinical testing tools to generate predictive data. Failure to detect the drug-induced toxicity to the vital human organs in clinical trials often leads to market withdrawal of the drug after launch, which causes enormous financial losses to the drug manufacturer and also negative physical and mental effects for patients. The proposed technology will significantly improve drug safety, increase the efficiency and lower the cost of drug development by providing more reliable and clinically relevant drug testing results in a high-throughput fashion. This technology can also provide patient-specific tissues for critical biomedical research (e.g. disease modeling) and in vivo therapeutic applications, providing a viable solution to diseases without no cures or effective treatment yet.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase II project will support the development of a high-throughput biofabrication platform that is compatible with the high-throughput screening (HTS) systems widely used for drug screening and assay development. Currently, the key bottleneck for traditional microfabrication strategies and mainstream nozzle-based bioprinters is the lack of scalability and throughput to accommodate scalable manufacturing necessary in HTS systems. With the growing adoption of 3D biomimetic human tissue models in the pharmaceutical industry, there is a critical need for advanced manufacturing systems that enable rapid and streamlined tissue fabrication methods that are compatible with already established HTS platforms for preclinical toxicity testing of potential drug candidates. The proposed project will develop a parallel optical projection-based 3D bioprinting platform for direct manufacturing of 3D tissues within multiwell plates commonly used in the HTS systems. Implementation of the proposed 3D bioprinting system will permit subsequent in situ drug screening or assay testing directly within the wells and drastically improve biofabrication workflow efficiencies for the pharmaceutical industry and biomedical research community. This bioprinter will serve as a powerful instrument for the mass production of 3D tissue models at the industrial scale to advance drug discovery and assay development.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/21/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/21/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>CoopAgrmnt</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2035835</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Wei</FirstName>
<LastName>Zhu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Wei Zhu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[wzhu@allegro3d.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000751937</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/21/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Allegro 3D, Inc</Name>
<CityName>San Diego</CityName>
<ZipCode>921212217</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8586993298</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>6868 Nancy Ridge Dr.</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>51</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA51</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>JKPRS6485RU4</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ALLEGRO 3D, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Allegro 3D, Inc]]></Name>
<CityName>San Diego</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>921212217</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[6868 Nancy Ridge Dr]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>51</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA51</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5373</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase II</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>090E</Code>
<Text>Chem/Bio and Physical Diagnostics</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8037</Code>
<Text>Advanced Manufacturing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~997692</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Currently, drug development in the pharmaceutical industry is a lengthy, inefficient, and expensive process which limits the output of new drugs reaching the consumer market. For instance, costs incurred can amount to $1.8 billion over a span of 12-15 years to launch a single drug. According to the FDA, approximately 92% of the drugs that had successfully passed preclinical animal testing failed in subsequent human trials, which highlights the lack of adequate preclinical testing tools to generate accurate predictive data. High throughput screening (HTS) systems are widely used by the pharmaceutical industry as an efficient method to process large numbers of compounds and molecular targets in a rapid manner. As such, pharmaceutical companies are turning to the use of 3D biomimetic human tissues in HTS format for preclinical toxicity testing of potential drug candidates. Recently, 3D bioprinting platforms have emerged to enable the fabrication of 3D cellularized tissue constructs with microscale resolution and cell patterning capabilities. With the potential to revolutionize the life science field, the global 3D bioprinting market is estimated to reach $1.65 billion with a compound annual growth rate of 20.7% by 2024. To address this growing market, this project has led to the development of an advanced 3D bioprinting platform that allows direct in-well printing of complex 3D biomimetic tissues in a range of standard multiwell plates in a high throughput and automated fashion. We have also successfully implemented multi-material printing to produce physiologically relevant 3D tissues with heterogeneous cellular compositions.</p> <p>With more relevant and functional 3D tissue models provided by the bioprinting platform developed in this project, drugs can be screened more predictably and accurately which will save pharmaceutical companies significant costs due to drug failure while also benefiting the advancement of healthcare and protecting the patients from unknown drug induced toxicity. Moreover, when combined with stem cell technology and high-quality biomaterials, our scalable high-throughput 3D bioprinter can provide patient-specific tissues for in vivo therapeutic applications, providing a viable solution to diseases that currently have no cures or effective treatment yet. As a result, our innovation in providing a high-throughput 3D bioprinter and bioink platform will help advance basic biomedical research and significantly increase the efficiency and lower the cost of drug development by providing more reliable and clinically relevant drug testing results in a high-throughput fashion. We believe the successful commercialization of this innovative bioprinting technology will greatly benefit the biotechnology and pharmaceutical industries, the biomedical research fields, and ultimately the welfare of the patients and the broader society.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/17/2023<br>      Modified by: Wei&nbsp;Zhu</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Currently, drug development in the pharmaceutical industry is a lengthy, inefficient, and expensive process which limits the output of new drugs reaching the consumer market. For instance, costs incurred can amount to $1.8 billion over a span of 12-15 years to launch a single drug. According to the FDA, approximately 92% of the drugs that had successfully passed preclinical animal testing failed in subsequent human trials, which highlights the lack of adequate preclinical testing tools to generate accurate predictive data. High throughput screening (HTS) systems are widely used by the pharmaceutical industry as an efficient method to process large numbers of compounds and molecular targets in a rapid manner. As such, pharmaceutical companies are turning to the use of 3D biomimetic human tissues in HTS format for preclinical toxicity testing of potential drug candidates. Recently, 3D bioprinting platforms have emerged to enable the fabrication of 3D cellularized tissue constructs with microscale resolution and cell patterning capabilities. With the potential to revolutionize the life science field, the global 3D bioprinting market is estimated to reach $1.65 billion with a compound annual growth rate of 20.7% by 2024. To address this growing market, this project has led to the development of an advanced 3D bioprinting platform that allows direct in-well printing of complex 3D biomimetic tissues in a range of standard multiwell plates in a high throughput and automated fashion. We have also successfully implemented multi-material printing to produce physiologically relevant 3D tissues with heterogeneous cellular compositions.  With more relevant and functional 3D tissue models provided by the bioprinting platform developed in this project, drugs can be screened more predictably and accurately which will save pharmaceutical companies significant costs due to drug failure while also benefiting the advancement of healthcare and protecting the patients from unknown drug induced toxicity. Moreover, when combined with stem cell technology and high-quality biomaterials, our scalable high-throughput 3D bioprinter can provide patient-specific tissues for in vivo therapeutic applications, providing a viable solution to diseases that currently have no cures or effective treatment yet. As a result, our innovation in providing a high-throughput 3D bioprinter and bioink platform will help advance basic biomedical research and significantly increase the efficiency and lower the cost of drug development by providing more reliable and clinically relevant drug testing results in a high-throughput fashion. We believe the successful commercialization of this innovative bioprinting technology will greatly benefit the biotechnology and pharmaceutical industries, the biomedical research fields, and ultimately the welfare of the patients and the broader society.          Last Modified: 05/17/2023       Submitted by: Wei Zhu]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
