<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Quieting systemic hyper-inflammation (COVID-19)]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>256000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>256000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Erik Pierstorff</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>epiersto@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922165</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is to alleviate the suffering caused by hyper-inflammation.  Hyper-inflammation is a mis-regulation of the immune system often brought on by viral pneumonia. It can have severe life-threatening complications, including acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS) and changes in blood clotting; hyper-inflammation has been seen in COVID-19 patients. Secondary conditions caused by hyper-inflammation can also have severe long-term consequences to patient health. This project will develop therapeutics that quiet the systemic mis-regulation of the immune system and reduce patient mortality. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed project will advance a treatment for hyper-inflammation, such as that induced by COVID-19. It arises from multiple stimuli and results in life-threatening mis-regulation of the immune system. With a novel molecular target, a new class of anti-fibrotic compounds have the potential to reduce cytokine levels and pro-coagulation factors, acting broadly to address the heterogeneity of inflammation responses. As information becomes available regarding the cytokine storm induced by COVID-19, relevant biomarkers have been proposed.  To demonstrate robust actions on inflammation this project will evaluate the effects of the therapeutic on 1) pro-inflammatory cytokine release, 2) activation of the innate immune system, and 3) systemic concentrations of cytokines and pro-coagulation factors after initiation of inflammation. Biomarkers will be established to track the efficacy of the therapeutic at early and late stages of inflammation, providing a strong rationale for testing the efficacy of this class of compounds in animal models of inflammation. Importantly, with the successful completion of this project, this class of therapeutics will have demonstrated potential to treat hyper-inflammation, coupled with a demonstrated ability to prevent pulmonary fibrosis, a potentially fatal complication.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/18/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/05/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2035857</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Scott</FirstName>
<LastName>Larsen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Scott D Larsen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[scott@fibrosix.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000828988</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/05/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kendell</FirstName>
<LastName>Pawelec</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kendell M Pawelec</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ceo@fibrosix.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000829374</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/18/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate>05/05/2021</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>FIBROSIX INC.</Name>
<CityName>EAST LANSING</CityName>
<ZipCode>488235606</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7346786688</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4942 DAWN AVE STE 150</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>HLLEW3GUYDM5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>FIBROSIX INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[FIBROSIX INC.]]></Name>
<CityName>East Lansing</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>488235606</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4942 Dawn Ave, Suite 150]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1982</Code>
<Text>BIOLOGICAL CHEMISTRY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~256000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The primary goal of this project was to determine whether a small molecule therapeutic agent (FBX081), that had previously been shown to reduce tissue thickening (fibrosis) in lung, could also prevent the damaging effects of hyper-inflammation in the lung that can occur in COVID-19 infections.&nbsp;</p> <p>To accomplish this goal, we tested our compound in inflammation models in cells growing in the lab (in vitro) and in mice (in vivo). Our compound was able to reduce the release of an inflammatory mediator (IL-6) from human lung cells grown in the lab. IL-6 has been implicated in inflammatory processes in lung injury from COVID-19 and other diseases. This result was promising and supported the next phase of the project to test our compound in vivo.&nbsp;</p> <p>For the in vivo studies, we used a bacterial inflammatory stimulus called lipopolysaccharide (LPS). LPS is frequently used in models of inflammatory lung injury to induce release of cytokines like IL-6 and others. To make these measurements, we used a powerful array technology to measure 29 cytokines at once. This study was repeated twice with our drug candidate administered to mice either after the LPS (treatment model) or before (prevention model). Unfortunately, our compound had a minimal effect on the release of these inflammatory cytokines by LPS, which suggests that it would not be effective in suppressing inflammation in cases where a strong inflammatory stimulus like LPS is involved.&nbsp;</p> <p>In addition to the cytokines, we also looked at the levels of a mediator of clotting phenomena that are also found in COVID-19. In this case, there was a small reduction in the clotting mediator (PAI-1) with our compound but it was not sufficient to be biologically significant.</p> <p>So overall, the results of this study did not confirm our prediction that our compound (FBX081) would be an effective treatment for the types of hyper-inflammation that are seen with COVID-19.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/18/2022<br>      Modified by: Scott&nbsp;D&nbsp;Larsen</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The primary goal of this project was to determine whether a small molecule therapeutic agent (FBX081), that had previously been shown to reduce tissue thickening (fibrosis) in lung, could also prevent the damaging effects of hyper-inflammation in the lung that can occur in COVID-19 infections.   To accomplish this goal, we tested our compound in inflammation models in cells growing in the lab (in vitro) and in mice (in vivo). Our compound was able to reduce the release of an inflammatory mediator (IL-6) from human lung cells grown in the lab. IL-6 has been implicated in inflammatory processes in lung injury from COVID-19 and other diseases. This result was promising and supported the next phase of the project to test our compound in vivo.   For the in vivo studies, we used a bacterial inflammatory stimulus called lipopolysaccharide (LPS). LPS is frequently used in models of inflammatory lung injury to induce release of cytokines like IL-6 and others. To make these measurements, we used a powerful array technology to measure 29 cytokines at once. This study was repeated twice with our drug candidate administered to mice either after the LPS (treatment model) or before (prevention model). Unfortunately, our compound had a minimal effect on the release of these inflammatory cytokines by LPS, which suggests that it would not be effective in suppressing inflammation in cases where a strong inflammatory stimulus like LPS is involved.   In addition to the cytokines, we also looked at the levels of a mediator of clotting phenomena that are also found in COVID-19. In this case, there was a small reduction in the clotting mediator (PAI-1) with our compound but it was not sufficient to be biologically significant.  So overall, the results of this study did not confirm our prediction that our compound (FBX081) would be an effective treatment for the types of hyper-inflammation that are seen with COVID-19.          Last Modified: 05/18/2022       Submitted by: Scott D Larsen]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
