<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[MsRI-EW: Planning the Infrastructural Needs to Meet National Research Demand and Support the United States’ Leadership in Biomanufacturing]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>49989.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>49989</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Steven Peretti</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>speretti@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924201</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The recent global pandemic has highlighted some critical areas for improvement in delivering safe and effective therapeutics.  An infrastructure that enables rapid, on-demand manufacturing of emerging therapies is critical to maintaining the health of the American people. This conference will bring together representatives from the public and private sectors. The conference will investigate all major aspects of vaccine and therapeutic development and production. The objective is to develop a roadmap to drive innovative biomanufacturing research and development. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Issues to be addressed include infrastructure to characterize products for clinical trials and  regulatory approval; cyberinfrastructure to provide secure communication and storage of research data; artificial intelligence and machine learning tools to accelerate research progress; and automation technologies to enable new, disruptive manufacturing technologies for vaccines and therapeutics. The conference will have virtual sessions covering (1) cell/gene manufacturing,  (2) emerging vaccine manufacturing, and (3) data integration, analytics, security, and management. Experts within each session will represent clinical research and application, academia, governmental agencies, and the industrial value chain.  Cross-cutting topics will be discussed in terms of needed infrastructure to support accelerated and expanded research efforts. These cross-cutting topics include Scale-up, Automation, Supply Chain, and Education and Workforce.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/10/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/10/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2035203</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Carolyn</FirstName>
<LastName>Yeago</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Carolyn Yeago</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[carolyn.yeago@ibb.gatech.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000825164</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Chun</FirstName>
<LastName>Zhang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Chun Zhang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[czhang343@isye.gatech.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000177397</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Johnna</FirstName>
<LastName>Temenoff</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Johnna S Temenoff</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[johnna.temenoff@bme.gatech.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000069068</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Andres</FirstName>
<LastName>Garcia</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Andres J Garcia</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[andres.garcia@me.gatech.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000484691</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Krishnendu</FirstName>
<LastName>Roy</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Krishnendu Roy</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[krish.roy@vanderbilt.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000107326</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Georgia Tech Research Corporation</Name>
<CityName>ATLANTA</CityName>
<ZipCode>30332</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4048944819</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>926 DALNEY ST NW</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>EMW9FC8J3HN4</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GEORGIA TECH RESEARCH CORPORATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>EMW9FC8J3HN4</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Georgia Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>303320002</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[225 North Avenue NW]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1385</Code>
<Text>SSA-Special Studies &amp; Analysis</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1642</Code>
<Text>Special Initiatives</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~49989</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The past few years have seen transformative changes in the way we treat chronic and often incurable diseases. The emergence of cell and gene therapies is revolutionizing modern medicine, and for the first time providing functional cures or long-term relief for many devastating conditions. Despite this rapid and unprecedented growth, little progress has been made to develop the national biomanufacturing research and development (R&amp;D) infrastructure for emerging therapeutics. The recent coronavirus pandemic (SARS-Cov2, COVID-19) has exposed gaps and systemic failure of this infrastructure ? from failures in supply chain management and surge protection, to standardized data analytics and integration; from lack of scalable manufacturing to absence of a nimble public&nbsp; health infrastructure that can make emerging therapies accessible and cost-effective for all. This national emergency has further highlighted what we already knew ? the United States must invest in developing a national R&amp;D infrastructure for scalable, cost-effective, and rapid, on-demand manufacturing of emerging therapies. This is critical, not only for our long-term public health needs, but also for the economic and social health, and global scientific leadership of this nation.<strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong><strong>Intellectual Merit:</strong> In light of the significant gaps and the complex multidisciplinary input required to address the challenges and barriers for scalable, low cost manufacturing of cells, vaccines, and viruses, this Mid-scale Research Infrastructure Engineering Workshop project put together a series of technical workhops focused on 1- Cell Therapy Manufacturing, 2- Virus and Gene Therapy Manufacturing, 3 ? Emerging Vaccine Manufacturing, and 4 ? Data Integration, Analytics, Security and Management.</p> <p>&nbsp;These workshops:</p> <ul> <li>Bought together a diverse, multidisciplinary group of thought leaders across academia, industry, and government to develop a convergent approach to support biomanufacturing science and research</li> <li>Uncovered and aligned needs across stakeholder groups to ensure all aspects of infrastructure development are addressed to close gaps and ensure national readiness and excellence</li> <li>Confirmed and expanded research infrastructure needs identified through previous biomanufacturing road-mapping efforts (ARMI, CMaT, NCMC, and NIIMBL) to align on the most pressing needs and identify infrastructure that would yield the greatest return on investment</li> <li>Thoroughly defined the required infrastructure ? including physical infrastructure, digital and cyber infrastructure, and intellectual and workforce infrastructure to close the identified gaps</li> <li>Prepared for the design and future implementation of mid-scale research infrastructure to meet the critical national need</li> </ul> <p><strong>Broader Impact:</strong> The results of this Workshop series are provided in a whitepaper that is pubically available through the NSF Engineering Center for Cell Manufacturing Technologies website (<a href="https://cellmanufacturingusa.org/ncmc">https://cellmanufacturingusa.org/ncmc</a>; Biomanufacturing Infrastructure Workshop Whitepaper). This whitepaper details the specific infrastructure needs across all biomanufacturing (including cell, virus, and gene therapy manufacturing and emerging vaccine manufacturing) regarding Facilities and Equipment, Systems and Tools, Education and Workforce, and Supply Chain and Distribution (represented in Figure 1). The needs identified serve to help direct where infrastructure investment will be most impactful across biomanufacturing, and result in the most return on investment. Addressing the infrastructure needs described will build the physical, digital, data-science, and workforce-training infrastructure that can be used by researchers around the country, thereby accelerating innovation and translation in the area of biomanufacturing. Ultimately, successfully addressing these needs will result in increased access to life saving and life changing therapeutics for patients across the U.S. and globally.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/30/2021<br>      Modified by: Carolyn&nbsp;Yeago</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2035203/2035203_10694853_1638302931468_InfrastructureNeedsGraphic--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2035203/2035203_10694853_1638302931468_InfrastructureNeedsGraphic--rgov-800width.jpg" title="High Level Infrastructure Needs"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2035203/2035203_10694853_1638302931468_InfrastructureNeedsGraphic--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="High Level Infrastructure Needs"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 1: Biomanufacturing research infrastructure needs identified through a series of four Technical Workshops.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Nexight Group</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Carolyn&nbsp;Yeago</div> <div class="imageTitle">High Level Infrastructure Needs</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The past few years have seen transformative changes in the way we treat chronic and often incurable diseases. The emergence of cell and gene therapies is revolutionizing modern medicine, and for the first time providing functional cures or long-term relief for many devastating conditions. Despite this rapid and unprecedented growth, little progress has been made to develop the national biomanufacturing research and development (R&amp;D) infrastructure for emerging therapeutics. The recent coronavirus pandemic (SARS-Cov2, COVID-19) has exposed gaps and systemic failure of this infrastructure ? from failures in supply chain management and surge protection, to standardized data analytics and integration; from lack of scalable manufacturing to absence of a nimble public  health infrastructure that can make emerging therapies accessible and cost-effective for all. This national emergency has further highlighted what we already knew ? the United States must invest in developing a national R&amp;D infrastructure for scalable, cost-effective, and rapid, on-demand manufacturing of emerging therapies. This is critical, not only for our long-term public health needs, but also for the economic and social health, and global scientific leadership of this nation.    Intellectual Merit: In light of the significant gaps and the complex multidisciplinary input required to address the challenges and barriers for scalable, low cost manufacturing of cells, vaccines, and viruses, this Mid-scale Research Infrastructure Engineering Workshop project put together a series of technical workhops focused on 1- Cell Therapy Manufacturing, 2- Virus and Gene Therapy Manufacturing, 3 ? Emerging Vaccine Manufacturing, and 4 ? Data Integration, Analytics, Security and Management.   These workshops:  Bought together a diverse, multidisciplinary group of thought leaders across academia, industry, and government to develop a convergent approach to support biomanufacturing science and research Uncovered and aligned needs across stakeholder groups to ensure all aspects of infrastructure development are addressed to close gaps and ensure national readiness and excellence Confirmed and expanded research infrastructure needs identified through previous biomanufacturing road-mapping efforts (ARMI, CMaT, NCMC, and NIIMBL) to align on the most pressing needs and identify infrastructure that would yield the greatest return on investment Thoroughly defined the required infrastructure ? including physical infrastructure, digital and cyber infrastructure, and intellectual and workforce infrastructure to close the identified gaps Prepared for the design and future implementation of mid-scale research infrastructure to meet the critical national need   Broader Impact: The results of this Workshop series are provided in a whitepaper that is pubically available through the NSF Engineering Center for Cell Manufacturing Technologies website (https://cellmanufacturingusa.org/ncmc; Biomanufacturing Infrastructure Workshop Whitepaper). This whitepaper details the specific infrastructure needs across all biomanufacturing (including cell, virus, and gene therapy manufacturing and emerging vaccine manufacturing) regarding Facilities and Equipment, Systems and Tools, Education and Workforce, and Supply Chain and Distribution (represented in Figure 1). The needs identified serve to help direct where infrastructure investment will be most impactful across biomanufacturing, and result in the most return on investment. Addressing the infrastructure needs described will build the physical, digital, data-science, and workforce-training infrastructure that can be used by researchers around the country, thereby accelerating innovation and translation in the area of biomanufacturing. Ultimately, successfully addressing these needs will result in increased access to life saving and life changing therapeutics for patients across the U.S. and globally.          Last Modified: 11/30/2021       Submitted by: Carolyn Yeago]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
