<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I: Mitigating the effects of isolation and absence of therapies through the delivery of cloud based digital treatments and remote patient monitoring]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>256000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>256000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Muralidharan Nair</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is to improve the quality of life for the more than 1 million Americans currently suffering from Parkinson’s Disease (PD) while reducing the growing economic burden on the healthcare system. Outpatient physical and occupational therapy, speech therapy, and mental health are key components in the treatment and management of PD. Early intervention and appropriate symptomatic management utilizing these therapies is essential for best long-term outcomes; Inadequate and infrequent treatment, especially during the COVID-19 pandemic, places a heavier burden on Person with Parkinson’s (PwP) and their families and a greater financial burden on the healthcare system. Delivering remote therapies and monitoring performance via the proposed in-home therapy platform may demonstrate a reduction in symptoms or slowing of disease progression, thereby helping to reduce costly, adverse medical complications and improving the PwP quality of life. Data collected from regular in-home, daily therapies may lead to improved standards of care and aid the research community in the search for a cure. Once proven effective in the beachhead market of PD, the technology could be trialed in the mainstream markets of Alzheimer’s, Dementia, and the aging population. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project will develop a prototype for an automated therapy delivery and remote patient monitoring platform for those suffering from Parkinson’s Disease (PD). This automated platform will provide access to daily therapies for the Person with Parkinson’s (PwP) by facilitating remote therapeutic exercise and social engagement via an in-home device that monitors real-time functionality to adapt cloud based digital content to optimize physical performance, cognition, and physiological response to exercise and cognitive tasks. Such a therapeutic system should have similar levels of efficacy as in-person therapy and treatment sessions, enabling participation in the much needed therapies while simultaneously reducing the burdens placed on the PwP, their families, and the healthcare system. The subjective report data, physiological response data, and objective performance data collected throughout each session will be summarized in a report for the PwP, their families, and their caregivers or healthcare providers to improve the continued delivery of treatment, clinical decision making, and health and safety of the patient. This proposed technology will help to reduce the effects of isolation, provide access to physical therapy and exercise treatments and improve the remote monitoring of patients throughout the COVID-19 pandemic crisis and beyond.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/19/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/19/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2036451</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Bennett</FirstName>
<LastName>Gatto</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Bennett Gatto</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[bgatto0@gmail.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000762999</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/19/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Active Therapy Systems LLC</Name>
<CityName>STAMPING GROUND</CityName>
<ZipCode>403799781</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5026094289</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1598 WHITE OAK RD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Kentucky</StateName>
<StateCode>KY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>KY06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NNDENR2JFGG1</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ACTIVE THERAPY SYSTEMS LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Active Therapy Systems LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>Nicholasville</CityName>
<StateCode>KY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>403561229</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[131 N 4th Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Kentucky</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>KY06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>6840</Code>
<Text>ROBOTICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8033</Code>
<Text>Hardware Software Integration</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~256000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Throughout the Phase I project, the Active Therapy Systems (ATS) team developed the foundation and infrastructure of a technology platform to deliver virtual physical therapy with remote patient monitoring for those with neurological disorders such as Parkinson's Disease (PD). Currently, there are over one million Americans living with PD. The economic burden, including direct and in-direct medical costs is estimated to be over $52 billion, annually. Those numbers are expected to increase by more than 50% within the next 20 years.</p> <p>Physical and occupational therapy (PT/OT) for those with neurological disorders is <strong><em>proven</em></strong> to help improve physical and cognitive function while significantly reducing depression and anxiety. A growing body of research suggests that when implemented correctly, neurological disease progression may be slowed or even prevented in PD, but when therapy is sporadic, as most are, retrogression ensues. Additionally, the effectiveness of the therapy intervention depends not only on the quality of treatment, but on the implementation parameters and frequency at which the intervention is performed. Therefore, a major problem exists for a majority of people living with PD due to the time, travel, and costs associated with seeking specialized treatment.</p> <p>Access to specialized physical therapy is severely limited by the distance or necessary travel required to see a specialist physical therapist, the time required by the individual with PD and their caregivers to attend regular appointments, and the out-of-pocket costs associated with on-going care that becomes too burdensome over time. It is imperative to provide a low-cost, non-pharmacologic solution to help manage systems and help individuals maintain their independence.</p> <p>The ATS PT platform, ?Total PT Connect (TotalPT),? provides unlimited access to personalized, virtual physical therapy sessions with remote patient monitoring for those with neurological disorders. The plug-and-play solution was designed with the end-user at the forefront of development. Using a tablet with proprietary software and associated remote monitoring devices, patients receive specialized care that is overseen by their own dedicated PT, from the comfort of their home. TotalPT combines PT guidance with real-time automation to deliver personalized disease specific treatment via physical and cognitive therapy with bio feedback monitoring, using exercise-based complex movements and tasks to enhance neuroplasticity through challenging specific areas of brain function. Unique data points are collected and analyzed by the platform to provide insight into a person?s condition and disease progression which will help guide the clinical decision making of the medical care team, including the patient?s neurologist.</p> <p>The goal for the Total PT Connect platform is to provide individuals with the tools needed to receive specialized care by reducing most barriers to participation. Through the personalization of therapy and on-going data monitoring, ATS hopes to provide more accurate information regarding disease progression and reduce adverse events with earlier interventions. Additionally, the team hopes to improve medication management through tracking features that will be implemented into the platform through future work. As the number of patients using the platform increase and the data sets being collected become more robust, ATS anticipates contributing to improvements in the standards of care for those with PD, and hopefully one day, contributing to finding the cure.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/24/2022<br>      Modified by: Bennett&nbsp;Gatto</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Throughout the Phase I project, the Active Therapy Systems (ATS) team developed the foundation and infrastructure of a technology platform to deliver virtual physical therapy with remote patient monitoring for those with neurological disorders such as Parkinson's Disease (PD). Currently, there are over one million Americans living with PD. The economic burden, including direct and in-direct medical costs is estimated to be over $52 billion, annually. Those numbers are expected to increase by more than 50% within the next 20 years.  Physical and occupational therapy (PT/OT) for those with neurological disorders is proven to help improve physical and cognitive function while significantly reducing depression and anxiety. A growing body of research suggests that when implemented correctly, neurological disease progression may be slowed or even prevented in PD, but when therapy is sporadic, as most are, retrogression ensues. Additionally, the effectiveness of the therapy intervention depends not only on the quality of treatment, but on the implementation parameters and frequency at which the intervention is performed. Therefore, a major problem exists for a majority of people living with PD due to the time, travel, and costs associated with seeking specialized treatment.  Access to specialized physical therapy is severely limited by the distance or necessary travel required to see a specialist physical therapist, the time required by the individual with PD and their caregivers to attend regular appointments, and the out-of-pocket costs associated with on-going care that becomes too burdensome over time. It is imperative to provide a low-cost, non-pharmacologic solution to help manage systems and help individuals maintain their independence.  The ATS PT platform, ?Total PT Connect (TotalPT),? provides unlimited access to personalized, virtual physical therapy sessions with remote patient monitoring for those with neurological disorders. The plug-and-play solution was designed with the end-user at the forefront of development. Using a tablet with proprietary software and associated remote monitoring devices, patients receive specialized care that is overseen by their own dedicated PT, from the comfort of their home. TotalPT combines PT guidance with real-time automation to deliver personalized disease specific treatment via physical and cognitive therapy with bio feedback monitoring, using exercise-based complex movements and tasks to enhance neuroplasticity through challenging specific areas of brain function. Unique data points are collected and analyzed by the platform to provide insight into a person?s condition and disease progression which will help guide the clinical decision making of the medical care team, including the patient?s neurologist.  The goal for the Total PT Connect platform is to provide individuals with the tools needed to receive specialized care by reducing most barriers to participation. Through the personalization of therapy and on-going data monitoring, ATS hopes to provide more accurate information regarding disease progression and reduce adverse events with earlier interventions. Additionally, the team hopes to improve medication management through tracking features that will be implemented into the platform through future work. As the number of patients using the platform increase and the data sets being collected become more robust, ATS anticipates contributing to improvements in the standards of care for those with PD, and hopefully one day, contributing to finding the cure.       Last Modified: 09/24/2022       Submitted by: Bennett Gatto]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
