<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Quantum cutting downconversion layers for improved solar PV performance]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>255927.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>255927</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Peter Atherton</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>patherto@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928772</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is to accelerate the deployment of solar power in the United States. The technology can potentially make solar panels up to 16% more efficient and result in up to 10% lower costs. This enables solar power to potentially become more economically viable across larger parts of the United States. This technology can serve the existing 110 GW solar panel market. Global commercialization of the technology can increase solar energy production by 14,000 TWh and reduce carbon emissions from the power sector by 6 billion tonnes.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project develops a light conversion material that combines a light absorber material, a wide bandgap inorganic perovskite, with a highly efficient, quantum cutting near-IR emitter, a ytterbium dopant. The material is applied to existing solar panel components using a rapid vapor deposition process to create drop-in replacements, avoiding changes to the panel production process.  Traditional silicon solar panels poorly convert ultraviolet light into electricity, generating substantial waste heat and degrading panels.  The light conversion materials developed here utilizes that traditionally wasted light, thereby boosting overall panel efficiencies.  This project will confirm the feasibility of the technology for solar applications by building coupon solar modules, measuring power performance improvements, and confirming intrinsic device stability through environmental stress tests.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/03/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/24/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041, 47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2036362</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jared</FirstName>
<LastName>Silvia</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jared S Silvia</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jared.silvia@bluedotphotonics.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000799894</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/03/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>BLUEDOT PHOTONICS INC.</Name>
<CityName>KIRKLAND</CityName>
<ZipCode>980345159</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6174609828</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>9212 NE 141ST ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WA01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>F8GGRBCWEGF5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>BLUEDOT PHOTONICS, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[BLUEDOT PHOTONICS INC.]]></Name>
<CityName>Seattle</CityName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>981054026</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4625 Union Bay Pl NE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8611</Code>
<Text>Energy Efficiency and End Use</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8990</Code>
<Text>Optics and Photonics</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~255927</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>In our Phase I SBIR project, we found a reproducible way to make materials that undergo quantum-cutting downconversion (QCD). QCD is a process that turns ultraviolet light (aka, the light that causes sunburns) into twice as much infrared light (aka, heat energy). Current solar panel technology is better at turning infrared light into electricity than ultraviolet light. If we made these materials at large enough scales, with the right level of performance, and integrated them into a solar panel, it could increase the output of a solar panel by up to 16%. This could decrease the cost of solar power in the US and the world by as much as 10%. This would accelerate the deployment of solar power. In turn, this would reduce greenhouse gas emissions, improve air quality, and increase energy security and resiliency.</p> <p>Our project focused on finding a way to make our QCD materials reproducibly and reliably, at a sufficient scale to test the impact our materials would have on a solar panel. By the end of the project, we nearly doubled the performance of our materials, tuned how much ultraviolet light the materials would absorb, and made mini-solar panels that had our materials inside them. When integrated into a mini-solar panel, we showed how the materials could improve the performance of today's solar cell technology. We also showed how durable these materials are. After 1000 hours of stress testing, our materials showed little to no degradation. The combination of these results confirms the commercial feasibility of our technology and set a clear path for continued R&amp;D to further improve the performance of the materials and the cost to make them.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/02/2022<br>      Modified by: Jared&nbsp;S&nbsp;Silvia</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2036362/2036362_10715714_1659460686507_MaterialPackage--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2036362/2036362_10715714_1659460686507_MaterialPackage--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Material Package"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2036362/2036362_10715714_1659460686507_MaterialPackage--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Material Package"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">A picture of a material sample made using the process we developed and packaged for durability testing.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Sarah Little</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (restricted use - cannot be shared)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jared&nbsp;S&nbsp;Silvia</div> <div class="imageTitle">Material Package</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2036362/2036362_10715714_1659460768784_TestDevices--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2036362/2036362_10715714_1659460768784_TestDevices--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Test Devices"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2036362/2036362_10715714_1659460768784_TestDevices--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Test Devices"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Examples of the mini-solar panels used for testing the material performance.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Daniel Kroupa</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (restricted use - cannot be shared)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jared&nbsp;S&nbsp;Silvia</div> <div class="imageTitle">Test Devices</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ In our Phase I SBIR project, we found a reproducible way to make materials that undergo quantum-cutting downconversion (QCD). QCD is a process that turns ultraviolet light (aka, the light that causes sunburns) into twice as much infrared light (aka, heat energy). Current solar panel technology is better at turning infrared light into electricity than ultraviolet light. If we made these materials at large enough scales, with the right level of performance, and integrated them into a solar panel, it could increase the output of a solar panel by up to 16%. This could decrease the cost of solar power in the US and the world by as much as 10%. This would accelerate the deployment of solar power. In turn, this would reduce greenhouse gas emissions, improve air quality, and increase energy security and resiliency.  Our project focused on finding a way to make our QCD materials reproducibly and reliably, at a sufficient scale to test the impact our materials would have on a solar panel. By the end of the project, we nearly doubled the performance of our materials, tuned how much ultraviolet light the materials would absorb, and made mini-solar panels that had our materials inside them. When integrated into a mini-solar panel, we showed how the materials could improve the performance of today's solar cell technology. We also showed how durable these materials are. After 1000 hours of stress testing, our materials showed little to no degradation. The combination of these results confirms the commercial feasibility of our technology and set a clear path for continued R&amp;D to further improve the performance of the materials and the cost to make them.          Last Modified: 08/02/2022       Submitted by: Jared S Silvia]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
