<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Enzyme-free detection of SARS-CoV2 using a PAINT-based single-molecule microscopy assay]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>199993.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>199993</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08090100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IOS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anna Allen</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>akallen@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928011</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The novel coronavirus that causes COVID-19 is composed of a spherical envelope that surrounds a genome made of ribonucleic acids (RNAs). These RNAs control viral replication and have distinct regions for each coronavirus strain. Most rapid detection tests for COVID-19 amplify three unique RNA regions with a protein called an enzyme. The activity of enzymes greatly increases the sensitivity of COVID-19 detection, but have disadvantages of requiring cold storage, short shelf life, and potential for false negative results due to the loss of enzymatic activity. This research develops an enzyme-free COVID-19 test that uses the binding of stabilized deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA) molecules that are locked into place along the novel coronavirus genome. The  novel coronavirus can be visualized using a micrscope when another marker DNA molecule constantly docks and undocks from the DNA attached to the coronavirus genetic material. The project will deliver a sensitive and stable test for rapid detection of COVID-19. A major goal of this project is to develop a flexible enzyme-free, shelf-stable viral test that can be readily adapted for the current as well as future viral outbreaks.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of this project is to develop an enzyme-free detection method for SARS-CoV-2 with single-molecule sensitivity that can detect single nucleotide polymorphisms of mutated strains in the United States. To achieve this goal, viral capture coverglasses will be engineered by covalently linking oligonucleotide (oligo) sequences that are reverse complementary to the 70-nt leader sequence (LS) and sequences 5’ to key regions of SARS-CoV-2 genome. Extracted viral RNA will be applied to the coverglass to pull down all viral transcripts that bind to the LS capture anchors. The specific regions for SARS-CoV-2 detection suggested by the Center of Disease Control &amp; Prevention (CDC) will be used as target sequences to design probes for small RNA detection via DNA-based points accumulation in nanoscale topography (sRNA-PAINT). Single-molecule viral detection and amplification of target regions will be achieved with sRNA-PAINT by deploying highly specific locked-nucleic acid (LNA) oligonucleotide probes linked to oligo “docking strands”.  Amplification is enzyme-free, and instead, the signal for any individual probe is amplified by the predictable binding and unbinding of oligo “imager strands” to the docking strands of the probe. Imager strands have a conjugated fluorophore and their binding is detected in thousands of images taken over 15 minutes on a microscope using a sensitive camera. The detection assay or kit will consist of an oligonucleotide (oligo)-linked capture coverglass, COVID-19 -specific oligo probes, fluorescent oligo imaging probes, buffers, and instructions on how to either deploy the assay on any microscope with single molecule sensitivity or build one.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/17/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/17/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2036801</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kun</FirstName>
<LastName>Huang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kun Huang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[huangkun@udel.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000828774</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/17/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jeffrey</FirstName>
<LastName>Caplan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jeffrey Caplan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jcaplan@UDel.Edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000569055</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/17/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Delaware</Name>
<CityName>NEWARK</CityName>
<ZipCode>197160099</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3028312136</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>220 HULLIHEN HALL</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Delaware</StateName>
<StateCode>DE</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DE00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>T72NHKM259N3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF DELAWARE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Delaware]]></Name>
<CityName>Newark</CityName>
<StateCode>DE</StateCode>
<ZipCode>197115449</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[15 Innovation Way]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Delaware</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DE00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1118</Code>
<Text>PLANT FUNGAL &amp; MICROB DEV MECH</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~199993</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Like all viruses, the novel coronavirus, SARS-CoV2, spreads by infecting new living hosts and then multiplies. To accomplish this feat, the virus replicates its genome, or blueprint, that is made of ribonucleic acids (RNA) and then packages it into a spherical envelope made of proteins. COVID-19 tests generally either detect the proteins on the outside of the virus or they detect the RNA on the inside.&nbsp; Many of the rapid antigen tests for home use detect the proteins via antibodies, which when bound to the viral protein, will show up as a slower moving colored band on a lateral flow strip.&nbsp; These test are rapid and relatively inexpensive, but their sensitivity is much lower than nucleic acid amplification tests (NAATs) that detect very low levels of the viral RNA. Reverse transcription polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR) is often considered the gold standard of this type of test.&nbsp; However, newer tests based on isothermal amplification have since come on to the market to provide rapid NAAT in under fifteen minutes. All of the NAATs require enzymes for the amplification, which is the key to their sensitivity.&nbsp; The goal of this project was to evaluate an enzyme-free detection method for SARS-CoV-2 that still detects RNA by does not rely on enzyme amplification.&nbsp; Instead the amplification occurs during the detection process, which can detect the same RNA multiple times.&nbsp; The method is based on a technique called small RNA detection via DNA-based points accumulation in nanoscale topography (sRNA-PAINT). Using this approach, single SARS-CoV-2 viral RNA molecules can be detected by the repeat binding of fluorescent molecules to a probe that is locked onto a specific part of the RNA.&nbsp; This is accomplished with a modified nucleic acid that is not found in nature called a locked-nucleic acid (LNA).&nbsp; These can be used to detect very small changes to the sequences, such are the underlying changes that lead to different SARS-CoV-2 variants like delta and omicron. The specificity of our assay is first enhanced by using viral capture strands bound to coverglass and then enhanced further with LNA probes. However, the disadvantage of our approach is that it only images RNA that are captured on the glass and requires a very sensitive microscope to detect the RNA. The advantages and disadvantages of this approach for the development of a rapid COVID-19 test were thoroughly explored. However, in the past few years, both rapid antigen tests and NAATs have filled the majority of the needs for day-to-day screening of COVID-19.&nbsp; Our approach shows future potential to rapidly detect known viral changes in variants. In the future, a microscopy-based approach using our sRNA-PAINT method evaluated here could be combined with single molecule fluorescence in situ hybridization (smFISH) to develop an assay with both high specificity and high sensitivity. &nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/30/2023<br>      Modified by: Jeffrey&nbsp;Caplan</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Like all viruses, the novel coronavirus, SARS-CoV2, spreads by infecting new living hosts and then multiplies. To accomplish this feat, the virus replicates its genome, or blueprint, that is made of ribonucleic acids (RNA) and then packages it into a spherical envelope made of proteins. COVID-19 tests generally either detect the proteins on the outside of the virus or they detect the RNA on the inside.  Many of the rapid antigen tests for home use detect the proteins via antibodies, which when bound to the viral protein, will show up as a slower moving colored band on a lateral flow strip.  These test are rapid and relatively inexpensive, but their sensitivity is much lower than nucleic acid amplification tests (NAATs) that detect very low levels of the viral RNA. Reverse transcription polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR) is often considered the gold standard of this type of test.  However, newer tests based on isothermal amplification have since come on to the market to provide rapid NAAT in under fifteen minutes. All of the NAATs require enzymes for the amplification, which is the key to their sensitivity.  The goal of this project was to evaluate an enzyme-free detection method for SARS-CoV-2 that still detects RNA by does not rely on enzyme amplification.  Instead the amplification occurs during the detection process, which can detect the same RNA multiple times.  The method is based on a technique called small RNA detection via DNA-based points accumulation in nanoscale topography (sRNA-PAINT). Using this approach, single SARS-CoV-2 viral RNA molecules can be detected by the repeat binding of fluorescent molecules to a probe that is locked onto a specific part of the RNA.  This is accomplished with a modified nucleic acid that is not found in nature called a locked-nucleic acid (LNA).  These can be used to detect very small changes to the sequences, such are the underlying changes that lead to different SARS-CoV-2 variants like delta and omicron. The specificity of our assay is first enhanced by using viral capture strands bound to coverglass and then enhanced further with LNA probes. However, the disadvantage of our approach is that it only images RNA that are captured on the glass and requires a very sensitive microscope to detect the RNA. The advantages and disadvantages of this approach for the development of a rapid COVID-19 test were thoroughly explored. However, in the past few years, both rapid antigen tests and NAATs have filled the majority of the needs for day-to-day screening of COVID-19.  Our approach shows future potential to rapidly detect known viral changes in variants. In the future, a microscopy-based approach using our sRNA-PAINT method evaluated here could be combined with single molecule fluorescence in situ hybridization (smFISH) to develop an assay with both high specificity and high sensitivity.         Last Modified: 01/30/2023       Submitted by: Jeffrey Caplan]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
