<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Endoluminal Fixation of a Distraction Enterogenesis Device]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>256000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>256000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Henry Ahn</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>hahn@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927069</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is to create a novel intestinal lengthening system for the treatment of Short Bowel Syndrome (SBS). SBS is a devastating condition defined by the loss of greater than 50% of a patient’s small bowel due to a congenital or acquired defect that often requires surgical treatment. For pediatric patients, SBS can be more devastating with the mortality rate approaching 50%. Existing non-surgical treatment options are inadequate and often lead to complications such as life-threatening central venous line infections, clotting of the major venous systems, metabolic imbalance, liver disease, and organ failure. The average cost per SBS patient ranges from $150,000-$200,000 for nutrition alone, and when combined with pharmaceutical therapies, the cost can exceed $500,000 per year. Today, there is no known restorative solution to SBS. This project will develop a technology that can be delivered endoscopically to the small intestine without the need of open surgery. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase 1 project intends to create the first fixation method for devices to be endoscopically placed inside the small intestine, held temporarily in place, and then released for natural passing out of the body in the stool. Current fixation methods and technology are permanent and require either an open surgical procedure or a device that remains in place.  This project will be accomplished as follows: (1) select a preferred fixation method, including fabrication and testing subassemblies on the laboratory bench to optimize fixation performance and subsequent release; (2) incorporate the optimal fixation and release concept with existing endoscopic imaging and delivery devices to demonstrate system feasibility on the laboratory bench; and (3) prepare a system for animal testing.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/21/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/21/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2036538</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Andre</FirstName>
<LastName>Bessette</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Andre Bessette</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[enterogenesis@gmail.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000782565</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/21/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>ECLIPSE ENTEROGENESIS, INC.</Name>
<CityName>MOUNTAIN VIEW</CityName>
<ZipCode>940404157</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6508040599</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2495 HOSPITAL DR STE 300</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>16</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA16</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NNJ5XHMGNKS8</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ECLIPSE REGENESIS, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[ECLIPSE ENTEROGENESIS, INC.]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>940251499</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>15</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA15</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5345</Code>
<Text>BIOMEDICAL ENGINEERING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~256000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Short bowel syndrome a nutrient uptake disorder that results from loss of functional bowel through injury, surgery, or congenital disorder affects tens of thousands of patients in the United States, many of whom are children. The current standard of care, dietary treatments (parenteral nutrition), are inadequate: they are associated with significant long-term morbidity and mortality, they are exceptionally expensive (~$300K per patient per year), and they do not work for all patients. Since the underlying issue in Short Bowel Syndrome is lack of intestinal surface area to support nutrient absorption, one intuitively attractive solution is to help these patients grow new intestine. In laboratory animal testing, distraction enterogenesis stretching the intestine to force it to grow has been used successfully, making this a promising approach to translate to humans. Hence, Eclipse Regenesis is developing a novel medical device to bring this technique into the clinic via a minimally invasive surgical procedure as a novel treatment for patients with Short Bowel Syndrome.</p> <p>Stretching the gut requires the ability to place anchors along the tissue that remain fixed; pressing against these anchors will then put force on the tissue between the anchors. An additional requirement is that anchors should be reversible (i.e., either passed with time or surgically removable). The goal of this Phase I project was to develop a strategy for anchoring to the gut tissue without perforating the bowel (which could lead to lethal infection) or obstructing it. We began by surveying available technologies that are approved for use in the bowel, but we quickly realized that these either: 1) provided insufficient anchoring; 2) were too insubstantial to push against, which precluded their use for stretching; or 3) would cause tissue damage that potentially could lead to perforations or necrosis (tissue death). Therefore, we set out to devise a novel anchoring system.</p> <p>We designed and prototyped numerous anchor concepts.&nbsp;&nbsp;We created a laboratory benchtop testing method that leveraged dissected intestine and allowed us to measure the anchoring ability of various prototypes, including the force required for the anchor to fail. Using this technique, we winnowed potential concepts, then we engaged in an iterative process through which we refined features of each design to better meet the various specifications we defined for the anchor.&nbsp;&nbsp;After several iterations, we arrived at two designs that we tested&nbsp;<em>in vivo</em>.</p> <p>We performed a limited animal study in an animal model.&nbsp;&nbsp;Briefly, we surgically implanted several anchors of each design in the pig's small intestine, then the animal was allowed to recover.&nbsp;&nbsp;During the recovery period, the animal showed no signs of distress or infection, suggesting no perforation or instruction. After 14 days, the animal was euthanized to harvest the bowel for histology and to ascertain the status of the implants.&nbsp;&nbsp;We found that some were still in place, and several were downstream in the bowel. This indicates the anchors can hold through the critical period and that the gut's contortions can eventually work them free, meeting the fundamental design requirements we articulated at the project's start.&nbsp;</p> <p>This project was successful in achieving all objectives.&nbsp;&nbsp;These promising results provide the foundation for our future work to create a system for delivering a compressed spring between two anchors as the spring expands, it stretches the gut, forcing the tissue to lengthen and grow. In addition to these engineering tasks, we will undertake additional preclinical studies that will be required for regulatory approval before we can bring this innovative treatment to the tens of thousands of patients it may benefit.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/07/2022<br>      Modified by: Andre&nbsp;Bessette</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Short bowel syndrome a nutrient uptake disorder that results from loss of functional bowel through injury, surgery, or congenital disorder affects tens of thousands of patients in the United States, many of whom are children. The current standard of care, dietary treatments (parenteral nutrition), are inadequate: they are associated with significant long-term morbidity and mortality, they are exceptionally expensive (~$300K per patient per year), and they do not work for all patients. Since the underlying issue in Short Bowel Syndrome is lack of intestinal surface area to support nutrient absorption, one intuitively attractive solution is to help these patients grow new intestine. In laboratory animal testing, distraction enterogenesis stretching the intestine to force it to grow has been used successfully, making this a promising approach to translate to humans. Hence, Eclipse Regenesis is developing a novel medical device to bring this technique into the clinic via a minimally invasive surgical procedure as a novel treatment for patients with Short Bowel Syndrome.  Stretching the gut requires the ability to place anchors along the tissue that remain fixed; pressing against these anchors will then put force on the tissue between the anchors. An additional requirement is that anchors should be reversible (i.e., either passed with time or surgically removable). The goal of this Phase I project was to develop a strategy for anchoring to the gut tissue without perforating the bowel (which could lead to lethal infection) or obstructing it. We began by surveying available technologies that are approved for use in the bowel, but we quickly realized that these either: 1) provided insufficient anchoring; 2) were too insubstantial to push against, which precluded their use for stretching; or 3) would cause tissue damage that potentially could lead to perforations or necrosis (tissue death). Therefore, we set out to devise a novel anchoring system.  We designed and prototyped numerous anchor concepts.  We created a laboratory benchtop testing method that leveraged dissected intestine and allowed us to measure the anchoring ability of various prototypes, including the force required for the anchor to fail. Using this technique, we winnowed potential concepts, then we engaged in an iterative process through which we refined features of each design to better meet the various specifications we defined for the anchor.  After several iterations, we arrived at two designs that we tested in vivo.  We performed a limited animal study in an animal model.  Briefly, we surgically implanted several anchors of each design in the pig's small intestine, then the animal was allowed to recover.  During the recovery period, the animal showed no signs of distress or infection, suggesting no perforation or instruction. After 14 days, the animal was euthanized to harvest the bowel for histology and to ascertain the status of the implants.  We found that some were still in place, and several were downstream in the bowel. This indicates the anchors can hold through the critical period and that the gut's contortions can eventually work them free, meeting the fundamental design requirements we articulated at the project's start.   This project was successful in achieving all objectives.  These promising results provide the foundation for our future work to create a system for delivering a compressed spring between two anchors as the spring expands, it stretches the gut, forcing the tissue to lengthen and grow. In addition to these engineering tasks, we will undertake additional preclinical studies that will be required for regulatory approval before we can bring this innovative treatment to the tens of thousands of patients it may benefit.          Last Modified: 04/07/2022       Submitted by: Andre Bessette]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
