<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I:  Rapid Development of a Protein Vaccine for COVID-19</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>256000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>256000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kaitlin Bratlie</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kbratlie@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922638</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is the development of a vaccine to prevent infection from the SARS-CoV-2 virus.  The proposed project is a novel vaccine that activates multiple components of the immune system, potentially more effective than other SAR-CoV-2 vaccines, and using a well-understood approach as a protein-based vaccine.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This SBIR Phase I project will advance a protein vaccine based upon a platform technology combining two functions, activating the immune system and targeting it to attack to a specific pathogen or cell.  The platform has a modular design that allows it to be re-engineered, in a cassette-like fashion, to redirect the attack to different targets.  Applications for the technology include vaccines against viruses and cells infected by viruses, as well as against specific cancer types.  The vaccine can be rapidly generated and easily re-engineered. The focus of this project will be to produce this SARS-CoV-2 targeted protein vaccine utilizing an immune-activating platform with the SARS-CoV-2 spike protein inserted into the targeting domain of the platform. The will be followed by studies to demonstrate the vaccine candidate activity in an in vitro model and an animal model.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/23/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/23/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2036226</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
<LastName>Leonardi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Peter M Leonardi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>peter.leonardi@omnicyte.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9174397479</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000828386</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/23/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>OMNICYTE, LLC</Name>
<CityName>GUILFORD</CityName>
<ZipCode>064373323</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9174397479</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3 INDIAN COVE RD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CT03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>HCUUZKFRCNL4</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OMNICYTE LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[OMNICYTE, LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>Branford</CityName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>064050001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[23 Business Park Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CT03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>008E</Code>
<Text>Gene and Drug Delivery</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8038</Code>
<Text>Biotechnology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~256000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Using our proprietary bispecific immune activating platform technology, we proposed to test the feasibility of creating a prophylactic vaccine to prevent infection with SARS-CoV-2. During the COVID-19 pandemic, it was unexpectedly observed that patients recovering from the disease expressed high levels of SARS-CoV-2 specific CD8+ T-cells. We previously had demonstrated that we can generate a CD8+ T-cell response using the OmniCyte platform technology. Therefore, we hypothesized that our platform could be used to engineer an effective vaccine to prevent COVID19.</p> <p>Our platform technology consists of two protein domains. The N-terminal domain encodes an immune activating domain that binds to, and activates dendritic cells, which are responsible for mounting an immune response in the body against pathogens and cells infected with pathogens, as well as tumor cells. This domain is conserved in all of our therapeutics, and is called VGP. The second domain is the targeting domain. It consists of a protein sequence that is present in the target cell, and through the interaction with the dendritic cell, it becomes the target of the immune response. This domain is the targeting domain (TD). For this Phase I SBIR project, we used the SARS-CoV-2 Spike protein.</p> <p>The Aims of the project were to make the expression construct, express the chimeric protein, purify the protein and then test its efficacy in a mouse model. Using&nbsp;<em>in silico</em>&nbsp;modeling and our previous experience, we were able to design a construct that was soluble and readily expressed. Additionally, using previous experience, we designed a production and purification strategy that allowed us to produce mg quantities of high quality, and highly pure, protein. We then treated mice with our vaccine candidate (OMN008). We expected that the candidate would stimulate a strong T-cell response, which it did. However, we could not be sure whether it would induce an antibody response, which is critical to preventing SARS-CoV-2 infection. We were very pleased to see that OMN008 induced a strong antibody response. Furthermore, we demonstrated that both the antibody response and the T-cell response were specific for the SARS-CoV-2 Spike protein. Finally, we demonstrated that OMN-008 generates an immune response that killed virus that expressed the SARS-CoV-2 Spike protein.</p> <p>We are pleased to report that our team, made up of world class vaccine and immunology experts, successfully completed the proposed Aims of the project. In doing so, we demonstrated feasibility for the use of OMN008 as a vaccine against SARS-CoV-2 infection. Based on this success, we plan on applying for a Phase II NSF SBIR grant to do the pre-IND studies required to move OMN008 into the clinic. While the need for a COVID-19 vaccine has changed since the project was initiated, a need for a novel vaccine does exist. Through customer and stakeholder interviews, we have identified a need for our therapeutic as a vaccine booster. We believe, and hope to demonstrate in Phase II, that our vaccine is safer and more durable than existing vaccines. Additionally, our experience has shown us that we can respond rapidly to new variants, by reengineering our vaccine.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/05/2022<br>      Modified by: Peter&nbsp;M&nbsp;Leonardi</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2036226/2036226_10709552_1649137102501_Figure1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2036226/2036226_10709552_1649137102501_Figure1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 1"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2036226/2036226_10709552_1649137102501_Figure1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 1"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Design and production of OMN008</div> <div class="imageCredit">Edward Quinlan</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Peter&nbsp;M&nbsp;Leonardi</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 1</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2036226/2036226_10709552_1649136958511_FIgure3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2036226/2036226_10709552_1649136958511_FIgure3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 3"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2036226/2036226_10709552_1649136958511_FIgure3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 3"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">OMN008 induces a CD8+ T-cell response.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Edward Quinlan</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Peter&nbsp;M&nbsp;Leonardi</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 3</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2036226/2036226_10709552_1649137217939_Figure2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2036226/2036226_10709552_1649137217939_Figure2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 2"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2036226/2036226_10709552_1649137217939_Figure2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 2"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">OMN008 induces a strong antibody response against the SARS-CoV-2 spike protein</div> <div class="imageCredit">Edward Quinlan</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Peter&nbsp;M&nbsp;Leonardi</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 2</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Using our proprietary bispecific immune activating platform technology, we proposed to test the feasibility of creating a prophylactic vaccine to prevent infection with SARS-CoV-2. During the COVID-19 pandemic, it was unexpectedly observed that patients recovering from the disease expressed high levels of SARS-CoV-2 specific CD8+ T-cells. We previously had demonstrated that we can generate a CD8+ T-cell response using the OmniCyte platform technology. Therefore, we hypothesized that our platform could be used to engineer an effective vaccine to prevent COVID19.  Our platform technology consists of two protein domains. The N-terminal domain encodes an immune activating domain that binds to, and activates dendritic cells, which are responsible for mounting an immune response in the body against pathogens and cells infected with pathogens, as well as tumor cells. This domain is conserved in all of our therapeutics, and is called VGP. The second domain is the targeting domain. It consists of a protein sequence that is present in the target cell, and through the interaction with the dendritic cell, it becomes the target of the immune response. This domain is the targeting domain (TD). For this Phase I SBIR project, we used the SARS-CoV-2 Spike protein.  The Aims of the project were to make the expression construct, express the chimeric protein, purify the protein and then test its efficacy in a mouse model. Using in silico modeling and our previous experience, we were able to design a construct that was soluble and readily expressed. Additionally, using previous experience, we designed a production and purification strategy that allowed us to produce mg quantities of high quality, and highly pure, protein. We then treated mice with our vaccine candidate (OMN008). We expected that the candidate would stimulate a strong T-cell response, which it did. However, we could not be sure whether it would induce an antibody response, which is critical to preventing SARS-CoV-2 infection. We were very pleased to see that OMN008 induced a strong antibody response. Furthermore, we demonstrated that both the antibody response and the T-cell response were specific for the SARS-CoV-2 Spike protein. Finally, we demonstrated that OMN-008 generates an immune response that killed virus that expressed the SARS-CoV-2 Spike protein.  We are pleased to report that our team, made up of world class vaccine and immunology experts, successfully completed the proposed Aims of the project. In doing so, we demonstrated feasibility for the use of OMN008 as a vaccine against SARS-CoV-2 infection. Based on this success, we plan on applying for a Phase II NSF SBIR grant to do the pre-IND studies required to move OMN008 into the clinic. While the need for a COVID-19 vaccine has changed since the project was initiated, a need for a novel vaccine does exist. Through customer and stakeholder interviews, we have identified a need for our therapeutic as a vaccine booster. We believe, and hope to demonstrate in Phase II, that our vaccine is safer and more durable than existing vaccines. Additionally, our experience has shown us that we can respond rapidly to new variants, by reengineering our vaccine.          Last Modified: 04/05/2022       Submitted by: Peter M Leonardi]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
