<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Slowing the Spread of COVID-19: Development of Persistent Antimicrobial Compositions to Prevent Cross-Contamination via Hands and Gloves]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>255990.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>255990</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anna Brady</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>abrady@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927077</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research SBIR project will be to transform the ability to control cross-contamination by pathogens via hands and gloves in the healthcare and food sectors and strengthen the nation’s response to the COVID-19 crisis by limiting its spread. This innovation will also reduce the healthcare-acquired infections from other pathogens that cause 1.7 million illnesses, 98,000 deaths and an estimated $45 billion annually in direct costs to US hospitals. Cross-contamination via hands and gloves is a leading cause of spread of pathogens and resulting infections. Handwashing and hand sanitizers provide periodic sanitation, however, cross-contamination via hands between periodic handwashing or sanitizing is an inherent risk. Likewise, donning fresh gloves helps ensure the gloves used are sanitary, but they become contaminated during use. Innovations described in this proposal provide continuous sanitation for hands between handwashing and between changes of gloves. Maintaining persistent antimicrobial activity for an extended period on hands and gloves of workers will reduce transmission of pathogens including SARS CoV-2. This research aims to develop cell-based antimicrobial compositions with diverse class of antimicrobials to coat both biotic surfaces (hands) and abiotic surfaces (gloves) for persistent antimicrobial activity.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This SBIR Phase I project proposes to address the technical challenges in maintaining persistent antimicrobial activity on both biotic and abiotic surfaces against viral and bacterial targets including SARS CoV-2. The technical challenges include: (a) ability of antimicrobial compositions to persist on biotic and abiotic surfaces in the presence of organic content including proteins, lipids and cells as well as physical factors including sweat and mechanical forces; (b) achieving rapid inactivation of contaminating pathogens on complex surfaces such as hands and gloves; and (c) ensuring the biocompatibility of the compositions and removal with simple washing steps.  To address these challenges this proposed research aims to develop innovations in the following technical areas: (a) discovery of cellular compositions and process engineering to stabilize diverse antimicrobials and maintain rapid inactivation of pathogens (b) development of nature inspired designs for retaining cell-based antimicrobial compositions on skin surfaces to maintain persistent antimicrobial activity (c) engineering polymer compositions to retain cell-based compositions on abiotic surfaces and (d) engineer cellular compositions to achieve rapid inactivation of these pathogens. This may be achieved based on engineering affinity of the carrier compositions for pathogens as well as the release rate of antimicrobials from cell-based carriers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/21/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/13/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2036017</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gulustan</FirstName>
<LastName>Ozturk</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gulustan Ozturk</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[gozturk@carrisan.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000827371</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/21/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate>05/13/2021</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Zachary</FirstName>
<LastName>Bendiks</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Zachary Bendiks</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[zbendiks@carrisan.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000855497</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/13/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>CARRISAN TECHNOLOGIES INC.</Name>
<CityName>DAVIS</CityName>
<ZipCode>956186530</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9787648874</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2913 PRADO LN</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>VBGAKN1AR4M8</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CARRISAN TECHNOLOGIES INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Carrisan Technologies, Inc.]]></Name>
<CityName>Davis</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>956189615</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[28605 County Rd. 104]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8030</Code>
<Text>Chemical Technology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~255990</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The overall goal of this project was to develop surface coatings that give persistent antimicrobial activity on hands and gloves. To achieve this, we stabilized the antimicrobial agent chlorine using <em>Saccharomyces cerevisiae </em>cells which acted as a cell-based carrier of the chlorine. We then incorporated the chlorinated cells into surface coating formulations and tested the mechanical, chemical, and antimicrobial properties of the coatings. In total, we developed over 30 hand and glove coating formulations for evaluation.</p> <p>We developed hand coating formulations that showed promising abrasion resistance and water tolerance, and these coatings were easily removable with standard handwashing techniques. The chlorine content, and presumably the antimicrobial activity, of these formulations was stable over multiple weeks in refrigeration conditions. When applied to a skin model, these formulations exhibited strong antibacterial activity against <em>Escherichia coli </em>O157 and moderate antiviral activity against MS2 bacteriophage. Furthermore, the coatings were able to prevent cross-contamination of these microbes from hands to steel surfaces. &nbsp;</p> <p>The glove coatings we developed formed stable films that exhibited strong water tolerance and were resistant to stretching but were susceptible to wet abrasion. They also showed rapid and robust antibacterial activity against <em>E. coli </em>O157. However, the antiviral activity against MS2 bacteriophage was minimal.</p> <p>Our results demonstrate that chlorinated cell particles can be incorporated into stable surface coating formulations with commefcially available polymers and maintain their antimicrobial activity. This is a valuable proof of concept for this new technology, and our work will inform future endeavors to commercialize this technology and produce these formulations at an industrial scale. We also showed that these formulations can quickly and effectively neutralize bacterial target organisms, but more research is needed to optimize the technology to inactivate viral particles, especially for the glove coating formulations. These optimizations could include cell surface modifications to target viral particles, using different cell-based carriers, or using different antimicrobial agents. Further development of this technology will be valuable for the food production and service industries as well as the healthcare industry, where minimization of microbial contamination is critical for public health and safety. &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/16/2022<br>      Modified by: Zachary&nbsp;Bendiks</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The overall goal of this project was to develop surface coatings that give persistent antimicrobial activity on hands and gloves. To achieve this, we stabilized the antimicrobial agent chlorine using Saccharomyces cerevisiae cells which acted as a cell-based carrier of the chlorine. We then incorporated the chlorinated cells into surface coating formulations and tested the mechanical, chemical, and antimicrobial properties of the coatings. In total, we developed over 30 hand and glove coating formulations for evaluation.  We developed hand coating formulations that showed promising abrasion resistance and water tolerance, and these coatings were easily removable with standard handwashing techniques. The chlorine content, and presumably the antimicrobial activity, of these formulations was stable over multiple weeks in refrigeration conditions. When applied to a skin model, these formulations exhibited strong antibacterial activity against Escherichia coli O157 and moderate antiviral activity against MS2 bacteriophage. Furthermore, the coatings were able to prevent cross-contamination of these microbes from hands to steel surfaces.    The glove coatings we developed formed stable films that exhibited strong water tolerance and were resistant to stretching but were susceptible to wet abrasion. They also showed rapid and robust antibacterial activity against E. coli O157. However, the antiviral activity against MS2 bacteriophage was minimal.  Our results demonstrate that chlorinated cell particles can be incorporated into stable surface coating formulations with commefcially available polymers and maintain their antimicrobial activity. This is a valuable proof of concept for this new technology, and our work will inform future endeavors to commercialize this technology and produce these formulations at an industrial scale. We also showed that these formulations can quickly and effectively neutralize bacterial target organisms, but more research is needed to optimize the technology to inactivate viral particles, especially for the glove coating formulations. These optimizations could include cell surface modifications to target viral particles, using different cell-based carriers, or using different antimicrobial agents. Further development of this technology will be valuable for the food production and service industries as well as the healthcare industry, where minimization of microbial contamination is critical for public health and safety.                Last Modified: 10/16/2022       Submitted by: Zachary Bendiks]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
