<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Automated Assembly of Discrete Cellular Structures]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>254430.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>254430</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rajesh Mehta</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rmehta@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922174</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is the development of architected, cellular materials at large scales. Size constraints of 3D printing can be overcome by discrete assembly of modular, mass-produced parts. This approach benefits from incremental assembly, which eliminates scale limitations and enables best-practice manufacturing for reliable, low-cost part production, and interchangeability through a consistent assembly process across part types. Further, the system can be automated. Precision and repeatability are embedded in the parts themselves. This project will match state-of-the-art performance metrics while reducing reliance on fixed tooling, offering customization for user-defined products. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project will address issues of large-scale, digital manufacturing by introducing a new type of material based on modular, cellular units. In contrast to continuous, layer-based, additive deposition processes, this approach relies on discrete assembly. Here, global geometries are defined by local constraints, errors can be incrementally detected and corrected, heterogeneous parts can be joined, and parts can be repaired, reused, and recycled. The goals of this project are to define a material system (constituent material, unit cell geometry, and fastening solution) that can achieve high stiffness-to-weight ratios at low cost. Such properties do not currently exist in a single monolithic material; rather, they are achieved through expensive processes to shape traditional materials into complex geometries. These methods are labor-intensive and have significant capital expenditure for tooling. This project will demonstrate the ability of discrete lattice materials to match state-of-the-art while offering cost reductions through automation, reduction in factory overhead, and performance benefits unachievable with traditional methods. Analytical and numerical models will be used to project performance and cost at larger scales (greater than one hundred meters).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/01/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/01/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2036680</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>benjamin</FirstName>
<LastName>jenett</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>benjamin jenett</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[bej@mit.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000829173</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/01/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>DISCRETE LATTICE INDUSTRIES, LLC</Name>
<CityName>LAGUNA BEACH</CityName>
<ZipCode>926516969</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9493380569</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>31732 4TH AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>47</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA47</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>DLNZGZNCZBB7</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>DISCRETE LATTICE INDUSTRIES LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[DISCRETE LATTICE INDUSTRIES, LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>Laguna Beach</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>926516969</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[31732 4th Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>47</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA47</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8021</Code>
<Text>Materials Engineering</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~254430</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>In this project, we investigated the potential for a new type of lightweight, cellular material to used in a range of real-world products and applications, with the goal of reducing material use, waste, and embodied emissions of our built environment. Our technology enables the production of large scale cellular materials with novel properties such as high stiffness to weight ratio, with scalable, economic manufacturing enabled by mass manufacturing and robotic assembly. This is a platform technology with many potential applications, and a major accomplishment of the project was identifying a beachhead market and product.</p> <p>We will bring our technology to market in a consumer product which utilizes a significant amount of metal springs and polyurethane foam to provide support and comfort. These products are bulky, and are made up of many heterogeneous layers which are difficult to separate for recycling, and as a result the majority of these products end up in a landfill. Our technology can provide spring-like and foam-like properties by controlling the cellular geometry of parts made from a common engineering polymer. The value propositions include over 50% weight reduction, increased ventilation, greater sustainability, and mass customization.</p> <p>Through extensive customer discovery, we validated our hypothesized pain points related to material shortage, waste, and cost. We identified a go to market strategy as a B2B supplier for large, multi-national manufacturers which cannot develop such disruptive innovations internally. We now plan to move forward with product testing and validation, and low volume production. Our company will then expand our product line to adjacent markets, thus offering cost savings and environmental benefits across a number of industries.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/29/2022<br>      Modified by: Benjamin&nbsp;Jenett</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ In this project, we investigated the potential for a new type of lightweight, cellular material to used in a range of real-world products and applications, with the goal of reducing material use, waste, and embodied emissions of our built environment. Our technology enables the production of large scale cellular materials with novel properties such as high stiffness to weight ratio, with scalable, economic manufacturing enabled by mass manufacturing and robotic assembly. This is a platform technology with many potential applications, and a major accomplishment of the project was identifying a beachhead market and product.  We will bring our technology to market in a consumer product which utilizes a significant amount of metal springs and polyurethane foam to provide support and comfort. These products are bulky, and are made up of many heterogeneous layers which are difficult to separate for recycling, and as a result the majority of these products end up in a landfill. Our technology can provide spring-like and foam-like properties by controlling the cellular geometry of parts made from a common engineering polymer. The value propositions include over 50% weight reduction, increased ventilation, greater sustainability, and mass customization.  Through extensive customer discovery, we validated our hypothesized pain points related to material shortage, waste, and cost. We identified a go to market strategy as a B2B supplier for large, multi-national manufacturers which cannot develop such disruptive innovations internally. We now plan to move forward with product testing and validation, and low volume production. Our company will then expand our product line to adjacent markets, thus offering cost savings and environmental benefits across a number of industries.          Last Modified: 09/29/2022       Submitted by: Benjamin Jenett]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
