<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[STTR Phase I:  Polymer Surfactant Therapy for Acute Respiratory Distress Syndrome (COVID-19)]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>256000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>256000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Erik Pierstorff</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>epiersto@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922165</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Technology Transfer (STTR) Phase I project will be to develop a first-in-kind therapeutic for treatment of Acute Respiratory Distress Syndrome (ARDS) as well as potentially other severe respiratory conditions that are characterized by high rates of mortality, morbidity, and hospitalization time. ARDS causes deactivation of the lungs’ surfactant, which is responsible for keeping the lung structure inflated and dry. This causes inadequate blood oxygenation and mutli-organ failure without invasive mechanical ventilation. ARDS is believed to account for 7% of the world’s ICU beds and can be caused by many root causes, including both direct lung injuries (i.e. bacterial/viral pneumonia) and indirect lung injuries (i.e. trauma). In the case of the pandemic, current data suggests that 14% of COVID-19 cases require hospitalization. Of these patients, 1 in 3 will develop ARDS, reducing their chance of survival to 60%. In a normal year there are 3 million ARDS cases globally (220k US) that are highly resource intensive (avg. $82k treatment cost), which presents a considerable financial burden on patients and healthcare systems. A therapeutic treatment would reduce patient deaths and frequency of chronic complications.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed project will develop a different approach to ARDS treatment via a synthetic Polymer Lung Surfactant (PLS) technology. This PLS technology overcomes shortcomings of previously attempted therapies as it is engineered to be safely used in the body, highly surface-active (lower surface tension), water-soluble (prepared in injectable aqueous suspension), and resistant to protein deactivation. Suspended in solution, PLS is evenly distributed in the lungs of mechanically ventilated patients. When PLS reaches the alveoli, it forms a gas-permeable micelle monolayer that mimics the function of human lung surfactant without being deactivated.  Doing so re-inflates the alveoli while reducing fluid accumulation and inflammation so that blood oxygenation can be restored. Building upon promising PLS safety/efficacy proof-of-concept data, specific aim #1 of this project will optimize delivery parameters in mice that have been induced with ARDS by differing root causes (infection vs. acid-aspiration). Specific aim #2 will use iodine-labeled PLS to generate distribution and clearance data in mice from delivery to several days post-treatment. This data will be used to optimize key delivery and PLS parameters to ensure that maximum efficacy is sustained for several days.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/08/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/08/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2036125</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>You-Yeon</FirstName>
<LastName>Won</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>You-Yeon Won</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[yywon@ecn.purdue.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000386647</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/08/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Davis</FirstName>
<LastName>Arick</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>Q</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Davis Q Arick</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[davis.arick@spirrowtherapeutics.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000780083</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/08/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>SPIRO THERAPEUTICS LLC</Name>
<CityName>WEST LAFAYETTE</CityName>
<ZipCode>479061171</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3177508879</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>132 VIGO CT</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IN04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>JJAGX5G85B16</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SPIRROW THERAPEUTICS LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Kurz Purdue Technology Center]]></Name>
<CityName>West Lafayette</CityName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>479064182</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1281 Win Hentschel Blvd]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IN04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1505</Code>
<Text>STTR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1982</Code>
<Text>BIOLOGICAL CHEMISTRY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~256000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong id="docs-internal-guid-e74826a9-7fff-893e-b060-16aa23b147ec" style="font-weight: normal;"> <p style="line-height: 1.2; margin-top: 0pt; margin-bottom: 8pt;" dir="ltr"><span style="font-size: 12pt; font-family: 'Times New Roman'; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">Every year nearly 200,000 adults in the US (3 worldwide) are diagnosed with acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS). Described as "like drowning from within," ARDS causes impaired lung function stemming from surfactant deactivation that can be caused by infection (COVID-19, pneumonia, sepsis, etc.) and/or physical injury (burns, car accidents, near-drowning, etc.). Unfortunately, there are currently no approved therapeutic treatments for these patients, which results in high risk of death (~40% on average) and high risk of long-term complications among survivors due to the invasive nature of current care. This poses a significant burden on both societies and healthcare systems around the world.&nbsp;</span></p> <p style="line-height: 1.2; margin-top: 0pt; margin-bottom: 8pt;" dir="ltr"><span style="font-size: 12pt; font-family: 'Times New Roman'; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">To address this unmet medical need, Spirrow Therapeutics has developed a first-in-kind polymer lung surfactant (PLS) that is intended to safely mimic the function of human lung surfactant while remaining immune to the deactivation mechansim of ARDS that hinders natural lung surfactant from functioning. Prior research performed in small animal models has demonstrated a promising safety and efficacy profile for PLS as a potential surfactant replacement therapy (SRT) that could potentially improve quality of care for patients with ARDS, with the hope being that risk of death, chronic complications, and time in intensive care could one day be reduced.</span></p> <p style="line-height: 1.2; margin-top: 0pt; margin-bottom: 8pt;" dir="ltr"><span style="font-size: 12pt; font-family: 'Times New Roman'; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">To further this pursuit, Spirrow Therapeutics sought to expand upon prior research into safety and efficacy of PLS as well as study the clearance of this surfactant from the body after being administered. With the support of the NSF, this research was conducted in partnership with the University of Michigan and Purdue University using small animal models (mice). Data collected from these studies was consistent with prior research and provides further support for the promising efficacy and safety profile of PLS. A number of key findings from this study also highlight key areas for future study that will be investigated in future R&amp;D activities.</span></p> <p style="line-height: 1.2; margin-top: 0pt; margin-bottom: 8pt;" dir="ltr"><span style="font-size: 12pt; font-family: 'Times New Roman'; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">The efficacy study conducted at the University of Michigan included animal models of acute lung injury induced by infection and by physical injury to assess whether root cause of ARDS influenced efficacy. A single dose of PLS treatment showed significant effect on the trajectory of injury symptoms in both animal models for an extended period of time.&nbsp;</span></p> <p style="line-height: 1.2; margin-top: 0pt; margin-bottom: 8pt;" dir="ltr"><span style="font-size: 12pt; font-family: 'Times New Roman'; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">The clearance mechanism study conducted at Purdue University involved labeling the PLS micelles with a fluorescent agent so that they could be tracked over the 2-month testing period. PLS was then administered at different dose concentrations into the lungs of healthy mice. Collected data suggests a time and dose dependent lung retention profile where nanoparticles are cleared from the lungs by macrophage and translocation through the blood-air barrier. Nanoparticle accumulation in secondary organs was not significant except in the liver where hepatobiliary clearance occurs. In the end, administered PLS nanoparticles were mainly excreted from the body as feces. All treated mice were confirmed to remain healthy, showing normal respiration, a steady growth in body weight, and a table lung weight throughout the period.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</span></p> </strong></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/21/2022<br>      Modified by: Davis&nbsp;Q&nbsp;Arick</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Every year nearly 200,000 adults in the US (3 worldwide) are diagnosed with acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS). Described as "like drowning from within," ARDS causes impaired lung function stemming from surfactant deactivation that can be caused by infection (COVID-19, pneumonia, sepsis, etc.) and/or physical injury (burns, car accidents, near-drowning, etc.). Unfortunately, there are currently no approved therapeutic treatments for these patients, which results in high risk of death (~40% on average) and high risk of long-term complications among survivors due to the invasive nature of current care. This poses a significant burden on both societies and healthcare systems around the world.  To address this unmet medical need, Spirrow Therapeutics has developed a first-in-kind polymer lung surfactant (PLS) that is intended to safely mimic the function of human lung surfactant while remaining immune to the deactivation mechansim of ARDS that hinders natural lung surfactant from functioning. Prior research performed in small animal models has demonstrated a promising safety and efficacy profile for PLS as a potential surfactant replacement therapy (SRT) that could potentially improve quality of care for patients with ARDS, with the hope being that risk of death, chronic complications, and time in intensive care could one day be reduced. To further this pursuit, Spirrow Therapeutics sought to expand upon prior research into safety and efficacy of PLS as well as study the clearance of this surfactant from the body after being administered. With the support of the NSF, this research was conducted in partnership with the University of Michigan and Purdue University using small animal models (mice). Data collected from these studies was consistent with prior research and provides further support for the promising efficacy and safety profile of PLS. A number of key findings from this study also highlight key areas for future study that will be investigated in future R&amp;D activities. The efficacy study conducted at the University of Michigan included animal models of acute lung injury induced by infection and by physical injury to assess whether root cause of ARDS influenced efficacy. A single dose of PLS treatment showed significant effect on the trajectory of injury symptoms in both animal models for an extended period of time.  The clearance mechanism study conducted at Purdue University involved labeling the PLS micelles with a fluorescent agent so that they could be tracked over the 2-month testing period. PLS was then administered at different dose concentrations into the lungs of healthy mice. Collected data suggests a time and dose dependent lung retention profile where nanoparticles are cleared from the lungs by macrophage and translocation through the blood-air barrier. Nanoparticle accumulation in secondary organs was not significant except in the liver where hepatobiliary clearance occurs. In the end, administered PLS nanoparticles were mainly excreted from the body as feces. All treated mice were confirmed to remain healthy, showing normal respiration, a steady growth in body weight, and a table lung weight throughout the period.               Last Modified: 11/21/2022       Submitted by: Davis Q Arick]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
