<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Measuring and Mapping Pain Intensity onto a 3D Image of the Human Body]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>256000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>256000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Alastair Monk</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>amonk@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924392</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project will significantly improve the way clinicians and researchers measure, study and treat pain.  Chronic pain affects 20% of U.S. adults and costs $600 billion annually. Opioids are often the first treatment option offered to patients with chronic pain. Currently pain is assessed using simplistic, subjective and generalized visual/verbal scales (1-10) with little ability to localize the origin. It is essential for clinicians and medical researchers to have calibrated and accurate measures of pain to assist patients in determining the underlying disease and directing patients to the most effective therapies. This project will develop a new biomedical tool to quantify pain data for multimodal treatment plans to potentially minimize opioid use. This tool will improve quality of life for people suffering from chronic pain and help those on opioids find better therapies. Furthermore, it will help clinicians with varied levels of training and experience achieve the highest level of exam skill.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project will digitize a physical exam by capturing palpation location and pressure and patient pain expression via multiple biosensors to create a personalized “contour” map of pain intensity onto a 3D image of the human body. This comprehensive and calibrated data set can then be used to assist clinicians in developing a more accurate differential diagnosis for the underlying pain condition. This project will advance the hardware and software components for future integration with augmented reality and artificial intelligence modules.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/18/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/18/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2036496</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Andru</FirstName>
<LastName>Zeller</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Andru Zeller</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[andru@painscansystem.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000816604</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/18/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>JUST HEALTH CARE, LTD. CO.</Name>
<CityName>ALBUQUERQUE</CityName>
<ZipCode>871082633</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5052660888</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>202 MORNINGSIDE DR SE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Mexico</StateName>
<StateCode>NM</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NM01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>J7RBG32CCSF3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>JUST HEALTH CARE LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[JUST HEALTH CARE, LTD. CO.]]></Name>
<CityName>Albuquerque</CityName>
<StateCode>NM</StateCode>
<ZipCode>871104906</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1804 Carlisle Blvd NE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Mexico</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NM01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>066E</Code>
<Text>INSTRUMENTATION &amp; DIAGNOSTICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>090E</Code>
<Text>Chem/Bio and Physical Diagnostics</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~256000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Pain was&nbsp;<em>invisible</em>. Until&nbsp;<em>now</em>.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>PainScan helps solve the challenge inherent in assessing and treating complex pain. 50 million adults in the United States suffer with chronic pain and pain is the #1 reason for medical visits.&nbsp;Even with state-of-the-art radiographic tools like CT scans and MRIs, assessing complex pain is challenging for doctors and often frustrating for patients.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>PainScan helps patients and their doctors shorten the path to accurate diagnosis and effective treatment by&nbsp;producing a vivid 3D representation of pain intensity on a personalized human digital replica. The resulting PainScans capture the patient&rsquo;s pain picture more clearly and visibly than any verbal explanation or the 1-10 pain scale ever could.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>With our patented system, patients no longer need to worry if their healthcare providers believe the pain they are experiencing is real. Instead, their healthcare team can focus on diagnosing those underlying conditions that would likely produce the patterns seen on the patient&rsquo;s PainScan.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Chronic pain disparately impacts women, elderly, and rural community members. Additionally, people of color receive lower quality care for pain treatment. Pain impacts relationships, work, mental health, and finances. We are dedicated to addressing health disparities in chronic pain assessment and treatment, helping ensure inclusivity and positive impact for all communities that will benefit from this new technology.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Thanks in large part to this National Science Foundation (NSF) SBIR Phase I grant, we have been able to assemble a team who believe in the mission, have the necessary technical skills, and look forward to bringing PainScan to the healthcare market.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><em>What is PainScan?</em></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>PainScan is a digital health solution that automates pain assessment to augment pain diagnosis. PainScan engenders a collaborative process between doctor and patient with both participants working together during a physical exam. The shared experience of generating the pain map ensures that the doctor and patient are both on the same page, sharing the same understanding of the full pain picture and validating the patients pain experience. PainScan lets doctors&nbsp;<em>see</em>&nbsp;what their patients&nbsp;<em>feel</em>.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><em>How does PainScan work?</em></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The PainScan system is comprised of three components:</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>-&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;a computer vision camera system that utilizes machine learning algorithms to locate clinician touch and place it accurately onto a&nbsp;life-like 3D image of the patient, called a digital twin</p> <p>-&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;a clinician glove with sensors that measure the pressure applied during each touch</p> <p>-&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;A hand-held device which the patient squeezes to silently share the pain level each time a clinician gently touches</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>As the clinician examines the patient, data and images are analyzed by proprietary software to find where the clinician is touching, how hard the clinician is touching, and how much pain the patient is feeling. At the end of an exam, all points touched and the patient&rsquo;s pain levels at each location are displayed on the digital twin for the clinician and patient to see.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The patient and doctor are then provided a 3D version of the painscan which can also be shared with other doctors and specialists, similar to sharing x-rays. However, PainScans are non-invasive and non-radiological. Just as x-rays made bones visible, PainScan now makes pain visible.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><em>What was funded by NSF?</em></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>NSF funds helped develop the software system and the method to identify the location of touch. Prior to this funded work there were no known methods to automatically track clinician touch and reproduce it on a&nbsp;3D digital twin&nbsp;of the patient.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Our team outlined ambitious R&amp;D goals for this NSF SBIR Phase I Award. Many technical, business and customer discovery milestones were accomplished. The NSF Phase I investment helped show that the core technical risk of mapping clinician touch onto a digital twin of the patient is attainable. The accuracy of our version 1 system is not yet sufficient for clinical use, but the prototype developed is a compelling proof of concept for digitizing the medical physical exam.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The benefits of PainScan include personal precise 3D pain assessment, longitudinal calibrated pain tracking, and comparison of pain patterns across large groups of people to improve diagnostic categories and find effective therapies. PainScan is the evolutionary next step in pain assessment technology, providing a comprehensive, modern software platform and human body database that will be adapted over time to include multiple pain biosensors.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>With further investment, the system will be improved to a level of accuracy that offers clinicians, patients, and researchers the ability to confidently capture and document a holistic and comprehensive view of the full pain picture. We thank the NSF community for this opportunity to develop our vision for improved pain assessment for the benefit of so many people suffering with chronic pain, in the United States and around the world.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/14/2022<br>      Modified by: Andru&nbsp;Zeller</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2036496/2036496_10717817_1646192648874_PainScanOverview--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2036496/2036496_10717817_1646192648874_PainScanOverview--rgov-800width.jpg" title="PainScan System Overview"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2036496/2036496_10717817_1646192648874_PainScanOverview--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="PainScan System Overview"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">PainScan let's doctors SEE what patients FEEL.</div> <div class="imageCredit">John Mierzwa and Andru Zeller</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Andru&nbsp;Zeller</div> <div class="imageTitle">PainScan System Overview</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2036496/2036496_10717817_1646192511412_ExamMockup--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2036496/2036496_10717817_1646192511412_ExamMockup--rgov-800width.jpg" title="PainScan Use Case - Physical Exam"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2036496/2036496_10717817_1646192511412_ExamMockup--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="PainScan Use Case - Physical Exam"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">PainScan is a new biomedical device used during a physical exam to measure and map pain intensity onto a 3D image of the human body.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Andru Zeller</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Andru&nbsp;Zeller</div> <div class="imageTitle">PainScan Use Case - Physical Exam</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2036496/2036496_10717817_1646192920755_PainMap3combined--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2036496/2036496_10717817_1646192920755_PainMap3combined--rgov-800width.jpg" title="PainScan Longitudinal Pain Assessment"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2036496/2036496_10717817_1646192920755_PainMap3combined--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="PainScan Longitudinal Pain Assessment"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Imagine being able to see how you feel your pain, then how your pain is revealed in a full collaborative physical exam, and then how your pain changes after an effective therapy is applied. PainScan offers patients and clinicians the opportunity to see pain patterns change over time.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Andru Zeller</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Andru&nbsp;Zeller</div> <div class="imageTitle">PainScan Longitudinal Pain Assessment</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2036496/2036496_10717817_1646193331558_PainScanComparisonPatientReportandExam--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2036496/2036496_10717817_1646193331558_PainScanComparisonPatientReportandExam--rgov-800width.jpg" title="PainScan Comparison - Patient Report and Exam"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2036496/2036496_10717817_1646193331558_PainScanComparisonPatientReportandExam--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="PainScan Comparison - Patient Report and Exam"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Chronic pain signals can be misleading, causing frustration and confusion for patients and doctors. With PainScan, a report of heel pain can reveal a broader pain pattern up the entire leg. This widens the focus to include pathologies that would otherwise remain invisible and untreated.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Andru Zeller</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Andru&nbsp;Zeller</div> <div class="imageTitle">PainScan Comparison - Patient Report and Exam</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2036496/2036496_10717817_1647096465678_version1systemaccuracy--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2036496/2036496_10717817_1647096465678_version1systemaccuracy--rgov-800width.jpg" title="PainScan Version 1 System Accuracy"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2036496/2036496_10717817_1647096465678_version1systemaccuracy--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="PainScan Version 1 System Accuracy"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">PainScan Version 1 Software and Analytic System shows a cumulative average error of 7.4cm. Target goal was 7cm. This demonstrates solid proof of concept for the success of the project and helps identify specific factors that need further research and development to improve mapping accuracy.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Aaron Martinez</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Andru&nbsp;Zeller</div> <div class="imageTitle">PainScan Version 1 System Accuracy</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Pain was invisible. Until now.     PainScan helps solve the challenge inherent in assessing and treating complex pain. 50 million adults in the United States suffer with chronic pain and pain is the #1 reason for medical visits. Even with state-of-the-art radiographic tools like CT scans and MRIs, assessing complex pain is challenging for doctors and often frustrating for patients.     PainScan helps patients and their doctors shorten the path to accurate diagnosis and effective treatment by producing a vivid 3D representation of pain intensity on a personalized human digital replica. The resulting PainScans capture the patient’s pain picture more clearly and visibly than any verbal explanation or the 1-10 pain scale ever could.     With our patented system, patients no longer need to worry if their healthcare providers believe the pain they are experiencing is real. Instead, their healthcare team can focus on diagnosing those underlying conditions that would likely produce the patterns seen on the patient’s PainScan.     Chronic pain disparately impacts women, elderly, and rural community members. Additionally, people of color receive lower quality care for pain treatment. Pain impacts relationships, work, mental health, and finances. We are dedicated to addressing health disparities in chronic pain assessment and treatment, helping ensure inclusivity and positive impact for all communities that will benefit from this new technology.     Thanks in large part to this National Science Foundation (NSF) SBIR Phase I grant, we have been able to assemble a team who believe in the mission, have the necessary technical skills, and look forward to bringing PainScan to the healthcare market.     What is PainScan?     PainScan is a digital health solution that automates pain assessment to augment pain diagnosis. PainScan engenders a collaborative process between doctor and patient with both participants working together during a physical exam. The shared experience of generating the pain map ensures that the doctor and patient are both on the same page, sharing the same understanding of the full pain picture and validating the patients pain experience. PainScan lets doctors see what their patients feel.     How does PainScan work?     The PainScan system is comprised of three components:     -        a computer vision camera system that utilizes machine learning algorithms to locate clinician touch and place it accurately onto a life-like 3D image of the patient, called a digital twin  -        a clinician glove with sensors that measure the pressure applied during each touch  -        A hand-held device which the patient squeezes to silently share the pain level each time a clinician gently touches     As the clinician examines the patient, data and images are analyzed by proprietary software to find where the clinician is touching, how hard the clinician is touching, and how much pain the patient is feeling. At the end of an exam, all points touched and the patient’s pain levels at each location are displayed on the digital twin for the clinician and patient to see.      The patient and doctor are then provided a 3D version of the painscan which can also be shared with other doctors and specialists, similar to sharing x-rays. However, PainScans are non-invasive and non-radiological. Just as x-rays made bones visible, PainScan now makes pain visible.     What was funded by NSF?     NSF funds helped develop the software system and the method to identify the location of touch. Prior to this funded work there were no known methods to automatically track clinician touch and reproduce it on a 3D digital twin of the patient.     Our team outlined ambitious R&amp;D goals for this NSF SBIR Phase I Award. Many technical, business and customer discovery milestones were accomplished. The NSF Phase I investment helped show that the core technical risk of mapping clinician touch onto a digital twin of the patient is attainable. The accuracy of our version 1 system is not yet sufficient for clinical use, but the prototype developed is a compelling proof of concept for digitizing the medical physical exam.     The benefits of PainScan include personal precise 3D pain assessment, longitudinal calibrated pain tracking, and comparison of pain patterns across large groups of people to improve diagnostic categories and find effective therapies. PainScan is the evolutionary next step in pain assessment technology, providing a comprehensive, modern software platform and human body database that will be adapted over time to include multiple pain biosensors.     With further investment, the system will be improved to a level of accuracy that offers clinicians, patients, and researchers the ability to confidently capture and document a holistic and comprehensive view of the full pain picture. We thank the NSF community for this opportunity to develop our vision for improved pain assessment for the benefit of so many people suffering with chronic pain, in the United States and around the world.       Last Modified: 03/14/2022       Submitted by: Andru Zeller]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
