<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase II:  Collaboration, Creativity and Computational Thinking - A Cooperative Music Tinkering Game]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1000000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1000000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Cooperative Agreement</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rajesh Mehta</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rmehta@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922174</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase II project is to enable the learning of Computational Thinking, which is widely viewed as the new literacy of the 21st Century and has become an important initiative in educational research, policy, and practice and represents a specific set of problem-solving skills applicable in any domain to create solutions. Teaching this kind of problem solving is difficult; problems in the real world are complex and ill-defined and require the ability to apply different strategies to be solved. The proposed solution provides learners a space to practice productive struggle with the concepts of algorithms and trying new solutions in concert with development of communication skills. Moreover, this learning environment will support students as they practice additional skills critical to their future, including collaboration, teamwork, leveraging one another’s expertise to find a solution, and communicating ideas. This platform will scale to accommodate deep learning experiences in interdisciplinary problem-solving, and will revolutionize game-based learning through advances in physical/digital integration and collaborative problem solving. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase II project will research, design and develop a flexible physical/digital learning platform targeting students in grades 3-5, focusing on learning collaborative problem solving, computational thinking, tinkering and debugging practices. Key technology objectives include development of a machine learning-powered adaptive game environment, refinement of the hardware system design and development of the teacher dashboard tools necessary to enable real-time teaching support and assessment. The adaptive learning environment will enable learners to participate in collaborative problem-solving while engaging in Computational Thinking practices that promote productive struggle, critical thinking and reflection. This project will advance the field of education technology by pushing innovation in designing collaborative connected play (digital/physical) solutions for classroom considerations and use; designing adaptivity that supports learners at the individual and group level; reimagining teacher tools for real-time support, insights and ability to manage multiple groups simultaneously; and developing best approaches in tangible interfaces to promote learning.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/08/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/08/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>CoopAgrmnt</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2036394</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Anna</FirstName>
<LastName>Jordan-Douglass</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Anna Jordan-Douglass</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[anna@makefullystudios.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000780731</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/08/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>MAKEFULLY, LLC</Name>
<CityName>KANSAS CITY</CityName>
<ZipCode>641102822</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8164906458</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5508 TROOST AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MO05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>E5KBKKMW48D6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MAKEFULLY LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Makefully, LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>Kansas City</CityName>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>641141300</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[7140 Wornall Road, Suite 203]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MO05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5373</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase II</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1707</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED LEARNING TECHNOLOGIES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~1000000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-c43b5a1e-7fff-784b-5e47-a846767ed102"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Makefully's NSF SBIR Phase I and II funding was used to develop a physical+digital learning environment designed for students in grades 3-5 with a focus on collaborative problem solving, computational thinking, tinkering and debugging practices. Our Phase II work built upon design and development research done in Phase I to: 1) determine the ideal play pattern(s) to achieve the learning goals, while also being a compelling consumer product; 2) create an elegant, scalable hardware solution; 3) find ways to seamlessly integrate play across a system comprising a phsyical board game environment, smart player pieces, and real-time multiplayer digital play; and 4) work with teachers to determine the critical areas of focus and tools to best support use in the classroom. While we designed the product to be easy-to-use in the classroom, we also designed the product for informal learning and home use.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Our R&amp;D led to two innovations: 1) a proprietary game system, which can support a vast array of multiplayer games across many curricular areas, and 2) </span><span>Making the Band</span><span>, a first of its kind multiplayer co-op smart board game RPG.</span></p> <p>Making the Band engages players in collaborative problem solving through a series of story-driven puzzles. The puzzles engage players together in problems that practice sequence, debugging, and problem decomposition, while also requiring collaboration and teamwork. Designed to be interdisciplinary, Making the Band integrates learning goals across computational thinking, collaborative problem solving, and ELA standards in reading, speaking and listening.&nbsp;</p> <p>During our Phase II research, we conducted a feasibility study in a school with 60 3rd-5th grade students, and six teacher facilitators. The goal of the study was to evaluate the product's feasibility for ease of use in the classroom, to collect teacher feedback on the system and what they observed of their students during play, and to collect teacher insights on the product and its use in the classroom. In interviews with teachers who observed and facilitated game play during the pilot, they reported high levels of engagement, including robust communication and collaboration, and that the game was very successful at including students at different levels in the problem solving. The teachers also noticed that the game evoked listening, understanding, and empathy among the students, all skills we value greatly but didn't specifically design for, making for an unexpected positive outcome and something we'll continue to emphasize. Overall teachers found the product to be effective at engaging students in collaborative problem solving, and at involving learners at all levels, including those that aren't often engaged in other types of activities. Students surveys also reported awareness that the game accommodated a wide range of players, and enjoyed the puzzles and the physical and digital connectedness of the system. Overall, our feasibility study helped to affirm where we assumed more refinements were needed on the hardware, but proved to be a highly engaging problem solving environment.&nbsp;</p> <p>Thanks to the NSF SBIR program, we have been able to develop a project that advances the field of learning games and educational technology by pushing innovation in designing collaborative connected play solutions for both classroom and home considerations; designing content and feedback systems that support the learner at the individual and group level; and designing best approaches in tangible interfaces to promote learning. We are well-suited to distribute this game for formal and informal learning environments, and are also excited to explore additional partner opportunities that leverage our novel game system.</p> <div><span><br /></span></div> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/18/2023<br>      Modified by: Anna&nbsp;Jordan-Douglass</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2036394/2036394_10746169_1692393897373_MTB_Poster_ForUpload--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2036394/2036394_10746169_1692393897373_MTB_Poster_ForUpload--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Making the Band"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2036394/2036394_10746169_1692393897373_MTB_Poster_ForUpload--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Making the Band"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Making the Band</div> <div class="imageCredit">Makefully</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Anna&nbsp;Jordan-Douglass</div> <div class="imageTitle">Making the Band</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2036394/2036394_10746169_1692393947551_MTB_Characters_ForUpload--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2036394/2036394_10746169_1692393947551_MTB_Characters_ForUpload--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Making the Band"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2036394/2036394_10746169_1692393947551_MTB_Characters_ForUpload--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Making the Band"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Making the Band</div> <div class="imageCredit">Makefully</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Anna&nbsp;Jordan-Douglass</div> <div class="imageTitle">Making the Band</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   Makefully's NSF SBIR Phase I and II funding was used to develop a physical+digital learning environment designed for students in grades 3-5 with a focus on collaborative problem solving, computational thinking, tinkering and debugging practices. Our Phase II work built upon design and development research done in Phase I to: 1) determine the ideal play pattern(s) to achieve the learning goals, while also being a compelling consumer product; 2) create an elegant, scalable hardware solution; 3) find ways to seamlessly integrate play across a system comprising a phsyical board game environment, smart player pieces, and real-time multiplayer digital play; and 4) work with teachers to determine the critical areas of focus and tools to best support use in the classroom. While we designed the product to be easy-to-use in the classroom, we also designed the product for informal learning and home use. Our R&amp;D led to two innovations: 1) a proprietary game system, which can support a vast array of multiplayer games across many curricular areas, and 2) Making the Band, a first of its kind multiplayer co-op smart board game RPG.  Making the Band engages players in collaborative problem solving through a series of story-driven puzzles. The puzzles engage players together in problems that practice sequence, debugging, and problem decomposition, while also requiring collaboration and teamwork. Designed to be interdisciplinary, Making the Band integrates learning goals across computational thinking, collaborative problem solving, and ELA standards in reading, speaking and listening.   During our Phase II research, we conducted a feasibility study in a school with 60 3rd-5th grade students, and six teacher facilitators. The goal of the study was to evaluate the product's feasibility for ease of use in the classroom, to collect teacher feedback on the system and what they observed of their students during play, and to collect teacher insights on the product and its use in the classroom. In interviews with teachers who observed and facilitated game play during the pilot, they reported high levels of engagement, including robust communication and collaboration, and that the game was very successful at including students at different levels in the problem solving. The teachers also noticed that the game evoked listening, understanding, and empathy among the students, all skills we value greatly but didn't specifically design for, making for an unexpected positive outcome and something we'll continue to emphasize. Overall teachers found the product to be effective at engaging students in collaborative problem solving, and at involving learners at all levels, including those that aren't often engaged in other types of activities. Students surveys also reported awareness that the game accommodated a wide range of players, and enjoyed the puzzles and the physical and digital connectedness of the system. Overall, our feasibility study helped to affirm where we assumed more refinements were needed on the hardware, but proved to be a highly engaging problem solving environment.   Thanks to the NSF SBIR program, we have been able to develop a project that advances the field of learning games and educational technology by pushing innovation in designing collaborative connected play solutions for both classroom and home considerations; designing content and feedback systems that support the learner at the individual and group level; and designing best approaches in tangible interfaces to promote learning. We are well-suited to distribute this game for formal and informal learning environments, and are also excited to explore additional partner opportunities that leverage our novel game system.               Last Modified: 08/18/2023       Submitted by: Anna Jordan-Douglass]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
