<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Offline Edge Learning Management System (COVID-19)]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>255221.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>255221</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Diane Hickey</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dhickey@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928875</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project will be to provide a solution for the students and schools with an urgent need for a remote learning solution.  An estimated 85% of families on rural Native American reservations do not have high-speed internet access. The need for a remote learning solution is especially pressing given the COVID-19 pandemic which is requiring many schools to implement online or hybrid learning models. If students are not able to participate in these new models, it is likely that they will have substantially lower achievement levels than their peers who do have access to remote learning. The proposed project advances a technology to enable online learning without access to high-speed internet.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project will advance a new system to support digital learning with lower access to high-speed internet.  First, this project will explore edge computing in innovation by building a new learning management system that has intelligent edge nodes capable of providing a complete student learning experience without access to a central server. Second, it will improve pedagogical approaches in this environment, supporting digital learning across limited or no access modalities, including print-to-digital workflows.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/13/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/13/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2036344</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Collin</FirstName>
<LastName>Sellman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Collin Sellman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[collin@firelinescience.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000802924</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/13/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>FIRELINE SCIENCE LLC</Name>
<CityName>TEMPE</CityName>
<ZipCode>852831815</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7203503667</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5501 S COLLEGE AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AZ09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>V5UKB8W2KTB1</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>FIRELINE SCIENCE LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[FIRELINE SCIENCE LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>Tempe</CityName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>852831815</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5501 South College Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AZ09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1707</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED LEARNING TECHNOLOGIES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~255221</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-8aa9c1e8-7fff-6fa7-b724-6bb9a74fd401"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Tufts University and the FCC estimate that there are 12 to 17 million school aged children in the United States without access to the internet at home. The FCC's Broadband Task Force reports 70 percent of teachers in the United States regularly assign homework that requires access to the internet. This difference between students who can do digital homework and those who can not given their lack of reliable home access is called the 'homework gap'. The homework gap has been called 'the cruelest part of the digital divide' given that the at-risk students who could benefit the most from digital homework are also those who are more likely to live in unconnected households. This is particularly a problem in rural areas like those in Indian Country. The homework gap results in lower student achievement. A 2020 study found the lack of home internet can have significant negative impacts on academic success, college admissions, and career opportunities even when controlling for socioeconomic status.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Our Phase I R&amp;D focused on building a new, innovative solution to bridge the digital homework gap for students who lack home internet. In Phase I, we successfully implemented the architectural foundation (termed the Offline Operating System or OOS) to support a consistent remote learning experience across connected, degraded, and unconnected internet scenarios on any modern device. This foundation uses a hybrid cloud-edge architecture where edge devices can work with limited or no internet access. Student work and teacher feedback is shared through a distributed version control system which manages updates and conflict resolution. Edge nodes can sync by briefly connecting to the internet or, in cases where this is not possible, by automatically building a digital backpack that can be sent between students and the school using physical devices like a USB drive. The system includes a complete digital homework workflow including bi-directional communication between students and teachers to enable authentic assessment and multiple student revisions as is required for instructional models like Project Based Learning (PBL).</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>We also implemented the initial version of our intelligent edge system which provides students with research-based smart prompts to optimize independent learning while not connected to the internet. The initial smart prompts are based on recent growth mindset digital intervention research. The pedagogical approach for the intelligent edge system was based on research into current practices related to homework and print/digital coursework. The system also includes several new, innovative digital learning tools which are optimized for offline learning including a complete interactive Python programming environment for Career and Technical Education which can work offline and requires no local environment. The platform is now at minimum viability to support pilot schools with the necessary administrative tasks and all core workflows functional, and with several meaningful integrations demonstrable. </span></p> <div><span><br /></span></div> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/09/2022<br>      Modified by: Collin&nbsp;Sellman</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   Tufts University and the FCC estimate that there are 12 to 17 million school aged children in the United States without access to the internet at home. The FCC's Broadband Task Force reports 70 percent of teachers in the United States regularly assign homework that requires access to the internet. This difference between students who can do digital homework and those who can not given their lack of reliable home access is called the 'homework gap'. The homework gap has been called 'the cruelest part of the digital divide' given that the at-risk students who could benefit the most from digital homework are also those who are more likely to live in unconnected households. This is particularly a problem in rural areas like those in Indian Country. The homework gap results in lower student achievement. A 2020 study found the lack of home internet can have significant negative impacts on academic success, college admissions, and career opportunities even when controlling for socioeconomic status.    Our Phase I R&amp;D focused on building a new, innovative solution to bridge the digital homework gap for students who lack home internet. In Phase I, we successfully implemented the architectural foundation (termed the Offline Operating System or OOS) to support a consistent remote learning experience across connected, degraded, and unconnected internet scenarios on any modern device. This foundation uses a hybrid cloud-edge architecture where edge devices can work with limited or no internet access. Student work and teacher feedback is shared through a distributed version control system which manages updates and conflict resolution. Edge nodes can sync by briefly connecting to the internet or, in cases where this is not possible, by automatically building a digital backpack that can be sent between students and the school using physical devices like a USB drive. The system includes a complete digital homework workflow including bi-directional communication between students and teachers to enable authentic assessment and multiple student revisions as is required for instructional models like Project Based Learning (PBL).    We also implemented the initial version of our intelligent edge system which provides students with research-based smart prompts to optimize independent learning while not connected to the internet. The initial smart prompts are based on recent growth mindset digital intervention research. The pedagogical approach for the intelligent edge system was based on research into current practices related to homework and print/digital coursework. The system also includes several new, innovative digital learning tools which are optimized for offline learning including a complete interactive Python programming environment for Career and Technical Education which can work offline and requires no local environment. The platform is now at minimum viability to support pilot schools with the necessary administrative tasks and all core workflows functional, and with several meaningful integrations demonstrable.                Last Modified: 08/09/2022       Submitted by: Collin Sellman]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
