<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[STTR Phase I:  Manufacturing of Enhanced Composites via Interlaminar Incorporation of CNT/Epoxy Nanoscaffolds using Genetic Algorithm Assisted Machine Learning and Neural Networks]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>256000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>256000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ela Mirowski</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>emirowsk@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922936</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Technology Transfer Program (STTR) Phase I project is to improve strength and stiffness of carbon fiber reinforced composites in aerospace, automotive, energy, and other applications. Carbon fiber reinforced polymer (CFRP) materials are used to reduce weight without compromising the strength of structural components, but because they are built layer by layer, they have certain weaknesses.  This project will advance a new approach to to enable production of higher performance automobiles, airplanes, turbines and more. The process can be highly automated, cost-effective, and seamlessly integrated with existing CFRP manufacturing. This can be integrated into existing processes. The continued development of stronger and lighter composite parts will also have an impact in related fields including renewable energy resources.  The technology holds the promise of reducing operating costs, improving fuel efficiency, and decreasing emissions. This will lead to significant impacts on national security in advanced manufacturing.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The strong technical innovation in the project is identifying the use of electrospinning to coat a prepreg CFRP roll with carbon nanotube (CNT)/epoxy nanofilaments that can form a CNT-reinforced bonding surface that is square meters in area and just tens of microns in thickness. This project will address the longstanding weak through-thickness interlaminar strength of CFRP prepreg laminates using a low materials-cost and highly automated process. The project will expand on the primary innovation to develop a theoretical understanding of multiscale nanoscaffold-enhanced CFRP advanced composites through genetic algorithm assisted machine learning (GAML) and artificial neural networks (ANN). The objective is to establish an experimentally and computationally supported GAML framework for determining optimal processing parameters and structural features. Results will lead to better optimization tools in the design of new composite materials, and the development of instrumentation supporting the emergence of new weight and cost saving opportunities in the composite industry for complex systems.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/05/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/16/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041, 47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2036490</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Hamid</FirstName>
<LastName>Dalir</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Hamid Dalir</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[hdalir@iupui.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000819698</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/05/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Asel</FirstName>
<LastName>Habarakada Liyanage</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Asel Habarakada Liyanage</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[asel.habarakada@mitechnologysolutions.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000868440</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/16/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Amanda</FirstName>
<LastName>Siegel</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Amanda P Siegel</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[apsiegel@iupui.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000829944</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/05/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate>12/16/2021</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>MULTISCALE INTEGRATED TECHNOLOGY SOLUTIONS LLC</Name>
<CityName>INDIANAPOLIS</CityName>
<ZipCode>462025191</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3172784430</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>723 W MICHIGAN ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[# 260]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IN07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>CJHAL88LM4H8</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MULTISCALE INTEGRATED TECHNOLOGY SOLUTIONS LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Indiana University-Purdue University Indianapolis]]></Name>
<CityName>Indianapolis</CityName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>462025195</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[799 W Michigan St, ET 126]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IN07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1505</Code>
<Text>STTR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8037</Code>
<Text>Advanced Manufacturing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8611</Code>
<Text>Energy Efficiency and End Use</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~256000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Most composite structures are comprised of carbon fiber reinforced polymer (CFRP) prepreg layers, which results in light vehicle parts and components that satisfy mechanical strength requirements and stability and safety standards. However, without a breakthrough in advanced lightweighting technologies, it will be difficult to further improve component production efficiencies and further reduce weight to satisfy the ever-increasing fuel economy and gas emission standards while improving safety, performance and lowering cost. Among CFRP prepreg structural enhancement techniques, use of nanocomposites has recently attracted great attention because of their superior mechanical properties coupled with their ultra-compact foot-print. However, difficulties with their preparation in large quantities and poor compatibility with CFRP prepreg resin systems, as well as their high cost, have limited their practical applications in the composite industry. In this NSF STTR Phase I project, electrospun carbon nanotubes (CNT)/epoxy nanocomposite nanoscaffolds were designed and optimized via genetic algorithm assisted machine learning (GAML) and were incorporated in between CFRP prepreg layers for composite enhancement. An artificial neural network (ANN) was employed to optimize the stiffness and strength of the interposed layers to accelerate the discovery and development of novel composites for further lightweighting. The objective was to establish an experimentally and computationally supported GAML framework for designing the processing parameters and structural features of a novel multiscale nanoscaffold enhanced (NSE) CFRP composite. By directly depositing CNT/epoxy electrospun optimized nanoscaffolds onto carbon fiber (CF)/epoxy prepregs, multiscale improved interfaces and interlayer bonding was achieved, opening new avenues for cost effective enhancement of composite laminates while using extremely low amounts of nanocomposites.</p> <p>This Small Business Innovation Research Phase I project has contributed to the composite prepreg industry by 1) preparation of highly oriented CNT/epoxy nanofilaments for manufacturing interlayer nanoscaffolds, 2) addressing and solving the longstanding weak through-thickness interlaminar strength of CFRP prepreg laminates, and 3) developing a theoretical understanding of multiscale nanoscaffold-enhanced CFRP advanced composites. The results of the specific tasks described in this project led to better optimization and development of instrumentation supporting the emergence of new weight and cost saving opportunities in composite industry for complex systems with significant impacts on national security and the quality of daily life.</p> <p>The general design of the proposed technology is applicable to multiple areas of aerospace, defense, wind energy, automotive, motorsports, and sporting goods. This project will bring the key underlying innovation closer to commercialization upon its completion through collaboration opportunities with larger commercial part and prepreg suppliers through technology licensing, joint-development, or equity participation for commercialization. Stronger and lighter composite parts and components will reduce landfill waste, lower vehicle operating costs, improve miles per gallon ratings, and lead to reduced CO2 emissions improving the national and international quality of life.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/29/2022<br>      Modified by: Hamid&nbsp;Dalir</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Most composite structures are comprised of carbon fiber reinforced polymer (CFRP) prepreg layers, which results in light vehicle parts and components that satisfy mechanical strength requirements and stability and safety standards. However, without a breakthrough in advanced lightweighting technologies, it will be difficult to further improve component production efficiencies and further reduce weight to satisfy the ever-increasing fuel economy and gas emission standards while improving safety, performance and lowering cost. Among CFRP prepreg structural enhancement techniques, use of nanocomposites has recently attracted great attention because of their superior mechanical properties coupled with their ultra-compact foot-print. However, difficulties with their preparation in large quantities and poor compatibility with CFRP prepreg resin systems, as well as their high cost, have limited their practical applications in the composite industry. In this NSF STTR Phase I project, electrospun carbon nanotubes (CNT)/epoxy nanocomposite nanoscaffolds were designed and optimized via genetic algorithm assisted machine learning (GAML) and were incorporated in between CFRP prepreg layers for composite enhancement. An artificial neural network (ANN) was employed to optimize the stiffness and strength of the interposed layers to accelerate the discovery and development of novel composites for further lightweighting. The objective was to establish an experimentally and computationally supported GAML framework for designing the processing parameters and structural features of a novel multiscale nanoscaffold enhanced (NSE) CFRP composite. By directly depositing CNT/epoxy electrospun optimized nanoscaffolds onto carbon fiber (CF)/epoxy prepregs, multiscale improved interfaces and interlayer bonding was achieved, opening new avenues for cost effective enhancement of composite laminates while using extremely low amounts of nanocomposites.  This Small Business Innovation Research Phase I project has contributed to the composite prepreg industry by 1) preparation of highly oriented CNT/epoxy nanofilaments for manufacturing interlayer nanoscaffolds, 2) addressing and solving the longstanding weak through-thickness interlaminar strength of CFRP prepreg laminates, and 3) developing a theoretical understanding of multiscale nanoscaffold-enhanced CFRP advanced composites. The results of the specific tasks described in this project led to better optimization and development of instrumentation supporting the emergence of new weight and cost saving opportunities in composite industry for complex systems with significant impacts on national security and the quality of daily life.  The general design of the proposed technology is applicable to multiple areas of aerospace, defense, wind energy, automotive, motorsports, and sporting goods. This project will bring the key underlying innovation closer to commercialization upon its completion through collaboration opportunities with larger commercial part and prepreg suppliers through technology licensing, joint-development, or equity participation for commercialization. Stronger and lighter composite parts and components will reduce landfill waste, lower vehicle operating costs, improve miles per gallon ratings, and lead to reduced CO2 emissions improving the national and international quality of life.           Last Modified: 03/29/2022       Submitted by: Hamid Dalir]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
