<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Low-Cost High-Efficiency Solar Desalination]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>256000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>256000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rajesh Mehta</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rmehta@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922174</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I award is through the development of a low-cost desalination technology directly powered by sunlight.  Combining cutting-edge nanotechnology, concentrating solar power, and innovative and compact design, the technology can convert any saline water or wastewater to potable quality fresh water using sunlight as the only energy source.  The research will evaluate a novel reactor design that allows the thermal energy converted from sunlight to be recovered and reused multiple times for desalination and purification of saline water, all in one compact, low cost device. If successful, this technology could provide a low-cost, energy-efficient, and environmentally sustainable solution to a wide range of water challenges: providing reliable and affordable drinking water for communities that lack access to fresh water or reliable power supplies; supplying clean water at off-grid industrial production sites; recovering clean water from municipal and industrial wastewaters; minimizing discharge of contaminants-laden waste streams to the environment. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This SBIR Phase I project aims to develop a high efficiency, low cost desalination technology directly powered by sunlight. The research pursues two innovations that greatly enhance the performance of a novel desalination process: nanophotonics enhanced solar membrane distillation (NESMD). First, a novel membrane module design (patent pending) could achieve multi-effect solarthermal membrane distillation in a compact, low-cost module; second, coupling the multi-effect module design with a low-cost solar concentrator would deliver high intensity solar irradiation necessary to drive a multi-effect process while maintaining high membrane flux. The goal is to increase in the gained output ratio (GOR) by a factor of 5. The high GOR value will reduce the specific energy consumption for desalination, and enhance water production rate per irradiated area.  Proposed research includes (1) constructing a multi-effect NESMD module that demonstrates multi-stage heat recovery, (2) modeling the nonlinear, and coupled heat, momentum, and mass transfer in the module, (3) determining the effect of solar concentration, and (4) determining the effect of operating conditions and feed water quality.  Model simulations will guide design, prototype testing, and optimization, while experimental research results will be used to improve the process model. Technoeconomic analysis will compare the proposed technology with existing desalination technologies.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/19/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/16/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041, 47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2036470</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Floyd</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John A Floyd</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jallenfloyd@me.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000826939</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/19/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate>09/16/2022</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ruikun</FirstName>
<LastName>Xin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ruikun Xin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[rxin@solmem.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000877004</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/16/2022</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>SolMem LLC</Name>
<CityName>SUGAR LAND</CityName>
<ZipCode>774785521</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7138420199</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>101 PARKLANE BLVD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[STE 103]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>22</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX22</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>CB2XJ3SWNWA5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SOLMEM LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[SolMem LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>Houston</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>770051303</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2617 Bissonnet St., Local Office]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1238</Code>
<Text>TECH FOR SUSTAINABLE ENVIRONMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~256000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The overall objective of the proposed SBIR Phase I study is to assess and demonstrate the performance of a prototype solar desalination system using the novel solar multi-effectsmembrane distillation (SolarMEMD, previously called ME-NESMD) module coupled with aparabolic trough to achieve at least a 300% increase in energy efficency (i.e., Gain output ratio, GOR) with respect to single effect NESMD.</p> <p>To realize the proposed objective, first, our group developed a standard operating procedure (SOP) to fabricate the SolarMEMD membrane roll and membrane module. In addition, two bench scale systems, one indoor and one outdoor, were built to investigate the impacts of design parameters, operation parameters, and environmental conditions on the performance of SolarMEMD process. The indoor system allows the implementation of experimentsunder controlled experimental conditions, and the causal effects of design parameters, operational parameters, and environmental conditions on SolarMEMD process were systematically investigated. The outdoor system was used to validate and demonstratethe feasibility of using SolarMEMD process in desalination under real environmental conditions. The experimental data collected from both systems were then used to calibrate and validate our heat and mass transfer model, and generate empirical equations that correlate the design and operational parameters with the performance of SolarMEMD systems under different environmental conditions. Last, such correlation equations were used in the technoeconomic analysis and optimization of the designand operation parameters to achieve the best levelized cost of water (LCOW).</p> <p>Our Phase I research results show great potential of the SolarMEMD technology in desalination. The research conducted also lays a solid foundation towards the scale-up ofthe SolarMEMD process. The experimental data from the indoor system show that the SolarMEMD system can handle feed water with a wide range of salinity up to 200,000 PPM. More importantly, more than a 300% increase in GOR from the highest GOR value reportedin the single effect NESMD process when coupled with a solar concentrating device was also successfully demonstrated: using concentrated sunlight at a concentration ratio of 2.5,we were able to achieve a gain-output-ratio (GOR) of 3.42, while the highest GOR reportedfor a single-effect process is only 0.746.&nbsp;In addition, the reactor scale process modeladequately describes the coupled heat and mass transfer processes; the GOR andmembrane flux predicted for a wide range of operating conditions agree well withexperimental data. Lastly, using optimized design and operation conditions and prediction ofsystem performance based on statistical correlation analyses, the calculated LCOW of the SolarMEMD technology ranges from $1.29/m<sup>3</sup> to 3.36/m<sup>3</sup>, depending on the supply chain (i.e., different membrane material price) and environmental conditions (i.e., covering a feedwater salinity from 5,000 to 185,000 PPM and an ambient irradiance from 0.15 to 1 sun).This is significantly lower than our competing technologies (i.e., deep well injection, and mechanical vapor recompression system with a similar treatment capacity).</p> <p>In summary, our group has developed the first solarthermal desalination prototype system (i.e., SolarMEMD) with in-situ energy (i.e., heat) generation, enery recovery, and water recovery (i.e., vapor condensation). After fully scaled up, our SolarMEMD system is expected to have alower physical footprint than the current state of art solar desalination system does. The high affordability as well as theexcellent energy efficiency, water recovery, and water quality of our SolarMEMD system will make it a good candidate insolving the water crisis issue.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/15/2022<br>      Modified by: Ruikun&nbsp;Xin</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2036470/2036470_10723196_1671122175445_SolMemLabScaleSolarMEMDSystem--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2036470/2036470_10723196_1671122175445_SolMemLabScaleSolarMEMDSystem--rgov-800width.jpg" title="SolMem Lab Scale SolarMEMD System"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2036470/2036470_10723196_1671122175445_SolMemLabScaleSolarMEMDSystem--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="SolMem Lab Scale SolarMEMD System"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The SolMem Lab Scale SolarMEMD System is comprised of a parabolic trough collector and a treatment skid (i.e., pumps, sensors, etc.).</div> <div class="imageCredit">SolMem LLC</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Ruikun&nbsp;Xin</div> <div class="imageTitle">SolMem Lab Scale SolarMEMD System</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The overall objective of the proposed SBIR Phase I study is to assess and demonstrate the performance of a prototype solar desalination system using the novel solar multi-effectsmembrane distillation (SolarMEMD, previously called ME-NESMD) module coupled with aparabolic trough to achieve at least a 300% increase in energy efficency (i.e., Gain output ratio, GOR) with respect to single effect NESMD.  To realize the proposed objective, first, our group developed a standard operating procedure (SOP) to fabricate the SolarMEMD membrane roll and membrane module. In addition, two bench scale systems, one indoor and one outdoor, were built to investigate the impacts of design parameters, operation parameters, and environmental conditions on the performance of SolarMEMD process. The indoor system allows the implementation of experimentsunder controlled experimental conditions, and the causal effects of design parameters, operational parameters, and environmental conditions on SolarMEMD process were systematically investigated. The outdoor system was used to validate and demonstratethe feasibility of using SolarMEMD process in desalination under real environmental conditions. The experimental data collected from both systems were then used to calibrate and validate our heat and mass transfer model, and generate empirical equations that correlate the design and operational parameters with the performance of SolarMEMD systems under different environmental conditions. Last, such correlation equations were used in the technoeconomic analysis and optimization of the designand operation parameters to achieve the best levelized cost of water (LCOW).  Our Phase I research results show great potential of the SolarMEMD technology in desalination. The research conducted also lays a solid foundation towards the scale-up ofthe SolarMEMD process. The experimental data from the indoor system show that the SolarMEMD system can handle feed water with a wide range of salinity up to 200,000 PPM. More importantly, more than a 300% increase in GOR from the highest GOR value reportedin the single effect NESMD process when coupled with a solar concentrating device was also successfully demonstrated: using concentrated sunlight at a concentration ratio of 2.5,we were able to achieve a gain-output-ratio (GOR) of 3.42, while the highest GOR reportedfor a single-effect process is only 0.746. In addition, the reactor scale process modeladequately describes the coupled heat and mass transfer processes; the GOR andmembrane flux predicted for a wide range of operating conditions agree well withexperimental data. Lastly, using optimized design and operation conditions and prediction ofsystem performance based on statistical correlation analyses, the calculated LCOW of the SolarMEMD technology ranges from $1.29/m3 to 3.36/m3, depending on the supply chain (i.e., different membrane material price) and environmental conditions (i.e., covering a feedwater salinity from 5,000 to 185,000 PPM and an ambient irradiance from 0.15 to 1 sun).This is significantly lower than our competing technologies (i.e., deep well injection, and mechanical vapor recompression system with a similar treatment capacity).  In summary, our group has developed the first solarthermal desalination prototype system (i.e., SolarMEMD) with in-situ energy (i.e., heat) generation, enery recovery, and water recovery (i.e., vapor condensation). After fully scaled up, our SolarMEMD system is expected to have alower physical footprint than the current state of art solar desalination system does. The high affordability as well as theexcellent energy efficiency, water recovery, and water quality of our SolarMEMD system will make it a good candidate insolving the water crisis issue.       Last Modified: 12/15/2022       Submitted by: Ruikun Xin]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
