<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Determine Performance Characteristics During Cultivation of Living Organisms in a Novel Single-Use Horizontal Modular and Pressurizable Microbial Fermentor]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>256000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>256000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Erik Pierstorff</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>epiersto@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922165</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is to significantly improve the ability to generate biological pharmaceuticals. The biopharmaceutical industry is working to grow specific genetically engineered microbial cells that will produce a vaccine, injectable protein, or other products. There is a pressing need to culture unique microbes, starting from small scale batches, that rapidly scale to commercially viable batch sizes with high product output. A pressurized horizontal fermentor supports the industry’s drive towards single-use bags for microbial fermentation, as single-use fermentors lower operating costs and reduce cross-contamination that can result in loss of an entire batch. This scalable, single-use fermentor should achieve higher yields and allow drug producers to produce kilogram quantities of protein in a more cost-effective manner. This innovative, flexible, pressurizable, horizontal modular design will decrease time-to-market for vaccines, therapeutic proteins or other microbially manufactured products, from both small and large biologics producers, to combat global infectious, and other diseases, at reduced operating costs, saving lives.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed project will advance the knowledge of how microbial cells are cultivated in a horizontal, pressurized single-use bag fermentor. The knowledge gained will validate microbial production using a modular design that provides flexibility to adjust the capacity of the system, without significant facility modifications or cost.  An initial prototype demonstrated highly encouraging results regarding fast mixing times, proper scalable power input, and excellent oxygen mass transfer.  The design to be refined here has the potential to transform the biologics manufacturing industry by impacting the ability to generate high cell densities and reduce the cost of microbial manufacturing. Research objectives are to demonstrate: a fully developed design with the heat removal capacity required of high cell density fermentation (currently unachievable using existing industry vertical single-use fermentor designs); a pressurized bag system that can achieve oxygen transfer rates needed for high density cultures; and a scalable format that allows for rapid scaling to 3000 liters.  A fully functioning test fermentor will be built and evaluated using both computational fluid dynamics analysis and laboratory testing of culture conditions. Experimental work will evaluate high agitation impellers, high gas flows, gas sparger designs, and system structural elements.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/09/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/27/2023</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041, 47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2036270</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ernest</FirstName>
<LastName>Stadler</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ernest L Stadler</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ernest.stadler@newhorizonbiotech.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000820215</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/09/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>NEW HORIZON BIOTECH INC</Name>
<CityName>NAZARETH</CityName>
<ZipCode>180648500</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6105703096</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>500 HEMLOCK LN</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>MNT9W1VJ6D17</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NEW HORIZON BIOTECH INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>MNT9W1VJ6D17</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[NEW HORIZON BIOTECH INC]]></Name>
<CityName>Bethlehem</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>180154731</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[116 Research Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8038</Code>
<Text>Biotechnology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~256000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="western"><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="font-family: Arial, sans-serif;"><span lang="en-US">New Horizon Biotech, Inc.</span></span></span><span style="font-family: Arial, sans-serif;"> (NHB), seeks to disrupt a conservative industry by innovating the way an essential class of worldwide products are</span><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="font-family: Arial, sans-serif;"><span lang="en-US"> produced</span></span></span><span style="font-family: Arial, sans-serif;">, making drugs more rapidly and widely available, in a more sustainable way with single-use (SU) bioprocess equipment.</span></p> <p class="western"><span style="font-family: Arial, sans-serif;">NHB's novel approach challenges the biopharmaceutical industry's conventional development and production methods. </span><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="font-family: Arial, sans-serif;"><span lang="en-US">Th</span></span></span><span style="font-family: Arial, sans-serif;">is industry conventionally manufactures in product-specific, dedicated facilities. Expanding drug production capacity means more and larger facilities, requiring more land and resources. </span><span style="font-family: Arial, sans-serif;">Moreover, conventional production equipment, specifically fermentors and bioreactors, grow larger, vertically, within the facility, to meet production volume. Like facilities, the equipment is custom designed and built. Cleaning the equipment between drug batches consumes vast amounts of water. The complexity associated with such facility construction and the bespoke nature of such equipment is engineering-, construction-, and, ultimately, time-intensive thus limiting the ability to reproducibly distribute manufacturing globally ? for example ? in the face of regional, or global pandemics.</span></p> <p class="western"><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="font-family: Arial, sans-serif;"><span lang="en-US">NHB</span></span></span><span style="font-family: Arial, sans-serif;">?s bioprocess equipment product design literally turns conventional thinking on its side, by re-imaging volumetric production expansion using horizontally oriented bioreactors and </span><span style="font-family: Arial, sans-serif;">fermentor</span><span style="font-family: Arial, sans-serif;">s (Figure 1)</span><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="font-family: Arial, sans-serif;"><span lang="en-US"> instead of maintaining the vertical paradigm. With equipment oriented horizontally, it </span></span></span><span style="font-family: Arial, sans-serif;">can be modularized and, thereby, standardized. Standardization is further achieved by adapting highly engineered polymers and components into a disposable culture bag pressurized vessel (Figure 2)</span><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="font-family: Arial, sans-serif;"><span lang="en-US"> where bulk drug product is produced</span></span></span><span style="font-family: Arial, sans-serif;">. The biopharmaceutical industry has already embraced this disposable concept, known as single-use (SU) technologies. The integrated combination of horizontal fermentation and cell culture equipment with SU pressurizable culture bags is expected to drive the adoption of a greater number of flexible, modular, more sustainable production facilities which can be rapidly reproduced around the world.</span></p> <p class="western"><span style="font-family: Arial, sans-serif;">Equivalent performance will be a critical first step toward industry acceptance of this paradigm shift and would demonstrate NHB's novel horizontal fermentor could match or exceed the performance of conventional vertical fermentors. Performance testing was conducted without and with microbes to characterize the SU fermentor design and its microbial growth capabilities.</span></p> <p><span style="font-family: Arial, sans-serif;">In order to generate performance data, a</span><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="font-family: Arial, sans-serif;"><span lang="en-US"> 50L pre-production prototype version of NHB?s </span></span></span><span style="font-family: Arial, sans-serif;">SU fermentor, capable of running microbial fermentations, was built under an NSF SBIR Phase 1 project (</span><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="font-family: Arial, sans-serif;"><span lang="en-US">2036270</span></span></span><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="font-family: Arial, sans-serif;"><span lang="en-US">)</span></span></span><span style="font-family: Arial, sans-serif;">. This project consisted of three phases: (a) design, (b) build, and (c) test; design and build phases were pre-requisites for being able to test.</span></p> <p class="western"><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="font-family: Arial, sans-serif;"><span lang="en-US">The design phase focused on the three subsystems: (1) the </span></span></span><span style="font-family: Arial, sans-serif;">modular </span><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="font-family: Arial, sans-serif;"><span lang="en-US">stainless steel fermentor/bioreactor vessel </span></span></span><span style="font-family: Arial, sans-serif;">(Figure 3) </span><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="font-family: Arial, sans-serif;"><span lang="en-US">where the bag would be installed</span></span></span><span style="font-family: Arial, sans-serif;"> and pressurized; (2) the SU fermentor bag (Figure 4&amp;5)</span><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="font-family: Arial, sans-serif;"><span lang="en-US"> in which the microbial fermentation would take place</span></span></span><span style="font-family: Arial, sans-serif;">; and (3) the automation (measurement and control) system used for maintaining the fermentation process environment within the fermentor bag where the organisms would be grown. The pre-production prototype design, including electrical schematics, control programs, mechanical drawing and bills of material for each of the subsystems was successfully completed.</span></p> <p><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="font-family: Arial, sans-serif;"><span lang="en-US">With the design phase completed the build phase was implemented, i.e. parts were </span></span></span><span style="font-family: Arial, sans-serif;">ordered, and services were contracted. The pre-production 50L system was assembled, instrumented and programmed. Test protocols were written, testing space was obtained, and testing resources were secured.</span></p> <p><span style="font-family: Arial, sans-serif;">Upon completion of the manufacturing, the test phase began. Performance testing was conducted without and with microbes to characterize the SU fermentor design and its microbial growth capabilities. </span><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="font-family: Arial, sans-serif;"><span lang="en-US">Organism-free wet-testing yielded performance data for power density (watts/L), volumetric oxygen mass transfer (k</span></span></span><span style="color: #000000;"><sub><span style="font-family: Arial, sans-serif;"><span lang="en-US">L</span></span></sub></span><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="font-family: Arial, sans-serif;"><span lang="en-US">a) and mixing time (seconds). Power d</span></span></span><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="font-family: Arial, sans-serif;"><span lang="en-US">ensity</span></span></span><span style="font-family: Arial, sans-serif;">, mixing times and k</span><sub><span style="font-family: Arial, sans-serif;">L</span></sub><span style="font-family: Arial, sans-serif;">a values </span><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="font-family: Arial, sans-serif;"><span lang="en-US">for the 50L pre-production </span></span></span><span style="font-family: Arial, sans-serif;">were comparable to those obtained on an early stage prototype. </span><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="font-family: Arial, sans-serif;"><span lang="en-US">A computational fluid dynamics model was </span></span></span><span style="font-family: Arial, sans-serif;">developed, and simulations were run to predict shear and velocity distribution data; again, the results were comparable to the early stage prototype. Heat transfer capacity (UA) was determined from flow and temperature measurements on the cooling system during the microbial experiments and was sufficient to maintain culture temperature throughout the growth of the microbes. Two microbial fermentations were run demonstrating the ability to culture microbes to substantial cell densities.</span></p> <p class="western"><span style="font-family: Arial, sans-serif;">NHB</span><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="font-family: Arial, sans-serif;"><span lang="en-US">, is </span></span></span><span style="font-family: Arial, sans-serif;">pleased with the results of the project having demonstrated success for the first time ever controlling pressure up to 5 psig in a SU bag (Figure 6).</span> <span style="font-family: Arial, sans-serif;">The design phase yielded a robust design and the establishment of a reliable supply chain to produce the SU </span><span style="font-family: Arial, sans-serif;">fermentor</span><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="font-family: Arial, sans-serif;"><span lang="en-US"> product. Test results </span></span></span><span style="font-family: Arial, sans-serif;">demonstrated performance characteristics of this modular, pressurizable, horizontal system that will allow NHB to enter the market with a novel world class scalable system that will offer substantial benefits to the end users regarding productivity output and lower cost facilities. The end goal will be to lower biologic drug costs to the public as new and existing therapies are produced in large quantities. NHB expects to collaborate with a BioPharm producer to further evaluate the system culturing proprietary cell lines specifically targeting a biologic product such as a therapeutic protein or vaccine.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/09/2023<br>      Modified by: Ernest&nbsp;L&nbsp;Stadler</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2036270/2036270_10716632_1696876782445_Figure1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2036270/2036270_10716632_1696876782445_Figure1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 1"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2036270/2036270_10716632_1696876782445_Figure1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 1"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">NHB SU Horizontal Fermentor: (a) 3D CAD Model (b) As-Built Production Prototype</div> <div class="imageCredit">New Horizon Biotech Inc.</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Ernest&nbsp;L&nbsp;Stadler</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 1</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2036270/2036270_10716632_1696876906478_Figure2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2036270/2036270_10716632_1696876906478_Figure2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 2"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2036270/2036270_10716632_1696876906478_Figure2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 2"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Single 50L Pressurizable Bag Retention Vessel (BRV)</div> <div class="imageCredit">New Horizon Biotech Inc.</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Ernest&nbsp;L&nbsp;Stadler</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 2</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2036270/2036270_10716632_1696877025785_Figure3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2036270/2036270_10716632_1696877025785_Figure3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 3"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2036270/2036270_10716632_1696877025785_Figure3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 3"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Flexibility: Three 50L modules combined for 150L capacity, the fermentation bag is made larger to fit the higher capacity.</div> <div class="imageCredit">New Horizon Biotech Inc.</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Ernest&nbsp;L&nbsp;Stadler</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 3</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2036270/2036270_10716632_1696877132910_Figure4--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2036270/2036270_10716632_1696877132910_Figure4--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 4"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2036270/2036270_10716632_1696877132910_Figure4--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 4"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">3D Model of Single Module 50L Pressurizable Fermentor Bag</div> <div class="imageCredit">New Horizon Biotech Inc.</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Ernest&nbsp;L&nbsp;Stadler</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 4</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2036270/2036270_10716632_1696877272440_Figure5--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2036270/2036270_10716632_1696877272440_Figure5--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 5"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2036270/2036270_10716632_1696877272440_Figure5--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 5"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Actual 50L SU pressurizable fermentation bag for 50L Bag Retention Vessel.</div> <div class="imageCredit">New Horizon Biotech Inc.</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Ernest&nbsp;L&nbsp;Stadler</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 5</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2036270/2036270_10716632_1696877401406_Figure6--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2036270/2036270_10716632_1696877401406_Figure6--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 6"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2036270/2036270_10716632_1696877401406_Figure6--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 6"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">50L Pressurized SU fermentor system culturing microbes in laboratory</div> <div class="imageCredit">New Horizon Biotech Inc.</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Ernest&nbsp;L&nbsp;Stadler</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 6</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[New Horizon Biotech, Inc. (NHB), seeks to disrupt a conservative industry by innovating the way an essential class of worldwide products are produced, making drugs more rapidly and widely available, in a more sustainable way with single-use (SU) bioprocess equipment. NHB's novel approach challenges the biopharmaceutical industry's conventional development and production methods. This industry conventionally manufactures in product-specific, dedicated facilities. Expanding drug production capacity means more and larger facilities, requiring more land and resources. Moreover, conventional production equipment, specifically fermentors and bioreactors, grow larger, vertically, within the facility, to meet production volume. Like facilities, the equipment is custom designed and built. Cleaning the equipment between drug batches consumes vast amounts of water. The complexity associated with such facility construction and the bespoke nature of such equipment is engineering-, construction-, and, ultimately, time-intensive thus limiting the ability to reproducibly distribute manufacturing globally ? for example ? in the face of regional, or global pandemics. NHB?s bioprocess equipment product design literally turns conventional thinking on its side, by re-imaging volumetric production expansion using horizontally oriented bioreactors and fermentors (Figure 1) instead of maintaining the vertical paradigm. With equipment oriented horizontally, it can be modularized and, thereby, standardized. Standardization is further achieved by adapting highly engineered polymers and components into a disposable culture bag pressurized vessel (Figure 2) where bulk drug product is produced. The biopharmaceutical industry has already embraced this disposable concept, known as single-use (SU) technologies. The integrated combination of horizontal fermentation and cell culture equipment with SU pressurizable culture bags is expected to drive the adoption of a greater number of flexible, modular, more sustainable production facilities which can be rapidly reproduced around the world. Equivalent performance will be a critical first step toward industry acceptance of this paradigm shift and would demonstrate NHB's novel horizontal fermentor could match or exceed the performance of conventional vertical fermentors. Performance testing was conducted without and with microbes to characterize the SU fermentor design and its microbial growth capabilities.  In order to generate performance data, a 50L pre-production prototype version of NHB?s SU fermentor, capable of running microbial fermentations, was built under an NSF SBIR Phase 1 project (2036270). This project consisted of three phases: (a) design, (b) build, and (c) test; design and build phases were pre-requisites for being able to test. The design phase focused on the three subsystems: (1) the modular stainless steel fermentor/bioreactor vessel (Figure 3) where the bag would be installed and pressurized; (2) the SU fermentor bag (Figure 4&amp;5) in which the microbial fermentation would take place; and (3) the automation (measurement and control) system used for maintaining the fermentation process environment within the fermentor bag where the organisms would be grown. The pre-production prototype design, including electrical schematics, control programs, mechanical drawing and bills of material for each of the subsystems was successfully completed.  With the design phase completed the build phase was implemented, i.e. parts were ordered, and services were contracted. The pre-production 50L system was assembled, instrumented and programmed. Test protocols were written, testing space was obtained, and testing resources were secured.  Upon completion of the manufacturing, the test phase began. Performance testing was conducted without and with microbes to characterize the SU fermentor design and its microbial growth capabilities. Organism-free wet-testing yielded performance data for power density (watts/L), volumetric oxygen mass transfer (kLa) and mixing time (seconds). Power density, mixing times and kLa values for the 50L pre-production were comparable to those obtained on an early stage prototype. A computational fluid dynamics model was developed, and simulations were run to predict shear and velocity distribution data; again, the results were comparable to the early stage prototype. Heat transfer capacity (UA) was determined from flow and temperature measurements on the cooling system during the microbial experiments and was sufficient to maintain culture temperature throughout the growth of the microbes. Two microbial fermentations were run demonstrating the ability to culture microbes to substantial cell densities. NHB, is pleased with the results of the project having demonstrated success for the first time ever controlling pressure up to 5 psig in a SU bag (Figure 6). The design phase yielded a robust design and the establishment of a reliable supply chain to produce the SU fermentor product. Test results demonstrated performance characteristics of this modular, pressurizable, horizontal system that will allow NHB to enter the market with a novel world class scalable system that will offer substantial benefits to the end users regarding productivity output and lower cost facilities. The end goal will be to lower biologic drug costs to the public as new and existing therapies are produced in large quantities. NHB expects to collaborate with a BioPharm producer to further evaluate the system culturing proprietary cell lines specifically targeting a biologic product such as a therapeutic protein or vaccine.          Last Modified: 10/09/2023       Submitted by: Ernest L Stadler]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
