<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Enhanced Lithium Isotope Separation]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>256000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>272000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ela Mirowski</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>emirowsk@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922936</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project will be a secure domestic supply of isotopes.  The initial target isotope for production is lithium-7-hydroxide for use in US light-water nuclear reactors. Currently the only source of this critical material is China or Russia and so the supply is susceptible to disruptions that would cripple the US electrical generating capability.  A cost-effective method to enrich very large quantities of lithium-7 is also required for the introduction of next-generation nuclear reactor technology.  Molten salt reactors will deliver inherently-safe, environmentally friendly, carbon-free base load electrical power generation.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project provides an innovative approach to enriching lithium-7.  The concept is to develop a liquid-liquid method for lithium isotope separation that will work with an innovative high-speed counter current chromatography (HSCCC) system.  All commercial HSCCC suppliers (UK and China) build their bobbins by winding tubing around a shaft.  The sides of the bobbins have the inlet and outlet fittings attached.  This restricts the bobbins to only having a single inlet and outlet and having only a single tubing 'style' on a bobbin.  Using 3-D printing to manufacture bobbins enables flexibility in design and manufacture while lowering cost.  In this project, 3-D printing will enable bobbins with different configurations to be manufactured and tested quicker and cheaper than the current conventional tube winding method enabling the bobbin configurations to be quickly adapted alongside the liquid-liquid method extractant/diluent formulations to optimize performance criteria.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/04/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/16/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2036545</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gordon</FirstName>
<LastName>Jarvinen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gordon D Jarvinen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[gdjarvinen@gmail.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000829776</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/04/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>MOLTEN SALT SOLUTIONS, LLC</Name>
<CityName>SANTA FE</CityName>
<ZipCode>875074072</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5056700232</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3900 PASEO DEL SOL STE D33</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Mexico</StateName>
<StateCode>NM</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NM03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NTLRX4XZHJK3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MOLTEN SALT SOLUTIONS, LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Santa Fe Business Incubator]]></Name>
<CityName>Santa Fe</CityName>
<StateCode>NM</StateCode>
<ZipCode>875074072</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3900 Paseo del Sol]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Mexico</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NM03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8037</Code>
<Text>Advanced Manufacturing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8611</Code>
<Text>Energy Efficiency and End Use</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~272000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This Small Business Innovation Research Phase I project resulted in the development of a novel liquid-liquid extraction method to enrich lithium isotopes. This method was developed to be compatible with high-speed counter-current chromatography solvent extraction systems. The demonstrated performance will ultimately lead to a new process for commercial enrichment of lithium isotopes.</p> <p><br />The nuclear power industry in the U.S. and Europe requires enriched lithium-7 hydroxide for the safe operation of many of the reactors. Currently this strategic material is supplied by a Russian company and supply disruptions could jeopardize 20% of the U.S. electrical generation capability. Continued development of the novel technology from this project will lead to new U.S. commercial production that will serve this market. Longer term, the development of safer, lower-impact new technology for nuclear power generation is critical to meet the U.S. and global goals of reducing carbon emissions. One of the most promising technologies, molten salt reactors, will require commercial production of tens of tons of lithium-7. The new enrichment technology developed in this SBIR project is capable of being scaled to meet this need. Even longer term, many of the fusion energy technologies in development will require large quantities of enriched lithium-6. The planned production of enriched lithium-7 will likewise increase the availability of enriched lithium-6 for fusion power generation research, development, and commercialization.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/30/2022<br>      Modified by: Gordon&nbsp;D&nbsp;Jarvinen</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This Small Business Innovation Research Phase I project resulted in the development of a novel liquid-liquid extraction method to enrich lithium isotopes. This method was developed to be compatible with high-speed counter-current chromatography solvent extraction systems. The demonstrated performance will ultimately lead to a new process for commercial enrichment of lithium isotopes.   The nuclear power industry in the U.S. and Europe requires enriched lithium-7 hydroxide for the safe operation of many of the reactors. Currently this strategic material is supplied by a Russian company and supply disruptions could jeopardize 20% of the U.S. electrical generation capability. Continued development of the novel technology from this project will lead to new U.S. commercial production that will serve this market. Longer term, the development of safer, lower-impact new technology for nuclear power generation is critical to meet the U.S. and global goals of reducing carbon emissions. One of the most promising technologies, molten salt reactors, will require commercial production of tens of tons of lithium-7. The new enrichment technology developed in this SBIR project is capable of being scaled to meet this need. Even longer term, many of the fusion energy technologies in development will require large quantities of enriched lithium-6. The planned production of enriched lithium-7 will likewise increase the availability of enriched lithium-6 for fusion power generation research, development, and commercialization.       Last Modified: 10/30/2022       Submitted by: Gordon D Jarvinen]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
