<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  A Novel Respiratory Ventilator for Clinical Care (COVID-19)]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>255382.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>255382</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Benaiah Schrag</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bschrag@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928323</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is to develop a transformational ventilator design targeted at the unmet clinical need for low-cost (&lt;$3000), highly functional, rugged, modular and low maintenance ventilators supporting advanced ventilation modes. Current midrange ventilators cost between $8,000-20,000 with high-end ventilation units costing up to $50,000. The proposed design uses highly efficient and low-cost modern technologies with few moving functional elements. Only four modules are employed, designed to connect together in a quick-release, tool-less fashion requiring no service technicians to maintain. The design ensures that the new ventilator will work in existing hospital and acute care settings by (a) supporting networking of mobile devices for remote monitoring, (b) networking to hospital information systems to integrate with patient records and analytic systems, (c) supporting standard breathing patient circuit tubing and intubation tubes, (d) inclusion of monitoring settings and alarms, (e) supporting the use of hospital oxygen, oxygen in cylinders, medical air and atmospheric air. The global mechanical ventilator market was valued at $2.94 billion in 2019 and is estimated to reach $12.54 billion by 2027, driven by the rising worldwide prevalence of respiratory diseases including Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease (COPD) and asthma, as well as the COVID-19 pandemic. This new design will favorably impact clinical settings including acute care facilities, in-transit systems, home health care and developing countries.  It is ideal for surge and scale requirements, such as stockpiling by hospitals, strategic national stockpiles, mass casualty response and humanitarian missions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This SBIR Phase I project leverages applied engineering principles and understanding the mechanics of compressible fluids.  It leverages the use of computer-aided design and engineering, 3D printing, networking and low-cost components in consideration of hospital protocols. Novel innovations include: (a) positive displacement, volumetric air motive system for air/O2 delivery, and (b) a multi-position single element rotary selector valve for flow control of the air motive system. An inexpensive bill of materials is achieved with minimal components for low weight (&lt;4 pounds not including battery backup), small logistics footprint, minimal component failure points, ease of maintenance and rapid scale of manufacture.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/18/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/18/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2036836</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Karl</FirstName>
<LastName>Wassmann</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Karl Wassmann</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[karl@sperrymedtech.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000839472</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/18/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>SPERRY MEDTECH INC.</Name>
<CityName>SPRINGFIELD</CityName>
<ZipCode>051568817</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7748934313</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>202 EUREKA RD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Vermont</StateName>
<StateCode>VT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>VT00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>FUPAMPTR68J1</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SPERRY MEDTECH INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[SPERRY MEDTECH INC]]></Name>
<CityName>Springfield</CityName>
<StateCode>VT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>051568817</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[202 Eureka Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Vermont</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>VT00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5345</Code>
<Text>BIOMEDICAL ENGINEERING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~255382</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Sperry Medtech has designed the Auto Breath Ventilator (ABV) specifically for the ventilation needs of patients with severe or life-threatening medical conditions who lack access to advanced medical resources of intensive care units (ICUs) in Acute Care Hospitals.&nbsp;ABV is designed with performance and safety features based on guidelines published in April 2020 by the World Health Organization (WHO). ABV is also designed to meet both European CE certification and FDA 510(k) clearance.</p> <p><strong>1. First design imperative</strong> is modular, rugged, MIL-SPEC design to a) simplify logistics, b) eliminate the need for service technicians and c) be able to operate in harsh environments.&nbsp;<br /><strong>2. Second design imperative</strong> is Low Life Cycle Cost with a price target of &lt;$3,000 and no manufacturers service contract required. The low-cost the ventilator conforms to non-proprietary industry standards to gain economy of scale wherever possible.&nbsp;<br /><strong>3. Third design imperative</strong> is Design for Modular Manufacturing instead of the sequential, chassis-build assembly line process used to manufacture existing ventilators. This allows multiple contract manufacturers to build the individual modules which can then be assembled and tested by the final contract manufacturer as required by FDA regulations.&nbsp;<br /><strong>4. Fourth design imperative</strong> is the ventilator must have the functionality of existing mid-range ventilators including advanced ease of use features. To meet this fourth imperative, a novel, patent pending air motive system was developed.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Sperry Ventilator Features</strong></p> <p>1)<span> </span><strong>Low Life Cycle Cost</strong> &ndash; Requires No Manufacturers Service Contract: Price &lt;$3,000. Service and preventive maintenance by end-user</p> <p>2)<span> </span><strong>Ruggedized, Portable, MIL-STD, Light weight, Small logistic footprint,</strong> 7-14 hr. Battery 7.0 lbs., 3.75&rdquo; by 7.25&rdquo; by 13.5&rdquo;, with battery, can be dropped from standing height and dropped in bulk in pallets from aircraft in the field</p> <p>3)<span> </span><strong>Modular</strong> Only four interchangeable/swappable modules for simple logistics and optimal manufacturing</p> <p>4)<span> </span><strong>Innovative single axial positive displacement air motive system</strong> &ndash; Allows rest of system to be very simple and inexpensive.</p> <p>5)<span> </span><strong>Minimal Functional Components for Supply Chain Optimization</strong><br /><br />6)<span> </span><strong>Operates in Field, Transport, ER, ICU, Critical Care and Mass Casualties: </strong>For all respiratory and pulmonary injuries and diseases</p> <p>7)<span> </span><strong>Invasive, Noninvasive Ventilation and integrated High Flow Oxygen Therapy (HFOT)</strong>: Supports endotracheal tubes, masks or High Flow nasal cannulas</p> <p>8)<span> </span><strong>MRI environmental shielded: </strong>Eliminates need for changing ventilators when patient is transported from ICU to MRI</p> <p><strong>9) Intuitive - Ease-of-use with minimal training</strong>. Includes preset and intelligent modes</p> <p><strong>10) Supports Advanced Data Communication Standards</strong> - Remote monitoring, data analytics, hospital EMR<br /><br /></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/02/2021<br>      Modified by: Karl&nbsp;Wassmann</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Sperry Medtech has designed the Auto Breath Ventilator (ABV) specifically for the ventilation needs of patients with severe or life-threatening medical conditions who lack access to advanced medical resources of intensive care units (ICUs) in Acute Care Hospitals. ABV is designed with performance and safety features based on guidelines published in April 2020 by the World Health Organization (WHO). ABV is also designed to meet both European CE certification and FDA 510(k) clearance.  1. First design imperative is modular, rugged, MIL-SPEC design to a) simplify logistics, b) eliminate the need for service technicians and c) be able to operate in harsh environments.  2. Second design imperative is Low Life Cycle Cost with a price target of &lt;$3,000 and no manufacturers service contract required. The low-cost the ventilator conforms to non-proprietary industry standards to gain economy of scale wherever possible.  3. Third design imperative is Design for Modular Manufacturing instead of the sequential, chassis-build assembly line process used to manufacture existing ventilators. This allows multiple contract manufacturers to build the individual modules which can then be assembled and tested by the final contract manufacturer as required by FDA regulations.  4. Fourth design imperative is the ventilator must have the functionality of existing mid-range ventilators including advanced ease of use features. To meet this fourth imperative, a novel, patent pending air motive system was developed.    Sperry Ventilator Features  1) Low Life Cycle Cost &ndash; Requires No Manufacturers Service Contract: Price &lt;$3,000. Service and preventive maintenance by end-user  2) Ruggedized, Portable, MIL-STD, Light weight, Small logistic footprint, 7-14 hr. Battery 7.0 lbs., 3.75" by 7.25" by 13.5", with battery, can be dropped from standing height and dropped in bulk in pallets from aircraft in the field  3) Modular Only four interchangeable/swappable modules for simple logistics and optimal manufacturing  4) Innovative single axial positive displacement air motive system &ndash; Allows rest of system to be very simple and inexpensive.  5) Minimal Functional Components for Supply Chain Optimization  6) Operates in Field, Transport, ER, ICU, Critical Care and Mass Casualties: For all respiratory and pulmonary injuries and diseases  7) Invasive, Noninvasive Ventilation and integrated High Flow Oxygen Therapy (HFOT): Supports endotracheal tubes, masks or High Flow nasal cannulas  8) MRI environmental shielded: Eliminates need for changing ventilators when patient is transported from ICU to MRI  9) Intuitive - Ease-of-use with minimal training. Includes preset and intelligent modes  10) Supports Advanced Data Communication Standards - Remote monitoring, data analytics, hospital EMR         Last Modified: 09/02/2021       Submitted by: Karl Wassmann]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
