<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Improved COVID-19 Testing by Rapid Sample Purification]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>256000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>256000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Henry Ahn</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>hahn@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927069</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is an improved reliability for coronavirus detection. The proposed project will develop a tissue purification technology to extract (purify) virus from patient samples. Purer samples (more coronavirus, less confounding materials) is anticipated to improve signal from virus and reduce signal from non-virus materials, and is therefore anticipated to improve the reliability of testing (fewer false positives and false negatives). This can potentially impact the social distancing of the pandemic. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project of a system to extract purified samples for coronavirus testing for downstream testing, such as PCR-based analysis. The system is a novel purification technology that uses biological (antibodies) and other physical to quickly and reliably extract target microorganisms (here COVID viruses) from human samples.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/21/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/18/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2036463</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Benjamin</FirstName>
<LastName>Shapiro</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Benjamin Shapiro</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[Ben@xMDDiagnostics.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000828952</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/21/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate>05/18/2021</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ting-Pau</FirstName>
<LastName>Oei</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ting-Pau Oei</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[tingpau@xmddiagnostics.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000839099</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/18/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>XMD DIAGNOSTICS, INC.</Name>
<CityName>ANNAPOLIS</CityName>
<ZipCode>214032536</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6466626669</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>415 4TH ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[STE 201]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MD03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>U9XFSLLMTLP9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>XMD DIAGNOSTICS, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[XMD DIAGNOSTICS, LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>Baltimore</CityName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>212155216</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2401 W BELVEDERE AVE., SCHAPIRO]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MD07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>004E</Code>
<Text>BIOMEDICAL ENG AND DIAGNOSTICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~256000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Introduction</span></p> <p>This Project Outcomes Report is submitted by <strong><em>x</em></strong>MD Diagnostics (<strong><em>x</em></strong>MD). This Report provides a summary of the completed NSF SBIR Phase-I Award, focused initially on COVID-19 sample purification and subsequently on colon cancer tumor cell sample purification.&nbsp; In both cases, the goal was to demonstrate the benefits of using xMD&rsquo;s microdissection platform technology for improving physicians&rsquo; ability to test and diagnose COVID-19, colon cancer and, potentially, other serious diseases from tissue and liquid biopsy samples.&nbsp;</p> <p><strong><em>x</em></strong>MD Diagnostics'<strong><em> </em></strong>patented expression microdissection platform technology (the <strong><em>x</em></strong>CELL System) utilizes a combination of staining and optical engineering to selectively isolate, purify and enrich cells of interest (e.g., virions or tumor cells) from surrounding tissue on a standard stained biopsy glass slide. The <strong><em>x</em></strong>CELL system (instruments and single-use consumables) automates and replaces what is currently a manual technique known as &ldquo;razorblade scraping&rdquo;. This century old technique is an outdated, crude, and inaccurate method of isolating and procuring cells of interest (e.g., tumor cells) from patient biopsy samples. Using the <strong><em>x</em></strong>MD <strong><em>x</em></strong>CELL platform, the precise cells of interest can be rapidly selected, isolated, purified and enriched so that subsequent PCR, sequencing and molecular analyses (NGS) can be more successfully conducted. We anticipate that incorporating <strong><em>x</em></strong>CELL into the typical clinical pathology laboratory workflow will significantly reduce the time between patient biopsy and diagnosis. Further, our platform technology is applicable to many diseases and biopsy types, encompassing both solid and liquid samples.</p> <p>Validation of our <strong><em>x</em></strong>CELL technology for future use in clinical laboratories forms the basis of our Phase I NSF SBIR grant. This innovative sample preparation<strong><em> </em></strong>technology, originally developed at the NIH, significantly improves the ability of pathologists to more precisely diagnose serious diseases such as COVID-19 or cancer, especially when genetic molecular profiling is required.</p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Results</span></p> <p>Our Phase I goals were focused on utilizing our <strong><em>x</em></strong>CELL microdissection technology to identify COVID-19 positive patients via saliva samples. In Phase I, we were able to successfully stain and isolate SARS-CoV-2 virions in saliva. However, with the changing landscape of COVID-19 and the growing availability of at-home rapid tests, we formally requested and received approval from our Program Officer to pivot our goals and milestones from COVID-19 to cancer. After pivoting to cancer, we successfully completed our program and accomplished the objectives and milestones as described below.&nbsp; The milestones for our pivot to cancer remained similar to those we had for COVID-19.</p> <p>1.&nbsp; <span style="text-decoration: underline;">Optimized <strong><em>x</em></strong>CELL microdissection for extracting tumor cells</span></p> <ol> </ol> <p>Utilizing colon adenocarcinoma, we were able to fine-tune our current and patented microdissection<strong><em> x</em></strong>CELL instrument to selectively isolate tumor cells (positively IHC stained with tumor-specific markers) from surrounding tissue. This included finding the correct thermal conditions (i.e., voltage and duration) to ensure maximum yield. This was confirmed via DNA isolation quantification and visual assessment via microscopy.</p> <p>2.&nbsp; <span style="text-decoration: underline;">Verified improved purity of isolated tumor cells via this method</span></p> <ol> </ol> <p>We then compared our method of extraction to the industry standard of using a razorblade to manually scrape off sections of interest from tissue on a biopsy slide. We found that <strong><em>x</em></strong>CELL methods were equal to or exceeded razorblade scraping, underscoring the precision and replicability of our technology to what is standard in the pathology field.</p> <p>3.&nbsp; <span style="text-decoration: underline;">Completed proof of principal studies of the <strong><em>x</em></strong>CELL-LS Laser Instrument</span></p> <ol> </ol> <p>Our existing <strong><em>x</em></strong>CELL instrument utilizes a flashlamp to achieve the thermal conditions necessary to lift the cells of interest from a slide. However, our next-generation instrument, the <strong><em>x</em></strong>CELL-LS uses a laser as the sole light source. This will be critical for our goal of scaling up our technology to be able to process upwards of 96 samples at a time for high-throughput labs (such as hospital diagnostics). We have begun optimizing this instrument in cancer and have shown via microscopy analysis that we can achieve a lifting rate of 84.3% (+/- 4.1%), which is comparable to or exceeds the <strong><em>x</em></strong>CELL flashlamp instrument and razorblade scraping.</p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Conclusions</span></p> <p>Current standards for cancer diagnostics rely on laboratory technicians to manually scrape cells of interest from a tissue slide using razorblades after a pathologist has circled these sections with a sharpie pen. This slow, outdated, inaccurate method represents a bottleneck in the pathology laboratory workflow and inhibits pathologists&rsquo; ability to successfully perform molecular analysis such as sequencing and NGS. <strong><em>x</em></strong>MD&rsquo;s patented microdissection technology performs as well or better than razorblade scraping, without the required oversight and expense of a pathologist. We are excited at the opportunity for our <strong><em>x</em></strong>CELL platform to advance the health and welfare of the American public by increasing the speed, accuracy, and precision of cancer diagnoses, molecular profiling and patient outcomes.</p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><br /></span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/12/2022<br>      Modified by: Ting-Pau&nbsp;Oei</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Introduction  This Project Outcomes Report is submitted by xMD Diagnostics (xMD). This Report provides a summary of the completed NSF SBIR Phase-I Award, focused initially on COVID-19 sample purification and subsequently on colon cancer tumor cell sample purification.  In both cases, the goal was to demonstrate the benefits of using xMD’s microdissection platform technology for improving physicians’ ability to test and diagnose COVID-19, colon cancer and, potentially, other serious diseases from tissue and liquid biopsy samples.   xMD Diagnostics' patented expression microdissection platform technology (the xCELL System) utilizes a combination of staining and optical engineering to selectively isolate, purify and enrich cells of interest (e.g., virions or tumor cells) from surrounding tissue on a standard stained biopsy glass slide. The xCELL system (instruments and single-use consumables) automates and replaces what is currently a manual technique known as "razorblade scraping". This century old technique is an outdated, crude, and inaccurate method of isolating and procuring cells of interest (e.g., tumor cells) from patient biopsy samples. Using the xMD xCELL platform, the precise cells of interest can be rapidly selected, isolated, purified and enriched so that subsequent PCR, sequencing and molecular analyses (NGS) can be more successfully conducted. We anticipate that incorporating xCELL into the typical clinical pathology laboratory workflow will significantly reduce the time between patient biopsy and diagnosis. Further, our platform technology is applicable to many diseases and biopsy types, encompassing both solid and liquid samples.  Validation of our xCELL technology for future use in clinical laboratories forms the basis of our Phase I NSF SBIR grant. This innovative sample preparation technology, originally developed at the NIH, significantly improves the ability of pathologists to more precisely diagnose serious diseases such as COVID-19 or cancer, especially when genetic molecular profiling is required.  Results  Our Phase I goals were focused on utilizing our xCELL microdissection technology to identify COVID-19 positive patients via saliva samples. In Phase I, we were able to successfully stain and isolate SARS-CoV-2 virions in saliva. However, with the changing landscape of COVID-19 and the growing availability of at-home rapid tests, we formally requested and received approval from our Program Officer to pivot our goals and milestones from COVID-19 to cancer. After pivoting to cancer, we successfully completed our program and accomplished the objectives and milestones as described below.  The milestones for our pivot to cancer remained similar to those we had for COVID-19.  1.  Optimized xCELL microdissection for extracting tumor cells    Utilizing colon adenocarcinoma, we were able to fine-tune our current and patented microdissection xCELL instrument to selectively isolate tumor cells (positively IHC stained with tumor-specific markers) from surrounding tissue. This included finding the correct thermal conditions (i.e., voltage and duration) to ensure maximum yield. This was confirmed via DNA isolation quantification and visual assessment via microscopy.  2.  Verified improved purity of isolated tumor cells via this method    We then compared our method of extraction to the industry standard of using a razorblade to manually scrape off sections of interest from tissue on a biopsy slide. We found that xCELL methods were equal to or exceeded razorblade scraping, underscoring the precision and replicability of our technology to what is standard in the pathology field.  3.  Completed proof of principal studies of the xCELL-LS Laser Instrument    Our existing xCELL instrument utilizes a flashlamp to achieve the thermal conditions necessary to lift the cells of interest from a slide. However, our next-generation instrument, the xCELL-LS uses a laser as the sole light source. This will be critical for our goal of scaling up our technology to be able to process upwards of 96 samples at a time for high-throughput labs (such as hospital diagnostics). We have begun optimizing this instrument in cancer and have shown via microscopy analysis that we can achieve a lifting rate of 84.3% (+/- 4.1%), which is comparable to or exceeds the xCELL flashlamp instrument and razorblade scraping.  Conclusions  Current standards for cancer diagnostics rely on laboratory technicians to manually scrape cells of interest from a tissue slide using razorblades after a pathologist has circled these sections with a sharpie pen. This slow, outdated, inaccurate method represents a bottleneck in the pathology laboratory workflow and inhibits pathologists’ ability to successfully perform molecular analysis such as sequencing and NGS. xMD’s patented microdissection technology performs as well or better than razorblade scraping, without the required oversight and expense of a pathologist. We are excited at the opportunity for our xCELL platform to advance the health and welfare of the American public by increasing the speed, accuracy, and precision of cancer diagnoses, molecular profiling and patient outcomes.          Last Modified: 05/12/2022       Submitted by: Ting-Pau Oei]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
