<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Micro-textured surfaces for high-performance drone propellers]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>255864.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>255864</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ela Mirowski</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>emirowsk@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922936</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project seeks to improve the performance of drones - unmanned aerial vehicles - that are quickly being adopted for numerous commercial and civil applications. It is estimated that by 2021 the number of new drones will reach 29 million worldwide. Two of the main challenges in drone operation are the limited flight time and the noise generated by the drone propellers. Both of these represent obstacles for a more efficient and universal use of drones, and both are linked to propeller aerodynamic performance, more specifically, flow separation on propellers. This project aims to use micro-textured surfaces to create favorable aerodynamic conditions to mitigate noise, vibrations, and efficiency losses. Passive mitigation of aerodynamic inefficiencies will prolong component lifespan, reduce radiated noise, and increase energy efficiency. &lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project seeks to evaluate the effect of micro-textured surfaces that were previously shown to be effective in increasing lift, reducing drag, and mitigating noise from airfoils on drone propeller blades.  The improvements may increase payload capacity, extend the flight time, and reduce the noise of drones. The main goal of the proposed effort is to design propellers with a micro-textured surface that improves the efficiency up to 10% over leading industry propellers and mitigate generated noise. Thrust, torque and noise will be quantified for a combination of micro-textures and propeller designs. Additionally, field experiments will be carried out to understand the impact of the micro-texture on flight performance, noise, and maneuverability of a drone. Project will pursue an overall understanding of micro-texture/flow relationship to effectively design micro-textured surfaces for industrial applications.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/21/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/05/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041, 47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2036312</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ali</FirstName>
<LastName>Doosttalab</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ali Doosttalab</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ali.d@flowraider.net]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000829704</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/21/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>FLOW RAIDER, LLC</Name>
<CityName>ANNAPOLIS</CityName>
<ZipCode>214013629</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4439943498</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>101 S CHERRY GROVE AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MD03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>ZU9SXCNSLM29</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>FLOW RAIDER LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[FLOW RAIDER, LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>Lubbock</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>794099805</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>19</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX19</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>6840</Code>
<Text>ROBOTICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8034</Code>
<Text>Hardware Components</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~255864</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Flow Raider LLC conducted research on the application of bio-inspired micro textured surface coating on increasing the aerodynamic efficiency of the drones. We performed a series of experiments and numerical simulations to validate the drag reduction capabilities of our engineered microfiber surface coating for the drone industry. Our technology has potential to make a significant impact on the energy consumption of electric powered mid-to-large sized drones. Due to limited capacity of batteries, drones suffer from limited range and flight time. As the energy consumption of drones depends on the aerodynamic performance of its wing and fuselage, reducing flow separation plays a key role in reducing the energy consumption of these types of aerial vehicles. Our microfiber surface coating showed promising results in terms of increasing the aerodynamic efficiency of drones.</p> <p>In the first part of the effort, our team, designed high efficiency propellers that increased the efficiency by 6% compared to the leading drone propellers designed by leading drone manufacturers, while producing higher thrust force and reduced aeroacoustic noise generation. Applying the engineered microfiber coating was shown to further increase the efficiency of the drone propellers, in some cases up to 8%.</p> <p>In the second part of the project, it was shown that our engineered micro textured coating increased the efficiency of a UAV wing-body by increasing the lift-to-drag ratio of more than 14%, which will result in increased flight-time, range, and allowable payload. Furthermore, the microfiber coating showed positive effect on controllability and maneuverability of the UAV by increasing the effectiveness of lift generation by aileron deflection inputs.</p> <p>Many industries can benefit from our technology, which include package delivery, and oil &amp; gas; pipeline surveying and refinery inspections. Furthermore, growth and expansion of using electric powered drones will lead to less carbon emissions and reduced harmful impact on the environment. Also, as an emerging field in science and technology, any advancement in the drone space, leads to growth of the U.S.A. competitiveness in this critical area, with implications on public health, national security, and economic growth. Finally, the engineered microfibers coating can be used in the future for many other industries and applications, such as wind energy, ground vehicles, urban air mobility (UAM), among others, with the potential to increase aerodynamic efficiency, operating performance, and cost effectiveness.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/18/2023<br>      Modified by: Ali&nbsp;Doosttalab</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Flow Raider LLC conducted research on the application of bio-inspired micro textured surface coating on increasing the aerodynamic efficiency of the drones. We performed a series of experiments and numerical simulations to validate the drag reduction capabilities of our engineered microfiber surface coating for the drone industry. Our technology has potential to make a significant impact on the energy consumption of electric powered mid-to-large sized drones. Due to limited capacity of batteries, drones suffer from limited range and flight time. As the energy consumption of drones depends on the aerodynamic performance of its wing and fuselage, reducing flow separation plays a key role in reducing the energy consumption of these types of aerial vehicles. Our microfiber surface coating showed promising results in terms of increasing the aerodynamic efficiency of drones.  In the first part of the effort, our team, designed high efficiency propellers that increased the efficiency by 6% compared to the leading drone propellers designed by leading drone manufacturers, while producing higher thrust force and reduced aeroacoustic noise generation. Applying the engineered microfiber coating was shown to further increase the efficiency of the drone propellers, in some cases up to 8%.  In the second part of the project, it was shown that our engineered micro textured coating increased the efficiency of a UAV wing-body by increasing the lift-to-drag ratio of more than 14%, which will result in increased flight-time, range, and allowable payload. Furthermore, the microfiber coating showed positive effect on controllability and maneuverability of the UAV by increasing the effectiveness of lift generation by aileron deflection inputs.  Many industries can benefit from our technology, which include package delivery, and oil &amp; gas; pipeline surveying and refinery inspections. Furthermore, growth and expansion of using electric powered drones will lead to less carbon emissions and reduced harmful impact on the environment. Also, as an emerging field in science and technology, any advancement in the drone space, leads to growth of the U.S.A. competitiveness in this critical area, with implications on public health, national security, and economic growth. Finally, the engineered microfibers coating can be used in the future for many other industries and applications, such as wind energy, ground vehicles, urban air mobility (UAM), among others, with the potential to increase aerodynamic efficiency, operating performance, and cost effectiveness.       Last Modified: 01/18/2023       Submitted by: Ali Doosttalab]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
