<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Optimizing black soldier fly genetics and husbandry for industrialization of organic waste bioconversion]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>254689.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>254689</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rajesh Mehta</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rmehta@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922174</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is in promoting insect protein as an alternative source of protein for animal feed with a considerably lower environmental footprint compared to soy and fishmeal. With over 40% of food produced in the U.S today wasted and a potential $162 billion in annual loss related to waste, the proposed technology leverages the bioconversion potential of the non-pestiferous, voracious black soldier fly larvae (BSFL) to rapidly convert these wasted materials into a valuable protein-rich, high-fat insect biomass suitable for animal feed.  &lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;The proposed project will explore dynamics related to generation of larval products in animal feed.  The project will untangle the dynamics controlling depletion of resources and heat exchange underpinning the insect-substrate-microbial complex within bioreactors. By leveraging the rapid turnover in insect generation time and applying Genomic Selection, the project will improve many economically relevant traits in BSFL, enhance bioconversion rates, and make the larvae more robust to thrive with a variety of waste feedstock materials. Similarly, by developing a proprietary bioreactor design to solve the challenges associated with heat exchange and oxygenation of colonies posed by traditional rearing systems and optimizing environmental conditions (heat, oxygen, and moisture) during larvae growth, the project will inhibit lethal conditions and permit a significantly higher stocking density. Overall, the main sustainability objective is to upcycle agricultural by-products that may contain toxic or undesired compounds. This project will assess the fate of pollutants in larval products, if any, in order to assure high-quality animal feed.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/01/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/01/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2036078</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lydia</FirstName>
<LastName>Miner</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>G</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lydia G Miner</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[lydia@biomilitus.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000821759</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/01/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>BIOMILITUS LLC</Name>
<CityName>SACRAMENTO</CityName>
<ZipCode>958264407</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7073642998</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>9024 ALDERSON AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>QFTNJK2EESL9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>BIOMILITUS LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Inventopia]]></Name>
<CityName>Davis</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>956185078</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1949 5th Street, Suite 110]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1238</Code>
<Text>TECH FOR SUSTAINABLE ENVIRONMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~254689</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-dd7390d3-7fff-39da-ef81-86ec7d2f71fd"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>A proof of concept was developed under the NSF SBIR phase I for solving issues related to safety and scalability of commercial black soldier fly larvae (BSFL) production. We successfully extended the life cycle of BSFL which is the first step of achieving genomic selection for advanced larval lines. We incorporated agricultural by-products into our production system and confirmed the safety of our commercial larval product. We confirmed our engineered bioreactor increases the volume of larvae production while decreasing the land footprint compared to traditional larvae rearing methods.&nbsp;&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><em>Advanced larvae lines</em></span></p> <p dir="ltr">We extended the duration of the prepupal stage of BSFL to assist the genomic selection process. We were able to identify the lower and upper temperature thresholds resulting in a delay of the prepupal stage for up to 40 days. However, additional measures should be done to reduce overall larval mortality.</p> <p dir="ltr"><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><em>Hazard monitoring in BSFL products</em></span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The quality of the feedstock for the larvae impacts the quality and safety of the larvae. This project screened for over a thousand water contaminants and toxins where only 20 compounds were detected. None of these compounds is of great concern according to the EPA. A common pesticide (Bifenthin) potentially present in agricultural by-products showed bioaccumulation in the larvae. This bioaccumulation seemed to depend on the feedstock. The pesticide showed higher affinity to fatty tissues confirming that defatting can be&nbsp; a potential cleaning step to decontaminate the BSFL protein fraction should the level of contaminant reach levels of concerns. Given the lack of contaminants observed in the first study and the short life cycle of BSFL, bioaccumulation does not seem to pose a big concern. However, proper storage of feedstock is still critical to ensure product safety when agricultural byproducts are used as feedstock.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><em>Engineered bioreactor</em></span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>We demonstrated our engineered bioreactor was able to remove excess heat and provide oxygen to otherwise anaerobic conditions, allowing larvae to migrate deep into the feedstock. Using our modular, industrial sized bioreactor, we can achieve a 10x to 30x land footprint savings compared to traditional larvae rearing methods while treating a larger volume of agricultural by-products. Another important objective was to determine whether larvae could be motivated to self-harvest, and therefore reduce the industry dependence on manual sorting techniques. Our bioreactor which used a proprietary self-harvesting technique, had an average larvae self-harvest rate of 62%, with a maximum of 71%, occurring over a 22.5 hour period. The self-harvested larvae were extremely clean (&gt;99% weight was larvae) in comparison to larvae that had been manually sorted using a trommel, with only 70-80% weight being larvae and 20-30% being spent feedstock, depending on the feedstock materials. This reduces downstream steps of further cleaning and sorting the larvae which is required when using manual sorting methods. This represents a decrease in human labor required and therefore, an overall cost savings.</span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/21/2022<br>      Modified by: Lydia&nbsp;G&nbsp;Miner</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2036078/2036078_10715105_1658456766788_BSFL--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2036078/2036078_10715105_1658456766788_BSFL--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Adult BSFL"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2036078/2036078_10715105_1658456766788_BSFL--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Adult BSFL"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Adult BSFL</div> <div class="imageCredit">Adult BSFL</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Lydia&nbsp;G&nbsp;Miner</div> <div class="imageTitle">Adult BSFL</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   A proof of concept was developed under the NSF SBIR phase I for solving issues related to safety and scalability of commercial black soldier fly larvae (BSFL) production. We successfully extended the life cycle of BSFL which is the first step of achieving genomic selection for advanced larval lines. We incorporated agricultural by-products into our production system and confirmed the safety of our commercial larval product. We confirmed our engineered bioreactor increases the volume of larvae production while decreasing the land footprint compared to traditional larvae rearing methods.   Advanced larvae lines We extended the duration of the prepupal stage of BSFL to assist the genomic selection process. We were able to identify the lower and upper temperature thresholds resulting in a delay of the prepupal stage for up to 40 days. However, additional measures should be done to reduce overall larval mortality. Hazard monitoring in BSFL products The quality of the feedstock for the larvae impacts the quality and safety of the larvae. This project screened for over a thousand water contaminants and toxins where only 20 compounds were detected. None of these compounds is of great concern according to the EPA. A common pesticide (Bifenthin) potentially present in agricultural by-products showed bioaccumulation in the larvae. This bioaccumulation seemed to depend on the feedstock. The pesticide showed higher affinity to fatty tissues confirming that defatting can be  a potential cleaning step to decontaminate the BSFL protein fraction should the level of contaminant reach levels of concerns. Given the lack of contaminants observed in the first study and the short life cycle of BSFL, bioaccumulation does not seem to pose a big concern. However, proper storage of feedstock is still critical to ensure product safety when agricultural byproducts are used as feedstock. Engineered bioreactor We demonstrated our engineered bioreactor was able to remove excess heat and provide oxygen to otherwise anaerobic conditions, allowing larvae to migrate deep into the feedstock. Using our modular, industrial sized bioreactor, we can achieve a 10x to 30x land footprint savings compared to traditional larvae rearing methods while treating a larger volume of agricultural by-products. Another important objective was to determine whether larvae could be motivated to self-harvest, and therefore reduce the industry dependence on manual sorting techniques. Our bioreactor which used a proprietary self-harvesting technique, had an average larvae self-harvest rate of 62%, with a maximum of 71%, occurring over a 22.5 hour period. The self-harvested larvae were extremely clean (&gt;99% weight was larvae) in comparison to larvae that had been manually sorted using a trommel, with only 70-80% weight being larvae and 20-30% being spent feedstock, depending on the feedstock materials. This reduces downstream steps of further cleaning and sorting the larvae which is required when using manual sorting methods. This represents a decrease in human labor required and therefore, an overall cost savings.       Last Modified: 07/21/2022       Submitted by: Lydia G Miner]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
