<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Early Diagnosis of the COVID-19 Cytokine Storm via Point-of-Care Antibody Profiling]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>256000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>256000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Henry Ahn</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>hahn@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927069</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is to predict a patient’s risk for developing an adverse and often lethal response to certain viral infections, such as COVID-19. This project proposes a fast and accurate test for the severity of COVID-19 infection.  The proposed assay has the potential to enable early intervention and save lives. It can potentially be used for many other infections and public health hazards beyond COVID-19.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project will produce a new technology capable of diagnosing immune response dysregulation to any infectious disease (e.g., SARS-CoV-2, dengue, influenza, hepatitis C, etc.) that progress through an antibody dependent enhancement (ADE) mechanism. While infection by the SARS-CoV-2 virus begins as a mild illness, some patients experience a sudden and rapid decline in health, precipitated by a massive release of pro-inflammatory cytokines, i.e., a “cytokine storm,” Cytokine storms cause hyperinflammation of the lungs, which leads to acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS), the leading cause of COVID-19 mortality. Unfortunately, there is presently no test capable of predicting this event. This project aims to fill this medical technology gap via the development of a highly multiplexed, rapid, sensitive, disposable immunoassay specific to COVID-19 infections to be deployed at scale. The effort will include designing, building, and optimizing a prototype immunoassay based on nanopore technology innovations and analytically validating the developed technology against industry standards.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/21/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/21/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2036098</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Anna</FirstName>
<LastName>Schibel</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Anna Schibel</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[aschibel@electronicbio.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000654735</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/21/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Electronic Bio Sciences</Name>
<CityName>San Diego</CityName>
<ZipCode>921214206</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8584121800</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5754 Pacific Ctr Blvd Ste 204</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>52</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA52</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>FLHHE89XH2H5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ELECTRONIC BIOSCIENCES, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>FLHHE89XH2H5</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Electronic BioSciences, Inc.]]></Name>
<CityName>Salt Lake City</CityName>
<StateCode>UT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>841081244</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[421 Wakara Way, Suite 328]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Utah</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>UT02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>004E</Code>
<Text>BIOMEDICAL ENG AND DIAGNOSTICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~256000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>During this SBIR Phase I project, Electronic BioSciences, Inc. (EBS) developed the prototype device and instrument for a new nanopore-based technology to enable rapid, sensitive, and accurate COVID-19 testing, specifically towards diagnosing COVID infections, and differentiating high-risk vs. low-risk COVID stratification. The motivation to develop such technology is to better enable medical diagnosis and patient treatment to increase the opportunity for medical intervention and save lives, especially via improved precision/personalized medicine. More generally, this technology will advance assays of biomarkers, point-of-care (POC) testing, and disease diagnosis and monitoring. The developments made during this project demonstrated feasibility for fabricating a low-cost, mass-producible device for detecting SARS-CoV-2 antibodies and the associated sensing/measurement method. Based on the results from this project, EBS is now in position to begin validating and optimizing the analytical performance of the system and launch a new biosensing technology for infection profiling and monitoring, which will subsequently improve public health and safety via identifying opportunities for interventive and preventative care based on individual patient needs. Furthermore, while the technology developed here specifically addresses COVID-19 infection, the device, instrumentation, and method are quite versatile, which will broadly impact the fields of biosensing and diagnostics upon the full development and commercial launch of this technology.<strong></strong></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/16/2022<br>      Modified by: Anna&nbsp;Schibel</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ During this SBIR Phase I project, Electronic BioSciences, Inc. (EBS) developed the prototype device and instrument for a new nanopore-based technology to enable rapid, sensitive, and accurate COVID-19 testing, specifically towards diagnosing COVID infections, and differentiating high-risk vs. low-risk COVID stratification. The motivation to develop such technology is to better enable medical diagnosis and patient treatment to increase the opportunity for medical intervention and save lives, especially via improved precision/personalized medicine. More generally, this technology will advance assays of biomarkers, point-of-care (POC) testing, and disease diagnosis and monitoring. The developments made during this project demonstrated feasibility for fabricating a low-cost, mass-producible device for detecting SARS-CoV-2 antibodies and the associated sensing/measurement method. Based on the results from this project, EBS is now in position to begin validating and optimizing the analytical performance of the system and launch a new biosensing technology for infection profiling and monitoring, which will subsequently improve public health and safety via identifying opportunities for interventive and preventative care based on individual patient needs. Furthermore, while the technology developed here specifically addresses COVID-19 infection, the device, instrumentation, and method are quite versatile, which will broadly impact the fields of biosensing and diagnostics upon the full development and commercial launch of this technology.       Last Modified: 06/16/2022       Submitted by: Anna Schibel]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
