<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Nanoremediation of oily waste waters from spills and discharges]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>255937.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>275937</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ela Mirowski</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>emirowsk@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922936</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impacts of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project address oil pollution in Alaskan waters by reducing costs associated with oil cleanup projects. In Alaska, the challenges of remoteness and cold raise oil cleanup costs by 100 times compared with other areas. The technology is a magnetic nanoparticle, 80,000 times smaller than the width of a human hair, that can completely remove oil from water. To become competitive with current oil cleanup methods, it will undergo improvements for large scale production. The project also includes design, building, and testing a new prototype device for the technology. The technology will make spill cleanup faster and reduce environmental harm. In Alaska alone, oil spills cost $150 million to clean up annually. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Phase I project is a cost-effective, environmentally-benign nanoparticle technology that can quantitatively remove oil from contaminated water. Alaska has been targeted as a testbed due to limitations posed by cold and geographical remoteness that raise oil cleanup costs 100-fold compared to less remote regions. The goal of the project is to develop an oil removal device that can be deployed to remote regions with low cost and effort, reducing the length and cost of a spill response. The first aim of the project will optimize the nanoparticle synthesis to minimize costs and maximize active yield at commercial scales. A laboratory-scale, prototype oil removal device will be designed, built, and validated to enable pilots with larger volumes of contaminated water. The initial application will be to dewater oil recovered from the environment within the holds of barges; this can exceed 80% water. Dewatering reduces waste volumes and transportation costs, reducing environmental exposure and subsequent environmental health impacts from oil pollution.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/01/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/11/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2036258</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
<LastName>Vecchiarelli</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Paul Vecchiarelli</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[Vecchiar@email.sc.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000828803</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/01/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>GEOMAT, LLC</Name>
<CityName>COLUMBIA</CityName>
<ZipCode>292015826</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8037671878</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1225 LAUREL ST STE 219</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>South Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>SC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>SC06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>JTF4PCXQZAJ4</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GEOMAT, LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[GEOMAT, LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>Columbia</CityName>
<StateCode>SC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>292010001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1225 Laurel St]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>South Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>SC06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8091</Code>
<Text>SBIR Outreach &amp; Tech. Assist</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8037</Code>
<Text>Advanced Manufacturing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8611</Code>
<Text>Energy Efficiency and End Use</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~275937</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>GeoMat LLC, located in Columbia, SC, completed research towards commercialization of its nanotechnology platform for environmental remediation supported by this NSF SBIR Phase I grant. The research aims for this project were based on substantial customer discovery, which helped determine a potential beachhead market for oily water treatment. The basic concept of the treatment process is shown in&nbsp;<strong>Figure 1</strong>.&nbsp;The customer discovery conducted prior to, and during, Phase I helped identify key technical areas where the technology required further research and develop to minimize technical risks. This process was, and remains, a crucial aspect of the company's business model development. &nbsp;</p> <p>The first technical area which was investigated in this project was the synthesis of nanoparticles. Previous studies had shown that changing the process from a batch method to a continuous method increased the potential for scalability. An outline of the continuous method is shown in&nbsp;<strong>Figure 2</strong>. By combining a fixed amount of the reactants continuously, issues with even mixing in a large batch system are minimized which enables production to reach expected commercial scales. Work on this part of the project focused on optimizing the synthesis, storage, and preparation parameters to maximize yield and oil removal capability and reduce costs where possible. The scalability of this system was also investigated, and a massively parallel modular pump system which could be quickly replicated and expanded by 3D printing was tested. Both technical objectives for synthesis are reported as successful within the scope of the project.&nbsp;</p> <p>The second technical area investigated in this project was the deployment of nanoparticles for oily water remediation. Due to regulations by the EPA and other agencies, chemical technologies require approval before commercial sale is allowed. The approval process helps to ensure that the benefit of putting a chemical into the environment outweighs any potential risk by a significant amount. While prior studies showed that the nanoparticles could be placed directly into a body of water and recovered with very little remaining in the environment, a self-contained system to treat oily water was developed where no nanoparticles were put directly into the environment, shown in&nbsp;<strong>Figure 3</strong>. The treatment system was further optimized in this project. This research required a project extension because interviews with the proposed customers indicated a need to streamline the system for its end users. The optimization experiments investigated changes in treatment efficiency based on the duration of exposure to the magnets, system flow rate, and the number of stages in the device. In contrast to other studies published by the group, these experiments also examined oil removal at concentrations up to 1% oil which more environmentally relevant than previously examined. The research conducted on nanoparticle deployment was also reported as successful within the scope of the project.</p> <p>Overall, this project contributed substantially towards advancing the GeoMat nanoparticle platform. Feasibility has been shown in the synthesis, and separate research has shown that the technology can be applied to contaminants beyond oil, such as dissolved metals, harmful algal blooms, and others. GeoMat will pursue these applications in sequence to ensure successful product launches and use the findings from this Phase I project as a template for further research and development.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/27/2022<br>      Modified by: Paul&nbsp;Vecchiarelli</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2036258/2036258_10715131_1664460563269_Figure1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2036258/2036258_10715131_1664460563269_Figure1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Nanoparticles for Oil Removal"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2036258/2036258_10715131_1664460563269_Figure1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Nanoparticles for Oil Removal"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 1. Depiction of oil particles bound to a nanoparticle coated with a sorbent polymer. Once saturated, nanoparticles are recovered magnetically.</div> <div class="imageCredit">GeoMat LLC</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Paul&nbsp;Vecchiarelli</div> <div class="imageTitle">Nanoparticles for Oil Removal</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2036258/2036258_10715131_1664463451656_Figure2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2036258/2036258_10715131_1664463451656_Figure2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Continuous Synthesis Process"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2036258/2036258_10715131_1664463451656_Figure2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Continuous Synthesis Process"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 2. Schematic of the continuous synthesis method developed prior to Phase I. This was optimized and expanded to a massively parallel synthesis in Phase I.</div> <div class="imageCredit">GeoMat LLC</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Paul&nbsp;Vecchiarelli</div> <div class="imageTitle">Continuous Synthesis Process</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2036258/2036258_10715131_1664463560314_Figure3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2036258/2036258_10715131_1664463560314_Figure3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Self-contained Oily Water Treatment System"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2036258/2036258_10715131_1664463560314_Figure3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Self-contained Oily Water Treatment System"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 3. A schematic of the oily water treatment system developed prior to Phase I. This system was optimized in Phase I.</div> <div class="imageCredit">GeoMat LLC</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Paul&nbsp;Vecchiarelli</div> <div class="imageTitle">Self-contained Oily Water Treatment System</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ GeoMat LLC, located in Columbia, SC, completed research towards commercialization of its nanotechnology platform for environmental remediation supported by this NSF SBIR Phase I grant. The research aims for this project were based on substantial customer discovery, which helped determine a potential beachhead market for oily water treatment. The basic concept of the treatment process is shown in Figure 1. The customer discovery conducted prior to, and during, Phase I helped identify key technical areas where the technology required further research and develop to minimize technical risks. This process was, and remains, a crucial aspect of the company's business model development.    The first technical area which was investigated in this project was the synthesis of nanoparticles. Previous studies had shown that changing the process from a batch method to a continuous method increased the potential for scalability. An outline of the continuous method is shown in Figure 2. By combining a fixed amount of the reactants continuously, issues with even mixing in a large batch system are minimized which enables production to reach expected commercial scales. Work on this part of the project focused on optimizing the synthesis, storage, and preparation parameters to maximize yield and oil removal capability and reduce costs where possible. The scalability of this system was also investigated, and a massively parallel modular pump system which could be quickly replicated and expanded by 3D printing was tested. Both technical objectives for synthesis are reported as successful within the scope of the project.   The second technical area investigated in this project was the deployment of nanoparticles for oily water remediation. Due to regulations by the EPA and other agencies, chemical technologies require approval before commercial sale is allowed. The approval process helps to ensure that the benefit of putting a chemical into the environment outweighs any potential risk by a significant amount. While prior studies showed that the nanoparticles could be placed directly into a body of water and recovered with very little remaining in the environment, a self-contained system to treat oily water was developed where no nanoparticles were put directly into the environment, shown in Figure 3. The treatment system was further optimized in this project. This research required a project extension because interviews with the proposed customers indicated a need to streamline the system for its end users. The optimization experiments investigated changes in treatment efficiency based on the duration of exposure to the magnets, system flow rate, and the number of stages in the device. In contrast to other studies published by the group, these experiments also examined oil removal at concentrations up to 1% oil which more environmentally relevant than previously examined. The research conducted on nanoparticle deployment was also reported as successful within the scope of the project.  Overall, this project contributed substantially towards advancing the GeoMat nanoparticle platform. Feasibility has been shown in the synthesis, and separate research has shown that the technology can be applied to contaminants beyond oil, such as dissolved metals, harmful algal blooms, and others. GeoMat will pursue these applications in sequence to ensure successful product launches and use the findings from this Phase I project as a template for further research and development.       Last Modified: 10/27/2022       Submitted by: Paul Vecchiarelli]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
