<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  A Medical Device to Secure Endotracheal Tubes and Reduce Unplanned Extubations for Neonates in Intensive Care]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>256000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>256000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Henry Ahn</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>hahn@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927069</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is to develop a device that effectively and reliably secures endotracheal tubes for babies in the neonatal intensive care unit.  Endotracheal tubes are airways placed in patients to help them breathe, but babies in the NICU experience high rates of unplanned dislodgement and early removal. These dangerous events are primarily attributed to poor and ineffective securement of the endotracheal tube to the patient. An integrated solution to endotracheal tube securement would reduce complications for the 80,000+ neonatal intubations that occur every year in the United States. This is especially urgent in lower-resourced settings that may have limited staff that are experienced in neonatal resuscitation. This project will develop a new system to support these patients. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project enables advanced patient securement to minimize the risk of unplanned extubations. Endotracheal tube securement presents unique challenges in neonates, given their delicate and small anatomy. The research objectives include developing a custom adhesive that maintains functionality in incubator environments and in use on underdeveloped neonatal facial skin; designing, validating, and manufacturing device securement mechanisms; and conducting bench testing and simulated use testing with clinicians.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/21/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/31/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041, 47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2036668</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Eric</FirstName>
<LastName>Chehab</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>F</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Eric F Chehab</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[echehab@gmail.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000738386</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/21/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Novonate Inc</Name>
<CityName>SOUTH SAN FRANCISCO</CityName>
<ZipCode>940801933</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6502752404</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>395 OYSTER POINT BLVD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[STE 501]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>15</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA15</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>RWBNRLB3BLL8</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NOVONATE INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Novonate Inc]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>940801933</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>15</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA15</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5345</Code>
<Text>BIOMEDICAL ENGINEERING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~256000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-4a6dfba8-7fff-c01b-bfbd-160d43f1e10c"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr">In the neonatal intensive care unit (NICU), endotracheal intubation and mechanical ventilation are vital to sustaining the lives of babies who are born without the ability to breathe on their own, due to prematurity or other congenital illnesses. Neonatal endotracheal tubes (ETTs) have a high risk of malposition and subsequent unplanned extubation (UE), due to the inability of current securement methods and techniques to maintain proper tube position throughout patient agitation, patient repositioning, ETT manipulation by caregivers, and the warm, humid environment of the neonatal incubator. The current standard of care for securing ETTs in the NICU are all based on tape and adhesives, used for fixation to the patient&rsquo;s face and for fixation of the tube itself. Most of these adhesives were not designed specifically for use on neonatal skin, and none were developed with the security of the ETT in mind. There is a clear and urgent need for a way to secure ETTs in the NICU that maintains ETT position amidst this procedure-heavy environment and reduces UE rates for babies. The product under development is a new neonatal ETT securement system, designed specifically to address the current gaps in securement options and reduce the risk of UEs in the hospital&rsquo;s most fragile patient population.</p> <p dir="ltr">This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project focused on initial development of the ETT securement device, by refining user needs, brainstorming and generating design concepts, and evaluating them in preliminary bench tests. Over 30 interviews with NICU clinicians were conducted to clarify product design requirements, and to identify major shortcomings in current tape-based ETT securement solutions. The iterative mechanical design effort consisted of 2 main rounds of concept generation, prototyping, and testing, for a) how the device will be secured to the patient&rsquo;s face, and b) how the device will secure the ETT itself. A subset of end-users who were initially interviewed provided feedback on preliminary prototypes and informed iterations. A wide range of neonatal-skin safe adhesives were sourced and tested, during which shortcomings and workarounds to existing bench test protocols were identified. Several methods for engineering skin adhesives for optimal performance in the warm, humid incubator conditions were explored, and initial prototypes hold promise for future development work. Novonate&rsquo;s successful completion of the Phase I objectives represents a significant step toward commercialization of this important medical device.</p> <p dir="ltr">The broader impact/commercial potential of this project is to improve the safety of the hundreds of thousands of NICU intubations in the U.S. per year. ETTs are critical life-sustaining devices to neonatal intensive care, and this product is an urgently-needed replacement of the tape-based methods currently used to secure them. A new device for ETT securement would enable neonatologists, respiratory therapists, and nurses to robustly secure and protect ETTs such that they are safer for their vulnerable patients, and reduce the risk of unplanned extubations. A reduction in UE rates would save hospitals tens of thousands of dollars per year, and more importantly, prevent complications to save neonatal lives in any hospital setting.</p> <p dir="ltr">&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/11/2022<br>      Modified by: Eric&nbsp;F&nbsp;Chehab</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   In the neonatal intensive care unit (NICU), endotracheal intubation and mechanical ventilation are vital to sustaining the lives of babies who are born without the ability to breathe on their own, due to prematurity or other congenital illnesses. Neonatal endotracheal tubes (ETTs) have a high risk of malposition and subsequent unplanned extubation (UE), due to the inability of current securement methods and techniques to maintain proper tube position throughout patient agitation, patient repositioning, ETT manipulation by caregivers, and the warm, humid environment of the neonatal incubator. The current standard of care for securing ETTs in the NICU are all based on tape and adhesives, used for fixation to the patient’s face and for fixation of the tube itself. Most of these adhesives were not designed specifically for use on neonatal skin, and none were developed with the security of the ETT in mind. There is a clear and urgent need for a way to secure ETTs in the NICU that maintains ETT position amidst this procedure-heavy environment and reduces UE rates for babies. The product under development is a new neonatal ETT securement system, designed specifically to address the current gaps in securement options and reduce the risk of UEs in the hospital’s most fragile patient population. This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project focused on initial development of the ETT securement device, by refining user needs, brainstorming and generating design concepts, and evaluating them in preliminary bench tests. Over 30 interviews with NICU clinicians were conducted to clarify product design requirements, and to identify major shortcomings in current tape-based ETT securement solutions. The iterative mechanical design effort consisted of 2 main rounds of concept generation, prototyping, and testing, for a) how the device will be secured to the patient’s face, and b) how the device will secure the ETT itself. A subset of end-users who were initially interviewed provided feedback on preliminary prototypes and informed iterations. A wide range of neonatal-skin safe adhesives were sourced and tested, during which shortcomings and workarounds to existing bench test protocols were identified. Several methods for engineering skin adhesives for optimal performance in the warm, humid incubator conditions were explored, and initial prototypes hold promise for future development work. Novonate’s successful completion of the Phase I objectives represents a significant step toward commercialization of this important medical device. The broader impact/commercial potential of this project is to improve the safety of the hundreds of thousands of NICU intubations in the U.S. per year. ETTs are critical life-sustaining devices to neonatal intensive care, and this product is an urgently-needed replacement of the tape-based methods currently used to secure them. A new device for ETT securement would enable neonatologists, respiratory therapists, and nurses to robustly secure and protect ETTs such that they are safer for their vulnerable patients, and reduce the risk of unplanned extubations. A reduction in UE rates would save hospitals tens of thousands of dollars per year, and more importantly, prevent complications to save neonatal lives in any hospital setting.            Last Modified: 10/11/2022       Submitted by: Eric F Chehab]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
