<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Build and Broaden: Bridging Critical Research Collaborations for Faculty Success in Texas MSIs]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>75000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>90000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jorge Valdes Kroff</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jvaldesk@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927920</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The state of Texas has more minority-serving institutions (MSI) than any state other than California. The state's pressing priorities mimic many at the national level, such as a need for greater inclusion at all levels of the scientific enterprise. While the National Science Foundation (NSF) has identified many effective strategies to demystify the grants process, funding rates at MSIs still lag behind other institutions with fewer students of color, including in the social, behavioral, and economic (SBE) sciences. In turn, this means MSI students have fewer opportunities to participate in research or to acquire cutting edge scientific techniques, the kinds of experiences that increase options for career paths and advanced education. This grant funds three mini-conferences for MSI faculty in Texas, with a focus on participation by faculty of color, women faculty, and mid-career faculty. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The mini-conferences will feature presentations by former NSF staff and other faculty who bring expertise in navigating different career pathways, including at MSIs. Through the events, faculty at MSIs will learn more about NSF grant proposals and research collaborations and will have access to on-site mentorship and collaboration opportunities. The conference organizers also plan to collect survey data on the career pathways of participating faculty in the SBE sciences at these institutions, with an eye towards better understanding how to support research capacity, especially for collaborations. As a result, a larger pool of faculty at MSIs will share an understanding of NSF proposals and fellow SBE researchers in the region. Increased attention to SBE research and funding in the state of Texas will advance fundamental knowledge in the SBE disciplines, highlighting the value of SBE research in a state which receives roughly 90% of its funding in the non-SBE disciplines, according to figures from the Texas Higher Education Coordinating Board.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/19/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/09/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2036909</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Colleen</FirstName>
<LastName>Fitzgerald</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Colleen M Fitzgerald</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[colleen.fitzgerald@ndsu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000556012</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/19/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Isabel</FirstName>
<LastName>Araiza</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Isabel Araiza</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[iaraiza2@delmar.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000827990</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/19/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Ramirez</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael E Ramirez</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[michael.ramirez@tamucc.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000824534</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/19/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jennifer</FirstName>
<LastName>Epley Sanders</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jennifer L Epley Sanders</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jennifer.epley@tamucc.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000827560</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/19/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Texas A&amp;M University Corpus Christi</Name>
<CityName>CORPUS CHRISTI</CityName>
<ZipCode>784125739</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3618252730</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>6300 OCEAN DR UNIT 5739</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>27</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX27</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>Y3RET2XN41S5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TEXAS A&amp;M UNIVERSITY-CORPUS CHRISTI</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Texas A&M University Corpus Christi]]></Name>
<CityName>Corpus Christi</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>784125844</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>27</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX27</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1311</Code>
<Text>Linguistics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>146Y</Code>
<Text>Build and Broaden</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1311</Code>
<Text>LINGUISTICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1331</Code>
<Text>SOCIOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1371</Code>
<Text>POLITICAL SCIENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~75000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~15000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The goal of this Build and Broaden Conference proposal was building research capacity and partnerships in the social, behavioral and economic (SBE) sciences at MSIs in Texas through a webinar series and a virtual conference. The proposed workshops accomplished three key objectives for SBE faculty at MSIs in Texas:</p> <ul> <li>Offered mechanisms to address the lack of socialization and familiarity with NSF funding programs and grant proposals and thus&nbsp;build capacity in the SBE sciences</li> </ul> <ul> <li>Provided on-site mentorship and collaboration opportunities for faculty</li> </ul> <ul> <li>Collected survey data on the career pathways of participating faculty in the SBE sciences to better understand how to support research capacity, especially for collaborations</li> </ul> <p>The Texas MSI faculty participating in the workshops displayed four key assets to assist them in moving toward their career goals:&nbsp;tenacity; passion for the field; interdisciplinary perspective; and a supportive environment.&nbsp;&nbsp;Through the survey data, team experiences and the implementation of the project, the greatest challenges that Texas MSI faculty in the SBE sciences face in achieving their goals are: time; teaching; lack of support from institution;&nbsp;lack of resources (institutional and individual); lack of grant experience; no mentor figures; and the Covid-19 Pandemic.</p> <p><strong>Intellectual Merit:</strong></p> <p>The project generated quantitative and qualitative data on the needs and barriers to producing successful grants that confront social science faculty at Texas MSIs&nbsp;who wish to be more active in the grant sphere.&nbsp;Data collection increased understanding of&nbsp;how MSI faculty, especially faculty of color and women, navigated their experiences and career trajectories in MSIs during the pandemic. Activities have also provided NSF with internal ability to evaluate&nbsp;the effectiveness of replicating a proven approach, "learning by seconding"&nbsp;(Kolympiris et al. 2019), which is the way in which short-term stints at one organization can enhance and bring about knowledge transfer at the home organization upon the employee's return.&nbsp;&nbsp;Seconding in this case applied to positive growth in NSF awards as generated by former NSF rotators returning back to their home departments and universities to share their knowledge. By assessing the impact on funding awards to MSIs in the SBE sciences, the proposal will thus advance knowledge on how the expertise of SBE rotating program officers can affect the funding success for participants.&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts:</strong></p> <p><span><span>Through a virtual webinar series and a virtual conference for social science faculty at Texas MSIs, the project&nbsp;increased individual research capacity in the SBE sciences in targeted MSIs and created new networks as prospective pathways for collaborative research.&nbsp;The project indirectly benefited students from underrepresented groups at Texas MSIs by supporting the faculty, some of whom themselves are from underrepresented groups.</span></span></p> <p><span><span><span>Participants emerged with key products and greater knowledge to support their efforts in securing potential success at NSF.&nbsp;Products included updated CVs, ORCID IDs, knowledge of navigating Fastlane and biosketch development. Many fulfilled professional development expectations for annual faculty reviews and workshops also offered strategies for preparing&nbsp;dossiers for promotion to full professor.&nbsp;The project's efforts with a workshop series did&nbsp;help&nbsp;MSI&nbsp;faculty with their resumes but not completely overcome&nbsp;institutional-level challenges. Structural constraints&nbsp;at MSIs cannot be completely solved/overcome with individual-level training, workshops, or advice from NSF insiders. Research capacity is an institutional investment and needs a systemic commitment. For example,&nbsp;Texas MSI faculty need significant time and resources in order to apply for grants and conduct research. Time is a key component in order to conduct the necessary reflection for doing research and building relationships. Institutional infrastructure is needed to build in that time and resources.&nbsp;&nbsp;Without clear commitments from institutions, there is a risk of reproducing inequalities existing among MSI faculty, at least at those Texas MSIs which participated in the workshops.</span><br /></span></span></p> <p><strong>Products and DMP:</strong></p> <p>Executed DMP through depositing materials at TAMU-CC Digital Repository.</p> <p><a href="https://tamucc-ir.tdl.org/handle/1969.6/89766">https://tamucc-ir.tdl.org/handle/1969.6/89766</a>&nbsp;</p> <p>Araiza, Isabel; Epley Sanders, Jennifer; and Ramirez, Michael. 2022. "With the Best of Intentions: The Limits of a Sociological Imagination when Operating within Institutional Structures.&#8203;"<em>&nbsp;</em>Paper presented March 13, 2022 at the Eastern Sociological Society, Boston, MA.</p> <p>Araiza, Isabel; Epley Sanders, Jennifer; and Ramirez, Michael. 2022. "Building Research Capacity or Building Resumes? Understanding the Opportunities and&nbsp;Obstacles of Building Research Capacity at&nbsp;Minority Serving&nbsp;Institutions (MSIs).&#8203;"<em>&nbsp;</em>Paper presented April 22, 2022 at the Southwestern Social Science Association, San Antonio, TX.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/15/2023<br>      Modified by: Colleen&nbsp;M&nbsp;Fitzgerald</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The goal of this Build and Broaden Conference proposal was building research capacity and partnerships in the social, behavioral and economic (SBE) sciences at MSIs in Texas through a webinar series and a virtual conference. The proposed workshops accomplished three key objectives for SBE faculty at MSIs in Texas:  Offered mechanisms to address the lack of socialization and familiarity with NSF funding programs and grant proposals and thus build capacity in the SBE sciences   Provided on-site mentorship and collaboration opportunities for faculty   Collected survey data on the career pathways of participating faculty in the SBE sciences to better understand how to support research capacity, especially for collaborations   The Texas MSI faculty participating in the workshops displayed four key assets to assist them in moving toward their career goals: tenacity; passion for the field; interdisciplinary perspective; and a supportive environment.  Through the survey data, team experiences and the implementation of the project, the greatest challenges that Texas MSI faculty in the SBE sciences face in achieving their goals are: time; teaching; lack of support from institution; lack of resources (institutional and individual); lack of grant experience; no mentor figures; and the Covid-19 Pandemic.  Intellectual Merit:  The project generated quantitative and qualitative data on the needs and barriers to producing successful grants that confront social science faculty at Texas MSIs who wish to be more active in the grant sphere. Data collection increased understanding of how MSI faculty, especially faculty of color and women, navigated their experiences and career trajectories in MSIs during the pandemic. Activities have also provided NSF with internal ability to evaluate the effectiveness of replicating a proven approach, "learning by seconding" (Kolympiris et al. 2019), which is the way in which short-term stints at one organization can enhance and bring about knowledge transfer at the home organization upon the employee's return.  Seconding in this case applied to positive growth in NSF awards as generated by former NSF rotators returning back to their home departments and universities to share their knowledge. By assessing the impact on funding awards to MSIs in the SBE sciences, the proposal will thus advance knowledge on how the expertise of SBE rotating program officers can affect the funding success for participants.   Broader Impacts:  Through a virtual webinar series and a virtual conference for social science faculty at Texas MSIs, the project increased individual research capacity in the SBE sciences in targeted MSIs and created new networks as prospective pathways for collaborative research. The project indirectly benefited students from underrepresented groups at Texas MSIs by supporting the faculty, some of whom themselves are from underrepresented groups.  Participants emerged with key products and greater knowledge to support their efforts in securing potential success at NSF. Products included updated CVs, ORCID IDs, knowledge of navigating Fastlane and biosketch development. Many fulfilled professional development expectations for annual faculty reviews and workshops also offered strategies for preparing dossiers for promotion to full professor. The project's efforts with a workshop series did help MSI faculty with their resumes but not completely overcome institutional-level challenges. Structural constraints at MSIs cannot be completely solved/overcome with individual-level training, workshops, or advice from NSF insiders. Research capacity is an institutional investment and needs a systemic commitment. For example, Texas MSI faculty need significant time and resources in order to apply for grants and conduct research. Time is a key component in order to conduct the necessary reflection for doing research and building relationships. Institutional infrastructure is needed to build in that time and resources.  Without clear commitments from institutions, there is a risk of reproducing inequalities existing among MSI faculty, at least at those Texas MSIs which participated in the workshops.   Products and DMP:  Executed DMP through depositing materials at TAMU-CC Digital Repository.  https://tamucc-ir.tdl.org/handle/1969.6/89766   Araiza, Isabel; Epley Sanders, Jennifer; and Ramirez, Michael. 2022. "With the Best of Intentions: The Limits of a Sociological Imagination when Operating within Institutional Structures.&#8203;" Paper presented March 13, 2022 at the Eastern Sociological Society, Boston, MA.  Araiza, Isabel; Epley Sanders, Jennifer; and Ramirez, Michael. 2022. "Building Research Capacity or Building Resumes? Understanding the Opportunities and Obstacles of Building Research Capacity at Minority Serving Institutions (MSIs).&#8203;" Paper presented April 22, 2022 at the Southwestern Social Science Association, San Antonio, TX.       Last Modified: 03/15/2023       Submitted by: Colleen M Fitzgerald]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
