<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[I-Corps:  Plasmonic Microarray Chips for Microbial Identification]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ruth Shuman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rshuman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922160</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this I-Corps project is to enhance the development of plasmonic microchips that enable microbial analysis in complex samples. This technology can have broad application in laboratory research, water quality assessment, food safety, and human health screening. The simplified sample preparation is advantageous for time sensitive testing, and the improved performance offers a technical feasibility for identifying microbial strains and bacterial contaminants using inexpensive bench-top mass spectrometric instruments. The method can be further adopted to identify viruses based on their lipid corona. This technology eliminates issues experienced with older, laborious techniques and accelerates the understanding of microorganisms’ impact in real-time.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project explores metal-enhanced plasmonic properties on microarrays for bacterial identification. Manipulation of metal layer structures offers fluorescence imaging localization, high throughput analysis, and enhanced Matrix-Assisted Laser Desorption/Ionization (MALDI) - Mass Spectrometer (MS) performance. The technique is based on lipidomic profiling on microchips, where sample location is pinpointed with fluorescent imaging for more accurate mass spectrometry analysis. The microchip is transferable to other technique platforms for identification of a range of components including metabolites and lipids at the single cell level that may lead to swift microbial identification.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/06/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/06/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2037821</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Quan</FirstName>
<LastName>Cheng</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Quan Cheng</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[quan.cheng@ucr.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000482293</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/06/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Riverside</Name>
<CityName>RIVERSIDE</CityName>
<ZipCode>925210001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9518275535</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>200 UNIVERSTY OFC BUILDING</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>41</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA41</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>MR5QC5FCAVH5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA AT RIVERSIDE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Riverside]]></Name>
<CityName>Riverside</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>925210001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>41</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA41</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project provided multiple training opportunities to graduate students working in the field of science to learn about technology transfer and commercialization of laboratory discoveries. The funding allowed students to attend training workshops, conduct interviews for market research, and interact with industrial mentors to have value assessment of the technology.</p> <p>The project established a learning foundation for students to explore the commercial potential of the technique developed at UCR that aims to provide swift bacterial analysis. Rapid identification of microbial species has broad impact to society as it improves human health care, food safety and enhances environmental protection. Current technology has known drawbacks including long processing time (i.e. traditional culture approaches) and high expense (for new technology). Advances in methodology on improving time and eliminating extraction requirements will allow strain specific analysis to be conducted rapidly. We have developed and improved a microchip-based MALDI mass spectrometry method that can accelerate sampling handling and provide high-performance analysis with benchtop instrument. By participating in the NSF-ICORP program, we have moved forward through translational research and technical development, learned the strategies for transition to the marketplace, and prepared for technology commercialization.</p> <p>The project improved the technology with metal-enhanced plasmonic microarray to enhance MALDI-MS performance. The use of microarray simplifies sample handling, improves fluorescence imaging, and enables high throughput analysis. It will benefit society for elevating single cell analysis capability. The plasmonic substrates improved ionization efficiency in the MALDI process, allowing direct analysis of lipid signatures of bacterial species that potentially lead to rapid microbial species ID.</p> <p>The project provided excellent learning experience for students to understand the values of market analysis, customer needs, IP process and protection, and technology transfer. The close interactions with industry offered unique opportunities to look at key issues beyond technology and provided students knowledge and skills for moving career direction to become tech leaders in future. With the interviews with industrial leaders and interactions with cohort of the program, our students have built valuable network that can have very positive impact to their career development. &nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/08/2022<br>      Modified by: Quan&nbsp;Cheng</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project provided multiple training opportunities to graduate students working in the field of science to learn about technology transfer and commercialization of laboratory discoveries. The funding allowed students to attend training workshops, conduct interviews for market research, and interact with industrial mentors to have value assessment of the technology.  The project established a learning foundation for students to explore the commercial potential of the technique developed at UCR that aims to provide swift bacterial analysis. Rapid identification of microbial species has broad impact to society as it improves human health care, food safety and enhances environmental protection. Current technology has known drawbacks including long processing time (i.e. traditional culture approaches) and high expense (for new technology). Advances in methodology on improving time and eliminating extraction requirements will allow strain specific analysis to be conducted rapidly. We have developed and improved a microchip-based MALDI mass spectrometry method that can accelerate sampling handling and provide high-performance analysis with benchtop instrument. By participating in the NSF-ICORP program, we have moved forward through translational research and technical development, learned the strategies for transition to the marketplace, and prepared for technology commercialization.  The project improved the technology with metal-enhanced plasmonic microarray to enhance MALDI-MS performance. The use of microarray simplifies sample handling, improves fluorescence imaging, and enables high throughput analysis. It will benefit society for elevating single cell analysis capability. The plasmonic substrates improved ionization efficiency in the MALDI process, allowing direct analysis of lipid signatures of bacterial species that potentially lead to rapid microbial species ID.  The project provided excellent learning experience for students to understand the values of market analysis, customer needs, IP process and protection, and technology transfer. The close interactions with industry offered unique opportunities to look at key issues beyond technology and provided students knowledge and skills for moving career direction to become tech leaders in future. With the interviews with industrial leaders and interactions with cohort of the program, our students have built valuable network that can have very positive impact to their career development.         Last Modified: 05/08/2022       Submitted by: Quan Cheng]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
