<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Advancing Sustainable Low Carbon Energy]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>71248.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>71248</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01060500</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OIA</Abbreviation>
<LongName>OIA-Office of Integrative Activities</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Mike Pozmantier</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mpozmant@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924475</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This project will bring together a broad group of stakeholders including industry, academia and government covering areas ranging from technical to economics, and other areas related to adoption for a moderated discussion of priorities, collaborative topics and deliverables related to sustainability through deployment of low carbon energy systems. This will provide a framework and path for impactful results that will result in the rapid deployment of sustainable energy paradigms in the short term. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Development of sustainable energy paradigms that are economically realizable and reliable remains at the forefront of technological development and policy drivers. Important challenges are developing grid-scale energy storage that is reliable and affordable, innovating novel carbon capture, utilization and sequestration (CCUS) that is economically feasible, reducing the energy and environmental footprint of chemical conversion, imagining and delivering a decarbonized and affordable industrial energy and a truly circular plastics economy that ensures a zero-waste paradigm. The convergence of advancing science and engineering focusing on issues of energy and sustainability including carbon management, renewable energy and alternate fuels such as hydrogen and energy storage are crucial to drive the energy transition. Moreover, developing the capabilities and competencies of the workforce and the tools that &lt;br/&gt;will enable this transition.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/21/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/14/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.083</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2037573</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ramanan</FirstName>
<LastName>Krishnamoorti</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ramanan Krishnamoorti</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ramanan@uh.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000199942</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/21/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Houston</Name>
<CityName>HOUSTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>772043067</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7137435773</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4300 MARTIN LUTHER KING BLVD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>QKWEF8XLMTT3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF HOUSTON SYSTEM</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Houston]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>772042015</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>066Y</Code>
<Text>Program Planning and Policy De</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~71248</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Accelerating the development and deployment of sustainable low-carbon energy solutions is required to continue to grow the availability of affordable, reliable and environmentally responsible energy for all, and make the US lead the energy transition world. The convergence of advancing the science and engineering of energy and sustainability, including carbon management, renewable energy, alternate fuels such as methanol and hydrogen, energy storage, and the circular economy, is necessary for driving this acceleration. Moreover, their alignment with policy and social drivers such as human behavior are crucial. Perhaps, the strongest accelerator for the transition relies on developing capabilities and competencies of the workforce with interdisciplinary tools. These include big data analytics, the integration of real-time artificial intelligence and machine learning with virtual and augmented reality to advance decision-making, and advanced technologies These technological and workforce assets must be complemented by aligning regulatory policy, public policy and business policy to improve and enhance the rapid adoption of such a sustainable energy paradigm.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Four distinct areas that contribute to the low-carbon energy systems of the future are seen as crucial accelerators of the energy transition: (a) Greenhouse gas mitigation through carbon capture, utilization and storage; (b) Process efficiency and process electrification; (c) Integration of renewable energy and incorporation of alternate fuels; and (d) Circular plastics and chemicals. The study here identifies tracks within these areas and crosscutting these areas that highlight convergence of scientific themes and their social drivers with the ambitious goal of leading to &ldquo;Net Zero by 2050&rdquo;. However, for significant progress to be made in the short-term and provide a solid basis for the future, four elements must be addressed simultaneously:</p> <p>(i) Establishment of crucial commercial deployments of carbon mitigation measures including circular plastic technologies, early successes of process efficiencies through electrification, and integration of renewables into a stable and reliable energy supply chain;</p> <p>(ii) Development of hardware infrastructure networks for the transport of carbon dioxide, alternate fuels, and electricity that underscore the ability to generate or use these in modular and distributed sites;</p> <p>(iii) Harmonization of public and regulatory policy drivers from the local to the national scales and across value chains with the intent to decarbonize the energy sector while maintaining affordability and reliability; and</p> <p>(iv) Development of an effective and nimble multi-disciplinary workforce that can adapt to a rapidly changing energy sector and further encourage and build awareness and knowledge across the population.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The study has identified 18 tracks of convergence enhanced fields in the four pillars that will rapidly accelerate acceleration the energy transition. The issues of improving efficiency, integrating renewables, adopting decarbonization and measuring it along with shifts in policies and social behaviors crosscut these tracks. The underlying interactions across those tracks and pillars and the connective tissue of enabling technologies and policies will define the pace of the energy transition. A significant challenge that the impending energy transition must confront is raising the awareness of a broad public and readying a workforce that is ready to integrate broad and disparate issues of science, technology and societal changes, and yet be nimble to adopt advances from adjacent spheres of influence.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/20/2022<br>      Modified by: Ramanan&nbsp;Krishnamoorti</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Accelerating the development and deployment of sustainable low-carbon energy solutions is required to continue to grow the availability of affordable, reliable and environmentally responsible energy for all, and make the US lead the energy transition world. The convergence of advancing the science and engineering of energy and sustainability, including carbon management, renewable energy, alternate fuels such as methanol and hydrogen, energy storage, and the circular economy, is necessary for driving this acceleration. Moreover, their alignment with policy and social drivers such as human behavior are crucial. Perhaps, the strongest accelerator for the transition relies on developing capabilities and competencies of the workforce with interdisciplinary tools. These include big data analytics, the integration of real-time artificial intelligence and machine learning with virtual and augmented reality to advance decision-making, and advanced technologies These technological and workforce assets must be complemented by aligning regulatory policy, public policy and business policy to improve and enhance the rapid adoption of such a sustainable energy paradigm.     Four distinct areas that contribute to the low-carbon energy systems of the future are seen as crucial accelerators of the energy transition: (a) Greenhouse gas mitigation through carbon capture, utilization and storage; (b) Process efficiency and process electrification; (c) Integration of renewable energy and incorporation of alternate fuels; and (d) Circular plastics and chemicals. The study here identifies tracks within these areas and crosscutting these areas that highlight convergence of scientific themes and their social drivers with the ambitious goal of leading to "Net Zero by 2050". However, for significant progress to be made in the short-term and provide a solid basis for the future, four elements must be addressed simultaneously:  (i) Establishment of crucial commercial deployments of carbon mitigation measures including circular plastic technologies, early successes of process efficiencies through electrification, and integration of renewables into a stable and reliable energy supply chain;  (ii) Development of hardware infrastructure networks for the transport of carbon dioxide, alternate fuels, and electricity that underscore the ability to generate or use these in modular and distributed sites;  (iii) Harmonization of public and regulatory policy drivers from the local to the national scales and across value chains with the intent to decarbonize the energy sector while maintaining affordability and reliability; and  (iv) Development of an effective and nimble multi-disciplinary workforce that can adapt to a rapidly changing energy sector and further encourage and build awareness and knowledge across the population.     The study has identified 18 tracks of convergence enhanced fields in the four pillars that will rapidly accelerate acceleration the energy transition. The issues of improving efficiency, integrating renewables, adopting decarbonization and measuring it along with shifts in policies and social behaviors crosscut these tracks. The underlying interactions across those tracks and pillars and the connective tissue of enabling technologies and policies will define the pace of the energy transition. A significant challenge that the impending energy transition must confront is raising the awareness of a broad public and readying a workforce that is ready to integrate broad and disparate issues of science, technology and societal changes, and yet be nimble to adopt advances from adjacent spheres of influence.       Last Modified: 06/20/2022       Submitted by: Ramanan Krishnamoorti]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
