<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SII Planning Grant: National Center for Radio Spectrum Innovations (NCRSI)]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>300000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>300000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AST</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ashley  Vanderley</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bevander@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922428</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This award is a planning grant for the Spectrum Innovation Initiative:  National Center for Wireless Spectrum Research (SII-Center).  The focus of a spectrum research SII-Center goes beyond 5G, IoT, and other existing or forthcoming systems and technologies to chart out a trajectory to ensure United States leadership in future wireless technologies, systems, and applications in science and engineering through the efficient use and sharing of the radio spectrum.  The radio spectrum should be utilized to the greatest public benefit at national and global scales. Spectrum shortages, both real and perceived, are leading to conflicts between existing users and anticipated new uses – some of which were not imagined when existing spectrum allocations were made decades ago. Many stakeholders seek to protect and advance their interests, with aspects of these interests overlapping and conflicting with each other. Hence, the public debate over the optimal model for managing spectrum is a complex interplay of technology, economics, law and regulation, policy, and the history of past successes and failures.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is aimed at the development of a comprehensive plan for an SII-Center which would help maintain and extend US leadership in future wireless technologies, systems, and applications in science and engineering through the efficient use and sharing of radio spectrum. The project team is led by the University of Notre Dame, with partners from Northwestern University, Clemson University, University of California, Berkeley, University of California, Los Angeles, New York University, and Stanford University. The team has an extensive record of successful research, as well as significant and relevant industry and implementation experience.  The project seeks to develop plans for a multi-disciplinary center that emphasizes instrumentation of the radio spectrum; collecting and sharing accurate regulatory, usage, and economic data; and developing data-rich system designs and regulatory policies for more efficient spectrum utilization.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/04/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/04/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2037852</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Honig</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael L Honig</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mlhonig@gmail.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000421069</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/04/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Anant</FirstName>
<LastName>Sahai</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Anant Sahai</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[sahai@eecs.berkeley.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000466924</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/04/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>J. Nicholas</FirstName>
<LastName>Laneman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>J. Nicholas Laneman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jnl@nd.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000394168</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/04/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Danijela</FirstName>
<LastName>Cabric</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Danijela Cabric</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[danijela@ee.ucla.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000527209</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/04/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sachin</FirstName>
<LastName>Katti</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sachin Katti</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[skatti@stanford.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000554437</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/04/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Notre Dame</Name>
<CityName>NOTRE DAME</CityName>
<ZipCode>465565708</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5746317432</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>940 Grace Hall</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IN02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>FPU6XGFXMBE9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF NOTRE DAME DU LAC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>KKBMKNFZ5PJ4</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Notre Dame]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>465565637</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IN02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>151Y</Code>
<Text>SII-Spectrum Innovation Initia</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>4444</Code>
<Text>INTERDISCIPLINARY PROPOSALS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~300000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-050dccfd-7fff-9d62-db59-31dbc1550c5c"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>SpectrumX (</span><a href="http://spectrumx.org/"><span>http://spectrumx.org</span></a><span>) became the first National Science Foundation (NSF) Spectrum Innovation Center, following the development of plans to engage in interdisciplinary innovations in radio spectrum research, education and workforce development, collaboration, management, and policy outreach. Coordination with the NSF, the Federal Communications Commission (FCC), the National Telecommunications and Information Administration (NTIA), a broader Government Working Group, and key industry partners has been established. SpectrumX formed from merging four Planning Grant teams--</span><span>NCRSI, OSIIC, WHISPERS, and WISE--</span><span>and now consists of a growing team of 41 researchers from 27 top universities, a key federal research facility (NRAO), a pioneering company (VA Diodes), and numerous collaborators all led by the Wireless Institute at the University of Notre Dame.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>SpectrumX has identified 6 flagship research projects to pursue breakthroughs at many levels -- in scientific receivers, spectrum sensing, coexistence and sharing mechanisms, cloud automation, flexible licenses, and enforcement. SpectrumX has also developed plans for holistic educational outreach and training, including citizen science, Grade 6-12, undergraduate, and graduate curriculum development as well as Research and Training Experiences (RTEs). Concrete pathways for diversifying the spectrum workforce have been established through partnerships with 15 minority-service and majority non-white institutions. SpectrumX will also integrate and streamline extensive facilities and resources across its partner institutions, and pursue new infrastructures. All of these activities will be enhanced through coordination interfaces for strategic planning, project collaboration, broadening participation, and policy outreach. To manage all of these activities, SpectrumX has matured an inclusive organizational culture with working groups and leadership roles throughout the planning process.</span></p> <p><span id="docs-internal-guid-19ac8026-7fff-1dad-8f2f-8629b964b3b1"><span>SII PG: AST20-37852, $300,000, 2020-2021, National Center for Radio Spectrum Innovations (NCRSI). PI: Laneman; Co-PIs: Honig, Sahai, Cabric, Katti. SII PG: AST20-37732, $198,809, 2020-2021, Olin Spectrum Innovation Initiative Center (OSIIC). PI: Lohmeyer. Grant: AST20-37838, $299,720, 2020- 2021, SII Planning: WHISPERS: Wireless Hardware Innovations and Signal Processing for Enhanced Radio Astronomy and Scientific Spectrum Sharing. PI: Weikle; Co-PIs: Sidiropoulos, Berry, Beasley, Schoenthal. SII PG: AST20-37918, $299,942, 2020-2021, SII Planning: Creating a Visionary, Interdisciplinary, and Transformational National Center for Spectrum and Wireless Systems Research (WISE). PI: Palo; Co-PIs: Cosman, Solis, Weiss, Gremban.</span></span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/04/2021<br>      Modified by: J. Nicholas&nbsp;Laneman</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   SpectrumX (http://spectrumx.org) became the first National Science Foundation (NSF) Spectrum Innovation Center, following the development of plans to engage in interdisciplinary innovations in radio spectrum research, education and workforce development, collaboration, management, and policy outreach. Coordination with the NSF, the Federal Communications Commission (FCC), the National Telecommunications and Information Administration (NTIA), a broader Government Working Group, and key industry partners has been established. SpectrumX formed from merging four Planning Grant teams--NCRSI, OSIIC, WHISPERS, and WISE--and now consists of a growing team of 41 researchers from 27 top universities, a key federal research facility (NRAO), a pioneering company (VA Diodes), and numerous collaborators all led by the Wireless Institute at the University of Notre Dame. SpectrumX has identified 6 flagship research projects to pursue breakthroughs at many levels -- in scientific receivers, spectrum sensing, coexistence and sharing mechanisms, cloud automation, flexible licenses, and enforcement. SpectrumX has also developed plans for holistic educational outreach and training, including citizen science, Grade 6-12, undergraduate, and graduate curriculum development as well as Research and Training Experiences (RTEs). Concrete pathways for diversifying the spectrum workforce have been established through partnerships with 15 minority-service and majority non-white institutions. SpectrumX will also integrate and streamline extensive facilities and resources across its partner institutions, and pursue new infrastructures. All of these activities will be enhanced through coordination interfaces for strategic planning, project collaboration, broadening participation, and policy outreach. To manage all of these activities, SpectrumX has matured an inclusive organizational culture with working groups and leadership roles throughout the planning process.  SII PG: AST20-37852, $300,000, 2020-2021, National Center for Radio Spectrum Innovations (NCRSI). PI: Laneman; Co-PIs: Honig, Sahai, Cabric, Katti. SII PG: AST20-37732, $198,809, 2020-2021, Olin Spectrum Innovation Initiative Center (OSIIC). PI: Lohmeyer. Grant: AST20-37838, $299,720, 2020- 2021, SII Planning: WHISPERS: Wireless Hardware Innovations and Signal Processing for Enhanced Radio Astronomy and Scientific Spectrum Sharing. PI: Weikle; Co-PIs: Sidiropoulos, Berry, Beasley, Schoenthal. SII PG: AST20-37918, $299,942, 2020-2021, SII Planning: Creating a Visionary, Interdisciplinary, and Transformational National Center for Spectrum and Wireless Systems Research (WISE). PI: Palo; Co-PIs: Cosman, Solis, Weiss, Gremban.       Last Modified: 12/04/2021       Submitted by: J. Nicholas Laneman]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
