<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[EAGER: Clima y Cafe: A Climate Change Adaptation Website for Policy and Production Decision-Making Support in Colombian Agriculture]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>71146.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>71146</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SMA</Abbreviation>
<LongName>SBE Off Of Multidisciplinary Activities</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Mary Feeney</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mfeeney@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927197</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[All communities do not have equal access to digital tools due to poverty, poor infrastructure, and lack of education. This is referred to as the digital divide—that is, a gap that exists between people and regions who have access to and are able to use modern information and communication technology and those who cannot. The goal of this project is to learn how we can overcome the digital divide through strategies that encourage online-to-offline sharing within local communities. The research focuses on a newly deployed website (Clima y Café) which is tailored towards Colombian coffee farmers. The project engages with the local community (i.e., local coffee grower associations with internet access) to disseminate digital information to hard-to-reach rural coffee farmers. The project will test four strategies that encourage these associations to engage in information-sharing activities of online content from the Clima y Café website and reduce the barriers of the digital divide that prevent the majority of coffee farmers from gaining access to information. The goal is to provide a novel assessment of the role of communication in constructing affordances to support policy decision-making around complex scientific issues and build a grounded theory from the data that can inform the creation of better digital affordances in other adaptation of complex scientific contexts.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project focuses specifically on addressing the capacity of communication to support climate change adaptation policy and production decision-making for Colombian coffee sector stakeholders. In 2020, the project team launched a digital platform tailored to the Colombian coffee sector to support climate change adaptation. Many farming communities, including Colombian coffee farmers, struggle with digital access, which can prevent much-needed information from reaching them. As such, one of the primary strategies was to leverage a previously identified social network strength, which are self-organizing local coffee-grower associations who have internet access, to serve as a conduit to hard-to-reach farmer populations without internet. This project seeks to uncover whether leveraging internet-access points within a community (local coffee-grower associations) and encouraging them to disseminate information across the digital divide will contribute to local engagement and information spread. This research will test four strategies to see if, how and why they do or do not lead to digital divide bridging affordances in local self-organizing associations to farmers. The four strategies include: (1) WhatsApp video messages, (2) targeted radio segments, (3) in-person small group trainings, and (4) social media engagement (Facebook + Instagram). The work will inform the development of novel models for disseminating digital information to hard-to-reach populations by utilizing the network strengths of their own local communities.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/25/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/14/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2037677</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jessica</FirstName>
<LastName>Eise</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jessica Eise</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jessica.eise@utsa.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000795495</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/25/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Purdue University</Name>
<CityName>WEST LAFAYETTE</CityName>
<ZipCode>479061332</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7654941055</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2550 NORTHWESTERN AVE STE 1900</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IN04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>YRXVL4JYCEF5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PURDUE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>YRXVL4JYCEF5</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Purdue University]]></Name>
<CityName>West Lafayette</CityName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>479072098</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[100 North University Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IN04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>125Y</Code>
<Text>Science of Science</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~71146</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Climate change is already impacting many regions around the world with changing temperatures and weather events. Some of the hardest hit are our farmers, who rely on the climate to grow the food that we need to survive and thrive. Farming depends on weather patterns and when these change, crops can be lost or the harvests reduced. Many farmers around the world live on the brink of poverty, and these variations can mean a loss of livelihood or extreme stress, duress and uncertainty. Our farmers, in every corner of the Earth, need support to adapt to the current or coming changes in the climate in order to protect their livelihoods and wellbeing, but also to ensure continued food security for all of us. Adaptation to climate change means learning to adjust the way we live to new climatic conditions wherever we are so we can continue to thrive. Mitigation means decreasing our greenhouse gas emissions that cause climate change or capturing carbon to decrease existing damage. We need both to occur in tandem now, as our window of opportunity to focus exclusively on mitigation is now gone.&nbsp;</p> <p><em><span>Clima y Caf?</span></em><span>&nbsp;is a blended academic/social project to help farmers adapt to climate change, with its current focus in the Colombian coffee region. It combines research-informed activities with collaborative activities that seek to (1) support farmers with useful, targeted information, resources and solutions, (2) draw attention to their needs and (3) inspire and motivate change in local, regional, national and international communities. This project is based on the website</span>&nbsp;<a href="http://www.climaycafe.com/">www.climaycafe.com</a>. This website was tailored to the community it is for - the Colombian coffee sector - through research to understand what they needed and how they liked to interact with technology. One of the challenges in this area is that many coffee farmers in this region do not have strong access to technology due to infrastructure (the ability to get internet), poverty (inability to buy devices) or education (not knowing how to use technology). Therefore, the current project aims to develop strategies to deliver this digital information to people on the other side of the 'digital divide.' Based on former research, we learned that some people and groups have digital access that can share with others who do not, such as local coffee grower associations. We explored different strategies to share this information. These differerent strategies included videos, radio segments, podcasts, posters, calendars, virtual meetings, photography exhibition and a children's schoolbook.</p> <p>This project delivers immediate information on climate change and adaptation, as these farmers face immediate challenges due to climate change impacts. Their ability to adapt will influence the future viability of their livelihoods. In the long-term, our work will help uncover&nbsp;or guide us toward a new model for sharing digital information to hard-to-reach populations by learning about the strengths each community has.&nbsp;Farming communities across the world struggle with internet access and digital accessibility. In the face of climate change, the ability to reach farmer groups across the globe with information that could help them grow and produce food when faced with increasing impacts of climate change (such as droughts, extreme weather events, heat, etc.) could be transformative in preserving their livelihoods and improving food security outcomes. Learning how to share information and science to hard-to-reach populations, such as rural agricultural communities, is very important for protecting our farmers and helping us to adapt to climate change.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/13/2021<br>      Modified by: Jessica&nbsp;Eise</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2037677/2037677_10701970_1639446416443_PhotoofSession(1)--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2037677/2037677_10701970_1639446416443_PhotoofSession(1)--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Team member filming"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2037677/2037677_10701970_1639446416443_PhotoofSession(1)--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Team member filming"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Team member Mario Isaza interviews a female coffee farmer on her relationship with the environment.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Diana Meza</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jessica&nbsp;Eise</div> <div class="imageTitle">Team member filming</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2037677/2037677_10701970_1639446640070_PhotoofSession--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2037677/2037677_10701970_1639446640070_PhotoofSession--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Preparing to film"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2037677/2037677_10701970_1639446640070_PhotoofSession--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Preparing to film"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Mario Isaza and Nico Gomez prepare to film and photograph farmers as they share adaptation strategies to climate change</div> <div class="imageCredit">Diana Meza</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jessica&nbsp;Eise</div> <div class="imageTitle">Preparing to film</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2037677/2037677_10701970_1639446775959_Team--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2037677/2037677_10701970_1639446775959_Team--rgov-800width.jpg" title="The team in virtual meeting"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2037677/2037677_10701970_1639446775959_Team--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="The team in virtual meeting"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Due to the pandemic, the team had to conduct most of the work remotely, and met weekly in virtual meetings</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jessica Eise</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jessica&nbsp;Eise</div> <div class="imageTitle">The team in virtual meeting</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Climate change is already impacting many regions around the world with changing temperatures and weather events. Some of the hardest hit are our farmers, who rely on the climate to grow the food that we need to survive and thrive. Farming depends on weather patterns and when these change, crops can be lost or the harvests reduced. Many farmers around the world live on the brink of poverty, and these variations can mean a loss of livelihood or extreme stress, duress and uncertainty. Our farmers, in every corner of the Earth, need support to adapt to the current or coming changes in the climate in order to protect their livelihoods and wellbeing, but also to ensure continued food security for all of us. Adaptation to climate change means learning to adjust the way we live to new climatic conditions wherever we are so we can continue to thrive. Mitigation means decreasing our greenhouse gas emissions that cause climate change or capturing carbon to decrease existing damage. We need both to occur in tandem now, as our window of opportunity to focus exclusively on mitigation is now gone.   Clima y Caf? is a blended academic/social project to help farmers adapt to climate change, with its current focus in the Colombian coffee region. It combines research-informed activities with collaborative activities that seek to (1) support farmers with useful, targeted information, resources and solutions, (2) draw attention to their needs and (3) inspire and motivate change in local, regional, national and international communities. This project is based on the website www.climaycafe.com. This website was tailored to the community it is for - the Colombian coffee sector - through research to understand what they needed and how they liked to interact with technology. One of the challenges in this area is that many coffee farmers in this region do not have strong access to technology due to infrastructure (the ability to get internet), poverty (inability to buy devices) or education (not knowing how to use technology). Therefore, the current project aims to develop strategies to deliver this digital information to people on the other side of the 'digital divide.' Based on former research, we learned that some people and groups have digital access that can share with others who do not, such as local coffee grower associations. We explored different strategies to share this information. These differerent strategies included videos, radio segments, podcasts, posters, calendars, virtual meetings, photography exhibition and a children's schoolbook.  This project delivers immediate information on climate change and adaptation, as these farmers face immediate challenges due to climate change impacts. Their ability to adapt will influence the future viability of their livelihoods. In the long-term, our work will help uncover or guide us toward a new model for sharing digital information to hard-to-reach populations by learning about the strengths each community has. Farming communities across the world struggle with internet access and digital accessibility. In the face of climate change, the ability to reach farmer groups across the globe with information that could help them grow and produce food when faced with increasing impacts of climate change (such as droughts, extreme weather events, heat, etc.) could be transformative in preserving their livelihoods and improving food security outcomes. Learning how to share information and science to hard-to-reach populations, such as rural agricultural communities, is very important for protecting our farmers and helping us to adapt to climate change.       Last Modified: 12/13/2021       Submitted by: Jessica Eise]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
