<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Societal Trust and Health amidst COVID-19, and an Evaluation Framework for the Societal Experts Action Network (SEAN)]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>199933.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>199933</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SMA</Abbreviation>
<LongName>SBE Off Of Multidisciplinary Activities</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Lee Walker</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lwalker@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927174</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Too often, decision-makers in government and business have been unable to extract actionable information from scientific studies. As a result, the potential public benefit from that knowledge is blunted. The Societal Experts Action Network (SEAN) is a unique effort to bridge that gap and improve transmission of actionable insights from the social, behavioral, and economic (SBE) sciences to decision-makers who can benefit from the knowledge. SEAN is part of the National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine (NASEM) focus on COVID-19. In coordination with the NASEM Standing Committee on Emerging Infectious Diseases and 21st Century Health Threats, SEAN provides SBE data and recommendations on social, behavioral, and economic (SBE) matters to decision-makers and the public. One of SEAN’s key goals is to rapidly gather and communicate actionable scientific evidence to public officials and other leaders who are managing the pandemic and working toward recovery.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will 1) utilize survey data gathered under SEAN’s auspices to examine societal trust and its relationships to health outcomes, and 2) create a framework for an evaluative assessment of SEAN. It will create original scientific evidence using COVID-19-related survey data and will provide an evaluation of the effectiveness and impact of SEAN’s COVID-19-related communication activities. The first part of this project will analyze survey data associated with the SEAN COVID-19 survey archive to understand the critical role that trust in authorities (medical, scientific, government, media) plays in critical health behaviors by members of the public. COVID-19 represents a grave threat to America’s public health and the well-being of its populace. It is predicted that government officials at the federal, state and local levels who are trusted by members of society to inform them about COVID-19 play a large role in the lay public’s behavioral responses to the disease and, ultimately, their positive health outcomes. In the second part of this project, the research team will work with SEAN leadership, to plan a thorough, external evaluation of SEAN.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/08/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/08/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2037331</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dave</FirstName>
<LastName>Marcotte</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Dave E Marcotte</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[marcotte@american.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000385586</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/08/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Elizabeth</FirstName>
<LastName>Suhay</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Elizabeth Suhay</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[suhay@american.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000322008</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/08/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Aparna</FirstName>
<LastName>Soni</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Aparna Soni</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[asoni@american.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000826217</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/08/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Claudia</FirstName>
<LastName>Persico</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Claudia L Persico</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[cpersico@american.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000828519</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/08/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>American University</Name>
<CityName>WASHINGTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>200168002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2028853440</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4400 MASSACHUSETTS AVE, NW</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>H4VNDUN2VWU5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>AMERICAN UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>H4VNDUN2VWU5</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[American University]]></Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>200168000</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4400 Massachusetts Avenue, NW]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1397</Code>
<Text>Cross-Directorate  Activities</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~199933</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Overview</strong></p> <p>Our grant had two purposes: (1) to provide an external evaluation of the Societal Experts Action Network (SEAN), and (2) to investigate Americans&rsquo; trust in government and health authorities, especially as it relates to the COVID-19 pandemic.</p> <p><strong>Evaluation of the Societal Experts Action Network (SEAN)</strong></p> <p class="Default">To improve national, state, and local governments&rsquo; responses to the unfolding COVID-19 crisis, the National Science Foundation and the National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine (NASEM) partnered to create the Societal Experts Action Network (SEAN). The goal of SEAN was to act as a conduit between academic social scientists and the policymaking community&mdash;synthesizing the best available evidence from the social sciences on addressing the economic and social harms caused by COVID-19 and providing those syntheses to policymakers, especially those at the state and local level.</p> <p>We conducted an external evaluation of SEAN, evaluating SEAN processes and outcomes. We evaluated SEAN founding documents and products (such as reports and webinars). We also interviewed SEAN leadership, NASEM staff, and public officials and organization leaders who had interacted with SEAN. Finally, we conducted an original survey of SEAN users, sending a survey to all attendees of SEAN webinars. We produced a report, published by the School of Public Affairs at American University.</p> <p>STRUCTURE AND PROCESSES</p> <p>SEAN began with clearly articulated structures and processes and appropriately adapted in response to feedback and a rapidly changing pandemic environment. We recommended that a more mature SEAN formalize its structures and processes and better utilize its Advisory Group.</p> <p>TIME HORIZON FOR TASK COMPLETION</p> <p>SEAN consistently produced high-quality academic products in a short time window. We concluded that its rapid pace would be difficult to maintain without more resources.</p> <p>ENGAGEMENT WITH POLICYMAKERS</p> <p>SEAN engaged with many partners to better understand policymaker needs. We recommended that SEAN expand its engagement, reaching out to organizations outside its existing network and increasing interactions with federal policymakers.</p> <p>USABILITY</p> <p>SEAN provided readily understood guidance for the policymaking community. We concluded that SEAN&rsquo;s products could be made even more understandable to lay people and that their website could be made easier to navigate.</p> <p>AUDIENCE AND REACH</p> <p>SEAN built a significant audience quickly by using existing NASEM networks and organizational partners. We suggested SEAN expand its reach beyond the academic community, especially to include more policymakers. This included making its findings more discoverable via the Web.</p> <p><strong>Public Opinion on Trust in Government</strong></p> <p><em>Americans&rsquo; Trust in Government and Health Behaviors During the COVID-19 Pandemic</em></p> <p>The importance of trust in government amidst health emergencies has become apparent, especially given its impact on health behavior. Yet, scholars often treat trust simplistically, measuring it at one point in time and in a unidimensional way. We use a unique series of surveys carried out during the first year of the pandemic to examine changing trust in different government actors over time and then link relative trust to compliance with expert-recommended health behaviors. We find that trust in government declined during this period, with especially large declines for federal and state relative to local government. We find somewhat steeper declines among women, Black Americans, the less educated, and Republicans. Finally, we find that trust in state governments and local health officials was positively associated with protective health behaviors, especially among Republicans, while trust in the federal government was associated with a <em>lower</em> likelihood of such behaviors.</p> <p>Citation: Suhay, Elizabeth, Aparna Soni, Claudia Persico, and Dave E. Marcotte. 2022. <em>RSF: The Russell Sage Foundation Journal of the Social Sciences 8</em>(8): 221-244.</p> <p><em>Unemployment, Benefits, and Trust in Government</em></p> <p>Trust in government institutions has been implicated in a wide array of important social and political outcomes. However, there is very little research on how economic cycles affect people&rsquo;s confidence in various institutions. We examine how individuals&rsquo; trust in different levels of government varies with their state unemployment rate, conditional on a variety of demographic controls and state and year fixed effects. In contrast with previous research, we find that the downward trend in trust in the federal government is not moderated by the business cycle, but a higher unemployment rate reduces public trust in state and local government. We also find that the relationship between unemployment and trust in state/local government is moderated by partisanship; the relationship is present only among those whose preferred party controls their state&rsquo;s governorship. Finally, we use state-level policy changes in the amount and length of unemployment benefits across states and over time to estimate the effect of benefits on public trust. We find that increasing the length of benefits is associated with increased trust in state governments, which control those benefits.</p> <p>Citation: Persico, Claudia, Dave E. Marcotte, Elizabeth Suhay, and Aparna Soni. 2022. Unemployment, Benefits, and Trust in Government. Paper presented at the annual conference of the Association for Public Policy and Management. Washington, D.C.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/27/2023<br>      Modified by: Elizabeth&nbsp;Suhay</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Overview  Our grant had two purposes: (1) to provide an external evaluation of the Societal Experts Action Network (SEAN), and (2) to investigate Americans’ trust in government and health authorities, especially as it relates to the COVID-19 pandemic.  Evaluation of the Societal Experts Action Network (SEAN) To improve national, state, and local governments’ responses to the unfolding COVID-19 crisis, the National Science Foundation and the National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine (NASEM) partnered to create the Societal Experts Action Network (SEAN). The goal of SEAN was to act as a conduit between academic social scientists and the policymaking community&mdash;synthesizing the best available evidence from the social sciences on addressing the economic and social harms caused by COVID-19 and providing those syntheses to policymakers, especially those at the state and local level.  We conducted an external evaluation of SEAN, evaluating SEAN processes and outcomes. We evaluated SEAN founding documents and products (such as reports and webinars). We also interviewed SEAN leadership, NASEM staff, and public officials and organization leaders who had interacted with SEAN. Finally, we conducted an original survey of SEAN users, sending a survey to all attendees of SEAN webinars. We produced a report, published by the School of Public Affairs at American University.  STRUCTURE AND PROCESSES  SEAN began with clearly articulated structures and processes and appropriately adapted in response to feedback and a rapidly changing pandemic environment. We recommended that a more mature SEAN formalize its structures and processes and better utilize its Advisory Group.  TIME HORIZON FOR TASK COMPLETION  SEAN consistently produced high-quality academic products in a short time window. We concluded that its rapid pace would be difficult to maintain without more resources.  ENGAGEMENT WITH POLICYMAKERS  SEAN engaged with many partners to better understand policymaker needs. We recommended that SEAN expand its engagement, reaching out to organizations outside its existing network and increasing interactions with federal policymakers.  USABILITY  SEAN provided readily understood guidance for the policymaking community. We concluded that SEAN’s products could be made even more understandable to lay people and that their website could be made easier to navigate.  AUDIENCE AND REACH  SEAN built a significant audience quickly by using existing NASEM networks and organizational partners. We suggested SEAN expand its reach beyond the academic community, especially to include more policymakers. This included making its findings more discoverable via the Web.  Public Opinion on Trust in Government  Americans’ Trust in Government and Health Behaviors During the COVID-19 Pandemic  The importance of trust in government amidst health emergencies has become apparent, especially given its impact on health behavior. Yet, scholars often treat trust simplistically, measuring it at one point in time and in a unidimensional way. We use a unique series of surveys carried out during the first year of the pandemic to examine changing trust in different government actors over time and then link relative trust to compliance with expert-recommended health behaviors. We find that trust in government declined during this period, with especially large declines for federal and state relative to local government. We find somewhat steeper declines among women, Black Americans, the less educated, and Republicans. Finally, we find that trust in state governments and local health officials was positively associated with protective health behaviors, especially among Republicans, while trust in the federal government was associated with a lower likelihood of such behaviors.  Citation: Suhay, Elizabeth, Aparna Soni, Claudia Persico, and Dave E. Marcotte. 2022. RSF: The Russell Sage Foundation Journal of the Social Sciences 8(8): 221-244.  Unemployment, Benefits, and Trust in Government  Trust in government institutions has been implicated in a wide array of important social and political outcomes. However, there is very little research on how economic cycles affect people’s confidence in various institutions. We examine how individuals’ trust in different levels of government varies with their state unemployment rate, conditional on a variety of demographic controls and state and year fixed effects. In contrast with previous research, we find that the downward trend in trust in the federal government is not moderated by the business cycle, but a higher unemployment rate reduces public trust in state and local government. We also find that the relationship between unemployment and trust in state/local government is moderated by partisanship; the relationship is present only among those whose preferred party controls their state’s governorship. Finally, we use state-level policy changes in the amount and length of unemployment benefits across states and over time to estimate the effect of benefits on public trust. We find that increasing the length of benefits is associated with increased trust in state governments, which control those benefits.  Citation: Persico, Claudia, Dave E. Marcotte, Elizabeth Suhay, and Aparna Soni. 2022. Unemployment, Benefits, and Trust in Government. Paper presented at the annual conference of the Association for Public Policy and Management. Washington, D.C.          Last Modified: 10/27/2023       Submitted by: Elizabeth Suhay]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
