<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[I-Corps: A physicochemical method for improving microorganism viability during manufacturing and storage]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ruth Shuman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rshuman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922160</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this I-Corps project is to develop technology to improve the viability and stability of microorganisms during manufacturing and thus enable the availability and efficacy of probiotics for use in the food, supplements, cosmetics, personal care products, animal feed, agriculture, and/or therapeutic industries. Current processing methods of probiotics cause significant cellular stresses and result in cell death, consequently limiting the efficacy and the number of probiotic species commercially available. This innovation may enable current production lines to manufacture novel probiotics without the need for costly equipment modifications and for new, beneficial species to be brought to market. Many bacteria species have been identified as targets for therapeutic use in a number of gastrointestinal disorders (e.g., Crohn’s, ulcerative colitis, colorectal cancer), for improved wellness in humans and animals, and for enhanced crop production. For example, the use of probiotics in livestock can improve growth and mitigate the use of antibiotics. The innovation may provide a safe and cost-effective method to bring these bacterial targets to market.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project is based on an the development of encapsulation technology that may be applied to protect cells. A major bottleneck in the commercialization of beneficial living microorganisms is manufacturing and storage. Current processes cause significant thermal, shear, osmotic, and oxidative stresses that impact the viability of microorganisms. Protection strategies currently used to enhance viability include addition of protective agents, controlling processing parameters, and prestressing the microorganisms prior to drying. The proposed technology uses a self-assembling, inorganic-organic hybrid coating for the protection of microorganisms during manufacturing. This material is biocompatible, permeable, thermally and mechanically stable, pH-responsive, functionalizable, acts as a reactive oxygen species (ROS) scavenger, and is made from generally recognized as safe (GRAS) ingredients. Previous work has demonstrated that this material can coat living cells and impart cytoprotective qualities (e.g., against UV radiation, lytic enzymes, and silver nanoparticles), enhance the Young’s modulus of the membrane, resist proteases, and increase antioxidant capacity, which benefits the stability of the microorganisms under stress.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/22/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/22/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2037748</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ariel</FirstName>
<LastName>Furst</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ariel L Furst</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[afurst@mit.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000686677</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/22/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Massachusetts Institute of Technology</Name>
<CityName>CAMBRIDGE</CityName>
<ZipCode>021394301</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6172531000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>77 MASSACHUSETTS AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>E2NYLCDML6V1</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MASSACHUSETTS INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>E2NYLCDML6V1</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Massachusetts Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021394307</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The major goals of this NSF I-Corps project were to participate in in an immersive, experiential learning process about innovation and learn how to find product market fit. Initially, the goal of this project was to explore industrial applications and potential challenges involved in delivering microbial soil inoculants to farmers for increased crop performance. From the program, we received training in identifying customer needs and pain points and developing value propositions for our technology. Based on the customer discovery interviews performed during the program, we pivoted to explore the probiotics industry. This is largely due to our findings of slim margins in agriculture. After completing the program, our vision for the project has shifted to meet the demands of microbiome therapeutics and probiotic supplements, which have similar needs and pain points to our initial target industry and can thus be pursued in parallel. In addition to the training received from participating in the I-Corps program, we have developed and implemented entrepreneurship curriculum based on our learnings in a Chemistry Lab course that serves 80-100 students per year. This curriculum implementation is anticipated to enable education on topics related to startup companies and entrepreneurship to reach and impact significantly more students than those that benefitted directly from the I-Corps program.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/29/2022<br>      Modified by: Ariel&nbsp;L&nbsp;Furst</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The major goals of this NSF I-Corps project were to participate in in an immersive, experiential learning process about innovation and learn how to find product market fit. Initially, the goal of this project was to explore industrial applications and potential challenges involved in delivering microbial soil inoculants to farmers for increased crop performance. From the program, we received training in identifying customer needs and pain points and developing value propositions for our technology. Based on the customer discovery interviews performed during the program, we pivoted to explore the probiotics industry. This is largely due to our findings of slim margins in agriculture. After completing the program, our vision for the project has shifted to meet the demands of microbiome therapeutics and probiotic supplements, which have similar needs and pain points to our initial target industry and can thus be pursued in parallel. In addition to the training received from participating in the I-Corps program, we have developed and implemented entrepreneurship curriculum based on our learnings in a Chemistry Lab course that serves 80-100 students per year. This curriculum implementation is anticipated to enable education on topics related to startup companies and entrepreneurship to reach and impact significantly more students than those that benefitted directly from the I-Corps program.       Last Modified: 01/29/2022       Submitted by: Ariel L Furst]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
