<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SII Planning: SPECTRA: Spectrum Policies, Economics, Coexistence, and Technological Research Advancements]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>175000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>175000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AST</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ashley  Vanderley</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bevander@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922428</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This award is a planning grant for the Spectrum Innovation Initiative:  National Center for Wireless Spectrum Research (SII-Center).  The focus of a spectrum research SII-Center goes beyond 5G, IoT, and other existing or forthcoming systems and technologies to chart out a trajectory to ensure United States leadership in future wireless technologies, systems, and applications in science and engineering through the efficient use and sharing of the radio spectrum. This award is for planning activities for a Center of Spectrum Policies, Economics, Coexistence, and Technological Research Advancements (SPECTRA), which will be a center of excellence for all spectrum-related issues for all stakeholders including government (federal, state and local, including regulatory agencies), industry, defense. The center will focus on future spectrum issues, projecting 5 to 10 years and beyond. The center will foster a multidisciplinary effort drawing on key contributors from the academia, industry partners ranging from service providers, equipment suppliers, and semiconductor manufacturers, as well as government labs. SPECTRA will work collaboratively with all stakeholders as part of its research activities but also from the beginning of the planning stages. A number of research theme areas will be explored during the SPECTRA planning process, including regulatory policies, new frequency bands, radio astronomy, atmospherics, weather sciences, cognitive radar, and cognitive radio. Spectrum partnership with all stakeholders, which includes an international component, will be developed in planning the SPECTRA Center and preparing a full spectrum innovation initiative center proposal. Collaborations and integrations with national and international leading radio test beds will be explored in planning SPECTRA infrastructure. One of the most critical efforts in the SPECTRA Center is the education and workforce development in radio spectrum science and engineering, which will be conducted by not only academic institutions, but also industry and other spectrum stakeholders. SPECTRA Center will address societal issues, serve communities, and contribute to reducing socioeconomic disparities in science, technology, and engineering fields. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award will fund planning activities for a Center of Spectrum Policies, Economics, Coexistence, and Technological Research Advancements (SPECTRA), which will draw expertise and resources from the US and Europe and create a multidisciplinary organization that will conduct research, foster collaboration, and guide policy making in spectrum utilization. Expertise at the center will include electrical engineering, computer science, artificial intelligence, semiconductor device technologies including analog and radio frequency design, information theory, signal processing, statistical interference, quantum sensing and networking, radio frequency safety, public policy, defense communications, law enforcement communications, radio astronomy, atmospherics, weather sciences, economics, physics and neuroscience. SPECTRA will utilize testing facilities, especially those funded by NSF. Topics of research will include new techniques for evaluating and quantifying harmful interference, spectrum sensing, spectrum sharing protocols, the economics of spectrum use, legal issues, dynamic spectrum access and exploitation of new frequency bands such as the Terahertz band, crowd-sensing of a variety of observables for smart environments, location and context awareness, integration of wireless and artificial intelligence, quantum information science applied to networks, and future scenario analysis for spectrum 5-10 years in the future. Topics of research in radio astronomy, atmospherics, and weather sciences will be explored. SPECTRA Center has the means, the expertise, the intention and the drive to bring the fruits of our effort to the broader communities. SPECTRA investigations and experiments will advance scientific research in diverse engineering and applications areas to serve the society and communities. SPECTRA Center carries out significant educational and workforce development programs, including new graduate certificate programs in radio spectrum science and engineering, capstone senior projects utilizing SPECTRA infrastructure, K-12 Summer Camps focused on mentoring students from under-represented communities, and annual radio spectrum summer school and symposium.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/03/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/03/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2037873</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jose</FirstName>
<LastName>Moura</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jose M Moura</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[moura@ece.cmu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000101574</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/03/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yu-Dong</FirstName>
<LastName>Yao</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Yu-Dong Yao</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[yyao@stevens.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000491019</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/03/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Moe</FirstName>
<LastName>Win</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Moe Win</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[moewin@mit.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000370320</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/03/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Victor</FirstName>
<LastName>Lawrence</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Victor Lawrence</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[vlawrenc@stevens.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000201728</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/03/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Stevens Institute of Technology</Name>
<CityName>HOBOKEN</CityName>
<ZipCode>07030</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2012168762</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1 CASTLEPOINT ON HUDSON</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NJ08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>JJ6CN5Y5A2R5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>THE TRUSTEES OF THE STEVENS INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Stevens Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>Hoboken</CityName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>070305991</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Castle Point On Hudson]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NJ08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>151Y</Code>
<Text>SII-Spectrum Innovation Initia</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>4444</Code>
<Text>INTERDISCIPLINARY PROPOSALS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~175000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The major goal of this project (planning grant) is to develop a full proposal to establish a national center of spectrum research, "SPECTRA: Spectrum Policies, Economics, Coexistence,&nbsp;and Technological Research Advancements". SPECTRA Center addresses a wide range of spectrum issues, including spectrum policies, economics, coexistence, and science/engineering research. The following describes four aspects of the SPECTRA Center. (1) Vision: SPECTRA is the national resource meeting the radio spectrum challenges of national and global significance through spectrum innovation. (2) Stakeholders: Universities will play major roles in spectrum research and education; Industry is a major spectrum user segment and it also produces products which use spectrum; Government, at all levels from federal, state, to local government, plays important roles in spectrum policies and uses; Defense is a major spectrum user and spectrum sharing among defense and commercial users is a critical issue in spectrum management; and International Collaborators are important stakeholder due to the nature of spectrum research considering radio astronomy, satellite systems, etc. (3) SPECTRA Expertise: SPECTRA Center expertise areas include, but not limited to, electrical engineering and computer science; radio astronomy; atmospherics and weather sciences; economics; and legal and public policy. (4) SPECTRA Pillars: Five pillars include Spectrum Innovation Research, which covers topics ranging from spectrum sensing, interference mitigation, to spectrum sharing among active and passive spectrum users; Partnerships and Research Infrastructures, which addresses the issue of collaboration among various stakeholders including national labs and NSF funded wireless testbeds and provides a platform for extensive experimentations on radio spectrum usage and interference scenarios; Education and Workforce Development, which develops radio spectrum educational materials and opportunities for students at all levels ranging from high school, community college, undergraduate/graduate programs and prepare students for careers in STEM and radio spectrum; Community Engagement and Broadening Participation, which covers activities including engaging and receiving input from the community and serving the community, especially engaging and serving underserved areas and population; and Systems and Applications, which addresses the issues of new systems, applications, and services development based on spectrum innovation research and through collaboration with industry. A full proposal was completed/submitted: "SII-Center: SPECTRA: Spectrum Policies, Economics, Coexistence, and Technological Research Advancements".</p> <p>In the coming years of world-wide competition, SPECTRA?s goal will be to maintain America?s&nbsp;leadership role in all aspects of spectrum science, technology and societal impact, especially in closing the ?digital divide?. We will see a massive proliferation of mobile devices and applications, which when combined with an aging spectra workforce and changing population demographics, will underscore the importance of SPECTRA?s efforts to integrate partner sites and collaborators around the globe to create a diverse and intellectually vibrant center that serves as the focal point of innovation and knowledge building. Important impacts will include: (a) a paradigm shift in spectrum management that permits timely and reliable access to spectrum for both scientific explorations and commercial applications, (b) hardware and software availability for identifying harmful interference, and (c) higher-quality sensing data for scientific explorations leading to new discoveries. Education and workforce development collaborations and community engagement will move us closer to producing spectrum knowledge workers, with diversity, to satisfy demand in industry, government, and academia in the 21st century.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/12/2022<br>      Modified by: Victor&nbsp;Lawrence</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The major goal of this project (planning grant) is to develop a full proposal to establish a national center of spectrum research, "SPECTRA: Spectrum Policies, Economics, Coexistence, and Technological Research Advancements". SPECTRA Center addresses a wide range of spectrum issues, including spectrum policies, economics, coexistence, and science/engineering research. The following describes four aspects of the SPECTRA Center. (1) Vision: SPECTRA is the national resource meeting the radio spectrum challenges of national and global significance through spectrum innovation. (2) Stakeholders: Universities will play major roles in spectrum research and education; Industry is a major spectrum user segment and it also produces products which use spectrum; Government, at all levels from federal, state, to local government, plays important roles in spectrum policies and uses; Defense is a major spectrum user and spectrum sharing among defense and commercial users is a critical issue in spectrum management; and International Collaborators are important stakeholder due to the nature of spectrum research considering radio astronomy, satellite systems, etc. (3) SPECTRA Expertise: SPECTRA Center expertise areas include, but not limited to, electrical engineering and computer science; radio astronomy; atmospherics and weather sciences; economics; and legal and public policy. (4) SPECTRA Pillars: Five pillars include Spectrum Innovation Research, which covers topics ranging from spectrum sensing, interference mitigation, to spectrum sharing among active and passive spectrum users; Partnerships and Research Infrastructures, which addresses the issue of collaboration among various stakeholders including national labs and NSF funded wireless testbeds and provides a platform for extensive experimentations on radio spectrum usage and interference scenarios; Education and Workforce Development, which develops radio spectrum educational materials and opportunities for students at all levels ranging from high school, community college, undergraduate/graduate programs and prepare students for careers in STEM and radio spectrum; Community Engagement and Broadening Participation, which covers activities including engaging and receiving input from the community and serving the community, especially engaging and serving underserved areas and population; and Systems and Applications, which addresses the issues of new systems, applications, and services development based on spectrum innovation research and through collaboration with industry. A full proposal was completed/submitted: "SII-Center: SPECTRA: Spectrum Policies, Economics, Coexistence, and Technological Research Advancements".  In the coming years of world-wide competition, SPECTRA?s goal will be to maintain America?s leadership role in all aspects of spectrum science, technology and societal impact, especially in closing the ?digital divide?. We will see a massive proliferation of mobile devices and applications, which when combined with an aging spectra workforce and changing population demographics, will underscore the importance of SPECTRA?s efforts to integrate partner sites and collaborators around the globe to create a diverse and intellectually vibrant center that serves as the focal point of innovation and knowledge building. Important impacts will include: (a) a paradigm shift in spectrum management that permits timely and reliable access to spectrum for both scientific explorations and commercial applications, (b) hardware and software availability for identifying harmful interference, and (c) higher-quality sensing data for scientific explorations leading to new discoveries. Education and workforce development collaborations and community engagement will move us closer to producing spectrum knowledge workers, with diversity, to satisfy demand in industry, government, and academia in the 21st century.          Last Modified: 09/12/2022       Submitted by: Victor Lawrence]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
