<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Conference: Measuring the Success of Institutional Efforts at Hispanic-Serving Institutions]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>99007.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>118209</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div. of Equity for Excellence in STEM</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sonja Montas-Hunter</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>smontash@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927404</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[With support from the Improving Undergraduate STEM Education: Hispanic-Serving Institutions (HSI Program), this conference aims to develop and test a series of measures to assess how HSIs achieve success in their efforts to serve their diverse students and improve STEM learning. While many indicators assess individual student retention and graduation, there is less consensus on how to measure the systemic changes needed to improve student learning and graduation rates. By bringing together practitioners from HSIs and scholars to co-develop measures of institutional change at HSIs, we expect to develop and test a series of measures to support work at a diverse set of HSIs, including community colleges, Primarily Undergraduate Institutions, and research-intensive universities.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The specific aims of the project are to operationalize a framework for servingness developed to conceptualize institutional changes necessary to improve educational attainment for the diverse student population at HSIs. The conference will specifically develop and test measures of change for: research development and success; faculty engagement with STEM curricular change and students; faculty success measures; STEM undergraduate student success measures; community engagement; and diverse cultural engagement and recognition. We expect that the identification and use of change measures will assist universities in improving the likelihood of student STEM degree attainment at HSIs. The work will be disseminated broadly through conference participation, publications, and the use of the measures at a diverse group of HSIs around the U.S. The HSI Program aims to enhance undergraduate STEM education and build capacity at HSIs. Projects supported by the HSI Program will also generate new knowledge on how to achieve these aims.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/30/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/20/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2037922</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Beth</FirstName>
<LastName>Mitchneck</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Beth Mitchneck</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[bethm@arizona.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000176163</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/30/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Arizona</Name>
<CityName>TUCSON</CityName>
<ZipCode>85721</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5206266000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>845 N PARK AVE RM 538</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AZ07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>ED44Y3W6P7B9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ARIZONA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Arizona]]></Name>
<CityName>Tucson</CityName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>857194824</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[888 N Euclid Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AZ07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>077Y</Code>
<Text>HSI-Hispanic Serving Instituti</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>102Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-Disproportionate Impcts Inst-Indiv</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8209</Code>
<Text>Improv Undergrad STEM Ed(IUSE)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0420</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0421</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>04002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~99007</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~19202</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Grounded in the servingness framework, this project provides institutions with tools to assess and grow their own structures for indicators of servingness. Servingness emphasizes the institutional role in creating a sense of belonging for students and impacting their academic and non-academic outcomes. This project is likely to change thinking about how to measure student success at colleges and universities that are culturally distinct from predominately white institutions. The intellectual merit of the project is centered on the operationalization of the servingness framework specific to Hispanic-serving institutions (HSIs). The metrics and indicators address the structures that support students, including Institutional Success, Faculty Success, Student Success; Community Engagement, and Research, Scholarship, and Creative Activity. While the servingness framework guided our selection of assessment categories, an institutional transformation framework focuses the metrics on institutional practices, processes, and policies that would need to change to achieve equity for Latinx students and to draw attention to cross institutional practices.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Broader impacts are likely to accrue at HSIs of all types &ndash; research intensive universities to community colleges wish to assess the institutional role in student success. The project outcomes are applicable to a wide range of institutions seeking to answer the question, &ldquo;How do we measure progress toward becoming an institution that serves the racially, ethnically, and economically diverse set of students at Hispanic-Serving Institutions?&rdquo; This question could not be more timely or more critical. Having agencies such as the National Science Foundation encourage the use of these metrics through capacity-building grants and/or reporting requirements could be an additional lever to facilitate their use and help foster institutional accountability. The results of this project also serve as a template for guiding institutional efforts for addressing servingness for other under-served, underrepresented, and minoritized groups.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The concept papers focus on five structures that support institutional success: Institutional Success, Faculty Success, Student Success, Community Engagement, and Research, Scholarship and Creative Activity.&nbsp; The two dimensions of this framework operationalized in the concept papers are: (1) structures for serving (tangible organizational structures), and (2) indicators of serving (measurable outcomes and experiences).&rdquo;&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Key areas deemed critically important for institutional transformation of STEM at HSIs for each of the five structures include:</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>1.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Institutional Success</p> <ul> <li>Institutional mission and value statements, as well as STEM unit statements, specific mention of engaging with and support for the Latinx community inside and outside the institution;</li> <li>Compositional diversity of institutional workforce (faculty, staff, and student) as well as promotion and retention rates should be assessed;</li> <li>Institutional advancement activities should be assessed for the ways that development personnel prioritize relationships that are community-based and equity-related with the Latinx community; and</li> <li>Racialized experiences within the structures must be measured and made visible especially in fields where research has shown the impact on student retention, like in STEM.</li> </ul> <p>2.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Faculty Success</p> <ul> <li>The use of culturally relevant curriculum and pedagogy;</li> <li>Faculty engagement with the Latinx community and diverse students; and</li> <li>Incentive structures (such as performance reviews specifically related to Latinx student success).</li> </ul> <p>3.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Student Success</p> <ul> <li>Meeting basic student needs;</li> <li>Student sense of belonging; and</li> <li>Multi-dimensional revisioning of degree completion metrics.</li> </ul> <p>4.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Community Engagement</p> <ul> <li>Student-facing metrics &ndash; assessing the degree to which students engage in curricular or extra-curricular activities with the Latinx community;</li> <li>Institution-facing metrics &ndash; assessing the degree to which offices throughout the institution incorporate direct input from the Latinx community and to which collaborative projects are co-created; and</li> <li>Community-facing metrics &ndash; the degree to which the community feels engaged in co-creation of activities and included in the educational process.</li> </ul> <p>5.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Research, Scholarship and Creative Activity (RSCA)</p> <ul> <li>HSI grants &ndash; the degree to which an institution applies for and received federal support through grant programs at the NSF, Department of Education, and other federal programs;</li> <li>Compositional diversity and incentive structures for faculty research teams;</li> <li>Use of culturally relevant curriculum and pedagogy as well as availability of undergraduate RSCA opportunities; and</li> <li>Engagement with Latinx community in research projects.</li> </ul> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The complete report and the executive summary detail how the servingness framework can be operationalized to assess a large set of processes and practices at HSIs. They provide ample detail to allow institutions to assess where they are on the path to serving diverse students, especially in STEM. The documents provide guidance for institutions to develop their own assessments specific to their institutional type.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Report- National Science Foundation Hispanic Serving Institution:&nbsp;<a href="https://issuu.com/sbstech/docs/nsf_hsi_report_v3_updated"><strong>Operationalizing the Servingness Framework: Metrics for Institutional Transformation at Hispanic-Serving Institutions</strong></a></p> <p>Executive Summary- National Science Foundation Hispanic Serving Institution Report:&nbsp;<a href="https://issuu.com/sbstech/docs/ua_nsf_hsi_report_-_executive_summary_updated"><strong>Operationalizing the Servingness Framework: Metrics for Institutional Transformation at Hispanic-Serving Institutions</strong></a></p> <p>A peer-reviewed publication will be available at the end of 2023 in <em>Change: The Magazine of Higher Learning</em>, https://www.tandfonline.com/journals/vchn20.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/10/2023<br>      Modified by: Beth&nbsp;Mitchneck</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Grounded in the servingness framework, this project provides institutions with tools to assess and grow their own structures for indicators of servingness. Servingness emphasizes the institutional role in creating a sense of belonging for students and impacting their academic and non-academic outcomes. This project is likely to change thinking about how to measure student success at colleges and universities that are culturally distinct from predominately white institutions. The intellectual merit of the project is centered on the operationalization of the servingness framework specific to Hispanic-serving institutions (HSIs). The metrics and indicators address the structures that support students, including Institutional Success, Faculty Success, Student Success; Community Engagement, and Research, Scholarship, and Creative Activity. While the servingness framework guided our selection of assessment categories, an institutional transformation framework focuses the metrics on institutional practices, processes, and policies that would need to change to achieve equity for Latinx students and to draw attention to cross institutional practices.     Broader impacts are likely to accrue at HSIs of all types &ndash; research intensive universities to community colleges wish to assess the institutional role in student success. The project outcomes are applicable to a wide range of institutions seeking to answer the question, "How do we measure progress toward becoming an institution that serves the racially, ethnically, and economically diverse set of students at Hispanic-Serving Institutions?" This question could not be more timely or more critical. Having agencies such as the National Science Foundation encourage the use of these metrics through capacity-building grants and/or reporting requirements could be an additional lever to facilitate their use and help foster institutional accountability. The results of this project also serve as a template for guiding institutional efforts for addressing servingness for other under-served, underrepresented, and minoritized groups.     The concept papers focus on five structures that support institutional success: Institutional Success, Faculty Success, Student Success, Community Engagement, and Research, Scholarship and Creative Activity.  The two dimensions of this framework operationalized in the concept papers are: (1) structures for serving (tangible organizational structures), and (2) indicators of serving (measurable outcomes and experiences)."      Key areas deemed critically important for institutional transformation of STEM at HSIs for each of the five structures include:     1.    Institutional Success  Institutional mission and value statements, as well as STEM unit statements, specific mention of engaging with and support for the Latinx community inside and outside the institution; Compositional diversity of institutional workforce (faculty, staff, and student) as well as promotion and retention rates should be assessed; Institutional advancement activities should be assessed for the ways that development personnel prioritize relationships that are community-based and equity-related with the Latinx community; and Racialized experiences within the structures must be measured and made visible especially in fields where research has shown the impact on student retention, like in STEM.   2.    Faculty Success  The use of culturally relevant curriculum and pedagogy; Faculty engagement with the Latinx community and diverse students; and Incentive structures (such as performance reviews specifically related to Latinx student success).   3.     Student Success  Meeting basic student needs; Student sense of belonging; and Multi-dimensional revisioning of degree completion metrics.   4.     Community Engagement  Student-facing metrics &ndash; assessing the degree to which students engage in curricular or extra-curricular activities with the Latinx community; Institution-facing metrics &ndash; assessing the degree to which offices throughout the institution incorporate direct input from the Latinx community and to which collaborative projects are co-created; and Community-facing metrics &ndash; the degree to which the community feels engaged in co-creation of activities and included in the educational process.   5.     Research, Scholarship and Creative Activity (RSCA)  HSI grants &ndash; the degree to which an institution applies for and received federal support through grant programs at the NSF, Department of Education, and other federal programs; Compositional diversity and incentive structures for faculty research teams; Use of culturally relevant curriculum and pedagogy as well as availability of undergraduate RSCA opportunities; and Engagement with Latinx community in research projects.      The complete report and the executive summary detail how the servingness framework can be operationalized to assess a large set of processes and practices at HSIs. They provide ample detail to allow institutions to assess where they are on the path to serving diverse students, especially in STEM. The documents provide guidance for institutions to develop their own assessments specific to their institutional type.     Report- National Science Foundation Hispanic Serving Institution: Operationalizing the Servingness Framework: Metrics for Institutional Transformation at Hispanic-Serving Institutions  Executive Summary- National Science Foundation Hispanic Serving Institution Report: Operationalizing the Servingness Framework: Metrics for Institutional Transformation at Hispanic-Serving Institutions  A peer-reviewed publication will be available at the end of 2023 in Change: The Magazine of Higher Learning, https://www.tandfonline.com/journals/vchn20.          Last Modified: 10/10/2023       Submitted by: Beth Mitchneck]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
