<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[NSF/FDA SIR: Focused ultrasound and microbubbles for transport of therapeutics across blood brain barrier: A cellular model]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>100000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>100000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Steve Zehnder</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>szehnder@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927014</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Neurological diseases are the second leading cause of death accounting for 17% of deaths in the US. A major limiting factor for medical interventions with these disorders is the transport of therapeutics past the blood brain barrier (BBB). The BBB has been shown to open transiently in presence of transcranial focused ultrasound (FUS) and microbubbles by disrupting the tight-junction proteins in animal and clinical trials. This offers a promising pathway for therapeutic interventions for neurological disorders. Thus, the goal of this one year NSF/FDA Scholar-in-Residence program is to investigate the effects of FUS and microbubbles on the BBB on a cellular level using a series of cell, microfluidic, and in vitro (lab based) models of the BBB.  The fundamental understanding that is gained from the detailed study of the cellular mechanisms in response to FUS and microbubble treatments can help scientists and clinicians develop more effective and safe treatment options of neurological diseases and disorders for patients. The in vitro BBB model can potentially become another regulatory tool to test criteria outlined in new FDA submissions for the safety and efficacy of the proposed procedures and can be used as a high-throughput model for fast evaluation.  The project will also establish a robust collaboration between the FDA and the Investigator’s lab and provide a unique training experience for a postdoctoral scholar who will in turn use experiences gained at the FDA to mentor high school, undergraduate and graduate students.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is focused on developing validated models to understand the fundamental cellular effects of focused ultrasound (FUS) and microbubbles on the blood brain barrier (BBB).  Though transcranial FUS in the presence of microbubbles is known to reversibly open the BBB and facilitate the delivery of therapeutic compounds with spatial and temporal control, the detailed physical and cellular mechanism of the BBB opening has not been studied, and as a result, it is difficult for regulatory agencies to understand safety-related issues.  The research plan is aimed at closing this gap, with goals of providing a fundamental understanding of the underlying bioeffects and creating a high-throughput in vitro BBB model backed by a physical computational model of induced acoustic stresses. These goals will be achieved by investigating the cellular phenomena in multiple in vitro setups, each more complex than the one before and offering new information. A microfluidic setup with embedded neurons will allow bioeffects investigation in biologically relevant flows. A 3D hydrogel scaffold will also be used to realistically recapitulate the brain morphology. Finally, fluid dynamics models and computation will be used to relate the FUS and microbubble dynamics to the shear stresses and microstreaming flows causing the bioeffects.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/11/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/14/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2037849</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kausik</FirstName>
<LastName>Sarkar</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kausik Sarkar</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[sarkar@gwu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000228546</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/11/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>George Washington University</Name>
<CityName>WASHINGTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>200520042</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2029940728</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1918 F ST NW</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>ECR5E2LU5BL6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GEORGE WASHINGTON UNIVERSITY (THE)</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[George Washington University]]></Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>200520086</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[800 22nd Street NW, Sute 3000]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7236</Code>
<Text>BioP-Biophotonics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~100000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The project supported Ms. Megan Anderson under the FDA/NSF SIR program. Ms. Anderson worked towards her PhD at George Washington University while also interacting with scientists at the FDA on a regular basis. Ms. Anderson completed her PhD coursework and her PhD qualifier. She has been working on acoustic and rheological characterization of hydrogel-based tissue engineering scaffolds.</p> <p>Ms. Anderson synthesized GelMA scaffolds by varying varying GelMA concentration as well as photocuring time. She also performed the first ever ultrasonic characterization of such scaffolds by measuring the speed of sound and the ultrasound attenuation in them. She also measured rheological properties of GelMA scaffold materials using a rheometer for cross validation. Her research showed that ultrasound could be an effective measurement tool for non-invasively measuring the material properties of a scaffold. Currently, she is extending the investigation to agar scaffolds with various glycerol concentrations.</p> <p>Ms. Anderson served as the student representative of the Biomedical Acoustics Technical Committee of the Acoustical Society of America for 2021-2023. She has presented 6 oral presentations in ASA and TEFC meetings. She is a co-author on a journal paper in Soft Matter. Currently she is working on a draft of another journal paper. She has also won scholarships from &nbsp;ARCS (Advancing Science in America) foundation. &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/06/2023<br>      Modified by: Kausik&nbsp;Sarkar</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2037849/2037849_10710764_1683370266565_2Figure--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2037849/2037849_10710764_1683370266565_2Figure--rgov-800width.jpg" title="GelMa hydrogel"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2037849/2037849_10710764_1683370266565_2Figure--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="GelMa hydrogel"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Fabrication of GelMA hydrogel. (a) GelMA solution (b) 3D-printed mold (c) GelMA solution under UV light (d) Crosslinked GelMA hydrogel.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Megan Anderson</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Kausik&nbsp;Sarkar</div> <div class="imageTitle">GelMa hydrogel</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2037849/2037849_10710764_1683370897588_9Figure--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2037849/2037849_10710764_1683370897588_9Figure--rgov-800width.jpg" title="ultrasound speed of sound in GelMa Scaffold"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2037849/2037849_10710764_1683370897588_9Figure--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="ultrasound speed of sound in GelMa Scaffold"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Speed of GelMa scaffold materials with varying curing time and concentration</div> <div class="imageCredit">Megan Anderson</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Kausik&nbsp;Sarkar</div> <div class="imageTitle">ultrasound speed of sound in GelMa Scaffold</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The project supported Ms. Megan Anderson under the FDA/NSF SIR program. Ms. Anderson worked towards her PhD at George Washington University while also interacting with scientists at the FDA on a regular basis. Ms. Anderson completed her PhD coursework and her PhD qualifier. She has been working on acoustic and rheological characterization of hydrogel-based tissue engineering scaffolds.  Ms. Anderson synthesized GelMA scaffolds by varying varying GelMA concentration as well as photocuring time. She also performed the first ever ultrasonic characterization of such scaffolds by measuring the speed of sound and the ultrasound attenuation in them. She also measured rheological properties of GelMA scaffold materials using a rheometer for cross validation. Her research showed that ultrasound could be an effective measurement tool for non-invasively measuring the material properties of a scaffold. Currently, she is extending the investigation to agar scaffolds with various glycerol concentrations.  Ms. Anderson served as the student representative of the Biomedical Acoustics Technical Committee of the Acoustical Society of America for 2021-2023. She has presented 6 oral presentations in ASA and TEFC meetings. She is a co-author on a journal paper in Soft Matter. Currently she is working on a draft of another journal paper. She has also won scholarships from  ARCS (Advancing Science in America) foundation.           Last Modified: 05/06/2023       Submitted by: Kausik Sarkar]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
