<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I: Genomically Optimized Turf Grass]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>253215.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>253215</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Erik Pierstorff</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>epiersto@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922165</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project will develop heartier, environmentally friendly grass varieties. An estimated 30% of US water usage goes to watering lawns and grass, with much of that wasted due to evaporation, runoff and overwatering. Chemical herbicides, pesticides and fertilizers used for grass can be extremely toxic. The project’s genomically optimized turf varieties will require substantially less water and nutrients, preserving precious resources and reducing environmental toxins. In addition, the enhanced root systems in this grass will capture and store carbon for longer time periods than conventional grass, leading to reduced atmospheric carbon. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed project will involve greenhouse and field testing with warm and cold climate turf grass species and varieties, achieving proof of concept in the greenhouse, and then transitioning to outdoor testing and field trials, allowing the project to progress quickly through the early phases of commercialization. The project will focus on: 1) establishing an efficient phenotyping system to monitor root growth in relevant and commercially viable warm and cold climate turf grass species; 2) establishing protocols for assays that involve the cross breeding of different turf varieties with simulations of physiological and chemical root phenotyping in response to that breeding; 3) generating a comprehensive proprietary database of quantitative root growth effects in response to the cross breeding assays, and 4) developing an accurate system to measure the amount of carbon captured and stored in the optimized root system.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/05/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/05/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2037522</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Temte</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John D Temte</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[johntemte@gmail.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000829034</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/05/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>CO2SYNC, INC.</Name>
<CityName>LARAMIE</CityName>
<ZipCode>820704620</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8585181411</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>821 S 10TH ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wyoming</StateName>
<StateCode>WY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WY00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>CTQDNVDAU2L1</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CO2SYNC, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[CO2SYNC, INC.]]></Name>
<CityName>Laramie</CityName>
<StateCode>WY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>820704620</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[821 S 10th St]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wyoming</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WY00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5187</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8038</Code>
<Text>Biotechnology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~253215</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="Normal1"><span lang="EN">Optimized turf grasses with enhanced root systems are one of the few novel and scalable approaches to capture and sequester carbon on a massive global scale. Plants and grasses have the capacity to draw down exponentially more carbon than humans emit each year. However, the majority of the carbon that plants capture is stored temporarily and released quickly. </span></p> <p class="Normal1">The aim of this project was to offer a scalable solution to counteract rising CO<sub>2</sub>&nbsp;levels in the atmosphere by &nbsp;developing an optimized turf grass with a robust root system. Root mass determines the amount of carbon deposited in the soil, root depth and the biochemistry of root structures and root exudates have a major impact on the decomposition rate of the carbon deposited by plants in the soil.</p> <p>The outcomes from our project showed definitively that the Hampton species of Kentucky Blue Grass ("KBG"), affectionaly known as the "Root Monster", formed the deepest and most robust root system of all the KGB species that were tested and studied under the same growing conditions. The Root Monster is also extremely strong, drought resistant and saline tolerant, making it the optimal candidate for the development of an optimized turf grass species that thrives in challenging climates and stores more carbon than other KBG species.</p> <p>It is our conclusion that further optimization of the Root Monster species would lead to a KBG turf species that is better suited for golf couses and parks, helps improve the health and condition of soils, and fights climate change through the capture and storage of higher levels of&nbsp;CO<sub>2.</sub>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/02/2022<br>      Modified by: John&nbsp;D&nbsp;Temte</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2037522/2037522_10716098_1661974645238_IMG_1375--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2037522/2037522_10716098_1661974645238_IMG_1375--rgov-800width.jpg" title="KBG Samples"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2037522/2037522_10716098_1661974645238_IMG_1375--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="KBG Samples"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Kentucky Blue Grass samples growing in the greenhouse</div> <div class="imageCredit">John Temte</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">John&nbsp;D&nbsp;Temte</div> <div class="imageTitle">KBG Samples</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2037522/2037522_10716098_1661974713949_IMG_1101--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2037522/2037522_10716098_1661974713949_IMG_1101--rgov-800width.jpg" title="KBG Close Up"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2037522/2037522_10716098_1661974713949_IMG_1101--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="KBG Close Up"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Close up of KBG samples</div> <div class="imageCredit">John Temte</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">John&nbsp;D&nbsp;Temte</div> <div class="imageTitle">KBG Close Up</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2037522/2037522_10716098_1661974803970_IMG_1470--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2037522/2037522_10716098_1661974803970_IMG_1470--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Root Study"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2037522/2037522_10716098_1661974803970_IMG_1470--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Root Study"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Roots from a KBG samples being prepared for data collection</div> <div class="imageCredit">John Temte</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">John&nbsp;D&nbsp;Temte</div> <div class="imageTitle">Root Study</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2037522/2037522_10716098_1661974869214_IMG_1429--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2037522/2037522_10716098_1661974869214_IMG_1429--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Root Systems"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2037522/2037522_10716098_1661974869214_IMG_1429--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Root Systems"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Roots systems from KBG samples</div> <div class="imageCredit">John Temte</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">John&nbsp;D&nbsp;Temte</div> <div class="imageTitle">Root Systems</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[Optimized turf grasses with enhanced root systems are one of the few novel and scalable approaches to capture and sequester carbon on a massive global scale. Plants and grasses have the capacity to draw down exponentially more carbon than humans emit each year. However, the majority of the carbon that plants capture is stored temporarily and released quickly.  The aim of this project was to offer a scalable solution to counteract rising CO2 levels in the atmosphere by  developing an optimized turf grass with a robust root system. Root mass determines the amount of carbon deposited in the soil, root depth and the biochemistry of root structures and root exudates have a major impact on the decomposition rate of the carbon deposited by plants in the soil.  The outcomes from our project showed definitively that the Hampton species of Kentucky Blue Grass ("KBG"), affectionaly known as the "Root Monster", formed the deepest and most robust root system of all the KGB species that were tested and studied under the same growing conditions. The Root Monster is also extremely strong, drought resistant and saline tolerant, making it the optimal candidate for the development of an optimized turf grass species that thrives in challenging climates and stores more carbon than other KBG species.  It is our conclusion that further optimization of the Root Monster species would lead to a KBG turf species that is better suited for golf couses and parks, helps improve the health and condition of soils, and fights climate change through the capture and storage of higher levels of CO2.           Last Modified: 09/02/2022       Submitted by: John D Temte]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
