<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[I-Corps: Regenerative High-Performance Curtain Wall for Net Zero Energy Buildings]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ruth Shuman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rshuman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922160</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this I-Corps project is the development of a cost-effective regenerative curtain wall specifically configured to achieve building energy cost-savings and user satisfaction for net-zero energy building applications.  Building envelopes contribute to an increase in heating, cooling, and lighting loads inside the building while affecting occupant comfort. This technology, a high-performance regenerative curtain wall, is designed to curtail building energy consumption and carbon dioxide (CO2) emissions to reduce broader societal, economic, and commercial impacts.  The successful application of the technology in commercial buildings is expected to accomplish 95 trillion Btu in annual energy reduction (i.e., $10 billion energy bill saving) and 13 million metric tons of CO2 sequestration.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project is based on the development of a multi-functional, energy-efficient curtain wall system. This regenerative curtain wall incorporates a 3D interlayer of concentrated micro-photovoltaic (CMPV) components within a double-pane glass assembly. Capitalizing on solar radiation, CMPV components consist of silicone-based solar cells with a Fresnel lens, which is a lightweight optical lens whose light concentration efficiency maximizes solar output within a small PV cell area. A key advantage of using the CMPV is that it allows optimization for various building performance needs, including energy efficiency (i.e., reduction of air conditioning load and maximum daylight transmission), user satisfaction (i.e., temperature, relative humidity, glare), and solar-powered energy production. The optimization algorithm for geometric configurations of the system may maximize power production and year-round energy savings for different climate conditions and building orientations where sunlight level varies. Reductions in building operational energy costs from lighting, cooling, and heating loads may result in energy cost savings. In addition, the system’s ability to allow viewing and daylight penetration is expected to improve the health and well-being of building occupants.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/23/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/23/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2037631</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kyoung-Hee</FirstName>
<LastName>Kim</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kyoung-Hee Kim</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[kkim33@uncc.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000623024</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/23/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of North Carolina at Charlotte</Name>
<CityName>CHARLOTTE</CityName>
<ZipCode>282230001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7046871888</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>9201 UNIVERSITY CITY BLVD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>JB33DT84JNA5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF NORTH CAROLINA AT CHARLOTTE, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>N8DMK1K4C2K5</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[UNC Charlotte]]></Name>
<CityName>Charlotte</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>282230001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[9201 University City Blvd]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Buildings play an important role in reducing resource consumption and carbon emissions. Low energy-efficient windows in commercial buildings, in particular, are responsible for more than half of commercial building energy use. High-performance windows with renewable energy production could mitigate the worldwide crisis of climate change. Tall building enclosures in urban settings offer a prime location for harnessing solar energy while regulating energy transfer between indoor and outdoor environments. Our proposed regenerative curtainwall incorporates a network of 3D solar cell interlayers to offer a high performance building enclosure. It offers a cost-effective, innovative solution that can enable conventional windows to produce clean energy while reducing heating, cooling, and lighting demands. With more stringent energy code compliance and global citizen movement, building owners and occupants are interested in reducing energy use and generating clean energy on site to offset building energy consumption.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The system, encapsulated in a protected air cavity where optimum temperature and a dust-free environment can be maintained, is designed to further improve the conversion efficiency and service life of a photovoltaics. The 3D solar cell interlayer is optimized to minimize summer heat gain and maximize winter solar gain, thus reducing cooling and heating loads respectively. The system further maximizes daylighting penetration and occupant views to outside, thereby reducing the artificial lighting load and providing occupant satisfaction. The team successfully carried out small scale prototyping and performance estimates. A commercialization plan was nurtured by developing business model, value chain, and stakeholder group. The broader societal impact is evident in that the proposed technology curtails building energy consumptions and CO<sub>2</sub> emissions. Both upfront and operational cost savings are possible by reducing energy bills and producing on-site electricity.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/01/2022<br>      Modified by: Kyoung-Hee&nbsp;Kim</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Buildings play an important role in reducing resource consumption and carbon emissions. Low energy-efficient windows in commercial buildings, in particular, are responsible for more than half of commercial building energy use. High-performance windows with renewable energy production could mitigate the worldwide crisis of climate change. Tall building enclosures in urban settings offer a prime location for harnessing solar energy while regulating energy transfer between indoor and outdoor environments. Our proposed regenerative curtainwall incorporates a network of 3D solar cell interlayers to offer a high performance building enclosure. It offers a cost-effective, innovative solution that can enable conventional windows to produce clean energy while reducing heating, cooling, and lighting demands. With more stringent energy code compliance and global citizen movement, building owners and occupants are interested in reducing energy use and generating clean energy on site to offset building energy consumption.     The system, encapsulated in a protected air cavity where optimum temperature and a dust-free environment can be maintained, is designed to further improve the conversion efficiency and service life of a photovoltaics. The 3D solar cell interlayer is optimized to minimize summer heat gain and maximize winter solar gain, thus reducing cooling and heating loads respectively. The system further maximizes daylighting penetration and occupant views to outside, thereby reducing the artificial lighting load and providing occupant satisfaction. The team successfully carried out small scale prototyping and performance estimates. A commercialization plan was nurtured by developing business model, value chain, and stakeholder group. The broader societal impact is evident in that the proposed technology curtails building energy consumptions and CO2 emissions. Both upfront and operational cost savings are possible by reducing energy bills and producing on-site electricity.          Last Modified: 01/01/2022       Submitted by: Kyoung-Hee Kim]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
