<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  HealthText: A Digital Decision Support Tool for Medicaid Patients]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>256000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>276000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Alastair Monk</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>amonk@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924392</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact / commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project will be to provide underserved Medicaid patients with accurate and culturally relevant medical advice outside of a standard healthcare setting.  This population often lacks access to timely medical advice and this contributes to further health inequalities and unnecessary rising Medicaid costs.  Medicaid patients may be less likely to engage with medical personnel face-to-face for fear of exorbitant out-of-pocket expenses.  The proposed mobile text-based solution will provide cost-free and culturally relevant health advice.  Proper and timely engagement will result in better outcomes for patients and potentially reduce unnecessary trips to the emergency room for routine care.  Currently, there is no firmly established text-based health solution for Medicaid patients. This service will be a key factor in enabling the organization’s objective to increase health literacy in underserved populations.  &lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project will develop a culturally-appropriate, text-based, digital platform designed exclusively for Medicaid beneficiaries and underserved populations who have largely been omitted from digital health innovation. This project’s research objective is to examine the receptiveness of the underserved population to this method of health information delivery and healthcare navigation support.  This study will explore patient engagement with a healthcare navigator using text messaging. The data will be analyzed for speech and content patterns needed to create an easily accessible artificial intelligence (AI) tool designed specifically for Medicaid and other patients from underserved communities. The data generated from this project will also be useful for researchers to refine methods to recruit underserved, black and Hispanic communities for clinical trials and public health research studies.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/21/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/11/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2037216</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lisa</FirstName>
<LastName>Fitzpatrick</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>K</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lisa K Fitzpatrick</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[lisa.fitzpatrick@grapevinehealth.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000826476</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/21/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>LISA FITZPATRICK &amp; ASSOCIATES MD PC</Name>
<CityName>WASHINGTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>200015272</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2022705647</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>475 K ST NW UNIT 1112</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>VC6YBGX96H95</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>LISA FITZPATRICK &amp; ASSOCIATES MD PC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[LISA FITZPATRICK & ASSOCIATES MD PC]]></Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>200325903</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3429 11TH PL SE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8091</Code>
<Text>SBIR Outreach &amp; Tech. Assist</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8018</Code>
<Text>Smart and Connected Health</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8042</Code>
<Text>Health and Safety</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~276000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-9f59db8f-7fff-aa75-d726-d9774188341b"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>At Grapevine Health, we know health literacy is a powerful social driver of health. With roots in healthcare, technology, content production, and community organizing, our team leverages technical expertise, trusted messengers, and empathetic storytelling to democratize health information, empower patients, and drive sustaining healthy behaviors.&nbsp; Under our SBIR Phase I award, </span><span>Grapevine Health (GH) proposed to build HealthText, a culturally-appropriate, SMS-based, digital platform designed exclusively for Medicaid beneficiaries and other populations who have largely been omitted from digital health innovation.</span><span> We also aimed to advance knowledge by exploring and documenting the use of standard telecommunications technologies for delivering digital health services and assess the receptiveness of the population to this method of delivering culturally-appropriate health information and healthcare navigation support.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>During the project period, the GH team accomplished our major objectives.&nbsp; First, we interviewed and surveyed Medicaid patients and other members of the community to better understand trust with the healthcare sector, preference to receive healthcare services, where they find health information, and opportunities for engaging them and their communities to improve health. Utilizing these insights, we designed, developed and implemented an SMS messaging platform that enables the initiation of campaigns that can be tuned to the individual member&rsquo;s clinical, utilization, and personal preferences. We tested the platform with patients and exceeded reported industry engagement standards in this population. Finally, to facilitate scaling our solution, we used and tested the feasibility of adding automated two-way messaging to enable patients to find the information they want, when they want it. Our early results are promising and suggest HealthText will help meet the health information needs of our target audiences.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Grapevine Health will continue testing trusted and relatable content delivered through our smart messaging platform and assessing its impact on engagement in care and related health outcomes. </span></p> <div><span><br /></span></div> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/08/2022<br>      Modified by: Lisa&nbsp;K&nbsp;Fitzpatrick</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   At Grapevine Health, we know health literacy is a powerful social driver of health. With roots in healthcare, technology, content production, and community organizing, our team leverages technical expertise, trusted messengers, and empathetic storytelling to democratize health information, empower patients, and drive sustaining healthy behaviors.  Under our SBIR Phase I award, Grapevine Health (GH) proposed to build HealthText, a culturally-appropriate, SMS-based, digital platform designed exclusively for Medicaid beneficiaries and other populations who have largely been omitted from digital health innovation. We also aimed to advance knowledge by exploring and documenting the use of standard telecommunications technologies for delivering digital health services and assess the receptiveness of the population to this method of delivering culturally-appropriate health information and healthcare navigation support.  During the project period, the GH team accomplished our major objectives.  First, we interviewed and surveyed Medicaid patients and other members of the community to better understand trust with the healthcare sector, preference to receive healthcare services, where they find health information, and opportunities for engaging them and their communities to improve health. Utilizing these insights, we designed, developed and implemented an SMS messaging platform that enables the initiation of campaigns that can be tuned to the individual member’s clinical, utilization, and personal preferences. We tested the platform with patients and exceeded reported industry engagement standards in this population. Finally, to facilitate scaling our solution, we used and tested the feasibility of adding automated two-way messaging to enable patients to find the information they want, when they want it. Our early results are promising and suggest HealthText will help meet the health information needs of our target audiences. Grapevine Health will continue testing trusted and relatable content delivered through our smart messaging platform and assessing its impact on engagement in care and related health outcomes.                Last Modified: 11/08/2022       Submitted by: Lisa K Fitzpatrick]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
