<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[I-Corps:  Photobiomodulation device for the treatment of neurodegenerative diseases]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ruth Shuman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rshuman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922160</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this I-Corps project is the development of a novel technology to slow the progression of Alzheimer’s Disease (AD). AD is a common and devastating disease that currently affects 1 in 3 seniors within the United States and will cost the nation over $1 trillion per year by 2050. The pathology of the disease has remained elusive through decades of study, and the field is awash in failed drug and device trials. The proposed technology helps reduce the impact of the disease.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project explores translation of an implantable technology that targets a AD pathway adjacent to the disease pathology.  It focuses on treatment reduction rather than curative outcomes. Initial outcome metrics will focus on biomarkers specific to the mechanism of the device and the longevity of effect.  Clinical outcomes will center on a battery of cognitive testing, including MOCA and MMSE scores.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/07/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/07/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2037640</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Anthony</FirstName>
<LastName>Costa</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Anthony Costa</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[anthony.costa@mssm.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000735403</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/07/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai</Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<ZipCode>100296504</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2128248300</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>ONE GUSTAVE L LEVY PL</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>C8H9CNG1VBD9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ICAHN SCHOOL OF MEDICINE AT MOUNT SINAI</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>DKCMJ8WRH2E5</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai]]></Name>
<CityName>New York</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>100296504</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1 GUSTAVE L LEVY PL]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Lumen team, participating in the national-phase I-Corps program run by the National Science Foundation (NSF), successfully completed their project focusing on Alzheimer's disease. Through conducting over 100 interviews with patients, doctors, and other stakeholders, the team was able to gain valuable insights and gather a significant amount of data on the current state of the field. The team also conducted market research and analysis to better understand the current landscape and potential opportunities for new solutions.&nbsp;</p> <p>The project outcomes included the identification of unmet needs and pain points within the Alzheimer's community, as well as the development of potential solutions to address these issues. The team also established a network of contacts and potential collaborators within the industry, positioning them well for further research and development in this area. The team also found out the willingness of alzheimer's patients to attempt surgical interventions, and the associated clinical benefits that would be needed for different levels of invasiveness.</p> <p>Overall, the project was a success and the Lumen team was able to make significant progress in advancing understanding and potential solutions for Alzheimer's disease. The team also developed a deeper understanding of the market and customer needs, which will be valuable as they move forward with their solution. They have also established a strong network of collaborators and contacts that will be valuable as they continue to commercialize their technology.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/23/2023<br>      Modified by: Anthony&nbsp;Costa</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Lumen team, participating in the national-phase I-Corps program run by the National Science Foundation (NSF), successfully completed their project focusing on Alzheimer's disease. Through conducting over 100 interviews with patients, doctors, and other stakeholders, the team was able to gain valuable insights and gather a significant amount of data on the current state of the field. The team also conducted market research and analysis to better understand the current landscape and potential opportunities for new solutions.   The project outcomes included the identification of unmet needs and pain points within the Alzheimer's community, as well as the development of potential solutions to address these issues. The team also established a network of contacts and potential collaborators within the industry, positioning them well for further research and development in this area. The team also found out the willingness of alzheimer's patients to attempt surgical interventions, and the associated clinical benefits that would be needed for different levels of invasiveness.  Overall, the project was a success and the Lumen team was able to make significant progress in advancing understanding and potential solutions for Alzheimer's disease. The team also developed a deeper understanding of the market and customer needs, which will be valuable as they move forward with their solution. They have also established a strong network of collaborators and contacts that will be valuable as they continue to commercialize their technology.          Last Modified: 01/23/2023       Submitted by: Anthony Costa]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
