<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Developing a universal modular platform to engineer coronavirus vaccine candidates]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>200000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>200000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Pui Ho</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>puiho@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032920000</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[With this award, the Chemistry of Life Processes program in the Chemistry Division supports the studies by Dr. Angad Mehta at the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign to make live attenuated forms of the severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) that require an unnatural compound to reproduce. SARS-CoV-2 is the virus that causes coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19). Live-attenuated viruses have reduced abilities to cause disease, but remain capable of providing immunity in humans. As such, live-attenuated viruses represent one of the effective strategies for the development of vaccines against wide-spread viral infections.  The genomic RNA of the virus must be modified with a methyl group in order to be copied by infected cells, and this methyl group is added by enzymes using the natural compound S-adenosylmethionine (AdoMet). Dr. Mehta’s project engineers SARS-CoV-2 particles that use synthetic forms of AdoMet (called xAdoMet) for this critical methylation step. The resulting engineered SARS-CoV-2* is a live virus in a laboratory, where xAdoMet can be added as a required supplement. The SARS-CoV-2*, however, cannot reproduce in normal cells, where xAdoMet is not present, but can still result in an immune response in an infected patient. The impact on society is that a unique platform is engineered for the development of vaccines to address viral diseases, including the COVID-19 pandemic.  The broader impacts of this project include the strong cross-disciplinary training of graduate students.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This goal of this study is to develop live attenuated SARS-CoV-2 particles that are dependent on an unnatural version of an essential cofactor for its replication that is added in a laboratory setting, but not available in the infected host. SARS-CoV-2 requires S-adenosylmethionine (AdoMet) as a cofactor for a critical methylation of the viral RNA by a methyl transferase in order to translate its genes and replicate its genome. Through this project, a strain of the coronavirus (SARS-CoV-2*) is engineered that utilizes and is dependent on an unnatural analogue of AdoMet (xAdoMet) for the critical methylation reactions. Such a virus requires supplements of xAdoMet in a laboratory in order to replicate. Once injected into a host, this viral strain can infect a cell and potentially induce an immune response in the host, but cannot replicate in the absence of exogenous supplementation with xAdoMet. The objectives are to synthesize a series of xAdoMet compounds; use the xAdoMet compounds to engineer SARS-CoV-2* through directed evolution; and test the live attenuated virus for induction of immune response in cell culture. The AdoMet-dependent methylation mechanism is conserved in all known coronavirus pathogens and, therefore, has the potential to serve as a far-reaching and modular platform for vaccine development well beyond SARS-CoV-2.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/08/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/08/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2037695</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Angad</FirstName>
<LastName>Mehta</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Angad P Mehta</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[apm8@illinois.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000827397</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/08/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</Name>
<CityName>URBANA</CityName>
<ZipCode>618013620</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>506 S WRIGHT ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>Y8CWNJRCNN91</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ILLINOIS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign Henry Admin Bldg]]></Name>
<CityName>Urbana</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>618013620</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[506 Wright Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6883</Code>
<Text>Chemistry of Life Processes</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~200000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span class="mceitemhidden"><span>Essential viral enzymes have been successfully targeted to combat the diseases caused by emerging pathogenic RNA viruses (e.g., viral RNA dependent RNA polymerase). Because of the conserved nature of such viral enzymes, therapeutics targeting these enzymes have the potential to be </span></span><span class="mceitemhiddenspellword"><span>repurposed</span></span><span class="mceitemhidden"><span> to combat emerging diseases, e.g., </span></span><span class="mceitemhiddenspellword"><span>Remdesivir</span></span><span class="mceitemhidden"><span> which was initially developed as potential Ebola treatment was </span></span><span class="mceitemhiddenspellword"><span>repurposed</span></span><span class="mceitemhidden"><span> for </span></span><span class="mceitemhiddenspellword"><span>COVID</span></span><span class="mceitemhidden"><span>-19. Our efforts described in this study, target another essential and highly conserved, but relatively less explored, step in RNA virus translation and replication, i.e., capping of the viral RNA genome. The viral genome cap structure disguises the genome of most RNA viruses to resemble the </span></span><span class="mceitemhiddenspellword"><span>mRNA</span></span><span class="mceitemhidden"><span> cap structure of their host, and is essential for viral translation, propagation and immune evasion. Here, we developed a synthetic yeast-based platform (YeRC0M) for molecular characterization and targeting of </span></span><span class="mceitemhiddenspellword"><span>SARS</span></span><span class="mceitemhidden"><span>-</span></span><span class="mceitemhiddenspellword"><span>CoV</span></span><span class="mceitemhidden"><span>-2 genome encoded RNA-cap 0 (guanine N7)-</span></span><span class="mceitemhiddenspellword"><span>methyltransferase</span></span><span class="mceitemhidden"><span> (N7-</span></span><span class="mceitemhiddenspellword"><span>MTase</span></span><span class="mceitemhidden"><span>) enzyme (nsp14). Using YeRC0M, we first identified important protein domains and amino acid residues that are essential for </span></span><span class="mceitemhiddenspellword"><span>SARS</span></span><span class="mceitemhidden"><span>-</span></span><span class="mceitemhiddenspellword"><span>CoV</span></span><span class="mceitemhidden"><span>-2 nsp14 N7-</span></span><span class="mceitemhiddenspellword"><span>MTase</span></span><span class="mceitemhidden"><span> activity. We also expanded YeRC0M to include key nsp14 variants observed in emerging variants of </span></span><span class="mceitemhiddenspellword"><span>SARS</span></span><span class="mceitemhidden"><span>-</span></span><span class="mceitemhiddenspellword"><span>CoV</span></span><span class="mceitemhidden"><span>-2 (e.g., e.g., delta variant of </span></span><span class="mceitemhiddenspellword"><span>SARS</span></span><span class="mceitemhidden"><span>-</span></span><span class="mceitemhiddenspellword"><span>CoV</span></span><span class="mceitemhidden"><span>-2 encodes nsp14 A394V and nsp14 P46L). </span></span></p> <p><span class="mceitemhidden"><span>We also combined YeRC0M with directed evolution to identify attenuation mutations in </span></span><span class="mceitemhiddenspellword"><span>SARS</span></span><span class="mceitemhidden"><span>-</span></span><span class="mceitemhiddenspellword"><span>CoV</span></span><span class="mceitemhidden"><span>-2 nsp14. Because of high sequence similarity of nsp14 in emerging </span></span><span class="mceitemhiddenspellword"><span>coronaviruses</span></span><span class="mceitemhidden"><span>, these observations could have implications on live attenuated vaccine development strategies. These data taken together reveal key domains in </span></span><span class="mceitemhiddenspellword"><span>SARS</span></span><span class="mceitemhidden"><span>-</span></span><span class="mceitemhiddenspellword"><span>CoV</span></span><span class="mceitemhidden"><span>-2 nsp14 that can be targeted for therapeutic strategies. We also anticipate that these readily tractable </span></span><span class="mceitemhiddenspellword"><span>phenotypic</span></span><span class="mceitemhidden"><span> platforms can also be used for identification of inhibitors of viral RNA capping enzymes as antivirals.</span></span></p> <p><span>We are also devloping directed evolution plaforms to engineer orthognal nsp14/unnatural coenzyme (X-AdoMet) pairs for genrating variants of viruses that depened on the unnatural coenzyme for its replication and propagation. Such variants are expected to be attenuated in the host due to lack of unnatural coenzyme. Such variants can be tested as live attenuated vaccine candidates. </span></p> <p><span class="mceitemhidden"><span>We have also developed a plasmid based </span></span><span class="mceitemhiddenspellword"><span>pseudoviral</span></span><span class="mceitemhidden"><span> system using </span></span><span class="mceitemhiddenspellword"><span>VSV</span></span><span class="mceitemhidden"><span> viruses. We have replaced the </span></span><span class="mceitemhiddenspellword"><span>VSV</span></span><span class="mceitemhidden"><span> N7-</span></span><span class="mceitemhiddenspellword"><span>methyltransferase</span></span><span class="mceitemhidden"><span> domain in the L-protein with the </span></span><span class="mceitemhiddenspellword"><span>SARS</span></span><span class="mceitemhidden"><span>-</span></span><span class="mceitemhiddenspellword"><span>CoV</span></span><span class="mceitemhidden"><span>-2 N7-</span></span><span class="mceitemhiddenspellword"><span>methyltransferase</span></span><span class="mceitemhidden"><span> domain. This system is ready to be utilized as soon as we identify nsp14 variants that orthogonally utilize X-</span></span><span class="mceitemhiddenspellword"><span>AdoMet</span></span><span class="mceitemhidden"><span>.</span></span></p> <p><span style="caret-color: #000000; font-variant-caps: normal; orphans: auto; text-align: start; widows: auto; float: none; word-spacing: 0px;"><span>Overall, this <span class="mceitemhidden">funding was really crucial for my lab to build the foundation of an important research direction in my lab which now serves as the basis of my CAREER application. We now have one manuscript submitted and under review, and another under preparation, and several other related studies that will likely result in publications. Also, we currently have 3 students (plus an incoming </span><span class="mceitemhiddenspellword">postdoc</span><span class="mceitemhidden">) in my lab working on related projects. In addition to this, the team that worked on these efforts comprised of a diverse group of students, including those from underrepresented groups in science, and the funding from NSF was crucial to assemble this team. I really appreciate your support to my lab in my very first year as an independent investigator; RAPID funding really allowed this area to blossom in my lab.</span> </span></span></p> <!-- @font-face  {font-family:"Cambria Math";  panose-1:2 4 5 3 5 4 6 3 2 4;  mso-font-charset:0;  mso-generic-font-family:roman;  mso-font-pitch:variable;  mso-font-signature:-536870145 1107305727 0 0 415 0;}@font-face  {font-family:Calibri;  panose-1:2 15 5 2 2 2 4 3 2 4;  mso-font-charset:0;  mso-generic-font-family:swiss;  mso-font-pitch:variable;  mso-font-signature:-536859905 -1073732485 9 0 511 0;}@font-face  {font-family:"Times New Roman \(Body CS\)";  panose-1:2 11 6 4 2 2 2 2 2 4;  mso-font-charset:0;  mso-generic-font-family:roman;  mso-font-pitch:auto;  mso-font-signature:0 0 0 0 0 0;}p.MsoNormal, li.MsoNormal, div.MsoNormal  {mso-style-unhide:no;  mso-style-qformat:yes;  mso-style-parent:";  margin:0in;  mso-pagination:widow-orphan;  font-size:12.0pt;  font-family:"Calibri",sans-serif;  mso-ascii-font-family:Calibri;  mso-ascii-theme-font:minor-latin;  mso-fareast-font-family:Calibri;  mso-fareast-theme-font:minor-latin;  mso-hansi-font-family:Calibri;  mso-hansi-theme-font:minor-latin;  mso-bidi-font-family:"Times New Roman";  mso-bidi-theme-font:minor-bidi;}p  {mso-style-noshow:yes;  mso-style-priority:99;  mso-margin-top-alt:auto;  margin-right:0in;  mso-margin-bottom-alt:auto;  margin-left:0in;  mso-pagination:widow-orphan;  font-size:11.0pt;  font-family:"Calibri",sans-serif;  mso-fareast-font-family:"Times New Roman";}span.EmailStyle15  {mso-style-type:personal;  mso-style-noshow:yes;  mso-style-unhide:no;  mso-ansi-font-size:11.0pt;  mso-bidi-font-size:11.0pt;  font-family:"Arial",sans-serif;  mso-ascii-font-family:Arial;  mso-hansi-font-family:Arial;  mso-bidi-font-family:"Times New Roman \(Body CS\)";  color:windowtext;}span.mceitemhidden  {mso-style-name:mceitemhidden;  mso-style-unhide:no;}span.mceitemhiddenspellword  {mso-style-name:mceitemhiddenspellword;  mso-style-unhide:no;}.MsoChpDefault  {mso-style-type:export-only;  mso-default-props:yes;  font-size:12.0pt;  mso-ansi-font-size:12.0pt;  mso-bidi-font-size:12.0pt;  font-family:"Calibri",sans-serif;  mso-ascii-font-family:Calibri;  mso-ascii-theme-font:minor-latin;  mso-fareast-font-family:Calibri;  mso-fareast-theme-font:minor-latin;  mso-hansi-font-family:Calibri;  mso-hansi-theme-font:minor-latin;  mso-bidi-font-family:"Times New Roman";  mso-bidi-theme-font:minor-bidi;}div.WordSection1  {page:WordSection1;} --><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/29/2022<br>      Modified by: Angad&nbsp;P&nbsp;Mehta</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Essential viral enzymes have been successfully targeted to combat the diseases caused by emerging pathogenic RNA viruses (e.g., viral RNA dependent RNA polymerase). Because of the conserved nature of such viral enzymes, therapeutics targeting these enzymes have the potential to be repurposed to combat emerging diseases, e.g., Remdesivir which was initially developed as potential Ebola treatment was repurposed for COVID-19. Our efforts described in this study, target another essential and highly conserved, but relatively less explored, step in RNA virus translation and replication, i.e., capping of the viral RNA genome. The viral genome cap structure disguises the genome of most RNA viruses to resemble the mRNA cap structure of their host, and is essential for viral translation, propagation and immune evasion. Here, we developed a synthetic yeast-based platform (YeRC0M) for molecular characterization and targeting of SARS-CoV-2 genome encoded RNA-cap 0 (guanine N7)-methyltransferase (N7-MTase) enzyme (nsp14). Using YeRC0M, we first identified important protein domains and amino acid residues that are essential for SARS-CoV-2 nsp14 N7-MTase activity. We also expanded YeRC0M to include key nsp14 variants observed in emerging variants of SARS-CoV-2 (e.g., e.g., delta variant of SARS-CoV-2 encodes nsp14 A394V and nsp14 P46L).   We also combined YeRC0M with directed evolution to identify attenuation mutations in SARS-CoV-2 nsp14. Because of high sequence similarity of nsp14 in emerging coronaviruses, these observations could have implications on live attenuated vaccine development strategies. These data taken together reveal key domains in SARS-CoV-2 nsp14 that can be targeted for therapeutic strategies. We also anticipate that these readily tractable phenotypic platforms can also be used for identification of inhibitors of viral RNA capping enzymes as antivirals.  We are also devloping directed evolution plaforms to engineer orthognal nsp14/unnatural coenzyme (X-AdoMet) pairs for genrating variants of viruses that depened on the unnatural coenzyme for its replication and propagation. Such variants are expected to be attenuated in the host due to lack of unnatural coenzyme. Such variants can be tested as live attenuated vaccine candidates.   We have also developed a plasmid based pseudoviral system using VSV viruses. We have replaced the VSV N7-methyltransferase domain in the L-protein with the SARS-CoV-2 N7-methyltransferase domain. This system is ready to be utilized as soon as we identify nsp14 variants that orthogonally utilize X-AdoMet.  Overall, this funding was really crucial for my lab to build the foundation of an important research direction in my lab which now serves as the basis of my CAREER application. We now have one manuscript submitted and under review, and another under preparation, and several other related studies that will likely result in publications. Also, we currently have 3 students (plus an incoming postdoc) in my lab working on related projects. In addition to this, the team that worked on these efforts comprised of a diverse group of students, including those from underrepresented groups in science, and the funding from NSF was crucial to assemble this team. I really appreciate your support to my lab in my very first year as an independent investigator; RAPID funding really allowed this area to blossom in my lab.         Last Modified: 08/29/2022       Submitted by: Angad P Mehta]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
