<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SII Planning: Creating a Visionary, Interdisciplinary, and Transformational National Center for Spectrum and Wireless Systems Research]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>299942.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>299942</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AST</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ashley  Vanderley</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bevander@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922428</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This award is a planning grant for the Spectrum Innovation Initiative:  National Center for Wireless Spectrum Research (SII-Center).  The focus of a spectrum research SII-Center goes beyond 5G, IoT, and other existing or forthcoming systems and technologies to chart out a trajectory to ensure United States leadership in future wireless technologies, systems, and applications in science and engineering through the efficient use and sharing of the radio spectrum. Over the past four decades, worldwide growth of wireless systems has provided tremendous societal benefit, enabling increased digital connectivity, telemedicine, social media, improved weather forecasting and more. It has also put significant and competing demands on many parts of the radio spectrum. To meet these challenges, this project supports the Wireless Innovation and Spectrum Evolution (WISE); which convenes former members of the Senior Executive Service in the FCC and NTIA and university faculty from the University of Colorado Boulder, the University of California San Diego, the University of Pittsburgh, and the University of Puerto Rico Mayaguez. The WISE group will develop a research agenda and partnerships through workshops and discussions. Students will be supported to participate in these workshops and to develop spectrum science modules for K-12 students.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Through the center development process, stakeholders from academia, the federal government, and industry will be engaged to identify key technology, policies and workforce challenges to be addressed by the center. Six core research focus areas will include: Spectrum Efficiency and Coexistence; Next Generation Radio Devices; Spectrum Science; Modeling and Measurement; Wireless Systems; and Policy, Economics and Privacy. The process of bringing researchers, policy makers, and key stakeholders will result in the development of a vision and road map for an integrated and successful Wireless Innovation and Spectrum Evolution Center.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/10/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/10/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2037918</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Pamela</FirstName>
<LastName>Cosman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Pamela C Cosman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[pcosman@ucsd.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000456426</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Scott</FirstName>
<LastName>Palo</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Scott E Palo</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[scott.palo@colorado.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000101770</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rafael</FirstName>
<LastName>Rodriguez Solis</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Rafael A Rodriguez Solis</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[rafael.rodriguez19@upr.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000479253</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Martin</FirstName>
<LastName>Weiss</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Martin B Weiss</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mbw@pitt.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000520499</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Keith</FirstName>
<LastName>Gremban</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Keith D Gremban</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[keith.gremban@colorado.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000824677</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Colorado at Boulder</Name>
<CityName>BOULDER</CityName>
<ZipCode>803090001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3034926221</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3100 MARINE ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[STE 481 572 UCB]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>SPVKK1RC2MZ3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>THE REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF COLORADO</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Colorado at Boulder]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>803090429</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>151Y</Code>
<Text>SII-Spectrum Innovation Initia</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>4444</Code>
<Text>INTERDISCIPLINARY PROPOSALS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~299942</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This award was granted as a 1 year planning grant from the National Science Foundation for the development of a National Spectrum Innovation Center.&nbsp; The WISE team combined with three other planning grant teams led by the University of Notre Dame, University of Virginia and Olin College to create the SpectrumX team.&nbsp; The SpectrumX team, which includes 27 Universities (14 Minority Serving Institutions) and 42 researchers, was selected by the National Science Foundation to create the first Spectrum Innovation Initiative Center.&nbsp;</p> <p>The focus of the first year of the proposal was to develop the fundamental elements of the center including the center structure of research, education, broadening participation, policy, collaboration and administration.&nbsp; The research is structured into 4 research working groups responsible for developing research roadmaps and six project teams executing ongoing research projects on spectrum sensing, passive coexistence, active coexistence, data and machine learning, economics and enforcement.</p> <p>This award was extended for a second year where the remaining grant funds were used to support the creation of the SpectrumX center including the development of a detailed implementation plan and building the foundation of the center.&nbsp; A key focus of our team has been with the leadership of SpectrumX, the development of spectrum related educational materials and the development of materials to broaden participation.</p> <p>Accomplishments include the creation of a new Spectrum related research center to support the national needs of a variety of users for radio spectrum, the development of educational materials and a focused effort to broaden participation in the center and radio spectrum community.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/22/2023<br>      Modified by: Scott&nbsp;E&nbsp;Palo</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2037918/2037918_10694751_1674402922902_SpectrumXMembership--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2037918/2037918_10694751_1674402922902_SpectrumXMembership--rgov-800width.jpg" title="SpectrumX Members"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2037918/2037918_10694751_1674402922902_SpectrumXMembership--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="SpectrumX Members"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Members of the SpectrumX SII Center Team</div> <div class="imageCredit">Notre Dame University</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Scott&nbsp;E&nbsp;Palo</div> <div class="imageTitle">SpectrumX Members</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2037918/2037918_10694751_1674403022585_SpectrumXannualmeeting--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2037918/2037918_10694751_1674403022585_SpectrumXannualmeeting--rgov-800width.jpg" title="SpectrumX Inaugural Meeting"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2037918/2037918_10694751_1674403022585_SpectrumXannualmeeting--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="SpectrumX Inaugural Meeting"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">SpectrumX Inaugural Meeting, Boulder CO, June 2022</div> <div class="imageCredit">Notre Dame University</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Scott&nbsp;E&nbsp;Palo</div> <div class="imageTitle">SpectrumX Inaugural Meeting</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2037918/2037918_10694751_1674403094625_SecretCodeLesson--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2037918/2037918_10694751_1674403094625_SecretCodeLesson--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Secret Code Lesson Plan"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2037918/2037918_10694751_1674403094625_SecretCodeLesson--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Secret Code Lesson Plan"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Secret Code Lesson Plan developed by Dr. Pam Cosman</div> <div class="imageCredit">University of California San Diego</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Scott&nbsp;E&nbsp;Palo</div> <div class="imageTitle">Secret Code Lesson Plan</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2037918/2037918_10694751_1674403222349_TessellationSecretCodeLesson--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2037918/2037918_10694751_1674403222349_TessellationSecretCodeLesson--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Tessellation Lesson Plan"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2037918/2037918_10694751_1674403222349_TessellationSecretCodeLesson--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Tessellation Lesson Plan"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Tessellation Lesson Plan created by Dr. Pamela Cosman</div> <div class="imageCredit">University of California San Diego</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Scott&nbsp;E&nbsp;Palo</div> <div class="imageTitle">Tessellation Lesson Plan</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This award was granted as a 1 year planning grant from the National Science Foundation for the development of a National Spectrum Innovation Center.  The WISE team combined with three other planning grant teams led by the University of Notre Dame, University of Virginia and Olin College to create the SpectrumX team.  The SpectrumX team, which includes 27 Universities (14 Minority Serving Institutions) and 42 researchers, was selected by the National Science Foundation to create the first Spectrum Innovation Initiative Center.   The focus of the first year of the proposal was to develop the fundamental elements of the center including the center structure of research, education, broadening participation, policy, collaboration and administration.  The research is structured into 4 research working groups responsible for developing research roadmaps and six project teams executing ongoing research projects on spectrum sensing, passive coexistence, active coexistence, data and machine learning, economics and enforcement.  This award was extended for a second year where the remaining grant funds were used to support the creation of the SpectrumX center including the development of a detailed implementation plan and building the foundation of the center.  A key focus of our team has been with the leadership of SpectrumX, the development of spectrum related educational materials and the development of materials to broaden participation.  Accomplishments include the creation of a new Spectrum related research center to support the national needs of a variety of users for radio spectrum, the development of educational materials and a focused effort to broaden participation in the center and radio spectrum community.          Last Modified: 01/22/2023       Submitted by: Scott E Palo]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
