<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Supporting Universities with Online Educational Materials through the MetEd Website]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>79821.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>79821</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06020300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AGS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Manda S. Adams</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>amadams@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924708</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[University faculty are faced with unprecedented challenges as they quickly transition many of their teaching activities to virtual environments. In atmospheric science, this transition requires finding ways to engage students in learning about complex scientific processes and creating ways for students to apply these concepts using numerical models and observational datasets. This project will develop an online guide to COMET’s MetEd lessons and graphics/animations so as to enable university faculty to quickly find and incorporate high-quality interactive lessons, graphics and datasets into their meteorology courses this fall.  The online guide that maps current COMET lessons and graphics/animations to standard undergraduate courses in meteorology will be broadly disseminated through COMET’s freely-available MetEd website, which has over 625,000 registered users.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will produce 1) an online guide that maps current lessons available on MetEd to standard courses in meteorology, 2) a gallery of graphics and animations bundled for standard courses in meteorology and 3) new online courses that contain the mapped MetEd lessons, with required and optional components, such that users can complete all required lessons to earn an online certificate of completion.  To create the university curricula lesson mapping, COMET staff will survey course curricula and syllabi from several leading university programs in meteorology to create a “composite curriculum” that represents the typical in-major course requirements for an atmospheric science/meteorology degree. COMET will also reference the most recent American Meteorological Society Statement on Bachelor’s Degree to ensure alignment with current and future academic needs from the professional vantage point. The project will focus on seven widely taught courses in meteorology/atmospheric science degree programs; introductory meteorology, physical meteorology, dynamic meteorology, synoptic meteorology, weather analysis &amp; forecasting, mesoscale meteorology, and remote sensing&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/29/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/29/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2037034</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Elizabeth</FirstName>
<LastName>Page</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Elizabeth M Page</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[epage@ucar.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000776630</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/29/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Andrea</FirstName>
<LastName>Smith</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Andrea Smith</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[asmith5@ucar.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000817831</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/29/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University Corporation For Atmospheric Res</Name>
<CityName>BOULDER</CityName>
<ZipCode>803012252</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3034971000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3090 CENTER GREEN DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>YEZEE8W5JKA3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY CORPORATION FOR ATMOSPHERIC RESEARCH</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>YEZEE8W5JKA3</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[UCAR]]></Name>
<CityName>Boulder</CityName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>803012252</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3090 Center Green Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7700</Code>
<Text>EDUCATIONAL LINKAGES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~79821</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-859173a4-7fff-de1f-ac25-997c0349a261"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>During spring semester 2020, many colleges and universities were forced to suddenly transition from primarily in-person classes to entirely virtual learning experiences. This abrupt shift placed unprecedented and unfamiliar demands on many faculty, especially STEM instructors that had to find engaging ways to teach students about complex scientific processes and their applications.&nbsp;&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>To respond to this situation, The COMET Program surveyed its university user base to assess specific ways to support geoscience faculty and students in their move to online learning. A main recommendation was to create a university course support resource that maps the content of the 500+ geoscience lessons available on COMET's MetEd website to core undergraduate meteorology course curricula. These lessons, which span 20 different operational meteorology and geoscience topics, each contain a variety of 2D and 3D conceptual diagrams, calculators, case study datasets, immersive simulations, pre- and post-tests, and other learning materials. These customized university packages were designed to enable faculty and students to quickly find and incorporate high-quality interactive lessons, graphics and datasets into core meteorology courses.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>COMET staff developed and published seven university course support packages listed below and available at https://www.meted.ucar.edu/education_training/ucourses.</span></p> <ul> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Introduction to Meteorology</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Dynamic Meteorology</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Mesoscale Meteorology</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Physical Meteorology</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Synoptic Meteorology</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Thermodynamic Meteorology</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Environmental Satellites and Radar</span></p> </li> </ul> <p dir="ltr"><span>Each course support package contained three to six subtopics that represented the most common meteorological concept categories taught at universities with meteorology programs and as suggested by the American Meteorological Society's </span><span>Statement on Bachelor's Degrees in Atmospheric Science</span><span>.&nbsp; For example, the </span><span>Thermodynamic Meteorology </span><span>course support package contained subtopics including "foundational concepts", "first and second law of thermodynamics", "hydrostatic concepts", "thermodynamics and moisture in the atmosphere", and "thermodynamic diagrams".&nbsp; Applicable lessons and/or section(s) of lessons from the suite of 500 lessons were then identified for each package's subtopics. A general instructor's usage guide was developed for each course support package, and additional information describing the type and location(s) of applicable content within each lesson was provided.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Graphics and media items, which included 2D and 3D images, movies, and data loops, were packaged so that instructors could easily search and download them to use as support for lectures, laboratory activities or other applications. Since these images are public domain, creative commons, or under copyright approval agreement with COMET sponsors, faculty and students are free to use and modify them.&nbsp;&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The University Course Support Resource saw frequent usage throughout the 2020-2021 academic year. By May 2021, there were over 24,000 pageviews for the resource, with Introduction to Meteorology, Dynamic Meteorology, and Synoptic Meteorology being the most popular packages.&nbsp; A university instructor user survey was developed and distributed in May 2021, with overwhelmingly positive responses from over 30 respondents: 76% of survey respondents indicated that they agreed or strongly agreed that the resource met their course objectives, and 73% said that they would recommend the resource to others.&nbsp; Survey respondents primarily used the resource to: 1 - supplement existing lecture, lab, or class material (58%), 2 - serve as additional homework or assignment material (42%), and 3 - serve as alternative to usual classroom or textbook material (39%).</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>This resource clearly addressed demonstrated onsite and virtual classroom needs from US meteorology faculty, and will enable university staff and students to more easily integrate high-quality conceptual and case example materials into their own courses, to easily assign refresher training, or to support exploratory experiences to their students. The materials also boost faculty members' abilities to attempt a "flipped classroom" experience by increasing the amount of background material available for students' review before discussion.&nbsp; Further, the availability of pre- and post-tests for each lesson allow faculty to more easily assess concepts with which students are struggling.&nbsp; The course packages can potentially ease the burden that early-career and/or small-department faculty members may face by providing a repository of relevant conceptual diagrams and case study datasets, allowing them to devote attention to the many competing aspects of their job.&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span>Finally, the resource was used by a variety of non-university users, including government employees, private sector employees, emergency managers, broadcasters, and even weather enthusiasts. Moving beyond the United States, this resource is directly applicable to many national hydrometeorological services in meeting the requirements of the World Meteorological Organization's </span><span>Basic Instruction Package for Meteorologists</span><span>, and will remain freely-available to anyone interested in accessing high-quality geoscience learning materials well beyond the COVID era.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/29/2021<br>      Modified by: Andrea&nbsp;Smith</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   During spring semester 2020, many colleges and universities were forced to suddenly transition from primarily in-person classes to entirely virtual learning experiences. This abrupt shift placed unprecedented and unfamiliar demands on many faculty, especially STEM instructors that had to find engaging ways to teach students about complex scientific processes and their applications.   To respond to this situation, The COMET Program surveyed its university user base to assess specific ways to support geoscience faculty and students in their move to online learning. A main recommendation was to create a university course support resource that maps the content of the 500+ geoscience lessons available on COMET's MetEd website to core undergraduate meteorology course curricula. These lessons, which span 20 different operational meteorology and geoscience topics, each contain a variety of 2D and 3D conceptual diagrams, calculators, case study datasets, immersive simulations, pre- and post-tests, and other learning materials. These customized university packages were designed to enable faculty and students to quickly find and incorporate high-quality interactive lessons, graphics and datasets into core meteorology courses. COMET staff developed and published seven university course support packages listed below and available at https://www.meted.ucar.edu/education_training/ucourses.   Introduction to Meteorology   Dynamic Meteorology   Mesoscale Meteorology   Physical Meteorology   Synoptic Meteorology   Thermodynamic Meteorology   Environmental Satellites and Radar   Each course support package contained three to six subtopics that represented the most common meteorological concept categories taught at universities with meteorology programs and as suggested by the American Meteorological Society's Statement on Bachelor's Degrees in Atmospheric Science.  For example, the Thermodynamic Meteorology course support package contained subtopics including "foundational concepts", "first and second law of thermodynamics", "hydrostatic concepts", "thermodynamics and moisture in the atmosphere", and "thermodynamic diagrams".  Applicable lessons and/or section(s) of lessons from the suite of 500 lessons were then identified for each package's subtopics. A general instructor's usage guide was developed for each course support package, and additional information describing the type and location(s) of applicable content within each lesson was provided. Graphics and media items, which included 2D and 3D images, movies, and data loops, were packaged so that instructors could easily search and download them to use as support for lectures, laboratory activities or other applications. Since these images are public domain, creative commons, or under copyright approval agreement with COMET sponsors, faculty and students are free to use and modify them.   The University Course Support Resource saw frequent usage throughout the 2020-2021 academic year. By May 2021, there were over 24,000 pageviews for the resource, with Introduction to Meteorology, Dynamic Meteorology, and Synoptic Meteorology being the most popular packages.  A university instructor user survey was developed and distributed in May 2021, with overwhelmingly positive responses from over 30 respondents: 76% of survey respondents indicated that they agreed or strongly agreed that the resource met their course objectives, and 73% said that they would recommend the resource to others.  Survey respondents primarily used the resource to: 1 - supplement existing lecture, lab, or class material (58%), 2 - serve as additional homework or assignment material (42%), and 3 - serve as alternative to usual classroom or textbook material (39%). This resource clearly addressed demonstrated onsite and virtual classroom needs from US meteorology faculty, and will enable university staff and students to more easily integrate high-quality conceptual and case example materials into their own courses, to easily assign refresher training, or to support exploratory experiences to their students. The materials also boost faculty members' abilities to attempt a "flipped classroom" experience by increasing the amount of background material available for students' review before discussion.  Further, the availability of pre- and post-tests for each lesson allow faculty to more easily assess concepts with which students are struggling.  The course packages can potentially ease the burden that early-career and/or small-department faculty members may face by providing a repository of relevant conceptual diagrams and case study datasets, allowing them to devote attention to the many competing aspects of their job.   Finally, the resource was used by a variety of non-university users, including government employees, private sector employees, emergency managers, broadcasters, and even weather enthusiasts. Moving beyond the United States, this resource is directly applicable to many national hydrometeorological services in meeting the requirements of the World Meteorological Organization's Basic Instruction Package for Meteorologists, and will remain freely-available to anyone interested in accessing high-quality geoscience learning materials well beyond the COVID era.             Last Modified: 10/29/2021       Submitted by: Andrea Smith]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
