<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SII Planning: NASCE: A National Spectrum Center to Conquer, Program, and Protect the Wireless Spectrum]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>175000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>175000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AST</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ashley  Vanderley</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bevander@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922428</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This award is a planning grant for the Spectrum Innovation Initiative:  National Center for Wireless Spectrum Research (SII-Center).  The focus of a spectrum research SII-Center goes beyond 5G, IoT, and other existing or forthcoming systems and technologies to chart out a trajectory to ensure United States leadership in future wireless technologies, systems, and applications in science and engineering through the efficient use and sharing of the radio spectrum. The objective of this project is to lay the foundations to establish the new Spectrum Innovation Initiative (SII) center NASCE: A National Spectrum CEnter for convergent research on transformative approaches to develop new spectrum science and technology. Today’s wireless spectrum is exceptionally crowded. It is expected that by 2025, over 75 billion devices will be absorbed into the Internet, generating a global network of “things'' of dimensions never seen before, all in need of unbounded wireless access. Beyond the clear commercial strategic needs, technologies such as 5G and the Internet of Things (IoT) are also critical for national security, shaping a technological revolution with far-reaching social, economic, and geostrategic consequences. Wireless systems will continue to change the way we live, work, manufacture goods, and protect our citizens. Furthermore, the role that wireless connectivity is playing as a unique vehicle to provide work and educational opportunities during the current COVID-19 pandemic—especially in rural areas—cannot be overstated. The overarching objective of this center is to foster the creation of next generation wireless systems capable of using the whole wireless spectrum, from a few Hertz (Hz) to Terahertz. The team will conduct advanced research in technology areas in support of the commercial sector, all segments of the wireless market, defense and intelligence agencies, in cooperation with leading industries in the field.  All center activities are designed to prepare students and continuous learners for careers in spectrum-related fields via experiential learning, research, new workshops and shareable educational modules.    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research promoted by this project is organized into three interdependent research thrusts: (i) Conquering the spectrum, with a focus on interdisciplinary approaches for broadening existing available spectrum options; (ii) programming the spectrum, for developing the foundations of applying modern data-driven techniques and software-defined networking for blue-sky approaches to spectrum sharing and exploitation; (iii) protecting the spectrum, for new algorithms and systems for reliable exploitation of the available spectrum in civil and contested environments, and protecting incumbent users. Orthogonal and pervasive to these fundamental thrusts, center plans and operations will be informed by the following technological themes: (a) policing the spectrum, with the twofold aim of providing technology for enforcing regulatory policies, and providing key agencies with technological and policy advice to shape the wireless future of our nation; (b) an Artificial Intelligence approach to new data-driven techniques for inference and control of large amount of spectrum data, and (c) perform and enable large scale experimentation and emulation thanks to our privileged access to NSF PAWR platforms, Colosseum, the largest RF networked channel emulator in the world, and to a Terahertz wireless networking testbed.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/04/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/04/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2037896</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Stefano</FirstName>
<LastName>Basagni</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Stefano Basagni</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[basagni@ece.neu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000097788</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/04/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kaushik</FirstName>
<LastName>Chowdhury</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kaushik R Chowdhury</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[krc@ece.neu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000541186</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/04/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Josep</FirstName>
<LastName>Jornet</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Josep M Jornet</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[j.jornet@northeastern.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000657374</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/04/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tommaso</FirstName>
<LastName>Melodia</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Tommaso Melodia</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[melodia@northeastern.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000676111</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/04/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Abhimanyu</FirstName>
<LastName>Gosain</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Abhimanyu Gosain</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[agosain@coe.neu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000762779</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/04/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Northeastern University</Name>
<CityName>BOSTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>021155005</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6173733004</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>360 HUNTINGTON AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>HLTMVS2JZBS6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORTHEASTERN UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Northeastern University]]></Name>
<CityName>Boston</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021155005</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[360 Huntington Ave, 540-177 HU]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>151Y</Code>
<Text>SII-Spectrum Innovation Initia</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>4444</Code>
<Text>INTERDISCIPLINARY PROPOSALS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~175000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The planning grant has made it possible to prepare, finalize and eventually submit the NASCE proposal to the NSF. Despite the proposal was ultimately not selected for funding, this grant has fostered and facilitated cooperation between the involved institutions which took this unique opportunity to start cooperative research within the scope of the NASCE ecosystem. These joint efforts have been successful in driving convergent and cooperative research, which will ultimately impact the research community and the US people. &nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <ul> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><strong>Dynamic spectrum sharing between active and passive users above 100 GHz </strong><span>- Sixth-generation wireless networks will aggregate higher-than-ever mobile traffic into ultra-high capacity backhaul links, which could be deployed on the largely untapped spectrum above 100 GHz. Current regulations however prevent the allocation of large contiguous bands for communications at these frequencies, since several narrow bands are reserved to protect passive sensing services. These include radio astronomy and Earth exploration satellites using sensors that suffer from harmful interference from active transmitters. Here we show that active and passive spectrum sharing above 100&thinsp;GHz is feasible by introducing and experimentally evaluating a real-time, dual-band backhaul prototype that tracks the presence of passive users (in this case the NASA satellite Aura) and avoids interference by automatically switching bands (123.5&ndash;140&thinsp;GHz and 210&ndash;225 GHz). Our system enables wide-band transmissions in the above-100-GHz spectrum, while avoiding harmful interference to satellite systems, paving the way for innovative spectrum policy and technologies in these crucial bands.</span></p> </li> <li><strong>Coexistence and spectrum sharing above 100 GHz</strong> - We explored how spectrum policy and spectrum technologies can evolve to enable sharing among different stakeholders in the above 100 GHz spectrum, without introducing harmful interference or disrupting either security applications or fundamental science exploration. This portion of the spectrum presents new opportunities to design spectrum sharing schemes, based on novel antenna designs, directional ultra-high-rate communications, and active/passive user coordination. The paper provides a tutorial on current regulations above 100 GHz, and highlights how sharing is central to allowing each stakeholder to make the most out of this spectrum. It then defines - through detailed simulations based on standard International Telecommunications Union (ITU) channel and antenna models - scenarios in which active users may introduce harmful interference to passive sensing. Based on this evaluation, it reviews a number of promising techniques that can enable active/passive sharing above 100 GHz. The critical review and tutorial on policy and technologies of this paper have the potential to kickstart future research and regulations that promote safe coexistence between active and passive users above 100 GHz, further benefiting the development of digital technologies and scientific exploration.</li> </ul> <ul> <li><strong>6G Spectrum Sharing and Platform Technologies</strong> - NASCE researchers presented at the Fall 2022 6GSymposium held in Washington D.C. October 11-12 &lt;<a href="https://www.6gworld.com/6gsymposium-fall-2022/">https://www.6gworld.com/6gsymposium-fall-2022/</a>&gt;. This event is the first North American venue discussing 6G technologies and policy. PI Melodia led the event as the main co-organizer&nbsp; with introductory remarks and Co-PI(s) Jornet and Gosain led panels on Next G Technology &ndash; The Air Interface and Building Blocks Of The Experience: Spectrum and Testbeds. The event was attended by a live audience of 300 participants from industry,academia and government and hundreds more online. All panel recordings are made available online.</li> </ul><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/20/2023<br>      Modified by: Tommaso&nbsp;Melodia</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The planning grant has made it possible to prepare, finalize and eventually submit the NASCE proposal to the NSF. Despite the proposal was ultimately not selected for funding, this grant has fostered and facilitated cooperation between the involved institutions which took this unique opportunity to start cooperative research within the scope of the NASCE ecosystem. These joint efforts have been successful in driving convergent and cooperative research, which will ultimately impact the research community and the US people.      Dynamic spectrum sharing between active and passive users above 100 GHz - Sixth-generation wireless networks will aggregate higher-than-ever mobile traffic into ultra-high capacity backhaul links, which could be deployed on the largely untapped spectrum above 100 GHz. Current regulations however prevent the allocation of large contiguous bands for communications at these frequencies, since several narrow bands are reserved to protect passive sensing services. These include radio astronomy and Earth exploration satellites using sensors that suffer from harmful interference from active transmitters. Here we show that active and passive spectrum sharing above 100&thinsp;GHz is feasible by introducing and experimentally evaluating a real-time, dual-band backhaul prototype that tracks the presence of passive users (in this case the NASA satellite Aura) and avoids interference by automatically switching bands (123.5&ndash;140&thinsp;GHz and 210&ndash;225 GHz). Our system enables wide-band transmissions in the above-100-GHz spectrum, while avoiding harmful interference to satellite systems, paving the way for innovative spectrum policy and technologies in these crucial bands.  Coexistence and spectrum sharing above 100 GHz - We explored how spectrum policy and spectrum technologies can evolve to enable sharing among different stakeholders in the above 100 GHz spectrum, without introducing harmful interference or disrupting either security applications or fundamental science exploration. This portion of the spectrum presents new opportunities to design spectrum sharing schemes, based on novel antenna designs, directional ultra-high-rate communications, and active/passive user coordination. The paper provides a tutorial on current regulations above 100 GHz, and highlights how sharing is central to allowing each stakeholder to make the most out of this spectrum. It then defines - through detailed simulations based on standard International Telecommunications Union (ITU) channel and antenna models - scenarios in which active users may introduce harmful interference to passive sensing. Based on this evaluation, it reviews a number of promising techniques that can enable active/passive sharing above 100 GHz. The critical review and tutorial on policy and technologies of this paper have the potential to kickstart future research and regulations that promote safe coexistence between active and passive users above 100 GHz, further benefiting the development of digital technologies and scientific exploration.   6G Spectrum Sharing and Platform Technologies - NASCE researchers presented at the Fall 2022 6GSymposium held in Washington D.C. October 11-12 &lt;https://www.6gworld.com/6gsymposium-fall-2022/&gt;. This event is the first North American venue discussing 6G technologies and policy. PI Melodia led the event as the main co-organizer  with introductory remarks and Co-PI(s) Jornet and Gosain led panels on Next G Technology &ndash; The Air Interface and Building Blocks Of The Experience: Spectrum and Testbeds. The event was attended by a live audience of 300 participants from industry,academia and government and hundreds more online. All panel recordings are made available online.        Last Modified: 01/20/2023       Submitted by: Tommaso Melodia]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
