<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Virtual Reality Cyberinfrastructure Enabling Data Visualization, Exploration, and Collaboration Among Distant Individuals]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>66833.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>66833</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AST</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Hans Krimm</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>hkrimm@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922761</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The COVID-19 pandemic has introduced obstacles to many areas of astronomical research, especially topics requiring access to shared facilities and driven by interaction between scientists to interpret complex multi-dimensional data. A research team at Purdue University will accelerate production of the Virtual Reality (VR) data visualization platform Collaborative Astronomy VR, which leverages recent advancements in high-powered consumer hardware and cloud-based multi-user server architecture. Building this platform will globally connect individuals isolated by COVID-19 restrictions and provide virtual environments where they can actively engage with complex data and representations. The distributed application will be tailored for immersive visualization of supernova explosions and other topics in astronomy, but will have flexibility for potential use in other fields requiring visualization and interaction with 3D data environments. The work will contribute to a graduate student thesis and provide opportunities for undergraduate students, who will actively help develop and showcase the technology. A small instructional lab for physics and astronomy classes will also be created.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The platform will be appropriate to visualize, explore, and collaborate with data made from observations and simulations of astronomical objects and phenomena. The flexible data ingestion pipeline will support multi-dimensional formats common to astronomical data, and will have clean up and optimization procedures to ensure data fidelity and fluid visualizations.  This project fulfills the urgent need for scientists to navigate complex, multi-dimensional data collaboratively with distant individuals via scalable multiuser connectivity and broad platform compatibility. Collaborative Astronomy VR enables rapid and intuitive exploration of multidimensional data with on-the-fly scaling, rotation, and changing of perspective among many participants connected online simultaneously.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/16/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/16/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2037297</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Danny</FirstName>
<LastName>Milisavljevic</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Danny Milisavljevic</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[dmilisav@purdue.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000763991</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/16/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Purdue University</Name>
<CityName>WEST LAFAYETTE</CityName>
<ZipCode>479061332</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7654941055</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2550 NORTHWESTERN AVE STE 1900</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IN04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>YRXVL4JYCEF5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PURDUE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>YRXVL4JYCEF5</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Purdue University]]></Name>
<CityName>West Lafayette</CityName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>479072114</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IN04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1215</Code>
<Text>STELLAR ASTRONOMY &amp; ASTROPHYSC</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1206</Code>
<Text>THEORETICAL &amp; COMPUTATIONAL ASTROPHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~66833</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Background</strong>: The COVID-19 pandemic introduced obstacles to many areas of astronomical research, especially topics requiring access to shared facilities and driven by interaction between scientists to interpret multi-dimensional data. Virtual Reality (VR) was identified as powerful tool that could provide unique solutions to these problems and accelerate research benefiting from immersive visualization, given wide-spread interest and significant investment by companies in the technology. Unfortunately, VR infrastructures are generally either 1) too focused on social interaction for large audiences and lack options to appropriately visualize and explore scientific data in a scalable format, or 2) lack multiuser connectivity and instead focus on specialized individual experiences for use on high-end devices. Hence, we were motivated to create a VR application that could overcome this infrastructure gap and fulfill the need for scientists to navigate complex, multi-dimensional data collaboratively without a steep financial barrier, either between co-located participants or with remotely connected individuals via scalable multiuser connectivity and broad platform compatibility. &nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Intellectual Merit</strong>: The research funded by this NSF RAPID grant made it possible to create a Collaborative Astronomy VR app on very short timescales that could respond to some of the urgent challenges faced by astronomical research introduced by the COVID-19 pandemic. The platform itself is built using the Unity 3D engine and deployed on Oculus (now Meta) Quest headsets connected via a cloud computing service MLAPI. Users share a virtual space and can perform on-the-fly scaling, rotation, and changing of perspective, to collaboratively explore multi-dimensional data of four supernova remnants located in the Milky Way and Magellanic Clouds: Cassiopeia A, the Crab Nebula, 1E0102.2-7219, and N132D. Participants utilize customized avatars with expressions, and communicate with their microphones and a variety of sketching and gesturing motions made possible with their hand controllers. The app has been used in multiple research projects attempting to understand the progenitor systems and explosion mechanisms of supernovae via their remnants where comparative 3D morphology is needed, and has contributed to analysis and visualizations presented in several peer-reviewed papers. Ultimately, by placing appropriately visualized 3D reconstructions in an immersive VR platform, the Collaborative Astronomy VR application has made it much easier to interpret, explore, and share formidable and heterogeneous collections of information.&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts</strong>: The Collaborative Astronomy VR app has been used as an enabling tool for a variety of research projects and proposals that have been reported in peer-reviewed articles, colloquia, conference talks, and public presentations. Several undergraduate and graduate students have benefited from using and developing the application, and it has been incorporated into multiple graduate theses. The application is relatively easy to load into headsets, and the code is publicly available to download. The infrastructure is flexible enough to allow potential use in many other fields requiring visualizing and interacting with 3D data and environments, enabling professionals and non-professionals to explore the packaged data sets or import their own data. Collaborative Astronomy VR has also been featured in numerous articles as an example of state-of-the-art immersive learning using AR/VR technologies. Finally, the application has been used extensively in astronomy teaching at Purdue University. Many classes now use it for keystone virtual field trip experiences to illustrate and explain supernova explosions and their remnants.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/28/2023<br>      Modified by: Danny&nbsp;Milisavljevic</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2037297/2037297_10677501_1688007728259_milisavljevic-cropLO--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2037297/2037297_10677501_1688007728259_milisavljevic-cropLO--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Collaborative Astronomy VR"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2037297/2037297_10677501_1688007728259_milisavljevic-cropLO--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Collaborative Astronomy VR"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Close up of avatar used by PI Danny Milisavljevic to teach astronomy class to students using Collaborative Astronomy VR.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Danny Milisavljevic</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Danny&nbsp;Milisavljevic</div> <div class="imageTitle">Collaborative Astronomy VR</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2037297/2037297_10677501_1688007345679_class-photo-vr--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2037297/2037297_10677501_1688007345679_class-photo-vr--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Class Photo from Collaborative Astronomy VR classroom"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2037297/2037297_10677501_1688007345679_class-photo-vr--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Class Photo from Collaborative Astronomy VR classroom"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Example of Collaborate Astronomy VR used for class instruction.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Danny Milisavljevic</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Danny&nbsp;Milisavljevic</div> <div class="imageTitle">Class Photo from Collaborative Astronomy VR classroom</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2037297/2037297_10677501_1688007637389_class-instruction-crab--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2037297/2037297_10677501_1688007637389_class-instruction-crab--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Collaborative Astronomy VR used for Crab Nebula"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2037297/2037297_10677501_1688007637389_class-instruction-crab--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Collaborative Astronomy VR used for Crab Nebula"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Example of multiple participants using final version of Collaborative Astronomy VR to explore the Crab Nebula</div> <div class="imageCredit">Danny Milisavljevic</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Danny&nbsp;Milisavljevic</div> <div class="imageTitle">Collaborative Astronomy VR used for Crab Nebula</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Background: The COVID-19 pandemic introduced obstacles to many areas of astronomical research, especially topics requiring access to shared facilities and driven by interaction between scientists to interpret multi-dimensional data. Virtual Reality (VR) was identified as powerful tool that could provide unique solutions to these problems and accelerate research benefiting from immersive visualization, given wide-spread interest and significant investment by companies in the technology. Unfortunately, VR infrastructures are generally either 1) too focused on social interaction for large audiences and lack options to appropriately visualize and explore scientific data in a scalable format, or 2) lack multiuser connectivity and instead focus on specialized individual experiences for use on high-end devices. Hence, we were motivated to create a VR application that could overcome this infrastructure gap and fulfill the need for scientists to navigate complex, multi-dimensional data collaboratively without a steep financial barrier, either between co-located participants or with remotely connected individuals via scalable multiuser connectivity and broad platform compatibility.    Intellectual Merit: The research funded by this NSF RAPID grant made it possible to create a Collaborative Astronomy VR app on very short timescales that could respond to some of the urgent challenges faced by astronomical research introduced by the COVID-19 pandemic. The platform itself is built using the Unity 3D engine and deployed on Oculus (now Meta) Quest headsets connected via a cloud computing service MLAPI. Users share a virtual space and can perform on-the-fly scaling, rotation, and changing of perspective, to collaboratively explore multi-dimensional data of four supernova remnants located in the Milky Way and Magellanic Clouds: Cassiopeia A, the Crab Nebula, 1E0102.2-7219, and N132D. Participants utilize customized avatars with expressions, and communicate with their microphones and a variety of sketching and gesturing motions made possible with their hand controllers. The app has been used in multiple research projects attempting to understand the progenitor systems and explosion mechanisms of supernovae via their remnants where comparative 3D morphology is needed, and has contributed to analysis and visualizations presented in several peer-reviewed papers. Ultimately, by placing appropriately visualized 3D reconstructions in an immersive VR platform, the Collaborative Astronomy VR application has made it much easier to interpret, explore, and share formidable and heterogeneous collections of information.   Broader Impacts: The Collaborative Astronomy VR app has been used as an enabling tool for a variety of research projects and proposals that have been reported in peer-reviewed articles, colloquia, conference talks, and public presentations. Several undergraduate and graduate students have benefited from using and developing the application, and it has been incorporated into multiple graduate theses. The application is relatively easy to load into headsets, and the code is publicly available to download. The infrastructure is flexible enough to allow potential use in many other fields requiring visualizing and interacting with 3D data and environments, enabling professionals and non-professionals to explore the packaged data sets or import their own data. Collaborative Astronomy VR has also been featured in numerous articles as an example of state-of-the-art immersive learning using AR/VR technologies. Finally, the application has been used extensively in astronomy teaching at Purdue University. Many classes now use it for keystone virtual field trip experiences to illustrate and explain supernova explosions and their remnants.       Last Modified: 06/28/2023       Submitted by: Danny Milisavljevic]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
