<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Build and Broaden: We Still Remain: A Conference Toward the Promotion of Southeast Indigenous Research, Scholarship, and Collaboration]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>144236.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>144236</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Enrique Pumar</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>epumar@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925188</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The stories of the Southeastern Indigenous Peoples who remain often are lost in the white-black binary story that is told in this region. We Still Remain Conference (WSRC) is co-hosted by the University of Arizona and University of North Carolina at Pembroke to improve the public’s understanding of SE Indigenous Peoples. This two-day conference will gather Indigenous and non-Indigenous students and scholars from various disciplines to (1) examine areas of tension in research affecting underserved groups; (2) document ways Indigenous Peoples without federal recognition might govern research within their jurisdiction; and (3) test how a community of practice model might change individual and institutional behaviors of research. This conference will amplify the general awareness of the sovereign status of SE Indigenous Peoples. The results will be disseminated broadly for academic and non-academic audiences. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;WSRC objectives are to: (1) characterize and define SE Indigenous studies; (2) encourage underrepresented undergraduate and graduate students interested in SE Indigenous Peoples; (3) increase the promotion of SE Indigenous Peoples research and education; and (4) support early career and senior scholars in their research development. The conference will feature a plenary session, small group workshops, student poster sessions and invited guest speakers to provide context and perspective of emergent themes. Expected outcomes are to increase collaborative research opportunities and share evidence-based practices. The conference will broaden policy impact--not only among Indigenous communities, but local and state governments that engage these communities, and connect researchers and their research topics more closely to community needs. The success of the conference will be measured through pre- and post-conference evaluations, anecdotal and empirical evidence, and subsequent publications disseminated.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/24/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/14/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2037256</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Danielle</FirstName>
<LastName>Hiraldo</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>V</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Danielle V Hiraldo</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[hiraldo@unc.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000749556</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/24/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mary</FirstName>
<LastName>Jacobs</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mary A Jacobs</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mary.jacobs@uncp.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000829605</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/24/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Arizona</Name>
<CityName>TUCSON</CityName>
<ZipCode>85721</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5206266000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>845 N PARK AVE RM 538</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AZ07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>ED44Y3W6P7B9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ARIZONA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Arizona]]></Name>
<CityName>Tucson</CityName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>857194831</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[803 E. 1st Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AZ07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>146Y</Code>
<Text>Build and Broaden</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1390</Code>
<Text>CULTURAL ANTHROPOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~144236</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-35339e74-7fff-4962-7c34-edac756c5060"><span>The University of Arizona (UArizona) and University of North Carolina at Pembroke (UNCP) co-hosted We Still Remain: A Conference Toward the Promotion of Southeast Indigenous Research, Scholarship, and Collaboration (WSRC), a two-day conference that gathered Indigenous and non-Indigenous students and scholars from education, social sciences, STEM, and humanities. A significant feature of the conference was the incorporation of community voices. Community members, students, and faculty discussed gaps in Southeast (SE) Indigenous research and offered solutions to building a network to elevate SE Indigenous voices. All of the presentations were from researchers who were engaged with Native American community partners, some who had decades long relationships over multiple projects. The WSRC offered great insight on how universities and SE Indigenous communities might partner in research. The prevailing point that came out of the conference is the need to continue to tell our stories. SE Indigenous communities are more than capable of telling their own stories. Researchers need to recognize tribal community capacity and solutions that exist within these communities and approach building partnerships that continue to strengthen that capacity rather than being extractive to tell our stories for us. The outcomes of WSRC are increased collaborative research opportunities and shared evidence-based practices. The conference heightened understanding of the conditions that impact the Indigenous peoples who have remained, broadened discussions on policy impact--not only among Indigenous communities, but local and state governments that engage these communities, and connected researchers and their research topics more closely to community needs.</span></span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/24/2023<br>      Modified by: Danielle&nbsp;V&nbsp;Hiraldo</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The University of Arizona (UArizona) and University of North Carolina at Pembroke (UNCP) co-hosted We Still Remain: A Conference Toward the Promotion of Southeast Indigenous Research, Scholarship, and Collaboration (WSRC), a two-day conference that gathered Indigenous and non-Indigenous students and scholars from education, social sciences, STEM, and humanities. A significant feature of the conference was the incorporation of community voices. Community members, students, and faculty discussed gaps in Southeast (SE) Indigenous research and offered solutions to building a network to elevate SE Indigenous voices. All of the presentations were from researchers who were engaged with Native American community partners, some who had decades long relationships over multiple projects. The WSRC offered great insight on how universities and SE Indigenous communities might partner in research. The prevailing point that came out of the conference is the need to continue to tell our stories. SE Indigenous communities are more than capable of telling their own stories. Researchers need to recognize tribal community capacity and solutions that exist within these communities and approach building partnerships that continue to strengthen that capacity rather than being extractive to tell our stories for us. The outcomes of WSRC are increased collaborative research opportunities and shared evidence-based practices. The conference heightened understanding of the conditions that impact the Indigenous peoples who have remained, broadened discussions on policy impact--not only among Indigenous communities, but local and state governments that engage these communities, and connected researchers and their research topics more closely to community needs.       Last Modified: 03/24/2023       Submitted by: Danielle V Hiraldo]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
