<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Building Accessible Pathways for a Broad Workforce of Mathematics and Science Teachers]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>49997.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>49997</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>HRD</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Emanuel WAddell</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The Historically Black Colleges and Universities - Undergraduate Program (HBCU-UP) supports conferences and workshops that seek to increase the research and education capacity of science, technology, engineering, and mathematics (STEM) students and faculty at HBCUs. Lincoln University in Missouri, in partnership with the University of Missouri – Columbia, will hold a workshop to address issues of STEM teacher recruitment, retention, and lack of diversity. University faculty and administrators, principals, superintendents, and teachers will participate in the two-day student conference on May 19-20, 2021 at Lincoln University. Plans include changing the meeting to a virtual format, if needed. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The conference activities will be guided by three goals: 1) to provide structure and guidance for an online alternative certification program for mathematics and science teachers; 2) to develop a multi-pronged recruitment plan for the alternative certification program; and 3) to identify a viable research collaboration between Lincoln University and the University of Missouri related to the alternative certification of mathematics and science teachers of color. The conference will have substantial impact on the partnership and collaborations between mathematics and science educators at Lincoln University and the University of Missouri. The inclusion of state representatives, as well as various school and community stakeholders, at the conference can lead to broader impacts across the state of Missouri.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/30/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/30/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2037429</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gouranga</FirstName>
<LastName>Saha</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME>Dr</PI_SUFX_NAME>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gouranga Saha</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[sahag@lincolnu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000125607</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/30/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Charles</FirstName>
<LastName>Munter</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Charles M Munter</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[munterc@missouri.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000617521</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/30/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Samuel</FirstName>
<LastName>Otten</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Samuel J Otten</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ottensa@missouri.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000627800</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/30/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Lincoln University</Name>
<CityName>JEFFERSON CITY</CityName>
<ZipCode>651023537</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5736815030</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>820 CHESTNUT ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MO03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>JJLJP4TQ9HM7</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>LINCOLN UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>JJLJP4TQ9HM7</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Lincoln University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>651023500</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MO03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1594</Code>
<Text>Hist Black Colleges and Univ</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0420</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~49997</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="Pa4">We held the virtual symposium on May 19-20, 2021, with various stakeholders from schools, universities, state departments, communities, and scholarly experts. The leadership team also met throughout the summer to plan and debrief from the virtual symposium in relation to the major goals.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p class="Default">The two-day virtual symposium involved presentations of historical context and research literature on alternative certification for science and mathematics teachers and with regard to diversity in the teaching workforce. This had the potential of increasing awareness for school officials, state leaders, and university personnel alike.</p> <p class="Default">&nbsp;</p> <p class="Default">The project also involved two student assistants working closely throughout the activities of the project. They were able to learn about the information mentioned above and also about the roles of various people in the school, university, and state education systems. The student assistants, and the PI/Co-PIs, and indeed many of the symposium attendees, made new professional connections.</p> <p>How have the results been disseminated to communities of interest?</p> <p>Science education and mathematics education leaders at Lincoln University and the University of Missouri were impacted with regard to their understanding of the school&rsquo;s needs and desires related to teacher recruitment and retention. This information will impact the revision of alternative certification programs at the universities. For example, at the University of Missouri, they are seeking to activate an online alternative certification program that will allow teacher candidates to be placed immediately in the school settings (a desire expressed by several school leaders at the symposium) and they are seeking to build a retention strategy that begins with research-informed mentoring during the certification program and also continued university supports after certification (a recommendation expressed by consultants at the symposium).</p> <p class="Default">Slides from the virtual symposium and key resources (e.g., reports, scholarly articles) have been shared with all attendees via a shared digital folder. We are also preparing a written report that will be sent to all attendees, containing a summary of the points of discussion from the symposium. We intend for the report to be finalized and sent in August 2021.</p> <p class="Default">&nbsp;</p> <p>Additionally, one of the Co-PIs has been sharing about the symposium at a meeting of a statewide equity advisory committee, which includes representatives from multiple organizations and institutions who are pursuing equity initiatives in K-16 educational and career settings.&nbsp;</p> <p class="Default">&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/29/2021<br>      Modified by: Gouranga&nbsp;Saha</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[We held the virtual symposium on May 19-20, 2021, with various stakeholders from schools, universities, state departments, communities, and scholarly experts. The leadership team also met throughout the summer to plan and debrief from the virtual symposium in relation to the major goals.    The two-day virtual symposium involved presentations of historical context and research literature on alternative certification for science and mathematics teachers and with regard to diversity in the teaching workforce. This had the potential of increasing awareness for school officials, state leaders, and university personnel alike.   The project also involved two student assistants working closely throughout the activities of the project. They were able to learn about the information mentioned above and also about the roles of various people in the school, university, and state education systems. The student assistants, and the PI/Co-PIs, and indeed many of the symposium attendees, made new professional connections.  How have the results been disseminated to communities of interest?  Science education and mathematics education leaders at Lincoln University and the University of Missouri were impacted with regard to their understanding of the school’s needs and desires related to teacher recruitment and retention. This information will impact the revision of alternative certification programs at the universities. For example, at the University of Missouri, they are seeking to activate an online alternative certification program that will allow teacher candidates to be placed immediately in the school settings (a desire expressed by several school leaders at the symposium) and they are seeking to build a retention strategy that begins with research-informed mentoring during the certification program and also continued university supports after certification (a recommendation expressed by consultants at the symposium). Slides from the virtual symposium and key resources (e.g., reports, scholarly articles) have been shared with all attendees via a shared digital folder. We are also preparing a written report that will be sent to all attendees, containing a summary of the points of discussion from the symposium. We intend for the report to be finalized and sent in August 2021.    Additionally, one of the Co-PIs has been sharing about the symposium at a meeting of a statewide equity advisory committee, which includes representatives from multiple organizations and institutions who are pursuing equity initiatives in K-16 educational and career settings.             Last Modified: 09/29/2021       Submitted by: Gouranga Saha]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
