<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SII Planning: Escaping Gravity: The End of Gs]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>175000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>175000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AST</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ashley  Vanderley</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bevander@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922428</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This award is a planning grant for the Spectrum Innovation Initiative:  National Center for Wireless Spectrum Research (SII-Center).  The focus of a spectrum research SII-Center goes beyond 5G, IoT, and other existing or forthcoming systems and technologies to chart out a trajectory to ensure United States leadership in future wireless technologies, systems, and applications in science and engineering through the efficient use and sharing of the radio spectrum. This project aims to catalyze the activities of a multi-disciplinary academic team and stakeholders towards collaborative long-term research, education, workforce development and establishing the definitive center of spectrum engineering, policy and science. The SII-Center is envisioned as the corner stone of trans-disciplinary effort, amalgamating efforts of academics, industry, government, policy, standard bodies and scientific and civic communities. The center will transform wireless communications anytime, anywhere, providing use and utilization of spectrum ubiquitously and seamlessly across networks, devices and communities, addressing the critical need of closing the digital divide, providing reliable and secure access to information for all.  The broader impact of this effort will directly contribute to the United States reclaiming its rightful place as the global leader in wireless communications and information processing in the internet of everything era.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The comprehensive research vision of the center is to establish the next and last generation of wireless connectivity by an integrative system design that will build on optimal use of wireless resources throughout the spectrum, from hardware to system design, software and policy, ensuring coexistence requirements of communities who are primary users of the spectrum. The project will seek to (i) refine the research vision by engaging industry, government, research labs, and communities with use requirements such as remote sensing and radio astronomy; (ii) formulate research partnerships towards executing the vision; (iii) prepare a comprehensive white paper which will not only contribute to the center proposal, but importantly, will be a stand alone guide for government, learned societies, communities, industry and academia on the last generation of wireless, i.e., a holistic system design making optimum and seamless spectrum utilization an innate component from the outset.  The center vision includes inter-disciplinary curricula and workforce development for spectrum science and engineering.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/04/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/04/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2037839</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Joel</FirstName>
<LastName>Johnson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>T</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Joel T Johnson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[johnson.1374@osu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000258473</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/04/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Muriel</FirstName>
<LastName>Medard</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Muriel Medard</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[medard@mit.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000106371</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/04/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Aylin</FirstName>
<LastName>Yener</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Aylin Yener</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[yener@ece.osu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000203128</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/04/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Starobinski</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David Starobinski</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[staro@bu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000491258</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/04/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tara</FirstName>
<LastName>Javidi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Tara Javidi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[tara@ece.ucsd.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000331478</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/04/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Ohio State University</Name>
<CityName>COLUMBUS</CityName>
<ZipCode>432101016</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6146888735</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1960 KENNY RD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OH03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>DLWBSLWAJWR1</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OHIO STATE UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>MN4MDDMN8529</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Ohio State University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>432101016</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OH03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>151Y</Code>
<Text>SII-Spectrum Innovation Initia</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>4444</Code>
<Text>INTERDISCIPLINARY PROPOSALS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~175000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>MIT participated in multiple meetings and the writing of a proposal. It received no funding.&nbsp;</p> <p>Our motivation in wanting to pursue this vision, other than the engineering impact we could collectively have&nbsp;make with an authoritative center, was to help US leapfrog to its rightful position as the world leader in wireless<br />and spectrum innovations. Its ambition was to be&nbsp;the corner stone of transdisciplinary effort&nbsp;starting from hardware all the way to services and policy making, amalgamating efforts of academics, industry, government, policy, standard bodies and communities.&nbsp;</p> <p>The MIT PI and the MIT colleagues provided input and leadership on new methods for next generation wireless systems, with particular emphasis on matters such as open standards (through universal decoding), new hardware techniques for integrating machine learning and networking, wireless networks and machine learning, the effect of next Gs on organizations and work, security in future networks, and policy matters.</p> <p>The efforts were arranged according to the following themes: holistic wireless network architectures to operate seamlessly over wide spectral bands and signaling technologies across a wide range devices with different capabilities; purposeful component and hardware design for high adaptability,&nbsp;security and energy efficiency; distributed multi-access for dynamic spectrum sharing through&nbsp;identifying fundamental limits of key performance metrics in the presence of diverse user dynamics and delay sensitivities; fast learning and optimization for mobile wireless networks&nbsp;to adapt quickly to changing environments&nbsp;through new online learning and optimization strategies; security, privacy, sustainable and responsible spectrum use as spectrum agility and sharing, implies openness, but brings the possibility of new attack&nbsp;surfaces.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/01/2022<br>      Modified by: Muriel&nbsp;Medard</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ MIT participated in multiple meetings and the writing of a proposal. It received no funding.   Our motivation in wanting to pursue this vision, other than the engineering impact we could collectively have make with an authoritative center, was to help US leapfrog to its rightful position as the world leader in wireless and spectrum innovations. Its ambition was to be the corner stone of transdisciplinary effort starting from hardware all the way to services and policy making, amalgamating efforts of academics, industry, government, policy, standard bodies and communities.   The MIT PI and the MIT colleagues provided input and leadership on new methods for next generation wireless systems, with particular emphasis on matters such as open standards (through universal decoding), new hardware techniques for integrating machine learning and networking, wireless networks and machine learning, the effect of next Gs on organizations and work, security in future networks, and policy matters.  The efforts were arranged according to the following themes: holistic wireless network architectures to operate seamlessly over wide spectral bands and signaling technologies across a wide range devices with different capabilities; purposeful component and hardware design for high adaptability, security and energy efficiency; distributed multi-access for dynamic spectrum sharing through identifying fundamental limits of key performance metrics in the presence of diverse user dynamics and delay sensitivities; fast learning and optimization for mobile wireless networks to adapt quickly to changing environments through new online learning and optimization strategies; security, privacy, sustainable and responsible spectrum use as spectrum agility and sharing, implies openness, but brings the possibility of new attack surfaces.                   Last Modified: 07/01/2022       Submitted by: Muriel Medard]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
