<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[I-Corps:  Cell Culture Platform Using Engineered Micropatterns to Control Differentiation]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ruth Shuman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rshuman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922160</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this I-Corps project is the development of an in vitro, articular cartilage model for osteoarthritis (OA). This model is designed to increase the likelihood of successful clinical translation of research on the causes of OA into potential treatments.  OA often occurs with age or injury and affects over 32.5 million US adults. There are currently no known disease-modifying treatments to stop or reverse the progression of OA – all current treatments are limited to either various methods of pain management or surgical tissue replacement. The proposed technology will advance the translation of OA research by facilitating studies of chondrocytes, the primary cells that cause OA, using traditional and state-of-the-art genomic, proteomic, and imaging techniques. It is expected that the proposed technology will bridge the gap between the 2D and 3D cell culture markets, represented by an annual market of ~$1 billion in the US. Due to the prevalence and crippling nature of OA, joint replacements represent a $19 billion industry annually in the US. In addition to its role in OA treatments, the model may clinical implications in improving outcomes for autologous chondrocyte transplantation, increasing its commercial impact.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project is based on the development of a cell culture platform that improves control over the differentiation of chondrocytes. This control is enabled through the regulation of cell shape via a novel combination of nanotechnology, micropatterning, and mechanically-tunable, thin-film composite materials. Chondrocytes rapidly transform into non-physiological cell types in standard 2D culture systems. More advanced 3D culture systems prevent this problem but introduce difficulties in compatibility with analytical techniques. The proposed technology may act as an egg crate for individual cells, nesting each one in an environment that allows it to maintain its physiological nature without restricting their ability to be studied. The technology may maintain the physiological cell shape of chondrocytes for at least 28 days, four times as long as competing micropatterned technologies. The technology has potential applications in drug development, gene therapy, stem cell medicine, tissue engineering, the elucidation of molecular pathogeneses, and other biomedical applications.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/13/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/14/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2037874</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Scott</FirstName>
<LastName>Wood</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Scott Wood</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[scott.wood@sdsmt.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000770123</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/13/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>South Dakota School of Mines and Technology</Name>
<CityName>RAPID CITY</CityName>
<ZipCode>577013901</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6053941218</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>501 E SAINT JOSEPH ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>South Dakota</StateName>
<StateCode>SD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>SD00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>CJAJYT2KW771</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SOUTH DAKOTA SCHOOL OF MINES &amp; TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>URFPBWBM1C58</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[South Dakota School of Mines and Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>Rapid City</CityName>
<StateCode>SD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>577013995</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[501 East Saint Joseph Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>South Dakota</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>SD00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><h1>Project Outcomes Report</h1> <p>Award Title: I-Corps: Cell Culture Platform Using Engineered Micropatterns to Control Differentiation</p> <p>Recipient Organization: South Dakota School of Mines and Technology</p> <p>PI: Scott Wood</p> <p>Federal Award ID: 2037874</p> <p>Project/Grant Period: 08/01/2020 ? 01/31/2023</p> <p>In 2020, our team, CellField Technologies, received an award by the National Science Foundation to participate in its I-CORPS Teams program. Over the project period, we interviewed 135 potential customers, pharmaceutical industry experts, and regulatory experts across six countries on three continents, including 28 US states. In our interviews, we explored the potential for commercialization of the CellWell in vitro articular cartilage model and all its features by testing various product-market fit hypotheses. Although our team thought at the beginning that pharmaceutical scientists would be attracted to an in vitro platform for maintaining chondrocyte phenotype in preclinical disease-modifying osteoarthritis drug (DMOAD) screens, our hypothesis was not aligned with their pains. However, we learned several valuable lessons along the way that have helped us to pivot to what we believe is a strong product-market fit.</p> <p>The first lesson we learned was that pharmaceutical companies do very little preclinical research anymore, and that most of that work is now done by contract research organizations (CROs). This was validated by interviewee comments such as the one we heard from a chief medical officer (CMO) of a California-based genomics company who said that ?CROs are the pre-clinical researchers of the pharma industry? and the one we heard from a chief scientific officer (CSO) of a biopharmaceutical company in California who said that ?all of [their] pre-clinical research work is contracted out.?</p> <p>The second lesson we learned was that the sale of the CellWell to CROs as a research tool would not likely be a viable path to market for us. This was validated by interviewee comments such as a representative one we heard from a CSO of a CRO in Massachusetts that ?we do everything in-house ? if we have to buy or sub-contract something, we simply won?t do it.?</p> <p>The final key lesson we learned was that large pharmaceutical companies have all but given up on developing DMOADs. This lesson was validated by senior scientists who had previously run clinical trials on DMOADs that did not receive regulatory approval for ?big pharma? companies. We heard comments such as ?osteoarthritis (OA) is a huge market, but big pharma companies are not interested in doing Phase-3 clinical trials for disease modification for fear of money and time and how difficult OA is to treat,? and ?the biggest problem for OA is that the development process is so long, costly, and risky that pharmaceutical companies have essentially given up trying to treat the disease itself.? This was balanced, however, by findings that small- and medium-sized pharmaceutical companies are still trying to develop DMOADs and that CROs are doing preclinical research on DMOADs for those companies. While the pharmaceutical scientists we spoke to who were currently or previously focused on DMOAD development recognized the need for improved phenotype maintenance of chondrocytes in preclinical research studies, we learned that this was not a focus for them. Instead, we learned that their primary pain point is that they do not have access to any systems that would enable them to test the efficacy of their drugs in an in vitro system that mimics the highly ordered and complex tissue structure of human joints.</p> <p>Taken together, the lessons we learned from our I-Corps customer discovery interviews led us to realize that successful commercialization of the CellWell would likely require a substantial pivot for CellField Technologies. Rather than being a ?widget? manufacturer as initially envisioned, there might be an actual market for us if we instead (1) further develop our technology to incorporate it into a novel microphysiological system based on the concept of the joint as an organ, and (2) shift toward a business model with a broader impact focused on leveraging our technology as a platform to offer CRO drug screening services to de-risk the development of drugs to treat a broad array of joint diseases.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/08/2023<br>      Modified by: Scott&nbsp;Wood</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[Project Outcomes Report  Award Title: I-Corps: Cell Culture Platform Using Engineered Micropatterns to Control Differentiation  Recipient Organization: South Dakota School of Mines and Technology  PI: Scott Wood  Federal Award ID: 2037874  Project/Grant Period: 08/01/2020 ? 01/31/2023  In 2020, our team, CellField Technologies, received an award by the National Science Foundation to participate in its I-CORPS Teams program. Over the project period, we interviewed 135 potential customers, pharmaceutical industry experts, and regulatory experts across six countries on three continents, including 28 US states. In our interviews, we explored the potential for commercialization of the CellWell in vitro articular cartilage model and all its features by testing various product-market fit hypotheses. Although our team thought at the beginning that pharmaceutical scientists would be attracted to an in vitro platform for maintaining chondrocyte phenotype in preclinical disease-modifying osteoarthritis drug (DMOAD) screens, our hypothesis was not aligned with their pains. However, we learned several valuable lessons along the way that have helped us to pivot to what we believe is a strong product-market fit.  The first lesson we learned was that pharmaceutical companies do very little preclinical research anymore, and that most of that work is now done by contract research organizations (CROs). This was validated by interviewee comments such as the one we heard from a chief medical officer (CMO) of a California-based genomics company who said that ?CROs are the pre-clinical researchers of the pharma industry? and the one we heard from a chief scientific officer (CSO) of a biopharmaceutical company in California who said that ?all of [their] pre-clinical research work is contracted out.?  The second lesson we learned was that the sale of the CellWell to CROs as a research tool would not likely be a viable path to market for us. This was validated by interviewee comments such as a representative one we heard from a CSO of a CRO in Massachusetts that ?we do everything in-house ? if we have to buy or sub-contract something, we simply won?t do it.?  The final key lesson we learned was that large pharmaceutical companies have all but given up on developing DMOADs. This lesson was validated by senior scientists who had previously run clinical trials on DMOADs that did not receive regulatory approval for ?big pharma? companies. We heard comments such as ?osteoarthritis (OA) is a huge market, but big pharma companies are not interested in doing Phase-3 clinical trials for disease modification for fear of money and time and how difficult OA is to treat,? and ?the biggest problem for OA is that the development process is so long, costly, and risky that pharmaceutical companies have essentially given up trying to treat the disease itself.? This was balanced, however, by findings that small- and medium-sized pharmaceutical companies are still trying to develop DMOADs and that CROs are doing preclinical research on DMOADs for those companies. While the pharmaceutical scientists we spoke to who were currently or previously focused on DMOAD development recognized the need for improved phenotype maintenance of chondrocytes in preclinical research studies, we learned that this was not a focus for them. Instead, we learned that their primary pain point is that they do not have access to any systems that would enable them to test the efficacy of their drugs in an in vitro system that mimics the highly ordered and complex tissue structure of human joints.  Taken together, the lessons we learned from our I-Corps customer discovery interviews led us to realize that successful commercialization of the CellWell would likely require a substantial pivot for CellField Technologies. Rather than being a ?widget? manufacturer as initially envisioned, there might be an actual market for us if we instead (1) further develop our technology to incorporate it into a novel microphysiological system based on the concept of the joint as an organ, and (2) shift toward a business model with a broader impact focused on leveraging our technology as a platform to offer CRO drug screening services to de-risk the development of drugs to treat a broad array of joint diseases.       Last Modified: 03/08/2023       Submitted by: Scott Wood]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
