<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Interdisciplinary Science Session: Can Machine Learning and Data-driven Science Lead to Breakthroughs in Earth System Modeling and Analysis?; Aspen, Colorado; June 7-11, 2021]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>18000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>18000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06020100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AGS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Eric DeWeaver</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>edeweave@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928527</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Recent years have seen an explosion in the use of machine learning (ML) and other data science techniques in applications from self-driving cars to targeted advertising to medical diagnosis.  Meanwhile climate and earth system science have become increasingly data intensive, as the volume of data from observing systems and computer models has increased almost exponentially.  There is thus considerable interest in finding ways to apply the tools of data science to the problems of climate and earth system science.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This workshop brings together a group of researchers from the fields of climate, earth system science, statistics, data science, and related disciplines to seek novel and productive ways to apply data science tools to climate and earth system science. One application to be considered is the use of ML as a means of representing small-scale processes in climate and earth system models.  Another is the use of ML and similar techniques for the analysis of large volumes of data.  Particular challenges to be considered include the incorporation of physical constraints into ML algorithms and the extent to which results of ML-based analysis can be interpreted in physically meaningful ways.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The workshop has broader impacts through its attempt to introduce new and powerful tools into climate and earth system science.  Data science tools have the potential to enhance the societal value of research results, for example by allowing scientists to provide better guidance to planners and stakeholders facing threats posed by extreme weather, climate change, and other earth system phenomena.  Public outreach will be performed through a keynote lecture and web-accessible videos of workshop presentations, and a perspective paper will be published as a result of the meeting.  The workshop is planned for the week of 7 June 2021.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/09/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/09/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2038111</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Arnott</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>James C Arnott</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jamesa@agci.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000560489</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/09/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Emily</FirstName>
<LastName>Jack-Scott</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Emily Jack-Scott</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ejs@agci.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000755009</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/09/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Aspen Global Change Institute</Name>
<CityName>BASALT</CityName>
<ZipCode>816218379</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9703009080</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>104 MIDLAND AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[UNIT 205]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>FN9MQFY7LQU7</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>THE ASPEN GLOBAL CHANGE INSTITUTE, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Aspen Global Change Institute]]></Name>
<CityName>Basalt</CityName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>816218379</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[104 Midland Ave UNIT 205, Basalt]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5740</Code>
<Text>Climate &amp; Large-Scale Dynamics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~18000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Aspen Global Change Institute (AGCI) successfully hosted an interdisciplinary science workshop entitled ?<strong>Exploring the Frontiers in Earth System Modeling with Machine Learning and Big Data,?&nbsp;</strong>from June 5-10, 2022 in Aspen, CO. AGCI collaborated with co-chairs William Collins (Berkeley Lab &amp; UC Berkeley, USA), Veronika Eyring (DLR, Germany), with input from a co-organizing team that included Pierre Gentine (Columbia), Dorit Hammerling (Colorado School of Mines, USA), Gerald Meehl (NCAR, USA), Markus Reichstein (MPI, Germany), and Jakob Runge (DLR, Germany), to develop the workshop agenda and roster. The group of 32 workshop participants included geoscientists, climate modelers, machine learners, statisticians, computer scientists, and cyberinfrastructure experts.</p> <p>The top workshop objectives were to:</p> <p>-&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; To further understand the value proposition of machine learning and the capability of this method to advance Earth systems science research.</p> <p>-&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; To further understand how machine learning can aid with actionable climate information for societal applications.&nbsp;</p> <p>-&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; To build community, and foster future productive collaborations, between climate modelers and machine learners, among other related disciplines.</p> <p>AGCI staff worked intensively with workshop co-chairs over the course of over a year on participant recruitment, agenda development, and facilitation of planning efforts. Due to the Covid-19 pandemic, the workshop was postponed from its original dates in June 2021, to June 2022. The workshop was held in-person with Covid-19 safety protocols in place. AGCI staff provided logistical and financial support for participants including support for their travel expenses, lodging and meals.</p> <p>As part of the workshop, AGCI also organized a public lecture, given by Dr. Hannah Christensen (of the University of Oxford) entitled, ?Accelerating Actionable Climate Information Through Machine Learning.? The public lecture was streamed live to global audiences through a Zoom webinar, and open to the public in Aspen, CO, followed by an interactive question and answer session and reception.</p> <p>The workshop identified, and galvanized interest in pursuing opportunities to advance Earth system modeling through the incorporation of machine learning methods. Examples of key opportunities include</p> <p>-&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; improving Earth system models with machine learning by better representing smaller scale physical processes, informed by high-resolution simulations or observations to build hybrid models (that combine traditional and machine learning methods),</p> <p>-&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; detection, attribution, and forecasting of high impact extreme events, and</p> <p>-&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; machine learning-based climate model evaluation and analysis.</p> <p>Participants have summarized detailed workshop findings, to be published in a peer-reviewed scientific journal (<em>Nature Climate Change</em>). In addition, a proposal has been submitted to the Gordon Research Conference (GRC) Evaluation Committee by the co-chairs of the AGCI workshop in the hopes of creating a recurring and sustained interdisciplinary series of workshops where leaders can continue working together in this rapidly evolving field. Beyond these outputs, the ideas and new collaborations generated at the workshop will carry on in the individual and organizational research agendas of those represented at a meeting.&nbsp;</p> <p>Video recordings of workshop proceedings were published on the AGCI website and shared through social media, extending the impact of workshop to public audiences. The extended workshop topic description, participant profiles, workshop agenda, public lecture, session video recordings, presentation PDFs, and other educational materials are available on the workshop webpage:&nbsp;<a href="https://www.agci.org/event/22s3">https://www.agci.org/event/22s3</a>.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/21/2022<br>      Modified by: Emily&nbsp;Jack-Scott</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2038111/2038111_10683910_1671651349058_22s3_GrouptPhoto--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2038111/2038111_10683910_1671651349058_22s3_GrouptPhoto--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Workshop Group Photo"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2038111/2038111_10683910_1671651349058_22s3_GrouptPhoto--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Workshop Group Photo"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Group photo of workshop participants</div> <div class="imageCredit">Aspen Global Change Institute</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Emily&nbsp;Jack-Scott</div> <div class="imageTitle">Workshop Group Photo</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2038111/2038111_10683910_1671651190752_4B1A4149--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2038111/2038111_10683910_1671651190752_4B1A4149--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Breakout Group moderator and rapporteur"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2038111/2038111_10683910_1671651190752_4B1A4149--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Breakout Group moderator and rapporteur"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Breakout Group moderator and rapporteur synthesize their group's discussion before sharing with the rest of the group</div> <div class="imageCredit">Aspen Global Change Institute</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (restricted use - cannot be shared)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Emily&nbsp;Jack-Scott</div> <div class="imageTitle">Breakout Group moderator and rapporteur</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2038111/2038111_10683910_1671650888017_PXL_20220607_162125974--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2038111/2038111_10683910_1671650888017_PXL_20220607_162125974--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Panel discussion"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2038111/2038111_10683910_1671650888017_PXL_20220607_162125974--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Panel discussion"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Workshop Participants engaged in a group discussion</div> <div class="imageCredit">Aspen Global Change Institute</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (restricted use - cannot be shared)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Emily&nbsp;Jack-Scott</div> <div class="imageTitle">Panel discussion</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Aspen Global Change Institute (AGCI) successfully hosted an interdisciplinary science workshop entitled ?Exploring the Frontiers in Earth System Modeling with Machine Learning and Big Data,? from June 5-10, 2022 in Aspen, CO. AGCI collaborated with co-chairs William Collins (Berkeley Lab &amp; UC Berkeley, USA), Veronika Eyring (DLR, Germany), with input from a co-organizing team that included Pierre Gentine (Columbia), Dorit Hammerling (Colorado School of Mines, USA), Gerald Meehl (NCAR, USA), Markus Reichstein (MPI, Germany), and Jakob Runge (DLR, Germany), to develop the workshop agenda and roster. The group of 32 workshop participants included geoscientists, climate modelers, machine learners, statisticians, computer scientists, and cyberinfrastructure experts.  The top workshop objectives were to:  -       To further understand the value proposition of machine learning and the capability of this method to advance Earth systems science research.  -       To further understand how machine learning can aid with actionable climate information for societal applications.   -       To build community, and foster future productive collaborations, between climate modelers and machine learners, among other related disciplines.  AGCI staff worked intensively with workshop co-chairs over the course of over a year on participant recruitment, agenda development, and facilitation of planning efforts. Due to the Covid-19 pandemic, the workshop was postponed from its original dates in June 2021, to June 2022. The workshop was held in-person with Covid-19 safety protocols in place. AGCI staff provided logistical and financial support for participants including support for their travel expenses, lodging and meals.  As part of the workshop, AGCI also organized a public lecture, given by Dr. Hannah Christensen (of the University of Oxford) entitled, ?Accelerating Actionable Climate Information Through Machine Learning.? The public lecture was streamed live to global audiences through a Zoom webinar, and open to the public in Aspen, CO, followed by an interactive question and answer session and reception.  The workshop identified, and galvanized interest in pursuing opportunities to advance Earth system modeling through the incorporation of machine learning methods. Examples of key opportunities include  -       improving Earth system models with machine learning by better representing smaller scale physical processes, informed by high-resolution simulations or observations to build hybrid models (that combine traditional and machine learning methods),  -       detection, attribution, and forecasting of high impact extreme events, and  -       machine learning-based climate model evaluation and analysis.  Participants have summarized detailed workshop findings, to be published in a peer-reviewed scientific journal (Nature Climate Change). In addition, a proposal has been submitted to the Gordon Research Conference (GRC) Evaluation Committee by the co-chairs of the AGCI workshop in the hopes of creating a recurring and sustained interdisciplinary series of workshops where leaders can continue working together in this rapidly evolving field. Beyond these outputs, the ideas and new collaborations generated at the workshop will carry on in the individual and organizational research agendas of those represented at a meeting.   Video recordings of workshop proceedings were published on the AGCI website and shared through social media, extending the impact of workshop to public audiences. The extended workshop topic description, participant profiles, workshop agenda, public lecture, session video recordings, presentation PDFs, and other educational materials are available on the workshop webpage: https://www.agci.org/event/22s3.          Last Modified: 12/21/2022       Submitted by: Emily Jack-Scott]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
