<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[STTR Phase I:  Allogeneic Stem Cell Delivery for Efficacy-Enhanced Equine Biotherapeutics]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>256000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>256000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Erik Pierstorff</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>epiersto@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922165</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact /commercial potential of this Small Business Technology Transfer (STTR) Phase I project involves the development of technology to extend the therapeutic window of cell-based tissue regeneration therapies. This technology will significantly enhance the scientific understanding of cellular therapies, and enable the healing of injuries more rapidly and less invasively than current techniques. A significant need for this technology exists in the competition horse market. 98% of competitive horses suffer from soft tissue injuries and more than 80% develop suspensory ligament defects. Injuries to suspensory ligaments can take years to heal and are the leading cause of missed performances owners. The proposed technology provides veterinarians a means of healing suspensory ligament injuries significantly faster, resulting in fewer missed performances, reduced financial losses, and most importantly, improved quality of life for the animal. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Technology Transfer (STTR) Phase I project will address the problem of slow healing suspensory ligament injuries for racehorses. 98% of vets use stem cell injections to aid in recovery of these injuries, but this strategy has limited efficacy due to poor viability of injected cells and short cell retention times at the site of injury. This problem is addressed by developing technology to preserve and localize mesenchymal stem cells (MSCs) at an injury site through delivery in inert, injectable hydrogel microparticles. The research objectives of this proposal are twofold; 1. Quantitively assessing metrics of cell viability and stromal cell-like behavior of hydrogel microencapsulated cells and compare them to baseline unencapsulated cell metrics, and 2. Provide explicit evidence that the encapsulation process localizes cells and preserves their viability, is nontoxic and non-immunogenic, and demonstrates markers of superior tissue regeneration in a small animal model similar to that of its intended commercial use. This study is expected to enable the quantitative elucidation of cell viability and biomolecular response to encapsulation in hydrogel microenvironments and establish preliminary safety and efficacy results of hydrogel-encapsulated MSCs.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/23/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/25/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041, 47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2038460</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Oakey</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John Oakey</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[joakey@uwyo.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000055688</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/23/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Benjamin</FirstName>
<LastName>Noren</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Benjamin E Noren</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ben@celldrop.co]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000793213</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/23/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>CellDrop Inc</Name>
<CityName>LARAMIE</CityName>
<ZipCode>820723037</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3072207465</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1938 HARNEY ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wyoming</StateName>
<StateCode>WY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WY00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NJXGWEBDRJH5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CELLDROP INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Wyoming]]></Name>
<CityName>Laramie</CityName>
<StateCode>WY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>820712000</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1000 E University Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wyoming</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WY00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1505</Code>
<Text>STTR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1982</Code>
<Text>BIOLOGICAL CHEMISTRY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~256000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>CellDrop Biosciences has developed a biotherapeutic for rapid and permanent healing of tendons and ligaments via immobilizing Mesenchymal Stem Cells (MSCs) in inert, injectable microparticles. Initial commercialization will be for tendon and ligament injuries in performance horses. Customer discovery indicates an acute need for veterinarians treating these frequently incurred injuries, as there is currently no method to achieve satisfactory recovery. This costs horse owners hundreds of thousands of dollars, a pain point that is passed to veterinarians who make treatment decisions. Scale-up efforts in Phase I showed our patented encapsulation method has no negative effect on cell behavior or viability. Histology, immunology, and gene expression analysis in a rodent model showed that our system can localize cells at an injury site, provide superior tissue regeneration through mitigation of deleterious immune responses leading to scar tissue formation, and is safe in animals, de-risking this technology. These results demonstrates readiness for a larger experimental trial in the species of therapeutic interest?horses. CellDrop has submitted a Phase II Proposal to continue commercialization of this technology. &nbsp;Phase II will build on small animal data by using similar methods of analysis paired with well recognized clinical outcomes to assess both short term (3 mo) and long term (1 yr) therapeutic benefits in an equine model.</span></p> <p><span>The superficial digital flexor tendon (SDFT) and suspensory ligament (SL) are structurally similar tissues that work in tandem to support equine fetlock joints and serve to store elastic energy essential to movement. Repeated high loads placed on these tissues result in frequent injury, with incidence as high as 80% in performance horses; slow healing and a high rate of reinjury are primary pain points for veterinarians that are not addressed by existing solutions. CellDrop Bio aims to offer a critically needed solution with the proposed technology, which will be further developed in Phase II via the following objectives: 1) Examination of early healing metrics in an equine model of SDFT injury over a 3-month period to assess healing speed, and 2) Examination of long-term healing metrics in equine model of SDFT injury in a year-long animal study to observe healing durability. CellDrop's long-term goal is to apply this biotherapeutic to the human healthcare system; however, expanding to human healthcare is risky, considering the high cost and low success rate of the regulatory approval process for cell-based therapies. Stepwise implementation of CellDrop's product in the veterinary market via this Phase II project mitigates risk by providing crucial evidence of efficacy and the necessary revenue for future translation to humans.</span></p> <p><span>The next-generation biotherapeutics being developed by CellDrop Biosciences will positively impact society by enabling both humans and animals to maintain a higher level of health and vitality over the course of their lives. CellDrop's encapsulated cell delivery product and patented hydrogel technology increase the economic growth and competitiveness of the United States in the biotherapeutic sector, in which the United States currently lags. CellDrop's project will also serve to advance the health and welfare of the American public; implementation of CellDrop's product in the beachhead market of performance horses is the first step towards bringing the technology to the humans. Customer discovery indicates a strong need for CellDrops technology in horse racing and other equestrian sports, and a stepwise approach to broad commercialization will be implemented by expanding to all disciplines of performance equestrianism for tendon and ligament regeneration, then for cartilage degradation and desmitis. CellDrop Bio ultimately envisions broad use in companion animals to correct issues such as hip dysplasia in dogs, arthritis in cats, and a final extension to human healthcare where early evidence has shown efficacy for a number of currently incurable tissue diseases such as osteoarthritis, projected to affect 72 million Americans by 2030.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/14/2022<br>      Modified by: Benjamin&nbsp;E&nbsp;Noren</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ CellDrop Biosciences has developed a biotherapeutic for rapid and permanent healing of tendons and ligaments via immobilizing Mesenchymal Stem Cells (MSCs) in inert, injectable microparticles. Initial commercialization will be for tendon and ligament injuries in performance horses. Customer discovery indicates an acute need for veterinarians treating these frequently incurred injuries, as there is currently no method to achieve satisfactory recovery. This costs horse owners hundreds of thousands of dollars, a pain point that is passed to veterinarians who make treatment decisions. Scale-up efforts in Phase I showed our patented encapsulation method has no negative effect on cell behavior or viability. Histology, immunology, and gene expression analysis in a rodent model showed that our system can localize cells at an injury site, provide superior tissue regeneration through mitigation of deleterious immune responses leading to scar tissue formation, and is safe in animals, de-risking this technology. These results demonstrates readiness for a larger experimental trial in the species of therapeutic interest?horses. CellDrop has submitted a Phase II Proposal to continue commercialization of this technology.  Phase II will build on small animal data by using similar methods of analysis paired with well recognized clinical outcomes to assess both short term (3 mo) and long term (1 yr) therapeutic benefits in an equine model.  The superficial digital flexor tendon (SDFT) and suspensory ligament (SL) are structurally similar tissues that work in tandem to support equine fetlock joints and serve to store elastic energy essential to movement. Repeated high loads placed on these tissues result in frequent injury, with incidence as high as 80% in performance horses; slow healing and a high rate of reinjury are primary pain points for veterinarians that are not addressed by existing solutions. CellDrop Bio aims to offer a critically needed solution with the proposed technology, which will be further developed in Phase II via the following objectives: 1) Examination of early healing metrics in an equine model of SDFT injury over a 3-month period to assess healing speed, and 2) Examination of long-term healing metrics in equine model of SDFT injury in a year-long animal study to observe healing durability. CellDrop's long-term goal is to apply this biotherapeutic to the human healthcare system; however, expanding to human healthcare is risky, considering the high cost and low success rate of the regulatory approval process for cell-based therapies. Stepwise implementation of CellDrop's product in the veterinary market via this Phase II project mitigates risk by providing crucial evidence of efficacy and the necessary revenue for future translation to humans.  The next-generation biotherapeutics being developed by CellDrop Biosciences will positively impact society by enabling both humans and animals to maintain a higher level of health and vitality over the course of their lives. CellDrop's encapsulated cell delivery product and patented hydrogel technology increase the economic growth and competitiveness of the United States in the biotherapeutic sector, in which the United States currently lags. CellDrop's project will also serve to advance the health and welfare of the American public; implementation of CellDrop's product in the beachhead market of performance horses is the first step towards bringing the technology to the humans. Customer discovery indicates a strong need for CellDrops technology in horse racing and other equestrian sports, and a stepwise approach to broad commercialization will be implemented by expanding to all disciplines of performance equestrianism for tendon and ligament regeneration, then for cartilage degradation and desmitis. CellDrop Bio ultimately envisions broad use in companion animals to correct issues such as hip dysplasia in dogs, arthritis in cats, and a final extension to human healthcare where early evidence has shown efficacy for a number of currently incurable tissue diseases such as osteoarthritis, projected to affect 72 million Americans by 2030.          Last Modified: 11/14/2022       Submitted by: Benjamin E Noren]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
