<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research: LIA: Genomic Mechanisms Controlling the Slow Development of the Antarctic Urchin Sterechinus Neumayeri]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2022</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2025</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>356975.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>356975</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06090300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OPP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Polar Programs (OPP)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>William Ambrose</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>wambrose@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928048</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Antarctic marine invertebrates exhibit extraordinarily slow rates of development. This phenomenon has arisen repeatedly in independent Antarctic lineages, including sea urchins, sea stars, brachiopods, and ribbon worms. Despite these observations, little is known about the molecular mechanisms responsible for slow developmental rates in Antarctic marine invertebrates.  This proposal is developing the Antarctic sea urchin, Sterechinus neumayeri, as a model invertebrate organism to evaluate cold water organismal adaptation and development. Urchins collected from McMurdo Sound are being studied in carefully controlled laboratory experiments. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This work is specifically identifying the gene regulatory network components responsible for regulating developmental timing in S. neumayeri and, more generally, which gene regulatory network elements evolved during adaption to the extreme environment of the Southern Ocean. The lab-based work is focusing in two specific areas: 1) Identify unique gene regulatory network components of S. neumayeri that evolved during its developmental adaptation to the Southern Ocean, and 2) Analyze spatial expression and functions of key genes in the early S. neumayeri gene regulatory networks controlling specification and patterning of territories along the early anterior-posterior axis. A comparative analysis of better studied urchins from warmer regions will be used to inform this work. This effort is relevant to several fields of biology ranging from polar biology, developmental biology, evolution, and genomics while explicitly tying genotype to phenotype. Broader impacts: The proposal included three early career investigators who are new to Antarctic research programs working alongside a well-established Antarctic investigator. The team has developed an ambitious program for science and technology training in computer coding and biology targeted for underrepresented students. They also have developed web-based bioinformatics training blog, “2-bitbio”, which aims to decrease the ‘barrier to entry’ into the field of bioinformatics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/12/2022</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/12/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.078</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2038149</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jacob</FirstName>
<LastName>Warner</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jacob Warner</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[warnerj@uncw.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000828922</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/12/2022</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of North Carolina at Wilmington</Name>
<CityName>WILMINGTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>284033201</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9109623167</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>601 S COLLEGE RD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>L1GPHS96MUE1</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF NORTH CAROLINA AT WILMINGTON</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of North Carolina at Wilmington]]></Name>
<CityName>Wilmington</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>284035973</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[601 South College Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5111</Code>
<Text>ANT Organisms &amp; Ecosystems</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>116Z</Code>
<Text>LIA-Life in Antarctica</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5294</Code>
<Text>USGCRP</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>0100CYXXDB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2022~356975</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
