<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Strategic Outcome Progressions Conference: Exploring a Framework for Measuring Informal Education Outcomes and Institutional Impact]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>74999.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>74999</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DRL</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Julie Johnson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jjohnson@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928624</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Various measures exist to assess learning outcomes from informal science, technology, engineering, or math (STEM) education programming, especially for youth audiences. Although there has been growing interest in the field among practitioners, researchers and evaluators for the development and implementation of shared, common STEM measures and frameworks, informal STEM learning (ISL) institutions (e.g., museums, zoos, aquaria, botanic gardens, and the like) face a unique challenge when they design and evaluate educational programs. By nature of the broad-ranging topic areas these institutions emphasize, programming seeks to reach audiences that vary in age, ability, cultural background, interest, and more. Participation also varies--for example, participants choose which in a series of exhibits they attend and how much time they spend at each. Given this planned-for variance, how do educators target appropriate learning outcomes? To what extent do outcomes map to activity complexity? How does programming success link to institutional goals? One solution may be a framework of outcome progressions. “Progressions” are within outcome categories (e.g., interest, attitude, knowledge, skills, behavior, science capital, etc.), the ordinal series of effects that can be mapped to programming that ranges from short duration with simple content (e.g. a hallway cart demonstration can trigger situational interest) to extended duration with complex content (e.g. a youth internship can generate well-developed personal interest). STEM educators, evaluators and researchers working in or with ISL institutions will come together to consider the utility and feasibility of an outcome progressions framework. With this framework STEM learning institution educators may be better equipped to understand the impact of their programming and how to design for it. This work will be undertaken by the COSI Center for Research and Evaluation in conjunction with the Office of Education, Outreach, and Visitor Services of the National Museum of Natural History and the PEAR Institute.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The primary aim of this multi-day virtual convening is to inform future development of the framework for outcome progressions. These progressions will reflect and accommodate outcomes targeted by existing and shared evaluation measures. The framework will provide informal educators and evaluators with (1) a way of aligning outcome expectations with programming depth and dosage; (2) outcome choices achievable with various depths of programming; (3) a strategic tool for planning institution-wide targeted outcomes across a full portfolio of institution educational programming; and (4) a tool for documenting an education department’s varied outcomes across the full range of possible outcomes. To create rich and informed critical discussion, the conference will involve research consultant experts representing each outcome category; practitioners representing diverse programming; and evaluation theorists familiar with the broad needs of informal learning institutions. A conference subcommittee with expertise in culturally responsive and equitable program development and evaluation will ensure the agenda contains flexibility to generate emergent equitable and inclusive conversations. Conference participants will review and contribute to the soundness and utility of these categorizations as well as the progressions within them. These insights and inputs will inform future development of the framework as a valid and reliable tool. Deliverables include a paper summarizing the findings from the convenings and a related webinar that describes the framework and recommendations for its use. These will be shared broadly via the informalscience.org website and other professional venues. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This conference is funded by the Advancing Informal STEM Learning (AISL) program, which seeks to advance new approaches to, and evidence-based understanding of, the design and development of STEM learning in informal environments. This includes providing multiple pathways for broadening access to and engagement in STEM learning experiences, advancing innovative research on and assessment of STEM learning in informal environments, and developing understandings of deeper learning by participants.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/12/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/12/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2039209</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Colleen</FirstName>
<LastName>Popson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Colleen P Popson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[popsonc@si.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000534963</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/12/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Deborah</FirstName>
<LastName>Wasserman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Deborah L Wasserman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[dwasserman@cosi.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000730349</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/12/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Franklin County Historical Society</Name>
<CityName>COLUMBUS</CityName>
<ZipCode>432152738</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6146293120</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>333 W BROAD ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>15</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OH15</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>HFFSS5QV6M44</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>FRANKLIN COUNTY HISTORICAL SOCIETY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>HFFSS5QV6M44</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Franklin County Historical Society]]></Name>
<CityName>Columbus</CityName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>432152738</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[333 West Broad Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>15</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OH15</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7259</Code>
<Text>AISL</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0420</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~74999</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Informal Science, Technology, Engineering, or Math (S.T.E.M.) learning institutions face a unique challenge when they design and evaluate educational programs. By definition of &ldquo;informal,&rdquo; and by nature of their broad-ranging topic areas, programming seeks to reach audiences that vary broadly in age, ability, cultural background, interest, and more. Participation also varies--for example, participants choose which in a series of exhibits they&rsquo;d like to attend and how much time they spend at each. Given this intended variance, how do educators target appropriate learning outcomes?&nbsp;</p> <p>To help answer this question, Informal S.T.E.M. educators, evaluators and researchers convened in this conference to consider the utility and feasibility of a strategic outcomes framework. The framework gives informal education practitioners a way to identify types of learning outcomes they realistically can expect based on the amount of contact time and type of learning experience they offer.&nbsp; The framework divides each of eight learning categories (interest, attitude, knowledge, STEM skills, 21<sup>st</sup> century skills, behavior, building S.T.E.M. capital, and career activation) into outcome types that reflect the wide variation in informal learning experiences. Conference planning included attention to the framework as a tool that would engender culturally responsive, equitable, and inclusive programming. A committee specifically organized for that purpose integrally participated in both planning and evaluation.</p> <p>During the conference, participants agreed that the framework is an innovative and useful tool that informal education practitioners can use to:</p> <ul> <li>Parse learning experiences into outcome types that realistically reflect contact time and experience</li> <li>Articulate qualitative dimensions within existing learning categories</li> <li>Focus program planning</li> <li>Create an overview of institutional educational intentions</li> <li>Promote dialog about program design</li> <li>Build evaluation capacity for articulating and answering evaluation questions </li> <li>Build practitioner capacity for designing programs</li> <li>Aid in strategic planning</li> <li>Communicate impact with stakeholders</li> </ul> <p>Participants also provided recommendations that have improved the framework&rsquo;s utility. The most significant change occurred with recognizing the need to situate the entire framework and its use within a planning process that includes community voice. Use of this framework is now situated within a &ldquo;Voices and Choices&rdquo; planning process that includes community value holders who speak to the framework&rsquo;s use at each program phase including planning, marketing, and evaluation.&nbsp; Other changes involved further definition of the outcome categories, the outcome types within them, and&mdash;to create culturally responsive, equitable and inclusive programming&mdash;how practitioners can work with value holders to combine outcome types and specify outcomes within them.</p> <p class="BodyText1"><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Intellectual Merit</span></p> <p>The conference convened a diverse group of 24 research, evaluation, and education experts to work with the strategic outcomes framework over a ten-day period, exploring its potential and challenging its limits. Researchers were selected for their knowledge and experience with primary research in one of the framework&rsquo;s eight outcome categories. Evaluators and practitioners were selected for either their broad experience with informal education or experience with culturally responsive and equitable programming, or both.&nbsp;</p> <p class="BodyText1"><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Broader Impacts</span></p> <p>Participants recognized the important contribution of the outcomes framework to advancing informal STEM institution educational programming. Their feedback has led to the creation of a Voices and Choices planning process that now operates in tandem with the framework at every stage of program design and evaluation. As such this framework also may apply to informal learning in general, beyond STEM (e.g., arts, humanities) and to informal learning in the workplace, e.g., for corporate training.</p> <p>This &nbsp;framework, as it has evolved in response to the conference, contributes to a larger ISEE (Informal Science Education Evaluation) System which, , based on the outcome types and categories within this framework, the Voices and Choices planning process to select them, provides a picture of an institution&rsquo;s overall educational impact and the quality of programming that produces it Whether a part of the ISEE system or independently, the framework is already in use by practitioners from the conference and beyond.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/28/2022<br>      Modified by: Deborah&nbsp;Wasserman</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2039209/2039209_10696128_1634568699043_simplevisual--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2039209/2039209_10696128_1634568699043_simplevisual--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Quickview of framework types"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2039209/2039209_10696128_1634568699043_simplevisual--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Quickview of framework types"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The revised Strategic Outcome Framework consists of 8 categories each consisting of outcome types arranged according to complexity of the programming that leads to them.</div> <div class="imageCredit">COSI CRE</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Deborah&nbsp;Wasserman</div> <div class="imageTitle">Quickview of framework types</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Informal Science, Technology, Engineering, or Math (S.T.E.M.) learning institutions face a unique challenge when they design and evaluate educational programs. By definition of "informal," and by nature of their broad-ranging topic areas, programming seeks to reach audiences that vary broadly in age, ability, cultural background, interest, and more. Participation also varies--for example, participants choose which in a series of exhibits they’d like to attend and how much time they spend at each. Given this intended variance, how do educators target appropriate learning outcomes?   To help answer this question, Informal S.T.E.M. educators, evaluators and researchers convened in this conference to consider the utility and feasibility of a strategic outcomes framework. The framework gives informal education practitioners a way to identify types of learning outcomes they realistically can expect based on the amount of contact time and type of learning experience they offer.  The framework divides each of eight learning categories (interest, attitude, knowledge, STEM skills, 21st century skills, behavior, building S.T.E.M. capital, and career activation) into outcome types that reflect the wide variation in informal learning experiences. Conference planning included attention to the framework as a tool that would engender culturally responsive, equitable, and inclusive programming. A committee specifically organized for that purpose integrally participated in both planning and evaluation.  During the conference, participants agreed that the framework is an innovative and useful tool that informal education practitioners can use to:  Parse learning experiences into outcome types that realistically reflect contact time and experience Articulate qualitative dimensions within existing learning categories Focus program planning Create an overview of institutional educational intentions Promote dialog about program design Build evaluation capacity for articulating and answering evaluation questions  Build practitioner capacity for designing programs Aid in strategic planning Communicate impact with stakeholders   Participants also provided recommendations that have improved the framework’s utility. The most significant change occurred with recognizing the need to situate the entire framework and its use within a planning process that includes community voice. Use of this framework is now situated within a "Voices and Choices" planning process that includes community value holders who speak to the framework’s use at each program phase including planning, marketing, and evaluation.  Other changes involved further definition of the outcome categories, the outcome types within them, and&mdash;to create culturally responsive, equitable and inclusive programming&mdash;how practitioners can work with value holders to combine outcome types and specify outcomes within them. Intellectual Merit  The conference convened a diverse group of 24 research, evaluation, and education experts to work with the strategic outcomes framework over a ten-day period, exploring its potential and challenging its limits. Researchers were selected for their knowledge and experience with primary research in one of the framework’s eight outcome categories. Evaluators and practitioners were selected for either their broad experience with informal education or experience with culturally responsive and equitable programming, or both.  Broader Impacts  Participants recognized the important contribution of the outcomes framework to advancing informal STEM institution educational programming. Their feedback has led to the creation of a Voices and Choices planning process that now operates in tandem with the framework at every stage of program design and evaluation. As such this framework also may apply to informal learning in general, beyond STEM (e.g., arts, humanities) and to informal learning in the workplace, e.g., for corporate training.  This  framework, as it has evolved in response to the conference, contributes to a larger ISEE (Informal Science Education Evaluation) System which, , based on the outcome types and categories within this framework, the Voices and Choices planning process to select them, provides a picture of an institution’s overall educational impact and the quality of programming that produces it Whether a part of the ISEE system or independently, the framework is already in use by practitioners from the conference and beyond.          Last Modified: 01/28/2022       Submitted by: Deborah Wasserman]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
