<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  A novel carbon dioxide emission free iron-making process]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>255996.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>255996</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rajesh Mehta</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rmehta@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922174</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is to enable an environmentally sustainable, carbon-dioxide emission-free process for the iron and steel industry.  The novel process operates at relatively low temperatures allowing the process to start and stop on demand, thereby enabling seamless integration with intermittent renewable resources, like solar and wind energy.  The process can use widely available low-grade iron ores not commonly used in steelmaking today due to high impurity content. Furthermore, the process uses only iron ore and renewable electricity as a feedstock. Thus, the process plant is easily co-located with mining operations to eliminate the logistics and carbon emissions from shipping iron ore, supporting the domestic iron and steelmaking industries. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project will validate the feasibility of a novel carbon dioxide emission-free iron-making process. The proposed solution leverages intermittent renewable energy to convert iron ore to iron metal via an electrochemical process.  The objectives of this project are to 1) develop a process to convert the solid iron ore to a liquid electrolyte suitable for efficient iron extraction in a subsequent step, 2) demonstrate high faradaic efficiency for materials regeneration in a continuous closed-loop process, 3) build a novel electrochemical device with total specific energy consumption comparable to the energy intensity of the conventional process. The approach combines a fundamental understanding of iron ore dissolution kinetics with a novel electrochemical regeneration scheme to enhance iron ore dissolution and enable efficient iron extraction. The project will seek to understand the impact of key process variables and iron ore impurities on performance and stability. It is anticipated that the core innovation will lead to a novel process of reducing iron ore to high-purity iron for steelmaking.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/09/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/09/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2039232</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ai Quoc</FirstName>
<LastName>Pham</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ai Quoc Pham</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[quoc.pham@electrasteel.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000844806</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/09/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>ELECTRASTEEL, INC.</Name>
<CityName>BOULDER</CityName>
<ZipCode>803013377</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6503874085</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>6400 LOOKOUT RD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[STE 200]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>YTQCJUNJ1R54</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ELECTRASTEEL INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Electrasteel Inc.]]></Name>
<CityName>BOULDER</CityName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>803040997</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2100 RIVERSIDE LN]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8021</Code>
<Text>Materials Engineering</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~255996</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>ElectraSteel is developing a novel approach to decarbonize steelmaking, a trillion-dollar commodity market that accounts for roughly three gigatons of global carbon dioxide emissions per year. ElectraSteel&rsquo;s strategy is to digest iron ore in a liquid electrolyte, then electrochemically separate the iron out of the electrolyte using renewable energy while simultaneously regenerating electrolyte components that further enhance digestion of iron ore.</p> <p>&nbsp;In our Phase 1 performance period, the ElectraSteel team demonstrated what one year ago was thought by most to be an impossibility, the efficient production of a high-purity iron electrolyte from refractory iron ores with a digestion speed and cost conservation amenable to an iron price under $300/ton. Through the careful efforts of our team, we identified a viable pathway to this disruptive result requiring no high temperature processes, no new material science developments, and no expensive consumable reagents. Satisfactory conditions for digesting even low-grade iron ores were determined, and an electrochemical cell capable of regenerating the electrolyte was developed. Short term failure mechanisms were identified and mitigated, enabling and justifying long term testing.&nbsp;</p> <p>The ElectraSteel process is designed to radically transform and decarbonize the steelmaking industry. Steelmaking is a trillion-dollar commodity market that accounts for 10% or 3 gigatons of global carbon dioxide emissions per year. Over the next 10-20 years, the steel industry will have to reinvent itself in order to achieve the net-zero greenhouse gas emissions goal set by the UN's Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC) in 2018.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The ElectraSteel process will access a 300 billion dollar per year market with an environmentally sustainable, carbon-dioxide emission free EAF process. To decarbonize the EAF steel, roughly 6000 steel mills of 300 kiloton capacity per year will be required, representing a 1.5 trillion-dollar capital-equipment opportunity for the ElectraSteel process.&nbsp; Equally important, given the availability of the iron ore and low-cost renewables in the US, and more broadly in North America, the ElectraSteel process will revive the domestic steelmaking industry and create local manufacturing jobs.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/20/2022<br>      Modified by: Ai Quoc&nbsp;Pham</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ ElectraSteel is developing a novel approach to decarbonize steelmaking, a trillion-dollar commodity market that accounts for roughly three gigatons of global carbon dioxide emissions per year. ElectraSteel’s strategy is to digest iron ore in a liquid electrolyte, then electrochemically separate the iron out of the electrolyte using renewable energy while simultaneously regenerating electrolyte components that further enhance digestion of iron ore.   In our Phase 1 performance period, the ElectraSteel team demonstrated what one year ago was thought by most to be an impossibility, the efficient production of a high-purity iron electrolyte from refractory iron ores with a digestion speed and cost conservation amenable to an iron price under $300/ton. Through the careful efforts of our team, we identified a viable pathway to this disruptive result requiring no high temperature processes, no new material science developments, and no expensive consumable reagents. Satisfactory conditions for digesting even low-grade iron ores were determined, and an electrochemical cell capable of regenerating the electrolyte was developed. Short term failure mechanisms were identified and mitigated, enabling and justifying long term testing.   The ElectraSteel process is designed to radically transform and decarbonize the steelmaking industry. Steelmaking is a trillion-dollar commodity market that accounts for 10% or 3 gigatons of global carbon dioxide emissions per year. Over the next 10-20 years, the steel industry will have to reinvent itself in order to achieve the net-zero greenhouse gas emissions goal set by the UN's Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC) in 2018.     The ElectraSteel process will access a 300 billion dollar per year market with an environmentally sustainable, carbon-dioxide emission free EAF process. To decarbonize the EAF steel, roughly 6000 steel mills of 300 kiloton capacity per year will be required, representing a 1.5 trillion-dollar capital-equipment opportunity for the ElectraSteel process.  Equally important, given the availability of the iron ore and low-cost renewables in the US, and more broadly in North America, the ElectraSteel process will revive the domestic steelmaking industry and create local manufacturing jobs.          Last Modified: 06/20/2022       Submitted by: Ai Quoc Pham]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
