<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase II:  A Process to Extend the Shelf Life of Fruits, Vegetables, and Dairy at Ambient Temperature]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2022</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>991377.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>991377</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Cooperative Agreement</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anna Brady</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>abrady@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927077</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this SBIR Phase II project is to improve fruit and vegetable storage and dairy powder production in situations that currently require additives and carrier agents during the high-temperature processing techniques. The creation of novel, high-quality, shelf-stable food products is an important step toward increasing food system sustainability and accessibility.  The team seeks to increase shelf-stability, reducing reliance on the expensive and limited cold chain. This technology has potential applications for pharmaceutical drug preservation. Additionally, global water shortages have increased reliance on desalination technologies that are expensive and environmentally taxing. With the potential cost, scalability, and portability benefits of the proposed separation technology, there is further potential for use in water treatment.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This SBIR Phase II project seeks to further develop a hybrid separation technology combining supercritical fluids and sonication to instantly separate a solute and solvent at operational temperatures of 15-55 °C, with inputs as low as 1% solids.  The technology results in products with particles sizes of &lt;10um to &gt;250um and varying crystallization without hardware changes. By creating a continuous separation effect using velocity (supersonic flow as the kinetic driving force for phase separation instead of heat), the technology overcomes the end-product quality limitations of traditional thermal drying techniques, and has the potential to scale with attractive unit economics,.  This method is significantly more energy efficient than existing methodologies. Specifically, the technology can produce pure fruit, vegetable, and dairy powders without preprocessing concentration steps, additives, carrier agents, or thermal treatment.  The method may also be used to develop drug formulations for aerosol delivery and/or enhanced bioavailability, streamline sugar manufacturing to create co-energy generation, and potentially offer cost effective compact desalination systems to make drinkable water. The Phase II research seeks to design, construct, and optimize a scalable pilot system through computational fluid dynamics modeling, custom fabrication, and analytical testing to validate the unit economics and end-product attributes.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/21/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/21/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>CoopAgrmnt</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2039218</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Vipul</FirstName>
<LastName>Saran</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Vipul Saran</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[vipul@fartherfarms.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000764762</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/21/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Max</FirstName>
<LastName>Richman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Max Richman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[max.p.richman@gmail.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000785808</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/21/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Farther Farms, Inc.</Name>
<CityName>ROCHESTER</CityName>
<ZipCode>146184428</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6073192465</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>70 CRANDON WAY</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>25</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY25</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>UQKMR155L3U9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>FARTHER FARMS, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Farther Farms, Inc.]]></Name>
<CityName>Rochester</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>146042101</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[260 E. Main Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>25</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY25</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1591</Code>
<Text>STTR Phase II</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8030</Code>
<Text>Chemical Technology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002223DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2022~991377</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
