<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research: A Biotic Inventory of Terrestrial Vertebrates, Spiders, and Haemosporidian Parasites of Sulawesi, Indonesia]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/08/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>15564.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>15564</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010206</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Christopher Schneider</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cjschnei@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032920000</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The Indonesian island of Sulawesi is unusually rich in species and therefore is an important location for biodiversity discovery. This research project will inventory terrestrial vertebrates (amphibians, reptiles, birds and mammals), spiders, and vertebrate parasites of this large tropical island. Field teams composed of specialists on each of these taxonomic groups will survey 10 major mountains on Sulawesi over the course of five field seasons. By thoroughly sampling this island now while some forest remains fully intact and depositing these collections in natural history museums, the raw materials (specimens) supporting the study of tropical diversification will be made available to this and future generations of biological researchers. This project includes training of undergraduate and graduate students, postdocs, and technicians from US and Indonesian research institutions in biotic survey research. Senior Indonesian scientists will aid US researchers in a collaborative analysis of specimens. The research team will organize two workshops primarily oriented around molecular genetic data collection and analysis, including high-throughput sequence data, and corresponding population genetic, phylogenetic, and biogeographical analysis. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Sulawesi is characterized by a highly endemic biota, resulting from its large size, geographic setting, long period of isolation from all other land masses, and complex tectonic history. The island exhibits substantial topographical relief, with vast areas over 1000 m above sea level, 20 summits greater than 2500 m in height, and six summits above 3000 m. It probably has never been connected to the more proximate Sunda continental shelf to its west, nor with the more distant Sahul Shelf (New Guinea, Australia, and their land-bridge islands) to its east, and thus has been isolated for its entire history of 20-25 million years. Sulawesi is a composite island composed of at least five paleo-islands that were distantly separated from one another for several million years before merging more or less simultaneously between 10 and 5 million years ago. The composite nature of the island has been strongly implicated in the process of in situ species diversification on Sulawesi. Field sites for biotic survey work were selected to allow thorough sampling of the four arms of Sulawesi as well as its Central Core. A major focus of the program will be sampling along elevational transects on the largest mountains of each Area of Endemism, thereby enabling transects that reach &gt;2500 m in elevation. None of the focal taxa targeted here have been sampled adequately from high elevation sites. The scientific value of the proposed field efforts are considerable and fall broadly into the following themes: (1) documentation of biodiversity, including species and their distributions, evolutionary and population genetic relationships and affinities, and the chronology and geological context of species and community diversification, (2) conservation biology, including documentation of disease outbreak and response, invasive species, and extinction, and (3) understanding of interesting evolutionary processes, including adaptive radiation, hybridization, ecological opportunity, and the genetic basis of biological innovation.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/19/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/19/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2039257</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Susan</FirstName>
<LastName>Perkins</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Susan Perkins</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[sperkins@ccny.cuny.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000184338</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/19/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>CUNY City College</Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<ZipCode>100319101</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2126505418</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>160 CONVENT AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>L952KGDMSLV5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH FOUNDATION OF THE CITY UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>U7WPB7AFN7M2</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[CUNY City College]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>100319101</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1198</Code>
<Text>Biodiversity: Discov &amp;Analysis</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9169</Code>
<Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01001516DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~15564</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Because of its complex geological history and position between Austalia and mainland southeast Asia, Indonesia is exceptionally biodiverse. The island of Sulawesi (Fig1), one of the largest of the more than 17,000 islands that make up Indonesia, is especially known for its unique and unusual animals, many of which are found nowhere else. The purpose of this collaborative award was to survey, discover, and describe additional species of vertebrates (mammals, birds, reptiles, and amphibians) as well as insects from several of the island's mountaintops, which are remote and very undersampled. Work done by myself and my students focused on some of the microbial symbionts of these animals, in particular the blood parasites and the interaction of the gut microbiome (the collection of bacteria and other microbes in the intestinal tract) and those parasites. Of particular focus for us were the haemosporidians, a term for what are also known as "malaria parasites." These parasites are related to the species that cause the disease malaria in humans, but instead of humans, these species of parasites use rodents, bats, lizard, birds and other animals as their hosts. By studying these parasites, we hope to better understand the evolutionary history of this important group of organisms.&nbsp;</p> <p>Five major, collaborative expeditions were conducted between 2016 and 2019, sampling five different mountains. These expeditions involved scientists from the American Museum of Natural History, the University of California at Berkeley, Museum Victoria (Melbourne, Australia) and researchers from the Indonesian Institute of Sciences (LIPI; Fig2). For our work, we collected blood samples from vertebrates in the form of microscope slides and samples for further genetic analyses. Back in our home lab, we screened each sample using both miscroscopy and genetic methods that can detect parasite DNA.</p> <p>While the pandemic severely limited our ability to maintain access to our labs and complete the work, we have several interesting preliminary results. A study of the trypanosomes (related to the human parasites that cause Chagas Disease and sleeping sickness) in Sulawesi mammals revealed that the parasites on the island consist of a mixture of native parasites that are evolved on Sulawesi and others that likely came to the island in invasive mammals.&nbsp;</p> <p>Of the reptiles and amphibians that we have screened, we observe six very different kinds of eukaryotic (cells with a nucleus) blood parasites (Fig3). All of these organisms almost certainly represent species that are new to science and we are in the process of describing them.&nbsp;</p> <p>The avian malaria parasites are also extremely diverse. A few of the parasites that we have found are also found in birds in other parts of the world, but almost all of them are new species as well. Our current estimates are that more than 100 new lineages of avian malaria parasites have been discovered through these expeditions (Fig4).</p> <p>A CUNY Gradute Center Ph.D. student, Rachael Joakim, has been using this project as the basis of her dissertation work and City College of New York undergraduate Abbe Pannucci completed her senior honors thesis by studying the malaria parasites of lizards.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/15/2022<br>      Modified by: Susan&nbsp;Perkins</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2039257/2039257_10392642_1657900383275_Sulawesi_Regions_map.svg--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2039257/2039257_10392642_1657900383275_Sulawesi_Regions_map.svg--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Fig1 - Map of Sulawesi"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2039257/2039257_10392642_1657900383275_Sulawesi_Regions_map.svg--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Fig1 - Map of Sulawesi"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Map of the Indonesian island of Sulawesi. Its unusual shape is the result of millions of years of volcanic activity and shifting tectonic plates.</div> <div class="imageCredit">OpenStreetMap</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Susan&nbsp;Perkins</div> <div class="imageTitle">Fig1 - Map of Sulawesi</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2039257/2039257_10392642_1657900647454_IMG_5207--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2039257/2039257_10392642_1657900647454_IMG_5207--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Fig2 - Expedition crew, October 2016."><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2039257/2039257_10392642_1657900647454_IMG_5207--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Fig2 - Expedition crew, October 2016."></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Members of the expedition crew in October 2016 included scientists from the Indonesian Institute of Sciences (LIPI), the American Museum of Natural History, the University of California at Berkeley, and Museum Victoria.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Susan Perkins</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Susan&nbsp;Perkins</div> <div class="imageTitle">Fig2 - Expedition crew, October 2016.</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2039257/2039257_10392642_1657900831802_HerpParasites--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2039257/2039257_10392642_1657900831802_HerpParasites--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Fig3 - Parasites of reptiles and amphibians"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2039257/2039257_10392642_1657900831802_HerpParasites--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Fig3 - Parasites of reptiles and amphibians"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Eukaryotic parasites as well as bacterial and viral infections observed via microscopy from amphibians and reptiles collected during expeditions of 2016, 2017, and 2018.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Abbe Pannucci</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Susan&nbsp;Perkins</div> <div class="imageTitle">Fig3 - Parasites of reptiles and amphibians</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2039257/2039257_10392642_1657901254847_AvianParasites--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2039257/2039257_10392642_1657901254847_AvianParasites--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Fig4 - Avian Malaria parasites"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2039257/2039257_10392642_1657901254847_AvianParasites--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Fig4 - Avian Malaria parasites"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Preliminary results of surveying for malaria parasites in bird hosts. Top = Plasmodium and Parahaemoproteus; Bottom = Leucocytozoon. Samples are color-coded according to sampling location.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Rachael Joakim</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Susan&nbsp;Perkins</div> <div class="imageTitle">Fig4 - Avian Malaria parasites</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Because of its complex geological history and position between Austalia and mainland southeast Asia, Indonesia is exceptionally biodiverse. The island of Sulawesi (Fig1), one of the largest of the more than 17,000 islands that make up Indonesia, is especially known for its unique and unusual animals, many of which are found nowhere else. The purpose of this collaborative award was to survey, discover, and describe additional species of vertebrates (mammals, birds, reptiles, and amphibians) as well as insects from several of the island's mountaintops, which are remote and very undersampled. Work done by myself and my students focused on some of the microbial symbionts of these animals, in particular the blood parasites and the interaction of the gut microbiome (the collection of bacteria and other microbes in the intestinal tract) and those parasites. Of particular focus for us were the haemosporidians, a term for what are also known as "malaria parasites." These parasites are related to the species that cause the disease malaria in humans, but instead of humans, these species of parasites use rodents, bats, lizard, birds and other animals as their hosts. By studying these parasites, we hope to better understand the evolutionary history of this important group of organisms.   Five major, collaborative expeditions were conducted between 2016 and 2019, sampling five different mountains. These expeditions involved scientists from the American Museum of Natural History, the University of California at Berkeley, Museum Victoria (Melbourne, Australia) and researchers from the Indonesian Institute of Sciences (LIPI; Fig2). For our work, we collected blood samples from vertebrates in the form of microscope slides and samples for further genetic analyses. Back in our home lab, we screened each sample using both miscroscopy and genetic methods that can detect parasite DNA.  While the pandemic severely limited our ability to maintain access to our labs and complete the work, we have several interesting preliminary results. A study of the trypanosomes (related to the human parasites that cause Chagas Disease and sleeping sickness) in Sulawesi mammals revealed that the parasites on the island consist of a mixture of native parasites that are evolved on Sulawesi and others that likely came to the island in invasive mammals.   Of the reptiles and amphibians that we have screened, we observe six very different kinds of eukaryotic (cells with a nucleus) blood parasites (Fig3). All of these organisms almost certainly represent species that are new to science and we are in the process of describing them.   The avian malaria parasites are also extremely diverse. A few of the parasites that we have found are also found in birds in other parts of the world, but almost all of them are new species as well. Our current estimates are that more than 100 new lineages of avian malaria parasites have been discovered through these expeditions (Fig4).  A CUNY Gradute Center Ph.D. student, Rachael Joakim, has been using this project as the basis of her dissertation work and City College of New York undergraduate Abbe Pannucci completed her senior honors thesis by studying the malaria parasites of lizards.        Last Modified: 07/15/2022       Submitted by: Susan Perkins]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
