<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[I-Corps:  A two-step approach for dissolving barite for the oil and gas industry]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ruth Shuman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rshuman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922160</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this I-Corps project is the development of a chemical method to dissolve and remove solid deposits (scale) that block and damage pipelines. This problem is one faced by the oil and gas, geothermal, water treatment, and boiler industries. The cost to remove scale ranges from $15,000-150,000 per treatment per oil or gas well without considering the loss in revenue from the interruption in production. Approximately $5 billion is spent on just handling and managing the scale-associated problems in the oil and gas industry every year. In some cases, the scale is contaminated with radioactive material (called naturally occurring radioactive material, or NORM) and, in addition, some treatments release toxic gases. These conditions become extremely dangerous to the field workers and the environment and it is a serious liability for the energy companies and operators. This project explores the requirements needed to simplify the treatment method of scale removal to reduce the cost by 75%, to allow for more energy production by reducing production-halt time from 2 weeks to one day, and to prevent the buildup of the harmful NORM.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project is based on the development of a two-step approach to dissolve barite, one of the most common scale minerals. In the first step, the barite is converted to a value-added chemical product using an active solution. In the second step, the value-added chemical is dissolved by using formulated water. The second-step prevents the buildup of toxic material which provides an added benefit by enabling easier waste management. The benefit of the two-step technology is adaptability. Current scale dissolvers only work in very specific regions and cannot be applied to other domestic or international markets. Through simple modifications and additives, the proposed solution may be made compatible with a wide range of environments providing greater efficiency and flexibility.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/17/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/25/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041, 47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2039521</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Hamidreza</FirstName>
<LastName>Samouei</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Hamidreza Samouei</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[samouei@tamu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000831654</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/17/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Texas A&amp;M Engineering Experiment Station</Name>
<CityName>COLLEGE STATION</CityName>
<ZipCode>778433124</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9798626777</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3124 TAMU</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>QD1MX6N5YTN4</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TEXAS A&amp;M ENGINEERING EXPERIMENT STATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>QD1MX6N5YTN4</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Texas A&M Engineering Experiment Station]]></Name>
<CityName>College Station</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>778433116</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3116 TAMU]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Final Report: A Two-Step Approach for Dissolving Barite in the Oil and Gas Industry</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>1. Introduction</p> <p>This final report provides an overview of the progress made under the NSF I-Corps grant (NSF-2039521) titled "A two-step approach for dissolving barite for the oil and gas industry." The proposal aimed to develop an innovative and environmentally safe chemical solution for dissolving barite (barium sulfate, BaSO4) deposits in various industries that utilize water in their processes. The project has successfully completed three years of customer discovery, extensive interviews with industry experts, and evaluation of customer needs. This report highlights the intellectual merit of the proposed innovation, its potential impact on multiple industries, and the future prospects for commercialization.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>2. Proposed Innovation</p> <p>The proposed innovation focuses on addressing the challenges associated with removing barite scale in industries such as oil and gas. Barite scale deposits can cause flow obstruction, leading to increased costs and downtime in operations. Moreover, when the scale contains natural radioactive ions, it poses additional safety concerns. The aim of this project was to develop a low-cost, scalable, and efficient chemical solution for dissolving barite deposits, thereby reducing costs, downtime, and the handling of radioactive wastes.</p> <p>During the customer discovery phase, 359 industry experts from 38 different countries were interviewed to identify and evaluate customer needs. Factors such as water quality, mineralogy, temperature, and pressure were taken into account to ensure that the solution could be tailored to different industry requirements. The proposed innovation addresses these needs by providing an environmentally safe and efficient method for barite scale removal.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>3. Intellectual Merit</p> <p>The intellectual merit of this innovation lies in its potential to significantly improve the removal of barium sulfate scales at a low cost. The alpha version of the developed solution has demonstrated four to five times greater removal capacity while reducing treatment costs by 80%. This breakthrough offers substantial benefits to industries, particularly in oil and gas production and water desalination, where barite scale removal is a critical issue.</p> <p>The successful development of an efficient and safe method for removing barium-sulfate scales not only enhances the economic and energy security of the United States but also positions the country as a leader in advanced technologies for addressing global challenges. Texas A&amp;M University, through its involvement in this project, has the opportunity to take the lead in further developing and marketing this technology, thereby cementing its position as a pioneer in the industry.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>4. Future Prospects</p> <p>Moving forward, it is recommended to continue refining the developed solution and conducting additional field tests to validate its performance under various conditions. Collaborations with industry partners will be crucial for scaling up the production and implementation of the solution. It is essential to focus on cost optimization, ensuring that the final product remains competitive and cost-effective for end-users.</p> <p>Commercialization efforts should involve marketing and promotion strategies to raise awareness about the benefits and capabilities of the developed solution. Intellectual property protection should also be pursued to safeguard the innovative aspects of the technology. Engaging with regulatory bodies and industry associations will help facilitate the adoption of the solution and establish industry standards.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>5. Conclusion</p> <p>In conclusion, the NSF I-Corps grant project focused on developing an innovative chemical solution for dissolving barite deposits in various industries. The customer discovery process and evaluations of industry needs have laid the foundation for a scalable, low-cost, and efficient product that addresses the challenges associated with barite scale removal. The intellectual merit of this innovation lies in its potential to enhance economic and energy security while maintaining a technological lead in advanced technologies.</p> <p>Continued development, collaboration with industry partners, and strategic commercialization efforts will be key to realizing the full potential of this innovation. By leveraging the progress made under this project, Texas A&amp;M University and its partners can contribute significantly to the industry, promote sustainability, and establish themselves as leaders in addressing the challenges posed by barite scale deposits.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/21/2023<br>      Modified by: Hamidreza&nbsp;Samouei</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Final Report: A Two-Step Approach for Dissolving Barite in the Oil and Gas Industry     1. Introduction  This final report provides an overview of the progress made under the NSF I-Corps grant (NSF-2039521) titled "A two-step approach for dissolving barite for the oil and gas industry." The proposal aimed to develop an innovative and environmentally safe chemical solution for dissolving barite (barium sulfate, BaSO4) deposits in various industries that utilize water in their processes. The project has successfully completed three years of customer discovery, extensive interviews with industry experts, and evaluation of customer needs. This report highlights the intellectual merit of the proposed innovation, its potential impact on multiple industries, and the future prospects for commercialization.     2. Proposed Innovation  The proposed innovation focuses on addressing the challenges associated with removing barite scale in industries such as oil and gas. Barite scale deposits can cause flow obstruction, leading to increased costs and downtime in operations. Moreover, when the scale contains natural radioactive ions, it poses additional safety concerns. The aim of this project was to develop a low-cost, scalable, and efficient chemical solution for dissolving barite deposits, thereby reducing costs, downtime, and the handling of radioactive wastes.  During the customer discovery phase, 359 industry experts from 38 different countries were interviewed to identify and evaluate customer needs. Factors such as water quality, mineralogy, temperature, and pressure were taken into account to ensure that the solution could be tailored to different industry requirements. The proposed innovation addresses these needs by providing an environmentally safe and efficient method for barite scale removal.     3. Intellectual Merit  The intellectual merit of this innovation lies in its potential to significantly improve the removal of barium sulfate scales at a low cost. The alpha version of the developed solution has demonstrated four to five times greater removal capacity while reducing treatment costs by 80%. This breakthrough offers substantial benefits to industries, particularly in oil and gas production and water desalination, where barite scale removal is a critical issue.  The successful development of an efficient and safe method for removing barium-sulfate scales not only enhances the economic and energy security of the United States but also positions the country as a leader in advanced technologies for addressing global challenges. Texas A&amp;M University, through its involvement in this project, has the opportunity to take the lead in further developing and marketing this technology, thereby cementing its position as a pioneer in the industry.     4. Future Prospects  Moving forward, it is recommended to continue refining the developed solution and conducting additional field tests to validate its performance under various conditions. Collaborations with industry partners will be crucial for scaling up the production and implementation of the solution. It is essential to focus on cost optimization, ensuring that the final product remains competitive and cost-effective for end-users.  Commercialization efforts should involve marketing and promotion strategies to raise awareness about the benefits and capabilities of the developed solution. Intellectual property protection should also be pursued to safeguard the innovative aspects of the technology. Engaging with regulatory bodies and industry associations will help facilitate the adoption of the solution and establish industry standards.     5. Conclusion  In conclusion, the NSF I-Corps grant project focused on developing an innovative chemical solution for dissolving barite deposits in various industries. The customer discovery process and evaluations of industry needs have laid the foundation for a scalable, low-cost, and efficient product that addresses the challenges associated with barite scale removal. The intellectual merit of this innovation lies in its potential to enhance economic and energy security while maintaining a technological lead in advanced technologies.  Continued development, collaboration with industry partners, and strategic commercialization efforts will be key to realizing the full potential of this innovation. By leveraging the progress made under this project, Texas A&amp;M University and its partners can contribute significantly to the industry, promote sustainability, and establish themselves as leaders in addressing the challenges posed by barite scale deposits.          Last Modified: 06/21/2023       Submitted by: Hamidreza Samouei]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
