<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Community-Based Programs Expanding Geoscience Education Pathways]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>49858.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>49858</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>RISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div of Res, Innovation, Synergies, &amp; Edu</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Brandon Jones</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mbjones@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924713</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The workshop seeks to continue the conversation on the National Technical Association (NTA)-HBCU Geosciences collaborative strategic action plan. This collaboration, between the community-based NTA and the campus-based HBCU-GWG (Geoscience Working Group), is an untapped resource for broadening participation in STEM leveraging local, regional and national efforts. The role of geosciences in transforming education and career pathways to help broaden participation in STEM builds on nine prior NSF-funded conferences, workshops and grants. One conclusion derived from these previous collaborative activities is that the NTA-HBCU initiative will capitalize on the extensive STEM training and research experiences of these institutions. The purpose of the workshop is to expand the work and reach of the NTA-HBCU Geosciences interdisciplinary community of practice by creating a robust virtual infrastructure for producing STEM geoscience-based curricula, faculty and student engagement while drawing upon the untapped, culturally relevant and responsive capacities of these renowned HBCU and NTA institutions in serving, training, graduating and integrating underrepresented students in STEM professions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Due to the impact of the COVID 19 Pandemic, the NTA will conduct a Virtual 92nd Annual Conference to be held online. The conference will feature interactive remote presentations from students and technical experts with live participant interaction. Although climate change and COVID 19 are high priority topics, preparing and growing the future STEM workforce remains at the core of the NTA mission and the agenda. As a major component of the NTA conference, the HBCU-GWG will hold two community focused interactive workshop demonstration and training sessions. Clark Atlanta University will coordinate two workshop topics, one focused on Community-Based Programs Expanding Geoscience Education that will feature three community demonstration projects connecting campus and community to deliver STEM experiential education in under-resourced Black communities. The program will also include a Global Learning and Observations to Benefit the Environment (GLOBE) workshop. GLOBE is an international science and education program supported by NSF, NASA, NOAA and the US State Department that provides students and the public worldwide with the opportunity to participate in data collection and the scientific process. The Working Group has invested in faculty development training to reinforce strategies for incorporating societal impacts for several years, and they will engage community organizations in extending the impact of GLOBE into the African American neighborhoods that surround HBCU campuses. Specific workshop goals are to: Bring together university, government and organizational leadership to explore new opportunities for STEM education (partnerships, recruitment, curriculum, instruction); Explore HBCU responses to the COVID 19 pandemic including research, impacts, technology and implications for the future of STEM education; Identify and prioritize strategies proven to actually increase diversity in the STEM pipeline, persistence and performance.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/10/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/14/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2039267</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Myron</FirstName>
<LastName>Williams</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>N</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Myron N Williams</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mnwill@cau.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000476975</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Olugbemiga</FirstName>
<LastName>Olatidoye</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Olugbemiga Olatidoye</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[oolatidoye@cau.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000249723</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Clark Atlanta University</Name>
<CityName>ATLANTA</CityName>
<ZipCode>303144358</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4048806990</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>223 JAMES P BRAWLEY DR SW</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>JGA3E25MFDV9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CLARK ATLANTA UNIVERSITY, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Clark Atlanta University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>303144358</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7699</Code>
<Text>Integrat &amp; Collab Ed &amp; Rsearch</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7699</Code>
<Text>ICER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~49858</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Community-Based Programs Expanding Geoscience Education Pathways</strong></p> <p>The National Technical Association&rsquo;s 92<sup>nd</sup> Annual Conference hosted by Clark Atlanta University (CAU) was the first major HBCU conference delivered virtually and completely online.&nbsp; Remarkably, the September 2020 conference attracted more 700 participants with classes moved online due to a second COVID spike.&nbsp; CAU worked to maximize participation in the Geosciences Workshop by collaborating with local and national partners, particularly Morehouse College and their Africa Awareness Week and Los Angeles based Beyond the STEAM led by a FAMU graduate.&nbsp; Community-Based Programs Expanding Geoscience Education was a major track that featured programs and research underway designed to engage students and chart a pathway to STEM careers including the geosciences.&nbsp; This session provided an opportunity for participants to explore the diverse approaches to community engagement around STEM and ways that faculty can support or expand programs that work.&nbsp; &nbsp;</p> <p>Conference topics ranged from &ldquo;Responding to Coronavirus through the Lens of Environmental Equity and Justice&rdquo; to the CAU and Morehouse Makers&rsquo; Spaces.&nbsp; The Geosciences Webinar delivered by Kelly Taylor Mitchell connected arts, crafts and geoscience research in the "Great Dismal Swamp".&nbsp; She has integrated her craftwork into performances delivered in the Swamp that she studies.&nbsp; Explaining how contemporary art informs conceptual frameworks and the importance of remembering the forgotten, as expressed by Toni Morrison, in her own work, Mitchell adds texture and stretches the boundaries of what might be thought of as geoscience.&nbsp; She even integrates a spiritual dimension using the masks that she creates in performances.</p> <p>Climate Innovation: Panel moderated by Ms. Felicia Davis, Co-chair 92<sup>nd</sup>,&nbsp; NTA Virtual Conference: "Building Public-Private Partnerships and Intergovernmental relationships to address Sustainable Energy and Water challenges in the community and beyond", that includes Dr. Brandon&nbsp; Jones, Program Director - Education &amp; Broadening Participation, National Science Foundation (NSF) | GEO/OAD, who provided a government agency perspective. Other notable speakers during the Climate Innovation sessions are: Dr. Olugbemiga Olatidoye - PI/CAU_NTA NSF project, presented "Sustainable Energy Living Learning Lab", Dr. Bad Lehman - PI/Director NU S-POWE (NSF), presented "Solar Energy Technology Applications &amp; Eco-Entrepreneurship" and Dr. Victor Ibeanusi - Dean, FAMU, presented "Safe Water and Health: Rural Community at Risk". Two micro-projects led by Dr. Myron Williams - Co-PI/CAU_NTA NSF project, were inspired by the 2020 Geoscience Workshop: Use of biogas generation for homes in rural Senegal and The Weather as a STEM/Geo introduction at K-12 levels.</p> <p>In addition, there was an entire track focused on the theme &ldquo;Communicate access to STEM study and careers.&nbsp; Each community program featured innovative approaches to teaching and reinforcing math exposure an skills.&nbsp; Community was loosely defined as beyond the campus and extended from the local community all the way to Africa.&nbsp; Pan-African Geosciences Pedagogy is a unique area of inquiry for participants in the Geosciences Workshop and the collaboration with Morehouse College Africa Awareness Week wove an Africa centered thread throughout the conference that ranged from architecture and building to energy and waste.&nbsp; The Africa focus attracted students and faculty from social sciences and business drawn to STEM content from a different perspective.&nbsp; Pan-African geoscience pedagogy has been adopted as a long-range focus for the NTA and will be included in the 2021 workshop.</p> <p>The CAU_NTA-HBCU Geosciences partnership is worked to refine and apply principles in culturally competent pedagogy as a critical component for increasing student attraction and persistence in STEM education, particularly the geosciences. The partnership produced a conference that:</p> <p>&#9679;&nbsp; Explored the HBCU response to COVID 19 including research, impacts,&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; technology, and implications for the future of STEM education.</p> <p>&#9679;&nbsp; Identified strategies proven to increase diversity in the STEM pipeline,&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; persistence and performance.</p> <p>&#9679;&nbsp; Increased institutional, faculty, student and professional participation.</p> <p>&#9679;&nbsp; Fostered ties with other STEM organizations, programs and initiatives.</p> <p>&#9679;&nbsp; Established a robust online platform that facilitated networking and&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; collaboration.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>&#9679;&nbsp; Shared an update on NSF Geopaths Grant Award: Expanding HBCU&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; Pathways for Geoscience Education.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/09/2022<br>      Modified by: Olugbemiga&nbsp;Olatidoye</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Community-Based Programs Expanding Geoscience Education Pathways  The National Technical Association’s 92nd Annual Conference hosted by Clark Atlanta University (CAU) was the first major HBCU conference delivered virtually and completely online.  Remarkably, the September 2020 conference attracted more 700 participants with classes moved online due to a second COVID spike.  CAU worked to maximize participation in the Geosciences Workshop by collaborating with local and national partners, particularly Morehouse College and their Africa Awareness Week and Los Angeles based Beyond the STEAM led by a FAMU graduate.  Community-Based Programs Expanding Geoscience Education was a major track that featured programs and research underway designed to engage students and chart a pathway to STEM careers including the geosciences.  This session provided an opportunity for participants to explore the diverse approaches to community engagement around STEM and ways that faculty can support or expand programs that work.     Conference topics ranged from "Responding to Coronavirus through the Lens of Environmental Equity and Justice" to the CAU and Morehouse Makers’ Spaces.  The Geosciences Webinar delivered by Kelly Taylor Mitchell connected arts, crafts and geoscience research in the "Great Dismal Swamp".  She has integrated her craftwork into performances delivered in the Swamp that she studies.  Explaining how contemporary art informs conceptual frameworks and the importance of remembering the forgotten, as expressed by Toni Morrison, in her own work, Mitchell adds texture and stretches the boundaries of what might be thought of as geoscience.  She even integrates a spiritual dimension using the masks that she creates in performances.  Climate Innovation: Panel moderated by Ms. Felicia Davis, Co-chair 92nd,  NTA Virtual Conference: "Building Public-Private Partnerships and Intergovernmental relationships to address Sustainable Energy and Water challenges in the community and beyond", that includes Dr. Brandon  Jones, Program Director - Education &amp; Broadening Participation, National Science Foundation (NSF) | GEO/OAD, who provided a government agency perspective. Other notable speakers during the Climate Innovation sessions are: Dr. Olugbemiga Olatidoye - PI/CAU_NTA NSF project, presented "Sustainable Energy Living Learning Lab", Dr. Bad Lehman - PI/Director NU S-POWE (NSF), presented "Solar Energy Technology Applications &amp; Eco-Entrepreneurship" and Dr. Victor Ibeanusi - Dean, FAMU, presented "Safe Water and Health: Rural Community at Risk". Two micro-projects led by Dr. Myron Williams - Co-PI/CAU_NTA NSF project, were inspired by the 2020 Geoscience Workshop: Use of biogas generation for homes in rural Senegal and The Weather as a STEM/Geo introduction at K-12 levels.  In addition, there was an entire track focused on the theme "Communicate access to STEM study and careers.  Each community program featured innovative approaches to teaching and reinforcing math exposure an skills.  Community was loosely defined as beyond the campus and extended from the local community all the way to Africa.  Pan-African Geosciences Pedagogy is a unique area of inquiry for participants in the Geosciences Workshop and the collaboration with Morehouse College Africa Awareness Week wove an Africa centered thread throughout the conference that ranged from architecture and building to energy and waste.  The Africa focus attracted students and faculty from social sciences and business drawn to STEM content from a different perspective.  Pan-African geoscience pedagogy has been adopted as a long-range focus for the NTA and will be included in the 2021 workshop.  The CAU_NTA-HBCU Geosciences partnership is worked to refine and apply principles in culturally competent pedagogy as a critical component for increasing student attraction and persistence in STEM education, particularly the geosciences. The partnership produced a conference that:  &#9679;  Explored the HBCU response to COVID 19 including research, impacts,          technology, and implications for the future of STEM education.  &#9679;  Identified strategies proven to increase diversity in the STEM pipeline,              persistence and performance.  &#9679;  Increased institutional, faculty, student and professional participation.  &#9679;  Fostered ties with other STEM organizations, programs and initiatives.  &#9679;  Established a robust online platform that facilitated networking and                  collaboration.    &#9679;  Shared an update on NSF Geopaths Grant Award: Expanding HBCU              Pathways for Geoscience Education.          Last Modified: 01/09/2022       Submitted by: Olugbemiga Olatidoye]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
