<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Neuromatch Academy (NMA) support and evaluation</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>20000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>20000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kenneth Whang</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kwhang@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925149</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Neuromatch Academy (NMA) is an online summer school that will train about 7,000 neuroscientists in modern data science and modeling methods. These methods are the basis of considerable endeavors in industry and academia, including neuroscience, robotics, and cognitive modeling. This project will support student participation and evaluation of the academy.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A central component of the education of neuroscientists is intensive summer schools, which usually run for two weeks. They are usually expensive, require travel, and open only to small numbers of participants. NMA aims to provide a three-week summer school in an online fashion providing outstanding quality of education. It uses teaching-assistant-led small virtual tutorials (about 10 students each), globally broadcast question and answer sessions through crowdcast, professor-guided project work, and a host of further approaches to produce a deep learning experience. Focusing on a tight interactions with other participants, TAs, and professors give it a unique profile among approaches to online teaching. In a post-COVID world, innovating in online education is of crucial importance and NMA has both a strong mission of innovation and a strong evaluation plan to make sure it delivers on its promise. The evaluation approach will consists of questionnaires sent to participants, TAs, and lecturers as well as a causal analysis to see how NMA affects subsequent text use and collaboration patterns.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/08/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/14/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2039382</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Konrad</FirstName>
<LastName>Kording</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Konrad P Kording</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>koerding@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8579285370</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000096260</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/08/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Pennsylvania</Name>
<CityName>PHILADELPHIA</CityName>
<ZipCode>191046205</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2158987293</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3451 WALNUT ST STE 440A</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>GM1XX56LEP58</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF THE UNIVERSITY OF PENNSYLVANIA, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>GM1XX56LEP58</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Pennsylvania]]></Name>
<CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>191046116</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3700 Hamilton Walk]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1699</Code>
<Text>Cognitive Neuroscience</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7495</Code>
<Text>Robust Intelligence</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1699</Code>
<Text>COGNEURO</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7495</Code>
<Text>ROBUST INTELLIGENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8089</Code>
<Text>Understanding the Brain/Cognitive Scienc</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~20000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The award contributed to training at the neuromatch academy and the evaluation thereof. Neuromatch academy, as part of the proposed work at University of Pennsylvania, trained scientists in computational neuroscience techniques and evaluated what they learned. This included the full gamut of moder approaches of high importance to artificial intelligence. A novel teaching format focused on coding tutorials allowed rapid learning in a flipped classroom setting.</p> <p>The students learned about the many types of models used in computational neuroscience, with a focus on model classes popular in neuroscience. They learned the processes used in the construction of models. Importantly, they learned how these models can be fit to real data, a key skill in neuroscience. They learned how generalized linear models can be understandable models for neural activities. In the dimensionality reduction component they learned how data recorded from many neurons at the same time can be transformed into a low dimensional representation that can be plotted. They also learned about how deep learning can be applied to the modeling of neural data and how autoencoders are a useful tool. They also learned specific neuroscience models. This included linear systems, that are ubiquitously used. They got to learn about biological neuron models and dynamical networks. Lastly they learned about statistical methods. That included bayesian decision making approaches. It included systems with hidden dynamics. It covered optimal control and reinforcement learning. Lastly, they learned about causality and links to networks.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/01/2022<br>      Modified by: Konrad&nbsp;P&nbsp;Kording</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The award contributed to training at the neuromatch academy and the evaluation thereof. Neuromatch academy, as part of the proposed work at University of Pennsylvania, trained scientists in computational neuroscience techniques and evaluated what they learned. This included the full gamut of moder approaches of high importance to artificial intelligence. A novel teaching format focused on coding tutorials allowed rapid learning in a flipped classroom setting.  The students learned about the many types of models used in computational neuroscience, with a focus on model classes popular in neuroscience. They learned the processes used in the construction of models. Importantly, they learned how these models can be fit to real data, a key skill in neuroscience. They learned how generalized linear models can be understandable models for neural activities. In the dimensionality reduction component they learned how data recorded from many neurons at the same time can be transformed into a low dimensional representation that can be plotted. They also learned about how deep learning can be applied to the modeling of neural data and how autoencoders are a useful tool. They also learned specific neuroscience models. This included linear systems, that are ubiquitously used. They got to learn about biological neuron models and dynamical networks. Lastly they learned about statistical methods. That included bayesian decision making approaches. It included systems with hidden dynamics. It covered optimal control and reinforcement learning. Lastly, they learned about causality and links to networks.       Last Modified: 02/01/2022       Submitted by: Konrad P Kording]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
