<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Build and Broaden: Collaborative Research: African American Family Relationship Research through Partnerships with HBCUs]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>22544.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>22544</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Peter Vishton</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This award supports a conference that fosters connections and builds research collaborations between Historically Black Colleges/Universities (HBCUs), Minority-Serving institutions (MSIs), and research-intensive institutions (R1s). The proposal responds to NSF’s Dear Colleague Letter, Build and Broaden: Enabling New Social, Behavioral and Economic Science Collaborations with Minority-Serving Institutions (MSIs). The goal of the Build and Broaden program, and this workshop, is to foster connections that enable the submission of competitive collaborative research proposals. The resulting projects would support research activity and funding at both an HBCU/MSI and an R1 institution, providing valuable research experiences and lasting research infrastructure investment at both institutions. The conference includes invited faculty mentors who are developmental science scholars committed to working with families from underrepresented groups, using diverse methodologies, and using within-group research designs to study the roots of intimate/marital relationships. These senior, tenured scholars have strong records of securing external funding to support their research programs and have demonstrated the ability to effectively mentor and collaborate with other researchers. Faculty mentors will present their research and provide the scaffolding needed for individuals who are less knowledgeable about relevant programs at NSF and the research funding process in general. Faculty mentors will meet with scholars appointed at HBCUs/MSIs and exchange ideas. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;An evaluation survey will be conducted with all participants to assess the quality of the meeting, its impact on attendees, and the initial success at producing new collaborative partnerships. Follow up surveys will be used to assess how successful the meeting was at producing collaborative grant proposals that would not otherwise have been submitted. Understanding the developmental implications of interpersonal family function is important to many researchers, educators, practitioners, and policy makers. The proposed meeting seeks to enhance the breadth of talent and perspectives engaged in the research process, and in so doing to make new discoveries in this area.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/05/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/05/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2039815</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tera</FirstName>
<LastName>Jordan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Tera R Jordan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[trh@iastate.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000815968</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/05/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Iowa State University</Name>
<CityName>AMES</CityName>
<ZipCode>500112103</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5152945225</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1350 BEARDSHEAR HALL</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[515 MORRILL ROAD]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Iowa</StateName>
<StateCode>IA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>DQDBM7FGJPC5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>IOWA STATE UNIVERSITY OF SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Iowa State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Ames</CityName>
<StateCode>IA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>500112103</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1138 Pearson, 505 Morrill Rd]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Iowa</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>146Y</Code>
<Text>Build and Broaden</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1698</Code>
<Text>DS-Developmental Sciences</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~22544</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>PROJECT OUTCOMES</p> <p>Information about the Meeting &nbsp;</p> <p>This virtual conference fostered connections and built research collaborations between Historically Black Colleges/Universities (HBCUs), Minority- Serving Institutions (MSIs), and research-intensive institutions (R1s). This virtual conference responded to NSF&rsquo;s Dear Colleague Letter,&nbsp;<em>Build and Broaden: Enabling New Social, Behavioral and Economic Science Collaborations with Minority-Serving Institutions (MSIs).</em>&nbsp;The goal of the Build and Broaden program, and this virtual conference, was to foster connections that enable the submission of competitive collaborative research proposals. This virtual conference included identifying and faculty mentors/scholars who are committed to working with families from underrepresented groups, using diverse methodologies, and adopting within-group research designs to study the roots of intimate/marital relationships. These senior, tenured scholars have strong records of securing external funding to support their research programs and have demonstrated the ability to effectively mentor and collaborate with other researchers. Faculty mentors presented their research and provided the scaffolding needed for individuals who are less knowledgeable about relevant programs at NSF and the research funding process in general. Faculty mentors met with scholars appointed at HBCUs/MSIs and exchanged ideas. Mentees sent research project summaries to the conference organizers who then distributed the summaries to the mentors for review.&nbsp; Time was allotted for mentors to meet with the scholars and provide feedback on their research projects.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">HIGHLIGHTS OF THE PROGRAM</span></strong></p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">DAY 1 and DAY 2</span>:&nbsp; A Pre-Conference took place over the first two days of the conference.&nbsp; A facilitator from Grant Central presented the practical and conceptual aspects that are important to writing successful NSF proposals. The title of the presentation was&nbsp;<em>Writing Winning Proposals.&nbsp;</em>Mentees were required to attend the Pre-Conference.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">DAY 3</span></strong></p> <p>Introductions of conference hosts and mentors, and goals of the conference.</p> <p>Dr. Chalandra M. Bryant (University of Minnesota),<em>Overview of Grant that Led to Conference</em></p> <p>Dr. Tera R. Jordan (Iowa State University),&nbsp;<em>Pre-Conference Summary and Overview of Main&nbsp;Conference</em></p> <p>Dr. Jennifer J. Ross (Tuskegee University),&nbsp;<em>Introduction of Mentors</em></p> <p><strong>&nbsp;Presentations</strong></p> <p><strong>Dr. Norma Burgess:&nbsp;</strong>The Role Mentors Play In Our Academic Lives and the Importance of Having Multiple Mentors</p> <p><strong>Dr. Chalandra M. Bryant:&nbsp;</strong>Overview of the National Science Foundation and the<strong>&nbsp;</strong>Directorate for Social, Behavioral and Economic Science</p> <p><strong>Dr. Jennifer J. Ross, Dr. Tera R. Jordan:&nbsp;</strong><em>What Do We Mean by Developmental Sciences?</em></p> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p><strong>Break-Out Rooms:&nbsp;</strong>Speed mentoring - Each of the mentors had six minutes to discuss<strong>&nbsp;</strong>grantsmithing skills and tips with mentees.</p> <p><strong>Dr. M. Belinda Tucker, Dr. Claudia Mitchell-Kernan:&nbsp;</strong><em>&nbsp;</em>The impetus for their book titled,&nbsp;<em>The Decline in Marriage Among African Americans</em>, which set the stage a strength-based<em>&nbsp;</em>approaches to the study of African American<em>&nbsp;</em>families and couples.</p> <p><strong>Dr. Armon Perry:</strong><em>&nbsp;</em>The Development of African American Men&rsquo;s Perspectives on<em>&nbsp;</em>Marriage and Fatherhood</p> <p><strong>Dr. Jeffery Shears</strong>:&nbsp;<em>Values that Fathers Communicate to Sons&rsquo; about Relationships/Marriage: Direct and Indirect Influences on Development</em></p> <p><strong>Dr. Tera Jordan:&nbsp;</strong>Questions and Wrap-Up</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">DAY 4&nbsp;</span></strong></p> <p><strong>Dr. Jennifer Ross:&nbsp;</strong>Welcome Back, Overview of the Afternoon</p> <p><strong>Dr. Ming Cui:&nbsp;</strong><em>Romantic Relationship Development from Adolescence to Adulthood</em></p> <p><strong>Dr. Frank Fincham:&nbsp;</strong>Positive Approaches to Optimal Relationship Development</p> <p><strong>Break-Out Room Discussions:&nbsp;</strong>What observations you have made about relationship/family and/or developmental science research? What questions do you still have? How does your research reflect developmental science?</p> <p><em>&nbsp;</em></p> <p><strong>Dr. Michael Cunningham:&nbsp;</strong>Developmental Precursors of Bravado Attitudes in African American Male Adolescents</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">DAY 5&nbsp;</span></strong></p> <p><strong>Dr. Chalandra Bryant:&nbsp;</strong>Welcome Back, Overview of the Afternoon<strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p><strong>Break-Out Rooms:&nbsp;</strong>Mentees receive feedback on their research summaries.</p> <p><strong>Dr. Michael Young:&nbsp;</strong><em>Linking Your Project and Your Budget *Now that you have received feedback on your summaries, think about what it will take to launch and support your work.</em></p> <p><strong>Break-Out Room Discussions:&nbsp;</strong>Continuation of DAY 4's discussions<strong>.</strong></p> <p><strong>Closing Remarks</strong></p> <p><strong>Dr. Bryant</strong>:&nbsp;<em>Reminder of Grant that Led to Conference</em></p> <p><strong>Dr. Ross</strong>:&nbsp;<em>Pre-Conference &amp; Main Conference Meeting of Goals of Grant</em></p> <p><strong>Dr. Jordan</strong>:&nbsp;<em>Recognition of Mentors, Final words</em></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/27/2022<br>      Modified by: Tera&nbsp;R&nbsp;Jordan</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ PROJECT OUTCOMES  Information about the Meeting    This virtual conference fostered connections and built research collaborations between Historically Black Colleges/Universities (HBCUs), Minority- Serving Institutions (MSIs), and research-intensive institutions (R1s). This virtual conference responded to NSF’s Dear Colleague Letter, Build and Broaden: Enabling New Social, Behavioral and Economic Science Collaborations with Minority-Serving Institutions (MSIs). The goal of the Build and Broaden program, and this virtual conference, was to foster connections that enable the submission of competitive collaborative research proposals. This virtual conference included identifying and faculty mentors/scholars who are committed to working with families from underrepresented groups, using diverse methodologies, and adopting within-group research designs to study the roots of intimate/marital relationships. These senior, tenured scholars have strong records of securing external funding to support their research programs and have demonstrated the ability to effectively mentor and collaborate with other researchers. Faculty mentors presented their research and provided the scaffolding needed for individuals who are less knowledgeable about relevant programs at NSF and the research funding process in general. Faculty mentors met with scholars appointed at HBCUs/MSIs and exchanged ideas. Mentees sent research project summaries to the conference organizers who then distributed the summaries to the mentors for review.  Time was allotted for mentors to meet with the scholars and provide feedback on their research projects.     HIGHLIGHTS OF THE PROGRAM  DAY 1 and DAY 2:  A Pre-Conference took place over the first two days of the conference.  A facilitator from Grant Central presented the practical and conceptual aspects that are important to writing successful NSF proposals. The title of the presentation was Writing Winning Proposals. Mentees were required to attend the Pre-Conference.     DAY 3  Introductions of conference hosts and mentors, and goals of the conference.  Dr. Chalandra M. Bryant (University of Minnesota),Overview of Grant that Led to Conference  Dr. Tera R. Jordan (Iowa State University), Pre-Conference Summary and Overview of Main Conference  Dr. Jennifer J. Ross (Tuskegee University), Introduction of Mentors   Presentations  Dr. Norma Burgess: The Role Mentors Play In Our Academic Lives and the Importance of Having Multiple Mentors  Dr. Chalandra M. Bryant: Overview of the National Science Foundation and the Directorate for Social, Behavioral and Economic Science  Dr. Jennifer J. Ross, Dr. Tera R. Jordan: What Do We Mean by Developmental Sciences?     Break-Out Rooms: Speed mentoring - Each of the mentors had six minutes to discuss grantsmithing skills and tips with mentees.  Dr. M. Belinda Tucker, Dr. Claudia Mitchell-Kernan:  The impetus for their book titled, The Decline in Marriage Among African Americans, which set the stage a strength-based approaches to the study of African American families and couples.  Dr. Armon Perry: The Development of African American Men’s Perspectives on Marriage and Fatherhood  Dr. Jeffery Shears: Values that Fathers Communicate to Sons’ about Relationships/Marriage: Direct and Indirect Influences on Development  Dr. Tera Jordan: Questions and Wrap-Up     DAY 4   Dr. Jennifer Ross: Welcome Back, Overview of the Afternoon  Dr. Ming Cui: Romantic Relationship Development from Adolescence to Adulthood  Dr. Frank Fincham: Positive Approaches to Optimal Relationship Development  Break-Out Room Discussions: What observations you have made about relationship/family and/or developmental science research? What questions do you still have? How does your research reflect developmental science?     Dr. Michael Cunningham: Developmental Precursors of Bravado Attitudes in African American Male Adolescents     DAY 5   Dr. Chalandra Bryant: Welcome Back, Overview of the Afternoon   Break-Out Rooms: Mentees receive feedback on their research summaries.  Dr. Michael Young: Linking Your Project and Your Budget *Now that you have received feedback on your summaries, think about what it will take to launch and support your work.  Break-Out Room Discussions: Continuation of DAY 4's discussions.  Closing Remarks  Dr. Bryant: Reminder of Grant that Led to Conference  Dr. Ross: Pre-Conference &amp; Main Conference Meeting of Goals of Grant  Dr. Jordan: Recognition of Mentors, Final words          Last Modified: 02/27/2022       Submitted by: Tera R Jordan]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
