<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAGER: Collaborative Research: Feasibility of Self-Propelled Nanoparticles for Heat Transfer Enhancement</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>68193.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>68193</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ying Sun</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>yisun@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927443</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The performance of many devices, such as computers, is limited by the ability to remove heat from critical components. Improving heat removal technologies will enable faster, smaller, more reliable, and lower-cost devices. The research conducted under this award will focus on the enhancement of heat transfer fluids resulting from active “stirring” elements in the form of self-propelled microparticles. Theory indicates that substantial improvements may be possible. If these predictions can be realized, the resulting technological advances could lead to transformative improvements in the design of data centers, electric vehicle batteries, solar panels, medical devices and other such devices, potentially leading to cost savings of several billion dollars per year.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research objective of this project is to measure the effect on heat transfer of the addition of self-propelled microparticles to coolant liquids. A series of heat transfer measurements will be obtained using two different designs of self-propelled microparticles that have already been shown to generate bulk fluid mixing and active turbulence. The measurement of thermal conductivity in a microstirred liquid poses unique challenges. The figure of merit for heat transfer enhancement used in this work is the effective thermal conductivity, which is defined as the thermal conductivity of a fictitious stagnant liquid that permits the same heat transfer rates as the self-propelled microparticle suspensions. Enhancement is defined here as the increase in effective thermal conductivity relative to the thermal conductivity of the liquid containing identical particles but with their self-propelled motion deactivated. Measurements will be taken over a range of particle diameters, speeds, and volume fractions to quantify the effect of these parameters on effective thermal conductivity. Experimental results will be compared to finite-element simulations to facilitate comparison with extant theory and identify the thermal-fluid transport phenomena underlying enhancement. The intellectual merit of this research lies in a more comprehensive understanding of the thermal-fluid behavior of fluid-particle mixtures under conditions where the particles propel themselves through the fluid.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/17/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/17/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2039263</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Pawel</FirstName>
<LastName>Keblinski</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Pawel Keblinski</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>keblip@rpi.edu</EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000218776</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/17/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute</Name>
<CityName>Troy</CityName>
<ZipCode>121803522</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5182766000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>110 8TH ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>002430742</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RENSSELAER POLYTECHNIC INSTITUTE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>002430742</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute]]></Name>
<CityName>troy</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>121803590</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[110 8th st]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1406</Code>
<Text>TTP-Thermal Transport Process</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~68193</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="p1">The overarching goal of this project was to use simulations and modeling to demonstrate potential of using self-propelled micro- and nanoparticles to accelerate heat transfer through liquids. In support of this goal, we executed set of molecular-level simulations to estimate the effect that self-propelled nanoparticles have on thermal transport in the fluid.</p> <p class="p1">The results these simulations predict that self-propulsion yields a significant improvement in the performance of nanofluids. Nanofluids have been researched for over 25 years as potential heat transfer fluids but have yet to be broadly adopted in cooling applications due to inability of significant thermal conductivity enhancement by nanoparticles in fluids without accompanying significant viscosity increases. Our results suggest that with self-propulsion it is possible to increase conductivity significantly, without associated viscosity increase.</p> <p class="p2">Specifically, we found that self-propulsion can improve the effective thermal conductivity (ETC) of the fluid (compared to the case with the same nanoparticles but no propulsion) by several percent. These results, due to modeling domain size limitations of molecular simulations, are concerned with very small nanoparticles. These enhancements are expected to increase significantly as the size and propulsive speed of the particles is increased. We initiated continuum-level modeling of self-propelled nanoparticle system but encountered several challenges in properly describing heat and mass flow in multiphase system ? while these challenges may be overcome in the future, it reinforced our initial choice of the molecular-level modeling technique that naturally model both mass and heat transport without problems encountered by continuum-level modeling.</p> <p>Our simulations clearly elucidated the mechanism of the nanoparticle mass-diffusivity enhancement due to self-propelling force, demonstrating possibility of many orders of magnitude larger mass diffusion than that characterizing standard Brownian motion diffusion. In particular, consistent with theoretical consideration, we demonstrated that characteristic diffusion relaxation time governing self-propelled nanoparticles is controlled by rotational Brownian motion and is much larger than that characterizing by translational relaxation time of standard Brownian motion.</p> <p class="p1">&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/07/2022<br>      Modified by: Pawel&nbsp;Keblinski</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2039263/2039263_10686598_1641590298460_JAP21-AR-00797R_1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2039263/2039263_10686598_1641590298460_JAP21-AR-00797R_1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Model System"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2039263/2039263_10686598_1641590298460_JAP21-AR-00797R_1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Model System"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Self-propelled simulation schematic. Left panel: local surrounding fluid counter flow. Right panel: Global  counter flow.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Anirban Chandra</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Pawel&nbsp;Keblinski</div> <div class="imageTitle">Model System</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2039263/2039263_10686598_1641590700597_JAP21-AR-00797R_4--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2039263/2039263_10686598_1641590700597_JAP21-AR-00797R_4--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Relaxation Processes"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2039263/2039263_10686598_1641590700597_JAP21-AR-00797R_4--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Relaxation Processes"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Nanoparticle velocity auto- correlation function demonstrating large relaxation time characterizing self-propelled nanoparticles</div> <div class="imageCredit">Anirban Chandra</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Pawel&nbsp;Keblinski</div> <div class="imageTitle">Relaxation Processes</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2039263/2039263_10686598_1641591120257_JAP21-AR-00797R_13--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2039263/2039263_10686598_1641591120257_JAP21-AR-00797R_13--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Thermal Conductivity Enhancement"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2039263/2039263_10686598_1641591120257_JAP21-AR-00797R_13--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Thermal Conductivity Enhancement"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Temperature profile for heat flow via nanofluid with self-propelled and standard Brownian particles showing reduced temperature gradient with propulsion signifying inc increased thermal conductivity.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Anirban Chandra</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Pawel&nbsp;Keblinski</div> <div class="imageTitle">Thermal Conductivity Enhancement</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[The overarching goal of this project was to use simulations and modeling to demonstrate potential of using self-propelled micro- and nanoparticles to accelerate heat transfer through liquids. In support of this goal, we executed set of molecular-level simulations to estimate the effect that self-propelled nanoparticles have on thermal transport in the fluid. The results these simulations predict that self-propulsion yields a significant improvement in the performance of nanofluids. Nanofluids have been researched for over 25 years as potential heat transfer fluids but have yet to be broadly adopted in cooling applications due to inability of significant thermal conductivity enhancement by nanoparticles in fluids without accompanying significant viscosity increases. Our results suggest that with self-propulsion it is possible to increase conductivity significantly, without associated viscosity increase. Specifically, we found that self-propulsion can improve the effective thermal conductivity (ETC) of the fluid (compared to the case with the same nanoparticles but no propulsion) by several percent. These results, due to modeling domain size limitations of molecular simulations, are concerned with very small nanoparticles. These enhancements are expected to increase significantly as the size and propulsive speed of the particles is increased. We initiated continuum-level modeling of self-propelled nanoparticle system but encountered several challenges in properly describing heat and mass flow in multiphase system ? while these challenges may be overcome in the future, it reinforced our initial choice of the molecular-level modeling technique that naturally model both mass and heat transport without problems encountered by continuum-level modeling.  Our simulations clearly elucidated the mechanism of the nanoparticle mass-diffusivity enhancement due to self-propelling force, demonstrating possibility of many orders of magnitude larger mass diffusion than that characterizing standard Brownian motion diffusion. In particular, consistent with theoretical consideration, we demonstrated that characteristic diffusion relaxation time governing self-propelled nanoparticles is controlled by rotational Brownian motion and is much larger than that characterizing by translational relaxation time of standard Brownian motion.            Last Modified: 01/07/2022       Submitted by: Pawel Keblinski]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
