<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research: A Scalable Sustainability-Based Approach to a Novel Demand Response Paradigm in the Emerging Smart Grid]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/22/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>19686.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>29685</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ECCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Lawrence Goldberg</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The research project addresses energy efficiency and sustainability issues of electricity production and consumption in the United States. When the demand on the electric power system peaks, such as on hot summer days, the increased electricity is supplied by inefficient and polluting generators called peaking units. If the demand can be shifted or removed from this peak time, then electricity can be generated and consumed in a sustainable, energy-efficient manner. In this project, we introduce new methods for a coordinated multi-voltage-level energy management system to reduce peak electricity demand, which contributes to a sustainable energy future for the U.S. The project's scope is expected to significantly and positively impact several areas of vital importance to the future electric power system, including the integration, coordination, and deployment of distributed resources in the end-user realm; end-to-end interaction across the electric power system; full deregulation of electricity markets and control centers; and development of the engineering workforce. Additionally, the research will encourage, facilitate, and accelerate the deployment of new technologies in the electric grid and help achieve energy independence, low carbon footprint, reduced peak loads, and full-scale electric deregulation. The proposed intelligent energy management systems and new sustainability metrics may impact other critical energy delivery infrastructures, such as gas and oil delivery systems, transportation, hydroelectric dams (and associated irrigation contracts), deregulated markets, and telecommunications. The research will be disseminated to specific as well as broad audiences and through targeted K-12 STEM education. The success of the project outreach efforts will be evaluated by an independent educator.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;To achieve the technical goals of the research project, a unique infrastructural framework is proposed for a coordinated multi-voltage-level multi-aggregation-scale energy management system, extending from the individual end-user asset to the bulk transmission grid, with the goal of optimizing environmental and economic sustainability. This transformational new method utilizes aggregator entities to perform demand response via the aggregation and control of end-user assets (e.g., electric vehicles). Customer incentive pricing, a unique time-varying pricing method for demand response that coexists with bulk power pricing and retail electricity pricing, is introduced and its effectiveness is evaluated under different market and system conditions. To realize the new holistic aggregator-based demand response energy management system, new coordinated stochastic control algorithms will be designed and their applicability for the existing bulk and retail power markets will be evaluated. These algorithms will be assessed using high-fidelity modeling and co-simulation, with respect to newly developed sustainability metrics, market and power system efficiency, and algorithm scalability to a realistic-size power system on a unique test bed.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/26/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/24/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2039482</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Timothy</FirstName>
<LastName>Hansen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Timothy Hansen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[timothy.hansen@sdstate.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000698886</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/24/2022</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Siddharth</FirstName>
<LastName>Suryanarayanan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Siddharth Suryanarayanan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[sid.suryanarayanan@IEEE.ORG]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000575462</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/26/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate>02/24/2022</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>South Dakota State University</Name>
<CityName>BROOKINGS</CityName>
<ZipCode>570070001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6056886696</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>940 ADMINISTRATION LN</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>South Dakota</StateName>
<StateCode>SD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>SD00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>DNZNC466DGR7</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SOUTH DAKOTA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[South Dakota State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Brookings</CityName>
<StateCode>SD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>570070001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1015 Campanile Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>South Dakota</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>SD00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7607</Code>
<Text>EPCN-Energy-Power-Ctrl-Netwrks</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>155E</Code>
<Text>Electric power networks</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01001617DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01001819DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~19685</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~10000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>The report describes the project outcomes or findings for Federal Award ID: 2039482 that address the intellectual merit and broader impacts of the work as defined in the NSF merit review criteria.</strong></p> <p>In this research project we addressed energy efficiency and sustainability issues of electricity production and consumption in the United States using theoretical findings and real-world data from the public domain for proving the theory. We introduced a new method and market entity for a coordinated multi-voltage-level energy management system to reduce peak electricity demand by integrating, coordinating, and deploying distributed resources in the end-user realm with full deregulation of electricity markets.</p> <p>The significant outcomes of this project include: i) a proven method to achieve energy independence, low carbon footprint, reduced peak loads, and full-scale electric deregulation by tapping the potential of end-user resources; ii) a proof of concept of the combination of our method and a carbon tax for long term sustainability in the electricity system; iii) training, education, mentoring, and placement of scholars in the electric power engineering workforce, both domestic and international; iv) broad dissemination of results and products via presentations, publications, and panel discussions; and v) dedicated activities to interact with targeted K-12 STEM audiences.</p> <p>Specifically, this project impacted the education of three Ph.D. students, one female post-doctoral scholar, twelve undergraduate students (including four from underrepresented minority (URM) groups), five visiting international scholars (two from URM, three supported by prestigious external awards like Fulbright and BHAVAN), and one academic team of four students that competed and secured a runner-up position in the US DOE JUMPintoSTEM (two URM, one undergraduate member) in 2020-2021. Of these nine postgraduates, seven have joined the domestic or international academia on the tenure-track and one has joined the industry in the US. This work has directly supported two completed dissertations, five journal articles, and six conference proceedings articles. Further, we specifically focused on soft-skills development in college students, introduction to and cultivating an interest in renewable energy topics among K-12 students, and the use and dissemination of NSF-sponsored assets for high performance computing at two institutions that enabled greater insight into our results.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/22/2022<br>      Modified by: Timothy&nbsp;Hansen</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The report describes the project outcomes or findings for Federal Award ID: 2039482 that address the intellectual merit and broader impacts of the work as defined in the NSF merit review criteria.  In this research project we addressed energy efficiency and sustainability issues of electricity production and consumption in the United States using theoretical findings and real-world data from the public domain for proving the theory. We introduced a new method and market entity for a coordinated multi-voltage-level energy management system to reduce peak electricity demand by integrating, coordinating, and deploying distributed resources in the end-user realm with full deregulation of electricity markets.  The significant outcomes of this project include: i) a proven method to achieve energy independence, low carbon footprint, reduced peak loads, and full-scale electric deregulation by tapping the potential of end-user resources; ii) a proof of concept of the combination of our method and a carbon tax for long term sustainability in the electricity system; iii) training, education, mentoring, and placement of scholars in the electric power engineering workforce, both domestic and international; iv) broad dissemination of results and products via presentations, publications, and panel discussions; and v) dedicated activities to interact with targeted K-12 STEM audiences.  Specifically, this project impacted the education of three Ph.D. students, one female post-doctoral scholar, twelve undergraduate students (including four from underrepresented minority (URM) groups), five visiting international scholars (two from URM, three supported by prestigious external awards like Fulbright and BHAVAN), and one academic team of four students that competed and secured a runner-up position in the US DOE JUMPintoSTEM (two URM, one undergraduate member) in 2020-2021. Of these nine postgraduates, seven have joined the domestic or international academia on the tenure-track and one has joined the industry in the US. This work has directly supported two completed dissertations, five journal articles, and six conference proceedings articles. Further, we specifically focused on soft-skills development in college students, introduction to and cultivating an interest in renewable energy topics among K-12 students, and the use and dissemination of NSF-sponsored assets for high performance computing at two institutions that enabled greater insight into our results.             Last Modified: 08/22/2022       Submitted by: Timothy Hansen]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
