<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[COVID-19 Postdoctoral Fellowship Program]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>343629.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>343629</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rebecca Peebles</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This support to the Research Corporation for Science Advancement (RCSA) helps to stabilize a portion of the scientific workforce by providing approximately four fellowships for highly trained postdoctoral associates in chemistry, materials research, physics, and astronomical sciences. This project is supported by the Divisions of Chemistry, Materials Research, Physics, and Astronomical Sciences in the Mathematical and Physical Science Directorate. COVID-19 has caused unprecedented disruption in many sectors of society. University budgets have been reduced, hiring freezes put in place, and work stoppages enacted. Newer science, technology, engineering, and mathematical (STEM) professionals hoping to enter the professoriate at this time face significant challenges that could force many of them to leave the professions. This activity extends existing RSCA programs to help these highly trained members of the STEM workforce bridge the gap between training and the start of their independent careers, by helping to retain them in STEM while also augmenting the breadth of their experience. Applicants apply through RSCA mechanisms. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This activity provides approximately four fellowships for individuals caught in the wake of the COVID-19 crisis that has impacted their prospects on the scientific job market. Rather than have these individuals leave the STEM fields, these fellowships provide them with at least one year of support. In addition to furthering their scientific expertise in areas which they are already familiar, this support provides these postdocs with opportunities to gain pedagogical training in active learning and its implementation in hybrid and online classrooms. This will make these fellows more competitive for academic positions when they return to the academic scientific job market. The mentors of these fellows also benefit since they are able to maintain some stability in their research endeavors. Research funding is stressed due to COVID-19 impacts and during these disruptions, when individuals leave a lab, it is not always possible to hire replacements. These fellowships help mentors retain highly trained and productive researchers at time when training new project members is difficult, if not impossible. Colleges and Universities benefit from these fellowships in that the fellows will become resource people for courses, both now during the fellowships, but also after, when the fellows continue to benefit from the pedagogical insights they gain as they move into their faculty careers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/10/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/10/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2039044</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Silvia</FirstName>
<LastName>Ronco</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Silvia Ronco</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[sronco@rescorp.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000569649</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/10/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Research Corporation for Science Advancement</Name>
<CityName>TUCSON</CityName>
<ZipCode>857121278</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5205711111</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4703 E CAMP LOWELL DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AZ06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>UM7TY9NPKQ29</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH CORP</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Research Corporation for Science Advancement]]></Name>
<CityName>Tucson</CityName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>857121292</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4703 E Camp Lowell Rd.,Suite 201]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AZ06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1798</Code>
<Text/>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1978</Code>
<Text>PROJECTS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7222</Code>
<Text>XC-Crosscutting Activities Pro</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9134</Code>
<Text>Integrative Activities in Phys</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~343629</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p style="text-align: left;">The purpose of this award was to partially alleviate employment challenges triggered by COVID-19 that impacted senior postdoctoral fellows working in Astronomy, Chemistry, Materials Sciences and Physics fields. Due to budget constraints in Spring 2020, universities across the US were forced to abruptly end on-going faculty searches for positions expected to start in Fall 2020, leaving talented scientists with no employment options. After 5-10 years of training, loss of this talent from the scientific workforce is a severe loss to the future of the physical sciences. This project was designed to support a total of four postdoctoral fellows, one in each discipline, to smoothly transition to permanent STEM jobs by providing gap funding for the academic year 2020-2021. While supported by these awards, selected participants sharpened their research and education credentials and developed new, valuable skills that improved their likelihood of success in the job market. All four participating fellows completed research projects, published results in prestigious scientific journals, and engaged in classroom instruction. As part of their professional development, postdoctoral fellows were invited to attend the annual Cottrell Scholar conference where they met, and networked with, over a hundred like-minded scientists who share their passion for cutting edge research and modern pedagogies proven to improve student performance, science equity and job-readiness. At the end of the award, two postdoctoral fellows had secured entry-level faculty positions with start dates in Fall 2021, and two were in the job market for Fall 2022 positions. They all reported that program interventions were hugely beneficial for their scientific development and future careers as researchers and educators. This award also benefitted higher education institutions where postdoctoral fellows conducted their research and educational activities, and a large number of undergraduate and graduate students who were mentored by awardees in their research laboratories and classrooms.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/23/2021<br>      Modified by: Silvia&nbsp;Ronco</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[The purpose of this award was to partially alleviate employment challenges triggered by COVID-19 that impacted senior postdoctoral fellows working in Astronomy, Chemistry, Materials Sciences and Physics fields. Due to budget constraints in Spring 2020, universities across the US were forced to abruptly end on-going faculty searches for positions expected to start in Fall 2020, leaving talented scientists with no employment options. After 5-10 years of training, loss of this talent from the scientific workforce is a severe loss to the future of the physical sciences. This project was designed to support a total of four postdoctoral fellows, one in each discipline, to smoothly transition to permanent STEM jobs by providing gap funding for the academic year 2020-2021. While supported by these awards, selected participants sharpened their research and education credentials and developed new, valuable skills that improved their likelihood of success in the job market. All four participating fellows completed research projects, published results in prestigious scientific journals, and engaged in classroom instruction. As part of their professional development, postdoctoral fellows were invited to attend the annual Cottrell Scholar conference where they met, and networked with, over a hundred like-minded scientists who share their passion for cutting edge research and modern pedagogies proven to improve student performance, science equity and job-readiness. At the end of the award, two postdoctoral fellows had secured entry-level faculty positions with start dates in Fall 2021, and two were in the job market for Fall 2022 positions. They all reported that program interventions were hugely beneficial for their scientific development and future careers as researchers and educators. This award also benefitted higher education institutions where postdoctoral fellows conducted their research and educational activities, and a large number of undergraduate and graduate students who were mentored by awardees in their research laboratories and classrooms.          Last Modified: 12/23/2021       Submitted by: Silvia Ronco]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
