<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Microbial production of paraxanthine, a caffeine replacement]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>255999.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>255999</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Erik Pierstorff</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>epiersto@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922165</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact of this Small Business Innovation (SBIR) Phase I project is the development of a biomanufacturing process to produce paraxanthine for use as a caffeine alternative in beverages and foods. For a large percentage of the population, caffeine is known to have negative side effects, including anxiety, jitteriness, and insomnia. In the case of anxiety, an estimated 40 million Americans suffer from an anxiety disorder, which may be exacerbated by caffeine in coffee, energy drinks, and other beverages. Paraxanthine is an active ingredient that has stimulatory qualities similar to caffeine but is less likely to cause anxiety and jitteriness. Thus, paraxanthine can play a role in contributing to improved mental health.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;The proposed project aims to develop a cost-efficient, biological method to manufacture paraxanthine. Producing paraxanthine at low cost is currently a significant technical challenge. The compound is only found naturally in substantial quantities within the human body as the result of caffeine metabolism; it is not produced in plants in above trace amounts. Furthermore, synthetic methods to produce paraxanthine are complex, inefficient, and expensive. The research goals of this Phase I project are to use a combination of protein and microbe engineering to develop a biological method to fermentatively produce paraxanthine at high yields and with high volumetric productivities. The approach uses directed evolution to select for enzymes and microbes with improved activity, enabling rapid iteration of the experimental design-build-test cycle. If successful, this technology will not only deliver an efficient paraxanthine production process, but it also establishes a novel, scalable platform that can be applied to improve upon other food ingredients, pharmaceuticals, and industrial chemicals.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/31/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/31/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2039060</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jeffrey</FirstName>
<LastName>Dietrich</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jeffrey Dietrich</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jadietrich@reveltech.co]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000552251</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/31/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>REVEL TECHNOLOGIES, INC.</Name>
<CityName>SAN LEANDRO</CityName>
<ZipCode>945771260</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6052525424</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1933 DAVIS ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>V79JVAZFQCX3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RAREBIRD, INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Revel Technologies]]></Name>
<CityName>Berkeley</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>947102262</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[626 Bancroft Way, Suite A]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>144E</Code>
<Text>Synthetic biology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~255999</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The goal of this National Science Foundation Phase I Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) grant was the development of a novel bio-based manufacturing technology to produce paraxanthine, a caffeine replacement. The Phase I work plan entailed identifying a naturally occuring enzyme exhibiting trace levels of paraxanthine production and subsequently engineer it for improved performance (i.e., yield and rate).<br /><br />The outcomes of this work plan were mutli-fold. First, subsequent screening of a library of naturally occurring cytochrome P450 enzymes multiple positive hits were identified exhibiting the desired ability to produce paraxnthine. Second, the top performing hit was then engineered for increased rate, increased specificity, and increased total turnover number. The resulting enzyme achieved levels of performance that enable it to be used to produce paraxanthine at commercially relevant price points. Lastly, a high-throughput screen was developed that was capable of identifying mutations in cytochrome P450 variants imparting improved activity; in addition to being applicable toward improving enzymatic production of paraxanthine, this screen can be repurposed to identify enzymes exhibiting improved activity toward other target small-molecule products.<br /><br />In conclusion, this Phase I SBIR research achieved the stated outcomes of the proposal and led to development of a novel, low-cost route to manufacture paraxanthine. As a product, paraxanthine is of interest due to its potential to improve mental and physical health relative to caffeine.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/23/2023<br>      Modified by: Jeffrey&nbsp;Dietrich</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The goal of this National Science Foundation Phase I Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) grant was the development of a novel bio-based manufacturing technology to produce paraxanthine, a caffeine replacement. The Phase I work plan entailed identifying a naturally occuring enzyme exhibiting trace levels of paraxanthine production and subsequently engineer it for improved performance (i.e., yield and rate).  The outcomes of this work plan were mutli-fold. First, subsequent screening of a library of naturally occurring cytochrome P450 enzymes multiple positive hits were identified exhibiting the desired ability to produce paraxnthine. Second, the top performing hit was then engineered for increased rate, increased specificity, and increased total turnover number. The resulting enzyme achieved levels of performance that enable it to be used to produce paraxanthine at commercially relevant price points. Lastly, a high-throughput screen was developed that was capable of identifying mutations in cytochrome P450 variants imparting improved activity; in addition to being applicable toward improving enzymatic production of paraxanthine, this screen can be repurposed to identify enzymes exhibiting improved activity toward other target small-molecule products.  In conclusion, this Phase I SBIR research achieved the stated outcomes of the proposal and led to development of a novel, low-cost route to manufacture paraxanthine. As a product, paraxanthine is of interest due to its potential to improve mental and physical health relative to caffeine.       Last Modified: 03/23/2023       Submitted by: Jeffrey Dietrich]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
