<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SNM: Customized Inkjet Printing of Graphene-Based Real-time Water Sensors]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>11/01/2019</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>887386.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>887386</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Khershed Cooper</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>khcooper@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927017</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Low-cost sensors for real-time monitoring of contaminants in water, such as toxic heavy metal ions, could provide early warning of contamination, thereby improving drinking water safety and protecting public health.  A graphene-based water sensor platform is thus explored for rapid, sensitive, and selective detection of various water contaminants, overcoming limitations of current sensing technologies such as slow detection and inadequate sensitivity. However, the commercialization of such a sensor system is limited by its relatively high manufacturing cost due to the batch processing that involves traditional lithographic electrode fabrication and multiple manual post-electrode fabrication processes.  This award explores a low-cost customized inkjet printing process for manufacturing of graphene-based water sensors. The research entails engineering various inks and modifying the standard inkjet printing process to produce the complete sensor system, continuously. High throughput manufacturing of the nano-enabled water sensing systems reduces their cost and enhances market acceptance. The research outcomes provide the rationale for substrate selection and treatment, scalable methods for producing various inks suitable for inkjet printing, and process models for customized inkjet printing. Project results could be used for many other applications such as solar cells, lithium-ion batteries, and supercapacitors, enabling low-cost manufacturing of a wide range of printable electronic devices. The project trains diverse student populations including women and minorities on scalable nanomanufacturing, nanodevice design and real-time water-sensing technologies through hands-on research experience, a course module, and enriching existing curricula.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The sensor platform is based on a field-effect transistor structure with reduced graphene oxide as the sensing channel and gold nanoparticles as anchoring sites of selective chemical probes.  A major challenge for inkjet printing is the customization of the inkjet printing process for a specific device or system architecture. Customization involves engineering suitable inks, modifying the standard printing process parameters, and integrating components at different scales.  The research team aims to close this knowledge gap by exploring inkjet printing of the entire graphene-based sensor system to enable the large-scale production via high throughput roll-to-roll nanomanufacturing of the sensor devices, which should result in low cost.  The scalable nanomanufacturing of inks for all sensor components: electrode, sensing material, and probe, and their printing and integration into water sensor systems are investigated, together with methods for selecting and treating polymer substrates and customizing inkjet printing parameters. The sensor performance is validated in industrial testbeds through collaboration with A. O. Smith Corporation and NanoAffix Science, LLC.  The project leads to a low-cost, high-yield scalable nanomanufacturing platform for graphene-based water sensor systems and other flexible electronic systems that can be readily commercialized by industrial partners.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/21/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/21/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2039268</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Junhong</FirstName>
<LastName>Chen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Junhong Chen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[junhongchen@uchicago.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000354061</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/21/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Chicago</Name>
<CityName>CHICAGO</CityName>
<ZipCode>606375418</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7737028669</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5801 S ELLIS AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>ZUE9HKT2CLC9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CHICAGO</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>ZUE9HKT2CLC9</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Chicago]]></Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>606372612</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[6054 South Drexel]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>025Y</Code>
<Text>SNM - Scalable NanoManufacturi</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>081E</Code>
<Text>NANO SCALE ASSEMBLY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>083E</Code>
<Text>MATERIAL TRANSFORMATION PROC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>084E</Code>
<Text>NANOMANUFACTURING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01001718DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~887386</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The overarching goal of this scalable nanomanufacturing (SNM) project is to explore the scalable manufacturing of sensor devices using inkjet printing technology as a platform, which will address current challenges for nanodevice manufacturing and integration, e.g., the presence of significant device-to-device variation, high cost, and low yield. Through this project, we have delivered several important outcomes: (1) a new manufacturing platform of tailored inkjet printing to continuously fabricate two-dimensional nanomaterials-based (e.g., graphene and molybdenum disulfide) water sensors; (2) a scalable inkjet printing testbed to manufacture two-dimensional nanomaterials-based field-effect transistor (FET) sensor chips for heavy metal ion detection in water; (3) a scalable manufacturing process to fabricate low-cost graphene oxide and molybdenum disulfide inks as source materials for sensor printing; (4) fundamental understanding of various flexible substrates and identification of an economical and robust substrate material that can withstand the manufacturing and service environments of sensors; and (5) low-cost, sensitive, selective, and reliable printed integrated sensor chips for real-time lead ion detection in water.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Towards the goal of improving 2D nanomaterials ink production and increasing printing throughput, we demonstrated innovations that (1) reduced ink processing times by over 90% and (2) allowed customization of the ratio of ethyl cellulose (EC) to graphene in the graphene/EC composite powders that comprise printable graphene inks, (3) identified the ideal ratio of EC to graphene for high-volume, reproducible deposition with consistently high electrical conductivity. Regarding the sensor substrate investigation, we have established a new method for testing the adhesion of thin film sensors and substrates. The method employs tape, applied to and peeled from the device in a controlled manner, combined with a load cell, to produce quantitative measurements with low variations. Digital image processing and a mathematical model have been developed to help define the failure modes of bonding and calculate bonding strength. While Kapton stands out as a substrate with the overall best results, a factorial analysis has been performed on the other parameters/treatments to identify the best combination of processes resulting in the best substrate adhesion. Towards the goal of optimizing solution-processed 2D nanomaterial printing to realize a fully printed sensor device, mechanical exfoliated graphene and electrochemical exfoliated molybdenum disulfide nanosheets have been formulated into printable inks. Using an inkjet printer, we have fabricated graphene conductive circuits and semiconducting molybdenum disulfide sensing channels though optimizing printing parameters, and finally integrated them into fully printed, fully functional FET-based water sensor devices on a variety of substrates. The resulting sensors have been used to detect lead ions in water. In the aspect of manufacturing optimization, we have established a Bayesian optimization method for stochastic constrained optimization problem to find the optimal sensor design that has the lowest sensor-to-sensor variations under a given constraint on the overall performance.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The SNM project overcomes key technical roadblocks and significantly facilitates the commercialization of 2D nanomaterials inks and integrated water sensors. The deployment of such low-cost, inkjet-printed, real-time water sensors could enable rapid water quality testing for various contaminants such as toxic heavy metal ions, thereby providing early-warning capabilities to avoid public safety catastrophes. Close collaboration with industrial partners ensures a rapid introduction of the resulting water sensors into commercial markets. Recipes for scalable fabrication of the inks and the inkjet printing parameters could be used for many other applications such as solar cells, lithium-ion batteries, and supercapacitors. We have trained the current and future workforces on scalable manufacturing of nanodevices and real-time water-sensing technologies by developing an inkjet printing nanomanufacturing testbed, providing hands-on experience for undergraduate and graduate students (including several female students), and integrating inkjet printing technology into existing curricula. Research results have also been widely disseminated through journal publications and invited talks.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/13/2022<br>      Modified by: Junhong&nbsp;Chen</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The overarching goal of this scalable nanomanufacturing (SNM) project is to explore the scalable manufacturing of sensor devices using inkjet printing technology as a platform, which will address current challenges for nanodevice manufacturing and integration, e.g., the presence of significant device-to-device variation, high cost, and low yield. Through this project, we have delivered several important outcomes: (1) a new manufacturing platform of tailored inkjet printing to continuously fabricate two-dimensional nanomaterials-based (e.g., graphene and molybdenum disulfide) water sensors; (2) a scalable inkjet printing testbed to manufacture two-dimensional nanomaterials-based field-effect transistor (FET) sensor chips for heavy metal ion detection in water; (3) a scalable manufacturing process to fabricate low-cost graphene oxide and molybdenum disulfide inks as source materials for sensor printing; (4) fundamental understanding of various flexible substrates and identification of an economical and robust substrate material that can withstand the manufacturing and service environments of sensors; and (5) low-cost, sensitive, selective, and reliable printed integrated sensor chips for real-time lead ion detection in water.     Towards the goal of improving 2D nanomaterials ink production and increasing printing throughput, we demonstrated innovations that (1) reduced ink processing times by over 90% and (2) allowed customization of the ratio of ethyl cellulose (EC) to graphene in the graphene/EC composite powders that comprise printable graphene inks, (3) identified the ideal ratio of EC to graphene for high-volume, reproducible deposition with consistently high electrical conductivity. Regarding the sensor substrate investigation, we have established a new method for testing the adhesion of thin film sensors and substrates. The method employs tape, applied to and peeled from the device in a controlled manner, combined with a load cell, to produce quantitative measurements with low variations. Digital image processing and a mathematical model have been developed to help define the failure modes of bonding and calculate bonding strength. While Kapton stands out as a substrate with the overall best results, a factorial analysis has been performed on the other parameters/treatments to identify the best combination of processes resulting in the best substrate adhesion. Towards the goal of optimizing solution-processed 2D nanomaterial printing to realize a fully printed sensor device, mechanical exfoliated graphene and electrochemical exfoliated molybdenum disulfide nanosheets have been formulated into printable inks. Using an inkjet printer, we have fabricated graphene conductive circuits and semiconducting molybdenum disulfide sensing channels though optimizing printing parameters, and finally integrated them into fully printed, fully functional FET-based water sensor devices on a variety of substrates. The resulting sensors have been used to detect lead ions in water. In the aspect of manufacturing optimization, we have established a Bayesian optimization method for stochastic constrained optimization problem to find the optimal sensor design that has the lowest sensor-to-sensor variations under a given constraint on the overall performance.     The SNM project overcomes key technical roadblocks and significantly facilitates the commercialization of 2D nanomaterials inks and integrated water sensors. The deployment of such low-cost, inkjet-printed, real-time water sensors could enable rapid water quality testing for various contaminants such as toxic heavy metal ions, thereby providing early-warning capabilities to avoid public safety catastrophes. Close collaboration with industrial partners ensures a rapid introduction of the resulting water sensors into commercial markets. Recipes for scalable fabrication of the inks and the inkjet printing parameters could be used for many other applications such as solar cells, lithium-ion batteries, and supercapacitors. We have trained the current and future workforces on scalable manufacturing of nanodevices and real-time water-sensing technologies by developing an inkjet printing nanomanufacturing testbed, providing hands-on experience for undergraduate and graduate students (including several female students), and integrating inkjet printing technology into existing curricula. Research results have also been widely disseminated through journal publications and invited talks.        Last Modified: 11/13/2022       Submitted by: Junhong Chen]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
