<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[EAGER: SARS-CoV-2  Pseudovirus via a novel eukaryotic construction in yeast]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>225742.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>225742</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>MCB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>David Rockcliffe</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>drockcli@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927123</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[One of the significant impediments in the fight against a disease like COVID-19 is the availability of a safe and effective mimic of the SARS-CoV-2 virus that could be used without the need of very specialized handling and laboratory equipment that could serve as early-stage substitute during technology development. As an early stage substitute the SARS-CoV-2 mimic, or pseudovirus, could serve as a safe, effective tool to create antibodies, develop purification methods, design vaccine candidates, and build diagnostic kits. In the absence of suitable mimics, the nationwide ability to quickly pass/fail ideas is vastly limited. In particular, due to the low number of facilities that are able to safely handle an infectious agent, a strain on infrastructure occurs which ultimately limits the number of teams “in the fight” who may have significant expertise but minimal accommodations.  This project will produce such a safe pseudovirus that could be widely used for the development of materials for this and potentially future pandemics.  In addition, a postdoc will be trained in an interdisciplinary environment.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The objective of this proposal is to develop a synthetic yeast construct that will serve as a safe (BSL-1), robust and reliable surrogate for SARS-CoV-2 or other infectious agents against which diagnostic and environmental testing assays could be developed and validated.   The key elements of the proposed work are 1) the development of a yeast surface display platform in which the surface density of key proteins normally found on the surface of SARS-CoV-2 can be expressed, 2) the development of a  robust production platform for the biomanufacturing of the yeast pseudovirus, and 3) the validation of the yeast pseudovirus against SARS-CoV-2 to demonstrate that  the yeast pseudovirus can be used as a mimic for SARS-CoV-2 for the development of biologics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/30/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/30/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2039528</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Vicki</FirstName>
<LastName>Thompson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Vicki Thompson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[vicki.thompson@nowdx.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000738004</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/30/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Shannon</FirstName>
<LastName>Servoss</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Shannon L Servoss</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[sservoss@uark.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000509188</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/30/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
<LastName>Beitle</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Robert R Beitle</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[rbeitle@uark.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000210556</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/30/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kaiming</FirstName>
<LastName>Ye</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kaiming Ye</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[kye@binghamton.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000216479</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/30/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Arkansas</Name>
<CityName>FAYETTEVILLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>727013124</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4795753845</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1125 W MAPLE ST STE 316</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arkansas</StateName>
<StateCode>AR</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AR03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>MECEHTM8DB17</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ARKANSAS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Arkansas]]></Name>
<CityName>Fayetteville</CityName>
<StateCode>AR</StateCode>
<ZipCode>727013124</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1125 W. Maple Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arkansas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AR03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8011</Code>
<Text>Systems and Synthetic Biology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7465</Code>
<Text>NANOSCALE BIO CORE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~225742</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Intellectual merit.</strong>&nbsp; One of the significant impediments in the fight against a disease like COVID-19 is the availability of a "safe" pseudovirus that may serve as early-stage substitutes during technology development.&nbsp; As an early stage substitute the pseudovirus could serve as a safe, effective tool to create antibodies, develop purification methods, design vaccine candidates, and build diagnostic kits. &nbsp;In the absence of suitable mimics, the nationwide ability to quickly pass/fail ideas is vastly limited.&nbsp; In particular, &nbsp;due to the low number of facilities that are able to safely handle an infectious agent, a strain on infrastructure occurs which ultimately limits the number of teams contributing to an overall effort who may have significant expertise but minimal accommodations.</p> <p>Addressing this impediment in a timely fashion was the focus of this proposal to the National Science Foundation.&nbsp; Our overarching mission was to demonstrate that SARS-CoV-2 could be mimicked by a simple yeast strain decorated with epitopes of the infectious agent.&nbsp; Since yeast has very simple biosafety requirements, when our pseudovirus yeast was cultured and recovered by centrifugation, a safe to use surrogate was obtained.&nbsp; This surrogate was able to serve as an internal, positive control for a lateral flow assay test.&nbsp; It was also able to elicit an antibody response in mice with high titer.</p> <p><strong>Broader impact.</strong>&nbsp; The use of a simple yeast decorated with receptor binding domain of SARS-CoV-2 and other proteins further illustrates the power of yeast surface display technology.&nbsp; In addition to developing the yeast strain specific for our study, it opened the possibility of yeast-based vaccines for SARS-CoV-2 or similar RNA viruses.&nbsp; Students who worked on the project included graduate and undergraduate students from both engineering and community colleges.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/13/2023<br>      Modified by: Robert&nbsp;R&nbsp;Beitle</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2039528/2039528_10691250_1678728463348_sebastiandata--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2039528/2039528_10691250_1678728463348_sebastiandata--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Antibody response of mice challenged with yeast decorated with RBD of SARS-CoV-2"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2039528/2039528_10691250_1678728463348_sebastiandata--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Antibody response of mice challenged with yeast decorated with RBD of SARS-CoV-2"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Freeman et al., unpublished data. Mice were challenged with saline (blue) and yeast (purple) as negative controls, RBD (orange, positive control), and RBD decorated yeast. Antibody response with both fresh and freeze-dried yeast demonstrated that SARS-CoV-2 could be mimicked by RBD decorated yeast.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Sebastian Freeman et al., SUNY Binghamton</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Robert&nbsp;R&nbsp;Beitle</div> <div class="imageTitle">Antibody response of mice challenged with yeast decorated with RBD of SARS-CoV-2</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Intellectual merit.  One of the significant impediments in the fight against a disease like COVID-19 is the availability of a "safe" pseudovirus that may serve as early-stage substitutes during technology development.  As an early stage substitute the pseudovirus could serve as a safe, effective tool to create antibodies, develop purification methods, design vaccine candidates, and build diagnostic kits.  In the absence of suitable mimics, the nationwide ability to quickly pass/fail ideas is vastly limited.  In particular,  due to the low number of facilities that are able to safely handle an infectious agent, a strain on infrastructure occurs which ultimately limits the number of teams contributing to an overall effort who may have significant expertise but minimal accommodations.  Addressing this impediment in a timely fashion was the focus of this proposal to the National Science Foundation.  Our overarching mission was to demonstrate that SARS-CoV-2 could be mimicked by a simple yeast strain decorated with epitopes of the infectious agent.  Since yeast has very simple biosafety requirements, when our pseudovirus yeast was cultured and recovered by centrifugation, a safe to use surrogate was obtained.  This surrogate was able to serve as an internal, positive control for a lateral flow assay test.  It was also able to elicit an antibody response in mice with high titer.  Broader impact.  The use of a simple yeast decorated with receptor binding domain of SARS-CoV-2 and other proteins further illustrates the power of yeast surface display technology.  In addition to developing the yeast strain specific for our study, it opened the possibility of yeast-based vaccines for SARS-CoV-2 or similar RNA viruses.  Students who worked on the project included graduate and undergraduate students from both engineering and community colleges.          Last Modified: 03/13/2023       Submitted by: Robert R Beitle]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
