<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[EAGER: Quantum Imaging for Precise Mapping of Protein Organization during Signaling]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>299997.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>299997</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>MCB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Engin Serpersu</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>eserpers@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927124</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Cells have proteins called receptors that bind to signaling molecules and initiate a physiological response. Receptors are generally transmembrane proteins, which bind to signaling molecules outside the cell and subsequently transmit the signal through a sequence of molecular switches to internal signaling pathways. Currently, there are no reliable methods to determine both stoichiometry and precise distances between proteins in a signaling cluster, which is critical for understanding the fundamental mechanisms that control signaling. Quantum-enhanced measurements proposed in this project will allow to approach the physical limits in precision to study protein-protein interactions and determine protein organization during cellular signaling.  Undergraduate and graduate students involved in the project will acquire experience in diverse areas including fluorescence microscopy, quantum optics and precision measurements, single-photon detection technologies, cell signaling, and biology.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will demonstrate quantum-enhanced measurements to realize ultra-precise characterization of protein-protein interactions in intact cells. An image inversion interferometer system for two-point source imaging with high precision will be constructed, and a fast feedback system for center of mass positioning required for the Quantum Imaging technique will be developed.     Analyses and estimators that integrate distance measurements and traditional single molecule super resolution microscopy (SMSR) information will be applied to study EGFR and EGFR/Ron clusters on the membrane of intact cells. The proposed work will develop a novel technology that merges quantum-enhanced imaging techniques with state-of-the art SMSR, to provide a 10-fold resolution enhancement for precise imaging of proteins in signaling clusters with approximately 1 nm resolution. This project is supported by the Biological Sciences Directorate.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/20/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/20/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2039517</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Diane</FirstName>
<LastName>Lidke</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Diane Lidke</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[dlidke@salud.unm.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000069353</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/20/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Keith</FirstName>
<LastName>Lidke</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Keith Lidke</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[klidke@unm.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000380180</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/20/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Francisco</FirstName>
<LastName>Becerra Chavez</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Francisco E Becerra Chavez</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[fbecerra@unm.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000656202</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/20/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of New Mexico</Name>
<CityName>ALBUQUERQUE</CityName>
<ZipCode>871063837</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5052774186</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1700 LOMAS BLVD NE STE 2200</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Mexico</StateName>
<StateCode>NM</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NM01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>F6XLTRUQJEN4</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF NEW MEXICO, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>C16BGHA4MLJ6</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of New Mexico]]></Name>
<CityName>Albuquerque</CityName>
<StateCode>NM</StateCode>
<ZipCode>871310001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[210]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Mexico</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NM01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7275</Code>
<Text>Cross-BIO Activities</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7465</Code>
<Text>NANOSCALE BIO CORE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~299997</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-9e075eed-7fff-cacc-f4c0-f3406f9f1c8b"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Intellectual Merit</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Modal imaging has the potential to provide unprecedented resolution for imaging point sources, such as fluorescent tags that can be used to study the structure and dynamics of proteins in cell membranes, and approach the quantum limits in optical resolution. However, these theoretical findings assume highly idealized physical systems, in which optical operations are modeled as quantum measurement operators. However, to make the potential of quantum measurements available for super resolution microscopy and bioimaging, it is imperative to understand the critical parameters in real optical systems for realizing such quantum measurements with high fidelity. Our efforts in this area focussed on determining these critical parameters and for developing an optical system capable of realizing quantum-optimal measurements for super resolving two incoherent point sources, fluorophore tags in cell membranes.&nbsp;</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>We designed and built an interferometric system capable of making distance measurements near or at the quantum bound (Super Localization by Image InVERsion interferometry, SLIVER) and combined this system with a microscope capable of imaging single fluorescent molecules.&nbsp; We assessed the performance of the SLIVER system, primarily through the metric of ?visibility? that quantifies performance of interferometer systems, using monochromatic laser sources, white light sources, and fluorescence light from imaging single molecules and small beads.&nbsp; We find that to reach optimal performance in a real system, aberrations both before and within the interferometer must be reduced to a suitable level, the system should include active phase stabilization, and that the system should include a mechanism for compensation of differential chromatic aberration between the arms of the interferometer.&nbsp;&nbsp;</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Broader Impacts</span></p> <p><br /><span>This project supported one graduate student for whom this work formed a substantial portion of their PhD dissertation. It additionally supported 3 other graduate students who contributed to aspects of this project and who learned concepts of optics, quantum metrology and quantum bounds.&nbsp; </span><span>It showed the potential and engineering challenges for implementation in microscope configuration that can be used to study protein clusters and interactions. This explorative project involving quantum metrology will contribute to the burgeoning application space of quantum technologies.&nbsp; </span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/13/2023<br>      Modified by: Keith&nbsp;Lidke</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   Intellectual Merit    Modal imaging has the potential to provide unprecedented resolution for imaging point sources, such as fluorescent tags that can be used to study the structure and dynamics of proteins in cell membranes, and approach the quantum limits in optical resolution. However, these theoretical findings assume highly idealized physical systems, in which optical operations are modeled as quantum measurement operators. However, to make the potential of quantum measurements available for super resolution microscopy and bioimaging, it is imperative to understand the critical parameters in real optical systems for realizing such quantum measurements with high fidelity. Our efforts in this area focussed on determining these critical parameters and for developing an optical system capable of realizing quantum-optimal measurements for super resolving two incoherent point sources, fluorophore tags in cell membranes.     We designed and built an interferometric system capable of making distance measurements near or at the quantum bound (Super Localization by Image InVERsion interferometry, SLIVER) and combined this system with a microscope capable of imaging single fluorescent molecules.  We assessed the performance of the SLIVER system, primarily through the metric of ?visibility? that quantifies performance of interferometer systems, using monochromatic laser sources, white light sources, and fluorescence light from imaging single molecules and small beads.  We find that to reach optimal performance in a real system, aberrations both before and within the interferometer must be reduced to a suitable level, the system should include active phase stabilization, and that the system should include a mechanism for compensation of differential chromatic aberration between the arms of the interferometer.      Broader Impacts   This project supported one graduate student for whom this work formed a substantial portion of their PhD dissertation. It additionally supported 3 other graduate students who contributed to aspects of this project and who learned concepts of optics, quantum metrology and quantum bounds.  It showed the potential and engineering challenges for implementation in microscope configuration that can be used to study protein clusters and interactions. This explorative project involving quantum metrology will contribute to the burgeoning application space of quantum technologies.               Last Modified: 01/13/2023       Submitted by: Keith Lidke]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
