<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Planning Grant: The Integrative Center for Emerging Contaminants (ICEC) At Coppin State University]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>249817.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>249817</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div. of Equity for Excellence in STEM</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Leroy Jones II</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ljones@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924684</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The Historically Black Colleges and Universities – Undergraduate Program (HBCU-UP) provides support to undertake an institutional self-analysis and to design activities in preparation for a research center. The project at Coppin State University seeks to establish the Integrative Center for Emerging Contaminants (ICEC).  The goal of the planning grant is to build the foundation for a center, envisioned to be funded by the Centers of Research Excellence in Science and Technology (CREST) program, to perform cutting-edge research in emerging contaminants (EC), which are derived from industry, agriculture, and  biotechnological and pharmaceutical sectors. Undergraduate students are actively involved in this project by participating in research. This project supports the goal of the CREST program to provide support to enhance the research capabilities of minority-serving institutions through the establishment of centers that effectively integrate education and research.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Through this planning grant, the project will form at least three convergent research collaborations to strategically strengthen research capacity and articulate shared areas of excellence. The three interrelated subprojects are:  identifying, characterizing and quantifying ECs; studying impacts of ECs on biological systems; and remediation of ECs.  Specific planning activities include: conducting a writing workshop, conceptualizing and planning for development of a center, piloting research projects to assess student learning during undergraduate research experiences, and faculty development. The project will be guided by formative and summative evaluation.  This project is jointly funded by the HBCU-UP and CREST programs.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/11/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/11/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2040364</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mintesinot</FirstName>
<LastName>Jiru</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mintesinot Jiru</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mjiru@coppin.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000571632</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/11/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Coppin State University</Name>
<CityName>BALTIMORE</CityName>
<ZipCode>212163633</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4109513838</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2500 W NORTH AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MD07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>THKNELBAWJG7</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>COPPIN STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Coppin State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Baltimore</CityName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>212163633</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2500 W. North Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MD07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1594</Code>
<Text>Hist Black Colleges and Univ</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9131</Code>
<Text>Centers for Rsch Excell in S&amp;T</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0420</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~249817</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Coppin State University, a Historically Black Institution in a dynamic urban setting, serves a multi-generational student population and provides educational opportunities while promoting lifelong learning. To better serve the community, Coppin has been building its research capacity and in this planning grant (# 2040364) we aimed at assessing the feasibility of establishing an Integrative Center for Emerging Contaminants (ICEC), with a focus on microplastics.</p> <p>The major goals of the grant were: (1) build research/grant writing capacity, (2) conceptualize and design the CREST center based on preliminary data (3) create a cohesive and motivated faculty team for the center and (4) develop a winning proposal for the establishment of a Coppin&rsquo;s CREST Center for Emerging Contaminants. In terms of intellectual merits, we achieved a proof of concept for several protocols/procedures to fully understand microplastics pollution in water and soil. Some of the methods have the potential to yield innovative techniques to remove microplastics from water sources. In another cluster, we were able to demonstrate the physiological impacts of microplastic ingestion on Tetrahymena (lower level protozoans). This finding has the potential to unveil the upward movement of microplastics in trophic levels. In terms of broader impacts, our faculty learned principles of grantsmanship, and our student interns developed research skills. The new microplastic remediation approaches we developed have the potential to be fitted in water treatment plants once we tested them in various scenarios/conditions to benefit the larger community.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/14/2022<br>      Modified by: Mintesinot&nbsp;Jiru</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Coppin State University, a Historically Black Institution in a dynamic urban setting, serves a multi-generational student population and provides educational opportunities while promoting lifelong learning. To better serve the community, Coppin has been building its research capacity and in this planning grant (# 2040364) we aimed at assessing the feasibility of establishing an Integrative Center for Emerging Contaminants (ICEC), with a focus on microplastics.  The major goals of the grant were: (1) build research/grant writing capacity, (2) conceptualize and design the CREST center based on preliminary data (3) create a cohesive and motivated faculty team for the center and (4) develop a winning proposal for the establishment of a Coppin’s CREST Center for Emerging Contaminants. In terms of intellectual merits, we achieved a proof of concept for several protocols/procedures to fully understand microplastics pollution in water and soil. Some of the methods have the potential to yield innovative techniques to remove microplastics from water sources. In another cluster, we were able to demonstrate the physiological impacts of microplastic ingestion on Tetrahymena (lower level protozoans). This finding has the potential to unveil the upward movement of microplastics in trophic levels. In terms of broader impacts, our faculty learned principles of grantsmanship, and our student interns developed research skills. The new microplastic remediation approaches we developed have the potential to be fitted in water treatment plants once we tested them in various scenarios/conditions to benefit the larger community.          Last Modified: 12/14/2022       Submitted by: Mintesinot Jiru]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
