<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[NSF INCLUDES Planning Grant: An NSF CREST Centers Collaboration to Advance Minority Undergraduate Student Researchers in STEM]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>11/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>99649.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>99649</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div. of Equity for Excellence in STEM</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Mark Leddy</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mleddy@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924655</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The growth of the United States STEM workforce is important to economic and global competitiveness.  Developing STEM talent among all sectors of society is needed in order to grow the workforce. This planning grant project is building on the established strengths and network of the NSF Centers for Research Excellence in Science and Technology (CREST) with a leadership team of experts from four minority-serving institutions: The California State University, Los Angeles; the University of New Mexico; the University of Puerto Rico-Mayagüez Campus; and the City College of New York, the City University of New York.  The project goal is to build a framework, based on the five NSF INCLUDES design elements, that create the capacity required to: (1) Provide support to CREST Centers and other institutions of higher education to develop robust undergraduate research programs and a pool of research-ready underrepresented minority undergraduate students; (2) Engage partnering organizations to expand opportunities to showcase their assets in conference and events that focus on historically underrepresented minority students in STEM; (3) Enhance channels of communication across collaborators, to share opportunities such as scholarships, internships, summer research programs, workshops, and research conferences; and (4) Develop pathway agreements between partnering universities to increase and improve the opportunities for students to go into doctoral and post-doctoral programs.  The outcomes of this planning grant are expected to lay the foundation for a future alliance, center or network to address the identified broadening participation challenge in STEM at a national scale.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The planning grant leadership team will engage a steering committee with representatives from the California State University, Bakersfield; the University of Texas at San Antonio; University of California, Merced; Prairie View A&amp;M University; and California State University, San Bernardino. Together, the leadership team and steering committee will conduct workshops with a broad group of institutions of higher education, other CREST Center awardees, professional societies, national laboratories and NSF HBCU Research Infrastructure for Science and Engineering (HBCU-RISE) awardees.  The workshops will provide a forum for partnering organizations to build a collaborative infrastructure: To develop a shared vision; to expand the partnerships to include a broad community of organizations and institutions; to establish shared goals and metrics; to solidify the leadership structure; and to establish and improve communication across the partners.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This NSF INCLUDES planning grant is funded by the NSF Inclusion across the Nation of Communities of Learners of Underrepresented Discoverers in Engineering and Science program (NSF INCLUDES), a comprehensive national initiative to enhance U.S. leadership in discoveries and innovations by focusing on diversity, inclusion and broadening participation in STEM at scale.  The planning grant is also funded by the NSF’s Centers for Research Excellence in Science and Technology program (CREST); and the CREST program provides support to enhance the research capabilities of minority-serving institutions (MSIs) through the establishment of centers that effectively integrate STEM education and research.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/12/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/20/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2040970</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Maria</FirstName>
<LastName>Tamargo</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Maria C Tamargo</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mtamargo@ccny.cuny.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000332998</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/12/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Oscar</FirstName>
<LastName>Suarez</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Oscar M Suarez</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[oscarmarcelo.suarez@upr.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000337718</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/12/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Arturo</FirstName>
<LastName>Pacheco-Vega</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Arturo Pacheco-Vega</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[apacheco@calstatela.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000513670</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/12/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gustavo</FirstName>
<LastName>Menezes</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gustavo B Menezes</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[gmeneze@exchange.calstatela.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000540739</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/12/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jose</FirstName>
<LastName>Cerrato</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jose M Cerrato</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jcerrato@unm.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000659357</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/12/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>California State L A University Auxiliary Services Inc.</Name>
<CityName>LOS ANGELES</CityName>
<ZipCode>900324226</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3233433648</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5151 STATE UNIVERSITY DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>34</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA34</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>C1ABLRAQTB48</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CAL STATE LA UNIVERSITY AUXILIARY SERVICES INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[California State University Los Angeles]]></Name>
<CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>900324226</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5151 State University Dr]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>34</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA34</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>032Y</Code>
<Text>Eddie Bernice Johnson INCLUDES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9131</Code>
<Text>Centers for Rsch Excell in S&amp;T</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0421</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~99649</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>URM Students at minority serving institutions (MSIs) enter college with very high hopes, motivation and diverse assets, yet often encounter seemingly insurmountable obstacles throughout their academic careers. These obstacles are encountered at key transition points in STEM research career pathways including: (i) Recruitment and application to STEM programs and STEM majors, (2) Early orientation to STEM program expectations, (3) Transition from passive course-taking experiences to early research participation, (4) Acquisition of research readiness skills through undergraduate research experiences and extra-mural experiences, (5) Mentoring and application to post-graduate STEM studies and doctoral programs, and (6) Acceptance and orientation to the post-graduate mentored research apprenticeship, completion of doctoral level studies inclusive of research and publication activity.</p> <p>Experience working with URM students has ignited a passion among the ARCLAMS leadership team for removing barriers to student success and broadening student participation in STEM. Under the NSF-funded Planning Proposal (NSF HRD 2040970) the team held workshops, using the design thinking framework&nbsp;and planned and implemented in collaboration with Blue Beyond Consulting to: (1) convene potential partners; (2) learn about and discuss, from the participants&rsquo; various perspectives, student journeys and the barriers students encounter; (3) propose an effective structure for a proposed NSF INCLUDES Alliance of Research Centers and Labs for the Advancement of Minorities in STEM (ARCLAMS); and (4) begin to establish a collaborative infrastructure to achieve the collaborative synergies needed to realize the mission and vision of the proposed ARCLAMS Alliance.</p> <p>Workshop 1 (03/26/2021) employed the first two phases of design thinking, empathize and define, to envision the development of the ARCLAMS Alliance. Workshop participants collaboratively created several <em>personas</em> to understand the various stakeholders and take into consideration how to engage each in the process of developing the Alliance. For this workshop, we were joined by 30 participants (including 4 students) from 20 different institutions (10 CREST Centers, 3 HBCU-RISE programs, 4 R1 Universities, 2 national labs, IGEN INCLUDES Alliance). Our second planning workshop (05/07/2021) mapped out student academic pathways, uncovered potential barriers, and discussed the unique assets URM students bring to their journeys. This process helped us keep the student perspective at the forefront and carefully articulate the impact our Alliance is uniquely positioned to make.&nbsp;</p> <p>During summer of 2021, we held individual meetings with professional organizations (Society of Women Engineering, American Chemistry Society, Society of Hispanic Professional Engineers, National Society of Black Physicists, and American Indian Science and Engineering Society), all current INCLUDES Alliances, and other strategic partners (GMIS, Cal State LSAMP, New Jersey GS-LSAMP). These workshops and meetings informed partners about NSF INCLUDES program and ARCLAMS, and gathered information with which, ARCLAMS leadership revisited the original vision and goals of the Alliance from the planning grant, defined strategic working areas and designed the preliminary Backbone structure for ARCLAMS. Then, We held a third workshop (10/22/2021) which brought together 20 CREST/HBCU-RISE members to (1) share the evolving vision of ARCLAMS and how it will provide value to stakeholders in supporting and catalyzing their broadening participation efforts; (2) gathered input on the proposed structure and strategic focus areas of the Alliance; (3) considered the roles, responsibilities and expectations for the Alliance members and partners; and (4) discussed ways to support collaboration among the Alliance partners. With the feedback and knowledge generated in the workshops and the know-how gathered from the INCLUDES Alliances, nonprofits and other stakeholders, we finalized the design of the Alliance structure that we agree will catalyze the broadening participation efforts of all prospective ARCLAMS Alliance collaborators, leading to us collaboratively achieving ARCLAMS&rsquo; vision, and submitted a proposal to NSF INCLUDES Program.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/31/2022<br>      Modified by: Gustavo&nbsp;B&nbsp;Menezes</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ URM Students at minority serving institutions (MSIs) enter college with very high hopes, motivation and diverse assets, yet often encounter seemingly insurmountable obstacles throughout their academic careers. These obstacles are encountered at key transition points in STEM research career pathways including: (i) Recruitment and application to STEM programs and STEM majors, (2) Early orientation to STEM program expectations, (3) Transition from passive course-taking experiences to early research participation, (4) Acquisition of research readiness skills through undergraduate research experiences and extra-mural experiences, (5) Mentoring and application to post-graduate STEM studies and doctoral programs, and (6) Acceptance and orientation to the post-graduate mentored research apprenticeship, completion of doctoral level studies inclusive of research and publication activity.  Experience working with URM students has ignited a passion among the ARCLAMS leadership team for removing barriers to student success and broadening student participation in STEM. Under the NSF-funded Planning Proposal (NSF HRD 2040970) the team held workshops, using the design thinking framework and planned and implemented in collaboration with Blue Beyond Consulting to: (1) convene potential partners; (2) learn about and discuss, from the participants’ various perspectives, student journeys and the barriers students encounter; (3) propose an effective structure for a proposed NSF INCLUDES Alliance of Research Centers and Labs for the Advancement of Minorities in STEM (ARCLAMS); and (4) begin to establish a collaborative infrastructure to achieve the collaborative synergies needed to realize the mission and vision of the proposed ARCLAMS Alliance.  Workshop 1 (03/26/2021) employed the first two phases of design thinking, empathize and define, to envision the development of the ARCLAMS Alliance. Workshop participants collaboratively created several personas to understand the various stakeholders and take into consideration how to engage each in the process of developing the Alliance. For this workshop, we were joined by 30 participants (including 4 students) from 20 different institutions (10 CREST Centers, 3 HBCU-RISE programs, 4 R1 Universities, 2 national labs, IGEN INCLUDES Alliance). Our second planning workshop (05/07/2021) mapped out student academic pathways, uncovered potential barriers, and discussed the unique assets URM students bring to their journeys. This process helped us keep the student perspective at the forefront and carefully articulate the impact our Alliance is uniquely positioned to make.   During summer of 2021, we held individual meetings with professional organizations (Society of Women Engineering, American Chemistry Society, Society of Hispanic Professional Engineers, National Society of Black Physicists, and American Indian Science and Engineering Society), all current INCLUDES Alliances, and other strategic partners (GMIS, Cal State LSAMP, New Jersey GS-LSAMP). These workshops and meetings informed partners about NSF INCLUDES program and ARCLAMS, and gathered information with which, ARCLAMS leadership revisited the original vision and goals of the Alliance from the planning grant, defined strategic working areas and designed the preliminary Backbone structure for ARCLAMS. Then, We held a third workshop (10/22/2021) which brought together 20 CREST/HBCU-RISE members to (1) share the evolving vision of ARCLAMS and how it will provide value to stakeholders in supporting and catalyzing their broadening participation efforts; (2) gathered input on the proposed structure and strategic focus areas of the Alliance; (3) considered the roles, responsibilities and expectations for the Alliance members and partners; and (4) discussed ways to support collaboration among the Alliance partners. With the feedback and knowledge generated in the workshops and the know-how gathered from the INCLUDES Alliances, nonprofits and other stakeholders, we finalized the design of the Alliance structure that we agree will catalyze the broadening participation efforts of all prospective ARCLAMS Alliance collaborators, leading to us collaboratively achieving ARCLAMS’ vision, and submitted a proposal to NSF INCLUDES Program.       Last Modified: 01/31/2022       Submitted by: Gustavo B Menezes]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
