<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[I-Corps:  A Novel Injectable Bone Healing Gel Device]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ruth Shuman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rshuman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922160</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this I-Corps project is to define the requirements for the development of natural polysaccharide (sugar)-based gel devices for bone healing. There has been a recent, sharp increase in the number of orthopedic surgeries worldwide; This is due to the increased aging population with orthopedic diseases and the rising incidence of road accidents. In addition, the increased number of obesity and osteoporosis patients are accompanied with high incidence of bone fracture. Currently available treatments including autografts, allografts, bone graft substitutes (BGSs), and bone morphogenetic proteins (BMPs) suffer from many drawbacks. The proposed gel consists of a natural polysaccharide that as been shown to promote rapid bone growth through osteoconductive and vascularizing effects. In addition, an associated anti-bacterial property is considered an important advantage as more than 70% of patients with fractures in distal extremities suffer from infection that requires treatment. The translation of the proposed gel device is expected to help the patients recover faster without infection. In addition, the treatment may be more cost-effective than the BGSs and BMPs available in the market. The global market is estimated to be the $3.25 billion for treating fractures in distal extremities.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project is based on the translation of developments for natural polysaccharide gel devices for bone healing. The device consists of gellan gum and FDA-approved components that demonstrate strong osteoconductive and angiogenetic activities for rapid bone healing with anti-bacterial effects. The current treatments for bone defects are autografts, allografts, bone graft substitutes (BGSs), and bone morphogenetic protein-2 (BMP-2). These methods often suffer from problems such as immuno-rejection, disease transmission, weak bone-forming potency, abnormal bone outgrowth, inflammation, and tumorigenesis. In a recent animal study with the proposed gel, it was found that the gel induced significant cortical bone ingrowth and thickened cortical bones at the injection sites. In addition, there was a significant increase in neovascularization within the cortical bones. Two major advantages of the device over the current bone healing devices available in the market are its ability to induce bone growth inwardly and suppress tumorous cell growth. Additionally, the anti-bacterial activity of the device is an improvement because bone fracture-related infection delays healing and increases complications and medical costs.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/26/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/01/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041, 47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2040076</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dong-Shik</FirstName>
<LastName>Kim</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Dong-Shik Kim</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[dong.kim@utoledo.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000325158</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/26/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Toledo</Name>
<CityName>TOLEDO</CityName>
<ZipCode>436063390</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4195302844</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2801 W BANCROFT ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OH09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>XA77NAJYELF1</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TOLEDO, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>XA77NAJYELF1</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Toledo]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>436063390</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OH09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>During the report period, Aug 15-Sep 30, 2022, the team submitted a project pitch to the NSF SBIR/STTR program and received permission to submit a proposal. This will be a team's 2nd trial for a SBIR award since the 1st proposal submitted to the same program in Oct, 2021. The 1st proposal passed the review with high marks, but didn't get an award. The team is revising the proposal based on the comments from the previous review and also the new information recently obtained from the interviews. Major outcomes from the I-Corps project are summarized as follows:</p> <p>1. A beta prototype has been developed and successfully tested. The alpha prototype was modified and optimized based on the opinions and suggestions obtained from the interviews with industrial professionals. The beta prototype showed superior efficacy and satisfied the unmet needs the team learned from the interviews.</p> <p>2. Learned how to grow and expand a start-up company at the 2022 TERMIS (Tissue Engineering and Regenerative Medicine International Society) Conference. Both PI and EL interviewed several start-up company managers and CEOs and set up short- and long-term goals for commercialization of the technology and for a start-up company.</p> <p>3. Set up a plan for a start-up company. The team is working in two-faceted efforts; 1) Fundamental study on the chemical and biological mechanisms of the rhamnose sugar-based chemicals in osteogenesis. 2) Applied study on the mass manufacturing, sterilization, shelf-life, application methods to patients, market survey, and economic analysis. One research proposal is being prepared for the fundamental study and a SBIR proposal for commercialization will be submitted in Feb 2023.</p> <p>4. Submission of a SBIR proposal to NSF with high review ratings. The SBIR proposal received high rates, but didn't get an award. The proposal is revised and ready to be re-submitted.</p> <p>5. Publication of three manuscripts in peer-reviewed journals. The rheological properties of rhamnose sugar-based chemical and its impacts on bone regeneration were published in International Journal of Biological Macromolecules (Vol. 211, 15-25, 2022). The effects of molecular weight on the antioxidant capacity of our chemical were published in Journal of Food Science (Vol. 86, 4245-4248, 2021). A review paper on the effects of our chemical on tendon and enthesis was published in Tissue Engineering (in press).</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/31/2022<br>      Modified by: Dong-Shik&nbsp;Kim</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ During the report period, Aug 15-Sep 30, 2022, the team submitted a project pitch to the NSF SBIR/STTR program and received permission to submit a proposal. This will be a team's 2nd trial for a SBIR award since the 1st proposal submitted to the same program in Oct, 2021. The 1st proposal passed the review with high marks, but didn't get an award. The team is revising the proposal based on the comments from the previous review and also the new information recently obtained from the interviews. Major outcomes from the I-Corps project are summarized as follows:  1. A beta prototype has been developed and successfully tested. The alpha prototype was modified and optimized based on the opinions and suggestions obtained from the interviews with industrial professionals. The beta prototype showed superior efficacy and satisfied the unmet needs the team learned from the interviews.  2. Learned how to grow and expand a start-up company at the 2022 TERMIS (Tissue Engineering and Regenerative Medicine International Society) Conference. Both PI and EL interviewed several start-up company managers and CEOs and set up short- and long-term goals for commercialization of the technology and for a start-up company.  3. Set up a plan for a start-up company. The team is working in two-faceted efforts; 1) Fundamental study on the chemical and biological mechanisms of the rhamnose sugar-based chemicals in osteogenesis. 2) Applied study on the mass manufacturing, sterilization, shelf-life, application methods to patients, market survey, and economic analysis. One research proposal is being prepared for the fundamental study and a SBIR proposal for commercialization will be submitted in Feb 2023.  4. Submission of a SBIR proposal to NSF with high review ratings. The SBIR proposal received high rates, but didn't get an award. The proposal is revised and ready to be re-submitted.  5. Publication of three manuscripts in peer-reviewed journals. The rheological properties of rhamnose sugar-based chemical and its impacts on bone regeneration were published in International Journal of Biological Macromolecules (Vol. 211, 15-25, 2022). The effects of molecular weight on the antioxidant capacity of our chemical were published in Journal of Food Science (Vol. 86, 4245-4248, 2021). A review paper on the effects of our chemical on tendon and enthesis was published in Tissue Engineering (in press).       Last Modified: 12/31/2022       Submitted by: Dong-Shik Kim]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
