<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Preparing for the Future of Survey Research]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>39778.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>39778</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jan Leighley</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This award provides support for a (virtual) conference about the future of survey research in the social sciences.  The conference brings together an interdisciplinary group of researchers from various academic fields and from various industries to discuss innovations in social, behavioral, and health surveys.  The goal is to overcome common disciplinary divides and to foster communication and collaboration about innovations that might address current and impending challenges for survey research. In particular, the conference focuses on the themes of increasing the quality of survey data, improving the utility of survey data, assessing advances in technologies applicable to survey data, integrating survey data with auxiliary data, such as census and social media “big data,” and examining the prospects for new institutional innovations in survey research across the social and behavioral sciences, governments, and industry.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The virtual conference will bring together scholars and practitioners from diverse backgrounds and fields in the various social and behavioral science areas that employ the highest quality survey research to support their activities.   The conference focuses on four subject areas over the two days:  1) Data quality and transparency.  Discussion of this topic helps to establish the standards by which data collections are evaluated.  2) Survey methods innovations.  Discussion of this topic is aimed at assembling novel advances at the research frontier.  3) Survey Plus or looking beyond survey responses.  Discussion of this topic is aimed at consideration of integration of auxiliary data, such as administrative records and other new types of “Big Data.”  4) Imagining new institutions.  Discussion of this topic builds on the earlier foundations to consider the potential for new frameworks and collaborations for conducting survey research in the social sciences.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/28/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/14/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2040847</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>D. Sunshine</FirstName>
<LastName>Hillygus</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>D. Sunshine Hillygus</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[hillygus@duke.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000498237</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/28/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Aldrich</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John H Aldrich</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[aldrich@duke.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000219884</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/28/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Duke University</Name>
<CityName>DURHAM</CityName>
<ZipCode>277054640</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9196843030</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2200 W MAIN ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>TP7EK8DZV6N5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>DUKE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Duke University]]></Name>
<CityName>DURHAM</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>277084677</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[c/o Office of Research Support,]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>120Y</Code>
<Text>AIB-Acctble Institutions&amp;Behav</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1333</Code>
<Text>Methodology, Measuremt &amp; Stats</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~39778</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Survey research is at a crossroads. For at least half a century, survey data have been essential to government agencies, policy-makers, businesses, and academics across different fields to inform a wide range of critical decisions with far-reaching consequences. Even in an era of &ldquo;big data,&rdquo; surveys remain fundamental to understanding and shaping the economy, politics and governance, and society. Yet challenges to conducting high quality surveys are substantial and increasing. Face-to-face interviewing remains the gold standard of survey research, but the rising costs of such interviews are prohibitive. New technologies, techniques, and data sources present opportunities to improve the efficiency and speed of survey data collection and/or reduce its costs but have shortcomings that may exceed their advantages. To examine and develop strategies to address the challenges facing survey research, the Duke Initiative on Survey Methodology hosted a conference January 14th and 15th, 2021, on the Future of Survey Research. This report summarizes the proceedings and highlights key recommendations that resulted.<br />Held virtually, the conference attracted attendants from across the U.S. and around the world.&nbsp; Panelists and presenters came from 11 universities across the U.S. and U.K. and from Facebook, Google, NORC, Pew Research, and the Research Triangle Institute. The conference commenced with a welcome from Arthur Lupia, Assistant Director of the National Science Foundation. Lupia remarked on the many challenges experienced in 2020 and the innovations those challenges have fostered, and detailed a hierarchy of needs for survey research from the perspective of federal funders centralized around a key need &ndash; identifying tools to produce content that generates more numerous, accurate interpretations of actionable information.&nbsp;&nbsp;<br />Over the course of two days, the conference then used four panel sessions, a keynote, and a brainstorming session to examine current innovations within survey research, the needs of the field and those it serves moving forward, and ideas for improving the extant social survey infrastructure. Conference participants broadly agreed that maintaining the extant survey infrastructure is untenable given the rising costs of conducting quality research at a national level. Drawing on their experiences working with and directing academic and government surveys, they examined recent innovations in survey research and the use of &ldquo;big data&rdquo; for ideas about how social survey infrastructure can be improved moving forward.&nbsp;</p> <p>The full report is posted at:</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/02/2021<br>      Modified by: John&nbsp;H&nbsp;Aldrich</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Survey research is at a crossroads. For at least half a century, survey data have been essential to government agencies, policy-makers, businesses, and academics across different fields to inform a wide range of critical decisions with far-reaching consequences. Even in an era of "big data," surveys remain fundamental to understanding and shaping the economy, politics and governance, and society. Yet challenges to conducting high quality surveys are substantial and increasing. Face-to-face interviewing remains the gold standard of survey research, but the rising costs of such interviews are prohibitive. New technologies, techniques, and data sources present opportunities to improve the efficiency and speed of survey data collection and/or reduce its costs but have shortcomings that may exceed their advantages. To examine and develop strategies to address the challenges facing survey research, the Duke Initiative on Survey Methodology hosted a conference January 14th and 15th, 2021, on the Future of Survey Research. This report summarizes the proceedings and highlights key recommendations that resulted. Held virtually, the conference attracted attendants from across the U.S. and around the world.  Panelists and presenters came from 11 universities across the U.S. and U.K. and from Facebook, Google, NORC, Pew Research, and the Research Triangle Institute. The conference commenced with a welcome from Arthur Lupia, Assistant Director of the National Science Foundation. Lupia remarked on the many challenges experienced in 2020 and the innovations those challenges have fostered, and detailed a hierarchy of needs for survey research from the perspective of federal funders centralized around a key need &ndash; identifying tools to produce content that generates more numerous, accurate interpretations of actionable information.   Over the course of two days, the conference then used four panel sessions, a keynote, and a brainstorming session to examine current innovations within survey research, the needs of the field and those it serves moving forward, and ideas for improving the extant social survey infrastructure. Conference participants broadly agreed that maintaining the extant survey infrastructure is untenable given the rising costs of conducting quality research at a national level. Drawing on their experiences working with and directing academic and government surveys, they examined recent innovations in survey research and the use of "big data" for ideas about how social survey infrastructure can be improved moving forward.   The full report is posted at:       Last Modified: 11/02/2021       Submitted by: John H Aldrich]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
