<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[NSF INCLUDES Planning Grant: A Collaboration of Tribal Colleges, Professional Organizations and Four-Year Degree-Granting Universities to Advance Native American Students in STEM]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>98865.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>98865</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div. of Equity for Excellence in STEM</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Mark Leddy</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mleddy@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924655</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The growth of the United States STEM workforce is important to economic and global competitiveness.  Developing STEM talent among all sectors of society is needed in order to grow the workforce.  This planning grant project includes a leadership team of experts from the American Indian Science and Engineering organization, Nueta Hidatsa Sahnish College and the University  of North Dakota.  The project leaders will engage Navajo Technical College, the Southwestern Indian Polytechnic Institute, the College of Muscogee Nation, Salish Kootenai College, Arizona State University, the University of New Mexico, Oklahoma State University, the University of Oklahoma, Montana State University and the American Indian Higher Education Consortium (AIHEC), to build a collaborative infrastructure.  The planning grant has two primary goals: To engage a core group of partners to inform the development of a Native American Indian STEM undergraduate student transfer model using best practices, and to develop a national network of partners who will adopt the model to strategically address the successful transfer of Native American Indian STEM students from two-year to four-year institutions.  By addressing both goals, the collaborators will be prepared to create an alliance, large-scale network or center for adapting and implementing the Native American Indian STEM student transfer model at scale across the country. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The participating colleges and universities will be engaged in paired collaborations to facilitate relationships, communication and the development of the shared vision and the partnership model that is functional and builds upon existing transfer support practices.  All of the partnering institutions and organizations will meet four times during the project duration to address the project goals.  By the completion of the project, the partners plan to engage all tribal colleges and universities in the US, and to connect and leverage resources with members of the existing NSF INCLUDES network.  The planned meetings will provide a forum for representatives from partnering colleges, universities and organizations to build a culturally appropriate collaborative infrastructure: To develop a shared vision; to expand the partnerships to include a broad community of organizations and institutions; to establish shared goals and metrics; to solidify the leadership structure; to establish and improve communication across the partners; and to scale or expand the work.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This NSF INCLUDES planning grant is funded by the NSF’s Inclusion across the Nation of Communities of Learners of Underrepresented Discoverers in Engineering and Science program (NSF INCLUDES), a comprehensive national initiative to enhance U.S. leadership in discoveries and innovations by focusing on diversity, inclusion and broadening participation in STEM at scale&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/19/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/20/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2040994</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kathy</FirstName>
<LastName>DeerInWater</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kathy DeerInWater</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[kdeerinwater@aises.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000703688</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/19/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Bethany</FirstName>
<LastName>Klemetsrud</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Bethany J Klemetsrud</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[bethany.klemetsrud@und.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000720907</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/19/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Poolaw</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>T</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John T Poolaw</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jpoolaw@aises.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000832733</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/19/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Amber</FirstName>
<LastName>Finley</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Amber D Finley</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[afinle@nhsc.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000832741</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/19/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>American Indian Science and Engineering Society (AISES)</Name>
<CityName>ALBUQUERQUE</CityName>
<ZipCode>871202641</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5057651052</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>6321 RIVERSIDE PLAZA LN NW</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[STE A]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Mexico</StateName>
<StateCode>NM</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NM01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>XUE5YPEN3UZ9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>AMERICAN INDIAN SCIENCE &amp; ENGINEERING SOCIETY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[American Indian Science and Engineering Society (AISES)]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NM</StateCode>
<ZipCode>871096708</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Mexico</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NM01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>032Y</Code>
<Text>Eddie Bernice Johnson INCLUDES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0421</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~98865</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-cab6f221-7fff-a73e-34c5-d55d88850c43"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Through a combination of surveys and virtual talking circles with faculty and staff who work with Indigenous students, four-year institutions establishing meaningful and reciprocal relationships with local TCUs and community colleges was an overarching common theme. Other notable themes arose that have been key in creating reciprocal relationships with local tribal nations and TCUs were: 1)</span><a href="https://www.collegetransfer.net/AskCT/What-is-an-Articulation-Agreement"><span> articulation agreements</span></a><span>; 2) sustainable and need-based infrastructure; 3) concurrent enrollment; 4) clarity around transferability of courses; 5) transfer academic guarantees; 6) co-curricular programming geared toward Indigenous students transferring from TCUs; 7) and the institutionalization of building tribal relationships from the administrative level.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>As for the TCU perspective, they wanted to be included from the beginning. Four-year faculty should be sharing research with TCUs and providing experiential learning opportunities. Research and teaching faculty should reach out to tribal partners and determine how best to work with Native students. This should be done initially and not as an afterthought for broadening impacts.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Recently developed in work with its local tribal colleges and four-year public institutions, the</span><a href="https://naair.arizona.edu/community-resources/arizona-tri-universities-indian-education-atuie"><span> Arizona Tri-Universities for Indian Education initiative</span></a><span> is a great model. The Fort McDowell Yavapai Nation asked the presidents of Arizona State University, Northern Arizona University, and the University of Arizona to designate a representative to meet regularly to discuss challenges and opportunities in promoting student success for Indigenous students. This helped to form this collaborative initiative with eight local two-year colleges, with four of them being TCUs.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Furthermore, we identified five major themes woven throughout participant surveys and conversations: 1) Difficult or rigorous course load compared to experience at two-year colleges; 2) College affordability and lack of financial support; 3) Familial environment at TCUs important to emulate at four-year institutions; 4) Non-linear pathways for Indigenous students; and 5) Mentors have a major impact on Indigenous student success. Recommendations as a result of these themes will be described in further detail below.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>RECOMMENDATIONS:</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>At the heart of the recommendations is a simple statement: eradicate barriers to access and success at the systemic level while providing resources to individuals that promote the transculturation process at each level of higher education.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Stakeholders identified building a sustainable and needs-based infrastructure that acknowledges the political nature of Indigenous communities and demonstrates an understanding of the historical injustices suffered by Indigenous communities due to federal policies on education. In action, this means bringing tribal college partners to the table at the planning stages of partnerships, rather than in the implementation phase. A recent example of leadership in affirming tribal sovereignty in higher education is The University of Minnesota&rsquo;s Towards Recognition and University-Tribal Healing Project. This project serves as a recent example of leadership as tribal partners were included from the inception of the project, the data collected are property of the tribal nations, and the recommendations provided are able to be represented through direct recommendations to both the system&rsquo;s president and governing board.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Building a solid foundation also includes supporting staff and faculty at both institutions in developing a skillset to ensure smooth transition between institutions.&nbsp; Institutions must convey a clear articulation of academic requirements for degree completion and a validation of coursework at the originating institution. Additionally, institutions on either end of the transfer process can benefit by engaging STEM staff and faculty in opportunities to grow their understanding of and skills in effectively teaching and supporting Indigenous learners. This includes having an awareness of resources to support the holistic, intersectional identity development of Indigenous STEM students.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Partners from both non-tribal and tribal institutions recommended formalizing relationships to ensure sustainability of support. Engaging in conversations can only go so far - outlining a university&rsquo;s commitment to engage in future conversations and work toward a common goal of supporting Indigenous STEM transfer students is necessary. These formalized partnerships commit each party to roles and responsibilities that span positions and offices with high staff turnover or an organizational shift in priorities. Exemplary formalized partnerships can be found at the University of Arizona and the Alaska Native Science and Engineering Program (ANSEP).</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>While the following recommendations support Indigenous STEM transfer students, one will note that these mirror programs or services traditionally offered to incoming first-year students. In essence, there may be opportunities to expand the scope of existing supports to encourage academic success and persistence in Indigenous communities. For example, a summer institute, bridge program and/or orientation program providing Indigenous students with identity-affirming experiences can help transfer students to navigate their new environment and improve their sense of belonging on campus while promoting persistence and academic achievement. These programs also encourage a deeper understanding of reciprocal relationships through involving local tribal college partners, families, and community stakeholders as appropriate. </span></p> <div><span><br /></span></div> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/31/2023<br>      Modified by: Kathy&nbsp;Deerinwater</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   Through a combination of surveys and virtual talking circles with faculty and staff who work with Indigenous students, four-year institutions establishing meaningful and reciprocal relationships with local TCUs and community colleges was an overarching common theme. Other notable themes arose that have been key in creating reciprocal relationships with local tribal nations and TCUs were: 1) articulation agreements; 2) sustainable and need-based infrastructure; 3) concurrent enrollment; 4) clarity around transferability of courses; 5) transfer academic guarantees; 6) co-curricular programming geared toward Indigenous students transferring from TCUs; 7) and the institutionalization of building tribal relationships from the administrative level.    As for the TCU perspective, they wanted to be included from the beginning. Four-year faculty should be sharing research with TCUs and providing experiential learning opportunities. Research and teaching faculty should reach out to tribal partners and determine how best to work with Native students. This should be done initially and not as an afterthought for broadening impacts.   Recently developed in work with its local tribal colleges and four-year public institutions, the Arizona Tri-Universities for Indian Education initiative is a great model. The Fort McDowell Yavapai Nation asked the presidents of Arizona State University, Northern Arizona University, and the University of Arizona to designate a representative to meet regularly to discuss challenges and opportunities in promoting student success for Indigenous students. This helped to form this collaborative initiative with eight local two-year colleges, with four of them being TCUs.   Furthermore, we identified five major themes woven throughout participant surveys and conversations: 1) Difficult or rigorous course load compared to experience at two-year colleges; 2) College affordability and lack of financial support; 3) Familial environment at TCUs important to emulate at four-year institutions; 4) Non-linear pathways for Indigenous students; and 5) Mentors have a major impact on Indigenous student success. Recommendations as a result of these themes will be described in further detail below.   RECOMMENDATIONS: At the heart of the recommendations is a simple statement: eradicate barriers to access and success at the systemic level while providing resources to individuals that promote the transculturation process at each level of higher education.   Stakeholders identified building a sustainable and needs-based infrastructure that acknowledges the political nature of Indigenous communities and demonstrates an understanding of the historical injustices suffered by Indigenous communities due to federal policies on education. In action, this means bringing tribal college partners to the table at the planning stages of partnerships, rather than in the implementation phase. A recent example of leadership in affirming tribal sovereignty in higher education is The University of Minnesota’s Towards Recognition and University-Tribal Healing Project. This project serves as a recent example of leadership as tribal partners were included from the inception of the project, the data collected are property of the tribal nations, and the recommendations provided are able to be represented through direct recommendations to both the system’s president and governing board.    Building a solid foundation also includes supporting staff and faculty at both institutions in developing a skillset to ensure smooth transition between institutions.  Institutions must convey a clear articulation of academic requirements for degree completion and a validation of coursework at the originating institution. Additionally, institutions on either end of the transfer process can benefit by engaging STEM staff and faculty in opportunities to grow their understanding of and skills in effectively teaching and supporting Indigenous learners. This includes having an awareness of resources to support the holistic, intersectional identity development of Indigenous STEM students.    Partners from both non-tribal and tribal institutions recommended formalizing relationships to ensure sustainability of support. Engaging in conversations can only go so far - outlining a university’s commitment to engage in future conversations and work toward a common goal of supporting Indigenous STEM transfer students is necessary. These formalized partnerships commit each party to roles and responsibilities that span positions and offices with high staff turnover or an organizational shift in priorities. Exemplary formalized partnerships can be found at the University of Arizona and the Alaska Native Science and Engineering Program (ANSEP).   While the following recommendations support Indigenous STEM transfer students, one will note that these mirror programs or services traditionally offered to incoming first-year students. In essence, there may be opportunities to expand the scope of existing supports to encourage academic success and persistence in Indigenous communities. For example, a summer institute, bridge program and/or orientation program providing Indigenous students with identity-affirming experiences can help transfer students to navigate their new environment and improve their sense of belonging on campus while promoting persistence and academic achievement. These programs also encourage a deeper understanding of reciprocal relationships through involving local tribal college partners, families, and community stakeholders as appropriate.                Last Modified: 07/31/2023       Submitted by: Kathy Deerinwater]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
