<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Enhancing the Process of Network-to-Network Collaboration:  A TDI-Facilitated PI Meeting for the AccelNet Program]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>100000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>100000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName/>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[In complex research environments such as networks of research networks, attention to process can be crucial to ensuring steady progress toward project objectives. The Toolbox Dialogue Initiative (TDI) will organize and deliver a meeting in Washington DC for newly funded members of international network-to-network collaborations, providing an early, focused opportunity to develop key components of their projects. TDI will stay engaged with awardees after the meeting to help facilitate the development of ideas generated through team reflection and social learning. One outcome of the meeting will be the fostering of a community of practice. The meeting will also expand abilities to enhance complex research communication and collaboration among broadly distributed network communities.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This workshop is to provide newly funded project members the opportunity to engage in activities designed to increase their collaborative and communicative capacity, learn from one another and members of the prior cohort, hear from experts, and interact with NSF officials. Workshop participants will represent the second cohort of funded projects in the Accelerating Research through International Network-to-Network Collaboration (AccelNet) program. Building on the previous AccelNet project meeting, the workshop will include structured team reflection and social learning on planning for network coordination, professional development, and evaluation. The TDI team will produce reports for the participating teams and follow-up webinars designed to support the development of the teams’ plans and a community of practice involving members of the cohort.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/14/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/29/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.079</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2040027</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Edgar</FirstName>
<LastName>Cardenas</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Edgar Cardenas</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[carden61@msu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000821064</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/14/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Marisa</FirstName>
<LastName>Rinkus</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Marisa Rinkus</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[rinkusma@msu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000572180</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/14/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>O'Rourke</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael R O'Rourke</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[orourk51@msu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000408598</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/14/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Stephanie</FirstName>
<LastName>Vasko</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Stephanie E Vasko</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[vaskoste@msu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000783626</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/14/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate>11/29/2021</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Chet</FirstName>
<LastName>McLeskey</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Chet McLeskey</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mcleskey@msu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000831755</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/14/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Michigan State University</Name>
<CityName>EAST LANSING</CityName>
<ZipCode>488242600</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5173555040</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>426 AUDITORIUM RD RM 2</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>R28EKN92ZTZ9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MICHIGAN STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>VJKZC4D1JN36</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Michigan State University]]></Name>
<CityName>East Lansing</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>488242600</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[426 Auditorium Road, Room 2, Han]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>069Y</Code>
<Text>AccelNet - Accelerating Resear</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~100000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>The &ldquo;Enhancing the Process of Network-to-Network Collaboration: A TDI-Facilitated PI Meeting for the AccelNet Program&rdquo; project (hereafter, &ldquo;the project&rdquo;) was designed to support the NSF Accelerating Research through International Network-to-Network Collaborations (AccelNet) Program. Directed by the Toolbox Dialogue Initiative (TDI) Center of Michigan State University, the project built on work conducted with the first cohort of AccelNet awardees while enhancing the ability of the teams in both the first and second cohorts to build and sustain international networks of networks.</span></p> <p><span>TDI Center developed a 3-phase program for this project that included (1) virtual Toolbox workshops for each team, (2) a 2-day virtual awardee meeting, and (3) a webinar series. In combination, these three elements contributed to the creation and maintenance of an online community of practice, facilitating relationship building, knowledge and resource sharing, and better understanding of communication and collaboration processes.</span></p> <p><span>Phase 1 of the program involved a&nbsp;&ldquo;Toolbox workshop&rdquo; facilitated by the TDI Center that used philosophically structured dialogue to enable collaborators to articulate and coordinate the often implicit and unacknowledged core beliefs and values they have as researchers (O&rsquo;Rourke &amp; Crowley 2013; Hubbs et al. 2020). The goal of the AccelNet Toolbox workshops was to give participating collaborators a chance to reflect on and build mutual understanding about issues of communication, collaboration, and success within their international network of networks.</span></p> <p><span>Phase 2 involved a 2-day virtual meeting that brought together collaborators from the 2019 and 2020 awarded project teams. This meeting was designed to help awardees learn about the other awarded projects, hear presentations by guest experts, and share knowledge and resources with each other.</span></p> <p><span>The webinar series, Phase 3, featured a series of presentations by guest experts on topics generated from members of the awarded projects, such as policies and procedures for teams and networks, data sharing, international perspectives on building collaborations, and equity-based mentorship. The series provided continued support to the community of practice through networking and the sharing of knowledge and resources.</span></p> <p><span>In support of fostering a community of practice within and across the AccelNet cohorts, a Slack channel was created as a communication tool for project members to exchange information and expand their professional networks. Multiple channels were created by participants to facilitate discussion, resource sharing, and information exchange around specific themes. In addition, the communication platform served as a site for announcements regarding the annual meeting and webinar series by the TDI Center.</span></p> <p><span>The project advanced scientific knowledge by providing the newly funded networks with a focused opportunity dedicated to developing the process aspects of building and sustaining international networks of networks. In addition, the project provided structured opportunities learning from experts and among the funded teams. The project also enabled TDI Center to refine the Toolbox dialogue method for distributed network communities.</span></p> <p><span>The project indirectly contributes to the broader impacts of the AccelNet program by supporting the awarded projects teams. Additionally, in working with multiple network of networks teams, the TDI Center has expanded the global network of cross-disciplinary efforts it supports. This has extended the Toolbox dialogue approach and strengthened the ability of TDI Center to contribute to international transdisciplinary efforts, while providing professional development for TDI Center personnel.</span></p> <p><span>&nbsp;</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/22/2022<br>      Modified by: Marisa&nbsp;Rinkus</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The "Enhancing the Process of Network-to-Network Collaboration: A TDI-Facilitated PI Meeting for the AccelNet Program" project (hereafter, "the project") was designed to support the NSF Accelerating Research through International Network-to-Network Collaborations (AccelNet) Program. Directed by the Toolbox Dialogue Initiative (TDI) Center of Michigan State University, the project built on work conducted with the first cohort of AccelNet awardees while enhancing the ability of the teams in both the first and second cohorts to build and sustain international networks of networks.  TDI Center developed a 3-phase program for this project that included (1) virtual Toolbox workshops for each team, (2) a 2-day virtual awardee meeting, and (3) a webinar series. In combination, these three elements contributed to the creation and maintenance of an online community of practice, facilitating relationship building, knowledge and resource sharing, and better understanding of communication and collaboration processes.  Phase 1 of the program involved a "Toolbox workshop" facilitated by the TDI Center that used philosophically structured dialogue to enable collaborators to articulate and coordinate the often implicit and unacknowledged core beliefs and values they have as researchers (O’Rourke &amp; Crowley 2013; Hubbs et al. 2020). The goal of the AccelNet Toolbox workshops was to give participating collaborators a chance to reflect on and build mutual understanding about issues of communication, collaboration, and success within their international network of networks.  Phase 2 involved a 2-day virtual meeting that brought together collaborators from the 2019 and 2020 awarded project teams. This meeting was designed to help awardees learn about the other awarded projects, hear presentations by guest experts, and share knowledge and resources with each other.  The webinar series, Phase 3, featured a series of presentations by guest experts on topics generated from members of the awarded projects, such as policies and procedures for teams and networks, data sharing, international perspectives on building collaborations, and equity-based mentorship. The series provided continued support to the community of practice through networking and the sharing of knowledge and resources.  In support of fostering a community of practice within and across the AccelNet cohorts, a Slack channel was created as a communication tool for project members to exchange information and expand their professional networks. Multiple channels were created by participants to facilitate discussion, resource sharing, and information exchange around specific themes. In addition, the communication platform served as a site for announcements regarding the annual meeting and webinar series by the TDI Center.  The project advanced scientific knowledge by providing the newly funded networks with a focused opportunity dedicated to developing the process aspects of building and sustaining international networks of networks. In addition, the project provided structured opportunities learning from experts and among the funded teams. The project also enabled TDI Center to refine the Toolbox dialogue method for distributed network communities.  The project indirectly contributes to the broader impacts of the AccelNet program by supporting the awarded projects teams. Additionally, in working with multiple network of networks teams, the TDI Center has expanded the global network of cross-disciplinary efforts it supports. This has extended the Toolbox dialogue approach and strengthened the ability of TDI Center to contribute to international transdisciplinary efforts, while providing professional development for TDI Center personnel.             Last Modified: 12/22/2022       Submitted by: Marisa Rinkus]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
