<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[NSF INCLUDES Planning Grant: Developing and Strengthening Partnerships to Better Support Women of Color in the Engineering Workforce]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>100000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>100000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div. of Equity for Excellence in STEM</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jesus Soriano Molla</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jsoriano@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927795</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This NSF INCLUDES planning grant is funded by NSF Inclusion across the Nation of Communities of Learners of Underrepresented Discoverers in Engineering and Science (NSF INCLUDES), a comprehensive national initiative to enhance U.S. leadership in discoveries and innovations by focusing on diversity, inclusion and broadening participation in STEM at scale. The goals of this planning grant are to: 1) establish the Women of Color in Engineering Collaborative (WCEC), a partnership network of professional engineering associations and STEM-based companies dedicated to addressing systemic barriers that prohibit equitable work environments for women engineers of color; 2) create a shared vision focused on dismantling systemic barriers that impede the retention and advancement of women engineers of color; and 3) develop a strategic plan to guide WCEC activities. Reaching parity in engineering cannot be accomplished by approaches that solely focus on the recruitment or “fixing” of underrepresented groups; rather, efforts that connect and energize people, cross divides, and drive systemic change toward equity are needed. To date, many NSF INCLUDES projects have focused on the recruitment and retention of students into STEM education programs, but the WCEC will focus on the often cited, yet understudied, challenge of retaining women in the engineering workforce. Through the WCEC, partner organizations will better leverage their resources to promote systemic change while working collectively to decrease the barriers that lead to the attrition of women engineers of color.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;To reach the goals stated above, this project includes two convenings and monthly workgroup meetings. The first two-day virtual convening will include representatives from thirty organizations, including professional engineering associations and STEM-based companies. Participants will develop a shared vision, identify barriers that exist in the workplace for women engineers of color, and determine which of these barriers the WCEC is best positioned to address. Workgroups will be established around specific supports aimed at addressing those barriers. Over the course of the next six months, WCEC partners will work within their workgroups to develop a strategy to facilitate collaborative activities for their specific support. A second virtual convening will be held to consolidate the workgroup strategies and develop an integrated strategic plan to support the continuation of WCEC activities. The WCEC will develop a final report that includes the integrated strategic plan that includes a Shared Vision statement, a detailed master list of resources to support women of color in the engineering workforce, potential collaborative activities, and an outlined infrastructure to facilitate these activities moving forward. We aim to create an engaged stakeholder community and develop a Shared Vision and Partnerships to support a collaborative infrastructure that encourages an alignment of efforts, removal of resource barriers, reduction of duplication, increased leveraging of resources, and greater reach to women engineers of color in the workforce. The work of the WCEC will add to the STEM equity knowledge base, with outcomes shared through the NSF INCLUDES National Network.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/30/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/20/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2040634</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dora</FirstName>
<LastName>Renaud</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Dora L Renaud</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[dorar@shpe.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000762932</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/30/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Roberta</FirstName>
<LastName>Rincon</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Roberta Rincon</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[Roberta.Rincon@swe.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000726863</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/30/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rochelle</FirstName>
<LastName>Williams</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Rochelle Williams</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[rwilliams@nsbe.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000729870</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/30/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Society of Women Engineers</Name>
<CityName>CHICAGO</CityName>
<ZipCode>606016314</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3125965223</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>130 E RANDOLPH STREET 3500</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>G389SLC891D3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SOCIETY OF WOMEN ENGINEERS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Society of Women Engineers]]></Name>
<CityName>CHICAGO</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>606016314</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[130 E RANDOLPH Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>032Y</Code>
<Text>Eddie Bernice Johnson INCLUDES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0421</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~100000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-bebba07e-7fff-bd5e-ebf8-ada292106033"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>This planning grant supported the development of the Women of Color in Engineering Collaborative (WCEC), a network of organizations committed to diversity, equity, and inclusion in the engineering profession. Recognizing that there is a particular lack of cohesive support for women of color in the engineering workforce, the WCEC brought together organizations that offer various programs and services to support increasing diversity and inclusion in engineering.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Led by the National Society of Black Engineers (NSBE), the Society of Hispanic Professional Engineers (SHPE), and the Society of Women Engineers (SWE), the WCEC successfully launched with 29 partner organizations. Through multiple convenings, workgroup meetings, and webinars, the WCEC developed a shared vision statement, a mission statement, defined the population of interest (women of color), identified five barriers that the collaborative was best positioned to address over the next four years, and developed goals and strategies to tackle each of the barriers. The outcomes of this work are included in the WCEC strategic plan.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>To help engage new and existing members in the collaborative and connect with individuals interested in the WCEC, the WCEC has a website that provides information and links to partner organizations and explains the goals and strategies included in the WCEC strategic plan. The website will house resources and reports shared by WCEC partner organizations as the collaborative begins implementing its strategic plan.</span></p> <p>Intellectual Merit:&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Outcomes of the planning grant include: (1) the establishment of a coalition of professional STEM associations and STEM-based companies dedicated to addressing systemic barriers that prohibit equitable work environments for women of color; (2) two convenings to create a shared vision; and (3) the development of a strategic plan to guide the collaborative?s activities.</span></p> <p>Broadening Participation:</p> <p><span>The WCEC partner organizations have begun generating a list of resources that will be offered to support women of color in the workplace and organizations interested in better supporting diverse engineering talent. These resources will be available on the WCEC website (</span><a href="https://www.womenofcolorengineers.org/"><span>https://www.womenofcolorengineers.org/</span></a><span>), once compiled. The WCEC partner organizations have a broad reach into the engineering workforce and can provide a coordinated ecosystem to address the systemic barriers that often impede women?s full participation and advancement in the workplace. Working together, these organizations have the potential to touch the lives of every woman engineer of color in higher education and the public and private sectors.</span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/03/2022<br>      Modified by: Roberta&nbsp;Rincon</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   This planning grant supported the development of the Women of Color in Engineering Collaborative (WCEC), a network of organizations committed to diversity, equity, and inclusion in the engineering profession. Recognizing that there is a particular lack of cohesive support for women of color in the engineering workforce, the WCEC brought together organizations that offer various programs and services to support increasing diversity and inclusion in engineering. Led by the National Society of Black Engineers (NSBE), the Society of Hispanic Professional Engineers (SHPE), and the Society of Women Engineers (SWE), the WCEC successfully launched with 29 partner organizations. Through multiple convenings, workgroup meetings, and webinars, the WCEC developed a shared vision statement, a mission statement, defined the population of interest (women of color), identified five barriers that the collaborative was best positioned to address over the next four years, and developed goals and strategies to tackle each of the barriers. The outcomes of this work are included in the WCEC strategic plan. To help engage new and existing members in the collaborative and connect with individuals interested in the WCEC, the WCEC has a website that provides information and links to partner organizations and explains the goals and strategies included in the WCEC strategic plan. The website will house resources and reports shared by WCEC partner organizations as the collaborative begins implementing its strategic plan.  Intellectual Merit:  Outcomes of the planning grant include: (1) the establishment of a coalition of professional STEM associations and STEM-based companies dedicated to addressing systemic barriers that prohibit equitable work environments for women of color; (2) two convenings to create a shared vision; and (3) the development of a strategic plan to guide the collaborative?s activities.  Broadening Participation:  The WCEC partner organizations have begun generating a list of resources that will be offered to support women of color in the workplace and organizations interested in better supporting diverse engineering talent. These resources will be available on the WCEC website (https://www.womenofcolorengineers.org/), once compiled. The WCEC partner organizations have a broad reach into the engineering workforce and can provide a coordinated ecosystem to address the systemic barriers that often impede women?s full participation and advancement in the workplace. Working together, these organizations have the potential to touch the lives of every woman engineer of color in higher education and the public and private sectors.       Last Modified: 10/03/2022       Submitted by: Roberta Rincon]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
