<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[NSF INCLUDES Planning Grant: Inclusive STEM Workforce Development Program]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>99963.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>99963</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div. of Equity for Excellence in STEM</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Peter Vishton</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[NSF INCLUDES Planning Grant: Inclusive STEM Workforce Development Program&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This NSF INCLUDES planning grant is funded by NSF Inclusion across the Nation of Communities of Learners of Underrepresented Discoverers in Engineering and Science (NSF INCLUDES), a comprehensive national initiative to enhance U.S. leadership in discoveries and innovations by focusing on diversity, inclusion and broadening participation in STEM at scale. The goal of this planning grant is broadening participation in STEM workplaces and increasing the ability of employers to hire and retain well qualified employees with intellectual and developmental disabilities. The current work will investigate the workplace training and mentoring within the Cincinnati STEM Accessibility Alliance to support the recruitment, selection, and retention of individuals with intellectual and developmental disabilities in the STEM workplace. This project will build upon the collaborative infrastructure previously established by the Cincinnati STEM Accessibility Alliance to develop a leadership and communication plan across a broad network of universities and local and national STEM companies. This network of national partners will collaboratively develop a shared vision to address a significant issue to the field.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This NSF INCLUDES Planning Grant project will enable the collaborative design and development of a workplace support model that will have the potential to shift the traditional job coaching programs that most often place employees with autism in secluded workplace environments, and move STEM industries towards a fully integrated and innovative workforce inclusive of neurodiverse perspectives. Future activities beyond the scope of this current planning grant project have the potential to lead to further evaluation, development, and implementation of workplace training programs across a wide range of STEM-industries and environments.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/02/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/20/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2040870</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sheryl</FirstName>
<LastName>Sorby</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sheryl A Sorby</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[sorbysa@ucmail.uc.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000331918</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/02/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Christina</FirstName>
<LastName>Carnahan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Christina Carnahan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[christi.carnahan@uc.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000722355</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/02/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Christopher</FirstName>
<LastName>Atchison</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Christopher L Atchison</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[christopher.atchison@uc.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000593200</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/02/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Cincinnati Main Campus</Name>
<CityName>CINCINNATI</CityName>
<ZipCode>452202872</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5135564358</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2600 CLIFTON AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OH01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>DZ4YCZ3QSPR5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CINCINNATI</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>DZ4YCZ3QSPR5</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Cincinnati Main Campus]]></Name>
<CityName>Cincinnati</CityName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>452210222</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[University Hall, Suite 530]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OH01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>032Y</Code>
<Text>Eddie Bernice Johnson INCLUDES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0421</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~99963</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-37fea371-7fff-d29f-05bd-7032a9d51b3f"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>As a result of the activities of this INCLUDES Planning Grant, we are continuing to establish a clearer picture of the current STEM opportunities available in postsecondary education programs for young adults with intellectual and developmental disabilities. As such, we have begun developing a national network, including families, STEM instructors, and STEM industry employers, all focused on STEM education for students with disabilities. The strength of this network is the focus on bringing individuals with disabilities themselves into the conversation - even when talking about people with disabilities, they have been historically left out.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>A Theory of Change model has been developed to guide our work (please see attached conceptual map image). Plan, Do, Study, Act (PDSA) cycles will be the foundation of our work to sustain and expand on the Planning Grant outcomes and continued network development. &nbsp; These cycles will serve as the framework for mentoring new network partners and be driven by shared specific, measurable, achievable, relevant and time-bound (SMART) objectives and specific drivers of change.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Additionally, the data collected during this project enabled the development and implementation of inclusive program focused on the application of STEM content and developing individual self regulation skills, which is a cutting edge practice, especially for students with intellectual and developmental disabilities.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>STEM Self-Determination Program Overview</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The program will serve up to 20 adolescents between the ages of 14 and 22 in the first offering, and increase by 50% over the next two years to reach capacity, ultimately serving up to 30 students per year by the end of the third year. The program will be specifically designed for two groups of students: high school students with intellectual and developmental disabilities who have extensive support needs, and students without disabilities who are at risk for school failure.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The program plan is designed to weave together evidence-based STEM curricula (e.g., Developing Spatial Thinking) with an evidence-based model for developing self-determination skills. After completing this curricula, the student will: a) develop spatial visualization skills; b) demonstrate critical thinking skills; and c) demonstrate problem solving skills related to STEM. The Self Determination Learning Model also meets the criteria for evidence-based practice and will be used to develop students' self-determination skills. Specific self-determination skills students will develop include a) goal setting, b) self-monitoring, and c) self-regulation.&nbsp; The specific assessments that will be used include a pre/ post assessment on the STEM curricular material. In addition, a pre/post assessment on self-determination will be utilized. The Self-Determination Inventory: Student Report (SDI:SR) asks students questions about how they feel about their ability to be self-determined; that is to make choices, set and go after goals, and make decisions. The program will ensure the necessary interventions and support are in place in several ways. First, the staffing structure for this program is intentionally designed and includes individuals with expertise in STEM, special education, and micro-credentialling. With direction from the program director, these individuals will provide the content for the instruction each day. Additionally, the program plan involves the use of near peer mentors, or individuals who are somewhat close in age to the individual participants, as the primary staff. The staffing ratios are intentionally high. In addition to the program director and content experts, approximately three near peer mentors will be present each day. The overall staffing ratio is three participants to each team member.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Students will increase skills associated with employment/postsecondary success in an inclusive, community-based program, and develop essential skills that promote post high school employment and education. As a result of participating in this program, students will develop spatial thinking and self determination skills necessary for advancing their careers after high school. Measurement efforts are aligned to these goals/anticipated outcomes. The specific intended outcomes of this program include:&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Students will:</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>&nbsp;</span>- Use visualization, spatial reasoning, and geometric modeling to solve problems.</p> <p dir="ltr">- Demonstrate the self-monitoring and self-regulation skills necessary to successfully complete a university course or work-based learning opportunity that supports progress toward alternate graduation requirements.</p> <p dir="ltr">- Articulate specific, concrete, individualized goals related to a career pathway of interest that includes specific academic (e.g., coursework toward credentials) and work-based learning experiences.</p> <p dir="ltr">- Develop a plan that specifies the actions necessary to achieve the desired goal outcome including steps to monitor their own progress to achieve their individual goals.</p> <p dir="ltr">- Demonstrate skills to evaluate their progress toward the goal and adjust the goal or plan as needed.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/10/2022<br>      Modified by: Christopher&nbsp;L&nbsp;Atchison</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2040870/2040870_10710056_1654729011732_Theoryofchangeconceptmap--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2040870/2040870_10710056_1654729011732_Theoryofchangeconceptmap--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Theory of Change Concept Map"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2040870/2040870_10710056_1654729011732_Theoryofchangeconceptmap--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Theory of Change Concept Map"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Theory of Change Concept Map</div> <div class="imageCredit">Atchison et al., 2022</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Christopher&nbsp;L&nbsp;Atchison</div> <div class="imageTitle">Theory of Change Concept Map</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   As a result of the activities of this INCLUDES Planning Grant, we are continuing to establish a clearer picture of the current STEM opportunities available in postsecondary education programs for young adults with intellectual and developmental disabilities. As such, we have begun developing a national network, including families, STEM instructors, and STEM industry employers, all focused on STEM education for students with disabilities. The strength of this network is the focus on bringing individuals with disabilities themselves into the conversation - even when talking about people with disabilities, they have been historically left out. A Theory of Change model has been developed to guide our work (please see attached conceptual map image). Plan, Do, Study, Act (PDSA) cycles will be the foundation of our work to sustain and expand on the Planning Grant outcomes and continued network development.   These cycles will serve as the framework for mentoring new network partners and be driven by shared specific, measurable, achievable, relevant and time-bound (SMART) objectives and specific drivers of change.  Additionally, the data collected during this project enabled the development and implementation of inclusive program focused on the application of STEM content and developing individual self regulation skills, which is a cutting edge practice, especially for students with intellectual and developmental disabilities.  STEM Self-Determination Program Overview The program will serve up to 20 adolescents between the ages of 14 and 22 in the first offering, and increase by 50% over the next two years to reach capacity, ultimately serving up to 30 students per year by the end of the third year. The program will be specifically designed for two groups of students: high school students with intellectual and developmental disabilities who have extensive support needs, and students without disabilities who are at risk for school failure. The program plan is designed to weave together evidence-based STEM curricula (e.g., Developing Spatial Thinking) with an evidence-based model for developing self-determination skills. After completing this curricula, the student will: a) develop spatial visualization skills; b) demonstrate critical thinking skills; and c) demonstrate problem solving skills related to STEM. The Self Determination Learning Model also meets the criteria for evidence-based practice and will be used to develop students' self-determination skills. Specific self-determination skills students will develop include a) goal setting, b) self-monitoring, and c) self-regulation.  The specific assessments that will be used include a pre/ post assessment on the STEM curricular material. In addition, a pre/post assessment on self-determination will be utilized. The Self-Determination Inventory: Student Report (SDI:SR) asks students questions about how they feel about their ability to be self-determined; that is to make choices, set and go after goals, and make decisions. The program will ensure the necessary interventions and support are in place in several ways. First, the staffing structure for this program is intentionally designed and includes individuals with expertise in STEM, special education, and micro-credentialling. With direction from the program director, these individuals will provide the content for the instruction each day. Additionally, the program plan involves the use of near peer mentors, or individuals who are somewhat close in age to the individual participants, as the primary staff. The staffing ratios are intentionally high. In addition to the program director and content experts, approximately three near peer mentors will be present each day. The overall staffing ratio is three participants to each team member. Students will increase skills associated with employment/postsecondary success in an inclusive, community-based program, and develop essential skills that promote post high school employment and education. As a result of participating in this program, students will develop spatial thinking and self determination skills necessary for advancing their careers after high school. Measurement efforts are aligned to these goals/anticipated outcomes. The specific intended outcomes of this program include:  Students will:  - Use visualization, spatial reasoning, and geometric modeling to solve problems. - Demonstrate the self-monitoring and self-regulation skills necessary to successfully complete a university course or work-based learning opportunity that supports progress toward alternate graduation requirements. - Articulate specific, concrete, individualized goals related to a career pathway of interest that includes specific academic (e.g., coursework toward credentials) and work-based learning experiences. - Develop a plan that specifies the actions necessary to achieve the desired goal outcome including steps to monitor their own progress to achieve their individual goals. - Demonstrate skills to evaluate their progress toward the goal and adjust the goal or plan as needed.             Last Modified: 06/10/2022       Submitted by: Christopher L Atchison]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
