<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Eco-epidemiological, population, and community ecology implications of RHDV2 emergence in New World lagomorphs (rabbits and close relatives)]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>199940.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>199940</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jeremy Wojdak</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jwojdak@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928781</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Beginning in early 2020, populations of multiple species of wild rabbits in the southwestern US have had mass mortality events due to the introduction of a novel pathogen: rabbit hemorrhagic disease virus 2 (RHDV2). This virus likely arrived in North America via the trade in non-native domestic European rabbits. The virus is spreading rapidly. Less than four months after RHDV2 was identified in dead wild rabbits in southeastern New Mexico and southwestern Texas, it has spread to seven US states and multiple Mexican municipalities, and has affected six rabbit species. The epidemic has also received extensive press coverage, much of it emphasizing how little is understood about impacts of RHDV2, and how changes in rabbit populations might in turn influence plant and animal communities. This work will provide detailed information on how RHDV2 influences rabbit populations and their associated ecosystems, and also information on the potential for rabbits to recover from infection. The study will also allow insights into the extent to which a novel pathogen might influence the abundance of herbivores and their predators, and thus play a significant role in the structure and function of arid-land ecosystems. This information will be provided to partnering state, federal and tribal wildlife and agricultural agencies who are tasked with managing native and domestic rabbits.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will provide insights into whether and how this emerging virus is able to persist in an animal community comprised of multiple host species, and whether it is spreading via a patchwork of smaller outbreaks versus a contiguous viral wave. This research will address these issues by (1) conducting occupancy and abundance surveys of rabbit populations for which pre-outbreak data are available to determine how the populations have changed numerically following RHDV2 exposure, and (2) serological assessments of rabbit populations to understand whether some individuals survive exposure to RHDV2. This information in turn will be used to (3) develop epidemiologic models to understand how the virus may affect rabbit populations, and how it may persist in ecosystems that include multiple rabbit host species. The information will also permit (4) predictions of whether and how RHDV2 is likely to spread in regions where it has yet to occur. Finally, this project will also allow for data collection to (5) understand how RHDV2, and the associated declines in rabbit abundance, may influence the predator community that depends on rabbits for food.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/05/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/05/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2040698</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gary</FirstName>
<LastName>Roemer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gary W Roemer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[groemer@nmsu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000337935</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/05/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Matthew</FirstName>
<LastName>Gompper</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Matthew E Gompper</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[gompperm@nmsu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000180173</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/05/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Todd</FirstName>
<LastName>Esque</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Todd C Esque</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[tesque@usgs.gov]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000308219</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/05/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
<LastName>Walsh</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Daniel P Walsh</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[dwalsh@usgs.gov]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000636324</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/05/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>New Mexico State University</Name>
<CityName>LAS CRUCES</CityName>
<ZipCode>88003</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5756461590</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1050 STEWART ST.</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Mexico</StateName>
<StateCode>NM</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NM02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>J3M5GZAT8N85</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NEW MEXICO STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[NEW MEXICO STATE UNIVERSITY]]></Name>
<CityName>Las Cruces</CityName>
<StateCode>NM</StateCode>
<ZipCode>880031245</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[FWCE, NMSU]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Mexico</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NM02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1128</Code>
<Text>Population &amp; Community Ecology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7242</Code>
<Text>Ecology of Infectious Diseases</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~199940</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Rabbit Hemorrhagic Disease Virus 2 (RHDV2) emerged in the borderland regions of eastern New Mexico and western Texas in early 2020 and has since rapidly spread across much of the southwestern US. Initial exposure resulted in mass mortality events of native cottontail and jackrabbit species. The goals of this project were three-fold: 1) to assess how the emergence of RHDV2 has influenced native leporid (rabbits, including jackrabbits and cottontails) populations; 2) to use laboratory approaches to assess the epidemiology of RHDV2 in these same native rabbit populations; 3) and to parameterize models of host-pathogen transmission and disease spread that will provide an improved understanding of maintenance and expansion of the pathogen.</p> <p>An extensive effort was conducted to survey rabbit populations inhabiting native habitat across southern New Mexico and southern Nevada. In addition, the collection of samples from rabbits was undertaken across this same region to allow for laboratory assessment of exposure. The New Mexico data allowed that assessment of the extent to which population of jackrabbits and cottontails declined following the emergence of RHDV2. Laboratory PCR assessments of samples were conducted on a subset of collected samples to determine the proportion of sampled animals that were actively infected by the virus, and serologic antibody assessments were conducted on all collected samples to examine the likelihood of rabbits being exposed to RHDV2 and recovering. Finally, efforts are underway to build host-pathogen models and landscape-scale models for the spread of RHDV2. For the former, spatially explicit models have been developed for Riparian Brush rabbits to assess the role of vaccination efforts in limiting the spread of RHDV2 within the population. For the later, we are using RHDV2 as a case study to assist with the development of a methodology for modeling pathogen spread with sparse data.&nbsp;</p> <p>Several significant preliminary results have emerged. First, based on surveys collected across southern New Mexico native leporid populations have declined significantly compared to baseline population measures collected prior to the emergence of RHDV2. Second, initial PCR-based assessments for active infection in a subset of sampled black-tailed jackrabbits collected from an area where mortality due to RHDV2 is known to have occurred failed to identify the occurrence of the virus. These RHDV2-negative results suggest that either no exposure has occurred among these particular animals, that exposed animals were not infected, or that these animals were able to overcome infection by clearing their viral load. As such, these results indicate that a serologic (antibody-based) approach is necessary to better discern the extent to which native species respond to RHDV2 exposure. To gain such insights, we screened for the presence of antibodies to RHDV2 in blood samples using a diagnostic assay designed for domestic rabbits. Seroprevalence rates indicate a preliminary value of 3.1% for black-tailed jackrabbits and 2.8% in desert cottontails. Since these tested animals were not diseased, these results indicate that approximately 3% of the surveyed animals have been exposed and recovered. However, the ELISA test being used to assess wild lagomorph antibody values is designed for use on domestic rabbits, and as such, further diagnostic assessment is necessary for conformation of these results.</p> <p>The challenges with modeling RHDV2 include sparse data which is a common issue for emerging diseases. Therefore, we are using RHDV2 as a case study to assist with the development of a methodology for modeling pathogen spread with sparse data. Our preliminary results suggest that increasing shrub cover is related to slower spread of RHDV2. &nbsp;This is possibly because more urban areas/less shrub cover facilitates the spread of RHDV2, or because rabbits may congregate in shrub areas where they have smaller movements which slows the spread of RHDV2.&nbsp; Additional analyses are underway. We are also modeling the response of a rabbit population to vaccination efforts, focusing on the riparian brush rabbit. Our model predicts that connectivity and disease transmission rates among susceptible hosts have the greatest influence on the outcome of a potential vaccination campaign. Our model projects that a 30% vaccination rate will result in an estimated population size that is 34% larger than an unvaccinated population. While this result is dependent on contact rate between individual rabbits, the results suggest vaccination programs are most likely to be successful for small target populations where vaccination rates are relatively high.</p> <p>In a broader impacts framework, this project has provided training opportunities for two graduate students, one post-doctoral associate and four undergraduate technicians who assisted with various aspects of the project. Preliminary findings have been communicated to the New Mexico Department of Game and Fish and the Nevada Department of Wildlife and several presentations have been made to scientific and wildlife management agencies to allow for a better understanding the impacts of RHDV2 on the health of lagomorphs in the southwest.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/21/2022<br>      Modified by: Matthew&nbsp;E&nbsp;Gompper</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Rabbit Hemorrhagic Disease Virus 2 (RHDV2) emerged in the borderland regions of eastern New Mexico and western Texas in early 2020 and has since rapidly spread across much of the southwestern US. Initial exposure resulted in mass mortality events of native cottontail and jackrabbit species. The goals of this project were three-fold: 1) to assess how the emergence of RHDV2 has influenced native leporid (rabbits, including jackrabbits and cottontails) populations; 2) to use laboratory approaches to assess the epidemiology of RHDV2 in these same native rabbit populations; 3) and to parameterize models of host-pathogen transmission and disease spread that will provide an improved understanding of maintenance and expansion of the pathogen.  An extensive effort was conducted to survey rabbit populations inhabiting native habitat across southern New Mexico and southern Nevada. In addition, the collection of samples from rabbits was undertaken across this same region to allow for laboratory assessment of exposure. The New Mexico data allowed that assessment of the extent to which population of jackrabbits and cottontails declined following the emergence of RHDV2. Laboratory PCR assessments of samples were conducted on a subset of collected samples to determine the proportion of sampled animals that were actively infected by the virus, and serologic antibody assessments were conducted on all collected samples to examine the likelihood of rabbits being exposed to RHDV2 and recovering. Finally, efforts are underway to build host-pathogen models and landscape-scale models for the spread of RHDV2. For the former, spatially explicit models have been developed for Riparian Brush rabbits to assess the role of vaccination efforts in limiting the spread of RHDV2 within the population. For the later, we are using RHDV2 as a case study to assist with the development of a methodology for modeling pathogen spread with sparse data.   Several significant preliminary results have emerged. First, based on surveys collected across southern New Mexico native leporid populations have declined significantly compared to baseline population measures collected prior to the emergence of RHDV2. Second, initial PCR-based assessments for active infection in a subset of sampled black-tailed jackrabbits collected from an area where mortality due to RHDV2 is known to have occurred failed to identify the occurrence of the virus. These RHDV2-negative results suggest that either no exposure has occurred among these particular animals, that exposed animals were not infected, or that these animals were able to overcome infection by clearing their viral load. As such, these results indicate that a serologic (antibody-based) approach is necessary to better discern the extent to which native species respond to RHDV2 exposure. To gain such insights, we screened for the presence of antibodies to RHDV2 in blood samples using a diagnostic assay designed for domestic rabbits. Seroprevalence rates indicate a preliminary value of 3.1% for black-tailed jackrabbits and 2.8% in desert cottontails. Since these tested animals were not diseased, these results indicate that approximately 3% of the surveyed animals have been exposed and recovered. However, the ELISA test being used to assess wild lagomorph antibody values is designed for use on domestic rabbits, and as such, further diagnostic assessment is necessary for conformation of these results.  The challenges with modeling RHDV2 include sparse data which is a common issue for emerging diseases. Therefore, we are using RHDV2 as a case study to assist with the development of a methodology for modeling pathogen spread with sparse data. Our preliminary results suggest that increasing shrub cover is related to slower spread of RHDV2.  This is possibly because more urban areas/less shrub cover facilitates the spread of RHDV2, or because rabbits may congregate in shrub areas where they have smaller movements which slows the spread of RHDV2.  Additional analyses are underway. We are also modeling the response of a rabbit population to vaccination efforts, focusing on the riparian brush rabbit. Our model predicts that connectivity and disease transmission rates among susceptible hosts have the greatest influence on the outcome of a potential vaccination campaign. Our model projects that a 30% vaccination rate will result in an estimated population size that is 34% larger than an unvaccinated population. While this result is dependent on contact rate between individual rabbits, the results suggest vaccination programs are most likely to be successful for small target populations where vaccination rates are relatively high.  In a broader impacts framework, this project has provided training opportunities for two graduate students, one post-doctoral associate and four undergraduate technicians who assisted with various aspects of the project. Preliminary findings have been communicated to the New Mexico Department of Game and Fish and the Nevada Department of Wildlife and several presentations have been made to scientific and wildlife management agencies to allow for a better understanding the impacts of RHDV2 on the health of lagomorphs in the southwest.       Last Modified: 12/21/2022       Submitted by: Matthew E Gompper]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
