<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[I-Corps: Single-domain antibody platform to develop cancer immunotherapies for the treatment of both canine and human cancers]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ruth Shuman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rshuman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922160</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercialization potential of this I-Corps project is the development and translation of a drug discovery platform for the treatment of both canine and human cancers. The proposed technology defines the requirements for harnessing the ability of immune-based cancer therapies to target and eradicate cancer with a drug platform that may be manipulated to create new and powerful therapies. Developing immune-based cancer therapies may result in the production of a number of cost effective and safe treatments that may be easily administered to patients, potentially making a significant commercial impact. The proposed technology is expected to translate the understanding of cancer progression using the dog as an animal model for clinical investigations. This approach would be a first for canine therapies and is expected to impact development of human cancer therapeutics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project is based on the development of a single-domain antibody platform to develop cancer immunotherapies for the treatment of both canine and human cancers. Cancer immunotherapies based on a single-domain antibody platform have yet to be approved for human use and the development of the proposed canine agents may provide valuable insight into the pharmacologic behavior of this type of agent in the appropriate disease setting. In addition, physically combining single-domain antibodies with other cancer treatment agents, may add a novel way immune molecules may be used to fight cancer growth. The proposed technology has the potential to result in tailored cancer therapies for patients of all types. Thus, this advancement of the state-of-the-art has the potential to quickly bring novel, effective products to all cancer-patients, with marked potential for high commercial and societal impact.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/13/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/14/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2040609</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Christopher</FirstName>
<LastName>Cebra</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Christopher Cebra</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[chris.cebra@oregonstate.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000832670</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/13/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Oregon State University</Name>
<CityName>CORVALLIS</CityName>
<ZipCode>973318655</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5417374933</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1500 SW JEFFERSON AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OR04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>MZ4DYXE1SL98</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OREGON STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Oregon State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Corvallis</CityName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<ZipCode>973318507</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1500 Jefferson Way]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OR04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The outcomes of the I-Corps project, ?Single-domain antibody platform to develop cancer immunotherapies for the treatment of both canine and human cancers?, have provided rationale to support the continued development of an innovative therapeutic to treat canine cancer, one that would improve the lives of pets and of owners that rely on companion animals. Every year over 6 million dogs are diagnosed with some form of cancer, but only 20% of them receive treatment. Eighty percent receive no more than palliative care, and current chemotherapies used to treat cancer in dogs reduce quality of life and end up costing more than the owner can afford. In over 100 interviews with veterinary oncologists, veterinarians, dog owners and breeders, strong support was revealed for an effective, safe and affordable canine cancer treatment. Our innovation is a cutting-edge drug design that harnesses the body?s own immune system to attack and kill cancer cells; it should be both safe and affordable. As an added benefit, the successful development of this treatment for dogs may provide valuable safety and efficacy data to speed the development of similar agents to treat cancer in humans. Other outcomes of this project include the continued optimization of the therapeutic prototype needed to initiate clinical testing. Progress was made in addressing the manufacturing and regulatory hurdles between this therapy and the clinic, and strategic partnerships were made to facilitate commercialization. The support from the National Science Foundation has allowed for the continued development of our innovative cancer therapeutic for dogs and, in combination with additional support from businesses, government agencies, and private investors, it is expected to positively impact the lives of dogs and owners who rely on dogs.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/31/2022<br>      Modified by: Christopher&nbsp;Cebra</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The outcomes of the I-Corps project, ?Single-domain antibody platform to develop cancer immunotherapies for the treatment of both canine and human cancers?, have provided rationale to support the continued development of an innovative therapeutic to treat canine cancer, one that would improve the lives of pets and of owners that rely on companion animals. Every year over 6 million dogs are diagnosed with some form of cancer, but only 20% of them receive treatment. Eighty percent receive no more than palliative care, and current chemotherapies used to treat cancer in dogs reduce quality of life and end up costing more than the owner can afford. In over 100 interviews with veterinary oncologists, veterinarians, dog owners and breeders, strong support was revealed for an effective, safe and affordable canine cancer treatment. Our innovation is a cutting-edge drug design that harnesses the body?s own immune system to attack and kill cancer cells; it should be both safe and affordable. As an added benefit, the successful development of this treatment for dogs may provide valuable safety and efficacy data to speed the development of similar agents to treat cancer in humans. Other outcomes of this project include the continued optimization of the therapeutic prototype needed to initiate clinical testing. Progress was made in addressing the manufacturing and regulatory hurdles between this therapy and the clinic, and strategic partnerships were made to facilitate commercialization. The support from the National Science Foundation has allowed for the continued development of our innovative cancer therapeutic for dogs and, in combination with additional support from businesses, government agencies, and private investors, it is expected to positively impact the lives of dogs and owners who rely on dogs.       Last Modified: 05/31/2022       Submitted by: Christopher Cebra]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
