<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[4th International Conference on Epigenetics and Bioengineering (EpiBio)]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>22455.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>22455</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Steven Peretti</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>speretti@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924201</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The 4th International Conference on Epigenetics and Bioengineering (EpiBio), will be held on October 9-11, 2020 on a virtual platform. This conference will bring together biologists, chemists, and engineers to discuss ways in which their disciplines can collaborate to find novel solutions to problems that are limiting the development of epigenetic modeling. EpiBio 2020 will focus on connecting professionals from academia and industry for the purpose of sharing newly uncovered fundamental knowledge in the field, as well as novel technologies that can ultimately be used to create effective, personalized treatments for a variety of diseases.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The EpiBio 2020 conference will focus on discoveries in biochemical systems, as well as emphasize bioengineering and engineering healthcare. The scientific program will address six topics, presented over two days in a single-track format. Sensing Epigenetic Modifications will focus on new advances in sensing of methylation and histone modification. Writing Epigenetic Modifications will focus on writing epigenetic modifications and the relevant toolset. Nuclear Organization will focus on expanding knowledge of epigenetic modifications and developing methods of treating diseases effectively. Single Cell Epigenetics will focus on developments in the study of epigenetics at the single-cell level. Emerging Technologies will focus on technologies such as acetylases, DNA ligases, methyltransferase, RNA ligases, reverse transcriptase, and others that can be used to make experimental epigenetic modifications. Epigenetics in Human Health &amp; Disease will address how epigenetic modifications can lead to disease and how bioengineering tools can be utilized to develop novel therapeutics. Peer-reviewed conference proceedings will be published on the AIChE website, and the International Journal of Molecular Sciences may publish a special issue around the themes of the conference.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/26/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/14/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2040094</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nathaniel</FirstName>
<LastName>Hathaway</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nathaniel Hathaway</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[natehat@email.unc.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000764475</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/26/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Izabela</FirstName>
<LastName>Balicka</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Izabela Balicka</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[izabb@aiche.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000832102</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/26/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>American Institute of Chemical Engineers</Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<ZipCode>100055991</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6464951350</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>120 WALL ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[23 FLO]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>KLPNCLPDAS45</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>AMERICAN INSTITUTE OF CHEMICAL ENGINEERS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[American Institute of Chemical Engineers]]></Name>
<CityName>New York</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>100055991</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[120 Wall Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1491</Code>
<Text>Cellular &amp; Biochem Engineering</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1757</Code>
<Text>Quantitative sys bio and biotech</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~22455</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The body of fundamental knowledge related to epigenetic modifications of proteins and nucleic acids as well as the mechanisms of epigenetic regulation in organisms ranging from microbes to humans is vast and rapidly expanding. Efforts to translate this knowledge into products and processes that benefit society have rapidly followed this explosion in fundamental understanding of molecular biology. These products and processes include new medical diagnostics, new ways to treat disease, and enhanced methods of producing therapeutic compounds, proteins, and other transformative chemical products.</p> <p>The 4th International Conference on Epigenetics and Bioengineering (EpiBio) was held on October 9-11, 2020 on a virtual platform and brought together scientists, engineers and other stakeholders to discuss and share ideas, innovations and achievements for developing novel engineering tools and discussing new research regarding fundamental science. Sessions integrated the recent achievements made by academia, government, and industry to discuss all advancements in the field.</p> <p>The conference featured six technical sessions: (1) Sensing Epigenetic Modifications, (2) Writing Epigenetic Modifications, (3) Nuclear Organization, (4) Single Cell Epigenetics, (5) Emerging Technologies and (6) Epigenetics in Human Health &amp; Disease. Although the conference was hosted on a virtual platform, live Q&amp;A panel discussions allowed attendees to interact with the speakers and the content being presented. The conference also featured many breaks for networking and exchanging ideas regarding the material presented, as well as poster sessions which allowed students to share their work.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/17/2021<br>      Modified by: Izabela&nbsp;Balicka</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The body of fundamental knowledge related to epigenetic modifications of proteins and nucleic acids as well as the mechanisms of epigenetic regulation in organisms ranging from microbes to humans is vast and rapidly expanding. Efforts to translate this knowledge into products and processes that benefit society have rapidly followed this explosion in fundamental understanding of molecular biology. These products and processes include new medical diagnostics, new ways to treat disease, and enhanced methods of producing therapeutic compounds, proteins, and other transformative chemical products.  The 4th International Conference on Epigenetics and Bioengineering (EpiBio) was held on October 9-11, 2020 on a virtual platform and brought together scientists, engineers and other stakeholders to discuss and share ideas, innovations and achievements for developing novel engineering tools and discussing new research regarding fundamental science. Sessions integrated the recent achievements made by academia, government, and industry to discuss all advancements in the field.  The conference featured six technical sessions: (1) Sensing Epigenetic Modifications, (2) Writing Epigenetic Modifications, (3) Nuclear Organization, (4) Single Cell Epigenetics, (5) Emerging Technologies and (6) Epigenetics in Human Health &amp; Disease. Although the conference was hosted on a virtual platform, live Q&amp;A panel discussions allowed attendees to interact with the speakers and the content being presented. The conference also featured many breaks for networking and exchanging ideas regarding the material presented, as well as poster sessions which allowed students to share their work.          Last Modified: 09/17/2021       Submitted by: Izabela Balicka]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
