<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[2021 Germination Investigator Workshop]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>49903.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>49903</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EFMA</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Emerging Frontiers &amp; Multidisciplinary Activities</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Louise R. Howe</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lhowe@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922548</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The EFMA Germination program seeks to promote the development and implementation of novel approaches, platforms, and environments for training academics to formulate societally impactful research questions. This award will provide support for a two-day workshop to be held at the National Science Foundation, which will convene teams funded through the Germination program together with other academic stakeholders (including senior leadership and individual researchers) to share the results obtained in their Germination-funded research. The workshop builds upon prior Germination investigator meetings with the aim of propelling information exchange and furthering community building.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The planned workshop will bring together Germination awardees and other stakeholders to reflect on how their projects have facilitated the formulation of transformative research questions. Primary objectives of the workshop include:&lt;br/&gt;1) Share the outcomes and positive strategies of Germination projects.&lt;br/&gt;2) Compare the strategies taken by different projects.&lt;br/&gt;3) Consider mechanisms and metrics for evaluating outcomes of Germination approaches.&lt;br/&gt;4) Build community and support collaboration among Germination awardees, with a specific emphasis on identifying both knowledge gaps and collaboration opportunities.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Assembling representatives from the Germination projects offers a unique opportunity to synthesize their knowledge of the multifaceted challenges inherent in current higher education and research infrastructures. This workshop will assist in building a community of practitioners committed to designing new learning frameworks, platforms, and/or environments for training academics to formulate research questions with substantive potential for societal impact. Importantly, participants will represent both predominantly white institutions and minority-serving institutions broadening the likely impact of discussions. Successful scaling and implementation of Germination approaches offers significant opportunity for broader impacts through catalysing research directions that address pressing societal challenges and needs.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/14/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/14/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2040539</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Marshall</FirstName>
<LastName>Poole</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Marshall S Poole</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mspoole@uiuc.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000369771</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/14/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>William</FirstName>
<LastName>Barley</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>William Barley</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[barley@illinois.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000716341</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/14/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Joseph</FirstName>
<LastName>Whittaker</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Joseph A Whittaker</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[chiefresearchofficer@jsums.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000759306</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/14/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Moder</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John Moder</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[johnjmoder@icloud.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000102904</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/14/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Algirdas</FirstName>
<LastName>Kuslikis</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Algirdas S Kuslikis</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[akuslikis@aihec.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000329454</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/14/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</Name>
<CityName>URBANA</CityName>
<ZipCode>618013620</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>506 S WRIGHT ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>Y8CWNJRCNN91</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ILLINOIS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Board of Trustees of the University of Illinois]]></Name>
<CityName>Urbana</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>618013620</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[506 S Wright St]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7633</Code>
<Text>EFRI Research Projects</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~49903</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The "Motivating Question"<strong>&nbsp;</strong>from the Dear Colleague letter in November 2015 announcing the Germination project call for proposals was "How can effective learning frameworks, platforms and/or nurturing experiential environments be designed in which early- and mid-career faculty, as well as graduate students and post-doctoral fellows can be stimulated to germinate transformative research ideas and questions to open large opportunities that address important societal needs?" The projects funded under this program represent a variety of approaches to that motivating question. Three previous conferences have taken place to share projects and preliminary results among the participants and build a sense of community among the Germination awardees. Yet, a strong opportunity remains to share and integrate the findings from these projects to broaden their application and impact across a wide community of potential stakeholders.</p> <p>The current conference aimed to take this information exchange and community building a step further. Informed by the individual project experience of the last two, three or four years, a gathering of the PIs of the Germination projects and other potential stakeholders revisited this motivating question to reflect on how our projects have sought to facilitate transformative research ideas. We believed that this focus would enable us to reflect on what we have done, hone our current projects, and help us identify opportunities for connection and extension as we moved forward. The primary objectives of this workshop were:</p> <p>1) Sharing the progress that each project made during the preceding year,</p> <p><br />2) Reflecting on the idea of "germinating transformative research ideas and questions" to articulate the multiple approaches projects taken toward achieving this objective,</p> <p>3) Drawing upon the answers from (2) to devote specific attention to techniques for measuring "success" that would align with each of these approaches,</p> <p><br />4) Engaging in a structured process to move forward as a cohort, with a specific emphasis on identifying gaps in our current knowledge, potential collaborations across projects, and next steps.</p> <ol> </ol> <p>The organizers disseminated a call for participation via email to the members of all grants awarded under the GERMINATION program in EFMA, to members of the NSF, and collaborators of ongoing and newly funded GERMINATION projects. The proposed date of the conference was January&nbsp; 7-8, 2021 for an in-person format at the National Science Foundation in Alexandria, Virginia. If an in-person conference is not possible because of COVID-19 restrictions, the conference would take a virtual format.</p> <p>Given the state of the COVID-19 pandemic in Fall 2020, the workshop organizers coordinated with NSF program officers to pivot toward an online workshop format. Upon making this decision, the organizers redesigned the workshop programming to remain as consistent with the original design as possible. Asynchronous activities for the workshop began with a virtual pre-conference starting on January 4th, 2020. Synchronous events occured as planned on January 7-8, 2021. In total, 42 participants registered for the conference and 40 of these individuals engaged in the conference activities. The virtual conference also included interactions with two invited guest speakers: Dr. Beronda Montgomery (<em>MSU Foundation Professor,&nbsp;<br /></em><em>Departments of Biochemistry &amp; Molecular Biology and Microbiology &amp; Molecular Genetics,&nbsp;</em><em>Michigan State University</em>) and Dr. Jonathan Kramer (<em>Director for Interdisciplinary Science,&nbsp;</em><em>National Socio-environmental Synthesis Center</em>)</p> <p>The workshop consisted of asynchronous activities punctuated by four synchronous sessions. asynchronous activities commenced with a virtual preconference where participants acquainted themselves by watching and commenting on virtual presentations of each team's work. The asynchronous portion of pre-conference by January 4th, 2021.&nbsp;Registered participants accessed these events via a password protected Moodle (a repurposed electronic course management platform that enabled multimodal interactivity such as viewing pre-recorded presentations and asynchronous commenting/discussion within the community).&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/28/2021<br>      Modified by: William&nbsp;Barley</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The "Motivating Question" from the Dear Colleague letter in November 2015 announcing the Germination project call for proposals was "How can effective learning frameworks, platforms and/or nurturing experiential environments be designed in which early- and mid-career faculty, as well as graduate students and post-doctoral fellows can be stimulated to germinate transformative research ideas and questions to open large opportunities that address important societal needs?" The projects funded under this program represent a variety of approaches to that motivating question. Three previous conferences have taken place to share projects and preliminary results among the participants and build a sense of community among the Germination awardees. Yet, a strong opportunity remains to share and integrate the findings from these projects to broaden their application and impact across a wide community of potential stakeholders.  The current conference aimed to take this information exchange and community building a step further. Informed by the individual project experience of the last two, three or four years, a gathering of the PIs of the Germination projects and other potential stakeholders revisited this motivating question to reflect on how our projects have sought to facilitate transformative research ideas. We believed that this focus would enable us to reflect on what we have done, hone our current projects, and help us identify opportunities for connection and extension as we moved forward. The primary objectives of this workshop were:  1) Sharing the progress that each project made during the preceding year,   2) Reflecting on the idea of "germinating transformative research ideas and questions" to articulate the multiple approaches projects taken toward achieving this objective,  3) Drawing upon the answers from (2) to devote specific attention to techniques for measuring "success" that would align with each of these approaches,   4) Engaging in a structured process to move forward as a cohort, with a specific emphasis on identifying gaps in our current knowledge, potential collaborations across projects, and next steps.    The organizers disseminated a call for participation via email to the members of all grants awarded under the GERMINATION program in EFMA, to members of the NSF, and collaborators of ongoing and newly funded GERMINATION projects. The proposed date of the conference was January  7-8, 2021 for an in-person format at the National Science Foundation in Alexandria, Virginia. If an in-person conference is not possible because of COVID-19 restrictions, the conference would take a virtual format.  Given the state of the COVID-19 pandemic in Fall 2020, the workshop organizers coordinated with NSF program officers to pivot toward an online workshop format. Upon making this decision, the organizers redesigned the workshop programming to remain as consistent with the original design as possible. Asynchronous activities for the workshop began with a virtual pre-conference starting on January 4th, 2020. Synchronous events occured as planned on January 7-8, 2021. In total, 42 participants registered for the conference and 40 of these individuals engaged in the conference activities. The virtual conference also included interactions with two invited guest speakers: Dr. Beronda Montgomery (MSU Foundation Professor,  Departments of Biochemistry &amp; Molecular Biology and Microbiology &amp; Molecular Genetics, Michigan State University) and Dr. Jonathan Kramer (Director for Interdisciplinary Science, National Socio-environmental Synthesis Center)  The workshop consisted of asynchronous activities punctuated by four synchronous sessions. asynchronous activities commenced with a virtual preconference where participants acquainted themselves by watching and commenting on virtual presentations of each team's work. The asynchronous portion of pre-conference by January 4th, 2021. Registered participants accessed these events via a password protected Moodle (a repurposed electronic course management platform that enabled multimodal interactivity such as viewing pre-recorded presentations and asynchronous commenting/discussion within the community).           Last Modified: 12/28/2021       Submitted by: William Barley]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
