<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[NSF Student Participation Grant for 2020 IEEE International Conference on Green and Sustainable Computing (IEEE IGSC)]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>10000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>10000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Marilyn McClure</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mmcclure@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925197</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This proposal is for support of participation in the 2020 International Green and Sustainable Computing Conference (IGSC). Due to the COVID pandemic, this year's conference is virtual.  There will be no travel but the award allows for expanded participation.  IGSC has established itself as the premier conference in this area. Green computing is a newly evolving research area that is establishing itself as an interdisciplinary research area spanning across the fields of computer science and engineering, electrical engineering and other engineering disciplines. Green computing or sustainable computing is the study and practice of using computing resources efficiently, which in turn can impact a spectrum of economic, ecological, and social objectives. Such practices include the implementation of energy-efficient central processing units and peripherals as well as reduced resource consumption. In addition, IGSC covers applications and systems that use computing and information systems to accomplish sustainability in power grid, environment, climate, agriculture, and many other social and economic applications. The conference offers researchers, industry participants, and students the forum for a growing awareness of the study and practice of using computing resources efficiently, which in turn can impact a spectrum of economic, ecological, and social objectives.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The grant encourages students interested in green or sustainable architecture, networks, circuit design, software, and applications, as well as students interested in use of computing for sustainability in other areas, to find useful information on the topics of their choice. It also provides an excellent opportunity for many students nationwide to get familiar with and engage in a new research area of national importance. Students not having a paper in IGSC or otherwise without the resources that allow the opportunity to attend IGSC will be eligible for these funds.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/17/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/14/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2040186</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mahdi</FirstName>
<LastName>Nikdast</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mahdi Nikdast</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mahdi.nikdast@colostate.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000763289</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/17/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Colorado State University</Name>
<CityName>FORT COLLINS</CityName>
<ZipCode>805212807</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9704916355</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>601 S HOWES ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>LT9CXX8L19G1</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>COLORADO STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>Q7VRM266G891</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Colorado State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Fort Collins</CityName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>805232023</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[601 S Howes St]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7354</Code>
<Text>CSR-Computer Systems Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~10000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>&nbsp;The Eleventh International Green and Sustainable Computing Conference (IGSC) [https://www.igscc.org] was held in October 2020 as a Live Virtual Conference. IGSC is technically cosponsored by IEEE and addresses key issues and topics related to energy efficiency in computing as well as computational sustainability. The conference aims to provide a forum to a wide audience for discussing, sharing, and investigating the state-of-the-art for all aspects of green and sustainable computing, ranging from energy-efficient algorithm and software designs to power-aware circuit, architecture, and hardware designs to sustainable large-scale supercomputers, cloud services, and data centers.</p> <p>The conference program included:</p> <ol> <li>Peer-reviewed paper presentations in multiple technical sessions.</li> <li>A Student Research Forum poster-presentation session.</li> <li>Two keynote speeches: Bruno Michel from IBM Research, and Luca Benini from ETH Zurich.</li> <li>Three panel sessions: Towards self-powered embedded computing systems; Software Energy Efficiency: When Academia Meets Industry; and ML for energy-efficient system design.</li> <li>Fours workshops in various areas of sustainable computing: AI at the Edge Workshop; Workshop on Computing with Unconventional Technologies (CUT); The Second International Workshop on Big Data Analytics of Cyber-Physical Systems; and Second Workshop on Energy-Efficient Machine Learning (E2ML).&nbsp;</li> </ol> <p>The NSF student participation funds were used to support <strong>30</strong> students&mdash;with <strong>27%</strong> students from minoritized groups&mdash;from <strong>20</strong> different universities to attend the online conference. The students participated in the Student Research Forum poster session and presented their research work in the areas of sustainable computing and computational sustainability. The students had many opportunities to interact with senior researchers in the green computing area and enjoyed networking occasions with fellow student researchers, all throughout multiple and varied online activities and sessions designed for the Live Virtual IGSC Conference.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/23/2021<br>      Modified by: Mahdi&nbsp;Nikdast</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  The Eleventh International Green and Sustainable Computing Conference (IGSC) [https://www.igscc.org] was held in October 2020 as a Live Virtual Conference. IGSC is technically cosponsored by IEEE and addresses key issues and topics related to energy efficiency in computing as well as computational sustainability. The conference aims to provide a forum to a wide audience for discussing, sharing, and investigating the state-of-the-art for all aspects of green and sustainable computing, ranging from energy-efficient algorithm and software designs to power-aware circuit, architecture, and hardware designs to sustainable large-scale supercomputers, cloud services, and data centers.  The conference program included:  Peer-reviewed paper presentations in multiple technical sessions. A Student Research Forum poster-presentation session. Two keynote speeches: Bruno Michel from IBM Research, and Luca Benini from ETH Zurich. Three panel sessions: Towards self-powered embedded computing systems; Software Energy Efficiency: When Academia Meets Industry; and ML for energy-efficient system design. Fours workshops in various areas of sustainable computing: AI at the Edge Workshop; Workshop on Computing with Unconventional Technologies (CUT); The Second International Workshop on Big Data Analytics of Cyber-Physical Systems; and Second Workshop on Energy-Efficient Machine Learning (E2ML).    The NSF student participation funds were used to support 30 students&mdash;with 27% students from minoritized groups&mdash;from 20 different universities to attend the online conference. The students participated in the Student Research Forum poster session and presented their research work in the areas of sustainable computing and computational sustainability. The students had many opportunities to interact with senior researchers in the green computing area and enjoyed networking occasions with fellow student researchers, all throughout multiple and varied online activities and sessions designed for the Live Virtual IGSC Conference.        Last Modified: 12/23/2021       Submitted by: Mahdi Nikdast]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
