<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[NSF INCLUDES Planning Grant: 331 STEM:Energy 3 Universities, in 3 Cities, 1 Vision]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>97130.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>97130</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div. of Equity for Excellence in STEM</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Christopher Atchison</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>catchiso@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922154</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This NSF INCLUDES planning grant is funded by NSF Inclusion across the Nation of Communities of Learners of Underrepresented Discoverers in Engineering and Science (NSF INCLUDES), a comprehensive national initiative to enhance U.S. leadership in discoveries and innovations by focusing on diversity, inclusion and broadening participation in STEM at scale. The goal of this planning grant is to develop a diverse, community-led, and national network for collective impact, supported by the latest academic thought leadership to prepare young people with valuable STEM education and workforce opportunities in energy by combining the resources of 3 universities and 3 cities to serve 1 singular vision: the 331 STEM:Energy Initiative. Many states and communities seek to increase the diversity of their local clean energy workforce as they pursue goals for decarbonization and clean-energy deployment. Yet, the supporting education systems and human capital "pipelines" are not sufficiently developed to support a diverse clean-energy workforce proportional to the scale of the envisioned energy transition. The initiative will initially focus on three major metro areas with diverse populations that are underrepresented in the growing clean energy workforce: Houston, Detroit, and Minneapolis.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This planning project will build an ecosystem of support for STEM education and workforce development in each of the three sites by connecting local universities, community leaders, schools, and clean energy companies to develop and deliver training and education in a distributed cohort of students who learn in parallel across the three sites. This work is unique in that each local cohort will be paired with a locally-sited community solar project. Community solar represents a growing trend across the US that has the potential to create significant local economic and environmental benefits. Each cohort will be directly working hands-on with a solar project that creates local benefits for the community in which the students live. Participants will develop a greater understanding of how they may become leaders in science, technology, engineering, and math; how their personal choices affect energy use and the environment; and potentially find opportunities for employment in the clean energy workforce. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This work will advance knowledge in several key areas that may broaden participation in STEM and ultimately the clean energy workforce. The nature of the model presents an opportunity to incorporate community-based participatory research as well as STEM education and local workforce development opportunities, intended to help improve the diversity of the clean energy workforce. The initiative will develop a unique, scalable method to evaluate curricular needs and pathways and create a workforce pipeline. Additionally, we will determine appropriate community engagement strategies based on roles, community needs, and project requirements to determine successful program elements between and within unique community contexts.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/02/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/20/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2040979</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dana</FirstName>
<LastName>Harmon</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>G</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Dana G Harmon</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[dana@txenergypoverty.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000771379</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/02/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Texas Energy Poverty Research Institute</Name>
<CityName>AUSTIN</CityName>
<ZipCode>787035106</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5127071009</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1402 W 6TH ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>25</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX25</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>GEXULDZXQMS7</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TEXAS ENERGY POVERTY RESEARCH INSTITUTE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Texas Energy Poverty Research Institute]]></Name>
<CityName>Austin</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>787041736</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[611 South Congress Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>21</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX21</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>032Y</Code>
<Text>Eddie Bernice Johnson INCLUDES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0421</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~97130</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-e19e83e4-7fff-77e3-7cba-799a590bd76f"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>In 2020, the Texas Energy Poverty Research Institute and its research partners received a one-year planning grant to develop the 331 STEM:Energy Initiative. The initiative explored and evaluated local and collaborative educational and job training strategies to diversify the clean energy workforce and address the persistent racial representation gap in the clean energy industry.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><strong>Project Background:&nbsp;</strong></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>There is a growing need for clean energy jobs, specifically for renewable energy generation and energy conservation in the U.S. While clean energy based jobs pay well, and ususally require a range of science, technology, engineering, and mathematics (STEM) knowledge and education. However, the lack of diversity in the mix of informal and formal STEM based education required for the growing clean energy workforce limits the diversity of the workforce across energy fields.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Using mixed methods research involving evaluation of STEM education and clean energy workforce development programs from project partners, review of national best practices, conducting interviews with stakeholders, community surveys of the participating cities to understand barriers related to clean energy education and jobs, and performing program observations; the 331 Initiative identified STEM-based education and training opportunities needed to allow the underrepresented workforce to fully participate in the clean energy industry.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The project partners included three STEM education program providers?the Detroit Area Pre-College Engineering Program, Renewable Energy Partners, and the South Union Community Development Corporation (South Union CDC). It also included three research partners?the University of Michigan, the University of Minnesota, Twin Cities, and the University of Texas at Austin. Three main outcomes were a result of this collaborating planning project.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><strong>Outcomes:&nbsp;</strong></p> <p dir="ltr"><em><strong>Identified Community Needs and Educational/Job Training Resources: </strong></em><span>Survey data of the three participating cities - Houston, the Twin Cities, and Detroit provided valuable insights about potential new program participants. Majority of respondents reported that their children?s schools offer some type of STEM education, however, </span><span>6.06% engaged in after school STEM education programs organized by an outside or third party organization. The survey also identified that </span><span>the majority of respondents (</span><span>80%) were interested in a STEM education program that would focus on clean energy for their children</span><span>.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>From partner interviews the project identified students' improved participation, and understanding of complex STEM concepts as key benefits of developing culturally relevant lessons and a curriculum that includes interactive programming and activities such as virtual reality and gaming. The tactile-based curriculum design was key for students remaining interested in learning about solar energy, energy efficiency, and electric vehicles through other RATC programs.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The interviews also identified that family engagement, especially with older siblings, both on-site and at home creates both additive and intergenerational learning, and that courses taught by Black instructors offer additional security to the students and their families because students could relate to their instructors. Overall, the findings indicate a link between the unique design of the educational and training strategies and improved future earning potential for the program participants.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Lastly, the stakeholder interviews identified that rather than a lack of clean energy jobs, barriers such as transportation, cost, and comfort/safety prevent low-income Black communities from accessing the available clean energy jobs.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><em><strong>Developed Sustainable Partnerships:</strong></em><span> TEPRI and the partners had existing relationships with each other, albeit more siloed to region and industry. For example, TEPRI initially had existing relationships with the University of Minnesota, Twin Cities, University of Texas at Austin, and the South Union CDC. Similarly, relationships existed among the local program providers and local universities.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>To facilitate cross-city relationships, TEPRI convened partners virtually from Summer 2021 through Spring 2022. Meetings included a mix of networking, resource-sharing, and research development activities. By providing this collaborative space, 331 partners shared resources such as curricula suggestions and funding opportunities. The developed cross-city relationships between key players in the energy workforce field led to participation in stakeholder programs, community engagement, and knowledge sharing.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The 331 Initiative also developed sustainable relationships with the local communities and clean energy companies across the three participating cities. The 331 partners observed the matchless value of local leadership to inspire lasting solutions to local community challenges through programs that are engaging, culturally relevant, tied to specific jobs and earning potential, and holistically supportive of not just participants but also their families.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><em><strong>Provided Place-based Recommendations: </strong></em><span>Three main recommendations for program providers and stakeholders to improve clean energy participation and STEM education were developed. First, organizations and funders working towards developing clean energy educational and workforce training programs should defer to local knowledge and prioritize including community representatives, especially leadership in their strategic planning. Second, STEM and clean energy program providers should continue to prioritize engaging, culturally relevant programs that adapt to changing employer needs and technology advances. Finally, program providers should develop more structured systems for tracking and reporting program metrics that can support a data-informed programmatic and organizational strategy.&nbsp;</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/28/2022<br>      Modified by: Dana&nbsp;G&nbsp;Harmon</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   In 2020, the Texas Energy Poverty Research Institute and its research partners received a one-year planning grant to develop the 331 STEM:Energy Initiative. The initiative explored and evaluated local and collaborative educational and job training strategies to diversify the clean energy workforce and address the persistent racial representation gap in the clean energy industry.  Project Background:  There is a growing need for clean energy jobs, specifically for renewable energy generation and energy conservation in the U.S. While clean energy based jobs pay well, and ususally require a range of science, technology, engineering, and mathematics (STEM) knowledge and education. However, the lack of diversity in the mix of informal and formal STEM based education required for the growing clean energy workforce limits the diversity of the workforce across energy fields.  Using mixed methods research involving evaluation of STEM education and clean energy workforce development programs from project partners, review of national best practices, conducting interviews with stakeholders, community surveys of the participating cities to understand barriers related to clean energy education and jobs, and performing program observations; the 331 Initiative identified STEM-based education and training opportunities needed to allow the underrepresented workforce to fully participate in the clean energy industry.  The project partners included three STEM education program providers?the Detroit Area Pre-College Engineering Program, Renewable Energy Partners, and the South Union Community Development Corporation (South Union CDC). It also included three research partners?the University of Michigan, the University of Minnesota, Twin Cities, and the University of Texas at Austin. Three main outcomes were a result of this collaborating planning project.  Outcomes:  Identified Community Needs and Educational/Job Training Resources: Survey data of the three participating cities - Houston, the Twin Cities, and Detroit provided valuable insights about potential new program participants. Majority of respondents reported that their children?s schools offer some type of STEM education, however, 6.06% engaged in after school STEM education programs organized by an outside or third party organization. The survey also identified that the majority of respondents (80%) were interested in a STEM education program that would focus on clean energy for their children.  From partner interviews the project identified students' improved participation, and understanding of complex STEM concepts as key benefits of developing culturally relevant lessons and a curriculum that includes interactive programming and activities such as virtual reality and gaming. The tactile-based curriculum design was key for students remaining interested in learning about solar energy, energy efficiency, and electric vehicles through other RATC programs.  The interviews also identified that family engagement, especially with older siblings, both on-site and at home creates both additive and intergenerational learning, and that courses taught by Black instructors offer additional security to the students and their families because students could relate to their instructors. Overall, the findings indicate a link between the unique design of the educational and training strategies and improved future earning potential for the program participants.  Lastly, the stakeholder interviews identified that rather than a lack of clean energy jobs, barriers such as transportation, cost, and comfort/safety prevent low-income Black communities from accessing the available clean energy jobs.  Developed Sustainable Partnerships: TEPRI and the partners had existing relationships with each other, albeit more siloed to region and industry. For example, TEPRI initially had existing relationships with the University of Minnesota, Twin Cities, University of Texas at Austin, and the South Union CDC. Similarly, relationships existed among the local program providers and local universities.  To facilitate cross-city relationships, TEPRI convened partners virtually from Summer 2021 through Spring 2022. Meetings included a mix of networking, resource-sharing, and research development activities. By providing this collaborative space, 331 partners shared resources such as curricula suggestions and funding opportunities. The developed cross-city relationships between key players in the energy workforce field led to participation in stakeholder programs, community engagement, and knowledge sharing.  The 331 Initiative also developed sustainable relationships with the local communities and clean energy companies across the three participating cities. The 331 partners observed the matchless value of local leadership to inspire lasting solutions to local community challenges through programs that are engaging, culturally relevant, tied to specific jobs and earning potential, and holistically supportive of not just participants but also their families.  Provided Place-based Recommendations: Three main recommendations for program providers and stakeholders to improve clean energy participation and STEM education were developed. First, organizations and funders working towards developing clean energy educational and workforce training programs should defer to local knowledge and prioritize including community representatives, especially leadership in their strategic planning. Second, STEM and clean energy program providers should continue to prioritize engaging, culturally relevant programs that adapt to changing employer needs and technology advances. Finally, program providers should develop more structured systems for tracking and reporting program metrics that can support a data-informed programmatic and organizational strategy.              Last Modified: 09/28/2022       Submitted by: Dana G Harmon]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
