<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[2021 CRCNS Principal Investigators Meeting]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>49619.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>49619</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kenneth Whang</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kwhang@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925149</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Computational and quantitative approaches are a longstanding aspect of neuroscience; however, recent advances in the ability to scale up data collection, simulation, and analysis are leading to an even more central role for computational thinking in this field. The goal of this meeting is to foster interaction and collaboration among experimental and computational neuroscientists. The meeting will highlight both the intellectual advances and broader impacts of CRCNS awardees. A workshop will focus on machine learning for large-scale neuroscience.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Principal Investigators and Co-Principal Investigators of grants supported through the NSF-NIH-ANR-BMBF-BSF-NICT-AEI-ISCIII Collaborative Research in Computational Neuroscience (CRCNS) program meet annually to report on projects; to discuss scientific, educational, and program-related issues; and to develop a cohesive investigator community representing many different approaches to computational neuroscience. This 16th meeting of CRCNS investigators brings together a broad spectrum of computational neuroscience researchers supported by the program, and includes plenary lectures, oral and poster presentations, and panel discussions. The meeting and workshop are scheduled for July 8-10, 2021 and will be hosted by New York University.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/02/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/14/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2040622</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Zhe</FirstName>
<LastName>Chen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Zhe S Chen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[Zhe.Chen@nyulangone.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000627663</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/02/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>New York University Medical Center</Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<ZipCode>100166402</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2122638822</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>550 1ST AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>M5SZJ6VHUHN8</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NEW YORK UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>NX9PXMKW5KW8</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[New York University School of Medicine]]></Name>
<CityName>New York</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>100165802</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[One Park Avenue, Rm 8-226]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7327</Code>
<Text>CRCNS-Computation Neuroscience</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7327</Code>
<Text>CRCNS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8089</Code>
<Text>Understanding the Brain/Cognitive Scienc</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8091</Code>
<Text>BRAIN Initiative Res Support</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~49619</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><a name="OLE_LINK18"></a><a name="OLE_LINK17"><span>Funds are requested to support the 2021 CRCNS Principal Investigator meeting, which was held in Manhattan, New York City, on October 7-9, 2021. The meeting will bring together PIs from grants funded under the Collaborative Research in Computational Neuroscience (CRCNS) program to discuss research progress and the future directions of the field.</span></a><span> The goal of this meeting is to foster interaction and collaboration between experimental and computational neuroscientists.&nbsp;<span>All current or previously funded CRCNS grants&rsquo; PIs were invited to present their work at the meeting, and so all areas of computational neuroscience as represented by the funded projects of the CRCNS program will be covered at this meeting. The main meeting was two full days (Oct. 7-8), followed by one-day workshop &ldquo;<em>Machine Learning for Large-scale Neuroscience</em>&rdquo; held in the Flatiron Institute/ Simons Foundation.</span></span></p> <p>Overall, the CRCNS PI meeting was a great success, given the logistics/travel difficulties for PIs across the country and the world. First, many PIs expressed a gratitude to me personally for organizing a hybrid meeting/workshop that allowed in-person interactions, which deemed important for the computational neuroscience community. Second, for the workshop we have provided free registration to a large computational neuroscience community in the NY metropolitan area (NYU/Columbia/Mt. Sinai/Flatiron Institute, etc), and many postdoc or graduate students trainees were able to benefit from this event. Both meeting/workshop Zoom videos have been shared with the registered participants, who are allowed to further share them with their trainees. Finally, the hybrid meeting format also provided a successful template for other event organizers who was planning to organize future meetings. After the meeting, a few participants have reached out to me personally to acquire tips for organizing a hybrid meeting.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/07/2022<br>      Modified by: Zhe&nbsp;S&nbsp;Chen</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Funds are requested to support the 2021 CRCNS Principal Investigator meeting, which was held in Manhattan, New York City, on October 7-9, 2021. The meeting will bring together PIs from grants funded under the Collaborative Research in Computational Neuroscience (CRCNS) program to discuss research progress and the future directions of the field. The goal of this meeting is to foster interaction and collaboration between experimental and computational neuroscientists. All current or previously funded CRCNS grants’ PIs were invited to present their work at the meeting, and so all areas of computational neuroscience as represented by the funded projects of the CRCNS program will be covered at this meeting. The main meeting was two full days (Oct. 7-8), followed by one-day workshop "Machine Learning for Large-scale Neuroscience" held in the Flatiron Institute/ Simons Foundation.  Overall, the CRCNS PI meeting was a great success, given the logistics/travel difficulties for PIs across the country and the world. First, many PIs expressed a gratitude to me personally for organizing a hybrid meeting/workshop that allowed in-person interactions, which deemed important for the computational neuroscience community. Second, for the workshop we have provided free registration to a large computational neuroscience community in the NY metropolitan area (NYU/Columbia/Mt. Sinai/Flatiron Institute, etc), and many postdoc or graduate students trainees were able to benefit from this event. Both meeting/workshop Zoom videos have been shared with the registered participants, who are allowed to further share them with their trainees. Finally, the hybrid meeting format also provided a successful template for other event organizers who was planning to organize future meetings. After the meeting, a few participants have reached out to me personally to acquire tips for organizing a hybrid meeting.          Last Modified: 02/07/2022       Submitted by: Zhe S Chen]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
