<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Doctoral Consortium at the 2020 International Symposium on Experimental Robotics (ISER 2020)]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>15000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>15000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Juan Wachs</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jwachs@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928714</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This travel award project will provide travel funds for 15-20 US-based students to attend the 2020 International Symposium on Experimental Robotics (ISER) in Malta, Nov 9-12, 2020, and participate in the doctoral consortium. The symposium features both invited and selected research presentations that focus on robotics research that has been validated through experimental results. This unique conference presents the latest advances across various fields of robotics, with ideas that are not only conceived conceptually but also explored experimentally. It has a high visibility in the international robotics research community as well as a high relevance to applications due to its emphasis on experimental validation. ISER 2020 will provide excellent opportunities for students to learn about the latest advances across a wide spectrum of robotics research, development, and applications and to network with seasoned researchers and practitioners in the worldwide robotics community. In the case where the current schedule becomes not practical, the Doctoral Consortium Workshop will be held during the March 2021 period.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/13/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/14/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2040174</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Oussama</FirstName>
<LastName>Khatib</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Oussama Khatib</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[khatib@cs.stanford.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000472345</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/13/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Stanford University</Name>
<CityName>STANFORD</CityName>
<ZipCode>943052004</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6507232300</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>450 JANE STANFORD WAY</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>16</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA16</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>HJD6G4D6TJY5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>THE LELAND STANFORD JUNIOR UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Stanford University]]></Name>
<CityName>Stanford</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>943052004</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>16</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA16</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7495</Code>
<Text>Robust Intelligence</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7495</Code>
<Text>ROBUST INTELLIGENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~15000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p style="text-align: center;"><strong>NSF Doctoral Consortium Outcomes Report</strong></p> <p style="text-align: center;"><strong>Award 2040174</strong></p> <p><em><br /></em></p> <p>The principal purpose of this NSF award was to support doctoral candidates to get together with senior researchers and practitioners in the international robotics community to assess aspects of their studies, pooling and assessing their thoughts -- as a consortium -- on matters such as perspectives on the academic process, the structures of their education, career choices and opportunities in the field, and life-style issues they would encounter as they worked toward graduation and into their careers.</p> <p>Eighteen students across two international symposia prepared, along with senior researchers, a set of topics to address.&nbsp; These students then took leadership of small break-out luncheon discussion groups to engage all symposia participants (including faculty) and collected and organized the various contributions. The discussions covered issues such as perspective on rising technical themes in the field, stress and decision points as students, prospects across academia and industry, the impact of their research on society with possible responsibility concerns in this, and the role and expectations of conferences and symposia such as the one they were attending in both informing and framing their dissertation choices and establishing their connections to the world?s research community.</p> <p>Senior researchers, including faculty, helped guide the luncheon-group questioning and provided a level of guidance on solutions utilizing relevant experience as the discussions progressed.</p> <p>The final afternoon of the symposia provided a slot for the selected students to present their insights and learnings from the discussions and to further engage the group as a whole in reviewing and commenting on the themes presented.</p> <p>The most profound outcome was a collective expression of the value in having and disseminating such discussions. The learnings from such discussions would prepare doctoral students for many of the issues sure to confront them over their studies, and understanding the variety of both challenges and opportunities that lie ahead would better prepare them for dealing with internal and external uncertainties and conflicts that were likely to arise.&nbsp; The personal testimonials of senior members showed there were mechanisms for resolving challenges and indicated means for finding solutions through similarities with the situations covered in the discussions. They could see that their challenges and opportunities were everyone?s challenges and opportunities, and the community was there to help guide them through decision points and provide support along the way.</p> <p>The following testimonial from one of the awardees illustrates the value felt from across the consortium:</p> <p><em>This experience provided me with an interesting history on the format of robotics conferences over the years, inspired me to think more deeply about the consequences of the technology we develop, and begin formulating an important research direction as I complete my PhD and move on to the next phase of my research career.</em></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/18/2023<br>      Modified by: Oussama&nbsp;Khatib</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2040174/2040174_10696941_1681793284802_Consortium(3)--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2040174/2040174_10696941_1681793284802_Consortium(3)--rgov-800width.jpg" title="ISRR2022"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2040174/2040174_10696941_1681793284802_Consortium(3)--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="ISRR2022"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Consortium Awardees and ISRR Symposium Participants in Geneva</div> <div class="imageCredit">A Symposium Volunteer</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Oussama&nbsp;Khatib</div> <div class="imageTitle">ISRR2022</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2040174/2040174_10696941_1681793068506_Consortium(2)--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2040174/2040174_10696941_1681793068506_Consortium(2)--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Summary Presentation"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2040174/2040174_10696941_1681793068506_Consortium(2)--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Summary Presentation"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Presentations of the conclusions of the Consortium at ISRR2022 in Geneva</div> <div class="imageCredit">Oussama Khatib</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Oussama&nbsp;Khatib</div> <div class="imageTitle">Summary Presentation</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2040174/2040174_10696941_1681792693759_Consortium(1)--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2040174/2040174_10696941_1681792693759_Consortium(1)--rgov-800width.jpg" title="ISER Site in Malta"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2040174/2040174_10696941_1681792693759_Consortium(1)--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="ISER Site in Malta"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Attendees and Consortium Awardees at ISER in Malta.</div> <div class="imageCredit">A Symposium Volunteer</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Oussama&nbsp;Khatib</div> <div class="imageTitle">ISER Site in Malta</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[NSF Doctoral Consortium Outcomes Report Award 2040174     The principal purpose of this NSF award was to support doctoral candidates to get together with senior researchers and practitioners in the international robotics community to assess aspects of their studies, pooling and assessing their thoughts -- as a consortium -- on matters such as perspectives on the academic process, the structures of their education, career choices and opportunities in the field, and life-style issues they would encounter as they worked toward graduation and into their careers.  Eighteen students across two international symposia prepared, along with senior researchers, a set of topics to address.  These students then took leadership of small break-out luncheon discussion groups to engage all symposia participants (including faculty) and collected and organized the various contributions. The discussions covered issues such as perspective on rising technical themes in the field, stress and decision points as students, prospects across academia and industry, the impact of their research on society with possible responsibility concerns in this, and the role and expectations of conferences and symposia such as the one they were attending in both informing and framing their dissertation choices and establishing their connections to the world?s research community.  Senior researchers, including faculty, helped guide the luncheon-group questioning and provided a level of guidance on solutions utilizing relevant experience as the discussions progressed.  The final afternoon of the symposia provided a slot for the selected students to present their insights and learnings from the discussions and to further engage the group as a whole in reviewing and commenting on the themes presented.  The most profound outcome was a collective expression of the value in having and disseminating such discussions. The learnings from such discussions would prepare doctoral students for many of the issues sure to confront them over their studies, and understanding the variety of both challenges and opportunities that lie ahead would better prepare them for dealing with internal and external uncertainties and conflicts that were likely to arise.  The personal testimonials of senior members showed there were mechanisms for resolving challenges and indicated means for finding solutions through similarities with the situations covered in the discussions. They could see that their challenges and opportunities were everyone?s challenges and opportunities, and the community was there to help guide them through decision points and provide support along the way.  The following testimonial from one of the awardees illustrates the value felt from across the consortium:  This experience provided me with an interesting history on the format of robotics conferences over the years, inspired me to think more deeply about the consequences of the technology we develop, and begin formulating an important research direction as I complete my PhD and move on to the next phase of my research career.          Last Modified: 04/18/2023       Submitted by: Oussama Khatib]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
