<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[NSF INCLUDES Planning Grant: Increasing the Representation of  Minorities in Engineering (IRME)]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>11/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>100000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>100000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div. of Equity for Excellence in STEM</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tori Rhoulac Smith</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tosmith@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922315</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[NSF INCLUDES Planning Grant: Increasing the Representation of Minorities in&lt;br/&gt;Engineering (IRME)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This NSF INCLUDES planning grant is funded by NSF Inclusion across the Nation of Communities of Learners of Underrepresented Discoverers in Engineering and Science (NSF INCLUDES), a comprehensive national initiative to enhance U.S. leadership in discoveries and innovations by focusing on diversity, inclusion and broadening participation in STEM at scale. The goal of this planning grant is to address the urgent need for the development of a diverse and equitable engineering-capable workforce by planning for an alliance of institutions that will broaden the participation and success of Black, Hispanic, and other underrepresented groups in higher education engineering programs. This collective impact effort, led by Morgan State University, builds on an existing partnership that includes Jackson State University, North Carolina Agricultural and Technical State University, and Ziker Research. Propelled by the momentum of a strong backbone organization, GlobalMindED, the IRME project will develop a shared vision for an NSF INCLUDES alliance that will catalyze access to engineering careers and broaden the participation of underrepresented students in engineering; and crystalize partnerships between a consortium of engineering programs at historically Black colleges and universities (HBCUs) and Minority Serving Institutions (MSIs), nonprofit organizations, and industry.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The IRME project will contribute critical knowledge to the field of broadening participation research by engaging in catalytic activities that include: 1) synthesizing trends in broadening participation efforts and best practices in engineering education; 2) producing an evidence-based brief developed through the implementation of an online workshop designed for listening to and capturing the voices and perspectives of students, faculty, administrators, and industry partners seeking to hire engineering graduates; and 3) developing a robust research agenda that will examine the social, political, and academic factors that influence the success of groups historically underrepresented in engineering. Strategies for promoting equity, persistence, and effective practices will be identified and shared with the NSF INCLUDES National Network through the NSF INCLUDES Coordination Hub, as well as at relevant engineering conferences. The IRME project has the potential to bring about systemic change that will broaden participation in engineering by engaging relevant stakeholders in a multi-sector collaboration to increase minority representation in engineering through the development of an NSF INCLUDES Alliance.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/12/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/20/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2040830</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Cindy</FirstName>
<LastName>Ziker</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Cindy S Ziker</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[cindyziker@yahoo.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000679606</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/12/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Steve</FirstName>
<LastName>Efe</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Steve Efe</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[steve.efe@morgan.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000796196</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/16/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Steve</FirstName>
<LastName>Efe</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Steve Efe</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[steve.efe@morgan.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000796196</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/12/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate>12/16/2020</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jumoke</FirstName>
<LastName>Ladeji-Osias</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>O</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jumoke O Ladeji-Osias</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jumoke.ladeji-osias@morgan.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000228512</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/12/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate>12/16/2020</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kamal</FirstName>
<LastName>Ali</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kamal S Ali</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[kamal.ali@jsums.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000246940</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/12/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Morgan State University</Name>
<CityName>BALTIMORE</CityName>
<ZipCode>212510001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4438853200</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1700 E COLD SPRING LN</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MD07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>KULSKCCZJT27</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MORGAN STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>KULSKCCZJT27</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Morgan State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Baltimore</CityName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>212510002</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1700 East Cold Spring Lane]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MD07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>032Y</Code>
<Text>Eddie Bernice Johnson INCLUDES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0421</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~100000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-4f2e4725-7fff-43d2-c1b3-cf893ddbc078"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The IRME Project Overview</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The NSF INCLUDES: Increasing the Representation of Minorities (IRME) in Engineering project team leveraged two design elements of collaborative infrastructure (shared vision and partnerships) to coordinate planning meetings and implement a virtual workshop focused on achieving population parity in engineering. Strategies used to accomplish these tasks included identifying barriers that challenge minority students preparing for engineering careers. while focusing on improving engineering pathways for middle school, high school, undergraduate, and graduate students. The IRME project sought to 1) develop a shared vision and strategic plan for an Alliance or&nbsp; other large-scale network to address a broadening participation challenge at scale, led by minority-serving institutions that will address system-level challenges around minority enrollment in engineering, 2) crystallize partnerships between academia and industry to address this change, and 3) establish a research and implementation agenda that informs the field of broadening participation in engineering while contributing to advancing the goals of the NSF INCLUDES National Network through the Coordination Hub. Project activities aimed at unveiling ?What are clear evidence-based pathways to achieve population parity in engineering fields within and across academia and industry? ? and ?How can barriers to success be diminished for Blacks, Hispanics, women, and other underrepresented groups in engineering?</span><span><br /><br /></span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Intellectual Merit</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The NSF INCLUDES IRME project team conducted a systematic literature review that was used to identify gaps and challenges in engineering education. Results informed the selection of topics, panels, and presentations for a three-day virtual workshop hosted in partnership with GlobalMindED on June 2-4, 2021. As part of this effort, a two-hour virtual pre-workshop orientation was held on June 01, 2021, which brought together 25 engineering students, and 5 facilitators from engineering programs at Historically Black Colleges and Universities (HBCUs) and Tribal Colleges. Students participated in four break-out sessions and provided feedback about overcoming the challenges they faced during their K-12 years, their high school to higher education years, and their freshman to senior years of college in the engineering pathway. Data collection also included responses to a pre-workshop survey and a post-workshop essay about the workshop experience. Findings were synthesized and reported in an evidence-based brief. The workshop included 35 presenters and moderators and informed the development of a roadmap and research agenda for engineering education.</span></p> <div><span><br /></span></div> <p><span id="docs-internal-guid-a1ab87ab-7fff-726d-57e8-53ef83b99479">&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Broader Impacts</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The IRME project positively impacted minority students that participated in student orientation and workshop activities, as evidenced by post-workshop feedback. Videos of IRME Virtual Workshop presentations have been viewed by over a hundred stakeholders and are available to the public:</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>&nbsp;</span><a href="https://globalminded.org/home/nsf-includes-irme-workshop-day-1/"><span>https://globalminded.org/home/nsf-includes-irme-workshop-day-1/</span></a></p> <p dir="ltr"><a href="https://globalminded.org/home/nsf-includes-irme-workshop-day-2/"><span>https://globalminded.org/home/nsf-includes-irme-workshop-day-2/</span></a></p> <p dir="ltr"><a href="https://globalminded.org/home/nsf-includes-irme-workshop-day-3/"><span>https://globalminded.org/home/nsf-includes-irme-workshop-day-3/</span></a></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The IRME PIs provided input to the NSF INCLUDES Coordination Hub throughout the project period, and participated in the INCLUDES Evaluation and Shared Measures Affinity Groups. The team and project partners were able to spotlight the need to promote inclusive mentoring in ways that will support an HBCU pipeline for an diverse and prepared engineering workforce. In early 2022, the IRME Team submitted an NSF proposal to Track 3 of the NSF BPE program entitled, "Minority Mentoring for Advancement and Participation (Minority-MAP) in Engineering Hub" and was successful in being awarded a five year, $800,000 grant. This project is designed to promote inclusive and equitable mentoring practices that support engineering students at historically black colleges and universities (led by Morgan State University, in collaboration with North Carolina Agricultural and Technical State University, Jackson State University and Ziker Research).</span></p> <div><span><br /></span></div> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/15/2023<br>      Modified by: Steve&nbsp;Efe</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   The IRME Project Overview The NSF INCLUDES: Increasing the Representation of Minorities (IRME) in Engineering project team leveraged two design elements of collaborative infrastructure (shared vision and partnerships) to coordinate planning meetings and implement a virtual workshop focused on achieving population parity in engineering. Strategies used to accomplish these tasks included identifying barriers that challenge minority students preparing for engineering careers. while focusing on improving engineering pathways for middle school, high school, undergraduate, and graduate students. The IRME project sought to 1) develop a shared vision and strategic plan for an Alliance or  other large-scale network to address a broadening participation challenge at scale, led by minority-serving institutions that will address system-level challenges around minority enrollment in engineering, 2) crystallize partnerships between academia and industry to address this change, and 3) establish a research and implementation agenda that informs the field of broadening participation in engineering while contributing to advancing the goals of the NSF INCLUDES National Network through the Coordination Hub. Project activities aimed at unveiling ?What are clear evidence-based pathways to achieve population parity in engineering fields within and across academia and industry? ? and ?How can barriers to success be diminished for Blacks, Hispanics, women, and other underrepresented groups in engineering?   Intellectual Merit The NSF INCLUDES IRME project team conducted a systematic literature review that was used to identify gaps and challenges in engineering education. Results informed the selection of topics, panels, and presentations for a three-day virtual workshop hosted in partnership with GlobalMindED on June 2-4, 2021. As part of this effort, a two-hour virtual pre-workshop orientation was held on June 01, 2021, which brought together 25 engineering students, and 5 facilitators from engineering programs at Historically Black Colleges and Universities (HBCUs) and Tribal Colleges. Students participated in four break-out sessions and provided feedback about overcoming the challenges they faced during their K-12 years, their high school to higher education years, and their freshman to senior years of college in the engineering pathway. Data collection also included responses to a pre-workshop survey and a post-workshop essay about the workshop experience. Findings were synthesized and reported in an evidence-based brief. The workshop included 35 presenters and moderators and informed the development of a roadmap and research agenda for engineering education.      Broader Impacts The IRME project positively impacted minority students that participated in student orientation and workshop activities, as evidenced by post-workshop feedback. Videos of IRME Virtual Workshop presentations have been viewed by over a hundred stakeholders and are available to the public:  https://globalminded.org/home/nsf-includes-irme-workshop-day-1/ https://globalminded.org/home/nsf-includes-irme-workshop-day-2/ https://globalminded.org/home/nsf-includes-irme-workshop-day-3/ The IRME PIs provided input to the NSF INCLUDES Coordination Hub throughout the project period, and participated in the INCLUDES Evaluation and Shared Measures Affinity Groups. The team and project partners were able to spotlight the need to promote inclusive mentoring in ways that will support an HBCU pipeline for an diverse and prepared engineering workforce. In early 2022, the IRME Team submitted an NSF proposal to Track 3 of the NSF BPE program entitled, "Minority Mentoring for Advancement and Participation (Minority-MAP) in Engineering Hub" and was successful in being awarded a five year, $800,000 grant. This project is designed to promote inclusive and equitable mentoring practices that support engineering students at historically black colleges and universities (led by Morgan State University, in collaboration with North Carolina Agricultural and Technical State University, Jackson State University and Ziker Research).                  Last Modified: 06/15/2023       Submitted by: Steve Efe]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
