<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[AI and the Future of STEM Learning: Engaging Research and Practitioner Audiences]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>49952.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>49952</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DRL</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Amy Baylor</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>abaylor@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925126</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Advances in artificial intelligence (AI) are rapidly accelerating, both in the United States and abroad. In the context of STEM learning, there is a strong need to engage both investigators and practitioners to create a research agenda that builds from an understanding of the strengths, weaknesses, and challenges presented by AI. Building on two recent invitational convenings in AI and education, the nonprofit Digital Promise will implement three online workshops to engage multiple communities in developing a future-oriented research agenda. The activities will build on recent research results from interdisciplinary conference proceedings (e.g., International Conference on Artificial Intelligence in Education, International Conference of the Learning Sciences).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Specific activities will include three online workshops in STEM application areas, to include the role of AI with respect to: (1) learning and learning environments; (2) teacher learning and work; and (3) assessment. In the first part of each workshop, invited experts will provide an overview of current knowledge, expected advances, and important issues and barriers.  Using a structured interactive tool, attendees will extend and refine the presentation. In the second part of each workshop, attendees will work in breakout groups to envision what must happen in the next 3-5 years to strengthen applications of AI to education. Approximately 60-100 participants will engage synchronously in each online workshop, drawing from Historically Black Colleges and Universities and other Minority Serving Institutions, school networks, and NSF INCLUDES awardees. Outcomes of the workshops will be published rapidly for wide distribution through both formal mechanisms as well as social media.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/16/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/16/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2040753</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jeremy</FirstName>
<LastName>Roschelle</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jeremy Roschelle</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jroschelle@digitalpromise.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000124596</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/16/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Judith</FirstName>
<LastName>Fusco</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Judith Fusco</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jfusco@digitalpromise.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000406772</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/16/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Digital Promise Global</Name>
<CityName>WASHINGTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>200365565</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2024503675</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1001 CONNECTICUT AVE NW STE 935</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>CDX6SVVKJ1Q1</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>DIGITAL PROMISE GLOBAL</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Digital Promise]]></Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>200365561</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>152Y</Code>
<Text>Accelerating Discovery in Ed</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>092Z</Code>
<Text>AI-Supported Learning</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0420</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~49952</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-499f7a0d-7fff-d9d7-feb1-39bc3d587fba"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><strong>Intellectual Merit</strong></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Engaging larger numbers of STEM practitioners is a needed step in planning for the future of learning with emerging technologies such as AI systems.&nbsp;There are many unknowns about the strengths, weaknesses, challenges, and barriers that will be introduced by AI technologies. To begin to engage, STEM education researchers and practitioners who are not specialists in AI applications need to gain:</span></p> <ul> <li>Understanding of emerging strengths and weaknesses of AI;</li> <li>Familiarity with a broader range of possible AI applications in education; and</li> <li>Awareness of issues, challenges, and barriers in need of further investigation.&nbsp;</li> </ul> <p><strong>Activities</strong></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The funded project prepared and conducted three online webinars designed to introduce a wider audience to these issues. The three webinars had 399 attendees and have received nearly 600 additional views since they occurred. The topics of the webinars were: </span></p> <ul> <li>Introducing AI and STEM learning environments,</li> <li>How AI systems can support teachers' work and their learning, and</li> <li>AI and Assessment.</li> </ul> <p dir="ltr"><span>The three webinars were designed to bring together researchers and practitioners to share and learn about the state of the art; pose important questions about the future, including issues of equity; and to consider how practitioners could be more strongly involved in creating and using AI and the Future of STEM Learning in the coming years.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span><span> </span></span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Each webinar was centered around a thought provoking question related to the impact of Artificial Intelligence on three key areas of STEM teaching and learning. The webinars took place in March - April 2021 while many teachers were still in remote learning situations due to COVID-19. The questions posed in the webinars were:&nbsp;</span></p> <ul> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Assessments (3/2/2021)</span><span>: Teachers can sense what their students are "getting" in a classroom, but not so much in remote learning. How might AI systems help teachers understand what students need or can do when they are not with their students all the time?</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Teacher Support (3/23/2021)</span><span>: AI systems could give me insight into my teaching, but will it be safe to share my personal and classroom data?&nbsp;</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Learning Environments (4/21/2021)</span><span>: Will AI technologies make teachers' lives both easier and better, or is that an illusion?</span></p> </li> </ul> <p dir="ltr"><strong>Broader Impacts</strong></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Each webinar was designed to address concerns and questions that teachers have about AI, introduce them to the topic areas above, and present a perspective on AI where equity, data, privacy, and the teacher's role in the classroom are valued.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The webinars included an introduction to the <span id="docs-internal-guid-60388fb6-7fff-ed67-d9b5-a01db6422538"><a href="https://circls.org/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/CIRCLS-AI-Report-Nov2020.pdf"><span>AI Expert Panel Report</span></a></span>&nbsp;and featured 1-3 experts who were part of the expert panel. To promote a conversation between researchers and practitioners, each webinar panel included and highlighted the perspectives of AI-savvy practitioners in an interactive discussion. During and after each webinar, we engaged the audiences to hear their questions, and learn about their reactions. &nbsp;&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>In addition to producing the three webinars, we prepared five curated reading lists and three reflection blogs&nbsp;for dissemination. All materials&nbsp;are available on the <span id="docs-internal-guid-841256a0-7fff-f669-2eb9-fa80fd19793c"><a href="https://circls.org/educatorcircls/educators-artificial-intelligence-and-the-future-of-learning"><span>CIRCLS website</span></a></span>. Additional dissemination was done through Digital Promise channels with two more blog posts (also linked through the CIRCLS website; see above URL).</span></p> <p><span>Other outreach and dissemination about the event and topic included the PI, CoPI, and an educator leading a session on AI and the future of learning for approximately 80-90 participants at the Consortium of School Networking (CoSN) conference. For CoSN, the PI and CoPI participated in an </span><a href="https://edtechmagazine.com/k12/media/video/cosn2021-ai-and-future-learning"><span>interview</span></a><span> to give an overview of topics and discuss the AI and Future of Learning Expert Panel Report; the work was also mentioned in </span><a href="https://districtadministration.com/ideas-use-artificial-intelligence-machine-learning-teaching-education/"><span>a District Administration post</span></a><span>, as well as the </span><span><a href="https://mailchi.mp/hechingerreport.org/future-of-learning-what-role-will-ai-play-as-schools-reopen?e=670e8a2341">Hechinger Report</a>.&nbsp;The recorded webinars, reading lists, and blog posts continue to be available and will inform future work in emerging technologies.</span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/08/2021<br>      Modified by: Judith&nbsp;Fusco</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2040753/2040753_10686206_1636146709306_AI-webinar-grfx_Blog--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2040753/2040753_10686206_1636146709306_AI-webinar-grfx_Blog--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Images relating to people, classrooms, and technology"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2040753/2040753_10686206_1636146709306_AI-webinar-grfx_Blog--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Images relating to people, classrooms, and technology"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">How Does Artificial Intelligence Fit into the Future of Education?</div> <div class="imageCredit">Digital Promise</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Judith&nbsp;Fusco</div> <div class="imageTitle">Images relating to people, classrooms, and technology</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   Intellectual Merit Engaging larger numbers of STEM practitioners is a needed step in planning for the future of learning with emerging technologies such as AI systems. There are many unknowns about the strengths, weaknesses, challenges, and barriers that will be introduced by AI technologies. To begin to engage, STEM education researchers and practitioners who are not specialists in AI applications need to gain:  Understanding of emerging strengths and weaknesses of AI; Familiarity with a broader range of possible AI applications in education; and Awareness of issues, challenges, and barriers in need of further investigation.    Activities The funded project prepared and conducted three online webinars designed to introduce a wider audience to these issues. The three webinars had 399 attendees and have received nearly 600 additional views since they occurred. The topics of the webinars were:   Introducing AI and STEM learning environments, How AI systems can support teachers' work and their learning, and AI and Assessment.  The three webinars were designed to bring together researchers and practitioners to share and learn about the state of the art; pose important questions about the future, including issues of equity; and to consider how practitioners could be more strongly involved in creating and using AI and the Future of STEM Learning in the coming years.   Each webinar was centered around a thought provoking question related to the impact of Artificial Intelligence on three key areas of STEM teaching and learning. The webinars took place in March - April 2021 while many teachers were still in remote learning situations due to COVID-19. The questions posed in the webinars were:    Assessments (3/2/2021): Teachers can sense what their students are "getting" in a classroom, but not so much in remote learning. How might AI systems help teachers understand what students need or can do when they are not with their students all the time?   Teacher Support (3/23/2021): AI systems could give me insight into my teaching, but will it be safe to share my personal and classroom data?    Learning Environments (4/21/2021): Will AI technologies make teachers' lives both easier and better, or is that an illusion?   Broader Impacts Each webinar was designed to address concerns and questions that teachers have about AI, introduce them to the topic areas above, and present a perspective on AI where equity, data, privacy, and the teacher's role in the classroom are valued.  The webinars included an introduction to the AI Expert Panel Report and featured 1-3 experts who were part of the expert panel. To promote a conversation between researchers and practitioners, each webinar panel included and highlighted the perspectives of AI-savvy practitioners in an interactive discussion. During and after each webinar, we engaged the audiences to hear their questions, and learn about their reactions.    In addition to producing the three webinars, we prepared five curated reading lists and three reflection blogs for dissemination. All materials are available on the CIRCLS website. Additional dissemination was done through Digital Promise channels with two more blog posts (also linked through the CIRCLS website; see above URL).  Other outreach and dissemination about the event and topic included the PI, CoPI, and an educator leading a session on AI and the future of learning for approximately 80-90 participants at the Consortium of School Networking (CoSN) conference. For CoSN, the PI and CoPI participated in an interview to give an overview of topics and discuss the AI and Future of Learning Expert Panel Report; the work was also mentioned in a District Administration post, as well as the Hechinger Report. The recorded webinars, reading lists, and blog posts continue to be available and will inform future work in emerging technologies.       Last Modified: 11/08/2021       Submitted by: Judith Fusco]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
