<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[NSF Convergence Accelerator- Track C: QuSTEAM: Convergent Undergraduate Education in Quantum Science, Technology, Engineering, Arts, and Mathematics]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>709707.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>709707</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ITE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Innovation and Technology Ecosystems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Pradeep Fulay</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>pfulay@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922445</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The NSF Convergence Accelerator supports use-inspired, team-based, multidisciplinary efforts that address challenges of national importance and will produce deliverables of value to society in the near future. This project aims to develop an undergraduate curriculum that combines Quantum Information Science, Technology, Engineering, Arts and Mathematics (QuSTEAM) to build a quantum smart workforce. The QuSTEAM curriculum will have a modular format with in-person, online, and hybrid delivery modalities. The modules will provide educational opportunities for a variety of stakeholders including members of the workforce, 2-year institutions, 4-year institutions, and minority-serving institutions. The project will leverage partnerships with industry and national labs to both identify critical skills and modes of thought, and to directly participate in education and pedagogy, ensuring that the curriculum will develop a diverse quantum smart workforce.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The QuSTEAM curriculum will rely on research-based educational best practices to provide a convergent and inclusive curriculum to develop a diverse quantum smart workforce. This curricular structure will be designed from the ground up to address structural barriers that have to date limited the diversity and inclusiveness of STEM training, and will include concurrent training in the societal impact of QIS technologies by incorporating content beyond traditional STEM disciplines. The project will engage with those conducting quantum research as well as STEAM education research to create a multi-tiered curriculum at the major, minor, and certificate level. Deliverables include (1) a schematic of interdisciplinary modules that details how the building blocks of QIS competency can be organized for different educational targets (BS, AD, certificate); (2) a map of steps taken to actively promote equity and inclusivity in the curriculum that will serve as a model for curricular development beyond QuSTEAM; and (3) individual course curricula that demonstrate the implementation of QuSTEAM. This curriculum will provide a framework for quantum information sciences (QIS) education that can be implemented at a national scale to develop a diverse quantum smart workforce.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/22/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/12/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.083</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2040581</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Awschalom</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David D Awschalom</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[awsch@uchicago.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000193504</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/22/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Russell</FirstName>
<LastName>Ceballos</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Russell R Ceballos</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[rceballo@uchicago.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000801736</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/22/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Angela</FirstName>
<LastName>Wilson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>K</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Angela K Wilson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[akwilson@msu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000433411</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/22/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Andrew</FirstName>
<LastName>Heckler</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>F</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Andrew F Heckler</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[heckler.6@osu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000281393</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/22/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ezekiel</FirstName>
<LastName>Johnston-Halperin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ezekiel Johnston-Halperin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ejh@mps.ohio-state.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000481110</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/22/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Ohio State University</Name>
<CityName>COLUMBUS</CityName>
<ZipCode>432101016</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6146888735</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1960 KENNY RD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OH03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>DLWBSLWAJWR1</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OHIO STATE UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>MN4MDDMN8529</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Ohio State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Columbus</CityName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>432101016</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OH03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>131Y</Code>
<Text>Convergence Accelerator Resrch</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~709707</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span class="NormalTextRun SpellingErrorV2Themed SCXW33168049 BCX9">QuSTEAM</span><span class="NormalTextRun SCXW33168049 BCX9"> (Quantum Information Science, Technology, Engineering, Arts and Mathematics) is a transformational undergraduate curriculum that provides a national educational model for the emerging field of quantum information science and engineering (QISE). The development of </span><span class="NormalTextRun SpellingErrorV2Themed SCXW33168049 BCX9">QuSTEAM</span><span class="NormalTextRun SCXW33168049 BCX9"> relies on collaborative and research-based educational strategies to build a convergent and inclusive curriculum for a diverse community of future scientists and </span><span class="NormalTextRun SCXW33168049 BCX9">engineers.</span><span class="NormalTextRun SCXW33168049 BCX9"> </span><span class="NormalTextRun SCXW33168049 BCX9">The severe human-resource shortage in all areas of quantum science, technology, engineering, and mathematics is projected to significantly slow the societal impact of the second quantum revolution. To address this need and accelerate the NSF Quantum Leap, a comparable leap in education strategy is required. The </span><span class="NormalTextRun SpellingErrorV2Themed SCXW33168049 BCX9">QuSTEAM</span><span class="NormalTextRun SCXW33168049 BCX9"> curriculum has a modular format and an iterative design approach, with in-person, online, and hybrid delivery modalities to meet the educational needs of diverse stakeholders, including future quantum professionals and members of the current industrial workforce, community colleges, minority-serving institutions, and other bachelors and doctoral degree-granting institutions. We draw on the extensive expertise of the core participants in both quantum research and STEAM education to create a new curriculum with multiple implementations at the m</span><span class="NormalTextRun SCXW33168049 BCX9">odule, class</span><span class="NormalTextRun SCXW33168049 BCX9">, minor, and certificate level. </span><span class="NormalTextRun SCXW33168049 BCX9">The curriculum has been piloted at participating institutions, leveraging partnerships with industry and national labs while demonstrating the ability to train a quantum smart workforce at the scale necessary to support economic development.&nbsp;</span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/28/2022<br>      Modified by: Ezekiel&nbsp;Johnston-Halperin</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ QuSTEAM (Quantum Information Science, Technology, Engineering, Arts and Mathematics) is a transformational undergraduate curriculum that provides a national educational model for the emerging field of quantum information science and engineering (QISE). The development of QuSTEAM relies on collaborative and research-based educational strategies to build a convergent and inclusive curriculum for a diverse community of future scientists and engineers. The severe human-resource shortage in all areas of quantum science, technology, engineering, and mathematics is projected to significantly slow the societal impact of the second quantum revolution. To address this need and accelerate the NSF Quantum Leap, a comparable leap in education strategy is required. The QuSTEAM curriculum has a modular format and an iterative design approach, with in-person, online, and hybrid delivery modalities to meet the educational needs of diverse stakeholders, including future quantum professionals and members of the current industrial workforce, community colleges, minority-serving institutions, and other bachelors and doctoral degree-granting institutions. We draw on the extensive expertise of the core participants in both quantum research and STEAM education to create a new curriculum with multiple implementations at the module, class, minor, and certificate level. The curriculum has been piloted at participating institutions, leveraging partnerships with industry and national labs while demonstrating the ability to train a quantum smart workforce at the scale necessary to support economic development.        Last Modified: 11/28/2022       Submitted by: Ezekiel Johnston-Halperin]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
