<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Planning Workshop: Addressing Wireless Communication Needs in Underwater Technologies. The Workshop is Scheduled to be Held in the Fall of 2020.]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>23047.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>23047</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ECCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Zhengdao Wang</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Oceans, lakes and rivers cover more than 70 percent of the Earth surface with water and the value of key ocean assets is estimated to be over $24 trillion. Therefore, it is of great importance to sustain the growth of the blue economy and develop the ocean technologies, such as ocean energy harvesting, Autonomous Underwater Vehicles (AUV), and Internet of Underwater Things (IoUT), etc. However, underwater wireless communication has been a long-standing bottleneck to advancing ocean technologies because the physical communication media are hostile to radio frequency, optical, or acoustical means of wireless communications. The future growth of blue economy especially calls for underwater wireless communication technologies that are reliable, medium-distance, and high data-rate.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This planning workshop is to invite 50 -- 100 researchers from different sectors of underwater technologies and discuss funding recommendations via two days of Zoom meetings. The goal is to engage the multiple sectors of stakeholders including underwater infrastructure and environmental monitoring, offshore fishing and aquaculture, offshore oil and gas and energy harvesting, diving and recreation, scientific research, and military surveillance. The specific objectives of the workshop are to answer the questions regarding the most important applications, performance requirements, and environmental impacts of underwater wireless communications for the research community to focus on in the next five to ten years, and the recommended funding mechanisms and research topics for the research community to achieve the desired technology advances. The outcome of the planning workshop will aid the NSF to create a potential funding program that aims at advancing the underwater wireless technolgies. The workshop has the potential to engage researchers from different ocean technology sectors and foster multi-disciplinary research. The workshop findings will be disseminated through website sharing and conference presentation, and will be used to create course modules with the entrepreneurial mindset learning (EML) approach.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/11/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/11/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2040361</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yahong</FirstName>
<LastName>Zheng</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Yahong R Zheng</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[yrz218@lehigh.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000398958</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/11/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Lehigh University</Name>
<CityName>BETHLEHEM</CityName>
<ZipCode>180153008</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6107583021</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>526 BRODHEAD AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>E13MDBKHLDB5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>LEHIGH UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Lehigh University]]></Name>
<CityName>Dept. of ECE 404B Packard</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>180153005</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[19 Memorial Dr. West]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1620</Code>
<Text>Marine Geology and Geophysics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7564</Code>
<Text>CCSS-Comms Circuits &amp; Sens Sys</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~23047</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The NSF&ndash;sponsored workshop on Advancing Underwater Cyber Infrastructure for Blue Science, or BLUE-UCI 2021, was held virtually on Jan. 12 and Jan. 14, 2021, where webinar presentations and discussion panels were organized into four sessions: 1. Ocean Science Perspectives: Needs and Challenges; 2. IoUT Hardware, Electronics, and Applications in Extreme Environments; 3. Underwater Communications, Signal Processing, and Networking; and 4. Marine Robotics and Artificial Intelligence for IoUT.&nbsp;</p> <p>The webinar presentations in each session included one 30-minute keynote speech, a couple of 10-minute short talks, and a few 3-minute pre-recorded lightning talks. The discussion panel ran for an hour after each session of the webinar presentations. The discussion panel utilized a Zoom meeting and four breakout rooms to facilitate the discussion. More than 160 researchers from academia, industry, and government agencies attended the webinars and discussion panels. Discussions were aimed to answer the three important questions related to underwater cyber infrastructure: Q1. What are the most important challenges in underwater cyber infrastructure? Q2. What are the actions we can take to address these challenges in short term (~5 years) and in long term (~10 years)? Q3. What are the environmental and societal impacts of the technological advances in underwater cyber infrastructure?</p> <p>Based on the webinar presentations and panel discussions, the organizing team summarized four recommendations and several specific research directions. A formal report was submitted to the NSF in February 2021. The recommendations will help the NSF with a strategic planning and funding program that supports the next-generation advances in underwater technologies while reducing environmental footprint. As the UN Decade of Ocean Science for Sustainable Development starts in 2021, it is timely for the NSF to develop such a program that addresses the cyber infrastructure of underwater technologies and directly impacts the blue economy and the blue science.</p> <p>&nbsp;The outcomes of the workshop include a detailed report and a website hosting the video recordings of the presentations, slides, and lightnling talk recordings. The workshop website: <a href="https://www.blue-uci2021.org/">https://www.blue-uci2021.org</a>&nbsp; will be maintained for the next two years.</p> <p>The Workshop Planning Team includes: Dr. Rosa Zheng, Lehigh University, Dr. Catherine Edwards, Skidaway Institute of Oceanography, University of Georgia, Dr. Majid Manteghi, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Dr. Miao Pan, University of Houston, Dr. Lloyd Emokpae, U.S. Naval Research Laboratory, Dr. Nina Mahmoudian, Purdue University, and Dr. Fumin Zhang, Georgia Institute of Technology. &nbsp;The participating NSF Program Managers include: Drs. Mohammod Ali, Kiki Ikossi,  Albert Wang, Zhengdao Wang from &nbsp;Electrical, Communications, and Cyber Systems (ECCS) of&nbsp; the Directorate of Engineering, Dr. Giovanna Biscontin from Civil, Mechanical and Manufacturing Innovation (CMMI) of the Directorate of Engineering, &nbsp;Deborah K. Smith from the Ocean Sciences Division, Marine Geology and Geophysics program of the Directorate of Geosciences, Dr. Michael E Jackson from the Office of Polar Programs of the Directorate of Geosciences, and the Environmental Compliance Officer Dr. Holy Smith from the Office of General Counsel.</p> <p>The impact of the workshop lays in: 1) building and enhancing the research community for the ocean technology development, 2) bridging the engineering research effort with ocean science needs; 3) enhancing the awareness of ocean-related research and technology on environmental impact.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/16/2021<br>      Modified by: Yahong&nbsp;R&nbsp;Zheng</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The NSF&ndash;sponsored workshop on Advancing Underwater Cyber Infrastructure for Blue Science, or BLUE-UCI 2021, was held virtually on Jan. 12 and Jan. 14, 2021, where webinar presentations and discussion panels were organized into four sessions: 1. Ocean Science Perspectives: Needs and Challenges; 2. IoUT Hardware, Electronics, and Applications in Extreme Environments; 3. Underwater Communications, Signal Processing, and Networking; and 4. Marine Robotics and Artificial Intelligence for IoUT.   The webinar presentations in each session included one 30-minute keynote speech, a couple of 10-minute short talks, and a few 3-minute pre-recorded lightning talks. The discussion panel ran for an hour after each session of the webinar presentations. The discussion panel utilized a Zoom meeting and four breakout rooms to facilitate the discussion. More than 160 researchers from academia, industry, and government agencies attended the webinars and discussion panels. Discussions were aimed to answer the three important questions related to underwater cyber infrastructure: Q1. What are the most important challenges in underwater cyber infrastructure? Q2. What are the actions we can take to address these challenges in short term (~5 years) and in long term (~10 years)? Q3. What are the environmental and societal impacts of the technological advances in underwater cyber infrastructure?  Based on the webinar presentations and panel discussions, the organizing team summarized four recommendations and several specific research directions. A formal report was submitted to the NSF in February 2021. The recommendations will help the NSF with a strategic planning and funding program that supports the next-generation advances in underwater technologies while reducing environmental footprint. As the UN Decade of Ocean Science for Sustainable Development starts in 2021, it is timely for the NSF to develop such a program that addresses the cyber infrastructure of underwater technologies and directly impacts the blue economy and the blue science.   The outcomes of the workshop include a detailed report and a website hosting the video recordings of the presentations, slides, and lightnling talk recordings. The workshop website: https://www.blue-uci2021.org  will be maintained for the next two years.  The Workshop Planning Team includes: Dr. Rosa Zheng, Lehigh University, Dr. Catherine Edwards, Skidaway Institute of Oceanography, University of Georgia, Dr. Majid Manteghi, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Dr. Miao Pan, University of Houston, Dr. Lloyd Emokpae, U.S. Naval Research Laboratory, Dr. Nina Mahmoudian, Purdue University, and Dr. Fumin Zhang, Georgia Institute of Technology.  The participating NSF Program Managers include: Drs. Mohammod Ali, Kiki Ikossi,  Albert Wang, Zhengdao Wang from  Electrical, Communications, and Cyber Systems (ECCS) of  the Directorate of Engineering, Dr. Giovanna Biscontin from Civil, Mechanical and Manufacturing Innovation (CMMI) of the Directorate of Engineering,  Deborah K. Smith from the Ocean Sciences Division, Marine Geology and Geophysics program of the Directorate of Geosciences, Dr. Michael E Jackson from the Office of Polar Programs of the Directorate of Geosciences, and the Environmental Compliance Officer Dr. Holy Smith from the Office of General Counsel.  The impact of the workshop lays in: 1) building and enhancing the research community for the ocean technology development, 2) bridging the engineering research effort with ocean science needs; 3) enhancing the awareness of ocean-related research and technology on environmental impact.                  Last Modified: 09/16/2021       Submitted by: Yahong R Zheng]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
