<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research: REU Site: Resilience and Adaptation to Coastal Change Across Virtual Communities (C2-Virtual-C)]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>15519.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>15519</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Aisha Morris</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>armorris@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927081</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This REU Pilot will contribute to developing an interdisciplinary, systems-level understanding of the interplay between the environment and society in coastal regions using a Team Science approach.  The project will host REU students at East Carolina University, Clemson University, and the University of Puerto Rico at Arecibo to investigate and document how human actions positively or negatively influence coastal resilience in the face of extreme weather events, sea level rise, and population growth.  The project includes important training elements in Team Science that will prepare students to effectively address problems in interdisciplinary work and graduate research settings, build their ability to communicate science to the public, and take a systems perspective on solving societal challenges.  The Team Science focus of this REU is on remote collaboration between student researchers.  The professional development activities and use of virtual collaboration tools to support Team Science emphasized in the project will therefore also engage students in working across geographic and cultural boundaries.  These skills will prepare the students to participate in research when direct contact between research team members is not possible, including situations such as the current pandemic where isolation is due to health concern and not just geographic or cultural factors.    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Students will be recruited from universities across the Carolinas and Puerto Rico through PR-LSAMP and partnerships with HBCUs and 2yr Colleges to reach a wide population with varying demographic backgrounds and limited access to research opportunities.  REU Students will pursue research projects across a range of interdisciplinary areas that drive the evolution of environmental and social systems.  Systems science concepts will integrate projects across the REU, enabling students to identify and understand how dependencies between earth science and other disciplines impact society. Team Science and virtualization of collaboration efforts will engage REU participants in (1) online cohort building and preparatory activities over the spring prior to the REU, (2) an intensive week-long training bootcamp, and (3) seven weeks of team-based research where students are divided between the three host institutions. Professional development activities will be structured to enable the students to overcome geographic and cultural barriers to collaboration, thereby providing them a unique skill set to pursue global change research as an effective interdisciplinary team member.  The project will conclude with a student Symposium where regional stakeholders will participate and view student research videos developed using science communication strategies to engage the public in their research.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/02/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/14/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2041427</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kelly</FirstName>
<LastName>Lazar</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kelly Lazar</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[klazar@clemson.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000761129</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/02/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Clemson University</Name>
<CityName>CLEMSON</CityName>
<ZipCode>296340001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8646562424</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>201 SIKES HALL</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>South Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>SC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>SC03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>H2BMNX7DSKU8</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CLEMSON UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>H2BMNX7DSKU8</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Clemson University]]></Name>
<CityName>Clemson</CityName>
<StateCode>SC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>296340001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[230 Kappa Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>South Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>SC03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1575</Code>
<Text>EDUCATION AND HUMAN RESOURCES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9250</Code>
<Text>REU SITE-Res Exp for Ugrd Site</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~15519</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The C2-Virtual-C REU program hosted 10 undergraduate researchers from diverse backgrounds at East Carolina University's Coastal Studies Institute on Roanoke Island, NC over a period of 8 weeks during the summer of 2021.&nbsp; The participants undertook mentored research addressing coastal resilience in a wide range of fields spanning ecology, social science, geoscience, and engineering.&nbsp; Each participant collaborated with one or more research mentors from ECU, Clemson University, or the University of Puerto Rico at Arecibo.&nbsp; Project topics pursued by the students were:</p> <ul> <li>Compound Extremes in the Southeast USA: Evaluating Flooding and Storm Surge with Copulas</li> <li>Perceptions of Climate Change Among Anglers in Coastal North Carolina</li> <li>Water flow simulation using cave geometrical data collected by underground Lidar</li> <li>Processes and biomass driving and maintaining accretion in a microtidal wind-driven salt marsh in Eastern North Carolina</li> <li>Determining the Fractal Dimension of Puerto Rico's Shorelines</li> <li>Critically Connected Communities: Resilience and Vulnerability of Energy Systems to Extreme Weather</li> <li>Hurricane resilience of two North Carolina marine fish species</li> <li>Economic valuation of coral reef ecosystem services in West Hawai'i</li> <li>Measuring hurricane Maria's impacts and recovery remotely with blue-traps and nightlights through Puerto Rico</li> <li>Foraminifera as Indicators of Environmental Change &amp; Potential Metal Contamination, Croatan Sound, NC</li> </ul> <p>A key aspect of the program introduced participants to team-science by having them work in small groups to explore and define an additional coastal research problem beyond their independent research project.&nbsp; REU participants put their science communication skills into practice by developing video proposals sharing their team's project ideas with a general audience.&nbsp;</p> <p>In addition to their research experiences, the participants gained valuable skills, background, and exposure to different areas of earth and environmental science through an initial bootcamp and weekly lectures and/or field trips.&nbsp; They also received professional development experiences preparing them for future careers in research or industry, such as how to review literature and approaches for putting your best foot forward as a professional through resumes and social media.&nbsp; The REU concluded with a hybrid poster symposium allowing the participants to share their research with mentors and guests regardless of whether they were in person or remote.&nbsp;</p> <p>Two key themes emerged from participants in the assessment of the REU program.&nbsp; First the participants demonstrated the importance of communication in producing effective science and working in teams.&nbsp; In particular, they identified accountability, listening and speaking skills, and following-up as key skills for producing effective science teams.&nbsp; They also identified diversity and inclusion of multiple perspectives as important to advancing science and illustrated both professional (e.g., check-ins and scheduling) and personal (e.g., being kind and sharing credit) strategies that can be used to support this goal within science teams.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/29/2022<br>      Modified by: Kelly&nbsp;Lazar</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The C2-Virtual-C REU program hosted 10 undergraduate researchers from diverse backgrounds at East Carolina University's Coastal Studies Institute on Roanoke Island, NC over a period of 8 weeks during the summer of 2021.  The participants undertook mentored research addressing coastal resilience in a wide range of fields spanning ecology, social science, geoscience, and engineering.  Each participant collaborated with one or more research mentors from ECU, Clemson University, or the University of Puerto Rico at Arecibo.  Project topics pursued by the students were:  Compound Extremes in the Southeast USA: Evaluating Flooding and Storm Surge with Copulas Perceptions of Climate Change Among Anglers in Coastal North Carolina Water flow simulation using cave geometrical data collected by underground Lidar Processes and biomass driving and maintaining accretion in a microtidal wind-driven salt marsh in Eastern North Carolina Determining the Fractal Dimension of Puerto Rico's Shorelines Critically Connected Communities: Resilience and Vulnerability of Energy Systems to Extreme Weather Hurricane resilience of two North Carolina marine fish species Economic valuation of coral reef ecosystem services in West Hawai'i Measuring hurricane Maria's impacts and recovery remotely with blue-traps and nightlights through Puerto Rico Foraminifera as Indicators of Environmental Change &amp; Potential Metal Contamination, Croatan Sound, NC   A key aspect of the program introduced participants to team-science by having them work in small groups to explore and define an additional coastal research problem beyond their independent research project.  REU participants put their science communication skills into practice by developing video proposals sharing their team's project ideas with a general audience.   In addition to their research experiences, the participants gained valuable skills, background, and exposure to different areas of earth and environmental science through an initial bootcamp and weekly lectures and/or field trips.  They also received professional development experiences preparing them for future careers in research or industry, such as how to review literature and approaches for putting your best foot forward as a professional through resumes and social media.  The REU concluded with a hybrid poster symposium allowing the participants to share their research with mentors and guests regardless of whether they were in person or remote.   Two key themes emerged from participants in the assessment of the REU program.  First the participants demonstrated the importance of communication in producing effective science and working in teams.  In particular, they identified accountability, listening and speaking skills, and following-up as key skills for producing effective science teams.  They also identified diversity and inclusion of multiple perspectives as important to advancing science and illustrated both professional (e.g., check-ins and scheduling) and personal (e.g., being kind and sharing credit) strategies that can be used to support this goal within science teams.        Last Modified: 12/29/2022       Submitted by: Kelly Lazar]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
