<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Quantum Leap Grantees Meeting 2020]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>64855.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>64855</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>John D. Gillaspy</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jgillasp@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927173</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The exploitation of the inherent quantum nature of systems holds great promise in enabling quantum technologies that far surpass our current systems. There remain significant barriers to reaching this goal. In the area of quantum simulation and modeling, there is a need for new quantum platforms that go beyond our current few-qubit systems as well as the development of algorithms to efficiently use those platforms. Development in sensing that shows quantum advantage is just now becoming possible, opening up the possibility of quantum sensors that can be deployed outside of the laboratory. Systems using quantum entanglement have demonstrated quantum communication, but much work is needed on quantum repeaters and the range of wavelengths to make such systems commercially viable. This research in quantum information science forms the Quantum Leap NSF Big Idea.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Understanding and controlling quantum systems is critical to achieving the next generation in quantum computing, sensing and communication. The National Quantum Initiative Act tasked the NSF to carry out a basic research and education effort in the area of quantum information science.  As part of that effort, NSF has made a number of awards in quantum information science, including the funding of three Quantum Leap Challenge Institutes. In order to introduce these new institutes, highlight NSF efforts in this area and facilitate communication between researchers, NSF will hold a virtual grantees workshop in Fall of 2020. This award will enable that effort. The meeting will be held over two days, September 29-30, 2020.  It is anticipated that there will be over 100 participants. There will be plenary talks introducing the Quantum Leap Challenge Institutes and parallel sessions by grantees in the area of quantum information science. These talks will range from quantum communication, sensing, computation, simulations as well as the development of new quantum platforms.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/17/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/14/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2041809</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Brian</FirstName>
<LastName>Smith</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Brian J Smith</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[bjsmith@uoregon.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000711892</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/17/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Raymer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>G</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael G Raymer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[raymer@uoregon.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000232470</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/17/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Oregon Eugene</Name>
<CityName>EUGENE</CityName>
<ZipCode>974031657</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5413465131</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1585 E 13TH AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OR04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>Z3FGN9MF92U2</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF OREGON</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>L17DBQFXJVJ6</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Oregon]]></Name>
<CityName>Eugene</CityName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<ZipCode>974035219</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OR04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>105Y</Code>
<Text>QL-The Quantum Leap: Leading t</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>057Z</Code>
<Text>(QL) Quantum Leap</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7203</Code>
<Text>QUANTUM INFORMATION SCIENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~64855</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Quantum information science (QIS) is proving to be a major driver of innovation in both basic science and emerging technologies. With the passage and funding of the National Quantum Initiative (NQI), it is clear that cross-disciplinary and team-based research is necessary for making crucial advances in the field.</p> <p>The University of Oregon hosted a virtual meeting for the grantees of the Quantum Leap program at NSF. The meeting was over two days in September 2020. The purpose of this meeting was to introduce the then-new Quantum Leap Challenge Institutes, to highlight and review the NSF then-current activities funded under the Quantum Leap Program, and to foster interaction between grantees.</p> <p>By all accounts the meeting was a success. Every Quantum Leap grant (approx. 50) was represented by a talk to review the purpose and progress on each grant. One non-grantee was invited to kick off the meeting with a high-level overview. The meeting was hosted on the virtual platform of the Optical Society of America.</p> <p>The meeting was hosted by PI Michael Raymer and coPI Brian Smith, both professors at the University of Oregon. IT support was provided by the Optical Society. A Keynote talk was presented by Chris Monroe. Audience participation was encouraged through the Zoom portal.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/20/2022<br>      Modified by: Michael&nbsp;G&nbsp;Raymer</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Quantum information science (QIS) is proving to be a major driver of innovation in both basic science and emerging technologies. With the passage and funding of the National Quantum Initiative (NQI), it is clear that cross-disciplinary and team-based research is necessary for making crucial advances in the field.  The University of Oregon hosted a virtual meeting for the grantees of the Quantum Leap program at NSF. The meeting was over two days in September 2020. The purpose of this meeting was to introduce the then-new Quantum Leap Challenge Institutes, to highlight and review the NSF then-current activities funded under the Quantum Leap Program, and to foster interaction between grantees.  By all accounts the meeting was a success. Every Quantum Leap grant (approx. 50) was represented by a talk to review the purpose and progress on each grant. One non-grantee was invited to kick off the meeting with a high-level overview. The meeting was hosted on the virtual platform of the Optical Society of America.  The meeting was hosted by PI Michael Raymer and coPI Brian Smith, both professors at the University of Oregon. IT support was provided by the Optical Society. A Keynote talk was presented by Chris Monroe. Audience participation was encouraged through the Zoom portal.       Last Modified: 01/20/2022       Submitted by: Michael G Raymer]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
