<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[I-Corps:   A device to improve the ability to monitor the fetus and uterus during pregnancy, labor, and delivery]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ruth Shuman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rshuman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922160</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this I-Corps project is the development of a new fetal monitor to accurately assess fetal health and the integrity of the uterine scar in the case where a woman has a previous C-section (operative) delivery. There are about 4 million births in the US annually. The fetal monitoring market is expected to reach approximately $3.6 billion in 2022. This project will advance translation of a monitor providing accurate data, improved maternal mobility, and better outcomes. Furthermore, the technology is envisioned to be disposable, reducing exposure to pathogen transmission - a benefit in particular during the pandemic.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project advances translation of a medical device that monitors the fetus and uterus during pregnancy, labor and delivery. Fetal monitors today are unreliable at providing consistent interpretive data of fetal well-being in utero and require constant readjustment to ensure consistent fetal tracing. This process is cumbersome and introduces dangerous errors, most often due to fetal, maternal and monitor movement. This process explores a wireless device generating valuable monitoring data in a consistent, thorough, hygienic, and efficient manner that is comfortable for the patient.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/18/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/20/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2041414</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Julie</FirstName>
<LastName>Hasenwinkel</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Julie M Hasenwinkel</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jmhasenw@syr.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000234759</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/18/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Syracuse University</Name>
<CityName>SYRACUSE</CityName>
<ZipCode>132440001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3154432807</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>900 S CROUSE AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>22</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY22</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>C4BXLBC11LC6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SYRACUSE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Syracuse University]]></Name>
<CityName>Syracuse</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>132441200</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>22</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY22</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5345</Code>
<Text>BIOMEDICAL ENGINEERING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>In 2018 the United States was identified as the most dangerous place to give birth among all developed countries. A more dismal fact is that African American women across the income spectrum and from all walks of life are dying from preventable pregnancy-related complications at three to four times the rate of non-Hispanic white women, while the death rate for black infants is twice that of infants born to non-Hispanic white mothers [1]. In response to this sobering fact, the CDC published a call to action for a National Maternal Morbidity Task Force [2]. As a nation, we can and we must do better to protect expectant patients and their babies because quality maternity care is a foundation of our nation&rsquo;s health. Advanced Fetal Monitoring LLC's (AFM) non-invasive fetal monitoring device stands to be part of the solution to improve alarming mortality statistics of the estimated 4 million births each year in the U.S.</p> <p>The Fetal Monitoring ecosystem includes doctors, nurses, midwives, expectant patients, insurance companies, and hospital administrators. During National I-Corp we identified distinct value propositions for each customer segment, and while they are all important members of the ecosystem, here we will focus on the economic buyer of the customer segment because that is who will pay for our product. The main value propositions for the economic buyer, Directors of Obstetric Departments, are to increase revenue and decrease liability. AFM's product line brings a solution to obtaining this important goal in a $412 million-dollar U.S. market. AFM identified a solution to an unmet need to safe guard the health and well-being of both mothers and babies through improvement of traditional fetal monitors in a ground breaking way. The time has come to make birth safer in the U.S.</p> <p>During the course of the program, we recorded 102 interviews. In the beginning we were focused on what expectant patients wanted. Then we realized we needed to find out who our economic buyer would be, and what they valued most. The answer: Hospitals, and what they value most is more revenue and less liability. Traditional continuous fetal monitoring had been shown to increase c-sections, which increase liability, so we had to make sure our continuous fetal monitor was better- and decreased c-sections. A eye opening discovery that Medicaid pays for at least half of all US births led us to consider the value from insurance companies perspectives. We found 6 different customer types are part of the eco system, but the one we would focus on was the person responsible for buying new medical devices in hospitals. We needed to prove our hypothesis that our monitor would increase revenue by offering higher patient satisfaction, fewer complications, and reduce c-section rates. At the end of the program, we set out to prepare for prototyping and clinical testing.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>[1] Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, &ldquo;Infant Mortality,&rdquo; available at&nbsp;<a href="https://www.cdc.gov/reproductivehealth/maternalinfanthealth/infantmortality.htm">https://www.cdc.gov/reproductivehealth/maternalinfanthealth/infantmortality.htm</a>&nbsp;(last accessed April 2019).</p> <p>[2] Gingrey J. P. (2020). &ldquo;Maternal Mortality: A US Public Health Crisis.&rdquo;&nbsp;<em>American </em>Journal<em> of Public Health</em>,&nbsp;<em>110</em>(4), 462&ndash;464. <a href="https://doi.org/10.2105/AJPH.2019.305552">https://doi.org/10.2105/AJPH.2019.305552</a></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/14/2021<br>      Modified by: Julie&nbsp;M&nbsp;Hasenwinkel</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ In 2018 the United States was identified as the most dangerous place to give birth among all developed countries. A more dismal fact is that African American women across the income spectrum and from all walks of life are dying from preventable pregnancy-related complications at three to four times the rate of non-Hispanic white women, while the death rate for black infants is twice that of infants born to non-Hispanic white mothers [1]. In response to this sobering fact, the CDC published a call to action for a National Maternal Morbidity Task Force [2]. As a nation, we can and we must do better to protect expectant patients and their babies because quality maternity care is a foundation of our nation’s health. Advanced Fetal Monitoring LLC's (AFM) non-invasive fetal monitoring device stands to be part of the solution to improve alarming mortality statistics of the estimated 4 million births each year in the U.S.  The Fetal Monitoring ecosystem includes doctors, nurses, midwives, expectant patients, insurance companies, and hospital administrators. During National I-Corp we identified distinct value propositions for each customer segment, and while they are all important members of the ecosystem, here we will focus on the economic buyer of the customer segment because that is who will pay for our product. The main value propositions for the economic buyer, Directors of Obstetric Departments, are to increase revenue and decrease liability. AFM's product line brings a solution to obtaining this important goal in a $412 million-dollar U.S. market. AFM identified a solution to an unmet need to safe guard the health and well-being of both mothers and babies through improvement of traditional fetal monitors in a ground breaking way. The time has come to make birth safer in the U.S.  During the course of the program, we recorded 102 interviews. In the beginning we were focused on what expectant patients wanted. Then we realized we needed to find out who our economic buyer would be, and what they valued most. The answer: Hospitals, and what they value most is more revenue and less liability. Traditional continuous fetal monitoring had been shown to increase c-sections, which increase liability, so we had to make sure our continuous fetal monitor was better- and decreased c-sections. A eye opening discovery that Medicaid pays for at least half of all US births led us to consider the value from insurance companies perspectives. We found 6 different customer types are part of the eco system, but the one we would focus on was the person responsible for buying new medical devices in hospitals. We needed to prove our hypothesis that our monitor would increase revenue by offering higher patient satisfaction, fewer complications, and reduce c-section rates. At the end of the program, we set out to prepare for prototyping and clinical testing.     [1] Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, "Infant Mortality," available at https://www.cdc.gov/reproductivehealth/maternalinfanthealth/infantmortality.htm (last accessed April 2019).  [2] Gingrey J. P. (2020). "Maternal Mortality: A US Public Health Crisis." American Journal of Public Health, 110(4), 462&ndash;464. https://doi.org/10.2105/AJPH.2019.305552          Last Modified: 10/14/2021       Submitted by: Julie M Hasenwinkel]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
