<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Acquisition of a tabletop SEM/EDS system at the University of Louisiana at Lafayette]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>162850.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>162850</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Luciana Astiz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lastiz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924705</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This Instrumentation and Facilities award supports the School of Geosciences at University of Louisiana at Lafayette with the acquisition of a tabletop analytical Scanning Electron Microscope [SEM] to advance on-campus undergraduate/graduate education and support research in STEAM [Science, Technology, Engineering, Art, Mathematics] disciplines. Thanks to its electron beam, SEM has distinct inherent advantages over optical microscopy: larger magnification, sharper images and chemical identification. A broad range of materials including wood, bones, fossils, rocks and minerals can be imaged and analyzed within a few minutes. The instrument will be used for advanced research in environmental studies, petroleum geology, and mining geology. The SEM will be remotely accessible through an internet connection, with an on-site operator, for demonstrations in classroom on campus and in secondary schools for science demonstrations. This connectivity will allow a large number of students from under-represented groups to participate in live exploration of materials. The best, high resolution images will be printed in large format to be displayed as part of science &amp; art exhibitions on campus.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The SEM instrument will allow the main investigators and their graduate students to acquire high quality digital imagery and will promote interactive exploration of the samples. The new, state of the art tabletop SEM, includes a modern energy dispersive (EDS) detector that provides rapid quantitative chemical analyses. This instrument will support the new interdisciplinary PhD program in Earth and Energy Sciences at UL Lafayette. The SEM+EDS system and its new microanalytical capabilities will enable scientists to conduct research on six targeted projects: 1) the microstructural record of co-seismic deformation in fault rock; 2) the roles of fluids in strain localization in the middle of the continental crust; 3) the record of climate/carbon cycle change in fossil wood; 4) the chemical record of climate change in precipitated carbonates in lakes; 5) life and death of methane-oxidizing microbial communities in relation with methane emissions; 6) the mineralogical record, in central Louisiana, of the asteroid impact that killed the dinosaurs 65 million years ago.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/24/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/24/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2041040</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Brian</FirstName>
<LastName>Schubert</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Brian Schubert</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[schubert@louisiana.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000587088</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/24/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Raphael</FirstName>
<LastName>Gottardi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Raphael Gottardi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[rxg0121@louisiana.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000674145</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/24/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Aubrey</FirstName>
<LastName>Hillman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Aubrey L Hillman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[aubreyhillman@gmail.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000720216</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/24/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Eric</FirstName>
<LastName>Ferre</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Eric C Ferre</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[eric.ferre@louisiana.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000796413</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/24/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Davide</FirstName>
<LastName>Oppo</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Davide Oppo</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[davide.oppo@louisiana.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000801784</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/24/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Louisiana at Lafayette</Name>
<CityName>LAFAYETTE</CityName>
<ZipCode>705032014</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3374825811</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>104 E UNIVERSITY CIR 3RD FL</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
<StateCode>LA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>LA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>C169K7T4QZ96</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF LOUISIANA AT LAFAYETTE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>F3GJXVP1L166</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Louisiana at Lafayette]]></Name>
<CityName>Lafayette</CityName>
<StateCode>LA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>705040001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[611 McKinley St]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>LA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1580</Code>
<Text>Instrumentation &amp; Facilities</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~162850</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The scanning electron microscope allows high magnification without any blurriness. The details viewed in the attached iamges help graduate students and their advisers advance knowledge of geological materials related the Earth marine environment, paleoclimate through the tree record and seismic activity in the conterminous United States.</p> <p>The graduate students and some undergraduate students have presented their findings at international conferences where peers evaluated and validated the results of their research.</p> <p>The scientific implications of the research projects undertaken range from reconstructuction of climatic conditions in the past, to paleoenvironmental condittions in the Gulf of Mexico and seismic risk in Montana and elsewhere.</p> <p>These results willfurther be disseminated through peer-reviewed articles published in scientific journals. None of the results obtained through the acquisition of this equipment could have been obtained using conventional (optical) microscopy.</p> <p>The last project that another group is currently working on involved a wooly mammoth, including teeth, recently discovered in a bayou in South West Louisiana. The investigation of the teeth enamel using the scanning electron microscope is underway and is being used to obtain a precise age for this fossil.</p> <p>The general public is regularly invited to visit the scanning electron microscope during open house events in the School of Geosciences.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/30/2023<br>      Modified by: Eric&nbsp;C&nbsp;Ferre</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2041040/2041040_10735336_1688162789111_1-1copy--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2041040/2041040_10735336_1688162789111_1-1copy--rgov-800width.jpg" title="foraminifera"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2041040/2041040_10735336_1688162789111_1-1copy--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="foraminifera"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Interior chamber of one foraminifera, a single-celled organism living in the ocean, recovered from the Bay of Bengal during IODP expedition 353. This individual has been exposed to a methane hydrates environment, which promoted the formation of fraboidal pyrite (spherical) and aragonite (needle-like</div> <div class="imageCredit">Davide Oppo</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Eric&nbsp;C&nbsp;Ferre</div> <div class="imageTitle">foraminifera</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2041040/2041040_10735336_1688162932433_10-5copy--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2041040/2041040_10735336_1688162932433_10-5copy--rgov-800width.jpg" title="fossil wood"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2041040/2041040_10735336_1688162932433_10-5copy--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="fossil wood"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Fossil wood from Siberia</div> <div class="imageCredit">Brian Schubert</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Eric&nbsp;C&nbsp;Ferre</div> <div class="imageTitle">fossil wood</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2041040/2041040_10735336_1688163105130_Hebgen_Lakecopy--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2041040/2041040_10735336_1688163105130_Hebgen_Lakecopy--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Hebgen Lake Fault mirror"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2041040/2041040_10735336_1688163105130_Hebgen_Lakecopy--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Hebgen Lake Fault mirror"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Fault mirror of the 1959 Mw7.2 earthquake at Hebgen Lake, MT</div> <div class="imageCredit">Nina Zamani/Eric Ferre</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Eric&nbsp;C&nbsp;Ferre</div> <div class="imageTitle">Hebgen Lake Fault mirror</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The scanning electron microscope allows high magnification without any blurriness. The details viewed in the attached iamges help graduate students and their advisers advance knowledge of geological materials related the Earth marine environment, paleoclimate through the tree record and seismic activity in the conterminous United States.  The graduate students and some undergraduate students have presented their findings at international conferences where peers evaluated and validated the results of their research.  The scientific implications of the research projects undertaken range from reconstructuction of climatic conditions in the past, to paleoenvironmental condittions in the Gulf of Mexico and seismic risk in Montana and elsewhere.  These results willfurther be disseminated through peer-reviewed articles published in scientific journals. None of the results obtained through the acquisition of this equipment could have been obtained using conventional (optical) microscopy.  The last project that another group is currently working on involved a wooly mammoth, including teeth, recently discovered in a bayou in South West Louisiana. The investigation of the teeth enamel using the scanning electron microscope is underway and is being used to obtain a precise age for this fossil.  The general public is regularly invited to visit the scanning electron microscope during open house events in the School of Geosciences.       Last Modified: 06/30/2023       Submitted by: Eric C Ferre]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
