<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Doctoral Dissertation Research: Morphological biodistances as indicators of slave trade migration histories in the African Diaspora]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>26615.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>26615</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rebecca Ferrell</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rferrell@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927850</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Millions of people were displaced due to slave trade during the 15th – 19th centuries. These systems profoundly influenced population dynamics as enslaved people were transported thousands of miles from their homes and experienced restricted social life and mobility in enslavement. This doctoral dissertation project examines skeletal morphology of these enslaved people and their descendants to understand how certain biological groups formed and changed over time, explores gene flow and other evolutionary processes that may explain how the biological variation is distributed, and investigates patterns of biological relatedness that may not be reflected in historic migration data. The project supports the doctoral training of a student from an underrepresented group in science, a multi-point research collaboration, outreach with community members, and student mentoring. The project also develops curricula and seminars in collaboration with the University of Florida’s College Reach Out Program to increase postsecondary admission and completion for students from groups historically underrepresented in STEM research. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project’s theoretical framework is rooted in stochastic microevolutionary expectations and diaspora studies. Microevolutionary processes such as population stratification are inferred from the premise that gene flow, rather than natural selection, is the main influence on observed biological patterns. Further, interpretations gleaned from the project derive from slave trade history, where European nations directly influenced the gene flow of the diaspora populations that formed across the Atlantic. The project asks two central questions: (1) What African and Afro-descendant diaspora groups show high biological relatedness as estimated by cranial morphology, and how do these data identify evidence of gene flow not otherwise described by historical migration data? and, (2) Given the social and legal restrictions that created physical separation among enslaved persons, do diaspora groups show stronger evidence of population stratification and genetic isolation than African groups? To investigate these questions, this project applies geometric morphometric methods to collect 3D landmarks from adult human cranial remains and uses these data to statistically analyze within-group and between-group variation in cranial morphology. Data will be collected from twenty-one sites, comprising cranial remains of 805 adult African descendants. These samples represent a variety of regions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/13/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/20/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2041182</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Valerie</FirstName>
<LastName>DeLeon</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Valerie DeLeon</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[vdeleon@ufl.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000484488</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/13/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Andreana</FirstName>
<LastName>Cunningham</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Andreana S Cunningham</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ascunningham@ufl.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000804237</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/13/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Florida</Name>
<CityName>GAINESVILLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>326111941</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3523923516</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1523 UNION RD RM 207</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NNFQH1JAPEP3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF FLORIDA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>D4GCCCMXR1H3</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Florida]]></Name>
<CityName>Gainesville</CityName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>326117305</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1112 Turlington Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7608</Code>
<Text>Bio Anthro DDRI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1392</Code>
<Text>Biological Anthropology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~26615</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Andreana Cunningham has completed research for her dissertation, ?Reframing Diaspora: Southeastern African Contributions to Biosocial Variation in Atlantic Afro-Descendant Groups,? supported by the NSF Dissertation Improvement Grant. During her funding period, she traveled to Alabama, Sint Maarten (Dutch Caribbean), South Africa, and St. Helena (South Atlantic Ocean) to collaborate with archaeology, heritage preservation, and museum professionals. As an interdisciplinary anthropologist, Cunningham integrated bioarchaeological and archival evidence to yield novel information about slave trade migration history. Her primary goal was to assess the within- and among-group biological relationships of slave trade regions that are not traditionally put in dialogue, such as the Caribbean and the Indian Ocean.</p> <p>Cunningham accomplished the goals of her research. The results of the biological data she collected from enslavement era human remains showed that all of the sites in the study were highly diverse. The results also showed evidence of subgrouping, meaning that there were social barriers in each site that resulted in smaller groups within the broader population that differed from one another (rather than becoming one large, homogeneous group). Even with this overall high within-group diversity, the sites were still highly correlated, suggesting that the people at those sites shared common geographic origins. Further, her results showed that Southeastern African origin was present in the South Africa, St. Helena, and Barbados sites. This suggested that, although the majority of enslaved Africans originated from West and West Central Africa, the number of enslaved people from Southeastern Africa may be higher than traditional migration records suggest.</p> <p>Cunningham also implemented public outreach initiatives, particularly in St. Helena. She shared all 3D scan data and related data from the project with local collaborators. During the research period in St. Helena, she collaborated with the St. Helena National Trust to circulate the research project to the St. Helena community through press releases, public talks, and interviews. This collaboration also allowed her to hire a paid student intern and lead workshops for primary and secondary students. The public outreach project included a facial approximation project, which is an ongoing collaboration with St. Helenian artists to artistically and anatomically estimate what enslaved people from an archaeological site on the island may have looked like. Updates on the results of the project and these ongoing initiatives are available on andreanacunningham.com.</p> <p>Cunningham?s biological research, archival text analysis, and biosocial analyses integrating her biological and archival datasets form the basis of her dissertation. The dissertation is an important contribution to Behavioral and Cognitive Sciences because it provides novel insight into the overlap between the Trans-Atlantic and Indian Ocean slave trade systems. This in turn contributes to efforts toward understanding Afro-descendant biosocial diversity and creating tools that enable Afro-descendants to meaningfully engage with their pasts.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/29/2023<br>      Modified by: Andreana&nbsp;S&nbsp;Cunningham</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2041182/2041182_10727690_1690656097284_picme--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2041182/2041182_10727690_1690656097284_picme--rgov-800width.jpg" title="In St. Helena"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2041182/2041182_10727690_1690656097284_picme--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="In St. Helena"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Co-PI at research site in St. Helena.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Helena Bennett</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Andreana&nbsp;S&nbsp;Cunningham</div> <div class="imageTitle">In St. Helena</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Andreana Cunningham has completed research for her dissertation, ?Reframing Diaspora: Southeastern African Contributions to Biosocial Variation in Atlantic Afro-Descendant Groups,? supported by the NSF Dissertation Improvement Grant. During her funding period, she traveled to Alabama, Sint Maarten (Dutch Caribbean), South Africa, and St. Helena (South Atlantic Ocean) to collaborate with archaeology, heritage preservation, and museum professionals. As an interdisciplinary anthropologist, Cunningham integrated bioarchaeological and archival evidence to yield novel information about slave trade migration history. Her primary goal was to assess the within- and among-group biological relationships of slave trade regions that are not traditionally put in dialogue, such as the Caribbean and the Indian Ocean.  Cunningham accomplished the goals of her research. The results of the biological data she collected from enslavement era human remains showed that all of the sites in the study were highly diverse. The results also showed evidence of subgrouping, meaning that there were social barriers in each site that resulted in smaller groups within the broader population that differed from one another (rather than becoming one large, homogeneous group). Even with this overall high within-group diversity, the sites were still highly correlated, suggesting that the people at those sites shared common geographic origins. Further, her results showed that Southeastern African origin was present in the South Africa, St. Helena, and Barbados sites. This suggested that, although the majority of enslaved Africans originated from West and West Central Africa, the number of enslaved people from Southeastern Africa may be higher than traditional migration records suggest.  Cunningham also implemented public outreach initiatives, particularly in St. Helena. She shared all 3D scan data and related data from the project with local collaborators. During the research period in St. Helena, she collaborated with the St. Helena National Trust to circulate the research project to the St. Helena community through press releases, public talks, and interviews. This collaboration also allowed her to hire a paid student intern and lead workshops for primary and secondary students. The public outreach project included a facial approximation project, which is an ongoing collaboration with St. Helenian artists to artistically and anatomically estimate what enslaved people from an archaeological site on the island may have looked like. Updates on the results of the project and these ongoing initiatives are available on andreanacunningham.com.  Cunningham?s biological research, archival text analysis, and biosocial analyses integrating her biological and archival datasets form the basis of her dissertation. The dissertation is an important contribution to Behavioral and Cognitive Sciences because it provides novel insight into the overlap between the Trans-Atlantic and Indian Ocean slave trade systems. This in turn contributes to efforts toward understanding Afro-descendant biosocial diversity and creating tools that enable Afro-descendants to meaningfully engage with their pasts.          Last Modified: 07/29/2023       Submitted by: Andreana S Cunningham]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
