<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Doctoral Dissertation Research: Production, Perception, and Acquisition of New Dialect Features by Speakers Moving Between Two Regions]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>11235.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>11235</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Mary Paster</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mpaster@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922762</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[When speakers of different dialects interact, their specific dialect features may change over time. The motivation for such changes can be due to many interrelated developmental, linguistic and social factors. This doctoral dissertation improvement research grant-funded project will investigate new dialect acquisition by mobile people relocating between two regions, one urban and characterized by a prestigious dialect, and one rural, whose dialect is stigmatized. Studies of dialect contact have been rare in comparison to studies of language contact, but such studies provide key opportunities to understand the processes of language change and the outcomes of contact situations broadly. This study will contribute new knowledge about how people are capable of learning and using new language forms and how speech sounds and words are represented in the mind. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Language samples from participants in each region will be collected according to gender, age, and length of residence in the new region. These and other social characteristics such as age of arrival, education level, occupation, social network, and language attitude will be examined for their possible effects on dialect acquisition. Each mobile speaker will take part in four activities: a conversational interview, reading a list of sentences, words, and minimal pairs. Importantly, by having an interview about the participants' experience growing up in their hometown and their experience in moving to a new region, this study can examine how participants vary their speech according to different topics. Transcriptions of interviews and associated audio files will ultimately form the basis of a corpus which will be shared with other researchers who are interested in the study of second dialect acquisition and variation within the studied language. This corpus will also be of value for related purposes, such as for forensic linguistics. Finally, by observing how both first dialect and second dialect features are used, this study will examine how speakers use linguistic features to craft identity-related meanings.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/04/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/20/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2041126</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yoojin</FirstName>
<LastName>Kang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Yoojin Kang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[yk569@georgetown.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000831969</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/04/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jennifer</FirstName>
<LastName>Nycz</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jennifer Nycz</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jn621@georgetown.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000693442</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/04/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Georgetown University</Name>
<CityName>WASHINGTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>200570001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2026250100</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>MAIN CAMPUS</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>TF2CMKY1HMX9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GEORGETOWN UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>ZFHYYLPJW7Q1</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Georgetown University]]></Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>200571789</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[37th & O St N W]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8374</Code>
<Text>DDRI Linguistics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1311</Code>
<Text>LINGUISTICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~11235</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project examines the acquisition of second dialect features by mobile  speakers relocating between two regions, one urban and characterized by a prestigious  dialect, and one rural, whose dialect is stigmatized. The participants in this study are 62  Korean speakers in two field sites: Seoul city and North Kyungsang province in South  Korea. This dissertation examines how mobile adult speakers acquire new dialect features.&nbsp;Several findings emerge from this project. Most of the speakers in both mobile  groups produce the Seoul-Korean-like distinction between /&#623;/ and /&#652;/, Seoul-Korean-like  /w&#593;/ diphthongization and do not show the North-Kyungsang-Korean-like word-initial  tensification and North Kyungsang Korean tones. I argue that the overall result that the  vast majority of mobile speakers produce the Seoul Korean features is related to both linguistic and  extralinguistic factors: Linguistic complexity, salience of features, speakers&rsquo; pre-existing  phonetic repertoire, high instrumental motivation, linguistic insecurity, and speaker  identity.</p> <p><span lang="EN-US">The study of second dialect acquisition is a fairly new focus in sociolinguistic research.&nbsp;</span>As Chambers points out, mobile speakers were &ldquo;purposely excluded&rdquo; from early dialectology research; instead, dialectologists focused on the speech of nonmobile, older, rural, male speakers (known as NORMs), whose speech was seen as unaffected by contact with other varieties. Since then, however, scholars have acknowledged that dialect contact itself is a phenomenon worth studying, and that the outcomes of contact may enable researchers to answer linguistic and social questions.&nbsp;<span lang="EN-US">For example, studies of short-term accommodation by adult speakers exposed to new dialect input has revealed both linguistic and attitudinal constraints on dialect shift&nbsp;<span lang="EN-US">while work on children has shed light on the processes by which kids change their speech patterns in response to new community input.</span></span></p> <p><span lang="EN-US"><span lang="EN-US"><span lang="EN-US">Research on long-term second dialect acquisition by mobile adults is less common, though has similarly sought to tease apart the linguistic, social, and exposure-based factors that influence dialect change. Moreover,&nbsp;<span lang="EN-US">no studies address dialect acquisition among adults moving within-nation from an urban region to a rural one &ndash; that is, native speakers of varieties seen as standard who are exposed to less-prestigious dialect input.&nbsp;<span lang="EN-US">This project filled this gap by examining dialect use among Korean speakers, focusing on two groups of mobile people (and two field sites): people who have moved from Seoul to Kyungsang province as well as people who have moved from Kyungsang province to Seoul.&nbsp;</span></span></span></span></span>This study will contribute to the literature on adult second dialect acquisition in situations of dialect contact between mutually intelligible but regionally different varieties.</p> <p>In addition,&nbsp;sociolinguistic interviews with each of the 62 mobile speakers were  transcribed. These transcriptions and their associated audio files will ultimately form the  basis of a corpus that can be shared with other researchers who are interested in the study  of second dialect acquisition and variation within Korean. The findings from this study  can also contribute to forensic investigations, which can be applied in speaker profiling  and forensic voice comparison such as identifying salient speaker characteristics and  inferring information about place of birth and current residence. This study can also aid&nbsp;speech recognition and speech-to-text technologies by training voice technology systems  to improve the recognition of accented speech by mobile speakers.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><span lang="EN-US"><span lang="EN-US"><br /></span></span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/13/2022<br>      Modified by: Yoojin&nbsp;Kang</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project examines the acquisition of second dialect features by mobile  speakers relocating between two regions, one urban and characterized by a prestigious  dialect, and one rural, whose dialect is stigmatized. The participants in this study are 62  Korean speakers in two field sites: Seoul city and North Kyungsang province in South  Korea. This dissertation examines how mobile adult speakers acquire new dialect features. Several findings emerge from this project. Most of the speakers in both mobile  groups produce the Seoul-Korean-like distinction between /&#623;/ and /&#652;/, Seoul-Korean-like  /w&#593;/ diphthongization and do not show the North-Kyungsang-Korean-like word-initial  tensification and North Kyungsang Korean tones. I argue that the overall result that the  vast majority of mobile speakers produce the Seoul Korean features is related to both linguistic and  extralinguistic factors: Linguistic complexity, salience of features, speakers’ pre-existing  phonetic repertoire, high instrumental motivation, linguistic insecurity, and speaker  identity.  The study of second dialect acquisition is a fairly new focus in sociolinguistic research. As Chambers points out, mobile speakers were "purposely excluded" from early dialectology research; instead, dialectologists focused on the speech of nonmobile, older, rural, male speakers (known as NORMs), whose speech was seen as unaffected by contact with other varieties. Since then, however, scholars have acknowledged that dialect contact itself is a phenomenon worth studying, and that the outcomes of contact may enable researchers to answer linguistic and social questions. For example, studies of short-term accommodation by adult speakers exposed to new dialect input has revealed both linguistic and attitudinal constraints on dialect shift while work on children has shed light on the processes by which kids change their speech patterns in response to new community input.  Research on long-term second dialect acquisition by mobile adults is less common, though has similarly sought to tease apart the linguistic, social, and exposure-based factors that influence dialect change. Moreover, no studies address dialect acquisition among adults moving within-nation from an urban region to a rural one &ndash; that is, native speakers of varieties seen as standard who are exposed to less-prestigious dialect input. This project filled this gap by examining dialect use among Korean speakers, focusing on two groups of mobile people (and two field sites): people who have moved from Seoul to Kyungsang province as well as people who have moved from Kyungsang province to Seoul. This study will contribute to the literature on adult second dialect acquisition in situations of dialect contact between mutually intelligible but regionally different varieties.  In addition, sociolinguistic interviews with each of the 62 mobile speakers were  transcribed. These transcriptions and their associated audio files will ultimately form the  basis of a corpus that can be shared with other researchers who are interested in the study  of second dialect acquisition and variation within Korean. The findings from this study  can also contribute to forensic investigations, which can be applied in speaker profiling  and forensic voice comparison such as identifying salient speaker characteristics and  inferring information about place of birth and current residence. This study can also aid speech recognition and speech-to-text technologies by training voice technology systems  to improve the recognition of accented speech by mobile speakers.             Last Modified: 12/13/2022       Submitted by: Yoojin Kang]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
