<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I: Automated In-Situ High-Resolution COVID-19 Wastewater-Based Epidemiology]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>256000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>256000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rajesh Mehta</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rmehta@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922174</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact of this SBIR Phase I project addresses the monitoring needs via wastewater-based epidemiology of current and emerging viruses that pose high risks to public health. With the rapidly evolving nature of the pandemic situation and the recent emergence of the coronavirus variants, one common concern is that the virus variants are more contagious than their predecessors, and will likely spread quickly within communities without early detection and warning. Other concerns are that future mutations may not be covered by existing vaccines, in which case early monitoring through high resolution wastewater-based epidemiology will become one of the only effective means of providing early alerts of the presence of such mutated virus variants within local communities. With a wide adaptation of the proposed instrumentation by municipalities, large and small communities such as college campuses and senior care facilities, the project enables the early detection and monitoring of the current coronavirus and its variants during the pandemic. The technology can also be extended to other emerging viruses with risks of community spread in the years to follow, not only in wastewater but also in widespread environmental and recreational water quality monitoring.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed project is a highly-optimized reverse transcription quantitative polymerase chain reaction (RT-qPCR) approach for in-situ sampling and analysis, and the realization of a corresponding instrumentation platform that is applicable to the early detection and monitoring of different viruses, including the current coronavirus (SARS-CoV-2), its variants, and other emerging viruses. The proposed technology aims to reduce the time-to-result compared to current wastewater-based epidemiology approaches while minimizing cost and logistics.  The effort will include the testing of several protocols that are amendable to adaption for automated in-situ SARS-CoV-2 measurement, followed by the selection and optimization of the most suitable one. The protocols will be subsequently tested and validated using spiked samples, along with appropriate positive and negative controls. The approach will implement, for the first time in an automated device, the latest advances in molecular biology protocols, such as extraction-free single-step RT-qPCR. The project strives to achieve the first in-situ RT-qPCR available, with the potential to completely revolutionize the fields of wastewater-based epidemiology, general environmental testing and source tracking.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/31/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/13/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041, 47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2041400</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Joyce</FirstName>
<LastName>Wong</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Joyce Wong</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[j.wong@fluidion.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000751226</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/31/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>FLUIDION US Inc.</Name>
<CityName>PASADENA</CityName>
<ZipCode>911075050</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6267655580</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>396 S SAN MARINO AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>28</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA28</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>KJA2G1FKF6C3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>FLUIDION US, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[FLUIDION US Inc.]]></Name>
<CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>900132217</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[525 S. Hewitt Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>34</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA34</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1238</Code>
<Text>TECH FOR SUSTAINABLE ENVIRONMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~256000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Phase I High-Resolution Water Based Epidemiology (HR-WBE) project focused on the development of an accurate and reliable automated technology for detecting and quantifying specific DNA and RNA targets in various types of water samples, including wastewater as well as ambient and recreational water, on a fully automated <em>in-situ</em> testing platform. The project leverages DNA/RNA quantification capability in conjunction with automated and autonomous field-deployable instruments to provide a game-changing innovation, significantly reducing analysis time and providing capability to target specific waterborne pathogens and indicator organisms directly, through their nucleic acids.</p> <p>During Phase I of the HR-WBE project, a protocol for the quantification of nucleic acids in water-based environmental samples was successfully developed and optimized. Its compatibility with automation and feasibility in various water matrices was demonstrated. The corresponding assays for key water quality markers have also been developed and tested. The resulting optimized DNA/RNA quantification protocol has proven effective for SARS-CoV-2 and other relevant targets, and our modified master mix composition has shown long-term stability at room temperature. Additionally, the nucleic acid extraction process has been simplified to make it compatible with field instrumentation. The technical feasibility of the DNA/RNA quantification approach has been established for the HR-WBE project, validating the potential for implementation in automated and portable field-use devices that will be developed in Phase II, if awarded, capable in performing community level surveillance of existing bacteria and viruses which can provide early warning and minimize public health risk.&nbsp;</p> <p>The HR-WBE project has immense potential to improve public health and environmental surveillance by rapidly quantifying pathogen markers, and by providing real-time monitoring of the safety of drinking, recreational and process waters. The HR-WBE technology can be easily deployed in a variety of scenarios and independently of existing infrastructure, including in disadvantaged communities. By equipping decision-makers with timely and accurate data and offering unprecedented adaptability through autonomous deployment and remote operation, HR-WBE will revolutionize the management of water resources and public health surveillance, fostering healthier, more resilient communities worldwide. HR-WBE's ease of use, minimal training requirements, centralized data management, and cost-effectiveness play a crucial role in creating a solid foundation for widespread positive impact across various societal layers. Its commercialization will also promote scientific discovery, broadening participation, improving research infrastructure, providing long-term societal benefits and directly contributing to economic growth.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/04/2023<br>      Modified by: Joyce&nbsp;Wong</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Phase I High-Resolution Water Based Epidemiology (HR-WBE) project focused on the development of an accurate and reliable automated technology for detecting and quantifying specific DNA and RNA targets in various types of water samples, including wastewater as well as ambient and recreational water, on a fully automated in-situ testing platform. The project leverages DNA/RNA quantification capability in conjunction with automated and autonomous field-deployable instruments to provide a game-changing innovation, significantly reducing analysis time and providing capability to target specific waterborne pathogens and indicator organisms directly, through their nucleic acids.  During Phase I of the HR-WBE project, a protocol for the quantification of nucleic acids in water-based environmental samples was successfully developed and optimized. Its compatibility with automation and feasibility in various water matrices was demonstrated. The corresponding assays for key water quality markers have also been developed and tested. The resulting optimized DNA/RNA quantification protocol has proven effective for SARS-CoV-2 and other relevant targets, and our modified master mix composition has shown long-term stability at room temperature. Additionally, the nucleic acid extraction process has been simplified to make it compatible with field instrumentation. The technical feasibility of the DNA/RNA quantification approach has been established for the HR-WBE project, validating the potential for implementation in automated and portable field-use devices that will be developed in Phase II, if awarded, capable in performing community level surveillance of existing bacteria and viruses which can provide early warning and minimize public health risk.   The HR-WBE project has immense potential to improve public health and environmental surveillance by rapidly quantifying pathogen markers, and by providing real-time monitoring of the safety of drinking, recreational and process waters. The HR-WBE technology can be easily deployed in a variety of scenarios and independently of existing infrastructure, including in disadvantaged communities. By equipping decision-makers with timely and accurate data and offering unprecedented adaptability through autonomous deployment and remote operation, HR-WBE will revolutionize the management of water resources and public health surveillance, fostering healthier, more resilient communities worldwide. HR-WBE's ease of use, minimal training requirements, centralized data management, and cost-effectiveness play a crucial role in creating a solid foundation for widespread positive impact across various societal layers. Its commercialization will also promote scientific discovery, broadening participation, improving research infrastructure, providing long-term societal benefits and directly contributing to economic growth.       Last Modified: 05/04/2023       Submitted by: Joyce Wong]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
