<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Aspire's Inclusive Faculty Framework Professional Development Series Building DEI Capacity in the INCLUDES National Network to Broaden Participation in STEM]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>91099.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>91099</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jolene Jesse</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jjesse@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927303</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[As our nation faces new and persistent challenges, university faculty and administrators, higher education leaders, and disciplinary and professional societies are all grappling with the need to build skills to transform teaching and overall institutional practices in ways that are more inclusive and equitable. The Aspire Alliance, co-led by the Association of Public &amp; Land-grant Universities (APLU) and the University of Wisconsin, Madison, has created Aspire’s Inclusive Faculty Framework (IFF) which provides opportunities for higher education professionals to acquire skills through three domains: understanding identity, intercultural awareness, and relational competencies. These domains, and the knowledge, skills, and attitudes associated with them, comprise a transferable set of inclusive practices that are applicable across the many roles faculty play within their careers (e.g., instructor, advisor, mentor, colleague, leader).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;With this award, the Aspire Alliance will host six, 1.5-hour synchronous, online seminars and develop a facilitation guide that will support participants to create ongoing local initiatives to further explore diversity, equity, and inclusion (DEI) in STEM. The Professional Development Series, will bring together topic experts, members of the broader NSF INCLUDES Network, other NSF initiatives, as well as disciplinary and professional societies, to build DEI capacity through a Community of Practice (CoP) model of regular interactions of people sharing a passion and learning together. This capacity building professional development approach has emerged from the development of Aspire’s Inclusive Faculty Framework (IFF). The IFF flips the traditional faculty development workshop model, which tends to focus on a single faculty role, to instead provide opportunities for higher education professionals to acquire skills framed in the context of understanding identity, intercultural concepts, and relationships applicable across all the roles faculty play in their careers. The series will begin in the Fall 2020 and conclude in Winter 2021.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/17/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/14/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2041006</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Robin</FirstName>
<LastName>Parent</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Robin A Parent</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[rparent@aplu.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000816616</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/17/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Travis</FirstName>
<LastName>York</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>T</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Travis T York</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[tyork@aaas.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000720967</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/17/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Association of Public and Land-Grant Universities</Name>
<CityName>WASHINGTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>200054825</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2024786084</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1220 L ST NW STE 1000</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>HKWACGZ96DK5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ASSOCIATION OF PUBLIC AND LAND-GRANT UNIVERSITIES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Association of Public and Land-Grant Universities]]></Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>200054722</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>152Y</Code>
<Text>Accelerating Discovery in Ed</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8212</Code>
<Text>Broaden Particip STEM Resrch</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0420</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~91099</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-3f204604-7fff-5583-7eee-07c4fff87d17"> <p dir="ltr">The major goals of the Equity in Action: Inclusive Professional Development Series were to:</p> <ul> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span><span>Host six, 1.5 hour synchronous, online seminar anchored by the Aspire Inclusive Professional Framework (IPF)</span></span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span><span>Develop a self-reflection guide to support continued engagement with the IPF.&nbsp;</span></span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span><span>Develop a pilot Community of Practice (CoP) for STEM faculty, staff, and institutional leaders to continue and deepen capacity around seminar topics.&nbsp;</span></span></p> </li> </ul> <p dir="ltr"><span><span>The Aspire Alliance hosted six, 1.5-hour synchronous, online seminars grounded through the Aspire Inclusive Professional Framework over the course of nine months. These sessions were co-developed with leading experts to share expertise and resources surrounding developing and supporting inclusive environments across institutional roles. This work is critical to supporting underrepresented STEM students, faculty, and colleagues in higher education.&nbsp;&nbsp;</span></span></p> <p dir="ltr"><strong>Intellectual Merit:</strong></p> <p dir="ltr"><span><span>These capacity building professional development approaches emerged from the development of&nbsp;</span></span><a title="IPF" href="https://sites.google.com/view/aspire-alliance/national-change/inclusive-professional-framework?authuser=0" target="_blank">Aspire&rsquo;s Inclusive Professional Framework (IPF)</a>. The IPF is a holistic approach to professional development, and provides opportunities for higher education professionals to acquire skills through three domains. This framework flips the traditional faculty development workshop model, which tends to focus on a role, to instead provide skills framed in the context of understanding social and cultural identities, intercultural concepts, and interpersonal relationships. The IPF model was piloted through the Aspire Summer Institute (ASI) in June 2020, as a week-long intensive synchronous and asynchronous online institute. As a pilot, the ASI included 37 faculty and faculty developers from 17 institutions. The positive feedback from participants, and requests for continued support, led Aspire to explore opportunities for ongoing engagement through this series.</p> <p dir="ltr"><strong>Broader Impacts:</strong></p> <p dir="ltr"><span><span>Aspire&rsquo;s seminar series was designed to focus on social equity/social justice topics in higher education and to support participants&rsquo; development of new skills in equitable and inclusive practices. The development of these skills and persons&rsquo; capacities to effectively conduct such work hold the potential for impact in their current projects and, moreover, their work to come. As such, the development of these capacities, and fostering of continued learning and engagement through a CoP, have the potential for far-reaching effects including the adoption of inclusive teaching, research, and leadership practices which may impact participants' work and most importantly the experiences of their URG students for decades to come.</span></span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Resources and materials can be found by visiting the <a title="Equity in Action PD Series" href="https://sites.google.com/view/aspire-alliance/equity-in-action-pd-series?authuser=0" target="_blank">Equity in Action PD Series</a> webpage.&nbsp;</span></p> <div><strong>Key Findings:</strong></div> <div></div> <div><strong>Learning Outcomes</strong> &ndash; participants reported low-moderate to high achievement of learning outcomes related to increases in <em>awareness</em> and <em>confidence</em>. See individual sections below.</div> <div></div> <div><strong>Potential Impact</strong> &ndash; Participants estimated that collectively, they teach 3184, advise 2126, and mentor 394 <em><span style="text-decoration: underline;">undergraduates</span></em> per semester. Notably, they also train 1565 faculty members, teach 446 graduate students, advise 394 faculty members, and train 275 graduate students per semester.</div> <div></div> <div><strong>Satisfaction</strong>&nbsp; &ndash; participants reported high satisfaction for all events.</div> <div></div> <div><strong>Implementation Preparation</strong>&nbsp; &ndash; generally, participants reported that the events helped them to prepare to implement inclusive faculty practices.</div> <div></div> <div><strong>Likelihood to Apply</strong>&nbsp; &ndash; generally, participants reported a high likelihood to apply what they learned from the sessions</div> </span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/07/2021<br>      Modified by: Robin&nbsp;A&nbsp;Parent</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  The major goals of the Equity in Action: Inclusive Professional Development Series were to:   Host six, 1.5 hour synchronous, online seminar anchored by the Aspire Inclusive Professional Framework (IPF)   Develop a self-reflection guide to support continued engagement with the IPF.    Develop a pilot Community of Practice (CoP) for STEM faculty, staff, and institutional leaders to continue and deepen capacity around seminar topics.    The Aspire Alliance hosted six, 1.5-hour synchronous, online seminars grounded through the Aspire Inclusive Professional Framework over the course of nine months. These sessions were co-developed with leading experts to share expertise and resources surrounding developing and supporting inclusive environments across institutional roles. This work is critical to supporting underrepresented STEM students, faculty, and colleagues in higher education.   Intellectual Merit: These capacity building professional development approaches emerged from the development of Aspire’s Inclusive Professional Framework (IPF). The IPF is a holistic approach to professional development, and provides opportunities for higher education professionals to acquire skills through three domains. This framework flips the traditional faculty development workshop model, which tends to focus on a role, to instead provide skills framed in the context of understanding social and cultural identities, intercultural concepts, and interpersonal relationships. The IPF model was piloted through the Aspire Summer Institute (ASI) in June 2020, as a week-long intensive synchronous and asynchronous online institute. As a pilot, the ASI included 37 faculty and faculty developers from 17 institutions. The positive feedback from participants, and requests for continued support, led Aspire to explore opportunities for ongoing engagement through this series. Broader Impacts: Aspire’s seminar series was designed to focus on social equity/social justice topics in higher education and to support participants’ development of new skills in equitable and inclusive practices. The development of these skills and persons’ capacities to effectively conduct such work hold the potential for impact in their current projects and, moreover, their work to come. As such, the development of these capacities, and fostering of continued learning and engagement through a CoP, have the potential for far-reaching effects including the adoption of inclusive teaching, research, and leadership practices which may impact participants' work and most importantly the experiences of their URG students for decades to come. Resources and materials can be found by visiting the Equity in Action PD Series webpage.  Key Findings:  Learning Outcomes &ndash; participants reported low-moderate to high achievement of learning outcomes related to increases in awareness and confidence. See individual sections below.  Potential Impact &ndash; Participants estimated that collectively, they teach 3184, advise 2126, and mentor 394 undergraduates per semester. Notably, they also train 1565 faculty members, teach 446 graduate students, advise 394 faculty members, and train 275 graduate students per semester.  Satisfaction  &ndash; participants reported high satisfaction for all events.  Implementation Preparation  &ndash; generally, participants reported that the events helped them to prepare to implement inclusive faculty practices.  Likelihood to Apply  &ndash; generally, participants reported a high likelihood to apply what they learned from the sessions        Last Modified: 10/07/2021       Submitted by: Robin A Parent]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
