<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Doctoral Dissertation Research: Genetic and evolutionary determinants of the immune response in wild primates]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>31649.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>31649</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rebecca Ferrell</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rferrell@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927850</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Viruses and bacteria are thought to have played an important role in shaping primate evolution, but many open questions remain about how pathogens have acted to change primate genomes and influence trait diversity. More can be learned about the types of pathogens that have been most important in primate evolution, the types of genetic variants that have arisen to deal with these threats, and whether genetic variation in immune genes influences fitness-related traits in the present. This doctoral dissertation project studies the regulation of genes involved in immune defense in a wild primate system, focusing on an intensively studied population for which demographic, behavioral, and physiological data are also available. The doctoral student investigates how natural selection has shaped the gene expression response to pathogens in the past, and examines associations between immune-related gene expression variation, dominance rank, and other physiological characteristics. The project supports student mentorship and training opportunities, international research collaborations, and public science engagement through museum and conference events. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The investigator measures genome-wide gene expression in either the presence or absence of stimuli that model bacterial or viral infection, for 160 individually recognized adult baboons. Differences in immune responses are examined for linkages to genetic differences between baboons, controlling for age, dominance rank, kinship, and other factors that also influence immune function. Integrating these findings with genome sequences from the same baboon population, the project investigates whether genes involved in the immune response to bacteria and/or viruses have been the target of historic or recent selection and tests whether genetic variation that influences the immune response also affects traits that are important to current physiological wellbeing and fitness.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/09/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/20/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2041621</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jenny</FirstName>
<LastName>Tung</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jenny Tung</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jt5@duke.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000238558</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/09/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jordan</FirstName>
<LastName>Anderson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jordan A Anderson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jordan.a.anderson@duke.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000829451</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/09/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Duke University</Name>
<CityName>DURHAM</CityName>
<ZipCode>277054640</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9196843030</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2200 W MAIN ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>TP7EK8DZV6N5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>DUKE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Duke University]]></Name>
<CityName>Durham</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>277054010</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2200 W. Main St, Suite 710]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7608</Code>
<Text>Bio Anthro DDRI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1392</Code>
<Text>Biological Anthropology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~31649</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Summary and intellectual merit:&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</strong></p> <p>Disease-causing pathogens have been an important selective force throughout primate evolution. How individuals identify and respond to invading pathogens affects their health and lifespan, and thus directly translates to differences in fertility and survival&mdash;the currencies of evolutionary fitness. Consequently, much of primate adaptive evolution has been centered on the immune system, which detects and coordinates responses to pathogens. These responses in turn require changes in gene regulation, which recent studies suggest are important targets of natural selection within and between human populations.</p> <p>Despite long-standing interest in the role of disease in primate evolution, little is known about the evolution of the gene regulatory response to pathogens in other primates, especially in natural populations. To address this gap, this project took advantage of a nearly 50-year field study of wild baboons in Kenya to understand how genetic differences between individuals affect the gene regulatory response to viral and bacterial stimuli. We collected blood from known individuals in this population and measured how cells in these samples respond to compounds that mimic bacterial and viral infection. We found widespread evidence for genetic differences between individuals that affect how they respond at the level of gene expression, one of the earliest changes detectable in immune cells. We also found that gene expression differences between two species of baboons that hybridize in this population are important targets of natural selection. Our results suggest that pathogens are an important driver of gene expression evolution in wild primates and point to genetic differences between individuals that may influence their success in the wild. Together, our findings contribute to a key question in biological anthropology: how selective pressures have shaped biodiversity in primates living today. Our project therefore serves as a model for how genomic approaches can be used to characterize the immune response in wild populations.&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts</strong></p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; The proposed work has had four broader impacts. First, it supported mentorship and training opportunities for a collaborating Duke PhD student and a Master&rsquo;s student at the Jomo Kenyatta University of Agriculture and Technology in Kenya. In doing so, it also provided teaching and mentorship training to the Co-PI. Second, the proposed project facilitated scientific training and capacity building in Kenya more broadly, by supporting a free-to-attend, two-day training seminar for Kenyan researchers and students at the Institute of Primate Research in Nairobi in field-based molecular genetic methods (e.g., lightweight DNA extraction, mobile sequencing techniques and analysis) led by the PI and co-PI. Third, the project contributed to the scientific and professional training of the co-PI by extending his thesis beyond its initial scope. The resulting data, code, and lab protocols will also help support similar work in evolutionary anthropology and related fields. Fourth, this project supported ongoing collaborations between the Amboseli Baboon Research Project and scientists and field staff in Kenya, including co-authorships on 3 recent publications.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/05/2023<br>      Modified by: Jordan&nbsp;A&nbsp;Anderson</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Summary and intellectual merit:     Disease-causing pathogens have been an important selective force throughout primate evolution. How individuals identify and respond to invading pathogens affects their health and lifespan, and thus directly translates to differences in fertility and survival&mdash;the currencies of evolutionary fitness. Consequently, much of primate adaptive evolution has been centered on the immune system, which detects and coordinates responses to pathogens. These responses in turn require changes in gene regulation, which recent studies suggest are important targets of natural selection within and between human populations.  Despite long-standing interest in the role of disease in primate evolution, little is known about the evolution of the gene regulatory response to pathogens in other primates, especially in natural populations. To address this gap, this project took advantage of a nearly 50-year field study of wild baboons in Kenya to understand how genetic differences between individuals affect the gene regulatory response to viral and bacterial stimuli. We collected blood from known individuals in this population and measured how cells in these samples respond to compounds that mimic bacterial and viral infection. We found widespread evidence for genetic differences between individuals that affect how they respond at the level of gene expression, one of the earliest changes detectable in immune cells. We also found that gene expression differences between two species of baboons that hybridize in this population are important targets of natural selection. Our results suggest that pathogens are an important driver of gene expression evolution in wild primates and point to genetic differences between individuals that may influence their success in the wild. Together, our findings contribute to a key question in biological anthropology: how selective pressures have shaped biodiversity in primates living today. Our project therefore serves as a model for how genomic approaches can be used to characterize the immune response in wild populations.   Broader Impacts              The proposed work has had four broader impacts. First, it supported mentorship and training opportunities for a collaborating Duke PhD student and a Master’s student at the Jomo Kenyatta University of Agriculture and Technology in Kenya. In doing so, it also provided teaching and mentorship training to the Co-PI. Second, the proposed project facilitated scientific training and capacity building in Kenya more broadly, by supporting a free-to-attend, two-day training seminar for Kenyan researchers and students at the Institute of Primate Research in Nairobi in field-based molecular genetic methods (e.g., lightweight DNA extraction, mobile sequencing techniques and analysis) led by the PI and co-PI. Third, the project contributed to the scientific and professional training of the co-PI by extending his thesis beyond its initial scope. The resulting data, code, and lab protocols will also help support similar work in evolutionary anthropology and related fields. Fourth, this project supported ongoing collaborations between the Amboseli Baboon Research Project and scientists and field staff in Kenya, including co-authorships on 3 recent publications.             Last Modified: 08/05/2023       Submitted by: Jordan A Anderson]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
