<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Emerging Areas of Science, Engineering, and Medicine for the Courts: A Workshop to Identify Chapters for a Fourth Edition of The Reference Manual on Scientific Evidence]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Reginald Sheehan</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rsheehan@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925389</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The Reference Manual on Scientific Evidence is a primary reference source for federal judges on questions of science in litigation.  It is used not only by federal judges, but by state judges, attorneys, legal scholars, and law students.  Its utility and widespread use is the result of the fair and balanced presentation it provides of fundamental principles of scientific methodology in areas likely to arise in expert testimony. Nine years have passed since the publication of the last (third) edition of the Reference Manual, and many of the chapters need updating to account for recent developments in science and law. For example, chapters on forensic science and DNA identification need updating to take into account new genetic testing techniques and methodologies, the chapter on neuroscience must take account of new approaches for detecting neural activity. A new edition will also need to address areas of science that have become important in litigation in recent years, e.g., computer software; prediction of dangerous behavior/genetic foundations of individual behavior; eyewitness identification; and climate change. The Committee on Science, Technology, and Law of the National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine, in collaboration with the Federal Judicial Center – the research and education agency of the judicial branch of the U.S. government – have agreed to pursue the development of a fourth edition of the Reference Manual and will convene a workshop to review the contents of the third edition and identify areas of science and technology that may be candidates for new or updated chapters in a new edition. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A planning committee of 6-8 members equally divided between the legal and scientific/engineering/medical communities will be convened to plan the two-day virtual workshop. Working via conference calls, staff and the committee will define the workshop agenda, format, and topics and identify speakers. A rapporteur-authored proceedings in brief for the workshop will be issued to provide information that will be useful in the development of a fourth edition of the Reference Manual on Scientific Evidence.  The workshop will advance the proper use and evaluation of scientific evidence in court by assisting judges in understanding scientific and technical information, thereby strengthening their understanding of the complex information that may be at issue in such disputes and their ability to engage in an informed conversation with lawyers, officers of the court, court-appointed experts, and others who seek to inform the court regarding relevant scientific and technical information.  Making the best use of available evidence helps the judiciary ensure that all people are treated justly in the courts.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/03/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/03/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2041530</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Anne-Marie</FirstName>
<LastName>Mazza</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Anne-Marie Mazza</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[amazza@nas.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000206373</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/03/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>National Academy of Sciences</Name>
<CityName>WASHINGTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>204180007</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2023342254</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2101 CONSTITUTION AVE NW</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>PKFJZHG2MLG9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NATIONAL ACADEMY OF SCIENCES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>PKFJZHG2MLG9</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[National Academy of Sciences]]></Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>200012721</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[500 Fifth Street NW]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>128Y</Code>
<Text>Law &amp; Science</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>On February 24-25, 2021, an ad hoc committee convened under the auspices of the National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine's Committee on Science, Technology, and Law (the Committee on Emerging Areas of Science, Engineering, and Medicine for the Courts: Identifying Chapters for a Fourth Edition of The Reference Manual on Scientific Evidence) hosted a virtual workshop to review the contents of the most recent edition of the <em>Reference Manual of Scientific Evidence</em> and explore emerging areas of science and technology that may have implications for the Courts and that may be candidates for new or updated chapters in a new edition. The workshop will provide valuable input to the development of the content of a fourth edition of the <em>Reference Manual on Scientific Evidence, </em>a critical resource in efforts to stimulate improved judicial decision making in cases where complex scientific evidence is presented.&nbsp; Making the best use of available evidence not only allows judges to fulfil the gatekeeper role assigned to them in the 1993 U.S. Supreme Court decision in <em>Daubert v. Merrell Dow Pharmaceuticals, Inc.</em>: it helps the judiciary ensure that all people are treated justly in the courts.</p> <p>The workshop planning committee held three virtual meetings and numerous conference calls to plan the event, which featured moderated panel discussions on: 1) Challenges in Evaluating Scientific Evidence in Court; 2) Emerging Issues in the Climate and Environmental Sciences; 3) Emerging Issues in Computer Science and Information Technology; 4) Emerging Issues in the Biological Sciences; and 5) Emerging areas in Psychology, Data, and Statistical Sciences. In addition, the workshop included a presentation that provided an overview of the <em>Reference Manual on Scientific Evidence</em>.</p> <p>The complete workshop agenda and workshop planning committee roster is available at: <a href="https://www.nationalacademies.org/event/02-24-2021/emerging-areas-of-science-engineering-and-medicine-for-the-courts-identifying-chapters-for-a-fourth-edition-of-the-reference-manual-on-scientific-evidence-virtual-workshop">https://www.nationalacademies.org/event/02-24-2021/emerging-areas-of-science-engineering-and-medicine-for-the-courts-identifying-chapters-for-a-fourth-edition-of-the-reference-manual-on-scientific-evidence-virtual-workshop</a>.&nbsp; Video of the event is available at <a href="https://vimeo.com/showcase/8214181">https://vimeo.com/showcase/8214181</a>. A proceedings of the workshop was published under the title <em>Emerging Areas of Science, Engineering, and Medicine for the Courts: Proceedings of a Workshop&ndash;in Brief</em> by the National Academies Press. The proceedings are available at: <a href="https://www.nap.edu/catalog/26231/emerging-areas-of-scienceengineering-and-medicine-for-the-courts">https://www.nap.edu/catalog/26231/emerging-areas-of-scienceengineering-and-medicine-for-the-courts</a>.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/15/2021<br>      Modified by: Anne-Marie&nbsp;Mazza</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ On February 24-25, 2021, an ad hoc committee convened under the auspices of the National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine's Committee on Science, Technology, and Law (the Committee on Emerging Areas of Science, Engineering, and Medicine for the Courts: Identifying Chapters for a Fourth Edition of The Reference Manual on Scientific Evidence) hosted a virtual workshop to review the contents of the most recent edition of the Reference Manual of Scientific Evidence and explore emerging areas of science and technology that may have implications for the Courts and that may be candidates for new or updated chapters in a new edition. The workshop will provide valuable input to the development of the content of a fourth edition of the Reference Manual on Scientific Evidence, a critical resource in efforts to stimulate improved judicial decision making in cases where complex scientific evidence is presented.  Making the best use of available evidence not only allows judges to fulfil the gatekeeper role assigned to them in the 1993 U.S. Supreme Court decision in Daubert v. Merrell Dow Pharmaceuticals, Inc.: it helps the judiciary ensure that all people are treated justly in the courts.  The workshop planning committee held three virtual meetings and numerous conference calls to plan the event, which featured moderated panel discussions on: 1) Challenges in Evaluating Scientific Evidence in Court; 2) Emerging Issues in the Climate and Environmental Sciences; 3) Emerging Issues in Computer Science and Information Technology; 4) Emerging Issues in the Biological Sciences; and 5) Emerging areas in Psychology, Data, and Statistical Sciences. In addition, the workshop included a presentation that provided an overview of the Reference Manual on Scientific Evidence.  The complete workshop agenda and workshop planning committee roster is available at: https://www.nationalacademies.org/event/02-24-2021/emerging-areas-of-science-engineering-and-medicine-for-the-courts-identifying-chapters-for-a-fourth-edition-of-the-reference-manual-on-scientific-evidence-virtual-workshop.  Video of the event is available at https://vimeo.com/showcase/8214181. A proceedings of the workshop was published under the title Emerging Areas of Science, Engineering, and Medicine for the Courts: Proceedings of a Workshop&ndash;in Brief by the National Academies Press. The proceedings are available at: https://www.nap.edu/catalog/26231/emerging-areas-of-scienceengineering-and-medicine-for-the-courts.       Last Modified: 09/15/2021       Submitted by: Anne-Marie Mazza]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
