<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Doctoral Dissertation Research: Evolution of the forelimbs of suspensory primates]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>6439.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>6439</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rebecca Ferrell</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rferrell@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927850</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Biological adaptations are often observed to have evolved multiple times within a group of species. This phenomenon may be related to the occurrence of particular co-occurring traits within a group of species that make the evolution of some adaptations more likely than others. Among primate groups that use suspensory locomotion, this pattern of movement seems to have evolved multiple times independently. This doctoral dissertation project investigates how covariation among biological traits within the forelimbs of primates affected the trajectory of their evolution. The project contributes to an emerging understanding of how covariation of traits impacts the evolution of new body plans, in particular the evolution of humans’ distinct form of upright walking. In addition to training a graduate student, this project generates a large dataset that can be used to train undergraduate and high school students in study design, statistics, and computer coding. The doctoral student plans to publish short, public-oriented video abstracts of this project’s results, creating a direct link between active scientists and the public.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project studies how changes in the way biological traits covary can affect the trajectory of evolution, potentially making specific adaptive suites more common in certain clades while inhibiting their evolution in other groups. The investigator plans to collect 3-dimensional data on the forelimb bones of primates from across the order, use evolutionarily informed statistics to identify traits that are associated with frequent suspensory behaviors, and examine how these traits covary in suspensory taxa and their close relatives using matrices. Different hypotheses about the evolution of suspension in primates predict different strengths and patterns of trait covariation in suspensory vs non-suspensory groups. The extent to which the common ancestors of humans, chimpanzees, and other apes were adapted for suspension is under active debate. By studying how suspension evolved in primates, this study will contribute to our understanding of early human evolution.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/06/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/20/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2041700</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jeffrey</FirstName>
<LastName>Spear</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jeffrey Spear</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jks417@nyu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000818699</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/06/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Scott</FirstName>
<LastName>Williams</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Scott A Williams</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[sawilliams@nyu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000701518</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/06/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>New York University</Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<ZipCode>100121019</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2129982121</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>70 WASHINGTON SQ S</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NX9PXMKW5KW8</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NEW YORK UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[New York University]]></Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>100121019</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[70 WASHINGTON SQUARE S]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7608</Code>
<Text>Bio Anthro DDRI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1392</Code>
<Text>Biological Anthropology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~6439</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span style="font-family: Liberation Serif, serif;"><span style="font-size: small;"><span style="background: #ffffff;"><span style="font-weight: normal;">Why do we walk upright on two legs when no other animals do? Why can we raise our arms above our heads when so few other animals can? Why do we get herniated discs in our back? The answer to all of these questions and more lies in our evolutionary history.</span></span></span></span></p> <p><span style="font-family: Liberation Serif, serif;"><span style="font-size: small;"><span style="background: #ffffff;"><span style="font-weight: normal;">In this project, we try to understand how our evolutionary history shapes our bodies. Specifically, we are trying to untangle the way that suspensory behaviors have impacted that history. Suspensory behaviors are behaviors where an animal is underneath the object that supports their weight, rather than on top of it. A sloth hanging from a tree or a child swinging across monkey bars are both examples of suspensory behaviors.</span></span></span></span></p> <p><span style="font-family: Liberation Serif, serif;"><span style="font-size: small;"><span style="background: #ffffff;"><span style="font-weight: normal;">Contrary to what is implied by the name &lsquo;monkey bars&rsquo;, however, the vast majority of monkeys are not suspensory &ndash; they would not use monkey bars the way we do, and instead would scramble across the top of them rather than swinging underneath. Indeed, many are unable to hold their arms over their head in a way that would even allow them to swing underneath monkey bars. But apes, the group of primates of which we are a part, do regularly use suspensory behaviors and most (including humans!) can and would cross monkey bars by swinging beneath them.</span></span></span></span></p> <p><span style="font-family: Liberation Serif, serif;"><span style="font-size: small;"><span style="background: #ffffff;"><span style="font-weight: normal;">So apes evolved the ability to be suspensory and we inherited that from our common ancestor, right? Well, as it turns out, it&rsquo;s far more complicated than that. There is a startling lack of evidence for suspensory adaptations in the fossil record of apes, leading many researchers to argue that some or even all living apes evolved the ability to be suspensory independently of one another. The question of how we explain the evolution of suspension multiple times within one small group of primates but almost never within all other groups of primates is the subject of a lively debate among scientists of human evolution.</span></span></span></span></p> <p><span style="font-family: Liberation Serif, serif;"><span style="font-size: small;"><span style="background: #ffffff;"><span style="font-weight: normal;">One commonly referenced hypothesis for why a certain adaptation might evolve multiple times in one group of animals but not in other, related groups, is that there is a shift in the way those traits develop and are correlated, making it easier for evolution to create certain adaptations but not others. For example, the length of arms and legs are highly correlated. If natural selection favors individuals with long arms and long legs, that variant already exists in the population and evolution will happen quickly. If instead evolution favors long arms and short legs, individuals meeting that description are much rarer, and evolution will happen more slowly, if at all. So perhaps, the thinking goes, early in the evolution of apes there was a change in the way some traits are correlated that made it easier to evolve adaptations useful for suspension.</span></span></span></span></p> <p><span style="font-family: Liberation Serif, serif;"><span style="font-size: small;"><span style="background: #ffffff;"><span style="font-weight: normal;">And this is the debate into which we are stepping with our project. We have created one of the largest databases of three dimensional data on primate limbs. It includes over 1500 individual primates, 10,000 individual bones, nearly 200,000 3D landmarks, and 1000 3D models. We are analyzing it using modern comparative statistical methods to identify which physical traits are associated with suspension in primates. We then test the way these physical traits are correlated to determine whether the correlation among these traits is, in fact, different in suspensory primates.</span></span></span></span></p> <p><span style="font-family: Liberation Serif, serif;"><span style="font-size: small;"><span style="background: #ffffff;"><span style="font-weight: normal;">As part of this project we will gain a better understanding of the role suspension played in the evolutionary history of humans and how that impacted the evolution of bipedalism. Did we inherit our ability to bring our arms over our head as part of a suspensory past? How about our upright back posture and the problems (like slipped disks) that come with it? Did we become bipedal by, essentially, dropping down from the trees or by rising up from all fours? With this project we hope to make substantial progress toward answering these and similar questions.</span></span></span></span></p> <!-- p { line-height: 115%; margin-bottom: 0.1in; background: transparent } --><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/20/2022<br>      Modified by: Jeffrey&nbsp;Spear</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Why do we walk upright on two legs when no other animals do? Why can we raise our arms above our heads when so few other animals can? Why do we get herniated discs in our back? The answer to all of these questions and more lies in our evolutionary history.  In this project, we try to understand how our evolutionary history shapes our bodies. Specifically, we are trying to untangle the way that suspensory behaviors have impacted that history. Suspensory behaviors are behaviors where an animal is underneath the object that supports their weight, rather than on top of it. A sloth hanging from a tree or a child swinging across monkey bars are both examples of suspensory behaviors.  Contrary to what is implied by the name ‘monkey bars’, however, the vast majority of monkeys are not suspensory &ndash; they would not use monkey bars the way we do, and instead would scramble across the top of them rather than swinging underneath. Indeed, many are unable to hold their arms over their head in a way that would even allow them to swing underneath monkey bars. But apes, the group of primates of which we are a part, do regularly use suspensory behaviors and most (including humans!) can and would cross monkey bars by swinging beneath them.  So apes evolved the ability to be suspensory and we inherited that from our common ancestor, right? Well, as it turns out, it’s far more complicated than that. There is a startling lack of evidence for suspensory adaptations in the fossil record of apes, leading many researchers to argue that some or even all living apes evolved the ability to be suspensory independently of one another. The question of how we explain the evolution of suspension multiple times within one small group of primates but almost never within all other groups of primates is the subject of a lively debate among scientists of human evolution.  One commonly referenced hypothesis for why a certain adaptation might evolve multiple times in one group of animals but not in other, related groups, is that there is a shift in the way those traits develop and are correlated, making it easier for evolution to create certain adaptations but not others. For example, the length of arms and legs are highly correlated. If natural selection favors individuals with long arms and long legs, that variant already exists in the population and evolution will happen quickly. If instead evolution favors long arms and short legs, individuals meeting that description are much rarer, and evolution will happen more slowly, if at all. So perhaps, the thinking goes, early in the evolution of apes there was a change in the way some traits are correlated that made it easier to evolve adaptations useful for suspension.  And this is the debate into which we are stepping with our project. We have created one of the largest databases of three dimensional data on primate limbs. It includes over 1500 individual primates, 10,000 individual bones, nearly 200,000 3D landmarks, and 1000 3D models. We are analyzing it using modern comparative statistical methods to identify which physical traits are associated with suspension in primates. We then test the way these physical traits are correlated to determine whether the correlation among these traits is, in fact, different in suspensory primates.  As part of this project we will gain a better understanding of the role suspension played in the evolutionary history of humans and how that impacted the evolution of bipedalism. Did we inherit our ability to bring our arms over our head as part of a suspensory past? How about our upright back posture and the problems (like slipped disks) that come with it? Did we become bipedal by, essentially, dropping down from the trees or by rising up from all fours? With this project we hope to make substantial progress toward answering these and similar questions.        Last Modified: 07/20/2022       Submitted by: Jeffrey Spear]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
