<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[I-Corps: Development of a rapid point-of-care test for coronavirus (COVID-19) and antibody testing]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ruth Shuman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rshuman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922160</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this I-Corps project is the development of a rapid point-of-care (POC) diagnostic test for COVID-19 based on a lateral flow assay (LFA).  The goal is to decrease community spread of infection and help mitigate the negative economic impacts of world-wide pandemics. The proposed diagnostic may allow for universal access to testing of both coronavirus infection and immunity via protein-protein interactions with virions and antibodies at once as compared with using a polymerase chain reaction (PCR)-based test that relies on time-consuming reverse transcription of RNA to detect the virus only.  The consensus among public health experts is that safely emerging from a lockdown will require regular testing of millions of Americans. Current testing technologies are limited due to a large percentage of false negatives (up to 20%). Additionally, access to coronavirus and antibody testing is limited in low resource settings that lack reliable electrical services, running water, and diagnostic devices and personnel to operate them. Although testing capabilities are increasing among currently employed technologies such as at-home nasopharyngeal sampling, the creation of a rapid, simple POC test has not been addressed. The proposed technology may decrease community spread of infection and help mitigate the negative economic impacts of the COVID-19 pandemic. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project is based on the translation of a lateral flow assay (LFA) diagnostic COVID-19 test, akin to a pregnancy test, that will report the presence of both the virus and its antibody in patient samples. Because LFAs employ capillary force on a polymeric strip with detection zones, they are easy-to-use, eliminate the need for specialized equipment, and may be carried out as a single step, reducing the amount of sample handling. Using commercially available computational software, detector proteins with high sensitivity and high specificity have been designed. Preliminary experimental results confirm the high sensitivity and computational results confirm high specificity. DNA constructs are concurrently under development with optimization of LFA test strips. For precise, rapid and large-scale loading, the requirements for aa multiplex lateral flow test strip (MLFTS) process design from a commercially-available, drop-on-demand printer that will accommodate the protein designs and facilitate scale-up and manufacturing will be evaluated.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/08/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/14/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2041364</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jin</FirstName>
<LastName>Montclare</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>K</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jin K Montclare</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[montclare@nyu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000132121</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/08/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>New York University</Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<ZipCode>100121019</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2129982121</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>70 WASHINGTON SQ S</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NX9PXMKW5KW8</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NEW YORK UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[NYU Tandon School of Engineering]]></Name>
<CityName>Brooklyn</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>112013840</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[6 Metrotech Center]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Intellectual Merit: </strong>We aim to develop a COVID-19 rapid antigen test utilizing less expensive antibody-mimics that utilize multivalency to be a more sensitive diagnostic compared to rapid tests currently on the market. During infection by SARS-CoV-2 (the virus causing COVID-19), the spike (S) protein on the virus surface recognizes the angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (ACE-2) of the host. We aim to develop antibody-mimics, or proteins that function as antibodies but are less complex and less expensive, to create engineered tagged assembled proteins (TAP) using a protein that we have extensively studied in our lab, the coiled-coil protein, C. By tagging C with a colorimetric marker and with the ACE2 protein we aim to make an ACE2 Tagged Assembled Protein (ACE-TAP) that can recognize the COVID-19 virus. We then aim to integrate this with the well-established lateral flow assay (LFA) platform commonly used in rapid testing to make a less expensive, but more sensitive, rapid test for COVID-19 infection.</p> <p><strong>Accomplishments</strong>: We have been able to successfully synthesize and validate the ACE-TAP protein as capable of improved binding affinity compared to on-the market antibodies used for detection of COVID-19 in rapid testing. We have also conducted 116 interviews in ICorps customer discovery processes. As a result, we have discovered beachhead markets for early adoption of LFA tests utilizing a sensitive and rapid LFA with the primary customer being high-publicity private universities. While this customer segment did prove to be an early adopter of rapid testing and COVID-19 diagnostics, many competitors entered the market during our research phase and the pandemic evolved quickly with new unmet market needs. In a second customer discovery phase done one year later, we discovered that our beachhead market was now rapid testing centers which have popped up all over the U.S. where the general population wanted to know infectiousness immediately by way of rapid testing. However, with many established and OTC rapid tests already launched, our new barrier to entry was creating a test of much greater sensitivity that it would be significantly more confident at diagnosing infection. To this extent we decided we were at a no-go phase of our venture and have been iterating on our research to increase sensitivity to meet market needs.</p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts:</strong> The technology developed by TAP Diagnostics will decrease community spread of infection and will help mitigate the negative economic impacts of the COVID-19 pandemic. This will provide robust health information to individuals and the world alike to home in contact tracing and prevent a more proliferation of the virus. Reducing spread will also decrease the acuity of COVID-19 cases and lessen the burden of a high influx of patients on our healthcare system and level the supply of high-demand life-saving equipment like respirators. This will be especially impactful in low resource communities where current testing technologies are unaffordable. The work will also impact research in several scientific disciplines including understanding the impact of rationale design and multivalency in protein engineering and the biochemistry of COVID-19 variants against a conserved protein sequence based on the protein-protein interaction used by the virus for infection. Additionally, participation in the I-Corps program will add entrepreneurial skills to the repertoires of members of TAP Diagnostics, allowing us to mentor the next generation of interdisciplinary entrepreneurs.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/23/2022<br>      Modified by: Jin&nbsp;K&nbsp;Montclare</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2041364/2041364_10705391_1653327077026_NSFIcoprsTApfigure--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2041364/2041364_10705391_1653327077026_NSFIcoprsTApfigure--rgov-800width.jpg" title="ACE-TAP design"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2041364/2041364_10705391_1653327077026_NSFIcoprsTApfigure--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="ACE-TAP design"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">SARS-CoV-2 S1 RBD in red bound to ACE-2 in blue. In green are residues critical to binding to ACE-2 RBD. In yellow dashes are the 17 hydrogen bonds and in black dashes is the critical salt bridge in the interface. b) The S protein RBD and ACE2binder are fused to the C (COMPcc) domain via linkers.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jin Montclare</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jin&nbsp;K&nbsp;Montclare</div> <div class="imageTitle">ACE-TAP design</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Intellectual Merit: We aim to develop a COVID-19 rapid antigen test utilizing less expensive antibody-mimics that utilize multivalency to be a more sensitive diagnostic compared to rapid tests currently on the market. During infection by SARS-CoV-2 (the virus causing COVID-19), the spike (S) protein on the virus surface recognizes the angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (ACE-2) of the host. We aim to develop antibody-mimics, or proteins that function as antibodies but are less complex and less expensive, to create engineered tagged assembled proteins (TAP) using a protein that we have extensively studied in our lab, the coiled-coil protein, C. By tagging C with a colorimetric marker and with the ACE2 protein we aim to make an ACE2 Tagged Assembled Protein (ACE-TAP) that can recognize the COVID-19 virus. We then aim to integrate this with the well-established lateral flow assay (LFA) platform commonly used in rapid testing to make a less expensive, but more sensitive, rapid test for COVID-19 infection.  Accomplishments: We have been able to successfully synthesize and validate the ACE-TAP protein as capable of improved binding affinity compared to on-the market antibodies used for detection of COVID-19 in rapid testing. We have also conducted 116 interviews in ICorps customer discovery processes. As a result, we have discovered beachhead markets for early adoption of LFA tests utilizing a sensitive and rapid LFA with the primary customer being high-publicity private universities. While this customer segment did prove to be an early adopter of rapid testing and COVID-19 diagnostics, many competitors entered the market during our research phase and the pandemic evolved quickly with new unmet market needs. In a second customer discovery phase done one year later, we discovered that our beachhead market was now rapid testing centers which have popped up all over the U.S. where the general population wanted to know infectiousness immediately by way of rapid testing. However, with many established and OTC rapid tests already launched, our new barrier to entry was creating a test of much greater sensitivity that it would be significantly more confident at diagnosing infection. To this extent we decided we were at a no-go phase of our venture and have been iterating on our research to increase sensitivity to meet market needs.  Broader Impacts: The technology developed by TAP Diagnostics will decrease community spread of infection and will help mitigate the negative economic impacts of the COVID-19 pandemic. This will provide robust health information to individuals and the world alike to home in contact tracing and prevent a more proliferation of the virus. Reducing spread will also decrease the acuity of COVID-19 cases and lessen the burden of a high influx of patients on our healthcare system and level the supply of high-demand life-saving equipment like respirators. This will be especially impactful in low resource communities where current testing technologies are unaffordable. The work will also impact research in several scientific disciplines including understanding the impact of rationale design and multivalency in protein engineering and the biochemistry of COVID-19 variants against a conserved protein sequence based on the protein-protein interaction used by the virus for infection. Additionally, participation in the I-Corps program will add entrepreneurial skills to the repertoires of members of TAP Diagnostics, allowing us to mentor the next generation of interdisciplinary entrepreneurs.          Last Modified: 05/23/2022       Submitted by: Jin K Montclare]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
