<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[I-Corps:  Handheld electric toothbrush with built-in vacuum and a collection reservoir to reduce aspiration risk]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ruth Shuman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rshuman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922160</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this I-Corps project is the development of a powered toothbrush with built-in suction to decrease aspiration risk during brushing. Pediatric, geriatric, and NPO (nothing by mouth) patients are at high risk for aspiration during toothbrushing, which may cause lung infections. Additionally, it has been recognized that a suction device potentially may minimize the spread of oral pathogens.  Current products that aim to reduce aspiration risk by suction are bulky, either brush or vacuum (but not both simultaneously) and have exterior collection bag or use vacuum suction lines, which limit the use.  An all-in-one portable device may be suitable for broader use.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project is based on the development of a device for use in dental cleaning that is a handheld electric toothbrush with built-in vacuum and a collection reservoir. Numerous studies have established the benefit of electric toothbrushing, and also have shown that concomitant aspirates cause lung infections. Using a vacuum while brushing has not been addressed outside of the dental clinic/in-patient services.  The proposed design uses a disposable head with a hole to allow evacuation of fluids from the oral cavity. An in-built pump and waste compartment differentiate enable simultaneous brush head cleaning and suction or in-device fluid collection.  This proposed device provides a multi-purpose power toothbrush incorporating an integrated high-vacuum functionality into a (battery) powered toothbrush, providing for effective removal of saliva, debris, and fluids during brushing. The removal of these potentially harmful and infectious materials aids in the prevention of aspiration-related respiratory disease and potentially may reduce disease transmittal through aerosols.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/18/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/20/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2041092</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Vivek</FirstName>
<LastName>Kumar</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Vivek A Kumar</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[vak@njit.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000742260</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/18/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Maxine</FirstName>
<LastName>Strickland</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Maxine Strickland</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[strickma@sdm.rutgers.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000831946</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/18/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Rutgers, The State University of New Jersey</Name>
<CityName>NEWARK</CityName>
<ZipCode>071032495</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9739720283</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>110 BERGEN ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NJ10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>JGMWFYLEBVK7</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RUTGERS, THE STATE UNIVERSITY OF NEW JERSEY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>M1LVPE5GLSD9</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[RUTGERS, THE STATE UNIVERSITY OF NEW JERSEY]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>071011709</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NJ10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5345</Code>
<Text>BIOMEDICAL ENGINEERING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="Default">Major Goals:To finish writing the paper on the toothbrush technology</p> <p class="Default">Continue to apply for funding to improve TRL level</p> <p class="Default">Complete research for the microbiological portion of the study</p> <p class="Default">Attend meetings to continue customer discovery and interest in the technology</p> <p class="Default">&nbsp;</p> <p class="Pa4">Major outcomes accomplished</p> <ol> <li>The paper is completed and I am now looking to submit to a journal</li> <li>I have applied for the PFI grant and the NJ ACTS Grant</li> <li>I have applied for the Tech-X-Press Grant waiting to hear back</li> <li>I Attended the American Association of Dental Cranial facial Research meeting (this year and last year) as an invited speaker regarding my technology 4-2023. I learned that many of the faculty and Scientist that attended the meeting were interested in learning about the progress of my work with the technology, especially the chairman of my department</li> <li>I attended the Tech Connect World Innovation Conference National Harbor Maryland my poster got an acceptance for the June 19<sup>th</sup> 2023 meeting.(I attended this year and last year since they seemed very interested) I spoke to many people that came to my the poster or that I got to speak to Robert Gordon, Jeff Lesho, Leigh Midkiff, Kaylan Sheally and from them I learned that people in the military space seemed to be more compassionate about the disabled population when compared to mainstream toothbrush companies and dental companies who seemed more interested in de-risking the technology (I have met and done pitches for several through the life of the project to see if they were interested in licensing,) however, as&nbsp; a result of the tech connect meeting this year I received many email follow ups after the Tech connect meeting. Nicole Reilly communications and outreach specialist said she knew someone who had these problems at one time and she gave me her card and sent me a link to attend a virtual SBIR phase zero training workshop. Nancy Augustine Project Manager School of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences from the University of Pittsburgh was also very kind and sent a link for me to look at their website and to also find other funding opportunities. Kip Meacham Director of Business Development mentioned to share his information with our tech transfer office that they are able to help with FDA meetings</li> <li>I was invited by Judith Sheft the executive Director of the New Jersey Commission on Science and Innovation Technology to the NJECC as a Panelist for the June 13<sup>th</sup> 2023 meeting at the New Brunswick campus. I learned from this experience that sometimes women and minorities have a challenging time in comparison to their male counter parts as entrepreneurs. Therefore The New Jersey Equity Commercialization Collective are trying to encourage women who are entrepreneurs. They also mentioned different funding opportunities the NJ Innovation Fellows Program-NJEDA. I learned that this program will offer mentorship and grants up to 400,000 to teams of would be entrepreneurs. The program will provide income replacement so that entrepreneurs can devote time to their startups</li> <li>Student poster presentation this year Balbo Science Day at Rutgers March 29<sup>th</sup> 2023. I mentored one of our senior dental students collaboratively with our microbiologist who works in the Oral Biology department. I learned that the student was very excited to do 3-D printing and was equally encouraged that he was helping with the project overall that was a new technology. (Last year I did this with a different student we compared the 2 different versions of the toothbrush technology)</li> </ol> <p class="Pa4">.</p> <p class="Pa4">Research Results:</p> <p class="Default">1.This year: CFU/ml growth on plates containing the original cell culture indicate the viability of the bacteria used in the experiment. Lack of growth on plates containing the collected third wash from both the experimental and the control indicate that 30 ml of wash for both the experimental and the control was sufficient to clear the internal suction mechanism from an amount of bacteria that could be considered harmful to the user and to keep the user safe.</p> <p class="Default">2.Last year: student research poster results:. There were no significant association found between using two different version of toothbrush and the responses of all survey questions (all p-value&gt;0.05. However, 60% felt version 2.0 was too heavy vs. 20% for version 3.0 and 90% in both groups said they would most likely recommend this toothbrush for the intended user.</p> <p class="Default">3.Title:&nbsp; PICO to an INNOVATION</p> <p class="Default">I have been given the opportunity to give an annual lecture</p> <p class="Default">&nbsp;It is now a part of the student curriculum,&nbsp; EBD II-Applying the EvidenceOBIO7250 (course code)share about NSF</p> <p class="Default">4. This work recived the NSF award and the TechAdvance Award from the Rutgers School of dental Medicine</p> <p class="Pa4">5.Patents:This technology filed a patent in the United States and in Europe. Patent numbers are US 16/972,954 and EU 19814148.3. A second provisional has been filed in the US 63/402,670.</p> <p class="Pa4">&nbsp;</p> <p class="Pa4">&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/03/2023<br>      Modified by: Maxine&nbsp;Strickland</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[Major Goals:To finish writing the paper on the toothbrush technology Continue to apply for funding to improve TRL level Complete research for the microbiological portion of the study Attend meetings to continue customer discovery and interest in the technology   Major outcomes accomplished  The paper is completed and I am now looking to submit to a journal I have applied for the PFI grant and the NJ ACTS Grant I have applied for the Tech-X-Press Grant waiting to hear back I Attended the American Association of Dental Cranial facial Research meeting (this year and last year) as an invited speaker regarding my technology 4-2023. I learned that many of the faculty and Scientist that attended the meeting were interested in learning about the progress of my work with the technology, especially the chairman of my department I attended the Tech Connect World Innovation Conference National Harbor Maryland my poster got an acceptance for the June 19th 2023 meeting.(I attended this year and last year since they seemed very interested) I spoke to many people that came to my the poster or that I got to speak to Robert Gordon, Jeff Lesho, Leigh Midkiff, Kaylan Sheally and from them I learned that people in the military space seemed to be more compassionate about the disabled population when compared to mainstream toothbrush companies and dental companies who seemed more interested in de-risking the technology (I have met and done pitches for several through the life of the project to see if they were interested in licensing,) however, as  a result of the tech connect meeting this year I received many email follow ups after the Tech connect meeting. Nicole Reilly communications and outreach specialist said she knew someone who had these problems at one time and she gave me her card and sent me a link to attend a virtual SBIR phase zero training workshop. Nancy Augustine Project Manager School of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences from the University of Pittsburgh was also very kind and sent a link for me to look at their website and to also find other funding opportunities. Kip Meacham Director of Business Development mentioned to share his information with our tech transfer office that they are able to help with FDA meetings I was invited by Judith Sheft the executive Director of the New Jersey Commission on Science and Innovation Technology to the NJECC as a Panelist for the June 13th 2023 meeting at the New Brunswick campus. I learned from this experience that sometimes women and minorities have a challenging time in comparison to their male counter parts as entrepreneurs. Therefore The New Jersey Equity Commercialization Collective are trying to encourage women who are entrepreneurs. They also mentioned different funding opportunities the NJ Innovation Fellows Program-NJEDA. I learned that this program will offer mentorship and grants up to 400,000 to teams of would be entrepreneurs. The program will provide income replacement so that entrepreneurs can devote time to their startups Student poster presentation this year Balbo Science Day at Rutgers March 29th 2023. I mentored one of our senior dental students collaboratively with our microbiologist who works in the Oral Biology department. I learned that the student was very excited to do 3-D printing and was equally encouraged that he was helping with the project overall that was a new technology. (Last year I did this with a different student we compared the 2 different versions of the toothbrush technology)  . Research Results: 1.This year: CFU/ml growth on plates containing the original cell culture indicate the viability of the bacteria used in the experiment. Lack of growth on plates containing the collected third wash from both the experimental and the control indicate that 30 ml of wash for both the experimental and the control was sufficient to clear the internal suction mechanism from an amount of bacteria that could be considered harmful to the user and to keep the user safe. 2.Last year: student research poster results:. There were no significant association found between using two different version of toothbrush and the responses of all survey questions (all p-value&gt;0.05. However, 60% felt version 2.0 was too heavy vs. 20% for version 3.0 and 90% in both groups said they would most likely recommend this toothbrush for the intended user. 3.Title:  PICO to an INNOVATION I have been given the opportunity to give an annual lecture  It is now a part of the student curriculum,  EBD II-Applying the EvidenceOBIO7250 (course code)share about NSF 4. This work recived the NSF award and the TechAdvance Award from the Rutgers School of dental Medicine 5.Patents:This technology filed a patent in the United States and in Europe. Patent numbers are US 16/972,954 and EU 19814148.3. A second provisional has been filed in the US 63/402,670.                             Last Modified: 07/03/2023       Submitted by: Maxine Strickland]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
