<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[I-Corps:  Air Quality Monitoring Based on Digital Inline Holography]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ruth Shuman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rshuman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922160</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this I-Corps project is to define the requirements for the development of a new generation of indoor air quality monitors based on digital inline holography (DIH). The physical pollutant monitoring segment in the global air quality monitoring market is around $1 billion and is projected to grow rapidly amid and after the COVID-19 pandemic.  The proposed DIH monitor may identify pollutant types in addition to pollutant counts and size distribution. The proposed DIH sensor also has a compact design that may be used as wearable/portable devices or that may be easily integrated into filtration systems both in home and automobiles for smart control. The proposed technology may be further expanded for monitoring and characterization of particles in a broad range of applications, including monitoring: outdoor airborne particles, particles suspended in water, particle characterization in atomization and sprays, particle processing, and high throughput cellular analysis in biomedical applications.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project explores the translation of machine learning-based digital inline holography (DIH). A highly compact 3D imaging sensor may perform real-time, in situ measurements of size distributions, shape, concentration, and other physical properties of particles (e.g., droplets, bubbles, dusts, cells, etc.) from 200 nm to ~1 mm. The proposed technology may serve as a platform technology that may be applied to monitor air quality. The DIH sensor may be used to monitor a wide range of airborne pollutants including physical pollutants (e.g., smoke, smog, dust, etc.) and biological pollutants (e.g., pollen, dust mites, house dust, animal dander, etc.)distinguishing particulate pollutants types based on particle shapes. At the conclusion of the project, the goal is to identify the requirements for air pollutant monitoring applications and the need for this technology in the broader particle diagnostic community.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/25/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/01/2023</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041, 47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2041968</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lei</FirstName>
<LastName>Feng</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lei Feng</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[fengl@umn.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000875541</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/23/2022</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jiarong</FirstName>
<LastName>Hong</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jiarong Hong</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jhong@umn.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000635512</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/25/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate>03/23/2022</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Minnesota-Twin Cities</Name>
<CityName>MINNEAPOLIS</CityName>
<ZipCode>554552009</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6126245599</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>200 OAK ST SE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>KABJZBBJ4B54</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MINNESOTA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Minnesota-Twin Cities]]></Name>
<CityName>Minneapolis</CityName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>554550150</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[111 Church St SE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Within academic environments, researchers often delve deep into their disciplines, pushing the boundaries of knowledge. However, translating these academic breakthroughs into practical, societal-benefiting solutions can be intricate. The I-Corps training program was pivotal in this transformation. It not only equipped us with the tools and insights to commercialize our innovations but also helped us identify the right market for our technology.</p> <p>In the midst of a rapidly evolving technological landscape, our team developed an advanced sensor technology capable of real-time detection and analysis of microscopic particles. While this innovation held promise for various applications, it was through the I-Corps program that we honed in on its most profound potential: addressing the needs of the pharmaceutical and food &amp; beverage sectors. The program's structured approach to customer discovery and market research revealed a significant industry challenge: the swift and accurate detection of microbial contaminants. Our technology emerged as a solution, offering faster and more precise detection than existing methods, setting the stage for new industry benchmarks in product safety and quality.</p> <p>Our commitment to societal impact is underscored by our strategic collaborations formed during the course of this award. We've established a partnership with Donaldson, a global leader in filtration solutions. Their expertise in sterile liquid filtration for pharmaceutical and food &amp; beverage manufacturing complements our technology, paving the way for innovations for inline monitoring in process analytical technology (PAT) that ensure the purity of products. Furthermore, our alliance with Baxter, the world's largest supplier of peritoneal dialysis, is a testament to the broader applicability of our technology. Baxter's vision to transform peritoneal dialysis aligns with our goal of ensuring patient safety through affordable, rapid microbial detection devices at point-of-care.</p> <p>These collaborations aren't just business ventures; they're partnerships with a shared vision. A vision of harnessing academic innovations to create products that ensure safety, enhance quality, and ultimately benefit society at large. Moreover, having strong partners like Donaldson and Baxter accelerates the commercialization process. Their established market presence, combined with our innovative technology, creates a synergy that facilitates quicker product development, regulatory approvals, and market entry. This partnership model not only validates our technology but also provides the necessary infrastructure and resources to bring our innovations to the masses.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/24/2023<br>      Modified by: Lei&nbsp;Feng</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Within academic environments, researchers often delve deep into their disciplines, pushing the boundaries of knowledge. However, translating these academic breakthroughs into practical, societal-benefiting solutions can be intricate. The I-Corps training program was pivotal in this transformation. It not only equipped us with the tools and insights to commercialize our innovations but also helped us identify the right market for our technology.  In the midst of a rapidly evolving technological landscape, our team developed an advanced sensor technology capable of real-time detection and analysis of microscopic particles. While this innovation held promise for various applications, it was through the I-Corps program that we honed in on its most profound potential: addressing the needs of the pharmaceutical and food &amp; beverage sectors. The program's structured approach to customer discovery and market research revealed a significant industry challenge: the swift and accurate detection of microbial contaminants. Our technology emerged as a solution, offering faster and more precise detection than existing methods, setting the stage for new industry benchmarks in product safety and quality.  Our commitment to societal impact is underscored by our strategic collaborations formed during the course of this award. We've established a partnership with Donaldson, a global leader in filtration solutions. Their expertise in sterile liquid filtration for pharmaceutical and food &amp; beverage manufacturing complements our technology, paving the way for innovations for inline monitoring in process analytical technology (PAT) that ensure the purity of products. Furthermore, our alliance with Baxter, the world's largest supplier of peritoneal dialysis, is a testament to the broader applicability of our technology. Baxter's vision to transform peritoneal dialysis aligns with our goal of ensuring patient safety through affordable, rapid microbial detection devices at point-of-care.  These collaborations aren't just business ventures; they're partnerships with a shared vision. A vision of harnessing academic innovations to create products that ensure safety, enhance quality, and ultimately benefit society at large. Moreover, having strong partners like Donaldson and Baxter accelerates the commercialization process. Their established market presence, combined with our innovative technology, creates a synergy that facilitates quicker product development, regulatory approvals, and market entry. This partnership model not only validates our technology but also provides the necessary infrastructure and resources to bring our innovations to the masses.          Last Modified: 08/24/2023       Submitted by: Lei Feng]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
