<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Conference: Science Museum Futures]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>90000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>90000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DRL</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Toni Dancstep</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tdancste@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927922</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Upon entering the STEM learning landscape, science museums enjoyed marked growth in public utilization and impact. However, since the turn of the century, reductions in visitor numbers, aging infrastructures and pedagogical approaches have made many in the sector question how these institutions might best evolve to stay relevant in a changing world. Although there have been numerous discussions around re-thinking practices and even some movement towards actualizing much of this rhetoric, overall, most institutions have largely continued business as usual. Meanwhile, the COVID-19 pandemic introduced additional challenges and created an important inflection point for science museums, a moment when all can and should seriously address not just the immediate future, but also the longer-term future of the next decade and beyond. This convening will meet this opportunity by virtually bringing together 50-60 diverse (expertise and role, background, demographics, geography) thoughtful STEM learning professionals to collaboratively re-imagine the future of the science museum community, in particular the particularly vulnerable small to medium size science museum sector. Participants will be asked to think strategically (rather than just tactically) about how science museums in the coming decade(s) can fulfill their STEM learning missions while truly serving the needs of all segments of their communities; particularly those who have been historically under-represented. The project will involve participants in an 8-step process involving pre-meeting readings, online discussions, large and small-group meetings, written and online dissemination efforts; with opportunities for local and national input throughout. The Science Museum Futures project represents an opportunity for the science museum community to seriously and collectively address its future; not just the very short-term future, but the longer-term future of the next decade and beyond. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;To remain an important part of the STEM learning landscape, the future demands that science museums re-think how they fulfill their STEM education roles in four key areas: 1) Understanding – facilitating STEM learning so all users can more clearly understand how an understanding of science and technology supports both a healthier and richer life; 2) Future Actions – supporting evidence-based solutions to challenges that currently face every community; 3) Social Cohesion – making it possible for all sectors of society to experience STEM learning as a natural an integral part of their family, group and community’s heritage and life experience; and 4) Physical Security – ensuring that all users have opportunities to gather (physically or virtually), interact, explore and learn STEM within a safe, healthy, anxiety-free and restorative environment. Going forward, science museums will need to re-envision how all four of areas can be addressed, not just individually, but collectively as core, interdependent goals. To ensure broad applicability and inclusion, diverse community voices and responses will be integrated throughout the process through a series of online focus groups and conversations with both members of the science museum community and the wider public science museums seek to serve. The Science Museum Futures project will create an initial Science Museums Futures Action Plan that will provide science museum practitioner’s with new approaches, processes and tools designed to enhance the ways they support STEM learning. All materials will be both vetted and disseminated with the aid of project partners through on-line webinars, focus groups, blog posts on social media such as LinkedIn and Facebook, conference presentations and organizational newsletters. This project seeks to help initiate an on-going effort to support science museums, allowing them to rethink and reshape their STEM learning offerings in ways that ensure that they are increasingly relevant and central to the lives of ALL members of their communities. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is funded by the Advancing Informal STEM Learning (AISL) program, which seeks to advance new approaches to, and evidence-based understanding of, the design and development of STEM learning in informal environments. One of AISL’s five priority goals is to invest in projects that seek to build infrastructure and/or capacity in the field, including efforts supporting collaborations, connections, and professional networks within and across sectors of informal STEM education. This project is also supported by the Education and Human Resources directorate's Accelerating Discovery in Education efforts to enable research in fundamental topics addressing persistent issues in the learning and teaching of STEM content as well as frontier topics that envision STEM learning environments of the future, push the boundaries of the use of technology in learning, and examine how learning will change because of advances in technology and developments in Industries of the Future.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/06/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/21/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2041474</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Falk</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John H Falk</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[john.falk@freechoicelearning.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000663796</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/06/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Chloe</FirstName>
<LastName>Poston</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Chloe Poston</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[chloe.poston@freechoicelearning.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000748642</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/21/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Judith</FirstName>
<LastName>Koke</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Judith M Koke</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[judy.koke@freechoicelearning.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000779419</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/06/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Institute for Learning Innovation</Name>
<CityName>PORTLAND</CityName>
<ZipCode>972174141</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4432230694</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5637 N GREELEY AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OR03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>HYX9HNCUQC35</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>INSTITUTE FOR LEARNING INNOVATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Institute for Learning Innovation]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<ZipCode>970087105</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OR01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>152Y</Code>
<Text>Accelerating Discovery in Ed</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7259</Code>
<Text>AISL</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8212</Code>
<Text>Broaden Particip STEM Resrch</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0420</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~90000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Over the course of this one-year project, Institute for Learning Innovation staff sought to engage the professional science museum community as well as the broader publics served by this community in a strategic process of re-imagining how science museums in the coming decade(s) could best fulfill their STEM learning missions while truly serving the needs of ALL segments of their communities; particularly those who have been historically under-represented.</p> <p>Emerging from this multi-step process were a series of essential actions that science museums can do to enhance the prospects of their long-term survival and success. Foundational to the entire process was a commitment to ensuring that any solutions offered be mission-consistent, financially sustainable and prioritize community well-being-related needs in four key areas:</p> <ul> <li>Personal Connection &ndash; catalyzing wonder, interest and a sense of identity with STEM; feelings that foster a sense of belonging and long-term engagement; </li> </ul> <ul> <li>Intellectual      Empowerment &ndash; facilitating STEM-related curiosity and learning, and the      ability to utilize STEM in the service of solving societal challenges; </li> <li>Social      Cohesion &ndash; making it possible for all sectors of a community to experience      STEM learning as a natural and integral part of their family, group and      community&rsquo;s heritage and life experience; </li> <li>Physical      Security &ndash; ensuring that all users have opportunities to gather (physically      or virtually), interact, explore and learn      within a safe, healthy, anxiety-free and restorative environment. </li> </ul> <p>The project resulted in the generation of 11 &ldquo;novel&rdquo; ideas for how science museums can transform their practices in ways that more directly serve the well-being-related needs of their communities. Although individually, each of these ideas represents a relatively small step forward in reinventing science museum practice, collectively these ideas suggest three critical ways in which the science museum community might dramatically rethink their focus and day-to-day practices.</p> <p><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Move from a focus on STEM as an academic topic to be learned to STEM as a topic that solves community-relevant problems and issues.</span></strong> The project underscored the importance of moving away from an emphasis on traditional &ldquo;fundamentals of STEM&rdquo; type exhibitions and programs to efforts that re-focused the work of the science museums on helping to solve community-focused concerns and topics.</p> <p><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Transformation of the role of the science museum from &ldquo;expert&rdquo; to &ldquo;learning resource.&rdquo;</span></strong> &nbsp;Noted was the need for institutions to shift away from &ldquo;we are the experts and know what you need to know&rdquo; (a deficit model) to an asset model of &ldquo;how can we be a better resource for what you want and need to learn.&rdquo; To support this shift, institutions need to make a greater investment in staff, with the issue of Diversity, Equity, Inclusion and Access representing an important first step involving changes in staff training; hiring practices and a transition away from the building to greater work out in the community.</p> <p><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Move away from the science museum as an island of expertise to more of a model where the science museums is just one, but integral, part of a greater ecosystem of effort:</span></strong> The events of past few decades demonstrate that science museums cannot have the level of significant impact they wish to have as long as they continue to work alone and unilaterally. Collective action is the only route to success, whether that is at the local or national level; collaborative, ecosystem-wide solutions are urgently needed.</p> <p><strong><em><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Reflections on a Better Science Museum Future</span></em></strong></p> <p>The <em>Science Museum Futures</em> project challenges museums to become a better resource for their community, a first step of which requires bringing more diverse community voices to the table as part of strategic planning, hiring practices and program planning. Genuine relationship building is at the core of this work. Passive, one-off interactions will prove insufficient for success. Long standing partnerships will create connections that will broaden the communities that gain from all that science museums have to offer. By allowing desired audiences to join the ideation and decision-making process, museums have a chance to move toward a sense of shared ownership and commitment to sustained success.</p> <p>Beyond the work of each individual museum lies an opportunity to build partnerships across similar and complementary organizations to develop an ecosystem of organizations working together to collectively ensure that free-choice/informal learning is accessible, valuable, and sustainable for all. Partner organizations could be broadly defined to include a variety of constituents, including corporate sponsors, social justice and advocacy organizations, as well as museums and centers with topical foci beyond STEM. Science museums have the capacity to serve as community hubs of innovation, as idea incubators, and catalysts for enacting synergistic and collaborative approaches to solving community problems. These are not easy roles to play, but they afford the best opportunity for science museums to be the kind of transformational change agents they desire to be, and the best chance for the community as a whole to be relevant and thrive in the future.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/05/2022<br>      Modified by: John&nbsp;Falk</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Over the course of this one-year project, Institute for Learning Innovation staff sought to engage the professional science museum community as well as the broader publics served by this community in a strategic process of re-imagining how science museums in the coming decade(s) could best fulfill their STEM learning missions while truly serving the needs of ALL segments of their communities; particularly those who have been historically under-represented.  Emerging from this multi-step process were a series of essential actions that science museums can do to enhance the prospects of their long-term survival and success. Foundational to the entire process was a commitment to ensuring that any solutions offered be mission-consistent, financially sustainable and prioritize community well-being-related needs in four key areas:  Personal Connection &ndash; catalyzing wonder, interest and a sense of identity with STEM; feelings that foster a sense of belonging and long-term engagement;    Intellectual      Empowerment &ndash; facilitating STEM-related curiosity and learning, and the      ability to utilize STEM in the service of solving societal challenges;  Social      Cohesion &ndash; making it possible for all sectors of a community to experience      STEM learning as a natural and integral part of their family, group and      community’s heritage and life experience;  Physical      Security &ndash; ensuring that all users have opportunities to gather (physically      or virtually), interact, explore and learn      within a safe, healthy, anxiety-free and restorative environment.    The project resulted in the generation of 11 "novel" ideas for how science museums can transform their practices in ways that more directly serve the well-being-related needs of their communities. Although individually, each of these ideas represents a relatively small step forward in reinventing science museum practice, collectively these ideas suggest three critical ways in which the science museum community might dramatically rethink their focus and day-to-day practices.  Move from a focus on STEM as an academic topic to be learned to STEM as a topic that solves community-relevant problems and issues. The project underscored the importance of moving away from an emphasis on traditional "fundamentals of STEM" type exhibitions and programs to efforts that re-focused the work of the science museums on helping to solve community-focused concerns and topics.  Transformation of the role of the science museum from "expert" to "learning resource."  Noted was the need for institutions to shift away from "we are the experts and know what you need to know" (a deficit model) to an asset model of "how can we be a better resource for what you want and need to learn." To support this shift, institutions need to make a greater investment in staff, with the issue of Diversity, Equity, Inclusion and Access representing an important first step involving changes in staff training; hiring practices and a transition away from the building to greater work out in the community.  Move away from the science museum as an island of expertise to more of a model where the science museums is just one, but integral, part of a greater ecosystem of effort: The events of past few decades demonstrate that science museums cannot have the level of significant impact they wish to have as long as they continue to work alone and unilaterally. Collective action is the only route to success, whether that is at the local or national level; collaborative, ecosystem-wide solutions are urgently needed.  Reflections on a Better Science Museum Future  The Science Museum Futures project challenges museums to become a better resource for their community, a first step of which requires bringing more diverse community voices to the table as part of strategic planning, hiring practices and program planning. Genuine relationship building is at the core of this work. Passive, one-off interactions will prove insufficient for success. Long standing partnerships will create connections that will broaden the communities that gain from all that science museums have to offer. By allowing desired audiences to join the ideation and decision-making process, museums have a chance to move toward a sense of shared ownership and commitment to sustained success.  Beyond the work of each individual museum lies an opportunity to build partnerships across similar and complementary organizations to develop an ecosystem of organizations working together to collectively ensure that free-choice/informal learning is accessible, valuable, and sustainable for all. Partner organizations could be broadly defined to include a variety of constituents, including corporate sponsors, social justice and advocacy organizations, as well as museums and centers with topical foci beyond STEM. Science museums have the capacity to serve as community hubs of innovation, as idea incubators, and catalysts for enacting synergistic and collaborative approaches to solving community problems. These are not easy roles to play, but they afford the best opportunity for science museums to be the kind of transformational change agents they desire to be, and the best chance for the community as a whole to be relevant and thrive in the future.       Last Modified: 04/05/2022       Submitted by: John Falk]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
