<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: The Impact of Being Policed Under Threat]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>199537.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>199537</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Songqi Liu</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>soliu@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928950</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This project advances scientific knowledge of how contextual stressors shape police behavior and, in turn, indirectly affect community members’ collective life and work outcomes. To do so, it investigates institutional, situational, and psychological factors that are associated with law enforcement in heavily policed communities. Moreover, this project provides racioethnic comparisons among members of urban area communities to better understand the differential impact of policing behaviors. A potential benefit of this project would be to help account for previously documented racial differences in community health and job performance. Results will draw attention to the spillover effects of police-community relations to public and private organizations embedded within these communities, potentially increasing the urgency of organizational leaders to take action to support more effective police-community partnerships for the good of the labor force and society. &lt;br/&gt;  &lt;br/&gt;The primary aims are to: investigate (1) how job insecurity, media attention, reform efforts, and consciousness of the “racist” stereotype among law enforcement shape patterns of policing in Black communities; (2) how patterns of policing behavior, in turn, impact psychophysiological health, well-being, and experiences of discrimination within Black communities; and, (3) how adverse community outcomes spillover to the civilian work domain to affect Black employees’ workplace performance. Timely data collection will allow this project to produce: (1) a multi-level understanding of the impact of external stressors on policing and community outcomes, (2) a framework for understanding the joint officer-community experience, and (3) recommendations for policing and organizational policy that align the joint experiences of officers and community members. Using a mixed-method approach, the project will incorporate thematic interviews of public officials, self-report police and community data, secondary analysis of public data, and secondary accounts of policing behavior scraped from the internet. Findings will inform theories on stress, identity, the work-life interface, experiences of discrimination, and organizational support.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/07/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/07/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2041556</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lars</FirstName>
<LastName>Johnson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>U</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lars U Johnson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[lars.johnson@uta.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000833143</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/07/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Wayne State University</Name>
<CityName>DETROIT</CityName>
<ZipCode>482023692</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3135772424</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5700 CASS AVE STE 4900</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>M6K6NTJ2MNE5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WAYNE STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Wayne State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Detroit</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>482024050</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5057 Woodward Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8031</Code>
<Text>SoO-Science Of Organizations</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~199537</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The overarching objective of this project was to understand the perceived threat of over-policing and hyper-policing experienced by Black people in the U.S., by non-Black people in the U.S., and within and between Black and non-Black U.S. communities following the World Health Organization&rsquo;s declaration of the pandemic COVID-19 Pandemic. Additionally, we sought to understand the spillover effect of these home- and community-based experiences on the work domain. This objective was prompted by 1) police killings of unarmed Black people prior to the pandemic and 2) police killings of and perceived aggression toward unarmed Black people during the pandemic.</p> <p>Breonna Taylor and George Floyd were two Black U.S. citizens that were killed by police while unarmed. Ms. Taylor was killed just two days after the World Health Organization&rsquo;s pandemic announcement, and Mr. Floyd was killed approximately two months after the pandemic announcement. The two lived in different states and had limited similarities beyond being Black and being killed by a group of police officers led by at least one White officer. Although the outcries due to these murders engendered social action by groups that similarly advocated for unarmed Black citizens killed by police&mdash;police of any race&mdash;murdered in previous years (e.g., Walter Scott, Jordan Edwards, Stephon Clark, Botham Jean, and Ronald Greene), the summer of 2020 ignited global protests of differential treatment Black U.S. citizens by police officers. Given the globe-spanning scale of these protests, historians and social scholars now regard these protests as the largest social movement in world history.</p> <p>We employed a multi-faceted sampling approach to answer a central question: What is the nature of differential treatment by police among Black and non-Black citizens during the COVID-19 pandemic? The project featured a multi-method designed, including multi-wave surveys and hour-long interviews. Police officers were required to have worked in their current role for at least months prior to the WHO&rsquo;s announcement of the pandemic, and community participants were required to be residents of their current community for at least six months and work at least 20 hours per week. The data were collected from law enforcement officers and community members from small, medium, and large urban areas throughout the contiguous United States. To ensure adequate representation of U.S. regions, we considered U.S. Census Bureau designations of metropolitan statistical areas, the number of police working in urban areas, area demographics, and marketing data.</p> <p>Results of the survey data revealed a distinct distrust of police held by Black participants&mdash;primarily due to concern for their safety and wellbeing. In comparison to White participants, Black participants reported higher levels of differential treatment by police officers and greater concern for injury or worse when interacting with the police. Moreover, these community- and home-based concerns spilled over into the workplace, showing a relationship which such attitudes and strain factors disengagement and exhaustion. <strong></strong></p> <p>The qualitative data presented two interesting trends, each unique to either law enforcement officers or community participants. Law enforcement officers reported a sense of support from their immediate community. Police officers reported feeling a sense of respect from and value within their communities, and they reported no meaningful changes to operations or guidance following the Summer 2020 protests. Officers also noted perceptions of bias in the media, suggesting the media presents law enforcement in a negative light but has done so for years. Community participants reported less than favorable views of policing. Participants shared examples of overt mistreatment of Black citizens. White participants mostly shared examples of how they witnessed or experienced preferential treatment in comparison to Black people, often stating Black people were mistreated by police officers in the same instance. <strong></strong></p> <p><strong>Discussion of broader impacts: </strong>Interestingly, there is a dearth of research on policing in the organizational sciences. This is not to say the field is without meaningful research. Indeed, there are papers that have made significant contributions to organizational sciences. Still, the volume of research on policing and policing-related outcomes does not compare to research on such occupations as medicine, sales, restaurants, or education. Moreover, previous research and existing methodologies primarily focus on investigations of smaller geographic locations, and the data are often collected from a single or limited number of organizations. This research leveraged and integrated existing data from multiple federal agencies for sampling decisions and analysis, expanding the approach to policing research by combining quantitative and qualitative methodology, multi-wave data collection, and consideration of the community/home-to-work spillover effects of differential police treatment perceptions and differences in reported fear of harm by police officers.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Taken together, this project yielded important implications for research, practice, community-based organizations. Because policing is omnipresent, and local law enforcement agencies are constantly scrutinized because of their engagement practices, these findings may inform efforts that attempt to promote collaboration, healing, and equity within and between law enforcement organizations and the communities they serve.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/29/2022<br>      Modified by: Lars&nbsp;U&nbsp;Johnson</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The overarching objective of this project was to understand the perceived threat of over-policing and hyper-policing experienced by Black people in the U.S., by non-Black people in the U.S., and within and between Black and non-Black U.S. communities following the World Health Organization’s declaration of the pandemic COVID-19 Pandemic. Additionally, we sought to understand the spillover effect of these home- and community-based experiences on the work domain. This objective was prompted by 1) police killings of unarmed Black people prior to the pandemic and 2) police killings of and perceived aggression toward unarmed Black people during the pandemic.  Breonna Taylor and George Floyd were two Black U.S. citizens that were killed by police while unarmed. Ms. Taylor was killed just two days after the World Health Organization’s pandemic announcement, and Mr. Floyd was killed approximately two months after the pandemic announcement. The two lived in different states and had limited similarities beyond being Black and being killed by a group of police officers led by at least one White officer. Although the outcries due to these murders engendered social action by groups that similarly advocated for unarmed Black citizens killed by police&mdash;police of any race&mdash;murdered in previous years (e.g., Walter Scott, Jordan Edwards, Stephon Clark, Botham Jean, and Ronald Greene), the summer of 2020 ignited global protests of differential treatment Black U.S. citizens by police officers. Given the globe-spanning scale of these protests, historians and social scholars now regard these protests as the largest social movement in world history.  We employed a multi-faceted sampling approach to answer a central question: What is the nature of differential treatment by police among Black and non-Black citizens during the COVID-19 pandemic? The project featured a multi-method designed, including multi-wave surveys and hour-long interviews. Police officers were required to have worked in their current role for at least months prior to the WHO’s announcement of the pandemic, and community participants were required to be residents of their current community for at least six months and work at least 20 hours per week. The data were collected from law enforcement officers and community members from small, medium, and large urban areas throughout the contiguous United States. To ensure adequate representation of U.S. regions, we considered U.S. Census Bureau designations of metropolitan statistical areas, the number of police working in urban areas, area demographics, and marketing data.  Results of the survey data revealed a distinct distrust of police held by Black participants&mdash;primarily due to concern for their safety and wellbeing. In comparison to White participants, Black participants reported higher levels of differential treatment by police officers and greater concern for injury or worse when interacting with the police. Moreover, these community- and home-based concerns spilled over into the workplace, showing a relationship which such attitudes and strain factors disengagement and exhaustion.   The qualitative data presented two interesting trends, each unique to either law enforcement officers or community participants. Law enforcement officers reported a sense of support from their immediate community. Police officers reported feeling a sense of respect from and value within their communities, and they reported no meaningful changes to operations or guidance following the Summer 2020 protests. Officers also noted perceptions of bias in the media, suggesting the media presents law enforcement in a negative light but has done so for years. Community participants reported less than favorable views of policing. Participants shared examples of overt mistreatment of Black citizens. White participants mostly shared examples of how they witnessed or experienced preferential treatment in comparison to Black people, often stating Black people were mistreated by police officers in the same instance.   Discussion of broader impacts: Interestingly, there is a dearth of research on policing in the organizational sciences. This is not to say the field is without meaningful research. Indeed, there are papers that have made significant contributions to organizational sciences. Still, the volume of research on policing and policing-related outcomes does not compare to research on such occupations as medicine, sales, restaurants, or education. Moreover, previous research and existing methodologies primarily focus on investigations of smaller geographic locations, and the data are often collected from a single or limited number of organizations. This research leveraged and integrated existing data from multiple federal agencies for sampling decisions and analysis, expanding the approach to policing research by combining quantitative and qualitative methodology, multi-wave data collection, and consideration of the community/home-to-work spillover effects of differential police treatment perceptions and differences in reported fear of harm by police officers.              Taken together, this project yielded important implications for research, practice, community-based organizations. Because policing is omnipresent, and local law enforcement agencies are constantly scrutinized because of their engagement practices, these findings may inform efforts that attempt to promote collaboration, healing, and equity within and between law enforcement organizations and the communities they serve.       Last Modified: 12/29/2022       Submitted by: Lars U Johnson]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
