<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[CONFERENCE: HSI Strategic Innovation Summit for Advanced Research and Instruction in Artificial Intelligence and Quantum Information Sciences (HSI-SIS)]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>99923.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>99923</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div. of Equity for Excellence in STEM</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sonja Montas-Hunter</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>smontash@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927404</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[With support from the Improving Undergraduate STEM Education: Hispanic-Serving Institutions (HSI Program) and the Division of Graduate Education, this conference project aims to bring together professors, senior university officials, industry experts, and government sponsors, to explore ways to accelerate research in artificial intelligence (AI) and quantum information sciences (QIS), and introduce learning activities in AI and QIS early in the education of students at Hispanic-Serving Institutions (HSIs). AI and QIS will have long term and cross-cutting influence on future technologies, education, the workforce, and our lives. HSIs are colleges and universities with more than 25% Hispanic student enrollment, educating more than two-thirds of America’s Hispanic students. Connecting faculty and senior leadership at HSIs, and minority serving institutions in general, to the networks and resources to support national needs, is expected to increase the number of underrepresented science and engineering students who will contribute to the future STEM workforce. The expected outcomes of this conference will be roadmaps that define pressing research questions and create educational initiatives in AI and QIS for the institutions in attendance.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The University of California, Davis will host the HSI Strategic Innovation Summit for Advanced Research and Instruction in Artificial Intelligence and Quantum Information Sciences (HSI-SIS). HSI-SIS, a virtual, two-day summit, will assemble computing faculty, institutional leaders, sponsoring agencies, and industry, to exchange ideas and foster partnerships to enhance HSI participation in the latest AI and QIS initiatives. HSI-SIS will use a 3-pillar interactive feedback model for convening groups across 3 areas: curriculum, research, and broadening participation. This model will be used to identify ways to develop or expand infrastructures needed to perform research and include AI and QIS into first and second-year college students’ experiences. The long-term goal of this summit is to increase the number of graduates from HSIs who are equipped with hiring-level knowledge of deep learning, big data analytics, quantum computing, and other evolving topics in AI and QIS. Pre- and post- event surveys will be developed and administered, with a report produced by an evaluator to understand the impact of this summit on meeting participants and their institutions. Meeting outcomes will be disseminated at relevant convenings of, for example, the Computing Alliance of Hispanic-Serving Institutions, the accrediting board’s ABET Symposium (which includes the Computing Accreditation Commission), Conference for Undergraduate Research, the American Educational Research Association, the Association for the Study of Higher Education, and the Hispanic Association of Colleges and Universities. The HSI Program aims to enhance undergraduate STEM education and build capacity at HSIs. Projects supported by the HSI Program will also generate new knowledge on how to achieve these aims. The project is being supported by funds contributed by the Division of Graduate Education.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/24/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/14/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2042655</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Damon</FirstName>
<LastName>Tull</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Damon L Tull</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[tullucdavis@gmail.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000746367</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/24/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Davis</Name>
<CityName>DAVIS</CityName>
<ZipCode>956186153</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5307547700</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1850 RESEARCH PARK DR, STE 300</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>TX2DAGQPENZ5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, DAVIS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>NUDGYLBB4S99</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Davis]]></Name>
<CityName>Davis</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>956186134</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[One Shield Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>152Y</Code>
<Text>Accelerating Discovery in Ed</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>092Z</Code>
<Text>AI-Supported Learning</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>093Z</Code>
<Text>AI Education/Workforce Develop</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7203</Code>
<Text>QUANTUM INFORMATION SCIENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8209</Code>
<Text>Improv Undergrad STEM Ed(IUSE)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0420</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~99923</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Funded by the National Science Foundation (Award #2042655), the Hispanic-Serving Institution (HSI) Strategic Innovation Summit for Advanced Research and Instruction in Artificial Intelligence (AI) and Quantum Information Sciences (QIS) was a multi-day virtual national summit of HSI faculty, industry experts, and sponsoring agencies hosted by the University of California Davis. This series reached a broad audience of faculty and administrators with ideas and strategies to introduce the advanced topics of AI and QIS earlier in undergraduate education.</p> <p><strong>Intellectual Merit</strong></p> <p>HSIs are colleges and universities with more than 25% Hispanic student enrollment, educating more than two-thirds of America`s Hispanic students. The faculty at HSIs, and minority-serving institutions in general, are force multipliers of change. Helping faculty to bring AI and QIS courses and concepts to the first two years of undergraduate education is expected to enhance AI and QIS literacy, broaden participation in these fields and prepare students for future careers and graduate work in areas of national need.</p> <p>A robust summit agenda included panels that explored AI and QIS pedagogy, formal and informal faculty development to support teaching and research capacity, administrative barriers to establishing new teaching and research programs, and the national need to broaden participation early in the development of AI and QIS. These sessions were led by experts from universities and organizations from around the country to inform and provide resources to attendees. The conference agenda, presenter bios, event resources, and videos of each session are online at <a href="https://ucdavis.hsisummit.edu" target="_blank">https://ucdavis.hsisummit.edu</a>.</p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts </strong></p> <p>Over two separate events, the summit gathered 122 faculty, administrators, industry experts, and program officers from 57 unique organizations representing 14 states plus the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico and the country of Canada. A total of 43 colleges and universities participated in the summit series, 36 of these institutions were HSIs. Eighty percent of participants came from states or territories with high concentrations of HSIs, including, for example, California, Texas, Arizona, New Mexico, Florida, Nevada, and Puerto Rico. Participating institutions represented the full spectrum of research capacities according to Carnegie Classifications from Very High, High, Master`s, Bachelor, and two-year Associate degree institutions.</p> <p>Corporations and non-profit organizations participating in the summit included Augustine Labs, the Computing Alliance of Hispanic-Serving Institutions (CAHSI), CSforAll, Excelencia in Education, Google, PsiQuantum, Quantum for All, R Studio, Rigetti Computing, Twitter, and Zapata Computing. In addition, senior officials from the White House Office of Science and Technology Policy and the National Science Foundation presented at the summit.</p> <p>According to attendee feedback, the summit met or exceeded expectations. There was overwhelming satisfaction with the keynote and panel presenters and series content. After attending the summit, most survey respondents indicated they were <em>likely</em> or <em>extremely likely</em> to incorporate AI or QIS concepts into their lectures, reading material, and undergraduate research projects. The QIS component of the summit appeared to have a profound impact on attendees. More than 85% of survey respondents stated that the summit increased their awareness of QIS research, applications, and workforce needs and were more likely to incorporate QIS concepts into their instructional activities.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/06/2023<br>      Modified by: Damon&nbsp;L&nbsp;Tull</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2042655/2042655_10701298_1678141290311_HSISIS-Website--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2042655/2042655_10701298_1678141290311_HSISIS-Website--rgov-800width.jpg" title="HSI Summit Website"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2042655/2042655_10701298_1678141290311_HSISIS-Website--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="HSI Summit Website"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">HSI Strategic Innovation Summit for Advance Research and Instruction In Artificial Intelligence and Quantum Information Sciences</div> <div class="imageCredit">University of California Davis</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Damon&nbsp;L&nbsp;Tull</div> <div class="imageTitle">HSI Summit Website</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Funded by the National Science Foundation (Award #2042655), the Hispanic-Serving Institution (HSI) Strategic Innovation Summit for Advanced Research and Instruction in Artificial Intelligence (AI) and Quantum Information Sciences (QIS) was a multi-day virtual national summit of HSI faculty, industry experts, and sponsoring agencies hosted by the University of California Davis. This series reached a broad audience of faculty and administrators with ideas and strategies to introduce the advanced topics of AI and QIS earlier in undergraduate education.  Intellectual Merit  HSIs are colleges and universities with more than 25% Hispanic student enrollment, educating more than two-thirds of America`s Hispanic students. The faculty at HSIs, and minority-serving institutions in general, are force multipliers of change. Helping faculty to bring AI and QIS courses and concepts to the first two years of undergraduate education is expected to enhance AI and QIS literacy, broaden participation in these fields and prepare students for future careers and graduate work in areas of national need.  A robust summit agenda included panels that explored AI and QIS pedagogy, formal and informal faculty development to support teaching and research capacity, administrative barriers to establishing new teaching and research programs, and the national need to broaden participation early in the development of AI and QIS. These sessions were led by experts from universities and organizations from around the country to inform and provide resources to attendees. The conference agenda, presenter bios, event resources, and videos of each session are online at https://ucdavis.hsisummit.edu.  Broader Impacts   Over two separate events, the summit gathered 122 faculty, administrators, industry experts, and program officers from 57 unique organizations representing 14 states plus the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico and the country of Canada. A total of 43 colleges and universities participated in the summit series, 36 of these institutions were HSIs. Eighty percent of participants came from states or territories with high concentrations of HSIs, including, for example, California, Texas, Arizona, New Mexico, Florida, Nevada, and Puerto Rico. Participating institutions represented the full spectrum of research capacities according to Carnegie Classifications from Very High, High, Master`s, Bachelor, and two-year Associate degree institutions.  Corporations and non-profit organizations participating in the summit included Augustine Labs, the Computing Alliance of Hispanic-Serving Institutions (CAHSI), CSforAll, Excelencia in Education, Google, PsiQuantum, Quantum for All, R Studio, Rigetti Computing, Twitter, and Zapata Computing. In addition, senior officials from the White House Office of Science and Technology Policy and the National Science Foundation presented at the summit.  According to attendee feedback, the summit met or exceeded expectations. There was overwhelming satisfaction with the keynote and panel presenters and series content. After attending the summit, most survey respondents indicated they were likely or extremely likely to incorporate AI or QIS concepts into their lectures, reading material, and undergraduate research projects. The QIS component of the summit appeared to have a profound impact on attendees. More than 85% of survey respondents stated that the summit increased their awareness of QIS research, applications, and workforce needs and were more likely to incorporate QIS concepts into their instructional activities.       Last Modified: 03/06/2023       Submitted by: Damon L Tull]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
