<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research: EAGER: Advancing Pedagogy and Inclusivity through Multimodal Upper Level Geophysics Education]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>5445.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>5445</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Eva Zanzerkia</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ezanzerk@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924734</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Today, classrooms are challenged by the need for flexible learning due to the COVID-19 pandemic and for dynamic course materials that attract students from diverse backgrounds and allow them to thrive. This EAGER initiates a pilot effort to develop research-based learning modules for the upper level geophysics classes that can be used by geophysics programs across the country. At the upper level there are fewer resources for teaching and course development guides, and there is a notable drop off in students from underrepresented groups. This EAGER will explore how to implement high quality teaching materials to create a more equitable and inclusive learning environment that can build student confidence and allow students from a variety of diverse backgrounds to succeed. The PI team brings together complementary academic expertise facilitating the creation of a broad range of teaching modules and the convergence between upper level geophysics students and students in core STEM disciplines such as physics, mathematics, and computational science, which are fundamental disciplines on which global seismology relies.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will design multimodal pilot modules on (1) Elastodynamics, (2) Seismology and Plate Tectonics, and (3) Near surface seismological methods and applications to the developed environment. The work has the potential to transform the traditional teaching mechanisms for upper level geophysics courses, and be used as a means to attract underrepresented groups to geophysics who may not have otherwise considered Earth science as a research focus. The project will incorporate flipped course design and mastery learning to help build student confidence, with the  materials created in such a way that they are adaptable to both on-line and in-person teaching. In addition, the team will further develop inclusivity through the creation of biographies featuring scientists from underrepresented groups that will be incorporated directly into the learning modules. The pilot modules will specifically focus on upper level geophysics courses to address and support students transitioning from undergraduate training to graduate school or to professional work in the geosciences, thus extending the pedagogical support from lower level to upper level geophysics teaching.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/14/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/14/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2042007</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tolulope</FirstName>
<LastName>Olugboji</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Tolulope M Olugboji</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[tolulope.olugboji@rochester.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000744580</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/14/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Rochester</Name>
<CityName>ROCHESTER</CityName>
<ZipCode>146113847</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5852754031</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>910 GENESEE ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[STE 200]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>25</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY25</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>F27KDXZMF9Y8</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ROCHESTER</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Rochester]]></Name>
<CityName>Rochester</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>146270140</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>25</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY25</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7222</Code>
<Text>XC-Crosscutting Activities Pro</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~5445</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-a657edf8-7fff-b227-ba00-a574e787cea7"><span>We completed a pilot program to develop two (2) research-based community learning modules for the upper level geophysics class suitable for&nbsp;learning in remote and online situations.&nbsp;</span></span>Here are a summary of the project outcomes:</p> <p>(1) We developed two (2) multi-modal modules for a seismology course: syllabus, notes, learning objectives and excercises using an evidence based teaching and learning framework.&nbsp;</p> <p>(2) We developed a series of sixteen (16) lightboard lectures on background mathematics and physics needed for research level proficiency in seismology and global geophysics:&nbsp;<span id="docs-internal-guid-c6f616f0-7fff-f9f8-79dc-17004db1e970"><a href="https://bit.ly/URNSFEager"><span>https://bit.ly/URNSFEager</span></a></span></p> <p>(3) We developed five (5) in-class real-time active learning exercises using the poll everywhere platform: <span id="docs-internal-guid-4b234fe8-7fff-3a8e-f2a2-4990eeae6738"><a href="https://bit.ly/NSFEager_ActiveLearn"><span>https://bit.ly/NSFEager_ActiveLearn</span></a></span>&nbsp;</p> <p>(4) We conducted thirteen (13) interviews with seismologists with a special emphasis on those from diverse backgrounds:&nbsp;https://bit.ly/NSFEagerInterview&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p><span id="docs-internal-guid-b543e0df-7fff-b0ed-0032-f3a90d7ea225"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The interviews have been uploaded to YouTube and IRIS, but we are finalizing some small pieces of the description on the IRIS site. We haven't yet made the course modules available because of some small delays in finalizing them. We will disseminate them informally by making people aware of these through social media and listservs.</span></p> <p><span id="docs-internal-guid-a657edf8-7fff-b227-ba00-a574e787cea7"><span>The recorded lectures, interviews and the active-learning pedagogical frameworks (lightboard and real-time quizzes),</span></span>&nbsp;will promote training, recruitment, education and outreach activities for the geophysics discipline.&nbsp;</p> <p>The proposal was developed in the era of disrupted learning due to the COVID-19 pandemic. However, the broader objectives in addition to those stated above include:</p> <p>(1) Reduce the burden among faculty to incorporating effective teaching techniques in their course offerings</p> <p>(2) Create a more inclusive classroom and broaden participation in geophysics.</p> <p>(3)&nbsp;<span id="docs-internal-guid-f628734a-7fff-c303-d4d2-8c9a7fb6ca9c"><span>Create a stronger Geophysics/Seismology education community </span></span></p> <p><span id="docs-internal-guid-0abade1b-7fff-dd47-6b1f-737dd4f37498"><span>The primary goal of this project was to build the seed of a seismology or geophysics course that better educates students, especially to encourage those undergraduates from underrepresented groups that seismology and graduate school is a viable option for them.&nbsp;</span></span>In this sense the modules have benefited students. It also has given undergraduate Cielo Martos and Shamya Pugh an opportunity to meet Latinx, Black, and first-in-their family seismologists, practice preparing for and interviewing individuals, and video editing. Ayla Martinelli (undergraduate student at University of Rochester) was involved in developing in-class quizzes (active learning resources) using poll everywhere software.&nbsp;</p> <p><span><span>As we look to future iterations, here are some proposed steps:</span></span></p> <p><span id="docs-internal-guid-c1d9d87b-7fff-aaf0-f71b-1a7506471de9"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>(1) Keep track of views and downloads of lectures and interviews (2) Send out content for external review (3) distribute questionnaires on how these resources are being used.</span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/29/2021<br>      Modified by: Tolulope&nbsp;M&nbsp;Olugboji</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2042007/2042007_10697263_1638200461368_ScreenShot2021-11-29at10.39.48AM--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2042007/2042007_10697263_1638200461368_ScreenShot2021-11-29at10.39.48AM--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Recorded Lightboard Lectures"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2042007/2042007_10697263_1638200461368_ScreenShot2021-11-29at10.39.48AM--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Recorded Lightboard Lectures"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The PI (Olugboji) presenting a recorded lecture on vector calculus. See entire lecture here: https://bit.ly/URNSFEager</div> <div class="imageCredit">Olugboji</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Tolulope&nbsp;M&nbsp;Olugboji</div> <div class="imageTitle">Recorded Lightboard Lectures</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2042007/2042007_10697263_1638200553315_ScreenShot2021-11-29at10.39.06AM--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2042007/2042007_10697263_1638200553315_ScreenShot2021-11-29at10.39.06AM--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Active Learning Excercises"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2042007/2042007_10697263_1638200553315_ScreenShot2021-11-29at10.39.06AM--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Active Learning Excercises"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Screen shot of a selection of sample active learning exercises used to engage students in a live lecture.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Olugboji</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Tolulope&nbsp;M&nbsp;Olugboji</div> <div class="imageTitle">Active Learning Excercises</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ We completed a pilot program to develop two (2) research-based community learning modules for the upper level geophysics class suitable for learning in remote and online situations. Here are a summary of the project outcomes:  (1) We developed two (2) multi-modal modules for a seismology course: syllabus, notes, learning objectives and excercises using an evidence based teaching and learning framework.   (2) We developed a series of sixteen (16) lightboard lectures on background mathematics and physics needed for research level proficiency in seismology and global geophysics: https://bit.ly/URNSFEager  (3) We developed five (5) in-class real-time active learning exercises using the poll everywhere platform: https://bit.ly/NSFEager_ActiveLearn   (4) We conducted thirteen (13) interviews with seismologists with a special emphasis on those from diverse backgrounds: https://bit.ly/NSFEagerInterview      The interviews have been uploaded to YouTube and IRIS, but we are finalizing some small pieces of the description on the IRIS site. We haven't yet made the course modules available because of some small delays in finalizing them. We will disseminate them informally by making people aware of these through social media and listservs.  The recorded lectures, interviews and the active-learning pedagogical frameworks (lightboard and real-time quizzes), will promote training, recruitment, education and outreach activities for the geophysics discipline.   The proposal was developed in the era of disrupted learning due to the COVID-19 pandemic. However, the broader objectives in addition to those stated above include:  (1) Reduce the burden among faculty to incorporating effective teaching techniques in their course offerings  (2) Create a more inclusive classroom and broaden participation in geophysics.  (3) Create a stronger Geophysics/Seismology education community   The primary goal of this project was to build the seed of a seismology or geophysics course that better educates students, especially to encourage those undergraduates from underrepresented groups that seismology and graduate school is a viable option for them. In this sense the modules have benefited students. It also has given undergraduate Cielo Martos and Shamya Pugh an opportunity to meet Latinx, Black, and first-in-their family seismologists, practice preparing for and interviewing individuals, and video editing. Ayla Martinelli (undergraduate student at University of Rochester) was involved in developing in-class quizzes (active learning resources) using poll everywhere software.   As we look to future iterations, here are some proposed steps:    (1) Keep track of views and downloads of lectures and interviews (2) Send out content for external review (3) distribute questionnaires on how these resources are being used.       Last Modified: 11/29/2021       Submitted by: Tolulope M Olugboji]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
