<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research: EAGER: Advancing Pedagogy and Inclusivity through Multimodal Upper Level Geophysics Education]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>5556.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>5556</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Eva Zanzerkia</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ezanzerk@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924734</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Today, classrooms are challenged by the need for flexible learning due to the COVID-19 pandemic and for dynamic course materials that attract students from diverse backgrounds and allow them to thrive. This EAGER initiates a pilot effort to develop research-based learning modules for the upper level geophysics classes that can be used by geophysics programs across the country. At the upper level there are fewer resources for teaching and course development guides, and there is a notable drop off in students from underrepresented groups. This EAGER will explore how to implement high quality teaching materials to create a more equitable and inclusive learning environment that can build student confidence and allow students from a variety of diverse backgrounds to succeed. The PI team brings together complementary academic expertise facilitating the creation of a broad range of teaching modules and the convergence between upper level geophysics students and students in core STEM disciplines such as physics, mathematics, and computational science, which are fundamental disciplines on which global seismology relies.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will design multimodal pilot modules on (1) Elastodynamics, (2) Seismology and Plate Tectonics, and (3) Near surface seismological methods and applications to the developed environment. The work has the potential to transform the traditional teaching mechanisms for upper level geophysics courses, and be used as a means to attract underrepresented groups to geophysics who may not have otherwise considered Earth science as a research focus. The project will incorporate flipped course design and mastery learning to help build student confidence, with the  materials created in such a way that they are adaptable to both on-line and in-person teaching. In addition, the team will further develop inclusivity through the creation of biographies featuring scientists from underrepresented groups that will be incorporated directly into the learning modules. The pilot modules will specifically focus on upper level geophysics courses to address and support students transitioning from undergraduate training to graduate school or to professional work in the geosciences, thus extending the pedagogical support from lower level to upper level geophysics teaching.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/14/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/14/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2042011</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Stefany</FirstName>
<LastName>Sit</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Stefany Sit</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ssit@uic.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000705535</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/14/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Illinois at Chicago</Name>
<CityName>CHICAGO</CityName>
<ZipCode>606124305</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3129962862</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>809 S MARSHFIELD AVE M/C 551</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>W8XEAJDKMXH3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ILLINOIS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Illinois at Chicago]]></Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>606077059</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[845 W. Taylor St.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7222</Code>
<Text>XC-Crosscutting Activities Pro</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~5556</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-abbfc39d-7fff-b131-f04b-97a5a05c3e8e" style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">We developed 2 multi-modal modules for a seismology course, a series of 16 lightboard lectures on background mathematics for seismology, 15 in-class real-time active learning exercises (poll everywhere), a set of interactive multimedia PDFs of seismotectonic observations, and 13 interviews with seismologists (with a special emphasis on those from diverse backgrounds). Our first objective is to create more inclusive classrooms and broaden participation in geophysics, with a particular focus on increasing the number of students from underrepresented groups that make the transition from undergraduate to graduate school. The developed course resources provide flexibility for student learners who may have more constraints on their time or may need additional resources for learning material. To improve efforts to broaden participation, the video spotlights feature varied academic and career paths of seismologists from underrepresented groups.&nbsp; An additional goal was to reduce the burden among faculty to incorporate effective teaching techniques through the development of adaptable and accessible course materials including video lectures, detailed derivations and homework solutions, interactive multimedia PDFs that include active links to citations, and seismologist video spotlights. These materials are developed to be an introduction to active learning teaching methods and are adaptable depending on teaching modality ? such as in-person, online, or for flipped classrooms.&nbsp; To help bridge the gap of learning how to translate research into a scientific paper or thesis, particularly for first generation students or for students who have been physically separated from their research group and advisor during the pandemic, </span><span style="font-size: 10.5pt; font-family: Arial; color: #000000; background-color: #ffffff; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">a short paper was revised that provides a framework in the form of an algorithmic flowchart on the major steps involved in the scientific research and writing process. </span><span style="font-size: 11pt; font-family: Arial; color: #000000; background-color: transparent; font-weight: 400; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">A final objective of the project was to create a strong geophysics/seismology education community. By making course resources available, we aimed to foster more discussion related to teaching among seismologists and also make the teaching of seismology more accessible to institutions that may not have seismologists as faculty members.</span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/02/2022<br>      Modified by: Stefany&nbsp;Sit</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ We developed 2 multi-modal modules for a seismology course, a series of 16 lightboard lectures on background mathematics for seismology, 15 in-class real-time active learning exercises (poll everywhere), a set of interactive multimedia PDFs of seismotectonic observations, and 13 interviews with seismologists (with a special emphasis on those from diverse backgrounds). Our first objective is to create more inclusive classrooms and broaden participation in geophysics, with a particular focus on increasing the number of students from underrepresented groups that make the transition from undergraduate to graduate school. The developed course resources provide flexibility for student learners who may have more constraints on their time or may need additional resources for learning material. To improve efforts to broaden participation, the video spotlights feature varied academic and career paths of seismologists from underrepresented groups.  An additional goal was to reduce the burden among faculty to incorporate effective teaching techniques through the development of adaptable and accessible course materials including video lectures, detailed derivations and homework solutions, interactive multimedia PDFs that include active links to citations, and seismologist video spotlights. These materials are developed to be an introduction to active learning teaching methods and are adaptable depending on teaching modality ? such as in-person, online, or for flipped classrooms.  To help bridge the gap of learning how to translate research into a scientific paper or thesis, particularly for first generation students or for students who have been physically separated from their research group and advisor during the pandemic, a short paper was revised that provides a framework in the form of an algorithmic flowchart on the major steps involved in the scientific research and writing process. A final objective of the project was to create a strong geophysics/seismology education community. By making course resources available, we aimed to foster more discussion related to teaching among seismologists and also make the teaching of seismology more accessible to institutions that may not have seismologists as faculty members.       Last Modified: 02/02/2022       Submitted by: Stefany Sit]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
