<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[I-Corps:  Mechanistic solid-state welding model for materially efficient metal extrusions]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ruth Shuman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rshuman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922160</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this I-Corps project is the development of a sustainable manufacturing process that reduces the costs and time to market for light metal extrusions increasingly used in electric vehicles, machinery, and buildings. This development has the potential to double an extruder’s profit margin, make U.S. manufacturers more competitive, and ultimately save the global industry around $4 billion per year. The proposed process may accelerate the adoption of efficient extrusion designs, leading to lighter vehicles and less pollution from transport. In addition, this process may make U.S. manufacturing more environmentally sustainable by reducing the scrap that is generated in conventional extrusion by 25-50%. If successful, this will increase the energy efficiency and reduce the carbon footprint of U.S. industry. Furthermore, the underlying science on solid-state welding developed for this technology may inform the development of other joining technologies to prevent undesirable welds from forming.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project is based on the development of mechanistic solid-state welding models, extrusion simulations, and algorithms for designing new light metal extrusion tools and billet shapes. This development may reduce the scrap generated in direct extrusion of aluminum and magnesium components. Currently, around one-quarter of the extruded material fails to make it to a final product and is scrapped within the manufacturing process. One source of manufacturing scrap is the removal of the weak, solid-state weld that forms between consecutively extruded metal billets. The proposed technology controls the geometry of the final transverse weld and the deformation conditions across the evolving interface as it passes through the extrusion die. This in turn determines the interface oxide fragmentation, normal and shear contact stresses at the interface, and subsequently the weld strength. This technology is designed to shorten the weld (reducing the quantity of the profile that must be removed) and increase the weld’s strength (negating the need to remove the weld in many non-critical applications). Early physical trials and simulations on aluminum billets indicate that the new technology may reduce the generation of extrusion scrap by at least 25%.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/17/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/15/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041, 47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2042608</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
<LastName>Cooper</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Daniel Cooper</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[drcooper@umich.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000757095</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/17/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Regents of the University of Michigan - Ann Arbor</Name>
<CityName>ANN ARBOR</CityName>
<ZipCode>481091079</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1109 GEDDES AVE, SUITE 3300</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>GNJ7BBP73WE9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MICHIGAN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Regents of the University of Michigan - Ann Arbor]]></Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3003 S. State St]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8037</Code>
<Text>Advanced Manufacturing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><div> <p>The global metal extrusion industry is rapidly expanding, but it faces a significant challenge as up to 25% of extruded material goes to waste during manufacturing due to the formation of weak, bullet-shaped, solid-state transverse welds between consecutively extruded billets. To address this issue, our patent-pending technology incorporates innovative solid-state welding models, extrusion simulations, and algorithms for designing new light metal extrusion tools (dummy blocks) and billet shapes. This technology reduces scrap material by 25-50%, depending on the profile shape.</p> <p>The intellectual merit of our research during the NSF I-Corps project focused on controlling the geometry and strength of aluminum extrusion transverse welds and deformation conditions during the extrusion process. By employing bespoke extrusion dummy block profiles and novel billet geometries, coupled with finite element analyses and a novel solid-state weld strength model, our technology minimizes scrap material and strengthens welds. This approach is groundbreaking because it addresses deformation conditions specific to the extrusion process, setting it apart from previous welding models and methods like friction stir welding or accumulative roll bonding.</p> <p>The broader impact of our work extends beyond the extrusion industry. Our models have potential applications in preventing solid-state welding of mechanical components in low-oxygen environments, such as outer space. Additionally, our technology promises substantial cost savings for extruders, potentially doubling their profit margins, and ultimately saving the global industry around $4 billion annually. Decreased extrusion costs will also drive the transition to more efficient extrusion designs in the transport sector, reducing carbon emissions. Furthermore, our technology aligns with sustainable manufacturing principles, reducing energy requirements and carbon footprints in the U.S. industry.</p> <p>The I-Corps customer discovery process has provided valuable insights that informed our successful NSF PFI proposal and led to the development of multiple journal and conference articles on energy and material efficiency in the aluminum extrusion industry. We also uncovered another significant opportunity, resulting in a new patent application and potential funding for a new technology concept. One key discovery was that reducing process scrap offers environmental benefits and productivity gains, addressing the industry's focus on reducing its carbon footprint and operational efficiency. This insight led to a new journal article on 'Reducing the environmental impacts of aluminum extrusion' and a new technology for reducing quench distortion in quench-sensitive aluminum alloys, along with seed funding and a patent application. Moreover, our I-Corps experience led to a successful NSF PFI award, industry funding, and the establishment of a new Michigan-based company, Saltaire Sustainability LLC, to commercialize these technologies.</p> </div><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/29/2023<br>      Modified by: Daniel&nbsp;Cooper</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  The global metal extrusion industry is rapidly expanding, but it faces a significant challenge as up to 25% of extruded material goes to waste during manufacturing due to the formation of weak, bullet-shaped, solid-state transverse welds between consecutively extruded billets. To address this issue, our patent-pending technology incorporates innovative solid-state welding models, extrusion simulations, and algorithms for designing new light metal extrusion tools (dummy blocks) and billet shapes. This technology reduces scrap material by 25-50%, depending on the profile shape.  The intellectual merit of our research during the NSF I-Corps project focused on controlling the geometry and strength of aluminum extrusion transverse welds and deformation conditions during the extrusion process. By employing bespoke extrusion dummy block profiles and novel billet geometries, coupled with finite element analyses and a novel solid-state weld strength model, our technology minimizes scrap material and strengthens welds. This approach is groundbreaking because it addresses deformation conditions specific to the extrusion process, setting it apart from previous welding models and methods like friction stir welding or accumulative roll bonding.  The broader impact of our work extends beyond the extrusion industry. Our models have potential applications in preventing solid-state welding of mechanical components in low-oxygen environments, such as outer space. Additionally, our technology promises substantial cost savings for extruders, potentially doubling their profit margins, and ultimately saving the global industry around $4 billion annually. Decreased extrusion costs will also drive the transition to more efficient extrusion designs in the transport sector, reducing carbon emissions. Furthermore, our technology aligns with sustainable manufacturing principles, reducing energy requirements and carbon footprints in the U.S. industry.  The I-Corps customer discovery process has provided valuable insights that informed our successful NSF PFI proposal and led to the development of multiple journal and conference articles on energy and material efficiency in the aluminum extrusion industry. We also uncovered another significant opportunity, resulting in a new patent application and potential funding for a new technology concept. One key discovery was that reducing process scrap offers environmental benefits and productivity gains, addressing the industry's focus on reducing its carbon footprint and operational efficiency. This insight led to a new journal article on 'Reducing the environmental impacts of aluminum extrusion' and a new technology for reducing quench distortion in quench-sensitive aluminum alloys, along with seed funding and a patent application. Moreover, our I-Corps experience led to a successful NSF PFI award, industry funding, and the establishment of a new Michigan-based company, Saltaire Sustainability LLC, to commercialize these technologies.        Last Modified: 10/29/2023       Submitted by: Daniel Cooper]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
