<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Science Diplomacy to Promote and Strengthen Basic Research and International Cooperation]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>49999.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>49999</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Roxanne Nikolaus</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rnikolau@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927578</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[As the science community works together to solve large-scale global challenges, the commitment and accord of funding agencies is invaluable in advancing the work necessary to solve these challenges. The planning meetings on Science Diplomacy to Promote and Strengthen Basic Research and International Cooperation will explore options and best practices for U.S. and other funding agencies to consider with regard to global norms for basic research collaboration. The meeting will also investigate the role of U.S. and other funding agencies in science diplomacy and how best to leverage and strengthen networks. As global problems affect the U.S population and others around the world, promoting the advancement of basic science aims to benefit the public within the context of working toward global solutions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Global Research Council (GRC) represents an important constituency of heads of science and engineering funding agencies from around the world that are dedicated to promoting high-quality collaboration among funding agencies worldwide. The GRC plays a unique role in the scientific research enterprise, as scientists rely on funding agencies to conduct their work. The planning meetings on will identify different mechanisms and approaches for investigating the links between international basic research cooperation in the context of science diplomacy, such as: What are the current structures currently available to look at international basic research cooperation in a frame of science diplomacy?; What are the areas within basic research that might be worth exploring in greater depth to better connect research funders and science diplomacy practitioners?; What opportunities are there for the GRC and funder community to find new ways to work together on those areas and projects?&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/19/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/16/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.079</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2042775</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nicole</FirstName>
<LastName>Cervenka</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nicole Cervenka</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ncervenka@nas.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000861454</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/16/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
<LastName>Gasior</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Robert Gasior</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[rgasior@nas.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000834019</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/19/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate>09/16/2021</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>National Academy of Sciences</Name>
<CityName>WASHINGTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>204180007</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2023342254</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2101 CONSTITUTION AVE NW</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>PKFJZHG2MLG9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NATIONAL ACADEMY OF SCIENCES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>PKFJZHG2MLG9</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[National Academy of Sciences]]></Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>200012736</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[500 Fifth St NW]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7298</Code>
<Text>International Research Collab</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1066</Code>
<Text>SOUTH AFRICA</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5913</Code>
<Text>BRAZIL</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5914</Code>
<Text>WESTERN EUROPE, OTHER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5946</Code>
<Text>UNITED KINGDOM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>6194</Code>
<Text>INDIA</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9200</Code>
<Text>US CHINA COOP IN BASIC SCIENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002021DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~49999</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Summary&nbsp;</strong><br />A three-day virtual workshop, Science Diplomacy to Promote and Strengthen Research and International Cooperation, was convened over the course of 3 days: March 12, 15, and 16, 2021. Participants from 46 countries attended, and panelists included those from science academies, funding agencies, research organizations, universities, and international/regional institutions. Workshop facilitators and panelists described (i) institutional goals and structures for international research cooperation in the framework of science diplomacy, (ii) basic research areas worth exploring in greater depth, (iii) opportunities for the GRC and funder communities to work together, and (iv) roles for multilateral organizations to contribute.&nbsp; The workshop also addressed challenges for science diplomacy, strategies to maximize opportunities, and what role might GRC play in relation to science diplomacy in the future.</p> <p>NASEM published a report following this workshop, <em>Science Diplomacy to Promote and Strengthen Research and International Cooperation: Proceedings of a Workshop?in Brief</em> (2021), a high-level summary of the workshop discussion, including the ways in which science diplomacy can promote basic research.&nbsp;</p> <p><br /><strong>Intellectual Merit</strong><br />The workshop Science Diplomacy to Promote and Strengthen Research and International Cooperation offered a unique opportunity for experts from a variety of disciplines to advise the Global Research Council on how to support basic science research and science diplomacy. A wide range of expertise was represented at the workshop, including but not limited to the following organizations: the Japan Society for the Promotion of Science, Science Foundation Ireland, Russian Foundation for Basic Research, UKRI, American Academy of Arts and Sciences, Indian National Science Academy, Brazilian Academy of Sciences, International Science Council, International Institute for Applied Systems Analysis, CERN, and National Research Foundation of South Africa. The panelists presented on not only specific problems and solutions for their discipline/area of expertise, but set this in the broader context of science diplomacy and how to connect with other disciplines. In particular, panelists offered suggestions on about how to address global challenges and advance the UN Sustainable Development Goals and, more generally, address climate change, biodiversity, disaster risks, the ocean, and public health. Panelists also explored topics in relation to science diplomacy, including open science, trust in science, basic science infrastructure, science communication, and collaboration between the Global North and South.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts</strong><strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p>In addition to providing advice to the Global Research Council, the workshop also offered attendees the opportunity to learn about the priorities of various funding agencies on promoting science diplomacy, including from private foundations and national government agencies. It also involved an exchange of ideas in areas of basic science research ripe for international cooperation, presented by scientific institutions and academies. Panelists discussed the linkages of science diplomacy and basic science research to: cybersecurity; security and visas; vaccine inequities; and diversity, equity, inclusion, and gender.</p> <p>The NASEM report was disseminated to the Global Research Council, including a presentation at the GRC annual meeting on the workshop report.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/01/2021<br>      Modified by: Nicole&nbsp;Cervenka</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Summary  A three-day virtual workshop, Science Diplomacy to Promote and Strengthen Research and International Cooperation, was convened over the course of 3 days: March 12, 15, and 16, 2021. Participants from 46 countries attended, and panelists included those from science academies, funding agencies, research organizations, universities, and international/regional institutions. Workshop facilitators and panelists described (i) institutional goals and structures for international research cooperation in the framework of science diplomacy, (ii) basic research areas worth exploring in greater depth, (iii) opportunities for the GRC and funder communities to work together, and (iv) roles for multilateral organizations to contribute.  The workshop also addressed challenges for science diplomacy, strategies to maximize opportunities, and what role might GRC play in relation to science diplomacy in the future.  NASEM published a report following this workshop, Science Diplomacy to Promote and Strengthen Research and International Cooperation: Proceedings of a Workshop?in Brief (2021), a high-level summary of the workshop discussion, including the ways in which science diplomacy can promote basic research.    Intellectual Merit The workshop Science Diplomacy to Promote and Strengthen Research and International Cooperation offered a unique opportunity for experts from a variety of disciplines to advise the Global Research Council on how to support basic science research and science diplomacy. A wide range of expertise was represented at the workshop, including but not limited to the following organizations: the Japan Society for the Promotion of Science, Science Foundation Ireland, Russian Foundation for Basic Research, UKRI, American Academy of Arts and Sciences, Indian National Science Academy, Brazilian Academy of Sciences, International Science Council, International Institute for Applied Systems Analysis, CERN, and National Research Foundation of South Africa. The panelists presented on not only specific problems and solutions for their discipline/area of expertise, but set this in the broader context of science diplomacy and how to connect with other disciplines. In particular, panelists offered suggestions on about how to address global challenges and advance the UN Sustainable Development Goals and, more generally, address climate change, biodiversity, disaster risks, the ocean, and public health. Panelists also explored topics in relation to science diplomacy, including open science, trust in science, basic science infrastructure, science communication, and collaboration between the Global North and South.      Broader Impacts   In addition to providing advice to the Global Research Council, the workshop also offered attendees the opportunity to learn about the priorities of various funding agencies on promoting science diplomacy, including from private foundations and national government agencies. It also involved an exchange of ideas in areas of basic science research ripe for international cooperation, presented by scientific institutions and academies. Panelists discussed the linkages of science diplomacy and basic science research to: cybersecurity; security and visas; vaccine inequities; and diversity, equity, inclusion, and gender.  The NASEM report was disseminated to the Global Research Council, including a presentation at the GRC annual meeting on the workshop report.        Last Modified: 10/01/2021       Submitted by: Nicole Cervenka]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
