<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Coronavirus API (COVID-19)]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>256000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>256000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Alastair Monk</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>amonk@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924392</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is to accelerate development of a digital infrastructure trust layer for public health data around monitoring and responding to COVID-19 public health objectives. This project will provide both trust and accessibility through the application of blockchain technology to public health data to transform it into verified, legally weighted, and tamper resistant data upon which decision makers in the public and private sector can benefit. This innovative combination of new technological solutions will allow for better products, data analytics, predictive modelling systems, and ESG (environmental, social and governance) responsiveness based on organized and trusted systems. Since public health statistics are used by private enterprise as well as the public sector and the general public, the addition of a trust layer to public health data more widely is important as fidelity in statistics is critical to effective individual and organizational action.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project’s goal is to develop tools and practices to make authoritative, reliable data available, enabled by cryptographic techniques and accessible to a broader set of individuals and organizations. The scope of the project looks to develop aggregation, access, and reporting systems which can support new decentralized economics, such as smart contract marketplaces, while remaining interoperable and accessible to users of legacy technology. The solution requires creation of a single, trustworthy platform that combines research, development and commercial application of emerging blockchain approaches with a suite of supporting technologies and systems including: distributed data infrastructure, flexible delivery methods, intuitive interfaces, and analytics tools. This research hopes to allow for the creation of novel resources to support the trustworthiness and consequently, the fundamental usefulness of all public health data records. The expected outcomes include: improved data integrity using blockchain-backed systems, tools enabling accelerated innovation in data driven decision making, and a prototype marketplace for COVID-19 resources managed by blockchain.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/21/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/14/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041, 47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2042690</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Susan</FirstName>
<LastName>Joseph</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>G</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Susan G Joseph</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[susan.joseph1786@gmail.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000832960</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/21/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>HEALTHTRENDS.AI LLC</Name>
<CityName>RYE BROOK</CityName>
<ZipCode>105731020</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9149241994</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>7 LAWRIDGE DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>16</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY16</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>YM7VKF5XKEM5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>HEALTHTRENDS.AI LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[HEALTHTRENDS.AI LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>BROOK</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>105731020</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[7 LAWRIDGE DR]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>16</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY16</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8018</Code>
<Text>Smart and Connected Health</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~256000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>SBIR Phase l HealthTrends.ai: Coronavirusapi(COVID-19)</p> <p>HealthTrends.ai's mission is to provide access to trusted public health data. Data is our first line of defense in a data-driven society and economy, especially in a global health crisis. The Covid pandemic brought the shortcomings of our existing health systems' public data into focus. The challenges in understanding and responding to the pandemic illustrate how unverified health data leads to an environment of misinformation. In the case of public health, that misinformation caused large commercial losses and health inequities with far-reaching consequences of significant illness and high death rates. The broader social impact of untrusted public health data is an overall environment of suspicion and confusion. Trusted public health data and information, and the ability to access it quickly, strengthens society and bolsters enterprise. During the SBIR Phase I project, Healthtrends.ai has designed and established feasibility for a validated data collection and distribution system that we call Valda. Valda takes a novel approach to data validation, backed by blockchain technology but accessible using traditional Web 2.0 tools. In addition to commercial value, our system is designed to provide usable and scalable tools in the face of any health emergency, pandemic, or other health crisis. The benefits of trusted data go beyond Covid to any reported public health dataset. In the case of the United States, numerous local governments by law have sovereign powers to surveil, collect, approve, and publish public health data such as hospitalization, mortality, case spread, vaccination, and long-term disease effects. There is no independent national source for this type of health data. The structure of this data is not standardized, nor are the delivery channels, extraction modes, formats, or definitions. We designed Valda to meet that challenge by providing a single platform for collecting, validating, cataloging, and analyzing complex and quickly-evolving datasets. Data access made easy, however, is not enough. We designed Valda not only as a public health data access platform but a data integrity platform. Our platform enables anyone using the data to quickly understand and audit precisely how the data was collected, what the source looked like at the time of collection, and correlate the raw data to supplemental contextual information even after transformation. The blockchain basis allows massive, cost-effective scaling of data processes by incentivizing trustworthy collaboration on data validation. Independent parties can orchestrate collecting, validating, and aggregating the data they need. Users need only imagine and request data aggregation via Valda. The platform's structure offers an app store like approach to public health data enabling third parties to construct innovative applications using this data. In an era of low public trust and data misinformation, the true power of Valda comes from creating an ecosystem around trusted data that provides societal benefits and improves business decisions.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/13/2022<br>      Modified by: Susan&nbsp;G&nbsp;Joseph</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ SBIR Phase l HealthTrends.ai: Coronavirusapi(COVID-19)  HealthTrends.ai's mission is to provide access to trusted public health data. Data is our first line of defense in a data-driven society and economy, especially in a global health crisis. The Covid pandemic brought the shortcomings of our existing health systems' public data into focus. The challenges in understanding and responding to the pandemic illustrate how unverified health data leads to an environment of misinformation. In the case of public health, that misinformation caused large commercial losses and health inequities with far-reaching consequences of significant illness and high death rates. The broader social impact of untrusted public health data is an overall environment of suspicion and confusion. Trusted public health data and information, and the ability to access it quickly, strengthens society and bolsters enterprise. During the SBIR Phase I project, Healthtrends.ai has designed and established feasibility for a validated data collection and distribution system that we call Valda. Valda takes a novel approach to data validation, backed by blockchain technology but accessible using traditional Web 2.0 tools. In addition to commercial value, our system is designed to provide usable and scalable tools in the face of any health emergency, pandemic, or other health crisis. The benefits of trusted data go beyond Covid to any reported public health dataset. In the case of the United States, numerous local governments by law have sovereign powers to surveil, collect, approve, and publish public health data such as hospitalization, mortality, case spread, vaccination, and long-term disease effects. There is no independent national source for this type of health data. The structure of this data is not standardized, nor are the delivery channels, extraction modes, formats, or definitions. We designed Valda to meet that challenge by providing a single platform for collecting, validating, cataloging, and analyzing complex and quickly-evolving datasets. Data access made easy, however, is not enough. We designed Valda not only as a public health data access platform but a data integrity platform. Our platform enables anyone using the data to quickly understand and audit precisely how the data was collected, what the source looked like at the time of collection, and correlate the raw data to supplemental contextual information even after transformation. The blockchain basis allows massive, cost-effective scaling of data processes by incentivizing trustworthy collaboration on data validation. Independent parties can orchestrate collecting, validating, and aggregating the data they need. Users need only imagine and request data aggregation via Valda. The platform's structure offers an app store like approach to public health data enabling third parties to construct innovative applications using this data. In an era of low public trust and data misinformation, the true power of Valda comes from creating an ecosystem around trusted data that provides societal benefits and improves business decisions.       Last Modified: 07/13/2022       Submitted by: Susan G Joseph]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
