<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Planning a Shared Autonomous Vehicle Mobility Pilot for Linking Affordable Housing and Jobs]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/15/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>49693.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>49693</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>David Corman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dcorman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928754</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Low-mid income residents living in affordable housing areas of a city are often faced with problems in accessing jobs or other locations of opportunity due to limited mobility choices including the lack of a public transportation system. Since the underlying problem is usually the high and therefore unfeasible cost of operating public transportation or other similar mobility options, operation of a fleet of ride hailing and ride-sharing autonomous vehicles that can also be used for the delivery of food and supplies during a pandemic like the current Covid-19 outbreak is proposed as a feasible solution. This approach of deploying ride Shared Autonomous Vehicles (SAV) in a transit desert will give residents an on-demand, fast and affordable option of connecting to their job locations, allowing them to have faster and reliable access to work, services and amenities that are otherwise not so easily accessible in reasonable travel periods. The broader impact of this project is to benefit society and advance the desired societal outcome of improving access to jobs from low-mid income neighborhoods in a smart city.  The team will be addressing these needs from both the technological perspective of SAVs as well as from the social science dimension of this technology can both work with the community and be shaped by it.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project brings together researchers from several disciplines with community partners to plan an affordable, innovative mobility solution that better connects residents to work, critical services, and amenities. The research pilot deployment that will be planned in this project is the use of SAVs in the City of Marysville, Ohio to give its residents a fast and affordable option of connecting to their job locations. The SAVs will be fully electric vehicles with an optimal routing algorithm that will reduce their trip time and energy footprint. The project team will identify demand locations corresponding to affordable housing in Marysville and destination locations corresponding to jobs, determine the geo-fenced area of SAV operation, plan integration with the existing transportation systems for increasing trip range, analyze existing traffic data, build an SAV operation simulation environment for the chosen geo-fenced area and use it to plan a research pilot deployment. The project team will also identify vendors and methods for operation of the pilot. The planning work of this Stage 1 planning project will be compiled into a Stage 2 proposal and will include the plan for the Stage 2 research pilot and how it will be evaluated for success.  This project is funded in response to CIVIC Innovation Challenge Track A. Communities and Mobility: Offering Better Mobility Options to Solve the Spatial Mismatch Between Housing Affordability and Jobs which is a collaboration between NSF and Department of Energy Vehicle Technology Office.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/08/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/20/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2042715</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Bilin</FirstName>
<LastName>Aksun-Guvenc</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Bilin Aksun-Guvenc</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[aksunguvenc.1@osu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000691044</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/08/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Levent</FirstName>
<LastName>Guvenc</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Levent Guvenc</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[guvenc.1@osu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000715930</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/08/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Ohio State University</Name>
<CityName>COLUMBUS</CityName>
<ZipCode>432101016</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6146888735</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1960 KENNY RD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OH03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>DLWBSLWAJWR1</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OHIO STATE UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>MN4MDDMN8529</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Ohio State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Columbus</CityName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>432101142</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Mechanical and Aerospace Eng.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OH03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>033Y</Code>
<Text>S&amp;CC: Smart &amp; Connected Commun</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>042Z</Code>
<Text>S&amp;CC: Smart and Connected Communities</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~49693</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Low-mid income residents living in affordable housing areas of a city are often faced with problems in accessing jobs or other locations of opportunity due to limited mobility choices including the lack of a public transportation system. Since the underlying problem is usually the high and therefore unfeasible cost of operating public transportation or other similar mobility options, operation of a fleet of ride hailing and ride-sharing autonomous vehicles that can also be used for the delivery of food and supplies during a pandemic was proposed as a feasible solution. This approach of deploying ride Shared Autonomous Vehicles (SAV) in a transit desert will give residents an on-demand, fast and affordable option of connecting to their job locations, allowing them to have faster and reliable access to work, services and amenities that are otherwise not so easily accessible in reasonable travel periods. The broader impact of this project was to benefit society and advance the desired societal outcome of improving access to jobs from low-mid income neighborhoods in a smart city. Ohio State University and the City of Marysville in Union County, Ohio worked together in this four-month planning project to identify the needs of the community and to plan a Shared Autonomous Vehicle service pilot deployment to demonstrate its efficacy as an affordable, implementable, scalable and replicable solution. A survey of 300 residents showed the interest in and the need for such a service. The project team identified and contacted several autonomous vehicle service providers and determined the methods for operation of the pilot together with the chosen company. Two autonomous vehicles with seven passenger capacity with on-demand ride-hailing of multiple passengers were chosen for the pilot deployment. Connectivity of the vehicles to the existing connected vehicle infrastructure in Marysville with 29 road-side-unit instrumented connected intersections with traffic lights, two of them being smart intersections capable of detecting oncoming traffic and pedestrians using camera/lidar and broadcasting Basic Safety Message (BSM) information for all of them based on camera/lidar perceived motion data was planned as part of the pilot deployment.</p> <p>An affordable, innovative mobility solution that better connects residents to work, critical services, and amenities was prepared as an excellent example of university and community cooperation to solve a real transportation challenge. The research pilot deployment that was planned in this project through the use of SAVs in the City of Marysville, Ohio was designed to give its residents a fast and affordable option of connecting to their job locations. The SAVs that were chosen were fully electric vehicles with an optimal routing algorithm that reduced their trip time and energy footprint. The project team identified demand locations corresponding to affordable housing in the periphery of Marysville and destination locations corresponding to jobs and other places of opportunity, determined the geo-fenced area of SAV operation, planned integration with the existing appointment based UCATS transportation system for transporting elderly and individuals with disabilities, planned for increasing trip range, analyzed existing traffic data, built an SAV operation simulation environment for the chosen geo-fenced area and used it to plan the research pilot deployment using traffic-in-the-loop simulation. The planning work was compiled into a proposal with a detailed risk and contingency management plan. Intermediate and final results were shared with other interested communities through the events organized by MetroLab Network.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/12/2022<br>      Modified by: Levent&nbsp;Guvenc</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Low-mid income residents living in affordable housing areas of a city are often faced with problems in accessing jobs or other locations of opportunity due to limited mobility choices including the lack of a public transportation system. Since the underlying problem is usually the high and therefore unfeasible cost of operating public transportation or other similar mobility options, operation of a fleet of ride hailing and ride-sharing autonomous vehicles that can also be used for the delivery of food and supplies during a pandemic was proposed as a feasible solution. This approach of deploying ride Shared Autonomous Vehicles (SAV) in a transit desert will give residents an on-demand, fast and affordable option of connecting to their job locations, allowing them to have faster and reliable access to work, services and amenities that are otherwise not so easily accessible in reasonable travel periods. The broader impact of this project was to benefit society and advance the desired societal outcome of improving access to jobs from low-mid income neighborhoods in a smart city. Ohio State University and the City of Marysville in Union County, Ohio worked together in this four-month planning project to identify the needs of the community and to plan a Shared Autonomous Vehicle service pilot deployment to demonstrate its efficacy as an affordable, implementable, scalable and replicable solution. A survey of 300 residents showed the interest in and the need for such a service. The project team identified and contacted several autonomous vehicle service providers and determined the methods for operation of the pilot together with the chosen company. Two autonomous vehicles with seven passenger capacity with on-demand ride-hailing of multiple passengers were chosen for the pilot deployment. Connectivity of the vehicles to the existing connected vehicle infrastructure in Marysville with 29 road-side-unit instrumented connected intersections with traffic lights, two of them being smart intersections capable of detecting oncoming traffic and pedestrians using camera/lidar and broadcasting Basic Safety Message (BSM) information for all of them based on camera/lidar perceived motion data was planned as part of the pilot deployment.  An affordable, innovative mobility solution that better connects residents to work, critical services, and amenities was prepared as an excellent example of university and community cooperation to solve a real transportation challenge. The research pilot deployment that was planned in this project through the use of SAVs in the City of Marysville, Ohio was designed to give its residents a fast and affordable option of connecting to their job locations. The SAVs that were chosen were fully electric vehicles with an optimal routing algorithm that reduced their trip time and energy footprint. The project team identified demand locations corresponding to affordable housing in the periphery of Marysville and destination locations corresponding to jobs and other places of opportunity, determined the geo-fenced area of SAV operation, planned integration with the existing appointment based UCATS transportation system for transporting elderly and individuals with disabilities, planned for increasing trip range, analyzed existing traffic data, built an SAV operation simulation environment for the chosen geo-fenced area and used it to plan the research pilot deployment using traffic-in-the-loop simulation. The planning work was compiled into a proposal with a detailed risk and contingency management plan. Intermediate and final results were shared with other interested communities through the events organized by MetroLab Network.          Last Modified: 08/12/2022       Submitted by: Levent Guvenc]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
