<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research:  Measuring the Long-Term Effects of California's 2004 Paid Family Leave Statute with U.S. Tax Data]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>117156.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>117156</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Nancy Lutz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>nlutz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927280</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Paid family leave has been championed as a policy to reduce labor market inequality and narrow the gender gap in wage earnings. California was the first state in the nation to enact a paid family leave statute effective in July 2014, but data have limited strong conclusions about the policy's impacts. This research uses novel, large-scale Internal Revenue Services (IRS) tax data to understand how California's paid leave policy affected parents' careers and family structure over its first decade in existence.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research uses large-scale administrative IRS tax data to quantify the effect of California's 2004 Paid Family Leave Statute on the short and long-term labor-market and family outcomes.  The sample consists of the universe of tax-filers allowing the investigators to follow individual mothers and fathers from 2001 to 2015, link to their children's exact date of birth using data from the Social Security Administration, and examine changes in labor market outcomes in the short-term (less than 1 year after her first birth), near term (1-5 years after birth), and long-term (6-10 years after birth). In addition, this research examines changes around first birth before the policy change took place as an internal validity check. For both mothers and fathers, the investigators provide novel evidence of how the 2004 Paid Family Leave Statute has impacted labor-force attachment, employer transitions, and wage growth. In addition, the investigators study how the Statute affected family structure, including both marital stability and childbearing.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/16/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/14/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2043244</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Martha</FirstName>
<LastName>Bailey</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Martha J Bailey</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[marthabailey@g.ucla.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000482550</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/16/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Los Angeles</Name>
<CityName>LOS ANGELES</CityName>
<ZipCode>900244201</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3107940102</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>10889 WILSHIRE BLVD STE 700</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>36</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA36</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>RN64EPNH8JC6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, LOS ANGELES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>NUDGYLBB4S99</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Los Angeles]]></Name>
<CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>900951406</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[337 Charles E Young Dr E]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>36</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA36</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1320</Code>
<Text>Economics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1371</Code>
<Text>Political Science</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9229</Code>
<Text>RES IN UNDERGRAD INST-RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01001819DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~117155</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="FirstPage">This project evaluates the short- and long-run effects of the 2004 California Paid Family Leave Act (CPFL) on women&rsquo;s careers using administrative tax data.&nbsp;</p> <p>Our research design relies on discontinuous changes in women&rsquo;s ability to take <em>consecutive</em> weeks of paid parental leave after the implementation of CPFL. Although women giving birth as early as August 2003 were eligible for at least six weeks of paid leave benefits under CPFL, only women giving birth after May 15, 2004, could take these additional weeks immediately following six weeks of partially paid under California's temporary disability insurance program. We find the ability to take consecutive weeks of leave mattered. The data show that women giving birth after May 15 were 16 percentage points more likely to take up paid leave than those giving birth too soon to take CPFL&rsquo;s paid leave consecutively.</p> <p>Our analysis exploits this sharp change in take up using a regression discontinuity in time (RDDiT). This approach compares women who gave birth after May 15, 2004 (our treatment group), to women who gave birth earlier in 2004 (our comparison group). Supporting the internal validity of this strategy, we find no evidence that women strategically delayed childbearing to take advantage of CPFL benefits. In addition, our treatment and comparison groups are well-balanced for a rich and well-measured set of pre-pregnancy outcomes. Owing to very large sample sizes, covariate balance means that differences in characteristics are extremely small and support our identification assumption that assignment to treatment and control groups is as good as experimentally randomized (Lee and Lemieux 2010).</p> <p>Our results challenge the conventional wisdom that paid leave benefits improve women&rsquo;s career outcomes. The local average treatment effect of taking up paid leave significantly <em>decreased </em>mothers&rsquo; employment, especially among first-time mothers whose employment fell by 5 percent in the short run and remained this low up to 14 years later. Similarly, CPFL&nbsp;<em>reduced</em> annual wage earnings among first-time mothers by over 10 percent in the 14 years after giving birth. These wage effects could reflect reductions in mothers&rsquo; work intensity (i.e., working fewer hours and weeks) as well as changes in jobs (i.e., working in jobs with lower wages). However, we find no evidence of persistent employment or wage effects of CPFL for the subset of mothers who had their first child before the policy and returned to work before CPFL passed.</p> <p>The lack of U.S. paid leave policy is often cited as a cause of the gender gap in pay and employment. This analysis, however, suggests that even small (relative to European standards) paid leave programs may have the unintended effect of <em>reducing</em> labor-market equality between the sexes. This finding will not be surprising to students of Europe&rsquo;s many paid leave programs, which have not led to reductions in the motherhood penalty over the last three decades (Blau and Kahn 2013, Kleven et al. 2019). To address gender inequities in the labor market, policy makers in Europe have begun trying to reverse the incentives created paid leave policies by mandating &ldquo;daddy quotas&rdquo; (Norway), earmarking paid leave time for fathers (Denmark), or requiring a minimum number of days for paid paternity leave (European Union&rsquo;s Directive on Work-Life Balance 2019/1158, effective in 2022).&nbsp;Our research suggests that US policymakers should not expect newly enacted or newly proposed paid leave policies in the U.S. to lead to greater labor market equity. Notwithstanding, we find suggestive evidence that CPFL benefitted U.S. families by increasing time with children&mdash;even if these policies increased the gender gap in pay.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/29/2021<br>      Modified by: Martha&nbsp;J&nbsp;Bailey</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[This project evaluates the short- and long-run effects of the 2004 California Paid Family Leave Act (CPFL) on women’s careers using administrative tax data.   Our research design relies on discontinuous changes in women’s ability to take consecutive weeks of paid parental leave after the implementation of CPFL. Although women giving birth as early as August 2003 were eligible for at least six weeks of paid leave benefits under CPFL, only women giving birth after May 15, 2004, could take these additional weeks immediately following six weeks of partially paid under California's temporary disability insurance program. We find the ability to take consecutive weeks of leave mattered. The data show that women giving birth after May 15 were 16 percentage points more likely to take up paid leave than those giving birth too soon to take CPFL’s paid leave consecutively.  Our analysis exploits this sharp change in take up using a regression discontinuity in time (RDDiT). This approach compares women who gave birth after May 15, 2004 (our treatment group), to women who gave birth earlier in 2004 (our comparison group). Supporting the internal validity of this strategy, we find no evidence that women strategically delayed childbearing to take advantage of CPFL benefits. In addition, our treatment and comparison groups are well-balanced for a rich and well-measured set of pre-pregnancy outcomes. Owing to very large sample sizes, covariate balance means that differences in characteristics are extremely small and support our identification assumption that assignment to treatment and control groups is as good as experimentally randomized (Lee and Lemieux 2010).  Our results challenge the conventional wisdom that paid leave benefits improve women’s career outcomes. The local average treatment effect of taking up paid leave significantly decreased mothers’ employment, especially among first-time mothers whose employment fell by 5 percent in the short run and remained this low up to 14 years later. Similarly, CPFL reduced annual wage earnings among first-time mothers by over 10 percent in the 14 years after giving birth. These wage effects could reflect reductions in mothers’ work intensity (i.e., working fewer hours and weeks) as well as changes in jobs (i.e., working in jobs with lower wages). However, we find no evidence of persistent employment or wage effects of CPFL for the subset of mothers who had their first child before the policy and returned to work before CPFL passed.  The lack of U.S. paid leave policy is often cited as a cause of the gender gap in pay and employment. This analysis, however, suggests that even small (relative to European standards) paid leave programs may have the unintended effect of reducing labor-market equality between the sexes. This finding will not be surprising to students of Europe’s many paid leave programs, which have not led to reductions in the motherhood penalty over the last three decades (Blau and Kahn 2013, Kleven et al. 2019). To address gender inequities in the labor market, policy makers in Europe have begun trying to reverse the incentives created paid leave policies by mandating "daddy quotas" (Norway), earmarking paid leave time for fathers (Denmark), or requiring a minimum number of days for paid paternity leave (European Union’s Directive on Work-Life Balance 2019/1158, effective in 2022). Our research suggests that US policymakers should not expect newly enacted or newly proposed paid leave policies in the U.S. to lead to greater labor market equity. Notwithstanding, we find suggestive evidence that CPFL benefitted U.S. families by increasing time with children&mdash;even if these policies increased the gender gap in pay.       Last Modified: 12/29/2021       Submitted by: Martha J Bailey]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
