<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Collaborative Research: Mobilization and transport of contaminants to groundwater in flood-impacted unconnected communities in South Texas following Hurricane Hanna]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>11/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>34836.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>58382</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Hendratta Ali</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>heali@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922648</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[With a potential increase in the occurrence of major hurricanes making landfall, there is an immediate need to understand their impacts in vulnerable coastal areas. Flooding from heavy rain and ocean storm surge may damage infrastructure and result in the release of sewage and other toxic chemicals into environmental waters. Flood water could also enter groundwater systems and mobilize contaminants to points of exposure. Particularly vulnerable are coastal communities that lack basic water infrastructure and have many potential sources of water pollutants. This study will collect groundwater samples from coastal areas that were flooded after Hurricane Hanna made landfall on the south Texas coast.  It will generate necessary data to advance understanding on the impacts to water quality and movement of microbial and chemical contaminants in coastal groundwater systems subjected to catastrophic flooding and input of contaminants after landfall of major storm events.  Results will provide data than can inform scientists, public officials, and community members on the spread and distribution of contaminants after flooding from extreme storm events in coastal areas. This information is essential for predicting and mitigating threats, increasing resilience and access to clean water and minimizing health impacts in coastal communities. The study will engage community members from underserved populations, share results with stakeholders, and support and train students from underrepresented groups in STEM fields. It will further prepare students on rapid-response research under challenging circumstances.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;The primary objective of this work is to advance knowledge and understanding about the immediate impacts to water quality and contamination in coastal areas subjected to flooding as a result of extremes events. It is hypothesized that contaminant inputs during flooding events can serve as tracers that can be monitored immediately following storms to gain knowledge about groundwater systems. The project will collect data to assess contamination in groundwater systems impacted by coastal flooding after the landfall of a major Hurricane in south Texas, determine the pathways and residence times of contaminants in groundwater following flooding by hurricanes, and quantify post-storm aquifer recharge and transport of contaminants. The proposed work entails collecting groundwater, runoff and river/lake samples from several flooded communities and use molecular and chemical analytical methods to measure and monitor presence and concentration levels of microbial contamination, trace metals, nitrates, hydrocarbons, pesticides and other organic pollutants over a 5-months period following Hurricane Hanna. The data will provide information on spatial and temporal concentrations in relation to flooded areas after the landfall of Hurricane Hanna. Mitigation and prevention efforts can then be designed to explicitly address groundwater contamination. Information from this study will be shared with outreach partners and stakeholders and used to develop factsheets on the health-risks of the identified contaminants and aquifer protection. This can translate to other communities in the US that have been affected by flooding and are facing similar issues. Through data dissemination, the project will educate and engage predominantly communities from underserved populations. The project will support and train students from underrepresented groups and help to broaden participation in STEM.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>10/29/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/20/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2043344</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dorina</FirstName>
<LastName>Murgulet</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Dorina Murgulet</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[dorina.murgulet@tamucc.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000621414</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>10/29/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Hussain</FirstName>
<LastName>Abdulla</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Hussain A Abdulla</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[hussain.abdulla@tamucc.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000588756</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>10/29/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Texas A&amp;M University Corpus Christi</Name>
<CityName>CORPUS CHRISTI</CityName>
<ZipCode>784125739</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3618252730</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>6300 OCEAN DR UNIT 5739</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>27</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX27</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>Y3RET2XN41S5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TEXAS A&amp;M UNIVERSITY-CORPUS CHRISTI</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Texas A&M University Corpus Christi]]></Name>
<CityName>Corpus Christi</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>784125843</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[6300 Ocean Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>27</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX27</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1579</Code>
<Text>Hydrologic Sciences</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7222</Code>
<Text>XC-Crosscutting Activities Pro</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>097Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Impacts on Existing Activities</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>102Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-Disproportionate Impcts Inst-Indiv</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~58382</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Large storms play an important role in moving waste and toxins in water and can cause water to become unsafe to drink through both heavy rains and from ocean waters pushed onto land. Flood waters also enter areas under the ground that store water (aquifers).&nbsp; This project tested above ground and below ground water from places in South Texas flooded during Hurricane Hanna and the impacts of subsequent weather conditions like drought or extreme wet seasons.&nbsp;</p> <p>Flooding and storm surges amplify the hazards of industrial sites and other above- and below-ground pollutants to nearby residents who consume water from local underground water (or groundwater) sources, presenting a high health risk to humans. This project monitored the chemistry of runoff and river/lake waters and groundwater in a rural area in the Rio Grande Valley (RGV) and another area near Baffin Bay in Texas where Hurricane Hanna brought flooding from downpours and storm surge, respectively. The research carried out quick-response observation of above- &nbsp;and below-ground &nbsp;water contamination in coastal areas.</p> <p>Hurricane Hanna made landfall in July 2020, impacting south Texas with storm surges reaching over 1.2m in Baffin Bay and floodwaters in the RGV over 1m deep. The project intensively measured the mobilization and persistence of fecal indicator bacteria, microbial pathogens, insecticides, nitrates, zinc, and lead, in flood waters and groundwater. Sample collection began days after Hurricane Hanna&rsquo;s landfall and continued until August 2021. Samples were collected biweekly for two months after landfall, monthly for the following three months, and bimonthly for the remainder of the project. Approximately 240 water samples were collected throughout the project.</p> <p>Nutrient (i.e., nitrate, or dissolved inorganic nitrogen) levels in groundwater were found to fluctuate based on both hydroclimate season and time of year. Dissolved inorganic nitrogen and phosphate were highest during the extended summer storms in 2021, lasting weeks/months, which coincided with the planting season when substantial amounts of fertilizer are typically used. Most of the samples collected throughout the project had varying amounts of total coliform present in both surface- and groundwater, with the highest concentration in surface water. <em>Escherichia coli,</em> a fecal coliform,<em> </em>was below detection limits regardless of the season in most groundwater samples. However, following Hanna a noticeable&nbsp;<em>E.coli&nbsp;</em>level was measured at one location in RGV, indicating direct contamination of the aquifer from flooding via water well conduits.</p> <p>Lead and zinc were present in groundwater, particularly at RGV, where concentrations significantly increased during the extended wet season in 2021. The quick response of the aquifer to hydroclimatic changes was also revealed by analyzing the stable isotopes of oxygen (&delta;<sup>18</sup>O) and hydrogen (&delta;D) present during the recharge process. Both surface- and groundwater were most depleted in the isotopes immediately after Hurricane Hanna with significant enrichment observed beginning approximately one month after the hurricane's landfall.</p> <p>As part of this study, surface water and groundwater samples were measured for pesticide contents. This is one of the most extensive studies that has screened and quantified over 200 pesticides in a single sample in the United States. The results of eight monitoring sampling campaigns revealed the occurrence of 21 pesticides with minimum instrumental limit of detection (LOD) of 0.05 ng/mL and limit of quantification (LOQ) of 0.10 ng/mL. Six herbicides were the most detected compounds, followed by insecticides (5), fungicides (4), &nbsp;transformation products of the original pesticides &nbsp;(3), and a plant growth regulator (1). The most frequently detected compounds were atrazine, clothianidin, cycluron, DEA, dinotefuran, and norflurazon and those with the highest concentrations were clothianidin (211 ng/L), DEET (13,885 ng/L), and norflurazon (952 ng/L).).In general, more compounds were detected in groundwater than in surface water, except for atrazine and DEA which were found at higher frequencies in surface water. &nbsp;Pesticides with high leaching potential are more likely to be transported in groundwater beyond application area. In this study, clothianidin and norflurazon with high leaching potential showed significant concentrations in groundwater.</p> <p>The data generated through this project provide means for mitigation and prevention efforts designed to explicitly address groundwater contamination. South Texas and communities like the colonias in RGV represent significant Hispanic populations, meaning this engagement supports underserved communities. Results are being disseminated to the communities included in the study. Funds provided from this grant enabled two underrepresented students to be trained in research of significant impact to their own community helping to broaden participation in STEM. The results of this study and the associated methods developed are largely applicable to other areas in the U.S. where extreme wet events like flooding or extended rain may mobilize pollutants to water supplies such as groundwater.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/27/2023<br>      Modified by: Dorina&nbsp;Murgulet</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2043344/2043344_10708283_1674831286778_Leadandzincpollution--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2043344/2043344_10708283_1674831286778_Leadandzincpollution--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Lead and zinc groundwater concentrations post hurricane flooding, dry weather, and during extreme wet conditions."><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2043344/2043344_10708283_1674831286778_Leadandzincpollution--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Lead and zinc groundwater concentrations post hurricane flooding, dry weather, and during extreme wet conditions."></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Lead (Pb, top) Zinc (Zn+2, bottom) and variability in a deeper sandy aquifer in the south Texas unincorporated community following Hurricane Hanna flooding (blue shaded) and the 2021 summer monsoon (green shaded). The yellow region indicates dry conditions.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Christopher Vickers</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Dorina&nbsp;Murgulet</div> <div class="imageTitle">Lead and zinc groundwater concentrations post hurricane flooding, dry weather, and during extreme wet conditions.</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2043344/2043344_10708283_1674706031592_PEN--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2043344/2043344_10708283_1674706031592_PEN--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Sampled wells"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2043344/2043344_10708283_1674706031592_PEN--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Sampled wells"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Well in the Rio Grande Valley sampled for the project.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Christopher Vickers</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Dorina&nbsp;Murgulet</div> <div class="imageTitle">Sampled wells</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2043344/2043344_10708283_1674706264407_DSCN6605--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2043344/2043344_10708283_1674706264407_DSCN6605--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Measuring pesticides"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2043344/2043344_10708283_1674706264407_DSCN6605--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Measuring pesticides"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">MS Jessie  Matarrita is measuring pesticides using high resolution mass spectrometry.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jessie Matarrita</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Dorina&nbsp;Murgulet</div> <div class="imageTitle">Measuring pesticides</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2043344/2043344_10708283_1674705892160_thumbnail_IMG_0057--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2043344/2043344_10708283_1674705892160_thumbnail_IMG_0057--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Sampled wells"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2043344/2043344_10708283_1674705892160_thumbnail_IMG_0057--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Sampled wells"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Well in the Rio Grande Valley sampled for the project. Note that the well is not properly capped which allows flood waters or spills to migrate downhole into the aquifer.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Christopher Vickers</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Dorina&nbsp;Murgulet</div> <div class="imageTitle">Sampled wells</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2043344/2043344_10708283_1674706556093_Picture1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2043344/2043344_10708283_1674706556093_Picture1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Sampled flood water"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2043344/2043344_10708283_1674706556093_Picture1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Sampled flood water"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The picture depicts an agricultural field that was flooded following Hurricane Hanna in early August 2020</div> <div class="imageCredit">Christopher Vickers</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Dorina&nbsp;Murgulet</div> <div class="imageTitle">Sampled flood water</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Large storms play an important role in moving waste and toxins in water and can cause water to become unsafe to drink through both heavy rains and from ocean waters pushed onto land. Flood waters also enter areas under the ground that store water (aquifers).  This project tested above ground and below ground water from places in South Texas flooded during Hurricane Hanna and the impacts of subsequent weather conditions like drought or extreme wet seasons.   Flooding and storm surges amplify the hazards of industrial sites and other above- and below-ground pollutants to nearby residents who consume water from local underground water (or groundwater) sources, presenting a high health risk to humans. This project monitored the chemistry of runoff and river/lake waters and groundwater in a rural area in the Rio Grande Valley (RGV) and another area near Baffin Bay in Texas where Hurricane Hanna brought flooding from downpours and storm surge, respectively. The research carried out quick-response observation of above-  and below-ground  water contamination in coastal areas.  Hurricane Hanna made landfall in July 2020, impacting south Texas with storm surges reaching over 1.2m in Baffin Bay and floodwaters in the RGV over 1m deep. The project intensively measured the mobilization and persistence of fecal indicator bacteria, microbial pathogens, insecticides, nitrates, zinc, and lead, in flood waters and groundwater. Sample collection began days after Hurricane Hanna’s landfall and continued until August 2021. Samples were collected biweekly for two months after landfall, monthly for the following three months, and bimonthly for the remainder of the project. Approximately 240 water samples were collected throughout the project.  Nutrient (i.e., nitrate, or dissolved inorganic nitrogen) levels in groundwater were found to fluctuate based on both hydroclimate season and time of year. Dissolved inorganic nitrogen and phosphate were highest during the extended summer storms in 2021, lasting weeks/months, which coincided with the planting season when substantial amounts of fertilizer are typically used. Most of the samples collected throughout the project had varying amounts of total coliform present in both surface- and groundwater, with the highest concentration in surface water. Escherichia coli, a fecal coliform, was below detection limits regardless of the season in most groundwater samples. However, following Hanna a noticeable E.coli level was measured at one location in RGV, indicating direct contamination of the aquifer from flooding via water well conduits.  Lead and zinc were present in groundwater, particularly at RGV, where concentrations significantly increased during the extended wet season in 2021. The quick response of the aquifer to hydroclimatic changes was also revealed by analyzing the stable isotopes of oxygen (&delta;18O) and hydrogen (&delta;D) present during the recharge process. Both surface- and groundwater were most depleted in the isotopes immediately after Hurricane Hanna with significant enrichment observed beginning approximately one month after the hurricane's landfall.  As part of this study, surface water and groundwater samples were measured for pesticide contents. This is one of the most extensive studies that has screened and quantified over 200 pesticides in a single sample in the United States. The results of eight monitoring sampling campaigns revealed the occurrence of 21 pesticides with minimum instrumental limit of detection (LOD) of 0.05 ng/mL and limit of quantification (LOQ) of 0.10 ng/mL. Six herbicides were the most detected compounds, followed by insecticides (5), fungicides (4),  transformation products of the original pesticides  (3), and a plant growth regulator (1). The most frequently detected compounds were atrazine, clothianidin, cycluron, DEA, dinotefuran, and norflurazon and those with the highest concentrations were clothianidin (211 ng/L), DEET (13,885 ng/L), and norflurazon (952 ng/L).).In general, more compounds were detected in groundwater than in surface water, except for atrazine and DEA which were found at higher frequencies in surface water.  Pesticides with high leaching potential are more likely to be transported in groundwater beyond application area. In this study, clothianidin and norflurazon with high leaching potential showed significant concentrations in groundwater.  The data generated through this project provide means for mitigation and prevention efforts designed to explicitly address groundwater contamination. South Texas and communities like the colonias in RGV represent significant Hispanic populations, meaning this engagement supports underserved communities. Results are being disseminated to the communities included in the study. Funds provided from this grant enabled two underrepresented students to be trained in research of significant impact to their own community helping to broaden participation in STEM. The results of this study and the associated methods developed are largely applicable to other areas in the U.S. where extreme wet events like flooding or extended rain may mobilize pollutants to water supplies such as groundwater.          Last Modified: 01/27/2023       Submitted by: Dorina Murgulet]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
