<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SCC-CIVIC-PG Track A: City of Bridges:  Using New Transportation Options to Drive Low-Income Mothers to Greater Success in Pittsburgh]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>49899.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>49899</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>David Corman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dcorman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928754</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Low-income residents of American cities tend to live far from the districts where job creation is concentrated, and therefore incur high transportation costs (in terms of time and money) when seeking employment outside their neighborhoods.  These high transportation costs depress income, limit employment, and lower socioeconomic mobility.  This is known as the spatial mismatch problem, and it is likely to pose even bigger challenges for low-income mothers with young children, given their parental responsibilities.  While this problem has existed for decades, the recent and widespread diffusion of smartphones has enabled a proliferation of new transportation options that offer some of the flexibility of personal vehicles without the high fixed cost of vehicle ownership.  Could these new transportation options significantly expand the geographic and socioeconomic mobility of low-income mothers? If so, how?  To explore these possibilities, this project proposes a set of field experiments which provide low-cost access to these transportation options for a treatment group and compare the mobility and socioeconomic outcomes to a control group.  The experiments can use the GPS capabilities embedded in modern smartphones to measure the quantity and nature of increased geographic mobility thereby conferred on low-income mothers in the treatment groups.  Through innovative partnerships with local government agencies, this project will measure the impact of increased geographic mobility on socioeconomic mobility in the short-run and the long-run. Through partnerships with a diverse set of regional nonprofits, this project will directly involve low-income mothers in our research design.  The results of the research will provide immediate guidance for policymakers seeking to fund practical policy and engineering solutions to the spatial mismatch problem. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Given the rapid diffusion of these transportation options across the country and around the world, policy lessons derived from our study could be implemented in hundreds of cities, potentially impacting the lives of millions.  The research will also support fundamental breakthroughs in the modeling of regional transportation systems.  Transportation researchers currently have limited visibility into how new transportation options are impacting multi-modal transit choices within regional transportation systems.  By leveraging the detailed data collected through our proposed research, this project will create new methods for modeling these regional transportation systems.  The new models will reflect the growing interaction between conventional mass transit and a range of complementary new (and old) transit technologies.  The knowledge gained from these models could further expand mass transit ridership and resident mobility, while also promoting environmental sustainability. This project is supported by the CIVIC Innovation Challenge program Track A. Communities and Mobility: Offering Better Mobility Options to Solve the Spatial Mismatch Between Housing Affordability and Jobs through a collaboration between NSF and the Department of Energy Vehicle Transportation Office.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/11/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/20/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2043634</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Karen</FirstName>
<LastName>Lightman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Karen H Lightman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[kh3m@andrew.cmu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000826336</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/11/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lowell</FirstName>
<LastName>Taylor</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lowell Taylor</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[lt20@andrew.cmu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000318265</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/11/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Beibei</FirstName>
<LastName>Li</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Beibei Li</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[beibeili@andrew.cmu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000629402</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/11/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sean</FirstName>
<LastName>Qian</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>Z</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sean Z Qian</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[seanqian@cmu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000650438</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/11/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lee</FirstName>
<LastName>Branstetter</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>G</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lee G Branstetter</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[branstet@cmu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000342657</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/11/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Carnegie-Mellon University</Name>
<CityName>PITTSBURGH</CityName>
<ZipCode>152133815</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4122688746</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5000 FORBES AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>U3NKNFLNQ613</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CARNEGIE MELLON UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>U3NKNFLNQ613</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Carnegie-Mellon University]]></Name>
<CityName>Pittsburgh</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>152133890</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>033Y</Code>
<Text>S&amp;CC: Smart &amp; Connected Commun</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>042Z</Code>
<Text>S&amp;CC: Smart and Connected Communities</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~49899</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>City of Bridges:&nbsp;&nbsp;Using New Transportation Options to Drive Low-Income Mothers to Greater Success in Pittsburgh&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Summary:&nbsp;&nbsp;</strong></p> <p>Low-income residents of American cities tend to live far from the districts where job creation is concentrated and therefore incur high transportation costs when seeking employment outside their neighborhoods.&nbsp;&nbsp;These transportation barriers are likely to pose especially significant challenges for low-income mothers with children, given their childcare responsibilities.&nbsp;&nbsp;Could new smartphone-enabled transportation options significantly expand the geographic &ndash; and socioeconomic&mdash; mobility of low-income mothers?&nbsp;&nbsp;To explore these possibilities, we proposed a set of field experiments in which we would reduce&nbsp;the costs of these transportation options for a treatment group and compare the mobility and socioeconomic outcomes to a control group. This was the basis of our proposal for NSF CIVIC Innovation Challenge (CIVID) which was ultimately not funded at the second stage.&nbsp;</p> <p>As a part of CIVIC, we participated in nine MetroLab Network and NSF Planning, Partnership, and Scoping Workshops. We developed methodologies to use the GPS capabilities embedded in modern smartphones to measure the quantity and nature of increased geographic mobility thereby conferred on low-income mothers in our treatment groups. We strengthened our collaboration with the region&rsquo;s planning commission to help broaden the impact of the proposed pilot. We conducted surveys and user-centered focus group meetings with low-income mothers, in which these mothers provided feedback to co-create our research plans by sharing their perspectives on which transportation modes best meet their needs. Finally, through innovative consultations with local government agencies, we planned a strategy to monitor the impact of increased geographic mobility on socioeconomic mobility in the short-run and the long-run.</p> <p><strong>Intellectual Merit:</strong></p> <p>The scientific literature on the spatial mismatch problem has suffered from a lack of credible experimental evidence that directly establishes the connection between transportation costs, geographic mobility, and socioeconomic mobility. Our plan focused specifically on mothers with children at home, who do not have regular access to a car, because this group may be particularly sensitive to a reduced cost of transportation. In our proposed experiments, the reduction in transportation cost will be implemented through subsidized access to an array of innovative transportation options that have high potential policy relevance.&nbsp;&nbsp;Our research design would allow us to measure the impact of this reduction on geographic&nbsp;<em>and</em>&nbsp;socioeconomic mobility.&nbsp;&nbsp;In our planning period, we&nbsp;created a robust smartphone application that low-income mothers will use to enable mobility tracking and an IT infrastructure for the transmission of monthly surveys. We also created algorithms for inferring mobility shifts using noisy GPS data transmitted by older smartphones. If and when it is funded at the requested level, this&nbsp;research could further expand resident geographic and socioeconomic mobility.&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Broader&nbsp;</strong><strong>Impacts:</strong></p> <p>With planning grant support, we developed a portfolio of smartphone-enabled transportation options which could provide new opportunities to citizens who are being left behind economically. By using these new transportation technologies to enhance the mobility of some of Pittsburgh's poorest citizens,&nbsp;we believed we could bring a new solution to the longstanding problem of spatial mismatch,&nbsp;help these citizens connect to better jobs, training, and social services, and dramatically improve the&nbsp;quality ofthe&nbsp;lives of their families.&nbsp;&nbsp;Given the&nbsp;rapid diffusion of these transportation options across the country and around the world, policy lessons derived from a fully funded study along the lines we proposed could be&nbsp;implemented in hundreds of cities&nbsp;potentially impacting the lives of millions.&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Continued Application:</strong></p> <p class="paragraph">Starting in July 2021, the team applied our spatial mismatch research to support the Pittsburgh &ldquo;Guaranteed Basic Mobility&rdquo; (GBM) pilot, which will provide up to 100 low-income residents of the Manchester neighborhood with monthly transit subscriptions and shared mobility services to address mobility insecurity.&nbsp; In addition to improving transportation flexibility and resiliency for the general public, the GBM pilot demonstration will specifically test if reliable access to transit and a range of shared mobility options improves employment and health outcomes for low-income workers and their households.&nbsp;The City of Bridges team will research the impacts of the GBM pilot. Additional funding will enable CMU researchers to evaluate the demonstration to potentially serve as a national model.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/28/2022<br>      Modified by: Lee&nbsp;G&nbsp;Branstetter</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ City of Bridges:  Using New Transportation Options to Drive Low-Income Mothers to Greater Success in Pittsburgh                                                                                                                   Summary:    Low-income residents of American cities tend to live far from the districts where job creation is concentrated and therefore incur high transportation costs when seeking employment outside their neighborhoods.  These transportation barriers are likely to pose especially significant challenges for low-income mothers with children, given their childcare responsibilities.  Could new smartphone-enabled transportation options significantly expand the geographic &ndash; and socioeconomic&mdash; mobility of low-income mothers?  To explore these possibilities, we proposed a set of field experiments in which we would reduce the costs of these transportation options for a treatment group and compare the mobility and socioeconomic outcomes to a control group. This was the basis of our proposal for NSF CIVIC Innovation Challenge (CIVID) which was ultimately not funded at the second stage.   As a part of CIVIC, we participated in nine MetroLab Network and NSF Planning, Partnership, and Scoping Workshops. We developed methodologies to use the GPS capabilities embedded in modern smartphones to measure the quantity and nature of increased geographic mobility thereby conferred on low-income mothers in our treatment groups. We strengthened our collaboration with the region’s planning commission to help broaden the impact of the proposed pilot. We conducted surveys and user-centered focus group meetings with low-income mothers, in which these mothers provided feedback to co-create our research plans by sharing their perspectives on which transportation modes best meet their needs. Finally, through innovative consultations with local government agencies, we planned a strategy to monitor the impact of increased geographic mobility on socioeconomic mobility in the short-run and the long-run.  Intellectual Merit:  The scientific literature on the spatial mismatch problem has suffered from a lack of credible experimental evidence that directly establishes the connection between transportation costs, geographic mobility, and socioeconomic mobility. Our plan focused specifically on mothers with children at home, who do not have regular access to a car, because this group may be particularly sensitive to a reduced cost of transportation. In our proposed experiments, the reduction in transportation cost will be implemented through subsidized access to an array of innovative transportation options that have high potential policy relevance.  Our research design would allow us to measure the impact of this reduction on geographic and socioeconomic mobility.  In our planning period, we created a robust smartphone application that low-income mothers will use to enable mobility tracking and an IT infrastructure for the transmission of monthly surveys. We also created algorithms for inferring mobility shifts using noisy GPS data transmitted by older smartphones. If and when it is funded at the requested level, this research could further expand resident geographic and socioeconomic mobility.   Broader Impacts:  With planning grant support, we developed a portfolio of smartphone-enabled transportation options which could provide new opportunities to citizens who are being left behind economically. By using these new transportation technologies to enhance the mobility of some of Pittsburgh's poorest citizens, we believed we could bring a new solution to the longstanding problem of spatial mismatch, help these citizens connect to better jobs, training, and social services, and dramatically improve the quality ofthe lives of their families.  Given the rapid diffusion of these transportation options across the country and around the world, policy lessons derived from a fully funded study along the lines we proposed could be implemented in hundreds of cities potentially impacting the lives of millions.   Continued Application: Starting in July 2021, the team applied our spatial mismatch research to support the Pittsburgh "Guaranteed Basic Mobility" (GBM) pilot, which will provide up to 100 low-income residents of the Manchester neighborhood with monthly transit subscriptions and shared mobility services to address mobility insecurity.  In addition to improving transportation flexibility and resiliency for the general public, the GBM pilot demonstration will specifically test if reliable access to transit and a range of shared mobility options improves employment and health outcomes for low-income workers and their households. The City of Bridges team will research the impacts of the GBM pilot. Additional funding will enable CMU researchers to evaluate the demonstration to potentially serve as a national model.                Last Modified: 04/28/2022       Submitted by: Lee G Branstetter]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
