<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SCC-CIVIC-PG Track B: Digital Backpack: Enabling Offline Web-based Content Access to Promote Student Academic Resiliency in Acute and Chronic Disaster Situations]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/15/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>49436.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>49436</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sandip Roy</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The lack of home Internet availability is extremely problematic when schools shift to remote learning as part of community disaster response plans. Some of the most severe “homework gaps” are experienced by students living in tribal communities, where households often lack reliable broadband connectivity and students experience the highest dropout rates in the nation. It is in this context that this project proposes Digital Backpack (DigiPack), an opportunistic content delivery network and mobile app that proactively uploads, downloads, and stores digital learning material to devices whenever they obtain an Internet connection. DigiPack will enable students’ mobile devices to automatically fetch and store digital education content that they can work on offline at home. Content generated and tagged for upload while working offline at home is automatically transferred when Internet connectivity is encountered.  This allows students to make the most of trips to hotspots and allows for more casual interaction with online learning; rather than having to remember a list of all the content that needs to be downloaded, uploaded, and interacted with whenever they are at a hot spot, students can focus on engaging in interactive learning activities (e.g., video calls with a teacher) when connectivity is available and DigiPack automatically handles content that can be engaged with asynchronously. We will partner with STAR School, a public preK-8 charter school located in the southwestern corner of Navajo Nation in Leupp, AZ, to plan and pilot the DigiPack system in Navajo Nation. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project's vision for research and civic engagement activities focuses on understanding the specific educational content needs of Navajo students and educators in Leupp, AZ. This research will (i) identify the specific educational information needs that DigiPack must support in the Leupp community; (ii) discern where DigiPack CDN nodes and access points should be placed in Leupp for optimal benefit to students and their families; and (iii) co-design the DigiPack mobile app user interface and back end service support to ensure that a deployment is effective and usable.  To this end, the project team will work with a community advisory board (CAB) comprised of Leupp families, educators and ISP operators to guide the design choices for DigiPack interfaces and services such that they best serve the learning needs of the community. This project's approach will integrate best practices from participatory action research, including asset-based community development and Lean UX design to work with community members as co-researchers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/12/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/20/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2043526</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Morgan</FirstName>
<LastName>Vigil-Hayes</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Morgan Vigil-Hayes</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[morgan.vigil-hayes@nau.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000745028</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/12/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Northern Arizona University</Name>
<CityName>FLAGSTAFF</CityName>
<ZipCode>86011</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9285230886</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>601 S KNOLES DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[ROOM 220]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AZ02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>MXHAS3AKPRN1</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORTHERN ARIZONA UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Northern Arizona University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>860010001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AZ02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>033Y</Code>
<Text>S&amp;CC: Smart &amp; Connected Commun</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>042Z</Code>
<Text>S&amp;CC: Smart and Connected Communities</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~49436</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Currently, students without home Internet rely on public hotspots (at libraries or restaurants) and will sit for hours in parking lots completing homework assignments. Students in tribal communities are disproportionately affected as an estimated 50-70% of tribal homes with school-aged children lack Internet access. To address the homework and learning gap in one of the most severely impacted communities, we partnered with STAR School, a charter school serving students from the Navajo Nation, to propose the design of Digital Backpack (DigiPack), a community-based opportunistic content delivery network (CDN) and mobile app. DigiPack is unique in its ability to help communities with limited Internet infrastructure through proactive delivery of Internet content during opportunistic connectivity.</p> <p>For the planning grant, our research objectives were to: (i) identify the specific educational information needs that DigiPack must support; (ii) discern where CDN nodes and access points should be placed in Leupp for optimal benefit to students and their families; and (iii) co-design the DigiPack mobile app user interface and back end service support to ensure that a deployment is effective and usable.</p> <p>For the first objective, we interviwed five teachers and five parents and found that all stakeholders identified language aquistion learning to be the most necessary type of content to support. Specifically, there was a strong desire to support interactive Navajo and English language learning through multimedia storytelling. To this end, we focused designing DigiPack to support asynchronous, interactive multimedia learning content that could be accessed online and offline.</p> <p>For the second objective, met with stakeholders and found that due to complex jursidictional boundaries, the sparsity of home sites, and the overwhelming need (most students did not have reliable Internet access at home), deploying physical layer infrastructure equitably as part of a 1 year, 1M innovation pilot was infeasible. Instead, we pivoted our focus to the development of software and application-level solutions for developing DigiPack, with the only technical infrastructure requirement being a DigiPack server hosted at the school site. We anticipate that by designing for this model, DigiPack can most flexibly and robustly serve a wide range of rural and tribal communities that face severe digital inqeuities with respect to Internet connectivity.&nbsp;</p> <p>For the third objective, we iteratively designed DigiPack with stakeholder focus groups, focusing on integrating features such as assignment management, asyncrhonous search, and asynchronous student-teacher feedback. We ultimately developed a prototype ready for piloting, which we host as an open source software project on GitHub: <a title="DigiPack Code Repository" href="https://github.com/CANIS-NAU/digiLearn" target="_blank">https://github.com/CANIS-NAU/digiLearn</a></p> <p>We envision that the outcomes of this project will be broadly impactful as we continue to identify partners (including schools and libraries) who are interested in offering educational, interactive, and multimedia web content that can be engaged with even when Internet access is unreliable.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/16/2021<br>      Modified by: Morgan&nbsp;Vigil-Hayes</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Currently, students without home Internet rely on public hotspots (at libraries or restaurants) and will sit for hours in parking lots completing homework assignments. Students in tribal communities are disproportionately affected as an estimated 50-70% of tribal homes with school-aged children lack Internet access. To address the homework and learning gap in one of the most severely impacted communities, we partnered with STAR School, a charter school serving students from the Navajo Nation, to propose the design of Digital Backpack (DigiPack), a community-based opportunistic content delivery network (CDN) and mobile app. DigiPack is unique in its ability to help communities with limited Internet infrastructure through proactive delivery of Internet content during opportunistic connectivity.  For the planning grant, our research objectives were to: (i) identify the specific educational information needs that DigiPack must support; (ii) discern where CDN nodes and access points should be placed in Leupp for optimal benefit to students and their families; and (iii) co-design the DigiPack mobile app user interface and back end service support to ensure that a deployment is effective and usable.  For the first objective, we interviwed five teachers and five parents and found that all stakeholders identified language aquistion learning to be the most necessary type of content to support. Specifically, there was a strong desire to support interactive Navajo and English language learning through multimedia storytelling. To this end, we focused designing DigiPack to support asynchronous, interactive multimedia learning content that could be accessed online and offline.  For the second objective, met with stakeholders and found that due to complex jursidictional boundaries, the sparsity of home sites, and the overwhelming need (most students did not have reliable Internet access at home), deploying physical layer infrastructure equitably as part of a 1 year, 1M innovation pilot was infeasible. Instead, we pivoted our focus to the development of software and application-level solutions for developing DigiPack, with the only technical infrastructure requirement being a DigiPack server hosted at the school site. We anticipate that by designing for this model, DigiPack can most flexibly and robustly serve a wide range of rural and tribal communities that face severe digital inqeuities with respect to Internet connectivity.   For the third objective, we iteratively designed DigiPack with stakeholder focus groups, focusing on integrating features such as assignment management, asyncrhonous search, and asynchronous student-teacher feedback. We ultimately developed a prototype ready for piloting, which we host as an open source software project on GitHub: https://github.com/CANIS-NAU/digiLearn  We envision that the outcomes of this project will be broadly impactful as we continue to identify partners (including schools and libraries) who are interested in offering educational, interactive, and multimedia web content that can be engaged with even when Internet access is unreliable.       Last Modified: 12/16/2021       Submitted by: Morgan Vigil-Hayes]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
