<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[I-Corps: Biodegradable plastics that incorporate plastic degrading enzymes]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ruth Shuman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rshuman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922160</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this I-Corps project is to make environmentally friendly plastics. Compostable plastics, one of the fastest growing innovations in the space, promises to enable a circular materials economy. Unfortunately, there is currently poor access to industrial compost nationally, and building infrastructure is costly. Our technology streamlines this degradation process, requiring only water and heat, to produce small molecules than can be readily composted, or turned back into high quality plastics. The global plastic market is $234 B, and successful commercialization could positively impact environmental sustainability while meeting the needs of industry to maintain modern quality of life. The technology can potentially be used for solutions across a breadth of applications, ranging from industrial chemistry to energy generation to biotechnology.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project supports efforts toward translation of a class of materials called random heteropolymers (RHPs). RHPs effectively stabilize enzymes in foreign environments, such as organic solvents or within plastics. Enzymes are nature’s chemists, performing chemical transformations with unparalleled efficiency and specificity within cells. However, enzymes are typically fragile and perform poorly, if at all, once removed from the cell. The proposed RHP technology enables enzymes to be covered in a nano-scale shell that shields them from the environment without harming their function. RHPs can be used to embed the enzymes that degrade plastic materials inside of the plastics. Upon triggering, the plastics biodegrade rapidly and completely, leaving behind no microplastics. The monomers can be recaptured and reused to make new plastics or disposed of as compost. The materials can also be processed using current manufacturing techniques. Altogether, this provides an opportunity to produce materials that meet the needs of industry while providing a better end of life with minimal investment in infrastructure. More broadly, RHPs offer the functionality of natural or engineered enzymes with the utility of plastics as a novel approach.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/18/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/20/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2043075</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ting</FirstName>
<LastName>Xu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ting Xu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[tingxu@berkeley.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000104902</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/18/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Berkeley</Name>
<CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
<ZipCode>947101749</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5106433891</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1608 4TH ST STE 201</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>GS3YEVSS12N6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>NUDGYLBB4S99</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Berkeley]]></Name>
<CityName>Berkeley</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>947201760</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[381 Hearst Memorial Mining Build]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9223</Code>
<Text>ENVIRON BENIGN CHEMICAL SYNTH &amp; PROCESS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>Plastic waste is a problem of global significance. Over 6.3B Metric Tonnes of plastic have ended up as waste within our land, ocean, and bodies. This enormous mass of material is a testament to the popularity and practical utility of plastics, and the difficulty society faces in adequately addressing the poor end-of-life prospects for plastics. While biodegradable plastics promise a more favorable end-of-life, significant progress, from both the material and infrastructure sides, is needed to ensure that they actually break down within reasonable timeframes and in accessible conditions. Further, this degradation potential must not prohibit the functional performance necessary for their adoption. Our technical solution, the embedding of stabilized enzymes within the plastics themselves, enables triggered self-degradation in mild conditions without compromising material performance or material properties. Through this I-Corps grant, we undertook a methodical and in-depth assessment of the plastics manufacturing and use landscape to ascertain the potential for this technical solution to provide value in the marketplace.</span><span>&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Through 150+ interviews with various players across the eco-system, we developed a clear understanding of the value provided by the technology, cultivated a vast network of connections within the industry (from raw material suppliers through to end-of-life waste management), identified opportunities for further technical development and optimization, and a qualitative and quantitative justification for the development of market suitable products. Using the business model canvas tool, along with the Lean Startup methodology taught in the coursework, the team developed a clear understanding of how product, ideas, and capital must flow to yield value for all associated parties, and ultimately impact for the environment and planet. Value propositions for the technology were refined to appeal to key decision makers within the plastics manufacturing and consumer products goods industries. The team was also enabled to attend trade shows and carry out site visits with potential partners and customers within the industry. This in-person interaction was immensely valuable in educating the team about the needs, limitations, and potential for working at industrial scales, which is many orders of magnitude larger in scale than what is typically done in research lab settings. This has culminated in the full-time pursuit of this commercialization effort by the team&rsquo;s entrepreneurial lead, Aaron Hall, with the start-up he founded, Intropic Materials. Hall received the prestigious 2021 Activate Cyclotron Road Fellowship to continue this development, and has since raised funding, expanded their team, built up lab-capabilities, and is on-track to bring product to the market.</span></p> <p><span>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;In addition to the aforementioned factual and technical understandings of the market gathered, the team developed and fostered their understanding of business, interpersonal communication and ethnographic interviewing. These skills provide a significant departure from tradition STEM educational training, and enable a new perspective to the traditional basic research efforts as well as support business development for Intropic Materials. Also of note is the fact that the resources and training provided in this grant supported a team comprised of historically underrepresented individuals within STEM and Entrepreneurship to pursue the commercialization potential of novel technology. This is in alignment with NSF&rsquo;s Broader Impacts and Diversity, Equity, Inclusion, and Belonging initiatives, and is an important contribution toward building a more equitable and sustainable society.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/10/2023<br>      Modified by: Ting&nbsp;Xu</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Plastic waste is a problem of global significance. Over 6.3B Metric Tonnes of plastic have ended up as waste within our land, ocean, and bodies. This enormous mass of material is a testament to the popularity and practical utility of plastics, and the difficulty society faces in adequately addressing the poor end-of-life prospects for plastics. While biodegradable plastics promise a more favorable end-of-life, significant progress, from both the material and infrastructure sides, is needed to ensure that they actually break down within reasonable timeframes and in accessible conditions. Further, this degradation potential must not prohibit the functional performance necessary for their adoption. Our technical solution, the embedding of stabilized enzymes within the plastics themselves, enables triggered self-degradation in mild conditions without compromising material performance or material properties. Through this I-Corps grant, we undertook a methodical and in-depth assessment of the plastics manufacturing and use landscape to ascertain the potential for this technical solution to provide value in the marketplace.                Through 150+ interviews with various players across the eco-system, we developed a clear understanding of the value provided by the technology, cultivated a vast network of connections within the industry (from raw material suppliers through to end-of-life waste management), identified opportunities for further technical development and optimization, and a qualitative and quantitative justification for the development of market suitable products. Using the business model canvas tool, along with the Lean Startup methodology taught in the coursework, the team developed a clear understanding of how product, ideas, and capital must flow to yield value for all associated parties, and ultimately impact for the environment and planet. Value propositions for the technology were refined to appeal to key decision makers within the plastics manufacturing and consumer products goods industries. The team was also enabled to attend trade shows and carry out site visits with potential partners and customers within the industry. This in-person interaction was immensely valuable in educating the team about the needs, limitations, and potential for working at industrial scales, which is many orders of magnitude larger in scale than what is typically done in research lab settings. This has culminated in the full-time pursuit of this commercialization effort by the team’s entrepreneurial lead, Aaron Hall, with the start-up he founded, Intropic Materials. Hall received the prestigious 2021 Activate Cyclotron Road Fellowship to continue this development, and has since raised funding, expanded their team, built up lab-capabilities, and is on-track to bring product to the market.              In addition to the aforementioned factual and technical understandings of the market gathered, the team developed and fostered their understanding of business, interpersonal communication and ethnographic interviewing. These skills provide a significant departure from tradition STEM educational training, and enable a new perspective to the traditional basic research efforts as well as support business development for Intropic Materials. Also of note is the fact that the resources and training provided in this grant supported a team comprised of historically underrepresented individuals within STEM and Entrepreneurship to pursue the commercialization potential of novel technology. This is in alignment with NSF’s Broader Impacts and Diversity, Equity, Inclusion, and Belonging initiatives, and is an important contribution toward building a more equitable and sustainable society.          Last Modified: 02/10/2023       Submitted by: Ting Xu]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
