<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research: The Future of Innovative Learning Environments in STEM Education]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>10113.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>10113</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Alexandra Medina-Borja</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>amedinab@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927557</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[To advance the use of novel technologies to increase student learning outcomes, educational technology must be coupled with a deep understanding of how students learn and retain information. Thus, technology and the learning environment must work together to enable pedagogical approaches that promote student-centered learning. To set a research agenda for the technology-enhanced learning environment of the future, this collaborative project will conduct a series of events that explore the Future of Innovative Learning Environments.  These events will include a series of interactive, online discussions followed by an in-person workshop. Workshop participants will include twenty-nine expert participants from academia, industry, and nonprofits.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project aims to inform the future of learning environments in STEM higher education.  The project will consider the near-term and longer-term impacts, opportunities, challenges, and future research initiatives related to the development and implementation of innovative learning environments. This project will include three components: 1) Interactive, online discussions (microlabs) prior to the workshop will introduce participants to different innovative learning environments and solicit feedback from a range of stakeholders;  2) Participants at a two-day in-person workshop will engage in creative activities that help them envision how innovative learning environments might transform STEM higher education; and 3) the PIs and invited participants will synthesize the discussions and produce a report that can guide future.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/03/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/03/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2043855</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kurt</FirstName>
<LastName>Winkelmann</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kurt J Winkelmann</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[kwinkelmann@valdosta.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000246146</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/03/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Valdosta State University</Name>
<CityName>VALDOSTA</CityName>
<ZipCode>316980100</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2293337837</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1500 N PATTERSON ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>UHCVCJL7RWV3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>VALDOSTA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Valdosta State University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>316980001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1998</Code>
<Text>IUSE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8045</Code>
<Text>Cyberlearn &amp; Future Learn Tech</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0419</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04001920DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~10113</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The eXploring the Future of Innovative Learning Environments (X-FILEs) project team organized a variety of student- and faculty-focused events to learn how they can better use technology in STEM higher education. The first and largest event was a workshop held in 2018 for 30 faculty and education researchers to envision how technology-enhanced learning environments could transform STEM higher education within the next seven years (2019-2026). Stakeholders such as university administrators, technology developers, and students were also represented in the workshop. Workshop participants discussed and explored four main technology categories as they relate to STEM teaching and learning: personalized and adaptive learning, multimodal learning, cross reality (XR), and artificial intelligence/machine learning (AI/ML). In order to frame the examination of where and how these technologies may impact students? learning experience, participants addressed opportunities for gains, challenges/barriers, implementation strategies, and future research questions related to each. In each case, they examined the impact on the various aspects of teaching and learning: Presentation and Instruction, Interactions and Communications, and Evaluation and Assessment Techniques.</p> <p>Participants synthesized the ideas, questions, challenges, and solutions proposed during the workshop into a scholarly book, <em>Innovative Learning Environments in STEM Higher Education</em>, published by Springer in 2021. Examples of education research discussed at the workshop appear in a special issue of special issue of the journal <em>Interactive Learning Environments</em> titled ?Cross Reality (XR) and Immersive Learning Environments (ILE) in Education,? published in 2020 and co-edited by several workshop organizers.</p> <p>The next phase of this project was to understand the perspective of students regarding their use of technology in STEM classes. The project team hosted a one-day Student Jam event in February 2020 and another in April 2021. Working in teams, college students majoring in STEM disciplines created solutions to improve or enhance college-level STEM education using various technologies. The second Student Jam, occurring towards the end of social distancing and masking requirements, focused more on post-pandemic STEM education. Keeping with connective themes of the original 2018 X-FILEs Workshop, the same four technology categories and aspects of teaching and learning were incorporated into the Jam. Each team?s ideation process was captured and transcribed. A summary of the first Student Jam is included in the X-FILEs workshop book mentioned earlier.</p> <p>The COVID-19 pandemic occurred soon after the first Student Jam. The ensuing social distancing and masking requirements caused college faculty to quickly change the way they teach traditionally hands-on STEM activities (e.g., lab experiments) to online instructional settings. How faculty and students use mundane technologies like video conferencing apps and their access to technologies like wifi became critical to students? education. In fall 2021, the research team decided to pivot to explore this issue, rather than focus on more cutting-edge technologies such as artificial intelligence and cross reality.</p> <p>&nbsp;The research team held online discussions in fall 2021 with faculty who, in spring 202, had little to no prior experience with remote/online teaching or using extensive educational technology in their classrooms. Participants shared the challenges that they faced while others presented unexpected advantages of using technologies related to online education. They also conveyed how their experiences shape their attitudes towards future use of technology in STEM education. These findings about teaching and learning during the pandemic are consistent with themes that are emerging in the education research literature. The project team continues to study this.</p> <p>In spring 2022, the research team conducted a series of focus groups with college STEM majors who had experienced STEM courses before the COVID-19 pandemic, during the pandemic?s disruption, and after students returned to face-to-face classes. The research team is analyzing the focus groups? transcripts now.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/25/2022<br>      Modified by: Kurt&nbsp;J&nbsp;Winkelmann</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The eXploring the Future of Innovative Learning Environments (X-FILEs) project team organized a variety of student- and faculty-focused events to learn how they can better use technology in STEM higher education. The first and largest event was a workshop held in 2018 for 30 faculty and education researchers to envision how technology-enhanced learning environments could transform STEM higher education within the next seven years (2019-2026). Stakeholders such as university administrators, technology developers, and students were also represented in the workshop. Workshop participants discussed and explored four main technology categories as they relate to STEM teaching and learning: personalized and adaptive learning, multimodal learning, cross reality (XR), and artificial intelligence/machine learning (AI/ML). In order to frame the examination of where and how these technologies may impact students? learning experience, participants addressed opportunities for gains, challenges/barriers, implementation strategies, and future research questions related to each. In each case, they examined the impact on the various aspects of teaching and learning: Presentation and Instruction, Interactions and Communications, and Evaluation and Assessment Techniques.  Participants synthesized the ideas, questions, challenges, and solutions proposed during the workshop into a scholarly book, Innovative Learning Environments in STEM Higher Education, published by Springer in 2021. Examples of education research discussed at the workshop appear in a special issue of special issue of the journal Interactive Learning Environments titled ?Cross Reality (XR) and Immersive Learning Environments (ILE) in Education,? published in 2020 and co-edited by several workshop organizers.  The next phase of this project was to understand the perspective of students regarding their use of technology in STEM classes. The project team hosted a one-day Student Jam event in February 2020 and another in April 2021. Working in teams, college students majoring in STEM disciplines created solutions to improve or enhance college-level STEM education using various technologies. The second Student Jam, occurring towards the end of social distancing and masking requirements, focused more on post-pandemic STEM education. Keeping with connective themes of the original 2018 X-FILEs Workshop, the same four technology categories and aspects of teaching and learning were incorporated into the Jam. Each team?s ideation process was captured and transcribed. A summary of the first Student Jam is included in the X-FILEs workshop book mentioned earlier.  The COVID-19 pandemic occurred soon after the first Student Jam. The ensuing social distancing and masking requirements caused college faculty to quickly change the way they teach traditionally hands-on STEM activities (e.g., lab experiments) to online instructional settings. How faculty and students use mundane technologies like video conferencing apps and their access to technologies like wifi became critical to students? education. In fall 2021, the research team decided to pivot to explore this issue, rather than focus on more cutting-edge technologies such as artificial intelligence and cross reality.   The research team held online discussions in fall 2021 with faculty who, in spring 202, had little to no prior experience with remote/online teaching or using extensive educational technology in their classrooms. Participants shared the challenges that they faced while others presented unexpected advantages of using technologies related to online education. They also conveyed how their experiences shape their attitudes towards future use of technology in STEM education. These findings about teaching and learning during the pandemic are consistent with themes that are emerging in the education research literature. The project team continues to study this.  In spring 2022, the research team conducted a series of focus groups with college STEM majors who had experienced STEM courses before the COVID-19 pandemic, during the pandemic?s disruption, and after students returned to face-to-face classes. The research team is analyzing the focus groups? transcripts now.          Last Modified: 08/25/2022       Submitted by: Kurt J Winkelmann]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
