<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SCC-CIVIC-PG Track A: Undesigning the redline and reimagining mobility investments to equitably link jobs, affordable housing, and services]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/15/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>49889.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>49889</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Linda Bushnell</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lbushnel@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928950</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Many urban neighborhoods that have experienced decades of disinvestment and displacement lack dense, frequent, and reliable transportation options, despite the growth in light rail construction, shared ride services, micro-modes of transportation, and technologies that support demand responsive transit. Yet, significant mobility improvements could save residents time and money and improve access to employment, education, food, health care, and other necessary destinations. At the same time, transportation improvements could lead to redevelopment that causes displacement. To advance inclusive and opportunity-rich urban regeneration without displacement, this project envisions a multi-sector and intersectional process to design, test, and institutionalize an innovative community engagement method in a formerly Redlined neighborhood in Denver, Colorado, Valverde, that results in strong community adoption of a technology-supported, community-designed neighborhood mobility system that connects multiple local and regional transportation modes, including traditional transit (bus and rail), micro-transit (e.g. demand responsive shuttles), and micro-modes (e.g. bikes, e-scooters, etc.). This project's approach furthers the development of smart city technologies to promote resident health, prosperity, and welfare through the design and implementation of an equitable and adaptive community-oriented mobility management platform and supportive backend systems that incorporate policies for equity, community ownership, ongoing feedback, rapid system changes, low-barrier participation for micro mobility entrepreneurs, and affordable user subscriptions. While there are many competing transit and mobility apps, none to the project team's knowledge, accommodate all potential modes, local providers, and the ability for ongoing feedback that informs rapid system responses. This approach will also test processes for public institutions and nonprofits to co-construct community engagement processes with residents that are focused on contextually appropriate mobility solutions without triggering displacement. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed system would upgrade and expand the Regional Transit District’s (RTD) existing front-end (e.g., Mobility as a System (MaaS) platform) and back-end technologies to provide affordable subscriptions for mobility packages, community management and ownership opportunities for demand responsive micro-mobilities, and user feedback loops that inform rapid adjustments to bus and shuttle routes and schedules. This project will also create a pilot neighborhood mobility hub to enhance visibility, access, and connectivity among modes; foster community dialog; provide mobility information; and support related entrepreneurial activities, e.g., community bike shops. The engagement plan builds on the Denver Undesign the Redline exhibit, which combined artifacts, storytelling, photos, and interactive activities; and the City’s use of photovoice methods for mobility planning. These exhibits help public officials and planners to understand community issues through the eyes of residents, which allows for more collaborative action.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is in response to Track A – CIVIC Innovation Challenge - Communities and Mobility a collaboration with NSF and the Department of Energy.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/11/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/20/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2043330</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Austin</FirstName>
<LastName>Troy</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Austin R Troy</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[austin.troy@ucdenver.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000439697</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/11/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Carrie</FirstName>
<LastName>Makarewicz</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Carrie L Makarewicz</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[carrie.makarewicz@ucdenver.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000671736</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/11/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Cara</FirstName>
<LastName>DiEnno</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Cara DiEnno</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[cara.dienno@du.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000740091</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/11/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yessica</FirstName>
<LastName>Holguin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>X</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Yessica X Holguin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[yessica@communitywealthbuilding.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000832465</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/11/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Colorado at Denver-Downtown Campus</Name>
<CityName>DENVER</CityName>
<ZipCode>802042055</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3037240090</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1380 LAWRENCE ST STE 300</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>M6CXZ6GSJW84</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF COLORADO AT DENVER</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Colorado at Denver-Downtown Campus]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>802173364</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>033Y</Code>
<Text>S&amp;CC: Smart &amp; Connected Commun</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>042Z</Code>
<Text>S&amp;CC: Smart and Connected Communities</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~49889</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>How can we undo infrastructural racism and co-create Responsive, Integrated, Diverse, and Equitable (RIDE) mobility systems that advance community-rooted health and wealth?&nbsp; The diverse members of the Valverde Movement Project (VMP) team are working to address the challenges created by many past transportation investments that contributed to myriad environmental injustices - including air pollution, traffic fatalities, exacerbation of a spatial mismatch between jobs and housing, and gentrification. VMP envisions a future where contextually appropriate mobility investments in digital, physical, and civic infrastructures support RIDE neighborhood mobility systems that serve diverse individuals and families through accessible and affordable connections to work, school, food, health care, recreation, goods, other services, and amenities within and beyond the neighborhood -- and allow for cooperative or local ownership models.&nbsp;</p> <p>With the support of the 2021 NSF Civic Innovation Mobility Challenge Planning grant, VMP developed and initiated an asset-based, multi-sector, culturally responsive, and community-rooted approach to develop RIDE mobility system investments, inspired by intersectional movements for social, racial, and environmental justice.&nbsp; During the four-month planning grant we:</p> <ul> <li> Hosted more than 110 meetings with neighborhood community members and professionals throughout the city, region, and nation to identify the interests and needs of the diverse community, the research needs of our civic and public partners, and the technical, financial, and temporal feasibility of our proposed set of mobility solutions;</li> <li>Conducted an asset-inventory that revealed a wealth of community resources, aligned plans, viable mobility options, and committed partners, as reflected by our SumApp/Kumu social system map of 28 partners;</li> <li>Drew from the resources of our diverse partners to complete extensive mixed-methods data collection on existing travel (origin-destination, volumes, times, and modes), mobility infrastructure, detailed land uses, and household characteristics;</li> <li>Identified new opportunities to integrate diverse existing efforts in the city and region including: integrated ticketing apps, app-distributed discounts and subsidies, E-mission customizable travel survey app with automated location sensing, Travel Training with local non-profits; equitably distributed Lyft and Lime e-bikes and e-scooters; and commute planning with DRCOG Way to Go and the Business Commute Optimization Software (BCOS);</li> <li>Identified opportunities to invest in complementary vetted mobility solutions through a community-driven process (e.g., participatory budgeting) including microtransit, pedestrian and bicyclist infrastructure safety and amenities, (micro)mobility hub; neighborhood carshare, pedal bike distribution and circulation programs, E-bike library and/or loan-to-own program in partnership with a local company (FattE-bikes), and people-powered mobility enterprises using pedi-cabs and pedal-trucks in partnership with Main Street Mobility solutions;</li> <li>Worked with the Valverde Neighborhood Association (VNA) to develop the VMP name and visual identity, recognizing RIDE mobility systems need social and civic infrastructures alongside digital and physical infrastructures;</li> <li>Partnered with VNA in planning and implementing an intensive outreach, capacity-building, and creative place-making initiative including two online surveys, door-to-door outreach to residents in the neighborhood public housing development, flyer distribution throughout the neighborhood, 2 pop-up events at nearby schools, and hosting a COVID-safe, outdoor, intergenerational engagement event, Valverde Movement Fest, attended by more than 100 residents and several nonprofits (see <a href="https://valverde-movement-project-dugis.hub.arcgis.com/pages/valverde-movement-fest">https://valverde-movement-project-dugis.hub.arcgis.com/pages/valverde-movement-fest</a>);</li> <li>Created a public website with several ArcGIS ?Story Maps? to share the results of the community-engaged research with VNA through participatory mapping, storytelling activities, and dot-mocracy voting on desired mobility solutions (see <a href="https://valverde-movement-project-dugis.hub.arcgis.com/">https://valverde-movement-project-dugis.hub.arcgis.com/</a>), including a story maps of (1)&nbsp; ?Valverde?s Past? - revealing the neighborhood?s history of redlining and infrastructural racism, (2) ?Valverde?s Present? - showing existing conditions based on secondary data sources and the observations of residents shared through community-based research, and (3) ?Valverde?s Promise? - presenting spatial inventory of past promises made compared to current conditions and a library of planning documents shaping the neighborhood context.</li> <li>Launched four summer ?pop-ups? in response to neighborhood concerns about street and park safety ? a multi-faceted strategy designed to activate a neighborhood park, continue community-based research, build community capacity, and catalyze new initiatives for VNA.</li> </ul> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Through this intersectional approach, VMP has developed a grounded vision and a contextualized understanding of both challenges and opportunities for developing RIDE mobility systems. Informed by our findings, VMP?s public sector and nonprofit advocacy partners are advancing context-specific priorities for Valverde in ongoing planning and policy initiatives. Moreover, VMPs intersectional approach has expanded network connections across multiple sectors. Our neighborhood partner, VNA, has grown its email list to 100 residents and continues to build momentum and people power through new community-led efforts including a campaign to name a pocket-park in honor of unsung neighborhood heroes from the Chicano movement.&nbsp; The intersectional, integrated research approach we developed is replicable and contributes to two critical gaps in transportation planning, engineering, and research: (1) a lack of methodologies producing nuanced and dynamic data on travel patterns and preferences outside the peak periods for households who are not making the dominant commute; and (2) insufficient understanding of civic engagement processes through which cross-sector partners can co-construct contextually appropriate mobility solutions that allow for socio-ecologically resilient, prosperous neighborhoods without displacement.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/29/2021<br>      Modified by: Carrie&nbsp;L&nbsp;Makarewicz</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2043330/2043330_10712942_1635524857576_VMPTheoryofChange--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2043330/2043330_10712942_1635524857576_VMPTheoryofChange--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Theory of Change"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2043330/2043330_10712942_1635524857576_VMPTheoryofChange--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Theory of Change"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Valverde Movement Project Theory of Change</div> <div class="imageCredit">Valverde Movement Project</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Carrie&nbsp;L&nbsp;Makarewicz</div> <div class="imageTitle">Theory of Change</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2043330/2043330_10712942_1635524955319_ValverdeContextMap--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2043330/2043330_10712942_1635524955319_ValverdeContextMap--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Valverde Neighborhood Context Map"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2043330/2043330_10712942_1635524955319_ValverdeContextMap--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Valverde Neighborhood Context Map"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Existing conditions and geographic context of the Valverde neighborhood in Denver, CO</div> <div class="imageCredit">Valverde Movement Project</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Carrie&nbsp;L&nbsp;Makarewicz</div> <div class="imageTitle">Valverde Neighborhood Context Map</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2043330/2043330_10712942_1635527403083_Partnerlogos--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2043330/2043330_10712942_1635527403083_Partnerlogos--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Valverde Movement Project Partners"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2043330/2043330_10712942_1635527403083_Partnerlogos--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Valverde Movement Project Partners"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The diverse partner organizations of the Valverde Movement Project from the private, nonprofit, public, and civic sectors.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Valverde Movement Project</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Carrie&nbsp;L&nbsp;Makarewicz</div> <div class="imageTitle">Valverde Movement Project Partners</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2043330/2043330_10712942_1635527706812_VMF_landscape--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2043330/2043330_10712942_1635527706812_VMF_landscape--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Valverde Movement Fest of the Valverde Movement Project"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2043330/2043330_10712942_1635527706812_VMF_landscape--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Valverde Movement Fest of the Valverde Movement Project"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The Valverde Movement Project Fest was a celebration of community, food, culture, knowledge & power.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Valverde Movement Project</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Carrie&nbsp;L&nbsp;Makarewicz</div> <div class="imageTitle">Valverde Movement Fest of the Valverde Movement Project</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2043330/2043330_10712942_1635528708758_VMP_website_landscape--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2043330/2043330_10712942_1635528708758_VMP_website_landscape--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Valverde Movement Project Website"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2043330/2043330_10712942_1635528708758_VMP_website_landscape--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Valverde Movement Project Website"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">An interactive website about the project and neighborhood to build civic and digital infrastructure that helps to build community capacity and create equitable mobility systems.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Valverde Movement Project</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Carrie&nbsp;L&nbsp;Makarewicz</div> <div class="imageTitle">Valverde Movement Project Website</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2043330/2043330_10712942_1635529215987_Visuallanguage--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2043330/2043330_10712942_1635529215987_Visuallanguage--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Valverde Movement Project Visual Language"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2043330/2043330_10712942_1635529215987_Visuallanguage--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Valverde Movement Project Visual Language"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">These custom icons were used to communicate the goals of the project and the various types of mobility options to create health and wealth.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Valverde Movement Project</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Carrie&nbsp;L&nbsp;Makarewicz</div> <div class="imageTitle">Valverde Movement Project Visual Language</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2043330/2043330_10712942_1635529756095_Visuallanguage--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2043330/2043330_10712942_1635529756095_Visuallanguage--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Valverde Movement Project Visual Language"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2043330/2043330_10712942_1635529756095_Visuallanguage--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Valverde Movement Project Visual Language"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Custom made icons to represent the goals of the project and the various mobility options to promote neighborhood health and wealth.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Valverde Movement Project</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Carrie&nbsp;L&nbsp;Makarewicz</div> <div class="imageTitle">Valverde Movement Project Visual Language</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ How can we undo infrastructural racism and co-create Responsive, Integrated, Diverse, and Equitable (RIDE) mobility systems that advance community-rooted health and wealth?  The diverse members of the Valverde Movement Project (VMP) team are working to address the challenges created by many past transportation investments that contributed to myriad environmental injustices - including air pollution, traffic fatalities, exacerbation of a spatial mismatch between jobs and housing, and gentrification. VMP envisions a future where contextually appropriate mobility investments in digital, physical, and civic infrastructures support RIDE neighborhood mobility systems that serve diverse individuals and families through accessible and affordable connections to work, school, food, health care, recreation, goods, other services, and amenities within and beyond the neighborhood -- and allow for cooperative or local ownership models.   With the support of the 2021 NSF Civic Innovation Mobility Challenge Planning grant, VMP developed and initiated an asset-based, multi-sector, culturally responsive, and community-rooted approach to develop RIDE mobility system investments, inspired by intersectional movements for social, racial, and environmental justice.  During the four-month planning grant we:   Hosted more than 110 meetings with neighborhood community members and professionals throughout the city, region, and nation to identify the interests and needs of the diverse community, the research needs of our civic and public partners, and the technical, financial, and temporal feasibility of our proposed set of mobility solutions; Conducted an asset-inventory that revealed a wealth of community resources, aligned plans, viable mobility options, and committed partners, as reflected by our SumApp/Kumu social system map of 28 partners; Drew from the resources of our diverse partners to complete extensive mixed-methods data collection on existing travel (origin-destination, volumes, times, and modes), mobility infrastructure, detailed land uses, and household characteristics; Identified new opportunities to integrate diverse existing efforts in the city and region including: integrated ticketing apps, app-distributed discounts and subsidies, E-mission customizable travel survey app with automated location sensing, Travel Training with local non-profits; equitably distributed Lyft and Lime e-bikes and e-scooters; and commute planning with DRCOG Way to Go and the Business Commute Optimization Software (BCOS); Identified opportunities to invest in complementary vetted mobility solutions through a community-driven process (e.g., participatory budgeting) including microtransit, pedestrian and bicyclist infrastructure safety and amenities, (micro)mobility hub; neighborhood carshare, pedal bike distribution and circulation programs, E-bike library and/or loan-to-own program in partnership with a local company (FattE-bikes), and people-powered mobility enterprises using pedi-cabs and pedal-trucks in partnership with Main Street Mobility solutions; Worked with the Valverde Neighborhood Association (VNA) to develop the VMP name and visual identity, recognizing RIDE mobility systems need social and civic infrastructures alongside digital and physical infrastructures; Partnered with VNA in planning and implementing an intensive outreach, capacity-building, and creative place-making initiative including two online surveys, door-to-door outreach to residents in the neighborhood public housing development, flyer distribution throughout the neighborhood, 2 pop-up events at nearby schools, and hosting a COVID-safe, outdoor, intergenerational engagement event, Valverde Movement Fest, attended by more than 100 residents and several nonprofits (see https://valverde-movement-project-dugis.hub.arcgis.com/pages/valverde-movement-fest); Created a public website with several ArcGIS ?Story Maps? to share the results of the community-engaged research with VNA through participatory mapping, storytelling activities, and dot-mocracy voting on desired mobility solutions (see https://valverde-movement-project-dugis.hub.arcgis.com/), including a story maps of (1)  ?Valverde?s Past? - revealing the neighborhood?s history of redlining and infrastructural racism, (2) ?Valverde?s Present? - showing existing conditions based on secondary data sources and the observations of residents shared through community-based research, and (3) ?Valverde?s Promise? - presenting spatial inventory of past promises made compared to current conditions and a library of planning documents shaping the neighborhood context. Launched four summer ?pop-ups? in response to neighborhood concerns about street and park safety ? a multi-faceted strategy designed to activate a neighborhood park, continue community-based research, build community capacity, and catalyze new initiatives for VNA.      Through this intersectional approach, VMP has developed a grounded vision and a contextualized understanding of both challenges and opportunities for developing RIDE mobility systems. Informed by our findings, VMP?s public sector and nonprofit advocacy partners are advancing context-specific priorities for Valverde in ongoing planning and policy initiatives. Moreover, VMPs intersectional approach has expanded network connections across multiple sectors. Our neighborhood partner, VNA, has grown its email list to 100 residents and continues to build momentum and people power through new community-led efforts including a campaign to name a pocket-park in honor of unsung neighborhood heroes from the Chicano movement.  The intersectional, integrated research approach we developed is replicable and contributes to two critical gaps in transportation planning, engineering, and research: (1) a lack of methodologies producing nuanced and dynamic data on travel patterns and preferences outside the peak periods for households who are not making the dominant commute; and (2) insufficient understanding of civic engagement processes through which cross-sector partners can co-construct contextually appropriate mobility solutions that allow for socio-ecologically resilient, prosperous neighborhoods without displacement.          Last Modified: 10/29/2021       Submitted by: Carrie L Makarewicz]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
