<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[I-Corps: Processing of high-performance optical isolator materials using magneto-optical garnets on Si wafers]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ruth Shuman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rshuman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922160</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this I-Corps project is the development of materials to improve communications. Current designs of certain components are limited to discrete bulk components that a have large footprint, need expensive raw materials and require a labor-intensive assembly processes.  The proposed technology will greatly simplify optical isolator manufacturing and performance. Applications for this technology include 5G wireless networks, data centers, and Internet of Things, and potentially photonic integrated circuits (PICs), which offer significant power, space and cost savings along with increased functionality for future communications systems. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project is based on the development of garnet-on-silicon optical isolator. Optical fiber technology has revolutionized communications, but expense and assembly difficulties have prevented step-function improvements. A hidden component in this expense is the optical isolator that sits in front of each laser to block reflections that otherwise interfere with the laser’s performance and lifetime. Composed of a thick iron garnet film, grown on a single-crystal garnet substrate, the isolator is also the likely roadblock in the expansion of fiber success.  The proposed technology enables the processing of high-performance magneto-optical garnets on Si wafers with oxide multilayers for optical resonance that enables isolation with 1000x thinner garnet films.  In addition, revolutionary garnet compositions and designs may provide magnet-free isolators. Together, these features may reduce cost and ease device assembly.  The use of Si as a substrate also enables integrated device manufacturing, rather than “pick and place” assembly methods of commercial products today.  With low-magnetization garnet compositions that maintain high Faraday rotations, this technology will have negligible dipole fields, and devices already have been designed that do not require external magnetic bias. These large-scale, inexpensive, magnet-free garnets open many applications in communications.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/18/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/18/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041, 47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2043044</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Bethanie</FirstName>
<LastName>Stadler</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Bethanie J Stadler</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[stadler@umn.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000281329</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/18/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Minnesota-Twin Cities</Name>
<CityName>MINNEAPOLIS</CityName>
<ZipCode>554552009</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6126245599</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>200 OAK ST SE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>KABJZBBJ4B54</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MINNESOTA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Minnesota - Twin Cities]]></Name>
<CityName>Minneapolis</CityName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>554550170</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[200 Union St SE, Keller Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8990</Code>
<Text>Optics and Photonics</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>An important outcome of this I-Corps program was the realization that our minimal viable product would be an optical isolator as a sub-component in a laser module, which in turn is a sub-component of an optical transceiver. The optical isolator by itself appears to be most valuable when it is integrated into the laser module because it has a smaller footprint, better SNR, eliminate packaging failures compared to competing &ldquo;pick and place&rdquo; isolators or current lasers without isolators. We found that the product ecosystem spans customers from fabless OEMs who design and contract foundries for manufacturing to users at the enterprise and hyperscale levels. The gap between the two is bridged with a variety of suppliers and service providers.</p> <p>After 103 interviews, during which 30 hypotheses were tested and 6 customer segments were considered, we identified OEMs as our primary customer segment. &nbsp;Specifically, the decision maker would be a Director/VP in the transceiver product development team, influenced by the recommendations of a principal design engineer. The OEM customer segment validated 6 of our hypotheses which allowed us to rephrase them as value propositions for the identified target market.</p> <p>As next steps, we are moving forward with an OEM who prefers not to be named at this early stage with plans to submit an STTR proposal within this calendar year. We have early results on commercial waveguides provided by AIM Photonics, and our near term goal is to have our technology licensed as a component in the product develop kit of several fabs, beginning with AIM Photonics.</p> <p>In addition our entrepreneurial lead has been working as a postdoc at Cornell, and has received a faculty offer, although he has not accepted yet so details are held back for now. A new PhD student has been trained and developed the monolithic processing of garnets on Si including waveguides purchased from AIM Photonics for non-recriprocal mode converting isolators.&nbsp; This student (Pang-Hsiao Liu) has also just passes his oral preliminary exam.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/29/2023<br>      Modified by: Bethanie&nbsp;J&nbsp;Stadler</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ An important outcome of this I-Corps program was the realization that our minimal viable product would be an optical isolator as a sub-component in a laser module, which in turn is a sub-component of an optical transceiver. The optical isolator by itself appears to be most valuable when it is integrated into the laser module because it has a smaller footprint, better SNR, eliminate packaging failures compared to competing "pick and place" isolators or current lasers without isolators. We found that the product ecosystem spans customers from fabless OEMs who design and contract foundries for manufacturing to users at the enterprise and hyperscale levels. The gap between the two is bridged with a variety of suppliers and service providers.  After 103 interviews, during which 30 hypotheses were tested and 6 customer segments were considered, we identified OEMs as our primary customer segment.  Specifically, the decision maker would be a Director/VP in the transceiver product development team, influenced by the recommendations of a principal design engineer. The OEM customer segment validated 6 of our hypotheses which allowed us to rephrase them as value propositions for the identified target market.  As next steps, we are moving forward with an OEM who prefers not to be named at this early stage with plans to submit an STTR proposal within this calendar year. We have early results on commercial waveguides provided by AIM Photonics, and our near term goal is to have our technology licensed as a component in the product develop kit of several fabs, beginning with AIM Photonics.  In addition our entrepreneurial lead has been working as a postdoc at Cornell, and has received a faculty offer, although he has not accepted yet so details are held back for now. A new PhD student has been trained and developed the monolithic processing of garnets on Si including waveguides purchased from AIM Photonics for non-recriprocal mode converting isolators.  This student (Pang-Hsiao Liu) has also just passes his oral preliminary exam.          Last Modified: 05/29/2023       Submitted by: Bethanie J Stadler]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
