<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SCC-CIVIC-PG Track B: Rehearsing Natural Disasters through Games and Simulations]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/15/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>49911.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>49911</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sandip Roy</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>saroy@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032920000</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Recent events requiring evacuations such as the Camp Fire in Paradise, California highlight the critical need to better prepare communities for life-threatening natural hazards (flooding, earthquakes and wildfires) that affect so many communities in California and the country as a whole. Resilience in the face of these dangerous events requires a variety of changes from personal behaviors to regional policies and infrastructure. Despite the high stakes, change in this realm has proven slow and illusive. This proposal addresses this challenge by providing a means for emergency officials, incident commanders and community members to explore alternative responses to different hazards through the use of scenario-based games. These games, often referred to as “digital twins”, probe the interdependencies between the networks of transportation, lifeline infrastructures of water, power, and communications, and organizational plans that need to align for effective response to urgent hazards. An interdisciplinary team of designers, civil engineers, policy experts, and community members  will create social games based on wildfire, traffic and communication simulations. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project's inter-disciplinary team will partner with organizations in Oakland and Bolinas, California who are seeking new ways to increase the ability of their communities to respond to wildfire evacuation events. Together, the team will co-develop the social games with the purpose of surfacing local insight, knowledge, and feedback. These games are far more than entertainment, rather, they are constructed as prototypes that are used to support a cycle of mutual learning between the community and the researchers. In doing so, the team will create more resilient communities by using these instruments in a novel way to address the long-standing, classic problem of the transition of cognition to action. This project will offer new lines of research into more humanized data simulations, rapid, and iterative policy exploration and use of design at a systems scale. The insights gained from this project will have applications for the many communities within California and the United States that need to develop ways to create more resilient communities prepared to take effective action quickly in response to recurring hazards.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/12/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/20/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2043357</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
<LastName>Maiorana</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Thomas Maiorana</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[tmaiorana@ucdavis.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000750603</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/12/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kenichi</FirstName>
<LastName>Soga</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kenichi Soga</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[soga@berkeley.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000735833</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/12/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Davis</Name>
<CityName>DAVIS</CityName>
<ZipCode>956186153</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5307547700</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1850 RESEARCH PARK DR, STE 300</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>TX2DAGQPENZ5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, DAVIS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>NUDGYLBB4S99</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California, Davis]]></Name>
<CityName>Davis</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>956165270</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1 Shields Avenue, 101 Cruess Hal]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>033Y</Code>
<Text>S&amp;CC: Smart &amp; Connected Commun</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>042Z</Code>
<Text>S&amp;CC: Smart and Connected Communities</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~49911</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-21b819aa-7fff-f85d-60b6-cf75cfa3a83e"> </span></p> <p><span id="docs-internal-guid-ea77317d-7fff-1f6b-d202-9129e50fde35"> <p dir="ltr"><span>During the course of this project our team developed partnerships in the community of Bolinas, California and Oakland, California. The goal of the project was to support these communities' existing efforts related to wildfire evacuations. To this end, we developed several interactive prototypes that were intended to allow the communities to rehearse a wildfire evacuation.&nbsp;</span></p> <br /> <p dir="ltr"><span>First, we prototyped and developed a fully functioning interactive story to explore the issue of wildfire evacuation with community members. The interactive story featured several characters in the setting of Bolinas and Oakland and the audience was prompted to answer questions about the decisions made by the characters in each story. In doing so, the audience was able to learn about the best practices of wildfire evacuations in a low-risk, low pressure way. As part of this work stream we hosted workshops with the Oakland Firesafe Council. The event was used as a way to iterate the prototype and develop a more interactive video game.&nbsp;</span></p> <br /> <p dir="ltr"><span>Our team developed Traffic and Fire Models for the&nbsp; Bolinas area with support from Dr Bingyu Zhao. We also created Communication Models using Anylogic to show how the intersection among fire risk, traffic capacity, and communications functions affected the time required for evacuation under different scenarios. Our team worked with two graduate students, Sae Mi Chang and Sena Soysal, to develop AnyLogic models that estimated the time required for evacuation of the population of Bolinas (1500) using different types of communications -- radio, ham radio, cell phone, Twitter/Facebook, door-to-door, cognition -- under different scenarios of communications access, fire location and progression, and number of vehicles per household.&nbsp;&nbsp;</span></p> <br /> <p dir="ltr"><span>Key findings Design and Policy:</span></p> <ul> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>The games was both a teaching tool and a tool to gain more insights from the community.&nbsp;</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Simplicity of Game more critical than accuracy of all elements</span></p> <ul> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>As a prototype, the game was most successful when it fostered communication between participants. In an effort to replicate as much of the experience as possible, we made the iterations of the game too complex and it wasn&rsquo;t engaging enough to communicate the major learning points to the players.&nbsp; In response, we stripped away some of the non-essential complexity and addressed those issues through discussion.</span></p> </li> </ul> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Interactivity offered opportunities for additional discussions</span></p> <ul> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>The interactivity of the game created unscripted moments of interaction. In many cases, the ambiguity of an interaction caused players to halt the game to discuss the &ldquo;rules&rdquo; and how those did, or did not, align with the overall evacuation goals.&nbsp;</span></p> </li> </ul> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Game itself a potential for community building</span></p> <ul> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>While the game was designed to create bi-directional learning between players and researchers, we also found an additional benefit; the players got to know each other </span><span>because</span><span> they were playing the game.&nbsp;</span></p> </li> </ul> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>fire personnel recognize that evacuation is a regional process, and identifying destination points before the fire is critical in a time-dependent event like wildfire.</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Communication that enables fire personnel and community residents to consider other alternatives is essential</span></p> </li> </ul> <br /> <p dir="ltr"><span>Key Findings: Engineering Models and Simulation</span></p> <ul> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Under optimal conditions, with cell towers functioning and communications flowing to all groups, exit roads not blocked by fire or fallen trees, the population of Bolinas (1500) could evacuate safely in 1.5 hours.</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Under conditions when cell tower was damaged and cell phones/internet was operating at 50% capacity, safe evacuation of the population of Bolinas would take 5 hours.&nbsp;</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Under the worst scenario, when cell towers were totally dysfunctional with potential blockage of single exit by fire or fallen trees, evacuation of Bolinas population would take approximately 10 hours.&nbsp;</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>The intersection among location and progression of the fire, access to, and functionality of, multiple means of communication among residents and tourists in Bolinas, and number of vehicles per household used in evacuation is critical to determining the safe evacuation of the population of Bolinas.&nbsp;</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Using modeling to identify the constraints imposed on the evacuation process under different conditions of access and functionality helps residents to consider other alternatives, such as sheltering in place and identify safe locations to do so before a wildfire occurs.</span></p> </li> </ul> <br /> <p dir="ltr"><span>Key Findings: Project Overall</span></p> <ul> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Desire for new ways of addressing systemic issues.&nbsp;</span></p> <ul> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Our partners were very interested in finding new ways to address the entrenched problems of wildfire preparedness.&nbsp;</span></p> </li> </ul> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Opportunities</span></p> <ul> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>The ability to integrate real world simulations with a game has tremendous promise.</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>It offers potential to understand more of they dynamics, (communication, behavioral, infrastructure) than would be possible in isolation or less integrated experiences</span></p> </li> </ul> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Challenges</span></p> <ul> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Technical integration. The granularity of the technical data was often different from what was needed for the mechanics of the game. This became particularly challenging when designing the data integration in parallel with the game mechanics.&nbsp;</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Identifying the proper &ldquo;resolution&rdquo;. Our team struggled to identify just how much we would &ldquo;recreate&rdquo; the locations of Bolinas and Oakland Hills. </span></p> </li> </ul> </li> </ul> </span></p> <p dir="ltr">&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/29/2022<br>      Modified by: Thomas&nbsp;Maiorana</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2043357/2043357_10713060_1656516959110_EvacuationGame--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2043357/2043357_10713060_1656516959110_EvacuationGame--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Title Screen: Evacuation Game"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2043357/2043357_10713060_1656516959110_EvacuationGame--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Title Screen: Evacuation Game"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The title screen for the latest incarnation of the game.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Tom Maiorana</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Thomas&nbsp;Maiorana</div> <div class="imageTitle">Title Screen: Evacuation Game</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2043357/2043357_10713060_1631138255056_Bolinas_overview--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2043357/2043357_10713060_1631138255056_Bolinas_overview--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Bolinas Resilience Screens"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2043357/2043357_10713060_1631138255056_Bolinas_overview--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Bolinas Resilience Screens"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Stills from the videogame, Bolinas Reslience.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Tom Maiorana</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Thomas&nbsp;Maiorana</div> <div class="imageTitle">Bolinas Resilience Screens</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2043357/2043357_10713060_1656516772907_reference-BKG-combo_v2_reference_1920--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2043357/2043357_10713060_1656516772907_reference-BKG-combo_v2_reference_1920--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Game World"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2043357/2043357_10713060_1656516772907_reference-BKG-combo_v2_reference_1920--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Game World"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The latest version of the Evacuation Game world.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Tom Maiorana</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Thomas&nbsp;Maiorana</div> <div class="imageTitle">Game World</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2043357/2043357_10713060_1656516894248_EvacuationGame--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2043357/2043357_10713060_1656516894248_EvacuationGame--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Title Screen"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2022/2043357/2043357_10713060_1656516894248_EvacuationGame--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Title Screen"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The title screen for the latest version of "Evacuation Game".</div> <div class="imageCredit">Tom Maiorana</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Thomas&nbsp;Maiorana</div> <div class="imageTitle">Title Screen</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2043357/2043357_10713060_1631138765144_Story-Layout--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2043357/2043357_10713060_1631138765144_Story-Layout--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Interactive Stories"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/2043357/2043357_10713060_1631138765144_Story-Layout--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Interactive Stories"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Stills from the Interactive Stories</div> <div class="imageCredit">Tom Maiorana</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Thomas&nbsp;Maiorana</div> <div class="imageTitle">Interactive Stories</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[     During the course of this project our team developed partnerships in the community of Bolinas, California and Oakland, California. The goal of the project was to support these communities' existing efforts related to wildfire evacuations. To this end, we developed several interactive prototypes that were intended to allow the communities to rehearse a wildfire evacuation.    First, we prototyped and developed a fully functioning interactive story to explore the issue of wildfire evacuation with community members. The interactive story featured several characters in the setting of Bolinas and Oakland and the audience was prompted to answer questions about the decisions made by the characters in each story. In doing so, the audience was able to learn about the best practices of wildfire evacuations in a low-risk, low pressure way. As part of this work stream we hosted workshops with the Oakland Firesafe Council. The event was used as a way to iterate the prototype and develop a more interactive video game.    Our team developed Traffic and Fire Models for the  Bolinas area with support from Dr Bingyu Zhao. We also created Communication Models using Anylogic to show how the intersection among fire risk, traffic capacity, and communications functions affected the time required for evacuation under different scenarios. Our team worked with two graduate students, Sae Mi Chang and Sena Soysal, to develop AnyLogic models that estimated the time required for evacuation of the population of Bolinas (1500) using different types of communications -- radio, ham radio, cell phone, Twitter/Facebook, door-to-door, cognition -- under different scenarios of communications access, fire location and progression, and number of vehicles per household.     Key findings Design and Policy:   The games was both a teaching tool and a tool to gain more insights from the community.    Simplicity of Game more critical than accuracy of all elements   As a prototype, the game was most successful when it fostered communication between participants. In an effort to replicate as much of the experience as possible, we made the iterations of the game too complex and it wasn’t engaging enough to communicate the major learning points to the players.  In response, we stripped away some of the non-essential complexity and addressed those issues through discussion.     Interactivity offered opportunities for additional discussions   The interactivity of the game created unscripted moments of interaction. In many cases, the ambiguity of an interaction caused players to halt the game to discuss the "rules" and how those did, or did not, align with the overall evacuation goals.      Game itself a potential for community building   While the game was designed to create bi-directional learning between players and researchers, we also found an additional benefit; the players got to know each other because they were playing the game.      fire personnel recognize that evacuation is a regional process, and identifying destination points before the fire is critical in a time-dependent event like wildfire.   Communication that enables fire personnel and community residents to consider other alternatives is essential     Key Findings: Engineering Models and Simulation   Under optimal conditions, with cell towers functioning and communications flowing to all groups, exit roads not blocked by fire or fallen trees, the population of Bolinas (1500) could evacuate safely in 1.5 hours.   Under conditions when cell tower was damaged and cell phones/internet was operating at 50% capacity, safe evacuation of the population of Bolinas would take 5 hours.    Under the worst scenario, when cell towers were totally dysfunctional with potential blockage of single exit by fire or fallen trees, evacuation of Bolinas population would take approximately 10 hours.    The intersection among location and progression of the fire, access to, and functionality of, multiple means of communication among residents and tourists in Bolinas, and number of vehicles per household used in evacuation is critical to determining the safe evacuation of the population of Bolinas.    Using modeling to identify the constraints imposed on the evacuation process under different conditions of access and functionality helps residents to consider other alternatives, such as sheltering in place and identify safe locations to do so before a wildfire occurs.     Key Findings: Project Overall   Desire for new ways of addressing systemic issues.    Our partners were very interested in finding new ways to address the entrenched problems of wildfire preparedness.      Opportunities   The ability to integrate real world simulations with a game has tremendous promise.   It offers potential to understand more of they dynamics, (communication, behavioral, infrastructure) than would be possible in isolation or less integrated experiences     Challenges   Technical integration. The granularity of the technical data was often different from what was needed for the mechanics of the game. This became particularly challenging when designing the data integration in parallel with the game mechanics.    Identifying the proper "resolution". Our team struggled to identify just how much we would "recreate" the locations of Bolinas and Oakland Hills.               Last Modified: 06/29/2022       Submitted by: Thomas Maiorana]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
