<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SCC-CIVIC-PG Track B: Hoomalu Halelea - Community-led Innovation for Integrated Flood Resilience]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/15/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>49997.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>49997</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>David Corman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dcorman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928754</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[In April 2018, Haleleʻa, Kauaʻi, set a U.S. record for 24-hr rainfall (49.69 in), causing $19.7 million in losses. Over two years later, with families and businesses still recovering, the event offers an opportunity to enhance resilience of area communities and other places worldwide which are increasingly vulnerable to floods. The Hawaiian Islands comprise a model social-ecological system of diversity in culture, rainfall, and ecosystems. Traditionally, Hawaiian food security was underpinned by oversight of water resources built across generations, but local knowledge alone can no longer encompass changes in rainfall, species invasion, and shifting land use. This proposal offers a model to restore capacity for local stewardship of waterways through scientific partnerships to enhance monitoring and communication tools. This project will enhance social and ecological community resilience to increasing flood risk through: 1) Collaborative Research - Working with community members to integrate diverse methods and knowledge of watershed change to enhance local level stream management; 2) Piloting restoration and stream clearing; 3) Monitoring and Communication to improve availability of historical and real-time hydrometeorological data to understand flood hazards, and promote connectedness around extreme events; and 4) Community Education and Training offering educational materials to enhance holistic resilience to future disasters. Project partners include seven community non-profits, the county disaster planning and response agency, three university faculty specializing in water - from atmosphere to groundwater - and one social scientist native to the study area, along with a community lead experienced in indigenous stewardship. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Project goals and scope of research include interviews and focus groups with community members, piloting stream restoration through invasive species removal, installation of real-time weather stations to monitor rainfall, development of a communication web portal, and course for community education that will include in-person on-site learning and video instruction.  Researchers and community members will together integrate elders’ knowledge, and historic stream data to generate research questions, place monitoring stations, and investigate hydrological responses during extreme rainfall events. This project provides a model for collaboration between university scholars, local non-profits, and indigenous community members to enhance research, infrastructure, and communication; provide monitoring, observation capability and training opportunities and enhance local resilience to climate change. This proposal will also contribute to understanding of cultural, social and contextual aspects of resilience; model collaborative processes to generate and assess locally relevant indicators of resilience over time; while testing applications of hydrological science and communication technology to climate change adaptation and planning.  This project addresses Track B – Resilience to Natural Disasters for the CIVIC Innovation Challenge a collaboration with NSF and the Department of Homeland Security.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/11/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/20/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2043358</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
<LastName>Giambelluca</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Thomas W Giambelluca</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[thomas@hawaii.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000228943</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/11/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mehana</FirstName>
<LastName>Vaughan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mehana Vaughan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mehana@hawaii.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000622265</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/11/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Hawaii</Name>
<CityName>HONOLULU</CityName>
<ZipCode>968222247</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8089567800</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2425 CAMPUS RD SINCLAIR RM 1</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Hawaii</StateName>
<StateCode>HI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>HI01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NSCKLFSSABF2</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF HAWAII</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Hawaii]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>HI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>968222234</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Hawaii</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>HI01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>033Y</Code>
<Text>S&amp;CC: Smart &amp; Connected Commun</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>042Z</Code>
<Text>S&amp;CC: Smart and Connected Communities</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~49997</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-04029ecc-7fff-eb18-2700-41dde76aec7a">&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The Hawaiian Islands, the most isolated land mass on earth, comprise a model social-ecological system with extreme rainfall gradients (Giambelluca et al. 2013) and highly diverse ecosystems (Vitousek 1995). In April 2018, a rain gauge in our project site, Halelea, a rural district on the Island of Kauai, Hawaii, set a US 24-hr rainfall record (49.7&rdquo;), causing $19.7M in losses. During the planning grant, Halelea experienced three flood events, 10 bridge closures, and a hillside collapse blocking the lone road into the area. Like other communities, Halelea is on the cusp of the climate crisis. In collaboration with community members and nonprofits, who have led flood and disaster response, and the Kauai Emergency Management Agency, we formulated a vision for enhancing community resilience to increasing flood risk in coastal communities by enhancing connectivity, which encompasses connections of community members with one another and their environment, as well as with government, tourists, and newer residents. Connectivity links Indigenous knowledge, local observations of ecological change and scientific instrumentation, to enhance capacity for mountain to sea watershed management, while connecting future generations to their responsibilities for reciprocal care. Our Stage 1 project focused on 1)</span><span>collaborative research</span><span> to integrated diverse knowledge of watershed changes, 2) </span><span>planning for restoration</span><span> to enhance stream management, </span><span>3) monitoring and communitcation</span><span> to improve availability of historical and real-time hydrometeorological data to enhance understanding of flood hazard, and </span><span>4) community education</span><span> and training to enhance resilience.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span><br /></span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>During Stage 1, we mapped historic ecological data on rainfall, streams and flooding. Hawaiian language newspapers from 1860-1940 showed a history of past extreme weather events in Halele&#699;a, including 15 droughts, two extreme floods, two landslides and 104 accounts of intense storms. Two interns worked with one community elder who has worked on water management his entire life to document area water systems, digitze and archive a century of sugar plantation rainfall and hydrology records.&nbsp; We held a six-month course for community learners age 18-65 interested in careers in environmental stewardship.&nbsp; We analyzed 80 interviews conducted after the 2018 floods, identifying key recommendations for flood resilience to guide our Stage 2 Grant application</span><span>. </span><span>We also conducted three focus groups with 22 long-time residents, five site visits, and three talk story sessions along streams, rivers, and coastlines across 5 watersheds.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span>Community members </span><span>described many ongoing changes in their environment</span><span> including proliferation of invasive species, unstable stream banks, increased run-off from surrounding&nbsp;</span>cliffs and sediment covering offshore reefs. They described heavier rains, frequent floods, and longer dry periods leaving farmers short of water to irrigate their crops. Key emerging areas of need to address in stage 2 include developing a handbook of best practices and institutional processes to support stream restoration, management of dangerous invasive species such as albizia, and soft restoration approaches, which work with the environment rather than hardening river banks or attempting to divert flow, along with non-tourism based jobs caring for watersheds. Community members and the Kaua&#699;i Emergency Management Area identified needs for more information on real time weather conditions and flood risk and means to transmit safety risks to visitor populations. In Stage 2 we will work to add resources (webcams, weather stations, and a data sharing platform) to build connectivity among community nonprofits, with government agencies and visitors, enhancing both daily and long-term decision making to support adaptation.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><span id="docs-internal-guid-68813d74-7fff-289b-6af2-1cb462475656"> </span></p> <p><span id="docs-internal-guid-56a234f8-7fff-7b11-800c-e17876b9ea2c">&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Intellectual Merit:</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>This project enhances understanding of connectivity and stream health adaptable to other small watersheds worldwide, while providing a model of collaborative research to weave Indigenous and western science approaches for resilience. It highlights the&nbsp; value of community-led watershed restoration within resilience planning. It enhances understanding of factors that underpin community resilience, building on scholarship defining resilience as ability to learn from a disaster and adapt to social and ecological change. </span><span>This work offers a model of university-community engaged and co-produced research for climate change resilience across the Pacific and in other regions, perpetuating Indigenous technologies and place-based knowledge, while integrating western scientific understanding to adapt for the future.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Broader Significance:</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>&nbsp;</span>This community-university partnership integrated diverse sources of knowledge of watershed change to enhance understanding of watershed change and flood risk in Halele&#699;a, Kaua&#699;i. This research strengthens decision making for public safety, as well as long term adapation in the face of climate change.&nbsp; The project will has also built pathways for university recruitment, education, and career advancement within a rural community, (one third Native Hawaiian and Pacific islander) under-served in higher education. We engaged senior, mid-career, and early-career researchers as PIs and members of the project leadership team (including one Native Hawaiians, three minorities and four women, three of whom are faculty), while growing university capacity to partner with diverse communities.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/03/2022<br>      Modified by: Mehana&nbsp;Vaughan</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   The Hawaiian Islands, the most isolated land mass on earth, comprise a model social-ecological system with extreme rainfall gradients (Giambelluca et al. 2013) and highly diverse ecosystems (Vitousek 1995). In April 2018, a rain gauge in our project site, Halelea, a rural district on the Island of Kauai, Hawaii, set a US 24-hr rainfall record (49.7"), causing $19.7M in losses. During the planning grant, Halelea experienced three flood events, 10 bridge closures, and a hillside collapse blocking the lone road into the area. Like other communities, Halelea is on the cusp of the climate crisis. In collaboration with community members and nonprofits, who have led flood and disaster response, and the Kauai Emergency Management Agency, we formulated a vision for enhancing community resilience to increasing flood risk in coastal communities by enhancing connectivity, which encompasses connections of community members with one another and their environment, as well as with government, tourists, and newer residents. Connectivity links Indigenous knowledge, local observations of ecological change and scientific instrumentation, to enhance capacity for mountain to sea watershed management, while connecting future generations to their responsibilities for reciprocal care. Our Stage 1 project focused on 1)collaborative research to integrated diverse knowledge of watershed changes, 2) planning for restoration to enhance stream management, 3) monitoring and communitcation to improve availability of historical and real-time hydrometeorological data to enhance understanding of flood hazard, and 4) community education and training to enhance resilience.   During Stage 1, we mapped historic ecological data on rainfall, streams and flooding. Hawaiian language newspapers from 1860-1940 showed a history of past extreme weather events in Halele&#699;a, including 15 droughts, two extreme floods, two landslides and 104 accounts of intense storms. Two interns worked with one community elder who has worked on water management his entire life to document area water systems, digitze and archive a century of sugar plantation rainfall and hydrology records.  We held a six-month course for community learners age 18-65 interested in careers in environmental stewardship.  We analyzed 80 interviews conducted after the 2018 floods, identifying key recommendations for flood resilience to guide our Stage 2 Grant application. We also conducted three focus groups with 22 long-time residents, five site visits, and three talk story sessions along streams, rivers, and coastlines across 5 watersheds.    Community members described many ongoing changes in their environment including proliferation of invasive species, unstable stream banks, increased run-off from surrounding cliffs and sediment covering offshore reefs. They described heavier rains, frequent floods, and longer dry periods leaving farmers short of water to irrigate their crops. Key emerging areas of need to address in stage 2 include developing a handbook of best practices and institutional processes to support stream restoration, management of dangerous invasive species such as albizia, and soft restoration approaches, which work with the environment rather than hardening river banks or attempting to divert flow, along with non-tourism based jobs caring for watersheds. Community members and the Kaua&#699;i Emergency Management Area identified needs for more information on real time weather conditions and flood risk and means to transmit safety risks to visitor populations. In Stage 2 we will work to add resources (webcams, weather stations, and a data sharing platform) to build connectivity among community nonprofits, with government agencies and visitors, enhancing both daily and long-term decision making to support adaptation.             Intellectual Merit: This project enhances understanding of connectivity and stream health adaptable to other small watersheds worldwide, while providing a model of collaborative research to weave Indigenous and western science approaches for resilience. It highlights the  value of community-led watershed restoration within resilience planning. It enhances understanding of factors that underpin community resilience, building on scholarship defining resilience as ability to learn from a disaster and adapt to social and ecological change. This work offers a model of university-community engaged and co-produced research for climate change resilience across the Pacific and in other regions, perpetuating Indigenous technologies and place-based knowledge, while integrating western scientific understanding to adapt for the future.   Broader Significance:  This community-university partnership integrated diverse sources of knowledge of watershed change to enhance understanding of watershed change and flood risk in Halele&#699;a, Kaua&#699;i. This research strengthens decision making for public safety, as well as long term adapation in the face of climate change.  The project will has also built pathways for university recruitment, education, and career advancement within a rural community, (one third Native Hawaiian and Pacific islander) under-served in higher education. We engaged senior, mid-career, and early-career researchers as PIs and members of the project leadership team (including one Native Hawaiians, three minorities and four women, three of whom are faculty), while growing university capacity to partner with diverse communities.          Last Modified: 02/03/2022       Submitted by: Mehana Vaughan]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
