<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research: The Criminal Deportation Pipeline]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>112949.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>112949</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Reginald Sheehan</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rsheehan@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925389</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The mass deportation of immigrants with criminal records has formed the cornerstone of increasingly punitive immigration policy in the United States over the past thirty years. The major categories of crimes for which lawful permanent residents (green card holders) can be removed are broad and amorphous, and for undocumented individuals, any conviction can lead to removal. Research has shown that racial and ethnic disparities profoundly impact the criminal justice system, adding to the risk of negative outcomes for Black and Latino immigrants in particular. We advance the concept of the “criminal deportation pipeline” to describe the intertwining criminal and immigration system processes that funnel certain immigrants toward removal. The study, drawing on the disciplines of sociology and criminology, focuses on the factors which shape and constitute this pipeline. Highlighting racial, ethnic and spatial disparities in criminal justice and immigration enforcement, as well as local policies and practices that aid immigrants targeted for expulsion, the study will demonstrate the pipeline’s functional presence in this iconic city of immigrants as well as factors that define its impact and character. The results of the research will contribute to the public debate on immigration policy and human rights reform while deepening our understanding of the relationship between citizenship, the law, and policing practices that have so impacted racialized immigrant communities. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Informed by theories of social exclusion and criminalization, particularly along the vectors of race, as well as the field of resistance, the study is oriented by the following research questions: (i) How do local patterns of non-immigration-related criminal justice enforcement shape the flow of the criminal deportation pipeline?; (ii) How do protective legal policies and practices affect the function of the criminal deportation pipeline?; and (iii) How do immigrants experience and respond to overlapping processes of criminalization and deportation? We will examine these questions using a mixed methods research design that combines 120 hours of targeted observation of deportation proceedings; secondary analysis of official documents and administrative government datasets; and 120 in-depth interviews with affected immigrants, legal practitioners, and community-based advocates. Research will expand upon preliminary spatial analysis of high deportation areas in order to: (i) better understand how spatial, racial, and ethnic patterns in policing shape processes of criminal deportation; (ii) assess the function and impacts of protective legal policies, and (iii) identify the experiences of immigrants facing deportation with criminal records, as well as the impacts of overlapping criminal and immigration. The new knowledge produced will allow further development of theory around processes of social control, state practices and human agency with regard to the collective and individual immigrant experience.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/25/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/02/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2043529</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sarah</FirstName>
<LastName>Tosh</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sarah R Tosh</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[sarah.tosh@rutgers.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000807313</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/25/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Rutgers University Camden</Name>
<CityName>CAMDEN</CityName>
<ZipCode>081021519</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8562252949</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>303 COOPER ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NJ01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>MPJFHQ7SMNH1</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RUTGERS, THE STATE UNIVERSITY OF NEW JERSEY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>M1LVPE5GLSD9</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Rutgers-Camden]]></Name>
<CityName>Camden</CityName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>081021521</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NJ01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>128Y</Code>
<Text>Law &amp; Science</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002223DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~44051</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2022~68898</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Through in-depth interviews, court observation, and archival analysis, this research examined the local practices that shape the &ldquo;criminalization-to-deportation pipeline&rdquo; in New York City&mdash;including racial, ethnic and spatial disparities in criminal justice enforcement, protective policies providing aid to immigrants with criminal records, and grassroots movements of community-based resistance. Over the course of this 2-year study, our research team conducted 101 interviews with impacted immigrants, legal practitioners, and community- based advocates; observed approximately 80 hours of deportation proceedings in local immigration courts; evaluated relevant policy texts, program advisories, procedural guidelines; and analyzed statistical government datasets. Through this investigation, we developed a holistic understanding of the enforcement and legal processes that comprise the &ldquo;criminalization-to-deportation pipeline&rdquo; in NYC, as well as the protective policies and community-based resistance that work to slow the pipeline&rsquo;s punitive and stratifying impacts.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Study findings have important implications for the overlapping fields of law and society, sociology of migration, and critical criminology&mdash;impacting in particular the concept of &ldquo;crimmigration,&rdquo; used to describe the increased intertwining of criminal and immigration law over the past forty years. Findings expand research on crimmigration by elucidating specific institutions and processes that facilitate this intertwining, even in a &ldquo;sanctuary&rdquo; city like NYC, and the uniquely determinative outcomes for non-citizens with non-immigration-related criminal convictions. They highlight the importance of local policing practices in funneling criminalized immigrants toward deportation, and the disparate impacts on non-citizens of color, especially Black immigrants, a group that is particularly concentrated in the NYC metropolitan area. Findings also speak to the importance of resistance at the crimmigration nexus, through local protective policies, like NYC&rsquo;s provision of universal representation for detained immigrants facing deportation, and by community-based activists who fight for the rights of immigrants with criminal convictions, and advocate for policy change in both the immigration and criminal legal systems.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Theoretical and empirical outcomes have already began to be disseminated, through scholarly presentations at academic conferences in the fields of sociology, criminology, and law and society, as well as in the undergraduate and graduate-level courses of the principal investigators. Findings will continue to impact scholarship through a special issue on the &ldquo;criminalization-to-deportation pipeline&rdquo; in the peer-reviewed journal, <em>Critical Criminology</em>, which will be published in Spring 2024, and will include articles detailing study findings, in conversation with relevant research conducted by esteemed scholars around the United States and beyond. Study findings will be further documented in refereed articles submitted for publication in academic journals in the fields of law and society, sociology, and criminal justice; as well as the doctoral dissertations of graduate students in sociology and criminal justice who served on the research team.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Broader impacts include the training received by these graduate students while working on the study, all of whom hail from communities underrepresented in the social sciences and higher education more broadly. Beyond this, study findings on the unequal and severe impacts of the &ldquo;criminalization-to-deportation pipeline&rdquo; will be disseminated to advocates, policymakers, impacted communities, and the broader public, in the hope of supporting reforms that will lead to more just systems of immigration law and criminal justice. This will be accomplished in part through a report that is being prepared in conjunction with the local immigrant rights organization, Families for Freedom, as well as a public-facing podcast &ldquo;Unearthing the Criminalization-to-Deportation Pipeline&rdquo; which will include interviews with researchers, advocates, and impacted community members encountered throughout the course of the study. Further plans for broader dissemination of research findings include public talks to be organized through the PIs&rsquo; universities, and co-sponsored by local community-based organizations.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/28/2023<br>      Modified by: Sarah&nbsp;R&nbsp;Tosh</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Through in-depth interviews, court observation, and archival analysis, this research examined the local practices that shape the "criminalization-to-deportation pipeline" in New York City&mdash;including racial, ethnic and spatial disparities in criminal justice enforcement, protective policies providing aid to immigrants with criminal records, and grassroots movements of community-based resistance. Over the course of this 2-year study, our research team conducted 101 interviews with impacted immigrants, legal practitioners, and community- based advocates; observed approximately 80 hours of deportation proceedings in local immigration courts; evaluated relevant policy texts, program advisories, procedural guidelines; and analyzed statistical government datasets. Through this investigation, we developed a holistic understanding of the enforcement and legal processes that comprise the "criminalization-to-deportation pipeline" in NYC, as well as the protective policies and community-based resistance that work to slow the pipeline’s punitive and stratifying impacts.     Study findings have important implications for the overlapping fields of law and society, sociology of migration, and critical criminology&mdash;impacting in particular the concept of "crimmigration," used to describe the increased intertwining of criminal and immigration law over the past forty years. Findings expand research on crimmigration by elucidating specific institutions and processes that facilitate this intertwining, even in a "sanctuary" city like NYC, and the uniquely determinative outcomes for non-citizens with non-immigration-related criminal convictions. They highlight the importance of local policing practices in funneling criminalized immigrants toward deportation, and the disparate impacts on non-citizens of color, especially Black immigrants, a group that is particularly concentrated in the NYC metropolitan area. Findings also speak to the importance of resistance at the crimmigration nexus, through local protective policies, like NYC’s provision of universal representation for detained immigrants facing deportation, and by community-based activists who fight for the rights of immigrants with criminal convictions, and advocate for policy change in both the immigration and criminal legal systems.     Theoretical and empirical outcomes have already began to be disseminated, through scholarly presentations at academic conferences in the fields of sociology, criminology, and law and society, as well as in the undergraduate and graduate-level courses of the principal investigators. Findings will continue to impact scholarship through a special issue on the "criminalization-to-deportation pipeline" in the peer-reviewed journal, Critical Criminology, which will be published in Spring 2024, and will include articles detailing study findings, in conversation with relevant research conducted by esteemed scholars around the United States and beyond. Study findings will be further documented in refereed articles submitted for publication in academic journals in the fields of law and society, sociology, and criminal justice; as well as the doctoral dissertations of graduate students in sociology and criminal justice who served on the research team.     Broader impacts include the training received by these graduate students while working on the study, all of whom hail from communities underrepresented in the social sciences and higher education more broadly. Beyond this, study findings on the unequal and severe impacts of the "criminalization-to-deportation pipeline" will be disseminated to advocates, policymakers, impacted communities, and the broader public, in the hope of supporting reforms that will lead to more just systems of immigration law and criminal justice. This will be accomplished in part through a report that is being prepared in conjunction with the local immigrant rights organization, Families for Freedom, as well as a public-facing podcast "Unearthing the Criminalization-to-Deportation Pipeline" which will include interviews with researchers, advocates, and impacted community members encountered throughout the course of the study. Further plans for broader dissemination of research findings include public talks to be organized through the PIs’ universities, and co-sponsored by local community-based organizations.          Last Modified: 06/28/2023       Submitted by: Sarah R Tosh]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
