<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SCC-CIVIC-PG Track B: Assessing the Feasibility of Systematizing Human-AI Teaming to Improve Community Resilience]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/15/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>49855.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>49855</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Linda Bushnell</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lbushnel@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928950</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Emergency managers need access to the right data to effectively and efficiently plan for and respond to disasters. Social media offers a data source that is increasingly relevant for disaster management, but emergency response organizations typically lack capacity to monitor and mine social media data at scale. One remedy is to pair human volunteers, who label relevant information, with computers to train and update artificial intelligence (AI) systems for scalable monitoring. Including local volunteers in the process is important because they are uniquely capable of identifying locally-relevant images, text, and conversations that reflect their communities.  Yet, we currently have no mechanism to systematically pair these human volunteer/AI-systems with emergency management organizations.  Therefore, the fundamental issue this project investigates is the feasibility of leveraging the strengths of local members of a Community Emergency Response Team (CERT) with AI—called human-AI teaming—to bridge this gap.  The unique CIVIC aspect of this project is to leverage existing collaborations with a CERT organization to assess the feasibility.  The long-term vision is to develop a sustainable, replicable, and empirically informed framework for integrating CERT volunteers into the automated processing of social media data using an AI-based system.  The project supports education and diversity by providing research experiences to diverse students, as well as training CERT volunteers in social media and human-AI teaming.  Findings can help emergency managers better train their volunteers who comb through social media using understandings of the built environment to help machines see new patterns in data.  Hence, this project supports NSF's mission to promote the progress of science and advance the nation's health, prosperity, and welfare by demonstrating the value of leveraging local CERT volunteers, in partnership with emergency managers, to generate disaster situation awareness.    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of this planning grant is to analyze existing human-AI teaming disaster data and involve civic partners in focus groups to better understand the attitudes and beliefs of CERT volunteers, emergency managers, key governmental organizations, and non-governmental organizations.  This project will develop deep knowledge of digital volunteer teams, how they work, how to motivate them, and how to have them support the objectives of emergency managers. Thus, we advance theory around volunteer teaming in the technology space and human-in-the-loop protocols.  This project provides meaningful ways for more citizens to participate in disaster planning and response, and develops a training curriculum for CERT volunteers who work with social media data in an effort to build sustainable volunteer efforts.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is in response to Track B - CIVIC Innovation Challenge - Resilience to Natural Disasters a collaboration with NSF and the Department of Homeland Security.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/08/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/20/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2043522</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Keri</FirstName>
<LastName>Stephens</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>K</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Keri K Stephens</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[keristephens@austin.utexas.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000537592</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/08/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Amanda Lee</FirstName>
<LastName>Hughes</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Amanda Lee Hughes</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[amanda_hughes@byu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000668319</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/08/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Christopher</FirstName>
<LastName>Zobel</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Christopher W Zobel</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[czobel@vt.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000395515</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/08/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Hemant</FirstName>
<LastName>Purohit</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Hemant Purohit</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[hpurohit@gmu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000703195</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/08/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Texas at Austin</Name>
<CityName>AUSTIN</CityName>
<ZipCode>787121139</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5124716424</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>110 INNER CAMPUS DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>25</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX25</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>V6AFQPN18437</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT AUSTIN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>X5NKD2NFF2V3</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[The University of Texas at Austin]]></Name>
<CityName>Austin</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>787121075</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2504-A Whitis Ave., Stop A1105]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>25</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX25</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>033Y</Code>
<Text>S&amp;CC: Smart &amp; Connected Commun</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>042Z</Code>
<Text>S&amp;CC: Smart and Connected Communities</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~49855</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>SCC-CIVIC-PG Track B: Assessing the Feasibility of Systematizing Human-AI Teaming to Improve Community Resilience</strong></p> <p>Emergency managers need access to the right data to effectively and efficiently plan for and respond to disasters. Social media offers a data source that is increasingly relevant for disaster management, but emergency response organizations typically lack capacity to monitor and mine social media data at scale. Using volunteers who are members of Community Emergency Response Teams (CERT) to identify local data in social media offers one way to help identify important information shared by the public during disasters. Therefore, the goal of this planning grant was to analyze existing human-AI teaming data for disaster response and involve the civic partners in executing focus groups to better understand the attitudes and beliefs of CERT volunteers, emergency managers, key governmental organizations, and non-governmental organizations.&nbsp; This project also further enhanced the relationship between our academic and CIVIC partners with the goal of jointly pursuing additional funding to enhance our work.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;The intellectual merit of this project includes developing a much deeper understanding of digital volunteer teams and how they view their role in teaming with AI/machine learning systems. Specifically, during this CIVIC planning grant, our team deepened our relationship with our CIVIC partners and by using a multi-interview approach, we identified that over time, people can work with machines and view them as a valued teaming partner. Furthermore, we interviewed many different types of stakeholders who need to be involved when changing disaster-related decision-making processes. We found that while all of them acknowledge technology?AI and machine learning in particular?is important to help them synthesize the vast amount of data available today, many of them also want the technology to be usable for real-time events and to be robust and reliable.&nbsp; &nbsp;</p> <p>The broader impacts of this project include demonstrating that volunteers can be trained to not only identify and provide data to help machine learn, but they can also correct machines and improve the accuracy of disaster-related machine learning. Convergence and implementing team science principles into larger interdisciplinary teams is a priority for the National Science Foundation and for scientific teams desiring to make novel scientific advancements. Not only did this project focus on these types of efforts but we also published a paper that makes the challenges and opportunities when working between academic and CIVIC partner teams more transparent. Hence, this project supports NSF's mission to promote the progress of science and to advance the nation's health, prosperity, and welfare by furthering our understanding of how humans can work with machines to make disaster-related decisions and the importance of including multiple stakeholders to obtain buy-in to use technology solutions.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/18/2023<br>      Modified by: Keri&nbsp;K&nbsp;Stephens</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2043522/2043522_10712694_1676763440161_CelebratingAnastazjasizedforTwitter--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2043522/2043522_10712694_1676763440161_CelebratingAnastazjasizedforTwitter--rgov-800width.jpg" title="CIVIC Team Example of Celebratory Meeting"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2043522/2043522_10712694_1676763440161_CelebratingAnastazjasizedforTwitter--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="CIVIC Team Example of Celebratory Meeting"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">This CIVIC Team became a stronger team throughout the project. Here we are celebrating our graduate student who received an NSF Dissertation Research Award.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Keri K. Stephens</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Keri&nbsp;K&nbsp;Stephens</div> <div class="imageTitle">CIVIC Team Example of Celebratory Meeting</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2043522/2043522_10712694_1676763576984_AmandaHughesusingCitizenHelper--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2043522/2043522_10712694_1676763576984_AmandaHughesusingCitizenHelper--rgov-800width.jpg" title="CIVIC Team Member Using Machine Learning Tool"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2023/2043522/2043522_10712694_1676763576984_AmandaHughesusingCitizenHelper--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="CIVIC Team Member Using Machine Learning Tool"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">All team members were trained to use Citizen Helper, the machine learning tool used in the project.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Brigham Young University</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Keri&nbsp;K&nbsp;Stephens</div> <div class="imageTitle">CIVIC Team Member Using Machine Learning Tool</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ SCC-CIVIC-PG Track B: Assessing the Feasibility of Systematizing Human-AI Teaming to Improve Community Resilience  Emergency managers need access to the right data to effectively and efficiently plan for and respond to disasters. Social media offers a data source that is increasingly relevant for disaster management, but emergency response organizations typically lack capacity to monitor and mine social media data at scale. Using volunteers who are members of Community Emergency Response Teams (CERT) to identify local data in social media offers one way to help identify important information shared by the public during disasters. Therefore, the goal of this planning grant was to analyze existing human-AI teaming data for disaster response and involve the civic partners in executing focus groups to better understand the attitudes and beliefs of CERT volunteers, emergency managers, key governmental organizations, and non-governmental organizations.  This project also further enhanced the relationship between our academic and CIVIC partners with the goal of jointly pursuing additional funding to enhance our work.    The intellectual merit of this project includes developing a much deeper understanding of digital volunteer teams and how they view their role in teaming with AI/machine learning systems. Specifically, during this CIVIC planning grant, our team deepened our relationship with our CIVIC partners and by using a multi-interview approach, we identified that over time, people can work with machines and view them as a valued teaming partner. Furthermore, we interviewed many different types of stakeholders who need to be involved when changing disaster-related decision-making processes. We found that while all of them acknowledge technology?AI and machine learning in particular?is important to help them synthesize the vast amount of data available today, many of them also want the technology to be usable for real-time events and to be robust and reliable.     The broader impacts of this project include demonstrating that volunteers can be trained to not only identify and provide data to help machine learn, but they can also correct machines and improve the accuracy of disaster-related machine learning. Convergence and implementing team science principles into larger interdisciplinary teams is a priority for the National Science Foundation and for scientific teams desiring to make novel scientific advancements. Not only did this project focus on these types of efforts but we also published a paper that makes the challenges and opportunities when working between academic and CIVIC partner teams more transparent. Hence, this project supports NSF's mission to promote the progress of science and to advance the nation's health, prosperity, and welfare by furthering our understanding of how humans can work with machines to make disaster-related decisions and the importance of including multiple stakeholders to obtain buy-in to use technology solutions.         Last Modified: 02/18/2023       Submitted by: Keri K Stephens]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
