<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Quantum Epistemology Beyond Quantum Measurement]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>450950.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>450950</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Frederick Kronz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>fkronz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927283</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[It is well known that quantum mechanics does not, in general, predict any one outcome of a given experiment with certainty, but instead predicts a distribution of probability values for possible outcomes. One enduring question in the interpretation of quantum mechanics is: just what do these probabilities signify? Many believe quantum probabilities represent something objective, such as frequencies of measurement outcomes in repeated trials. Others suggest a perhaps more radical view that quantum probabilities only represent a person’s subjective personal beliefs. On this subjective view, different people making predictions with quantum mechanics might even reasonably disagree about the probabilities of experimental outcomes.  These objective and subjective interpretations of quantum probability present starkly different philosophical viewpoints. And understanding quantum probabilities is not only important for making sense of the theory itself; it also has implications for the fields of quantum information and quantum computing, which aim to use quantum theory to develop new technologies. The goal of this project is to investigate the status of quantum probability by developing a view that does not require quantum probabilities to be only objective or only subjective, but instead allows for both possibilities. The project will analyze the relationships among objective and subjective probabilities in quantum mechanics to yield important insights about how they both figure into the nature of physical probability.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The current project approaches the interpretation of quantum probability in a novel way by separating questions about probability from other controversial topics in the interpretation of quantum mechanics. The question of whether probabilities are objective frequencies or subjective beliefs has been addressed in existing work by tying an answer to more contentious views about the status of measurements in quantum theory. For example, some investigators reach an understanding of probability based on a view of quantum measurement that implies the existence of a "multiverse" of many worlds. This project will develop methods for analyzing the relationship between objective and subjective probabilities, methods which do not depend on such highly debated issues. As such, the project aims to make a lasting impact by establishing tools for understanding quantum probability that will apply, regardless of the ultimate interpretation of quantum mechanics. The project will thus lay the foundation for further research and understanding, which will be aided by disseminating the developed methods in a workshop to train early career interdisciplinary researchers, as well as public lectures to engage the broader community in these deep questions about fundamental physics and the nature of probability.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/19/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/14/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2043089</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Samuel</FirstName>
<LastName>Fletcher</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Samuel C Fletcher</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[scfletch@umn.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000640697</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/19/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Benjamin</FirstName>
<LastName>Feintzeig</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Benjamin Feintzeig</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[bfeintze@uw.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000762263</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/19/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Washington</Name>
<CityName>SEATTLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>981951016</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2065434043</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4333 BROOKLYN AVE NE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>HD1WMN6945W6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF WASHINGTON</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Washington]]></Name>
<CityName>Seattle</CityName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>981950001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4333 Brooklyn Ave NE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>124Y</Code>
<Text>Science &amp; Technology Studies</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0122</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002223DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~242822</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2022~208128</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="p1">This project analyzed the philosophical foundations of objective and subjective probability in quantum mechanics.&nbsp; Previously, philosophical work on quantum mechanics and quantum probability has been thought to require a particular interpretation of quantum theory that solves the so-called measurement problem, explaining how quantum states yield determinate measurement results.&nbsp; The research team demonstrated that much philosophical analysis of quantum theory and quantum probability can proceed by considering only what these interpretations of quantum mechanics share in common.&nbsp; The researchers investigated the objective aspects of quantum probabilities through a method involving a notion of accuracy for updating probabilities, and through a method analyzing the long time behavior of quantum dynamics in measurement setups.&nbsp; The researchers investigated subjective aspects of quantum probabilities by engaging the formalism of quantum theory with methods from economics regarding subjective decision making.&nbsp; The researchers analyzed the status of properties and their determinate values in quantum mechanics, thereby separating logical aspects of quantum theory from particular interpretations.&nbsp; The researchers further investigated historical aspects of the epistemic status and social dynamics of discussions surrounding the interpretation of quantum mechanics.&nbsp; The research outcomes have led to new frameworks and new methods for approaching the philosophical foundations of&nbsp; quantum mechanics without committing a specific interpretation of quantum theory.&nbsp; Thus this research produced results significant for the general formalism of quantum theory, which should be of interest across the research community in the foundations of physics.</p> <p class="p1">In addition to the research outcomes, this project produced a number of broader impacts.<span>&nbsp;&nbsp;</span>The research team organized an early career workshop to build an interdisciplinary community of academic researchers in the summer of 2022.<span>&nbsp;&nbsp;</span>Additionally, the project provided mentoring and support for a postdoctoral scholar, two graduate students, and four undergraduate students.<span>&nbsp;&nbsp;</span>Finally, the PI organized a public lecture series in philosophy of physics.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/02/2023<br>      Modified by: Benjamin&nbsp;Feintzeig</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[This project analyzed the philosophical foundations of objective and subjective probability in quantum mechanics.  Previously, philosophical work on quantum mechanics and quantum probability has been thought to require a particular interpretation of quantum theory that solves the so-called measurement problem, explaining how quantum states yield determinate measurement results.  The research team demonstrated that much philosophical analysis of quantum theory and quantum probability can proceed by considering only what these interpretations of quantum mechanics share in common.  The researchers investigated the objective aspects of quantum probabilities through a method involving a notion of accuracy for updating probabilities, and through a method analyzing the long time behavior of quantum dynamics in measurement setups.  The researchers investigated subjective aspects of quantum probabilities by engaging the formalism of quantum theory with methods from economics regarding subjective decision making.  The researchers analyzed the status of properties and their determinate values in quantum mechanics, thereby separating logical aspects of quantum theory from particular interpretations.  The researchers further investigated historical aspects of the epistemic status and social dynamics of discussions surrounding the interpretation of quantum mechanics.  The research outcomes have led to new frameworks and new methods for approaching the philosophical foundations of  quantum mechanics without committing a specific interpretation of quantum theory.  Thus this research produced results significant for the general formalism of quantum theory, which should be of interest across the research community in the foundations of physics. In addition to the research outcomes, this project produced a number of broader impacts.  The research team organized an early career workshop to build an interdisciplinary community of academic researchers in the summer of 2022.  Additionally, the project provided mentoring and support for a postdoctoral scholar, two graduate students, and four undergraduate students.  Finally, the PI organized a public lecture series in philosophy of physics.       Last Modified: 10/02/2023       Submitted by: Benjamin Feintzeig]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
