<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[DDRIG: From SARS to COVID-19: Nursing, Knowledges, and Trauma]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2021</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>12600.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>12600</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Wenda K. Bauchspies</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>wbauchsp@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925034</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Nurses are essential to contemporary hospital-based healthcare. Healthcare providers’ work requires frequent contact with patients within a hospital that is often rapidly changing.  Hospitals prioritize certain forms of expertise and render other knowledge and labor invisible. Nurses experience trauma and stress in their everyday work from the social structure of the hospital to the unique demands and risks of healthcare givers. Nurses are most likely to be diagnosed with Posttraumatic Stress Disorder (PTSD). This project examines nurses' experiences of trauma within the specific historical and cultural context of nurses' expertise, skills, and labor in healthcare. By focusing on nurses' often invisible skills and knowledge, this project will identify the implications of that invisibility for nurses' risk of exposure and well-being. This project carries key lessons and insights for healthcare workers, policy makers and administrative decision makers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project focuses on nurses' invisible knowledge and labor by doing ethnographic interviews with nurses, trauma experts, and workplace health and safety experts, as well as participant observation at a hospital. It asks the following research questions: 1) how does devaluing nurses' practices, skills, and knowledges also obscure the preventable exposures, risks, and trauma laden in the everyday work of nursing, and in what ways are they subverted or sustained? 2) how might centering nurses' experiences with PTSD also offer insight into the roots of nurses' working conditions during pandemics such as COVID-19? This project contributes to research discourses in STS and medical anthropology on the development of professional knowledge and techniques, where nurses' expertise and skills are often ignored in a replication of existing healthcare hierarchies. By beginning from nurses' knowledges the project will reveal how stress and trauma can become embedded within technical knowledges in high stress professions. By locating nurses' experiences of trauma and stress within the broader dynamics through which nurses develop, learn, and share skills and knowledge, this project will explore how essential and fragile their role is within healthcare. The outcomes of this project will inform the development of policies to support and sustain healthcare workers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/24/2021</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/20/2021</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2043706</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rachel</FirstName>
<LastName>Prentice</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Rachel E Prentice</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[rep35@cornell.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000700212</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/24/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Shoshana</FirstName>
<LastName>Deutsh</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Shoshana M Deutsh</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[smd338@cornell.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000833306</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/24/2021</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Cornell University</Name>
<CityName>ITHACA</CityName>
<ZipCode>148502820</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6072555014</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>341 PINE TREE RD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>19</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY19</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>G56PUALJ3KT5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CORNELL UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Department of Science & Technology Studies]]></Name>
<CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>148534701</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[159 Central Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>19</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY19</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>124Y</Code>
<Text>Science &amp; Technology Studies</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0121</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~12600</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="p1">The main outcome of this project was the completion of data collection on nurses' experiences of trauma and Post Traumatic Stress Disorder (PTSD) within the specific historical and cultural context of devaluing nurses' expertise, skills, and labor in healthcare. Data collection included ethnographic interviews with nurses, trauma experts, and workplace health and safety experts as well as document collection and analysis. Research was conducted in Toronto, Canada, where the legacies of the 2003 SARS epidemic have obscured, rather than highlighted, the everyday contexts of nurses' trauma and the impact of a systematically defunded single-payer healthcare system on their working conditions, exposure risk, and experiences of trauma and stress. As an ethnographic account of nursing during the COVID-19 pandemic, this project was further able to collect data on how historical devaluations of nurses&rsquo; expertise, skill, and labour worsened their experiences of risk and trauma during the pandemic and beyond.<span>&nbsp;</span></p> <p class="p2">&nbsp;</p> <p class="p1"><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><span class="s1">Broader impacts:</span></span> During the first year of the COVID-19 pandemic, nurses were praised globally as &ldquo;heroes,&rdquo; a move meant to celebrate their work yet simultaneously casting them as superhuman, beyond risk and beyond trauma. As data collected for this project shows, marking nurses&rsquo; work as exceptional or heroic has also hidden poor working conditions, a situation which stems out of broader historical and cultural devaluations of gendered forms of caring and knowing, such as nursing, in healthcare settings. This data shows not only the invisibile details of nurses&rsquo; working conditions, or the ways in which their work is devaluated, but also how these devaluations and invisibilities are internalized into stigma within nursing that refuses nurses the possibility of being both a nurse and having mental health issues, including PTSD and other forms of trauma and stress.<span>&nbsp;</span></p> <p class="p2">&nbsp;</p> <p class="p1"><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><span class="s1">Intellectual merits:</span> </span>As the first substantive account of nurses&rsquo; experiences of trauma and stress from a qualitative, ethnographic perspective, this project marks a unique contribution to the fields of Science and Technology Studies and medical anthropology. Data collection for this project has approached nurses&rsquo; as knowledge producers in their own right and taken the novel approach of situating nurses&rsquo; working conditions as inherently tied to how their knowledge, skills, and profession is valued and devalued. In doing so, this project provides a critical contribution to these fields of study and advances knowledge on healthcare practitioners who themselves experience illness.<span>&nbsp;</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/27/2022<br>      Modified by: Shoshana&nbsp;M&nbsp;Deutsh</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[The main outcome of this project was the completion of data collection on nurses' experiences of trauma and Post Traumatic Stress Disorder (PTSD) within the specific historical and cultural context of devaluing nurses' expertise, skills, and labor in healthcare. Data collection included ethnographic interviews with nurses, trauma experts, and workplace health and safety experts as well as document collection and analysis. Research was conducted in Toronto, Canada, where the legacies of the 2003 SARS epidemic have obscured, rather than highlighted, the everyday contexts of nurses' trauma and the impact of a systematically defunded single-payer healthcare system on their working conditions, exposure risk, and experiences of trauma and stress. As an ethnographic account of nursing during the COVID-19 pandemic, this project was further able to collect data on how historical devaluations of nurses’ expertise, skill, and labour worsened their experiences of risk and trauma during the pandemic and beyond.    Broader impacts: During the first year of the COVID-19 pandemic, nurses were praised globally as "heroes," a move meant to celebrate their work yet simultaneously casting them as superhuman, beyond risk and beyond trauma. As data collected for this project shows, marking nurses’ work as exceptional or heroic has also hidden poor working conditions, a situation which stems out of broader historical and cultural devaluations of gendered forms of caring and knowing, such as nursing, in healthcare settings. This data shows not only the invisibile details of nurses’ working conditions, or the ways in which their work is devaluated, but also how these devaluations and invisibilities are internalized into stigma within nursing that refuses nurses the possibility of being both a nurse and having mental health issues, including PTSD and other forms of trauma and stress.    Intellectual merits: As the first substantive account of nurses’ experiences of trauma and stress from a qualitative, ethnographic perspective, this project marks a unique contribution to the fields of Science and Technology Studies and medical anthropology. Data collection for this project has approached nurses’ as knowledge producers in their own right and taken the novel approach of situating nurses’ working conditions as inherently tied to how their knowledge, skills, and profession is valued and devalued. In doing so, this project provides a critical contribution to these fields of study and advances knowledge on healthcare practitioners who themselves experience illness.           Last Modified: 04/27/2022       Submitted by: Shoshana M Deutsh]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
