<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Using Augmented Reality and Virtual Reality to Enhance Learning in Electromagnetics]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2023</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2025</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>296865.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>296865</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>R. Corby Hovis</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>chovis@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924625</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This project aims to serve the national interest by improving students' understanding of electricity and magnetism, which are key concepts in physics and engineering. Electromagnetics (or electromagnetism) (EM), the study of electrical and magnetic phenomena, is central to scientific research and modern technologies, such as quantum computing, cellular phones, electric cars, hydro and wind generators, and the electric power grid. EM is a fundamental topic in physics and electrical engineering curricula, where it usually constitutes a required course for all students. However, EM presents several challenges for students. First, it involves forces and dynamics that are not seen in classical mechanics or encountered in everyday life. Second, it relies heavily on vector analysis, and students often spend up to 20 percent of the semester just learning vector analysis (curl, divergence, etc.) and spherical and cylindrical coordinates (and calculus in those coordinates). The unintuitive nature of the topic, along with the focus on unfamiliar mathematical analysis, can hinder students from developing self-efficacy after a foundational course in EM. In this project, the project team will develop a curated series of augmented reality (AR) and virtual reality (VR) educational modules (studios) designed to significantly enhance the learning and application of conceptual knowledge for students in EM courses.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;By creating an augmented and virtual environment in which students can interact in a natural manner, integrated with a curriculum based around learning outcomes, the investigator intends to transform the educational experience of students in EM. The AR/VR simulations to be developed will place students in an augmented or virtual environment, allow them to interact by moving (walking or moving arms/hands) in the environment, and allow them to see the effects through visualization on a smartphone or tablet. By using the ability to visualize while at the same time physically move in an augmented or virtual space, students can more naturally explore phenomena and relationships in 3D. The studios will cover topics that align with most EM curricula and build from basic concepts such as "What is a field?" to advanced topics such as defining and understanding the boundary conditions and their effect on fields in different materials. The project team will field-test the AR/VR studios in courses and measure their efficacy through cognitive labs and assessments. They will also offer workshops and create an online portal to disseminate the application software and a guide for integrating the studios into EM courses. The NSF IUSE: EHR Program supports research and development projects to improve the effectiveness of STEM education for all students. Through the Engaged Student Learning track, the program supports the creation, exploration, and implementation of promising practices and tools.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/14/2022</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/14/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2044366</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Ricketts</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David S Ricketts</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[david.ricketts@ncsu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000508959</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/14/2022</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>North Carolina State University</Name>
<CityName>RALEIGH</CityName>
<ZipCode>27607</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9195152444</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2601 WOLF VILLAGE WAY</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>U3NVH931QJJ3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORTH CAROLINA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>N8DMK1K4C2K5</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[North Carolina State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Raleigh</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>276067911</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[890 Oval Dr]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1998</Code>
<Text>IUSE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8209</Code>
<Text>Improv Undergrad STEM Ed(IUSE)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8244</Code>
<Text>EHR CL Opportunities (NSF 14-302)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002223DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2022~296865</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
